26, regular meeting of the Memphis City Council will now come to order. Clerk Urnaby, please call the roll. Councilor Behrs? Present. Vice President Caraballo? Present. Councilor Knight? Present. Councilor Marks? Present. Councilor Morrell? Present. Councilor Scarpelli? Present.
President Falco. Present. All seven members are present. At this time, I'd ask everyone to please rise to salute the flag. I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America, and to the republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all. Justice for all. Mr. President. If I may, I just have to read the quicksand. Thank you, Vice President.
Pursuant to Governor Baker's March 12th, 2020 order suspending certain provisions of the Open Meeting Law, General Law, Chapter 38, Section 18, and the Governor's March 15th, 2020 order imposing strict limitation on the number of people that may gather in one place. This meeting of the Memphis City Council will be conducted via remote participation to the greatest extent possible.
specific information and the general guidelines for remote participation by members of the public and or parties with the right or requirement to attend this meeting can be found on the City of Medford website at www.medfordma.org. For this meeting, members of the public who wish to listen or watch the meeting may do so by accessing the meeting link contained herein. No in-person attendance of members of the public will be permitted, but every effort will be made possible to ensure that the public can adequately access the proceedings in real time via technological means.
In the event that we aren't able to do so, despite best efforts, we will post on the City of Mefford or Mefford Community Media website an audio or video recording transcript or other comprehensive record of proceedings as soon as possible after the meeting. To participate remotely outside of Zoom,
Please email ahertubise, that's A-H-U-R-T-U-B-I-S-E, at medford-ma.gov. Vice President Caviello. Mr. President, motion for suspension of the rules to take paper 20517 off the table. On the motion of Vice President Caviello to suspend the rules to take 20517 from the table.
Second. Seconded by Councilor Beers. Clerk Urtubez, please call the roll. Council Beers? Yes. Vice President Caravaglia? Yes. Councilor Knight? Yes. Councilor Knight? Yes. Councilor Marks? Yes. Councilor Morrell? Yes. Councilor Scopelli? Yes. President Falco? Yes. Sending the affirmative, zeroing the negative, the motion passes.
One minute please, I just have to get 2051 sent.
To the Honorable President and members of the Memphis City Council, City Hall, Memphis, Massachusetts 02155, dear Mr. President and city councilors. I respectfully request and recommend that your honorable body reprogram surplus proceeds in the amount of $112,692.73.
From the Medford High School HVAC Boiler Replacement Project to Medford High School Improvements Projects in accordance with Master General Law Chapter 44, Section 20. Finance Director Alicia Donnelly Benjamin is present to answer any of the council's questions regarding this matter. Sincerely, Brianna Longo Kern, Mayor. Let's see, we had, let's see, I believe Councilor Knight wanted to speak on that. Councilor Knight? I do believe Councilor Caballero was the moving party taken off the table, Mr. President.
My apologies, Vice President Caviello. Yes, Mr. President. If we could take that off the table. That paper has been taken from the table. Oh, I'm sorry. 20516, also. Second. Do you want to vote on this one first? Yes. OK. So are you making a motion to approve? Yes. OK. On the motion to approve, 20-517. Second. Mr. President, Mr. President, is Jonathan available, Mr. President? OK, on the motion of counselor.
Is John McLaughlin available, the facilities director? Let's see, is John McLaughlin on the phone? Or actually, is he on the meeting? If he's not on the meeting, we can wait until later on in the meeting. We have our superintendent of schools is with us as well. She's John's boss, so she should probably be.
Do you have a question for the superintendent? I do. I'd just like to give us a breakdown as to where funds are going to be expended. That was the reason why we tabled it last week. Thank you. So let's see. On the motion of Vice President Caviello, seconded by Councilor Behrs. And we have the superintendent of schools with us. Let's see. Dr. Marie Sedgwick-Vincent.
I believe.
and other members of my team, Dave Murphy, Dr. Peter Cushing, and possibly Suzanne Galussi as well. So we are prepared to respond to any questions that you may have regarding the,
the proposals for how we would recommend spending this money to advance work that needs to be done in all of the buildings for a safe opening of schools. Excellent. Thank you.
Thank you, Dr. Vincent. I appreciate you being here. Now, these funds, this $800 and somewhat thousand dollars, these funds are for capital improvements, correct? They're not for any personnel. They can't bring reading specialists back into the classroom or anything like that, right? These are just for capital expenses?
Yes, absolutely not for personnel. The request for these funds are to improve our infrastructure, in particular around the areas of air exchange, air quality, to get our buildings up to air balancing, all of those things that are currently working to try to fix to make sure that our buildings
are up and running and safe for a smooth reopening of schools. Right, but so the council's tabling of this item did not prevent the school department from bringing any teachers or any classroom teachers back, is that correct? That is correct. Excellent, thank you. Because sometimes there's a lot of misinformation that travels around the community, and that was something that was going around. So I just wanted to be sure, Dr. Vincent, that we were all clear.
that the funds here that were tabled by the council at the last meeting were for capital funds only. But the council did last meeting, I believe, increase the school department's budget by $1.08 million that would allow for those positions to be restored. Is that correct? That is correct. Excellent. And after last week's meeting, I did have the opportunity to pick up the phone and make a telephone call to John McLaughlin. And I spoke with John at length and he explained to me the situation at the high school especially.
relative to the heating, ventilation, and air conditioning system. He also explained to me that there were some air quality tests that were conducted that came back. And for the most part, all of our schools came back with very good reviews, with the exception of one. And I think we all know what school that is, Medford High School. So with that being said, Dr. Vincent, could you tell us a little bit about the scope of work that you're looking to spend this $800 and some odd thousand dollars on, please?
Yes, so there is a significant scope of work that does need to be done in particular if we focus on the high school, which is the oldest building in the district outside of the Curtis Tufts. But the high school being 50 years old has older rooms, more eighth graders.
some pains, if I can say that. And so there are areas that definitely need immediate attention in the HVAC area. And so we're currently, WB Engineering is currently conducting, completed their first report on the building of the high school and what they would make recommendations for in the area of HVAC. We also have,
UEC universal environmentalists coming in who are also looking at air quality and air balancing and we also have Precision, another engineering group that is continuing to look at how our HVAC systems function and work for the district. So with all of the different
engineering companies that have been coming in, the cost is truly significant. For example, at the high school on the roof, to repair the fans that are on the roof, which are part of the exhaust
system, HVAC system. We have approximately $150,000 worth of work on the roof alone, addressing fans and making sure that they are all properly functioning at their maximum speed and able to deliver and support intake and outtake in the building. In addition, from WB Engineering's initial report,
on the high school based on the mitigation strategies that they recommended. We're talking about prices that would exceed $200,000 at the high school complex alone. And the other off-campus buildings are still being assessed as we speak.
and so we are waiting for those reports to finish being completed. Some of that money also because, again, this building is 50 years old. Prior to the official ADA changes that newer buildings had to have to be properly
handicapped, accessible. We wanted to set aside approximately $50,000 to $100,000 to support making the entrance to the high school ADA compliant. There is a ramp there that vehicles go up and down, but for people in wheelchairs,
it is not fully compliant. And so those are some of the things that we want to be able to use these monies for. And as the other buildings are continued, are presently still being assessed, we anticipate that there will continue to be, you know, significant
requirements from the district to be able to mitigate all of these HVAC challenges that could present themselves in order for us to be able to get schools up and running as quickly as possible.
I also want to say to the entire body that we, as the work is being done, we are prepared and fully wanting to come back and share with both you and the school committee the progress of the work that's being done, the status of the work, and where we are in terms of using this funding to remedy the HVAC challenges that have presented themselves.
And in terms of total cost for us to bring our HVAC system at Medford High School into compliance and I guess efficient and effective working order. Is this $816 enough money to do that or will there be a request for a supplemental appropriation at a later date going forward?
So at this point in time, we are optimistic that this will allow us to address the high school. We don't know, again,
You know, we can't, I cannot definitively say that I will not need to come and ask your body for additional funding. Our hope is that the 816,000 will allow us to be able to address all of the key challenges with HVAC systems, in particular at the high school, that we would be able to remedy all of the things that were recommended in the reports.
And is it still the wishes of the committee to have this account be exclusive to Medford High School only and to the other schools? We would hope that this could be for the high school and if needed for, we know the outside schools are much younger, they're 20 years younger. However, we may need to spend purchasing additional HEPA filters and
We would hope to be able to use this funding not only at the high school, but potentially at some of the outside schools as well. That would be our hope if other things were to surface. But we know, we're fully aware that the high school needs significant work and that the lion's share of that funding definitely would be spent at the high school complex.
The reason I raise the question is because the way that the paper was drafted was that it would be reprogramming the funds to an account exclusive to Medford High School. And I know maybe Alicia's on the call, maybe Alicia can elaborate a little bit on that. But I do believe that when it was presented that those funds were restricted exclusively to Medford High School and were not going to be allowed to be used in other schools in the district. If I'm mistaken, please correct me. But maybe Ms. Nunley can help us out with that.
I also have Mister Murphy, David Murphy on the line. He's on the call as well. And he may be able to weigh in on that. Again, as the numbers are coming in, we know for certain, the roof fans,
At the high school, it's going to be a significant investment. And if the funds need to be spent exclusively at the high school, that there is so much work, capital projects, including additional bathrooms and those kinds of things that need to be renovated and updated, that I'm sure that we would be able to use all of this funding in short order.
So it's the committee's, the school department's wishes to keep the paper as is and not amend it and allow it for just MHS only because it's only $800,000 and you can spend that all up at the high school, no problem. If it is possible to allow if
If there was something that were to come up at one of the other schools and we had to take a very limited amount from this $800,000 to support the other buildings, if that was a possibility, I would ask this body to allow us
the additional flexibility to be able to use it throughout all of the schools. But if that would be problematic, then I would just say leave it for the high school because we know that there is plenty of work that can be done. It's certainly not a problem for me. The paper came from the administration, so maybe Alicia Nunley, my finance director, can talk a little bit about that.
We have the eye. If I may be a chief of staff, Dave Rodriguez has his hand raised. So at this point, I'd recognize chief of staff Rodriguez. So like, I'm happy to answer on her behalf. The reason the paper was drafted in this manner was that it just mirrored the original use of the
to high school use. The administration and the mayor are completely in support of removing the high school aspect of that and have it be applicable to the rest of the public school system and the rest of the buildings there. My understanding, after speaking with Alicia, is that this is completely improper and that it's completely in line with what the administration can do with these funding. So we'd have to amend the paper?
Mr. President, I would offer that in the form of a motion to amend the paper to reflect that these funds can be used across the school district, not just exclusive to Medford High School. Second. On the motion of Councilor Knight to amend the paper, seconded by Councilor Scott Kelly. Clerk, do you have the wording on that? On the amendment? I second.
So Councilor Knight's amendment is to allow the schools to use the funds across the school district, not just at the high school. That is correct. Correct. Councilor Knight, do you have any further questions? That's it for me, sir. Thank you. Thank you, Councilor Knight. Councilor Marks.
Thank you, Mr. President, and I thank the superintendent for being on the call tonight and the administrative staff. The email we received today talks about WB engineering report and that the amount to look at ventilation air quality, air exchange would significantly exceed $200,000. I was just wondering,
regarding the 200,000, is that particularly to the high school or is that in general across the board?
Yes, this first report that was released by WB Engineering was exclusively to high school. And so, that $200,000 to exceed the $200,000 was just for some of the mitigation work that needs to be done exclusively at the high school. We have not received,
all of the remaining engineering reports for the remaining outside schools, because the high school being the largest building takes the most time. Okay, so Madam Superintendent, you mentioned the roof fans. At Medford High School, I guess roughly 100 roof fans at an estimated cost of $125,000. Is that part of this $200,000 that's listed as WB engineering report?
So that $150,000 was in addition, I believe that the amount of the 150,000 was for the repairing of the roof fans. And then there are other mitigation strategies, which could potentially include HECA filters and those kinds of things. It's likely to not exceed 200,000. And I, again, significantly exceed that.
But I, again, I do have David Murphy on the call and John McLaughlin, so I don't know if Clerk Hurtubise could unmute them so they could weigh in as well. Okay, I'm about to unmute John McLaughlin. Okay, John, you've been unmuted, and David Murphy has been unmuted as well. David Murphy? I'm sorry, David Murphy, I apologize.
Councilman Marks, did you have a specific question for John McLaughlin? My question is regarding the $200,000 that was mentioned within the email we got today and also a previous email we received from the mayor. It mentioned that each classroom needed these filters at $1,500 a piece, but it didn't mention how many classrooms and if it was just the high school or if it was classrooms across the entire city.
I think I can respond to that, and I would ask Mr. McLaughlin to jump in. For those of you who don't know, I'm the assistant superintendent for finance and operations. I began work with the Medford Public Schools approximately three weeks ago, and so I've been clinging to John to try to get my own
I think for this particular question, I can answer and I'd ask John to fill in the details. So where we are right now is we have the initial assessment from WB Engineering of Medford High School. There is a tremendous amount of information in that report. We've been working with WB and have additional meetings scheduled with them in the coming days to make a determination as to which of the mitigation strategies
that they have identified in that report should be utilized. It looks to us like an estimate or a middle of the road approach to the work that they have acknowledged could be useful is somewhere in the vicinity of $200,000. That's where that estimate came from. The rough estimate of the $150,000 is specific to the work that is estimated needs to be done
that we're looking at over $400,000 of potential work that has been identified, but the $200,000 number, the potential assess mitigation strategies at Medford High School, a comparable report has not yet been done at the other schools. The reason for that is we are currently testing both for air quality and
for that expense is also also
And then once we have the data from that testing, we'll be in a better position to determine whether or not we should commission a similar assessment at the other schools, the way we have for Bedford High School. And it says in the memo that there is a, we understand there's an unusual sequence to having already received recommendations with regard to mitigation strategies at the high school, while the testing across the district, both at the high school and other schools,
And the reason for that is the high school is a unique entity, both with regard to its size, its age, and the complexity of its systems. And so we pushed forward with that study right away. And we solicited proposals. We have already three proposals to do similar work at the other schools. And we're going to hold off on actually commissioning that and making that investment until we actually have the data back from the testing that's currently being done.
So through you, Mr. President, when was the WB engineering study commissioned by the school department and voted on by the school committee? I'd have to defer on the vote of the school committee question, but it was commissioned, I believe, on the week of August 17th. Potentially August 25th. It was in that range.
Is there a particular reason why the school district waited so long to commission an air quality study? I think the point that is, I think we should sort of preface all of this commentary with is that we actually have no evidence right now that there is anything wrong with the air quality. Frankly, I understand there's a history and there have been some persistent questions, but
to make sure that we provide as much defense against any type of virus transmission. But I think there's been a
Right. And when did we find out there's hot evidence now that says the quality of air is fine? To be candid, I don't have any evidence that that is the case. I think it's an attempt to, given the context and the anxiety that folks are feeling, trying to be as responsive as possible to some of the concerns that have been raised. Right.
Right, so I'm just wondering why for the past six months, the school administration, knowing that eventually we're going to have faculty, students, staff back within our public schools. Over the last six months, didn't realize that a first step would have been to do an air quality test within the schools.
And I'm not sure why it took so long to do that. But putting that aside, Mr. President, this was tabled two weeks ago. And one of the motions made by the council was to ask the administration and the school committee for a list of their priorities.
Because at the time we heard of a number of priorities. One being ventilation, air quality, air exchange in order to provide a healthy and safe building. But we also heard about handicapped ramps accessibility. We also heard about the condition of our restrooms within the school department and a number of other concerns as well, Mr. President.
We just recently received an email from the mayor stating that if we could release the funds, they're also looking to use some of the funds for beautification purposes in the main entrance.
which I know firsthand that that is something that's needed, Mr. President. I was part of the crew that painted that several months back under the leadership of Bill Carr Jr. and a number of volunteers, so I know that's needed. But I believe, and I can't speak for my colleagues,
Why we asked for a priority list was to make sure that we had a reasonable assessment, Mr. President, on what are we going to do to get our children, and our teachers, and our faculty, and our staff back into a safe building. And to me, beautification of a front entrance is probably at the bottom of the list. And air quality, and air exchange, and ventilation, and other priorities, Mr. President, would be at the top of the list.
And that's what I was hoping to receive from the administration and the school committee. And to be quite frank, I am very disappointed that we didn't even get a response, Mr. President, from the council motion that was two weeks ago. That was from August 25th.
Unless I'm mistaken, I have yet to receive anything, Mr. President. That's not to say that I realize that work needs to be done in that building. But it would be helpful, Mr. President, if we're going to work in cooperation with the school side, that if we have requests, that they recognize and honor our request, Mr. President, as well.
I have no problem allotting money, Mr. President, but I'd like to know what it's going to go towards. Now, if we free up $800,000 tonight to go into this fund, there's no saying that they won't end up doing beautification over ventilation.
I would hope that's not the case, Mr. President. And clearly, if there are 100 fans that are currently not working on the roof, you can almost bet your bottom dollar the air quality and circulation in that building is not good, Mr. President. So this is not rocket science. They're already coming out saying they have to
can't change out all the filters, the fans on the roof aren't working, over 100 fans. That's what circulates air within a building. That's what provides proper air quality and air exchange and ventilation. So those are the concerns I have, Mr. President.
And maybe if the superintendent or someone else from the administration can assure us that if we do release money tonight, that the priority is to get people back into the building. And to make sure that the air quality and the safety of our students, and our teachers, and our staff, and our faculty is the number one priority, Mr. President. And then we can look at other needs.
My other point, Mr. President, is two weeks ago, Alicia Nunley represented to us when we took the vote that there was other money available. I believe I asked the question, because it was led to believe that if we didn't vote two weeks ago, that we were stalling students from getting back into the building. And I asked Alicia Nunley that question, and she said, there are CARES Act money available, and there's COVID-19 funds.
that are available to work with the air quality and safety concerns. So that's why I voted the way I did, Mr. President, knowing that there's other additional funds out there. And that the fact that I want to make sure as one member that if we're going to allot money,
that it go into the safety of our faculty, students, and kids, Mr. President. And I'm sure the school committee and the administration share the concerns, but if we're going to be responsible for allocating this money, like every other paper, Mr. President, it'd be nice to have a paper in front of us.
And I received an email today that I just happened to be able to take a look at just briefly, but I still haven't seen anything that prioritizes work. And I realize the testing is still underway and current, but that's why I felt that if this happened two, three, four months ago,
Don't forget the money that was in this account from the science labs, the 700,000, that's been sitting in the account for five years, Mr. President. Think about it. We could have moved that money in for restrooms in the high school for the past five years, for working water bubblers. You name it, Mr. President, what's needed in that high school. So this is money that could have been used over the past five years.
So those are the concerns I have, Mr. President. If the superintendent can assure me tonight that this money will be prioritized for the reopening and the ventilation and air quality and air exchange and safety concerns over aesthetics and beautification at this particular stage, I will give it a vote tonight. If not, Mr. President, I will not move forward. Thank you.
Yes, I can assure Councilor Marks and the entire council that our intention is to get the buildings up and running as quickly as possible so that we can have students return. That is our highest priority. The concerns about the ADA, which I did mention, accessibility at the front of the high school, that is something that has always been a concern.
a concern and so in fixing the ADA ramps at the front of the high school, the main entrance, at the same time that that's being fixed, in essence, you would be able to fix the school aesthetically by making it more handicap accessible and doing the work that needs to be done there.
But again, our priority is to be able to get the school up and running, meeting the HVAC standards and proper air ventilation in the entire complex. We want students to be safe. We want our staff to be safe.
everyone coming to work into the building to be safe. So that is our highest priority. And I can assure you as the entire council, that that's what we can focus on. Again, we are also willing to come before you as we continue to get additional reports. And as work is being done to come and update the council on the status of the work and how much of the money has been spent as well, as we continue to do the same for the school committee.
But I do want to stress that this funding will be a tremendous help to the schools and allow us to be able to open and get kids back in the schools as quickly as possible. Thank you, Superintendent Edward. Vincent, thank you, Councilor Marks. We have up next, Vice President Carviello and then Councilor Morrell. Vice President. Thank you, Mr. President. Mr. President, over eight years ago,
I brought up the heating and ventilation of all the schools with the exception of the high school. And so again, this is not a new problem. This has been going on long before the COVID came in. What is the plan to address those schools that have been, for all those units that haven't been operating in there for many years, Madam Superintendent?
Last year, for example, we did a lot of work on some of the outside buildings. I know the Columbus, we had a lot of units that were updated and if something wasn't working, there were a lot of repairs that were made to the outside schools. And so we are committed to having all buildings fully functioning, the outside buildings with their air conditioning and their heating to be working.
So we are committed to doing that, and that work has been ongoing. Now, what about the air quality in those buildings, Madam Superintendent? So the air quality in all of the outside buildings, they are currently still being assessed right now. Again, as I had said earlier, the high school being the largest complex, essentially the other schools can all fit into the high school complex.
that this building took the longest amount of time. And the engineers from the different engineering companies, they are out in the field right now doing the assessments on the outside buildings as well. So that is ongoing work. Madam Superintendent, how are we addressing the inequality issues in the high school with the classrooms that are on the inside of the corridor with no windows?
So exactly, that is a great question. So we are fully aware of the classrooms that do not have any windows at all, the inner classrooms in B building and C building, B building on the second floor. And so there are some classrooms that we are looking to take offline and there are other classrooms where what would be appropriate would be to put in the,
HEPA filters in other classrooms. Can you give me like five minutes? Yep. To put in air quality in the HEPA filters in the other buildings to be able to, those rooms, to be able to increase the air quality in that space. Will you be utilizing some of the theaters in that building, the study halls?
For the study halls, if they met the air quality standard, once all of the spaces meet the correct standard, every space will be able to be used. If there's an area that it can't be used, we were given suggestions to mitigate that. So whether it's looking at the windows or adding HEPA filters,
but to increase the air ventilation and air circulation. Once we establish a list and do the repairs to the high school, is there talk about bringing on a company on retainer to monitor these on a regular basis?
not just do it and walk away, but have a company that'll come in there, have somebody on retainer to constantly monitor these classrooms. because I'm sure those filters are going to need to be replaced on a constant basis. So is that something in the plans?
It is, one of the suggestions that we already have in plans is to increase, normally filters were changed twice a year and we're gonna increase that and double the filters being changed. So there are steps that we have already begun to put in place that we're gonna use moving forward to help all of the schools and to just keep a high level of air quality for everyone, all staff working and students in the Medford Public Schools.
And as far as the bathrooms that we've been talking about for many years, what's going to be happening with those?
So we would definitely like to upgrade and renovate the bathrooms, and that's still on our list to get that work done. But for right now, we really are prioritizing HVAC systems, the air quality, et cetera, testing. So that's our biggest priority first, and then we will definitely be tackling the bathrooms as well.
And I will echo my fellow council's remarks is I'd like to see a list, a detailed list of what's going on versus just talking about it. So if we can get that to us as soon as possible, that would be greatly appreciated, even though we asked for it a couple of weeks ago.
So the reports that were shared today were some of just the preliminary reports that we have. We don't have other reports as of yet because the testing is still ongoing. But as soon as we have additional reports to share, we will gladly share that with the entire council. And one last question, which is kind of a, what would the school department have done if we didn't find this $800,000?
Where would this funding come from? I mean, it's kind of- It would have been a tremendous challenge, and we would have needed to ask for additional support. All right, well, thank you. Thank you, Vice President Carbiel. Councilor Morrell.
Thank you, Mr. President. I want to thank members of the school administration for being here tonight. I understand the acute and immediate need of the schools in this time as far as preparing for the safest possible environment, and I also understand just the need to be agile and responsive in these times, especially when metrics and goalposts keep shifting. So I thank you for your work on this, and I do hope we can move this paper forward tonight. My question is,
Councilor Marks touched on this a bit about the HEPA filters, the $1,500 HEPA filters that are mentioned. And I apologize if I missed this, but is there a ballpark number of the number of these we might need? So as we are waiting on the additional reports from the outside schools as well,
I don't have a specific number, but I would like to defer to Assistant Superintendent David Murphy as well. I think he got muted. I would like to defer to him. He may have more of the specifics in terms of the total number of filters needed at the high school. Thank you. David. Thank you, Superintendent.
I think that's a good point. that information because there was a variety of recommendations that were contained in WB's initial report. We've been using a number that exceeds a 100, it's either 116 or 119 based on our very
we're not going to be able to sort of clean or attaching ourselves too much to that specific number because a lot of this testing is going on. And as I said before, there is sort of an unusual sequence to this in that we're in a two-week window of testing and we're getting that data and hope to have all of it somewhere between
that's why we commission this initial report. So we're using a number in the vicinity of 1, 10 to 1, 20, but that is without having fully digested or analyze the findings of WB or having access to the
the number as stated in the memo, it's significant, and that's why we're using sort of a placeholder number of $200,000 with regard to infrastructure, internal to Medford High School. But I can't say that after we've had a chance to truly analyze both the report and the data, I can't say that we may modify that position. Now, John, I don't know if you want to add anything to that.
Well, yeah, and we're going to meet again Thursday with the engineer. And we're going to probably try to get some high numbers of where we need additional support. So that's sort of where we stand right now. Yeah, I mean, the big thing for us is we want to make
decisions as to how to use based on as much data as possible, understanding that we're obviously very much up against the clock. But based on our current implementation plan with regard to when students will be in the building, we have these coming weeks to try to utilize whatever mitigation strategies we think are necessary to have as much defense as possible.
Okay, thank you. And then just one more question through the chair if I could. Does the assessment point to that these HEPA filters would then meet the needs or is there a chance we're going to put these HEPA filters in and it's tested again and we find that we have to go, you know, even farther as far as the HVAC and things like that?
I think that's an excellent question. And exactly the questions that we're currently posing to the engineers that we're meeting with to make a determination as to, I think both exactly what is the impact now and what is the impact long term? Because right now there's sort of a heightened standard that industry experts are advising districts and other employers, frankly, to potentially utilize. And I think there's a question as to, once we spend the $200,000,
the building, what exactly is the return on investment going forward? And obviously, we want the best air quality and best air exchange rates possible. And at the same time, as I said, today, we have no evidence that there's an actual problem with the building. But we're also operating in a context in which, again, people have very understanding of the
Okay, thank you. So really what I'm hearing is essentially it's just the nature of the beast because of the way these standards are coming down and just looking into the building this way, things are changing and sometimes it can be hard to nail down exact amounts because of that, but the intention is there as laid out in these papers and in the email we got, correct?
And I think that's correct. And to the superintendent's point that she made earlier, we certainly recognize our responsibility to report back, obviously, to the Medford School Committee and also to the Medford City Council, as to exactly what strategies are being employed, what impact we foresee those strategies having, and what is the return on investment for the community, whether it be installing capital filters, repairing fans on the roof,
I think that's all I have to say. I think that's all I have to say.
Thank you, Mr. President. I have a few. I know that the council has asked some great questions. Just to the superintendent, if I can, Mr. President, or Mr. Rodriguez. Legally, the money that was left in those accounts, it's okay to be used in this form. I know that sometimes when you get money in certain grants or
You have to use specific reasons, I just want to reassure that they are being used for what's intended and we can still move forward with that. If we could have someone from the administration, I'm not sure if Dave or Superintendent Edward Vincent, if you could, let's see, Dave Rodriguez, Chief of Staff. Okay.
this case.
in order to just reauthorize it, essentially reauthorizing the use of the funds. The funds have already been borrowed, they're cash in hand, so we don't have to go out to bond for these proceeds. And we've actually been paying debt service on them since they were borrowed. So we've been sending you an account that we've been paying debt service on since they were borrowed, by reprogramming them so we're allowed to release those funds for that specific use, pursuant to the reauthorization. That's allowed under Chapter 44. I forget the exact section, but it's quoted within the council paper.
Thank you. Mr. President, to the superintendent, I know probably one of the oldest schools is Curtis Tough School. Are we still planning on having a program running in a positive manner that it's always run? And how does that look with air quality testing? Is that one of the schools being looked at as we speak?
Yes, so ironically enough, because the Curtis Tufts is actually the oldest building, they have very, very large windows that can open. And so one of the best
based on what the engineers feedback that the engineers have given to us is to allow natural air to come into the spaces. So the Curtis Tufts has, you know, very tall ceilings, very large windows in every single classroom. So although we know we'll be waiting for what the reports say, we anticipate very good remarks, scores for the Curtis Tufts
that they have the ability to let in a lot of natural air to support air quality at that facility. So we are waiting again for the final reports from the outside schools that are still ongoing. And again, if air filters or something like that is needed, we are prepared to put those in place at all of the buildings, including the Curtis House.
Madam Superintendent, what neighbor communities and other schools are using across the country. Have we looked at using the viability of the gymnasium? We probably have one of the biggest gymnasiums in the state, and to use those as classrooms. I think that could be a viable way to move some of those classes that have some issues that can't be repaired. But is that something that we're investigating too?
But we have not ruled out using alternative spaces within the high school complex in particular. The only fear is, you know, we have very, very long winters and it is important for students to be able, while the weather permitting, you know, they can go outside and use the outside fields.
But that would be something that we would have to look at. But as a temporary measure, we would not rule out having to use other spaces, including the gymnasium. OK. And again, to the superintendent, through you, Mr. President,
No one thought you're going to come into Medford, become the new superintendent, handle a pandemic and other issues and the concerns that we're seeing today in society. I know that with the race issues we have, I think that I've talked to some teachers and
Already the staff in professional development, you've already started a dialogue that's talking about race and making sure that our teachers are prepared for our questions from our students. Because there are going to be a lot of questions, a lot of concerns, and I'm so happy to see that the team is moving forward.
It brings me to the bigger point, I think that it was easy a few weeks ago to people in higher power to slam this council because they think that what was thought was that we were hurting the kids of the city of Medford. Now, as a father of two kids in that system, that's the furthest from my mind. So I wanted to applaud this council.
Because this is our job, whether you like it or not, it's to look at every penny and making sure that we're using it for the right reasons. And look at the time we spent, it's almost been an hour, and we've been talking about, this is just scratching the surface, about what this money can be used for. And these questions,
If not used for the reasons to get our children back in the school for any reason, who would they hold accountable? That would be us, because we would have proved it. So I applaud this council for taking the extra time to make sure that we dotted our I's and crossed our T's to make sure we can get our students and faculty into a safe,
We've already heard that delaying it to two weeks didn't have any issues with moving that point forward. So again, I know that
It's easy to beat people up, but we need to stay positive. And I think that with the steps you're taking and your team is taking, Superintendent, and Johnny McLaughlin, we're trying to do to get our kids back into a safe, healthy school. What this council's doing to make sure any funding we do have goes right to the proper locations, making sure that Alicia Nunley's working with that COVID fund, making sure that we're doing what's right.
And I appreciate it, and I thank you. I do want to end just with one thing, some of the, that we have you, Madam Superintendent. The biggest question I'm hearing right now is, please, when will the kids know their schedule? I know they're scheduled to start next week. If you can answer that final question, just to give them an idea, I think it'll be very helpful. Thank you.
We did send out the tentative schedule of what their instructional day will look like. We have not sent out at the secondary level, the high school level over the next few days. The student schedules will be sent out. School brings is converting over and with the assignments
of teachers and working on the assignments of cohorts, all of that work is taking place right now. So under normal conditions, people would have had their schedules in advance, but due to all of the moving pieces that we are currently kind of working with right now, we were not able to create schedules. Had we sent schedules out, the schedules most likely would have ended up having to change.
So it's a situation where we are measuring twice in order to cut once. And so I ask the entire community for a little more patience for us to be able to match up the students with the cohorts.
With the days of the week, with the staffing that's available, with all of the adjustments that had to be made, we were not able to send out the schedule, but that will be completed over the next few days.
So again, Madam Superintendent, I thank you. And again, I just urge the community to, it's easy to stand on that soapbox and pound your chest, but let's all have a sense of a community and understand that this is the first time for a lot of communities. And the community I'm working in right now, this is exactly the issues they're going through. And it's been a mess. So we're all working together.
We're doing this together for the first time. Let's just stay positive and make sure that we do what's best for our community and our children. Thank you. Thank you, Councilor Scarapelli. Councilor Pierce. Thank you, Mr. President. And thank you, Dr. Vincent. I know you're working with a smaller staff than you were working with last year, I think including the data director, so I know it must be difficult.
I spent four years in Medford High School this side of the year 2000, and I can tell you if it was bad before, it's worse now. So I really appreciate the condition that the building is in and the work that needs to happen. I have two quick questions, hopefully. The first one is, has any spending on HVAC repairs or other repairs to, or upgrades to make sure the building, Medford High School, is safe? Have those happened already? Has any spending occurred?
So John McLaughlin would have to speak specifically to the spending that may have occurred.
outside of the reports not coming in yet. So we, again, as we're just getting this information kind of hot off the press, we were waiting for what the reports would reveal so that we could know which way to go. Because a lot of, there's a lot of vendors out there, a lot of people saying, do this, do that. But again, where the high school has its unique
It's unique structure. We have classrooms without windows. There are a lot of special parts of the high school. You know, the science wing, which is completely renovated. So we have so many different parts of the building. I know that we had held off waiting for guidance so that we would be able to really make smart decisions. But John McLaughlin could speak to what may have already been spent.
John McLaughlin. Yeah, so the money that you appropriated about a year ago, you appropriated, I think it was $325,000. We're going to look into doing bathrooms, a generator, repairs to the PA system, and a few other projects. So currently, the bathroom project
We had to get an architect in, so I'm awaiting the architect's plans so that we can go through the procurement process and move forward with that. The generator, I'm actually waiting for a price as well to repair that generator or to replace that generator that we had talked about about a year ago.
Things are moving slowly. People aren't out and about and around as much as they usually are. But we are. We're still working forward. We're also working with CPA grants to put in new soft surfaces and repair all the equipment, outside playground equipment at the Columbus, in the Brooks, as well as a study that we'll be conducting hopefully shortly about ADA compliance.
for the soft surface at the McGlynn area or maybe a redesign for the soft surface play area at the McGlynn. So those projects have been moving forward with them. But as you can imagine,
with everything going on it's not as it's not as easy to get the people you know to to come to come into the building and you know the exposure and things of that nature but yeah we're still moving forward and um you know and and and and if you if if you're gracious enough to
this money. We're going to do some good things with it. And it's going to be a win-win for the kids in the community. And yeah, we're going to have to really, really work hard to maintain what we have. I mean, we have over a million square feet in the district.
And, you know, there's a lot of moving parts, so we're constantly moving around through the city fixing things that break and as they break. And sometimes we find ourselves running around just putting out little fires and not necessarily doing, you know, some of the other maintenance issues go by the wayside. And unfortunately,
Sometimes this is what happens in programs that we want to put computers in kids' hands and run programs. So sometimes building as old as Method High School paid the price, and we're paying for the sins.
that have been going on since the 70s now. So it's not anybody in particular's fault. It's not somebody's fault because we're doing the best we can. We're trying as hard as we can. Now, every roof fan at Method High School isn't bad.
To take the time to diagnose the roof fans, it's easier to replace them all and start off with brand new roof fans. So I don't want you to think that it's all bad. It's just that what we're trying to do is make improvements to the whole roof situation and exhaust fans. I hope that answers your question.
Thank you, John. Yeah, I appreciate the answer, and I understand the concern of vendors coming into the building. My only other question, well, also I like Dr. Vinson saying that there are special parts of the building. I thought that was kind, kind language. My other question is just the timeline. Do you think that these repairs will be completed by the current estimated date where students might be coming back into the building, which I think is mid-October, or would they go past that?
So again, because we don't have all of the reports, we know right now that the high school needs significant work and over the next week, by the end of next week, we should have reports regarding the other schools. So again, if it's really,
small mitigation that's required in the outside buildings where we, you know, as it is, we're working around the clock, but we will continue to get it done. We want kids back in school as quickly as possible, but we need to ensure that the buildings are safe and meet the appropriate standards. And so we are trying to do it as quickly as possible. We're not taking shortcuts because we do know that this is,
everyone's safety and health at risk. So we want it to be done as quickly as possible, but we need it to be done correctly. So as soon as we have the data from the outside engineering reports, we will, you know, go into high gear action to mitigate, you know, and meet whatever it is that they're recommending for us to get our buildings back online as soon as possible.
So my hope would definitely be that by October, we would be up and running at all, if not the majority of our buildings. Thank you, Dr. Vincent, and I appreciate the due diligence and the documentation sent over today and look forward to further documentation. I would move approval of both papers.
Thank you, Councilor Behrs. Vice President Carviello. Thank you, Mr. President. To the chair, to the superintendent, before we install all these HEPA filters in the buildings, is all the ductwork going to be cleaned, the current ductwork going to be cleaned and disinfected?
So, I mean, based on what the engineering reports will show to us, I believe as everything's being worked on that everything will be cleaned or made to the appropriate standard, you know, possible because filters need to be added and there are a lot of other recommendations. So in just the natural course of getting the systems up and running, that would need to happen.
Well, I mean, I don't want to be putting brand new filters on ductwork that hasn't been cleaned and disaffected. So I think that was the question that I asked. So is that going to happen before we do this?
I can't speak to the steps in which, or the order in which it's going to happen. I do know that we do need filters. I don't know how the ducts would be sanitized per se, but I would believe that they're going to be putting filters onto the HVAC systems.
that they would definitely have to clean it before you put, you know, even when you get your air conditioning serviced at home, they clean it and they put in new filters. So I can't speak to the exact steps because, you know, I'm not, you know, an engineer that can address the, you know, appropriate steps, but I would definitely say that yes, they would have to clean it. You wouldn't want to,
you know, once you take out an old filter and you put in a new filter, that they would appropriately clean it before they added the next filter in. Again, I can't, you know, I'm not an HVAC expert, but I, you know, could not see them not taking the appropriate steps to get our system fully functioning based on what the reports are saying to us.
I would ask that you make that part of your report to them that these vents be cleaned and disinfected before they come back online. No, no, we can definitely do that. That can definitely be part of, once we get to the actual piece to say make sure all
and sanitized and before you add the new filters to it. Thank you Madam Superintendent.
Thank you, Mr. President. I was wondering if we, I asked the question earlier, I'm not sure if I got an answer. If the school administration knows how much, or maybe Mr. Rodriguez, how much money is available in the CARES Act and also the COVID funds for safety purposes within our public schools? Would someone like to, would David Murphy or David Rodriguez or Superintendent Edward Vincent have the answer to that?
I think Mr. Rodriguez might be able to speak specifically to that.
to the council as soon as possible. It was an allocation of $225 per student. directly for mitigation efforts.
And Mr. President, I have a question for the superintendent of schools regarding what is the current school policy on the rental of our buildings? So for buildings that are being rented, they have to go and be approved through the Board of Health, first and foremost. So at the high school, we do have one of the churches using the high school
care and theater, the little theater. And in order for that space to be used, it has to be used at a reduced capacity, which is following the governor's guidance. And in addition to that, the renters had to submit what their COVID-19 protocols would be to the board of health. And so they had to put specific things in place. The custodian sanitized,
and clean the spaces before and afterwards. They have one door that's used for an entrance, a separate door that's used for an exit way. So there are safety protocols that are put in place so that traffic, people are not crossing each other and they are maintaining social distancing. They are wearing their masks. So they have to, before anything is approved, it has to, that plan has to be approved through the Board of Health.
And that's what the renters are doing. They are meeting the standards that have been set for them. And we as a district, we are sanitizing and cleaning those spaces appropriately. So Madam Superintendent, I am astonished. We're talking about safety and health of our students, our faculty, our teachers, staff within our schools. Why we would introduce
hundreds of people that wouldn't necessarily be in our buildings into our buildings through the rental of our buildings. So it's not hundreds of people because the county theater has a capacity of maybe 400. And at any given time, it's probably filled at a quarter capacity.
so it is not hundreds of people that are in the building. I also want to state that I have been in the building every single day, along with the custodians, along with the secretaries, along with all of the staff that are physically reporting to work at the high school complex every day, and the building is being cleaned and sanitized. And as a normal citizen, I go to stop and shop, I go to CVS, I practice,
proper hygiene in terms of hand-washing, wearing a mask, using hand sanitizer, because we cannot allow the virus to stop us from living and from doing our daily living activities. And if there is fear that any part of the school is going to be rented, then that fear is also going to carry over to students being allowed to come into the building. So we need to be able to...
Thank you, Mr. President, and I was just trying to finish my thought, and I appreciate the superintendent's response. However, Mr. President, when I say hundreds, I said hundreds, and it's really thousands because it's not the one Saturday or Sunday they're in our building. It's over a course of time. So to sit back and say it's only a couple of hundred,
That may be true for one given weekend, Mr. President, or two, but not over the course of the year. It's thousands of people being introduced into our schools. And why subject students, staff, Mr. President, to the additional people coming into the building? And I understand and appreciate there's protocols and procedures, and they have to get signed off from the Board of Health.
And I can appreciate that, Mr. President. But in my opinion, when you have people from outside that are coming into the buildings, you're not sure what precautions they may be taking. They may sign a paper, Mr. President, but when they're in that building, what type of supervision is there? What type of protocols are being put in place to make sure, Mr. President, that our kids, our staff, our teachers are being safe when they enter the building the next day?
Why risk it, Mr. President? They're using our buildings, Mr. President. They're using classrooms. They're using cafeterias. They're using gymnasiums. They're using restrooms. They're using auditoriums. Now, you're telling me, Mr. President, that our staff, who are very capable at the high school, are going to make sure that every inch of the high school or the McGlynn School or any other school is sanitized, every inch of the building.
I have a tough time believing that, Mr. President. In the interest of safety that we're talking about and health, I would respectfully ask that the school committee look back at their policy and stop the policy of renting the buildings, Mr. President, until we're able to get this situation under hand. I realize it's a revenue source for the schools. I understand that, Mr. President, that we count on. But safety should come first.
I've heard from a number of parents, a number of faculty members that are concerned about going back into the buildings because of the rentals.
So I would respectfully ask the superintendent and the school committee, along with the administration, revisit the policy on renting the buildings, Mr. President, until we can get a better handle on our children going back. The issues that we're going to be confronting, not only with the rentals, Mr. President, but just going back to school in general under a COVID new society.
Why compound it with the rentals of the building? It makes zero sense to me. And no one's going to tell me otherwise, Mr. President. Thank you. Thank you, Councilor Marks. Councilor Peers. Thank you, Mr. President. I just think the same logic could be applied to having council meetings and other board and committee meetings at City Hall and City Hall staff. Thank you. Thank you, Councilor Peers. If I may, John McLaughlin, if you're still with us.
John McLaughlin. I'm trying to unmute John. John. Oh, sorry. Hold on one second. I've got to get my earplugs. No worries. My daughter's over with a bunch of her friends, so they wanted to get the fire going. I apologize. No worries.
Just let me know when you're ready and I'll...
John, you can start. I'm on. OK, thank you. So a couple of questions. So with regard to the roof fans, as a past graduate of Medford High School, are you familiar with the complex? Mr. President, could you say that again? As a graduate of Medford High School, I'm very familiar with the complex. So are we replacing all of the roof fans?
Yeah, we were intended on replacing them all, yes. We weren't going to get into diagnostics because we figured it would be more of an expense and it would be easier if we just went up there and replaced them all.
So when you replace the fans, are you cutting into the roof? Or how does that work? I don't mean to get into that. No, no, no. You unhook the fan that's currently there and replace it with another one. No, you would not be cutting on the roof. OK. I was just curious as far as I know, like when I was in the school committee, and we always had roof issues. So I just didn't want to solve one problem but create another. So that's what my question was going there. Nope. It wouldn't do that at all. It's just replacing existing motors.
in hoods that are up there currently. Okay, thank you very much. Are there any other questions from the council?
Mr. President, I would respectfully ask if the superintendent, I know she was trying to answer my questions and comments, if she can finish with her statement. Yes, Superintendent Ron Vinson, I'm sorry I didn't cut you off, but Councilor Marks had the floor, so if you could please continue with your comments, I'd greatly appreciate it.
And so essentially the comments that I was making were in regards to the rentals. And I think Councilor Beers made the equally valid point of saying that the chambers and City Hall are also used for other events. I do feel that we need to get students back into school. We need to use good judgment.
When our buildings are rented, we have security on hand. We have our custodians who get to work on the weekends and get overtime. So we have custodians who are ready, willing to clean and sanitize and follow the COVID procedures that we have in place. And yes, if we're renting a space, people do need to use the facilities from time to time. So the bathrooms will be cleaned and sanitized as well.
The school committee did vote that we can rent our building spaces and work with some of the partners that we've had for a long time, provided they meet the standards that the Board of Health has put before them. And so all of those that are using any of our buildings, they've met those standards, and that's why they've been able to use this space. Those are my final remarks.
Any other questions from the council? Mr. President, I just want to go on record that I disagree 100% with the rental of our buildings during this particular phase of COVID-19 based on the health and safety of our students, our faculties, our administrators, our teachers, and everyone else within our buildings, Mr. President. Thank you, Councilor Marks. Is the Board of Health Director on the call? Is she still here?
I don't think so, but I could be wrong. While you're looking, I think it's very important that Councilman Marks brings up a good point. The difference between having meetings here, this is our job. This is open for the community to get things done, whether it's voting, whether it's councils, city school committee meetings.
What Council Marks, I believe, is bringing up is an option. We have options whether to keep those schools closed and making sure that we're taking our precautions to the total responsibility that we have to make sure they're safe and clean. The difference of having people in this building, this is where we do the people's work.
Not to rent for a outside church group that's not even from Medford, or whether it's from Medford or not, or whether it's an athletic program or a dance or whatnot. These are things that, what I'd like to ask the health director, and I'll do that via email if she's not on, is I'd like the protocol that she used to allow 400 people to enter our schools.
But then limit this body to close the doors for the people that want to come to a podium. So everybody here in this room, everybody in this room, they've been putting themselves out there. They're shopping in supermarkets. They're handing out ballots. They're coming to these meetings. So we know.
That if that's the case, this building should be open. So this is going to be interesting to see what our Board of Health Director is going to answer these questions, because I, too, agree with Councilor Mox. The job that's done in this room is the business. The job that's going outside in those schools right now, that's for profit. And I don't think that's the equivalent for safety. I just don't.
Thank you. Thank you, Councilor Scott. Kelly, Councilor Morrell. Thank you, Mr. President. Yeah, I don't really think this is the appropriate forum to debate signs at this point. I move approval of both papers. Second. Councilor Nonson, what's the motion? I move approval of both papers. And I second. Thank you. I think, Clerk Cardavis, did you mention that there was someone wanted to comment on this? Mr. President, Sean Beaman from 362 Lawrence Road.
the city has the following question. Has anyone asked the teachers union whether, if this contemplated HVAC work is completed at the high school, will the teachers return to the building? Has the union made that commitment? I think what I would say in response is that the work that we're undertaking to ensure that our infrastructure
or exceeds the safety standards being set by public health officials has been a significant part of the dialogue, ongoing dialogue that we have with all of our collective bargaining partners. I didn't want to speak for them and certainly wouldn't want to make any representations as to what they have communicated in the course of those negotiations, but I would say that we
studies and the analysis that is part of what we've been talking about here tonight. The various engineering firms that we've retained have been an important part of the conversations that we're having with our bargaining partners. And I think that the one point that we've made throughout the course of our discussions with teachers and the other unions is that we recognize that the advocacy for
on behalf of safety, certainly recognize the importance of getting students into school and continuing their education process as early as possible. And those advocating for people for having in-person learning recognize that safety is a basic entitlement that everyone who enters the school should expect. So I think that we're trying to keep that dialogue as constructive as possible and recognizing the value from what may seem like inflicting points of view is something that's always important to remember.
Mr. President. Thank you. Counselor Scott Kelly. If I can, I did have discussions with the union president, and I think they're waiting for the word on the air quality test as well. So I think everybody's on the same page, but I believe they haven't heard back from the administration about any of the results, and I think we're still waiting for those. So I think that once that's done, I think we'll have a better understanding what the teachers union
And I think that for the discussions I've had with different teachers, if they get those assurances, I'm sure they want to get back to school too. So I've talked to many of them and they want to get back to the classroom. So thank you. Thank you, Councilor Scarpelli. Councilor Night. Mr. President, thank you very much. I don't have much to say about the paper, but I did want to
Welcome aboard, Assistant Superintendent Murphy, and thank him for going through his initiation this evening as his first appearance before the Memphis City Council. I do look forward to meeting him in a less formal setting, and I wish him all the best in his new endeavor. Thank you, I appreciate that. I look forward to coming back and reporting to your honorable body as to how we are being good fiscal stewards of the community's taxpayer dollars. On the motion, Mr. President. Thank you. On the motion of.
Councilor Morrell. Vice President Caviello, seconded by Councilor Behrs, as amended by Councilor Knight. Clerk Harnaby, please call the roll. Council Behrs. If I may, one minute.
Mr. Clerk, Councilor Marks. This vote includes that the school administration will provide us with a list of priorities and recommendations as soon as we get them from engineering reports, correct? What's the amendment? Can you please read the amendment?
Council night's amendment was to use the farm. It was to allow the schools to use the funds across the school district, not just at the high school. Okay, was that the only amendment? That is the only thing. Vice President Carabiello asked for a list of improvements to be made, but he didn't offer in the form of an amendment. I will second it. Okay, let's see. So if we could make that in the form of an amendment, please.
That would be fine. That's similar to the superintendent stating that she would honor that amendment. So I would vote that. I didn't get that last amendment from Council Mars. Let's see. The last amendment was from, I believe, Vice President Caviello. OK. So Vice President Caviello's request for a list was an amendment, OK? OK. Do you have that? I have it, yes. OK, perfect. So on the motion of?
Vice President Caviello, seconded by Councilor Behrs as amended by Councilors Knight and Councilors Marks. Clerk Artemis, please call the roll. Was it Councilor Marks or Vice President Caviello who just made the last amendment? They were co-sponsors of the amendment and I moved to second them all. Vice President Caviello. Thank you. Councilor Behrs? Yes. Vice President Caviello? Yes. Councilor Knight? Yes. Councilor Marks? Yes. Councilor Morrell?
Councilor Morrell? Yes. Councilor Scarpelli? Yes. I'm starting here, Councilor Scarpelli. Yes. Yes? He said yes. Thank you. President Fevella? Yes. Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative. The motion passes. We're under suspension, Mr. President. Paper 20517, the companion paper to the paper that was just on the table. Move for approval. Second. That would be 20516.
So we took seven first? We took seven first. Yeah. Well, let's give them the big money now. Still second. I gotta read it really quick. 20-516 to the honorable president and members of the Memphis City Council, City Hall, Memphis, Massachusetts, 02155, dear Mr. President and city councilors, I respectfully request and recommend that your honorable body reprogram surplus proceeds in the amount of $700,000
$703,489.80 from the Medford High School Science Labs Project to the Medford High School School Improvements Project in accordance with Mass General Law Chapter 44, Section 20. Finance Director Alicia Nunley-Benjamin is present to answer any of the council's questions regarding this matter. On the motion of council tonight-
Can we amend this to also allow these funds to be used for other schools, as we did for the last paper? There's no amendments on this. If someone wants to make amendments- I would second that motion. Mr. President, why don't we transfer all the amendments from the past paper to this paper? On the motion of Councilor Knight, seconded by Councilor Beers to transfer all of the amendments from the first paper to the second paper. Clerk Urtubis, please call the roll. I second.
Yes. Yes. Yes.
Councilor Morrell. Yes. Councilor Scarpelli. Yes. President Falco. Yes. 7-8 affirmative, 0 negative. The motion passes. Vice President Carviello. Move this motion. OK. Move for approval. Second. On the motion of Council Light, 2 approves. Seconded by? Second. Councilor Behrs. Clerk Curtis, please call the roll. Councilor Behrs. Yes. Vice President Carviello. Yes. Councilor Neidt. Yes. Councilor Neidt. Yes.
Councilor Marks? Yes. Councilor Morrell? Yes. Councilor Scarpelli? Yes. President Falco? Yes. 70 affirmative, zero negative. The motion passes. Mr. President, while we're under suspension. Mr. President, while we're under suspension, if we could take paper 20540. Yes. On the motion of
Vice President Caviello to take paper 20540, seconded by Councilor Knight. Let's see, petitions, presentations and similar papers.
Petition for common vigilance license by Mohamed Anwar 2292, Boston Turnpike, Coventry, Connecticut 06238 for the Anwar Group Incorporated, DBA 711, 133 Main Street, Memphis, Massachusetts 02155. On file, business certificate number 128, building department, fire department, police traffic impact, health department, letter of compliance, state tax ID, workman's compensation, petition and treasurer.
At this point, I recognize the Chairperson on Licensing, Councilor Scott Kelly. Thank you, Mr. President. Is the petitioner available? Do we have Mr. Anwar with us? I know the petitioner was notified. I don't know if the petitioner is on the call. I can't tell from the listing. Let's see, if Mohamed Anwar, if you are on the Zoom call, could you please raise your hand?
I don't recognize anything but Okay on the motion of Top all night second of a vice-president caveat to table this paper. Clark Artemis, please call the roll Thoughts of bears. Yes
Yes. Yes. Yes.
Councilor Scarpelli. Yes. Rosario Falco. Yes. 7 in the affirmative, 0 in the negative. The motion of the paper is tabled. Mr. President, while we're under suspension. On the motion of Councilor Marks to revert to the regular order of business, seconded by Vice President Carviello, Clerk Hernandez, please call the roll. Councilor Behrs. Yes. Vice President Carviello. Yes. Councilor Knight. Yes. Councilor Marks. Yes. Councilor Morrell. Yes.
Councilor Scarpelli? Yes. President Fevella? Yes. 7 in the affirmative, 0 in the negative. The motion passes 2-0-526. Under motions, orders, and resolutions offered by Councilor Knight, we have resolved that the Memphis Historic Commission furnish the city council with copies of its annual report filed with the mayor as required by section 48-33 of the code of Memphis ordinances compiled for the years 2016 through 2019. Councilor Knight?
Mr. President, thank you very much. I think this is a rather self-explanatory resolution. However, the reason that it's being filed is not so self-explanatory. Here in our community now, I've never served on the council at a time where I've gotten more calls.
about permits being delayed, demolition delays, and the like, Mr. President. And I'd like to take a review of the annual reports as required by the Historical Commission to be filed with the administration to take a look at what's going on. My brief research on this topic has shown me, Mr. President, that since 2009,
There have been over 50 plus cases where demolition delay has been implemented in the community, but only four homes have not been demolished during this time. Four buildings, I should say, not even homes, buildings. Four buildings have not been demolished.
the success rate is minimal, is minimal at this point in time. So I have a number of questions like, have these four homes been restored or did they just not get demolished? Were they restored to a historic state or were they left there to just be the same way that they were before they were deemed to be historically significant or preferentially preserved? Do these 50 plus cases include applicants who are delayed and withdrew their appeal?
the 18 month or the six month period was up at the time, Mr. President. I'm getting a lot of pushback and a lot of phone calls about people who feel as though the demolition delay is being used as a weapon against them for not complying with certain requirements and certain things that are being demanded of them. And it's starting to become very problematic, Mr. President. And the reason I say it's problematic is because when we look at what's going on in this community right now, when we look at our financial situation here in this community,
If we don't embrace development in the very near future, I'm going to say we don't have the ability to meet our payroll next year. For the past five years, we've generated at least $1.5 million in new growth in this community. And that $1.5 million is necessary for us to just meet the contractual obligations of our payroll. This fiscal year, we've estimated our new growth to be at $1 million, not $1.5 million as it has been for the past five years.
This coupled with the fact that we have certain sectors of our economy that we need to bring back, like the restaurant industry and the hotel industry. Because those sectors allow us to raise additional revenues here for the community, Mr. President. So I think we've done a great job in expanding the offerings that we have for outdoor dining in the community. And we need to do that because the meals tax is a benefit.
that we get when our restaurants do well. And the same goes for our hotels. If hotels are being turned over, we get a tax on that, Mr. President. And right now, with one in five adults out of work, 20% unemployment across the commonwealth, I think it's important for us to look down the line a little bit at what the financial situation is going to be in this community. And unless we start embracing development, generating permitting fees and new growth, we're not going to be
in a strong financial position come this time next year. And a lot of this, I think, surrounds some of the work that's being done relative to demolition delay. And now the next layer of that, which is going to be if you want a permit for basic
repairs or modifications to your home, you're also going to have to go before that other layer of bureaucracy and potentially be subject to an 18 month delay in the issuance of your permit. And I think that's a problem, Mr. President. So I raise this issue because we've asked for a committee of the whole on this months and months ago. It hasn't happened. We've asked for reports. We haven't gotten them. We haven't gotten them.
So here I am looking at this saying, what can we do in this community to help dig us out of this economic crisis? Well, one of those things we can do is develop wisely. Another thing we can do is generate permitting fees through development that's going to bolster.
When we sat down and we talked about the budget, the biggest thing we talked about was the $2.4 million deficit in forecasted permitting fees out of the building department. And how are we going to climb out of this hole? Well, I can tell you by making people who want to invest in our community jump through hoops for 18 months.
That's not going to do anything to jumpstart our economics, that's not going to do anything to generate more permitting fees, and that's not going to do anything to put us in a better economic and financial situation here in the community. Preserving historic homes is important, but I think we're going a bit too far at this point now, Mr. President. I think we're going a bit too far, and I think we really need to look at it, because quite frankly,
If you have someone that wants to do a development in this community and they're subject to the demolition delay, the next thing that happens is the historical commission presents itself as a design review board. That says, well, show us your designs and if we like them, then we'll let you move forward. But nothing's to say that the designs that they show the historic commission are going to be approved by the ZBA. So we have a situation where we have someone that's looking to invest money in this community.
who could be held up for 18 months at historic and then have to go through the whole process of the ZBA where they may or may not ever, ever get an approval for any design that they're seeking to implement in this community if variance is needed. I just think that it's very unfair, Mr. President, and rule number one in government for me has always been do no harm. Do no harm, rule number one in government. We had to help people, not hurt people. And when someone comes into the community and buys a parcel and wants to knock it down,
And when they buy the parcel, the home's just a junky home. And when they want to knock it down, it becomes historically significant. And they've invested $750,000, $600,000, their life savings into these parcels.
It's a life changing decision that's being made by a board or a commission that can harm these individuals. And I think it's very important, Mr. President, that we revisit the criteria, the circumstances, and the processes that we have in place when it comes down to the demolition delay or portions thereof. We spoke about it several weeks ago.
And we called for a need for a committee of the whole on this. And I ask that it be scheduled sooner rather than later. And the reason I ask is because people are being hurt. People are being hurt financially in their pocket. When one in five adults in the Commonwealth of Massachusetts are unemployed and people are coming to Medford looking to invest money.
I think we should embrace them and work with them, not against them, Mr. President. So with that being said, I ask for these reports to be issued and furnished to the council so that I can review them further and prepare myself for a committee of the whole, which is going to be scheduled. I have faith and confidence that it's going to get done, Mr. President. I know we're working under very strange circumstances these days. I feel like I'm at the zoo right now.
Zoo, circus, the case could be made for either. But with that being said, Mr. President, I ask my council colleagues to support this resolution to get this information so that when we do have this further discussion and this further dialogue, we're all well informed as to what goes on, what the process is, and what the pros and cons of our ordinance is right now and how it affects people. So with that being said, I ask my council colleagues to support the resolution.
Thank you, Council Knight. And Jeff, I may add really quick, that Committee of the Whole will be scheduled soon, as will, I'm working on the scheduling now for that, for rodents and for our big zoning meeting. So I can assure you that will be coming soon. Both equally important issues, Mr. President. Absolutely, so they're all on the agenda and they'll all be coming up soon. So thank you, Council Knight. And let's see, we have Councilor, Vice President Caviello.
Thank you, Mr. President. Councilman Knox, I'm sorry, Councilman Nutt is 100% right. We'll make it through this year with what we have, but next year is going to be a very trying year for us. Monies that we've normally had in the past aren't going to be coming in.
restaurants, sales, all these little things. And your building department generates millions of dollars in building permits for the city. Like it or not, development is a necessary part of the growth of a community, no matter what kind. And here we are.
We're stunting growth in this community, even on these small projects. So again, I support Councilor Knight on this, and I'll second the motion from this. But again, we have to look for ways to generate money for this community, and we can't be chasing people away from this community. So we need to start embracing some things. Thank you, Mr. President. Thank you, Vice President Cabrera. Point of information, Councilor Knight.
And I'm not talking about developers, Mr. President, like Locust Street or like Moderna or Mill Creek. I'm talking about the local builder. I'm talking about someone that wants to come in and make an investment in the community, someone that's going to maybe renovate a home. Maybe come in and do an addition to a house. Maybe someone that's going to come in and knock down a parcel that's
a single family home in an apartment two district and create a tax base for us with an apartment there that complies with the existing zoning. That's what I'm talking about, Mr. President. I'm not talking about these big wig developers that are coming in here from Boston that are just going to throw millions and millions of dollars away. I'm talking about builders that have a very small margin.
And if they're tied up for eight, nine, or ten months and it costs them $80,000 to $100,000, they have a very difficult time surviving. And when you look at these small builders, you also have to understand that they probably employ between 50 and 60 people. 50 and 60 people that are going to be doing a job in this community, that are going to have the opportunity to spend their money in our local business districts for lunch.
in our gas stations to gas up their cars, in our local hardware stores to pick up supplies. So it all goes to the circular flow of our economy, Mr. President. But I think it's very important that we look at this, and I know that we have a number of items on the agenda, and I don't want to go any longer than I already have. So thank you very much. Thank you, Councilor Knight. Councilor Morrell.
you. Thank you, Mister President. Yeah, I want just to address one point. I know there are a number of things that were maybe misrepresented in that in those talking points that were actually addressed in this large packet. We got this this week, but I do just want to point out the fact that to your own calculations to counsel night's own calculations that over 11
50 homes over 11 years, that's about five homes a year. I just want to address the scare tactics being used in that. I don't think that's exactly millions of dollars that have been lost because of a demo delay at five homes a year. Thank you. Thank you, Councilor Orell. Point of information, Councilor Knight. Not a scare tactic, a fact. There were 50 plus homes that have gone through the demolition delay and only four were saved. That's not a scare tactic. That's the truth. That's the facts that were included in the packet that were given to us by the
Medford Historic District Commission. And it came in the packet this evening, even though we've asked for it, I can't tell you how many months ago. And the packet that it came in this evening is unrelated to the council request that came back previously. Not a scare tactic, Mr. President, just a fact. Thank you, Councilman. Any other questions or comments from the council? Yeah, I've had my hand up since we started, so just FYI.
Yeah, I mean, a few things here. So one, I don't disagree that bringing in revenue is important. I think it's a little dangerous to be making land use and development decisions primarily on how they affect city revenue, although I do agree it's an important decision. I think more importantly, though, is the larger question of process. Last week, I helped a family work through the we've had this thing where now the building department is correctly
going through and making sure that the Historical Commission has at least seen permits when they go out and they've built a new online system to do just that. I helped a family last week who was having an issue with the delay and quite frankly the delay isn't from the Historical Commission. The issue has been in the building department. A permit was issued and then the building department said,
hold on a minute, we need to check. And then five days later, I made a couple calls, the building department sent it over to the historical commission, and that day, the historical commission brought it back. So these permits are sitting for days in the building department. The historical commission, when they get them, is turning them out the same day, if possible, and most of the time. So, you know, I just think we need to allow
or encourage the building department to accelerate the work, make sure they have the resources they need, as is well taken the amount of permits that are happening, make sure they have the resources to process them and get them over. I don't think the blockage here is the historical commission. And quite frankly, if you've driven down West Street, you can see the travesty that's happened on West Street, where a historical home has been turned into a monstrosity, and there's no new units.
It's still a single family home. It's just giant and takes up the lot now. So, you know, it's due diligence. I don't think the historical commission is the problem here. So if we can accelerate this process in the building department, get everything over, I think we'll be just fine. And maybe we can avoid some of this stuff like what's happening over on West Street. Thank you, Mr. President. Thank you, Councilor. One minute, Councilor.
Councilor Knight. I certainly support the councilor's position to accelerate the process. Maybe that's why we need to look at whether or not an 18-month delay is appropriate or whether it should be reverted back to six. Thank you, Councilor Knight. Mr. President. We have Councilor Morrell, and then we'll Councilor Morrell. Yeah, Mr. President, if I could just draw attention to rule number 17 of the council, just upon debatable merits, a councilor shall speak no more than three times or more than 15 minutes on a single issue. I think that's something that gets railroaded on this council often, and I just want to highlight that. Thank you.
She'll make a motion for the chair to make a ruling. Thank you, Council Member. Councilor Pierce. Thank you, Mr. President. Yeah, I don't think the issue here is the length of the demo delay. There's hundreds, if not thousands, of permits issued in this city. There's 50 over 10 years that have been subject to demo delay, and four have not been demoed, which, in my opinion, is a net benefit to the city. But again, I think the issue is making sure the building department has the resources to make sure this process moves well. I think people are doing good work.
the assertion that the historical commission's functioning as a design review board is really reflective of the work they're doing. They're taking a quick look. And 99% of the time, everything is moving through the process. And I think, you know, if we can get resources to the building department to make sure that process moves quickly, that's something we should do. Thank you, Mr. President. Thank you, Councilman Piers. Let's see, we have Thompson, are you all set? I am, Mr. President. Just a request for information.
Thank you, Councilman Knight. Okay, we have enough people that want to speak on this. Cheryl R., let's see, I'm going to try to unmute you. Cheryl, may I ask you to name and address for the record, please?
I'm Cheryl Rodriguez, 281 Park Street. I just want to clarify that the goal of the demo delay is not necessarily to stop demolition, so it's not failing. The length was increased to 18 months because we had a particular developer in the city who was refusing to engage with the historic mission because the time was short enough that it was profitable enough for him to just ignore them and wait it out. The 18-month period is rarely, if ever, used to its entirety, but it is an encouragement for the
to be redirected to rezoning.
waiting to be further blighted to increase their odds of gaining variances in the future. Perhaps you could focus on having some fees to prevent these types of developers from leaving these parcels intentionally empty to increase their profit margins in the future. This could immediately add money to the city of Medford coppers to be used in the way that Mr. Knight would like to have them.
The sale for flippers is misguided. It's being quickly used to price out residents. These homes that are being purchased are not all in knock-down condition. They are being purchased by flippers because the parcels the homes sit on are large enough for them to squeeze in an additional home on the property. So they're being purchased for spec rather than to be used by end residents.
This is not about the home condition. Every flip increases the assessments in those neighborhoods, which are increasing the cost for all of those who live around them. I welcome you to also embrace looking at assessments across the city, because there are some neighborhoods
that are being, seeing their assessment jump by leaps and bounds, but despite the fact that our homes are not increasing in value at these rates, but are being increased based on the comps from the flips, there are neighborhoods that are not seeing their assessments jump to this level, and those people seem to think they're paying not enough taxes, and I completely agree with them. So please call for an assessment review in the city so that we can
to realize that not everyone's house is worth what the flip next door is saying it is. Thank you, Cheryl. Point of information, Councilman Knight. Mr. President, I do believe statutorily, underneath the Department of Revenue, we are required to do real valuation every, I believe it's eight years, a defined period of eight years, every eight years we do a
It's 05 is it now? I think I might have changed it. So we actually do have a team that goes out into the community and does assessments, real assessments based upon appraisals as required by the Department of Revenue and in compliance thereof.
you are correct. I'm happy to send you some, a few addresses that you can compare to mine and see that my assessment has jumped by a couple of hundred thousand dollars and Maryland's nowhere near that. So it's not being done evenly applied across the city, which is why I asked for an audit.
Thank you. Thank you, Cheryl. Let me, I just want to remind everybody you have a minute and a half when you speak or have your question. I will now call upon, let's see, Will Navar? I'm sorry.
Thank you, President Falco, William Navarro, 108 Medford Street, apartment B. I think it's really, the canonical example here, we have a single-family home turned into a bigger single-family home. The original single-family home was unaffordable to ordinary working people, and the new single-family home was unaffordable to working people.
So I consider that a net, not very much at all, other than I guess we get some more revenue. So I think it's important to look at the zoning. Make sure maybe when we do that, you see these lots, they seem fairly underdeveloped because you see the land value has gone up insane amounts because City of Boston is a very desirable place to live and work.
And the house, it's just unlikely you have a $350,000 lot with a $200,000 building on it. I just don't think that makes a lot of sense. But ideally, rather than just build a massive single family home, we could build a duplex, triplex, tripledecker, something like that.
And as for Miss Rodriguez's point about Mystic Avenue, she talked about a fee. I would say, before we talk about a fee for leaving property blighted, let's just stop giving a discount to blighted property. You put up a nice building, your taxes go up, you tear it down, your taxes go down. Why do we do it that way? It makes no sense. Tradition is the answer, but it's not solving problems here or really anywhere.
So I hope we can take a look at that and about the zoning so that way we can, you know, zone so that families can sort of share the expensive land value by living in a duplex, triplex kind of thing. Thank you. Thank you, Will. Let's see. Next up is Kelly Catalo. Name and address for the record, please.
I'm not saying that
this is not just about the 18
I think we can get everybody to the same meaning we can come up with some great resolutions that benefit everybody. Thank you. Thank you.
And I think it's a growing
I'd like to echo my fellow residents, Cheryl and William's comments about the exacerbated change in values when developers and flippers take a parcel and take a single or a two-family and make mansions where those were, further eroding our housing affordability within the city.
And I want to just point out, when we say investing in a community, it's far more than dollars invested in a community. You can be highly invested in a community and not invest a penny. We have many people who advocate in this city, and they are investing in ways other than knocking down a house and putting up a new one. These developers are not investing in our community. They are investing in their projects, and they are doing it repeatedly.
lather, rinse, repeat. Madcalf, Walnut, Thomas,
Forest Street, Park Street, Court Street, Washington Street, Pleasant Street, Winthrop Street, Bower Street, South Street, just off the top of my head, the same thing over and over. Buy it for less than 500, sell one part of it for over seven. That does nothing to create housing affordability and everything to make these people a lot of money. And the gigantic holes in our zoning
and loopholes in our zoning perpetuate this. I would urge you, urge you to take on your primary responsibility of zoning review and zoning reform that creates purposeful development, that creates the things that are important to our community and does in fact invest in our community. Thank you so much for your time. Thank you. And our zoning kickoff meeting will be coming up on September 23rd, just to let everyone know.
Next up, we have Ryan Haywood. Ryan, I'm about to unmute you. If you could please have your name and address for the record, please. You have a minute and a half. Ryan. Ryan Haywood? Okay, we'll skip over Ryan.
Clerk Carter Beach, you said someone wanted to speak, I believe. Mr. President, that's correct. Paul Thumbel asked to speak.
Hi, thanks for giving me a second here. I just wanted to kind of lend a unique combination. And I spoke earlier this summer, if you don't recognize me, I had the huge beard last time some of you saw me. I have a good combination. I'm a local resident. I live on Douglas Road. I'm a small business owner. My wife is a builder. She comes from the architecture design world. So we are a small business owner in Medford and we,
on a very small scale are developing and building one or two projects in the Medford area a year. I'm also a tenured professor in the Business School of Northeastern, so I can kind of address, I see the vision of the economic impact that Councilor Knight had brought up.
And I know as a small business, we keep talking about these big developers, but as a small builder who lives and works in Medford, I quite literally invest my family's life savings every time we do a project.
The historical commission is a huge part of our city. I think in a different life, I would have been a history professor instead of a business professor. I love history. We strive in every project we do to save as much as we can. We have an obligation as a city to protect our history.
And I logged in today to talk about a project that's getting debated later in the call today. But I can tell you the economic impact that one of my small projects has. I hire 10 to 12 subs, subcontractors, sub-small business owners themselves. So we're talking council nice numbers is conservative.
50, 60, 70 people come on my projects, and that's just a small project. Tens of thousands of dollars in permit fees for my small projects. And so all of my employees, when they go out for lunch, they're eating in Medford Square. They're loving the Tanakh. They're loving the Goldilocks. They are shopping local. They're eating local every day.
The economic impact for me, if the Historical Commission can put my projects on hold for 18 months, could potentially bankrupt a small business owner like me. I cannot afford, at $5,000 to $8,000 a month, to wait for a potential hold to come through. If we get a full 18-month review, you're talking over $100,000 in financial impact. I'm one person. I don't have $100,000 to sit on.
Paul, your time is up. Thank you. I apologize for interrupting. I'm not sure what happened to Paul. Ryan Haywood was up next, but I. Ryan Haywood, name and address for the record.
I just want to point out to the City Council and just let everybody know here that we are, as a commission, taking note of everything that's being said. We do want to be helpful, and we want to get you guys the information that you need. So we'll be sure to send you over the information as soon as we can get it to you.
Councilor Night, seconded by? Second. Councilor Beers, Clerk Urnaby, please call the roll. Councilor Beers? Yes. Vice President Caraballo? Yes. Councilor Night? Yes. Councilor Marks? Yes. Councilor Morrell? Yes.
Yes. Councilor Morales, a yes? Yes. Councilor Scarpelli? Yes. President Falco? Yes. 7 in the affirmative, 0 in the negative. The motion passes. 20-527 offered by Council night be it resolved that the Memphis City Council extend its deepest and sincere condolences to the family of Edward Tyrantz on his recent passing.
Counselor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much. It's with deep sadness that I offer this resolution this evening. Eddie Terrence was a kid, I grew up with him, West Medford. A West Medford fixture, a West Medford legend. Had the opportunity of going to elementary school with Eddie, high school with Eddie, and always hanging out with him down the park.
Whether it be placed in a park or dug a park, playing basketball, everywhere in between, causing havoc, riding our bikes and the such, Mr. President. But Eddie passed away unexpectedly just over the last couple of weeks with a little heart problem, a little heart trouble. And he's no longer with us. And Eddie was the type of kid that made everybody around him just better. When Eddie was there, he put you in a better mood. He had a smile that could light up a room and a personality that could make the shyest person the most friendly person in the world.
A long time husband to Donna Doherty, CJ Doherty and Chuck Doherty's daughter and sister. And just an all around great kid, Mr. President. And I'm very sad to see him go and it's one of those.
situations where when someone's gone, you wish you had the opportunity to spend more time with them. And Eddie was one of those kids, and I don't think there's anybody that knows Eddie that could say right now that they wish they didn't spend more time with him now that he's gone. So with that being said, Mr. President, I ask my colleagues to join me in offering an offerings of condolences.
It's very unfortunate turn of events. I was on social media the other day and someone posted a picture. And it was a picture right across the hall in the mayor's office. And it was Eddie sitting down in Mayor McGlynn's chair with Mayor McGlynn next to him.
There was a kid named Cedric Taylor sitting next to Eddie, who's no longer with us as well, and Justin Springer. And if we think back to a couple months ago, this council just recognized Justin Springer for the work that he's done in the city of Boston, doing outreach and communications work with the less fortunate. So it's very sad, Mr. President, when you reach a certain age and you see a picture like that of kids you grew up with in elementary school and in junior high and in high school, and two out of three of them are gone, they're no longer with us.
So it just saddens me to see that he's gone, because like I said, he's a great person. And I'd ask my council colleagues to join me in supporting the family and offering this condolence to the family in this time of need. Thank you, Councilor Knight. At this point, I'd ask.
Yes, let's see, Councilor Marks. I want to thank Councilor Knight for putting this on. Those who knew Ed knew he was a great person and good person to be around and he will sorely be missed, Mr. President. I also would like to mention we lost a resident just recently, Giovanni Puccio.
On his recent passing, Mr. President, he was a tremendous father, husband, family man, and just a terrific guy. And he will be solely missed, Mr. President, as well. So I'd ask if my council colleague wouldn't mind putting that on as well, Mr. President. Mr. President. Thank you. Councilor Marks, thank you. And that will be added to the resolution as well as an amendment.
I'd like to thank Councilman Knight for bringing this up. What a great young man and working for Method Recreation and the boys at Duggar Park and Eddie's family and friends. I know how important he was to everybody.
And just a great, great young man. So my prayers to his family and our condolences. And I appreciate Councilor Mox bringing up Mr. Puccio's name. I know that it's tough when you don't have week after week meeting and people pass on in between. So this has been very difficult, but what a great person, left a great legacy.
His kids are committed, they're men and women that are committed to our community and making sure that they're giving back. And that's because he instilled that sense of community, and I think that he'll solely be missed. So my condolences to the Puccio family too, so thank you. Thank you, Councilor Scarpelli.
Let's see, so we will have a moment of silence in one second. We just have to vote on this first. So on the motion of Councilor Knight, as amended by Councilor Marks, and seconded by... Second. Councilor Scott Kelly. Councilor Morrell, did you want to speak on this? No, I was just getting my mic ready. Oh, okay. Okay. So on that motion, Clerk Hutterby, please call the roll.
Yes. Vice President Caravaglia. Yes. Council Knight. Yes. Council Marks. Yes. Council Morrell. Yes. Councilor Scarpelli. Yes. President Falco. Yes. On the 7 to 0 vote, the motion passes. Our thoughts and prayers are with the Tyrantz and Puccio families. At this point in time, I'd ask everyone to please rise for a brief moment of silence.
20-528 offered by Councilor Knight. Be it resolved that the Memphis City Council recognize the efforts of the community partner Armstrong Ambulance, most notably Gail Armstrong, Richard Armstrong, and Sean Mangan, for their contributions toward the success of the August 18th and 19th COVID-19 screening for Medford High School families. Councilor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much.
We've all been around Gail Armstrong, Richie Raymond, Sean Mangan at one point or another being involved in this community. And the outreach work that Armstrong Ambulance does and the give backs that they give to this community are innumerable.
Just recently, about a month ago, Armstrong Ambulance was tasked with the responsibility of helping do COVID testing for the MHS families up at Medford High School. And to say that that was a momentous task is an understatement. But through their efforts and that of our friends in the Board of Health, they were able to pull it off.
When you look at the testing that's been done in our community versus surrounding communities, you'll see that Medford's probably, at the time that this was done, about 1,000 tests ahead of the nearest community. I think the only community around here was Lynn that had tested more people than the city of Medford. So it goes to say and it goes to show that
The strength of community partnerships can go a long way in all aspects of public life, but especially public health here. We've seen the community rise up and come together during this coronavirus situation. And I think that the efforts in the work of Gail, Richie, and Sean shouldn't go unnoticed, Mr. President.
Not only in this endeavor, but in all that they do. Whether it comes to the free CPI training that they give to our coaches or the IADs that they've donated to our community. Armstrong does a lot, and I think it's important that we recognize what they do and the work that they do. So with that being said, I'm asking my council colleagues to support me in this agenda item this evening. Thank you, Councilman Knight. Vice President Caviello.
Thank you for bringing this up. The Armstrong family, Rich and Sean, they've been great people for our community. I mean, I've had the opportunity to work with them on many projects. I've been trained by Sean Manion many times to be CPS certified, Red Cross certified. So again, these are good people. They're there all the time. Long before the COVID, this company has been out there.
Anytime the community has needed some assistance with anything, they've been there. So again, I thank them for the work that they've done in our community. Thank you, Vice President Caviello. On the motion of Councilor Knight, seconded by- Second. Seconded by Vice President Caviello. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Behrs? Yes. Vice President Caviello? Yes. Councilor Knight? Yes. Councilor Knight?
have a motion to approve the
Councilor Strapelli? Yes. President Falco? Yes. Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative. The motion passes. 20-529 offered by Councilor Knight, be it resolved that the Memphis City Council be provided with a monthly report of crime statistics from the Chief of Police. Councilor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much. And I know Councilor Mox has a similar paper on the agenda this evening. I bring this paper forward.
Thank you, Mr. President. If my council colleague wouldn't mind adding my paper on to this, paper 20-542, where they are similar in nature. Sure. Would you like to make a motion to join the papers? Please. I second that motion and defer it to a senior member. On the motion of Councilor Marks, seconded by Councilor Night to join the papers, and that would be 20-529 off by Councilor Night.
542. 542 offered by Councilor Marks. That paper reads, be it resolved that the recent rash of break-ins and home invasions be discussed in the interest of public safety. Clerk Hertoghez, could you please call the roll on joining those two papers? Correct. And just so I'm clear, 20542, that was the emergency paper you added under suspension, Councilor Marks? Correct. OK. And this is to join the two.
Councilor Beres? Yes. Vice President Caraballo? Yes. Yes. Thank you. Councilor Knight? Yes. Councilor Marks? Yes. Councilor Morrell? Yes. Councilor Scarpelli? Yes. President Falco? Yes. Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative. The motion passes and the papers are joined. At this point I recognize Councilor Knight.
Mr. President, thank you very much, and thank you to Councilor Mox for allowing me to proceed first. I bring this paper forward, Mr. President, in light of a recent string of troubling events that have been brought to my attention. Home break-ins in the West Medford neighborhood, home invasions in the heights in South Medford, in the West Medford neighborhood.
We have a crime analyst, Mr. President, that we budgeted, and the crime analyst does an excellent job. And I know that our decision makers in the police department are using that data to make good policy recommendations and good policing recommendations. But I think it's also important, Mr. President, that we have the opportunity to review this data to see what type of crime is happening in our community, whether it's violent crime, whether it's crime of personal property, whether it's domestic violence, whether it is.
any number of identifiable trends or patents that will allow us to be dynamic and flexible in our response to it, Mr. President. I'm more than happy to sit down and discuss supplemental funding. I'm more than happy to sit down and discuss providing.
any department in this community with the tools that they need to succeed. And I think it's very important for us to have a good understanding as to what the trends are and what the patents are in this community, so that we can get ahead of it and invest money in certain areas that we need to invest money in. For example, we have Harold McGilvery, he's our dog officer. He's an awesome dog officer, he does a great job.
Maybe based upon the crime statistic and crime trends, we need two dog officers. We have a traffic division. We have a traffic division comprised of so many officers. Maybe based upon the crime statistics and the accident statistics, it shows that we should be having more officers in the traffic division and less officers in another division. Operational questions, Mr. President, certainly stuff that comes under the purview and scope of the Chief of Police.
But that's something that's contingent and reliant upon funding. And if we're going to be spending the money, I want to make sure we're spending it in the right place to make the most impact and the most bang for our buck. And with the uptick in violent crime in this community, I think this is something that we really need to look at. And I shouldn't even say it's an uptick, because I don't know, because I haven't seen the stats. I should say with the public reporting of violent crime of recent in the community, I'm wondering if this is something that we need to be worried about. So with that being said, I'm going to defer to Councilor Mox, Mr. President, but thank you very much for indulging me.
Thank you, Councilor Knight, Councilor Marks. Thank you, Mr. President. I want to thank my council colleague, Councilor Knight, for putting this on the agenda as well. For the past several years, Mr. President, I've called for a public safety summit within this community. And to date, I'm not proud to say that we have yet to have a public safety summit.
with all the parties to be within this community to discuss these very issues. And Councilor Knight may not say it, but I am going to say it, Mr. President. Violent crime is on the uptick in this community. And you only have to read the paper, watch the local news, and talk to your neighbors. And you'll hear what's happening in this community, Mr. President. From home invasions, to car break-ins, to home break-ins.
It's happening all over the community, and I think it's very important. I realize we do have a crime analyst in the community that's gathering crime data. But the data is only as good, Mr. President, when it's being used for.
So if it's not being used to update and provide the latest and greatest for our police department, then it's not good data. If it's not used, Mr. President, to get the word out to the community, and that is key. That is key in this community. I've talked to a lot of seniors in this community that are unaware, Mr. President, on what's happening. And I tell people constantly that may leave their front door open or their car unlocked to say, you know what?
Those days are behind us. I hate to say it, they're behind us now. And you should always proceed with caution. And I believe you should be locking your front door, even during the day, Mr. President. I believe you should be locking your car. You should be watching out for your neighbors. You should leave a light on.
that may deter someone from robbing a house or a car or so forth. But I think the announce of prevention goes a long way, the old saying. And we have to get word out to the community, not to alarm people, but to let them know what's happening.
To let them know that they should take extra precaution, Mr. President. And I ask that our police department step up patrol around the community. I ask that we do have this public safety summit to discuss some of the concerns we have.
Just recently, Mr. President, and I won't get into the details, we had a home invasion that involved a 92-year-old woman that luckily, Mr. President, was able to escape. because God knows what would have resulted if she was not able to escape, Mr. President. And there's been some scuttlebutt around the community that this person may have been part of.
a halfway house in the community, and living in our neighborhood, and living amongst us, Mr. President. And that raises some concern for residents, and rightfully so, Mr. President. So I think as a community, we have to take a step back and look at what's happening in our community, ways we can address issues, ways we can make our residents safer, Mr. President. We have a large percentage of seniors, and seniors are very vulnerable, Mr. President.
So that's my concern. I would ask once again that we create a public safety summit. I'm not sure why it's impossible to get a public safety summit together. I think I must have offered it three or four times. And I've yet to get any buy-in from the former chief or this chief or anyone else, Mr. President, administration or anyone else to sit down and discuss these issues.
Because this is hitting home now. It's not somewhere you're saying, well, this happens here or there. It's happening in our neighborhoods. It's happening to our neighbors. And it's concerning, Mr. President. So I just want to put that out there, that once again I ask for a public safety summit where we can sit down around the table and discuss some of the concerns we have. If it's funding, then as Councilor Knight mentioned,
then the council should be aware of that. If it's additional manpower, if it's additional tools that the police department needs to get the job done. If it's additional outreach, community outreach, then so be it to make sure that residents are aware of what's happening. I've asked in the past to use the reverse 911.
You know, it's great to get when there's a road race in the city and you get a reverse 9-1-1, but 9-1-1 is for emergency. What better emergency than if there are home invasions and people being attacked in our community, Mr. President? You know, and how blatant
when someone's sitting there and someone jumps through a picture window, a glass picture window, with the person sitting right there. They weren't trying to avoid detection. They weren't trying to avoid the person.
These are very serious incidences, Mr. President, and they need to be discussed and addressed. And I realize the police are probably working on their own, and things that they can't relay to the public, and I realize that. But I also believe the public should be well aware of what's going on, and we should be open and notorious when it comes to alerting residents of this community. And I want to thank my colleague for putting this on. Thank you, Councilor Mox. Councilor Behrs.
Thank you, Mr. President. Thank you, colleagues, for putting it on. I completely agree that we need to look at trends and patterns and really be able to analyze and make the best decisions possible. So I'd just, you know, I'd like to amend the paper for getting reports and data back to the year 2000, if possible. I understand that might take more time, so I'm not going to put a time limit on it, but I would love to be able to see the long-term trends. Thank you.
Thank you, Counselor Pierce. Point of information, Mr. President. Point of information, Counselor Knight. I do not believe we had a crime analyst going back that far. I think a crime analyst was something that
I believe in your first term, Councilor Scott-Pelly's first term was something that we had put into the budget. So while I think that the data exists in terms of paper records and paper files, there wasn't someone there that was actually working as a crime analyst compiling that stuff and looking at trends and patterns and the such. So I'd ask that it be offered in the B papers to not hold up the underlying paper that's been offered on top of it.
That's fine with me. I'm putting a timeline on it. It seems like there's data going back a few years. That could be really helpful, and maybe longer if it's there. Thank you, Councilor Behrs. Clerk Hutterby, do you have the language on the B paper? Yes, Mr. President. I have a question after that. Councilor Behrs originally offered an amendment, which is now a B paper, requesting reports and data back to the year 2000 on crime statistics.
if possible. OK. And then I have another question, if I may. Yep. Councilor Marks, you asked for a minute to the papers. I'm sorry, I didn't hear that. I didn't hear that. Did you say it was an amendment? Were you asking if it's an amendment?
I'm asking if Councilor Marks' request to create a public safety summit is an amendment to the papers. I didn't hear the answer. Yes. Thank you. Excuse me. Okay, so let's see. So we get a B paper from Councilor Behrs. Is that B paper seconded? Seconded. Seconded by Councilor Morrell.
We have Councilor Marks, did you wanna speak? Nope, okay. Councilor Knight. That's on from the beginning. Okay, I'm gonna shut it off. Okay, let's see. Okay, do we have any questions or comments from the public? Okay, seeing and hearing none. Okay, on the B paper, offered by Councilor Behrs, seconded by Councilor Morrell.
Court of Appeals, please call the roll. Councilor Behrs? Yes. Vice President Caraballo? Yes. Councilor Knight? Yes. I'm sorry, I didn't hear Councilor Knight. Yes. Thank you. Councilor Marks? Yes. Thank you. Councilor Morrell? Yes.
Councilor Scarpelli? Yes. President Franco? Yes. Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative. The motion passes. On the main paper offered by Councilor Knight and Councilor Marks. Seconded by Vice President Carviello. Clerk Carter, please call the roll. Councilor Behrs? Yes. Vice President Carviello? Yes. Councilor Knight? Yes. Councilor Marks? Yes. Councilor Morrell? Yes.
Councilor Scarpelli? Yes. President Franco? Yes. Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative, the motion passes. 20-530 offered by Councilor Morrell. Be it resolved that the Medford City Council demand that the MBTA reinstate bus routes 325 and 326 as they are an essential link to residents of Medford. Councilor Morrell.
Thank you, Mr. President. Yeah, I know this is something that has been raised by Councilor Marks a few months back when these two lines, which are the express lines from Medford, were suspended, as we were told, temporarily in the earlier days of the pandemic. We do have in our packet this week some back and forth from the mayor and Todd Blake with the MBTA, and the way the MBTA inevitably thanked the mayor for advocacy is suspending these routes indefinitely in mid-August.
So this is especially concerning to me because frontline workers, which are going into work every day, are people who are more likely to need public transportation. And we have essentially cut them off from these express routes, not we, the MBTA. And I did speak with our state delegation about this, and they are working on it.
What they told me that we can do is really show a unified front on this, so I'm just asking moving approval on this paper to really demand that the MBTA reinstate these essential links and help people from Medford get on those express routes into Boston where they need to go get to work. Thank you. Second, Mr. President.
Thank you, Councilor Morrell. On the motion of Councilor Morrell, seconded by Councilor Pierce. Councilor Scarpelli, you didn't want to- Thank you, Mr. President. Councilor Scarpelli. So I spoke with our state delegates with Councilor, Representative Donato and Representative Garbale. I think that I asked them for permission to hold a committee.
a subcommittee meeting on transportation to bring them back because the exact words they used, that they were lied to by the administration of the T. So that's bothersome considering those gentlemen and
And their partner in crime and Christine Barber have other people that make sure they get their funding needed to make sure their business runs. So these are the MO, this is the MO for the T that they promise and don't fulfill what they've asked, what they say when they come in. I know that we have many resolutions that can show that, so I did talk to our
representatives and did talk to a few people that traversed that route. And if we can, I know that we're very fortunate we have our city clerk that knows all the ins and outs and the people that need to be called. So I'm going to call on Adam Herterbees, if he can, to help us again.
To get those people that we need at a table, I think that before we do that, I think we need to do a ridership study that shows the numbers. I know the numbers are down right now, but that doesn't mean, that really doesn't mean anything because like we're saying, it's quality instead of quantity now. So we need those buses and
We'll be calling for a subcommittee meeting. They're ready to go whenever you are, Council President, where we can find a date that's open and get those representatives at a table to answer a lot of questions. I mean, we're also waiting for the Department of Transportation to still give us an answer on, ready, south of Maine. So as we're seeing traffic pick up now, there was a lull, so there wasn't a outcry, but as you're seeing the traffic
uptick that we're going to start seeing some issues again. It's something we need to do. So thank you, Mr. President. Thank you, Councilor Scarpelli. Councilor Behrs? Thank you, Mr. President. I think actually Councilor Scarpelli made most of the points. Again, it's just an example of
poor communication or directly false communication made to people in the city around this issue. So I completely agree. And I did not know that they were also sending their communications to our state delegation as well. So it sounds like we have some issues to address here. Thank you, Councilor Behrs. Councilor Knight. Mr. President, I find this ironic. I find it ironic that the MBTA cuts the express bus service that people take.
because
The other modes of transit that the t office is so inefficient and unreliable. I mean, ultimately, you take the bus, you take the 325. Counselor Mox takes the 325. You take the 325 because you don't want to take a bus to a train station and miss the bus or wait for a bus that's late to get to the train station to be packed in like a sardine or miss the first two trains when you get there because there's no room for you to get on the train. So it's nonsensical to me in a way, Mr. President. It's like they created these express lanes because people,
Needed to get to work and couldn't rely on the existing modalities that the MBTA was offering, right? So here we are now, going back, and they're going to cut these from our community, which is fine. They're going to cut them, okay, that's what you want to do. I'm assuming that there's going to be a corresponding cut in our assessment, because our assessment's based on the level of service that we receive. And if they're cutting our services, then they should also be cutting our assessments. So my question would be also, what impact does this have on the MBTA's assessment to the community of Medford, where they're cutting service for the bus line.
The assessments for our bus service should be cut as well. So I'd ask that question as to what the correlating assessment reduction with the reduction in these bus lines. I'd offer that in the form of an amendment. Thank you, Councilor Knight. So that is an amendment to the paper. Second the amendment. I'm still copying the amendment down.
Mr. President, I also neglected to- I also neglected to offer that as amendment too, that our clerk reach out to the state delegates who already know and the representatives from the T to one, begin by putting a study, a ridership study together and be prepared to hold a subcommittee on transportation as soon as possible.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
is to have the former MBTA Chief of Staff reach out to the State Delegation and the MBTA. And also to commission a ridership study. And then meet in the Subcommittee on Transportation. The State Delegates, correct. And the State Delegation, yes. Thank you. I'll take that former Chief of Staff too.
Thank you, Councilor Scarpelli. Thank you, Councilor Knight. Councilor Marks. Thank you, Mr. President. I want to thank Councilor Morrell for bringing this up. There's a pattern here. Over the last two years, mostly two years, the MBTA has tried to cut a number of bus routes.
over and over again, Mr. President, and residents have to stand up and fight and contact the T and contact the state delegation and the mayor and the city council. And it's pretty disturbing that an MBTA, that their chief mission is to provide access of transportation, and they're constantly looking to cut back.
transportation in surrounding communities. So that's number one, Mr. President. For full disclosure, I do, for the past four years, I've taken both the 325 and the 326. So some of this is from my own selfish standpoint, someone that takes that bus and has been on the bus with
many, many other people that rely on that bus for transportation to and from work, Mr. President. Counselor Knight hit the nail on the head. And I've been talking about this literally for, I hate to say it, probably close to 20 years.
Let me tell you. The MBTA has over $66 million in tax-exempt property in this community. Tax-exempt, Mr. President. $66 million that they don't pay the city of Method one nickel for. Their assessment to us for providing T services as of 2017 was about $3.7 million.
So that's what they charge us over and above when you pay a fare, when you get your T-card, when you pay 20% of the 5% sales tax. That's over and above we pay as a community, as Councilor Knight mentioned, for this particular service. So when we have an express bus, we have additional routes, people say, wow, Method has great access. We pay for it, Mr. President, in many surrounding communities.
Winchester, Arlington, you name it. They come to Method to jump on the express bus, or to get on the train in West Method, or to go to Wellington. They come into our community. We're paying a heavy assessment. And he's absolutely right. Back some years ago, I offered a motion, which was passed and sent to our state delegation many years ago, that we offset the T assessment.
based on the tax-exempt property they have in our community.
So if it's 3.7 million that they come and take from us to operate services, they owe us 66 million for having tax exempt property in the community. So that's how we offset it. Needless to say, it never went anywhere in the state legislature. But that's a whole other story for another time. Method has the sixth highest assessment out of the 175 communities that use the local assistance fund. We have the sixth highest assessment.
So when it's mentioned, like Councilman Wright mentioned that, you know what, if they're going to take service away, why wouldn't you cut the assessment? Why wouldn't you cut that assessment? We're paying for it. It's not something we're getting for free. We're paying for it through many different streams.
It comes right off our charity sheet. So whatever local aid we get from the state, they look at it and say, okay, you're going to get 15 million. We're taking 3.7 million from the T assessment. So we're paying, Mr. President. And I think the T should answer to this. They really need to answer. So I support what Councilor Knight offered. I'd also like to know, Mr. President,
How are they going to start to pay us back for the $66 million in tax-exempt property they have in this community? Between Wellington Station, the car bonds on Salem Street.
So I appreciate my colleague putting this on there, and I'd like to hear back from the MBTA to find out exactly, Mr. President. If this is a temporary cut or reduction in service, that's one thing. That's not the impression I'm getting. Once they make the cut, it's going to be very difficult to get it back.
You remember the days, Mr. President, that we had a fight because there were so many people standing on the 325 and 326. It became a safety concern. You are correct. It was over the capacity. And we asked them to put on additional buses because the 325 and 326 couldn't accommodate the needs of our community.
And they never did so, Mr. President. I think they may have put on a route here and there, and then they ended up, yeah, I think they ended up putting one route on, and then they ended up canceling that. But that shows you the need in the community. I realize COVID has decreased the need, but it's gonna come back. Everything's gonna come back, and that's gonna come back. And I don't wanna be behind the eight ball, Mr. President, when residents are looking for the 325 and 326. So I would ask that you give us a commitment in the form of a motion, Mr. President.
That this is just a temporary reduction in what their plans are for future service for the express bus. They want to keep people off the roads, they want to keep cars from going into Boston. Why would you eliminate express bus? We have an express lane. What's that used for if there's no express bus? You are correct. Thank you, Mr. President. Thank you, Councilor Marks.
And if I may, I thank Councilor Morrell for bringing this forward. And I know a number of councilors, Councilor Marks, in particular, and myself, I've brought up numerous resolutions about the 325 and the 326 bus for years. I've been a passenger on that 325 and the 326 for probably
Probably just about 20 years now, and like Consular Marks mentioned, these bus routes have become more and more popular pre-pandemic than I've ever seen since I've been taking them. And one of my biggest concerns is when they said they were going to temporarily suspend service, that they would never bring service back.
That seems to come to fruition now, and I did give Representative Donato a call today to talk specifically about this. And he basically told me the same thing he told Councilor Scarpelli, and that is that the MBTA lied to him and to the whole entire state delegation. It's very unfortunate. I know he is.
Representative Donato and the rest of the state delegation is fighting to bring this bus service back, the 325 and 326. I know they're working hard at it, but it's very unfortunate that the MBTA has done this. And I think knowing the MBTA, when we try to bring it back, they're not just going to bring it back, they're going to probably want all kinds of proof that ridership is there. And that's a piece I think that's going to be.
Probably we had to prove because right now ridership is low due to the pandemic. So Councilor Scarpelli, I like the idea of scheduling a subcommittee to look at this and bring in the state delegation and bring in the MBTA and ask really good solid questions. And really getting them to commit to a timetable as to when they're going to bring things back or when they're going to reevaluate. But this needs to be addressed.
And it needs to be addressed sooner than later. So, Councilor Morrelle, thank you for bringing this forward tonight. And at this time, I would call upon Councilor Behrs. Thank you, Mr. President. You just used the phrase temporarily suspended, and it reminded me, I'm pretty sure the E branch of the Green Line past Heath Street has been temporarily suspended since 1998. And the clerk could correct me, but the A branch maybe has been temporarily suspended since 1969, so. Thank you. All right. Councilor Behrs, 1969 was before I was born. Sorry.
Me, too. Thank you, Council of Bears. So on the motion of Councilor Morrell, seconded by Vice President Caballero, as amended by Councilor Knight, Councilor Scott Pelley, and Councilor Marks. Clerk Hertoghese. Actually, are there any questions on this before we call the roll? I don't see any hands raised. Clerk Hertoghese, please call the roll. Council of Bears. Yes.
have a motion for approval.
Councilor Scarpelli? Yes. President Falco? Yes. Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative. The motion passes. 2-0-531 offered by Vice President Caviello will be a result of the Memphis City Council request that the administration immediately provide funding to the clerk's office to hire additional personnel both permanent and temporary for the upcoming November and future elections.
Vice President Caviello. Mr. President, I think Councilor Beas has a similar resolution, 20536, if you'd like to read that also. Yep, move to join. Was that 20560? 536. I'm sorry, 536, okay. So 20536 offered by Councilor Beas, whereas Medford residents had serious concerns about voting during the September 1st.
State primary election, including missing materials, incorrect information, limited public statements, enforcing of some voters to vote in person without an effective mail option. Now therefore, be it resolved that the Memphis City Council urges the city administration to ensure that the registrars
Our voters and city clerk have all resources and staff necessary to conduct the November 3rd general election given the significant increase in demand for mail ballots. Be it further resolved that the city administration provide ballot drop boxes at locations other than Memphis City Hall. Be it further resolved that all elections communications be translated into languages other than English in a prompt manner for public consumption.
So the motion is by Councilor Caviello, seconded by Councilor Behrs to join these resolutions. Clerk Carter, please call the roll. Councilor Behrs? Yes. Vice President Caviello? Yes. Councilor Night? Yes. Councilor Marks? Yes. Councilor Morrell? Yes.
Councilor Starkelli? Yes. President Falco? Yes, the affirmative, zero in the negative. The motions are joined. At this point, I call on Vice President Carviello. Thank you, Mr. President. Mr. President, I think we've all seen after this last election that the way we've done elections in the past are no longer viable.
Especially with the early voting for a week, the mail-in ballots, this is no longer a one-day event like it has been in the past. The day of using volunteers to do this is now in the past. I think it's time that through the clerk's office and the election department that we come up with
some staffing requirements and some funding mechanisms to bring our election process and voting process up to this new way of doing it.
You know, we've talked about in the past how we encourage people to vote, we encourage people to vote. Well, I think this primary was a tremendous turnout. I think we had probably one of the best primaries we had in many, many years. And you saw the clerk struggle with staffing problems and funding problems. So again, I think it's time that the clerk and his election department
start requesting some funding and start changing the ways that we've done in the past to bring it up the way voting is going to be going forward. Thank you, Councilor. Vice President Carviello.
Councilor Fierros. Thank you, Mr. President. I agree with Vice President Caraballo wholeheartedly. I think it's necessary that we get the resources down. I'm almost able to talk, but he's washing his window. I really think it's important that we get resources to City Hall, including a permanent elections coordinator, which has clearly been requested over and over again. Additionally, I think there are some things we could do to
make sure that residents are more informed and have the information in a more prompt way, as well as providing these ballot drop boxes in a couple other locations other than City Hall. I have spoken to the clerk extensively about this and I just want to relay, you know, I think the clerk did
a very difficult job in very difficult circumstances in a way that produced a result that we can count on. So I want to make that clear, but that doesn't mean that we can't do more. And that doesn't mean that the clerk doesn't need more to do things right. We know the turnout's going to be significantly higher.
On November 3rd, I think Councilor Scarpelli is also raising his hand. Everybody wants to talk on this, so keep going. But, you know, again, there's a lot that we can do to help. I have spoken with the clerk. I've also spoken with Chief of Staff Dave Rodriguez, and I'm confident that efforts are going to be made to accomplish the election in a better way in November. Thank you. Thank you, Councilor Peers. We have, oops, we have Councilor, Councilor Morrell.
Thank you, Mr. President. Yeah, and I thank my fellow counselors for bringing this forth. I know we all heard from many residents about this and I did, I think we've talked about communication on a number of issues around this and I think it would be beneficial and I'd like to add it in the form of amendment to get a report from the clerk's communication that can be posted on the website or shared in another way that just addresses how
we're addressing for this upcoming election to ensure that the mistakes that happened, and I know it has to do with volume and many issues, but that the mistakes that happened for the state primary do not happen again and people can have faith in whatever option or vehicle they use to vote for the November election. So I'd like to add that in the form of an amendment. Thank you, Councilor Morrell. Councilor Knight.
Mr. President, thank you very much, and through to the city clerk and his team. Babe, Janice Haley, the registrars of voters, they didn't have an easy task. And they really didn't know what was going on until the last minute. And I think that the state didn't help us out in allowing us ample opportunity to plan properly. And because of that, we met some bumps in the road and snafus. But I think it's important to point out.
the hours of work that these employees put in during early voting, vote by mail, and the like, Mr. President. And it expands further than just the clerk's office and the registrar's office. So the countless volunteers that were up here hour after hour, day after day during early voting. So I think it's important to point out that mistakes will happen and mistakes do happen. And as long as we identify that a mistake happened, we own it, which is one of Clerk Herderby's favorite things to do when a mistake happens.
Provide corrective action, we're all going to be in a better place. And I think that the clerk has the team around him that's going to allow him to do that. All right, so with that being said, Mr. President, I know there were some bumps in the road, and I know that it could have been handled a little bit smoother. And I have all the confidence in the world and the team that's down there now that this won't happen again. But getting back to operations, and from an operational standpoint,
Would it make sense for us, because of COVID, to condense the number of polling locations?
Just a question to put out there, Mr. President. Do we need 15 polling locations when we have early voting and vote by mail, and then a lower turnout at the polls because of this? It's a question to chew on. It's a policy question that's going to have to go through the Board of Registrars of Voters. I know that it would probably require a homeward petition, because state law does mandate that I think there's, what, 4,000 voters per precinct, something like that. So it would take some work, Mr. President. But I don't know if it's an effort worth exploring or not.
For the simple fact that it will reduce the cost of elections. There's ample opportunity and time for people to come in and early vote, vote by mail, and absentee vote. And we can consolidate the locations. We won't need as much personnel, so the margin of error might be smaller, is all I'm saying. So it's something to talk about, something to think about, Mr. President, that I look forward to discussing at a future committee of the whole, if possible. Thank you. Counselor Knight. We have Counselor Marks.
Thank you, Mr. President. I want to thank Councilor Caviello and Councilor Biaz for putting this on tonight. If we recall when we were deliberating the budget, it was mentioned, I know I brought it up. The city clerk did request for an additional position within the registrar voters office.
It never found its way into the budget, but there was a request. So at the time, the city clerk realized that due to the upcoming election, the nature of the election, what's going to be requested of his office, the amount of votes that will be potentially early voting, mail-in and so forth, that it required someone from the Registrar of Voters Office to coordinate these efforts.
which currently doesn't exist right now. As my colleague mentioned, you have Mrs. Joyce, you have Mrs. Lamoni in there, you have Sandy that does a great job on, I believe, a part-time basis. You have a number of other staff people, Mr. President. They did the best they could.
But clearly, the clerk who is also the chief election officer of the community felt fit that it would require additional personnel. And I think the time to stand up was during the budget, now it's after the fact.
And I think we're all looking back saying, in retrospect, we probably should have asked for that position, even though it wasn't part of the budget, but was requested as, if you want to call it a wish list. And that would have been an important position, Mr. President, in my opinion, to make sure that our elections are on the up and up and the integrity of our elections, which should be of the utmost importance.
us as elected officials and as a community, Mr. President. So I just want to put that out there that I don't think it's too late now if we do need it, Mr. President, that we as a council can ask that the city administration, which I'm going to do in the form of a motion, that the city administration put into
language that would put forth the position of a coordinator in the registrar or voter's office. And I know the city clerk has the exact title and what the job description would be, Mr. President. And I would ask that he supply that on this resolution back to the city administration because we know it's going to be needed. It's not, as my council colleagues mentioned, this is not going to get any easier.
in November or next year or the following election. And the position is needed, and it's a long time coming in this community, Mr. President. We're able to get through elections for many years, but I think now's the time we have to, as a community, step up our game and ensure the integrity of our elections. And in doing so, hire the appropriate personnel to make sure that happens. Second, Mr. President. Thank you, Councilor Marks. Councilor Marks, is that a
That's a wrong motion. Is that a B paper? Yes, if you want to make it a B paper. That'll be a B paper. It's on the motion of Council Marks' B paper, seconded by Councilor Pierson here. Yep. Clerk Hertoghez, do you have the language on the B paper? Hang on just a second, Mr. President.
for the city administration to put into the budget language for election coordinator in the registrar's and voters office with the language for that position to be supplied by the city clerk.
Okay, and if I may add briefly, thank you to everyone in the clerk's office, the registrar voter's office. I know they are very hardworking. I know they go nonstop. They do a great job. Were there some issues? Yes, but I know that the clerk has been working on that. And the important thing is to figure out what those issues were and
to make sure that they don't happen again. I know he's been, him and his team have been working on that, and they will continue to work on that. I know that they will do a great job in November, but I think it is also important that the administration look at supplying additional funding to make sure that those offices have the help that they need in November. So I thank the councilors for bringing this resolution forward, and at this point in time, since no one has a hand up, I-
Councilor Scarpelli. Thank you. Thank you for my colleagues for bringing this forward. I think that I too talked to City Clerk and our administration. I think this is important that I think Councilor Carvell hit the nail on the head. This isn't.
the elections of old, and I know that when you see Adam Hurtubise like I did on election day, it hurt me just watching him pound the pavement. So his staff works super hard and he puts in the extra hours, but I think sometimes hard work and overdoing it hourly isn't the answer. I think it's making sure that we give him
the tools that are going to make them successful. Because again, what you're seeing, especially in today's society, you're opening yourself up for a lot of negativity and a lot of negative feedback. So especially with this upcoming presidential election, we want to make sure that we have everything in order so we eliminate any of the negativity. So again, I appreciate it, and I thank Claire Kurterbees and the staff for
doing the work that they do, and I concur with Councilor Moxley. I think it's a great idea. We move forward with it. Thank you. Thank you, Councilor Scarpelli. We have, let's see, we have, I believe it's Marjorie wants to speak. Marjorie, name and address for the record, please.
Hi, my name is Marcia Shearson. I live at 11 Upton Terrace in Redford. And I thank all of you for listening to me as you have many times in the past. This is an incredibly important issue to me because this is the most crucial election that's ever happened in my lifetime, which is longer than you might think.
And my particular concern was around having sufficient ballot boxes supervised, if possible, around the city so that people who are unable to vote in person or maybe voting for the first time and not have transportation be able to cast their vote.
And I thank you all for bringing this issue to your attention and all of your interest. The other concern I have is that there is a possibility that there may be more poll watching happening
Thank you.
Melissa Young, name and address for the record, Melissa. Hi, I'm Melissa Young, I'm at 68 Bolton Street, and I also sent in a letter, so I won't go into detail, and you guys have it for the record. I just want to say I would encourage you to support this resolution. I worked the March election, so I would also go ahead and say that I would not recommend reducing the number of polling locations, whether or not they get added on.
That's another story. But we aligned at the door during the March election, and that was even nearly as busy as the previous election. In addition, a coordinator would help the city in just getting the communication on.
I mean, when you have a dedicated staff member and this is their role to modernize things, things just happen faster. I just would encourage you to support it. And I have more examples in my letter to support, but I just wanted to provide that information. Thank you.
Okay, Councilor Marks. Do you all set, Councilor Marks, just to make sure. Okay, thank you. I wasn't, did you have your hand up earlier or no? Clerk Carter-Bees, I wasn't. No, okay, perfect, okay. On the motion, so there's a number of papers here. So on the B paper that was offered by Councilor Knight, I'm sorry, Councilor Marks, and it was seconded by, I believe it was Councilor Beers. Clerk Carter-Bees, can you please call the roll?
Councilor Behrs. Councilor Behrs, I didn't hear you. Councilor Behrs left the room. OK. Well, that explains why I didn't hear him. Vice President Caraballo. Yes. Yes. Councilor Mike. Yes. Councilor Marks. Yes. Councilor Morrell. Yes. Councilor Scarpelli. Yes. President Falco.
Yes, and Councilor Beers just walked into the room. Yes. Was that a yes? That was a yes. OK, that's on the B paper. 7, the affirmative. 0, the negative. The motion passes on the B paper. On the main motion that was offered by, actually, by Vice President Caviello and Councilor Beers. Mr. President, I offer an amendment. Did it get a second? I offer an amendment.
You offer an amendment? Yeah, to knock it. I can't remember if it's a second or not. On the main paper? Yes, on the main paper. Oh, OK. So Councilor Morrell had an amendment to the main paper. Yeah, I get it here. So on the motion of Vice President Carbiello and Councilor Behr, seconded by? Second. What's the second? As amended by Councilor Morrell? Yes, as amended by Councilor Morrell. Clerk Herderby, please call the roll. Who's the second on the motion?
Councilor Scott Kelly. Thank you. Councilor Bears. Yes. Vice President Caraballo. Yes. Vice President Caraballo. Yes. Thank you. Councilor Night. Yes. Councilor Marks. Yes. Councilor Morrell. Yes.
Councilor Scarpelli? Yes. President Falco? Yes. Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative. The motion passes. 2-0-532 offered by Vice President Caviello. Be it resolved that the Memphis City Council have the DCR repair the guardrail on Route 16 bridge in Auburn Street in the interest of public safety. Vice President Caviello.
Thank you, Mr. President. Mr. President, this is something I put on about eight months ago. And it took a while to fix, and it was fixed. And three months later, the guardrail has been hit again.
Just that spot. And again, the guardrail is on the side, it's broken onto the sidewalk and it's making it hard for people to traverse. So again, if we could refer this to Representative Garbling's office, I did speak to him briefly about it, but if you could send him an official thing in the DCR to have this repaired again in the interest of public safety. And Mr. President,
While we're sending something to the DCR in to Representative Godley, on August 11th, I made a resolution, 20474, about removing the trees in the river. Because Paddle Boston's there, and a lot of people kayak and everything. It never went to the DCR, it ended up going to Aggie Jordan.
And she wrote back that she has no jurisdiction over the waterway and the trees. So I think this 20474 should have gone to Representative Gabbard and the DCR. So if you want to combine these two together, when the clerk sends this paper to both offices. So why don't we amend it to have that paper sent to the correct agency to have the tree taken care of. Thank you.
So on the motion of Vice President Caviello, seconded by Councilor Behrs, is amended by Vice President Caviello. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Behrs? Yes. Vice President Caviello? Yes. Councilor Knight? Yes. Councilor Marks? Yes. Councilor Morrell? Yes. Councilor Scarpelli? Yes.
President Falco. Yes, seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative, the motion passes.
2-0-533 offered by Vice President Caviello be resolved at the Memphis City Council. Have the school department have the two collection bins at the Andrews School emptied as soon as possible in the interest of public health. Mr. Caviello? Thank you, Mr. President. Mr. President, I was by the Andrews School last week, and they have two collection bins there, and they're overflowing. And all along the side of them is all,
These have gone from collection bins to garbage dumps now. There's furniture there, there's car seats. I think they've kind of gone a different way. And I know we did receive communication from the mayor's office about something I offered last year about ordinances for the collection bins. So I'm glad to see.
The motion that I made last year has gone up. But again, this is at the school, it looks horrible when you drive by there. There's all rubbish between all of them, and there's road instead of going in and out of there. So if we could have that taken care of, I'd appreciate it. Thank you, Vice President Caviello. Councilmate. Mr. President, I second the motion. Okay.
Any questions from the council any questions in general? Okay on the emotion of vice-president cabio seconded by a council and I correct her to be please call the roll That's a bears. Yes vice-president care of y'all Thank You council night yes, that's a marks Council Morrell. Yes, that's a star pellet. Yes, I
President Falco. Yes. Sending the affirmative, zeroing the negative, the motion passes. 20-534 offered by Councilor Behrs. Whereas the new Ball Square MBTA Green Line is designed as a walkable transit station for the South Memphis neighborhood. And whereas pedestrian safety and infrastructure conditions.
require improvements to support the transit-oriented mixed-use development in multimodal reality of the new station. Now, therefore, be it resolved by the Medford City Council that the representatives of the Office of Community Development, Community Development Board, Greenline Extension Project, Building Commissioner, and South Medford residents together meet with the City Council and Committee of the Whole to discuss a district plan for the Ball Square-Foster Avenue corridor.
Councilor Behrs. Thank you, Mr. President. So as we're aware, the Green Line Extension Project is well underway, nearing completion, hopefully next year if all targets are met. The stations in Medford, the Ball Square station is actually mostly in Medford, and of course the
Hillside or the Tufts station, I believe Medford Tufts is what it's called, you know, they are walkable stations. There is not parking designated for those stations. So they are designed to be walked to and use other modes of transportation like buses and bikes. The intent of this resolution is after speaking to some folks in the area and also some
developments with development in the area, really taking a hard look at making a district plan for the region along Boston Ave near Ball Square. Obviously, Somerville has just gone through a major rezoning that's going to significantly affect traffic into Medford. So the proposal here is that we would meet in Committee of the Whole.
to discuss a district plan that would include transportation improvements, zoning, all the things that would need to go into really updating what we do in that area. One part of the Green Line extension is that around these walkable stations, the MBTA is really supposed to work with the local authorities, with the municipality.
to make significant improvements around the stations. I think we want to do that as part of a coherent plan, addressing concerns of neighbors, as well as addressing, you know, kind of some of the new opportunities we might have around growth, around development, around improving the area. So again, that's the intent here, meeting committee of the whole with representatives who have a stake in this, and I move approval. Thank you, Council Members.
On the motion, any questions? Oh, we have a question. Oh, we actually, let's see, Laurel Ruma. Okay. Thank you so much. I would please ask that the resolution be changed to include the station stops of Medford-Tufts. Medford does have two Greenline stations here in Medford, which is a fantastic part of the Greenline extension. Ball Square in South Medford, and then Medford-Tufts at College and Boston Avenue.
this project is that people will come from at least a mile radius to the station. And again, because there's no parking at the train station, people will be walking and riding bikes. So just like to make sure the resolution actually includes both of the train stations. Thank you. Thank you. One last thing. Yes. We're on budget and on time to have the trains running by December 2021. So we're a year away. Almost there.
Awesome. Thank you, Laurel, and I'd be happy to amend the paper to add the, you know, Medford-Tufts station and to look at all the way down to Boston Ave to the Medford-Tufts station. So you want to amend it? Yeah. Okay. Yes, let's see. Counselor Knight. Can we invite Tufts University to the meeting as well? Yes. Given the circumstances, yeah, that makes sense.
OK, so we'll see you on the motion of Councilor Behrs, seconded by Councilor Morrell, as amended by Councilors Behrs and Councilor Night. On that motion, Clerk Hurnabys, please call the roll. Councilor Behrs. Yes. Vice President Caravaglia. Yes. Councilor Night. Yes. Councilor Marks. Yes. Councilor Morrell. Yes.
Councilor Scarpelli? Yes. President Falco? Yes. Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative. The motion passes. 2-0-535 offered by Council of Bears be it resolved that President Falco meet with the Board of Health to define what public health metrics will be used to determine the ability of the council to meet in council chambers or if the council must meet in a virtual setting and how often they will be considered.
Be it further resolved that President Falco meet with the Board of Health to define what conditions and public health measures will be used to determine whether members of the public can attend meetings in council chambers. Be it further resolved that President Falco and the Board of Health work with the city solicitor to ensure compliance with state law regulations and emergency orders. Councilor Behrs. Thank you, Mr. President. Yeah, I think this issue has come up a lot from a lot of folks, including myself.
And it goes back to something that was said earlier around having options. We have options around these meetings. I think we've added another option, which is not without its flaws in this meeting hybrid that we're having right now, which has its own issues as well as Zoom. But I think the views of
What public health says, we have not chosen the safest option. We have not chosen the option to meet virtually, not meet in person, which would be the safest option. So I'd like to have some public health metrics and guidance around this beyond just let's meet in the chamber. We can't have the public here. We can't have any of our guests here. Let me tell you, sitting over here between four different barriers trying to look at this TV screen and see what people are saying is, you know,
not the easiest thing in the world when my glasses are fogged up because I'm wearing my mask. So there's benefits and costs to all of the models that we've looked at so far with Zoom and the hybrid model. I think given that fact that neither is perfect, we should be taking the safest choice. So that's what my resolution is intended to do. And quite frankly, I've received several messages tonight asking why some counselors are wearing masks and others aren't. So I would also propose a B paper
that the Council President mandate masks behind the rail while we're meeting. That's not how this works. Mr. President. Okay, thank you Councilor Knight.
We have Councilor Morrell and then Councilor Scott Kelly, I'm sorry. I got the names mixed up on the screen, so. Thank you, Mr. President. I want to thank Councilor Behrs for bringing this forth, because it is a reminder that it's not just us in here. It's our families. It's everyone we interact with in those essential activities. So any time you bring together X number of people, you increase the rate of potential transmission. So I think it's just important to note, it's not just us. It's everyone we interact with in the community. And it's a public health issue. Thank you.
Thank you, Councilor Morrell. Councilor Scarpelli. Councilor Falco, to keep things positive, we are in a chambers where we are protected by glass, with an open seat, where I am at least 8 to 10 feet away from Councilor Knight. I'm 15 feet away from Councilor Morrell. There's nobody else around me. No one else around me.
There's PPE equipment all over the room that we can use. CDC guidelines has me run camps every day with up to 50 kids.
using these schematics, these guidelines, to say that this is any way dangerous because the ruling of social media again spewing negativity is a shame. Stay positive. We agree with Councilor Beas with having the opportunity to have many options that people need.
But what he seems to return over and over again, that there are people that don't do Zoom. So even if there's people scattered out here, six feet apart, and even if it's the five people that can't make these meetings, this is the reason why we had the issue months ago at the budget meetings. Cuz people have an option to come to these chambers.
I am positive that I do not want to be COVID positive. Thank you. Hypocrisy is amazing, but going forward, going forward, this is, this is, this is the city's forum. So like I said, I appreciate my fellow council talking about having people have the opinion to stay healthy and choosing zoom. I understand that.
Whether I like it or not, I understand it, and I support it. But at the same time, if it's one, or two, or three, or five, or 25 people that want to come to this forum because they won't do this Zoom, they have an opportunity too. So I look forward to sitting with the Board of Health. I appreciate that. I welcome that. I'll vote in support of that 1,000%, because I want to hear the Board of Health person, the board members, going to tell me that you're going to allow 400 people in a school
But you're not going to lock people here. People voted here. People volunteered here with no fear. No fear at all. Hypocrisy is amazing. Thank you, Mr. President. Point of information, Mr. President. Point of information, Mr. President. Yeah, I mean, that's a false equivalence. Those are not the same things. We've been sitting and, yeah, it is. I mean, we can talk about it or not, but you can't compare two entirely different things and say they're the same thing and then call someone a hypocrite. It's just not true, Counselor Scarpelli.
And if we want to talk about how this virus spreads, it's a lot of people sitting in this, do you think this glass is protecting anyone in a long term when airborne particles and droplets are spreading? I mean, it's just not based in the science around how this spreads. And quite frankly, I'm the youngest one here. I'm wearing a mask. If you wear a mask, it's to protect other people. I'm at the least risk here. So I'm just saying, I don't think we want to be in a situation where there are counselors who are sick and God forbid there's four counselors who are sick. And I understand that, you know,
Other people may feel differently. I don't think this is a time for feelings. I think this is a time for science and public health. We have Councilor Morrell and then Councilor Marks.
Councilor Morrell. Thank you, Mr. President. I mean, this is really an innocuous, ironically, an innocuous resolution. And I think there is, you know, the research and studies are still coming out, to Councilor Behr's point, about how this transmits. Sure, these, you know, you look at any spray, this actually doesn't do anything. And we're sitting in recirculated air, so we can't sit here and say, we just had long conversations about the air quality in the high school, and then it's,
I'm at a loss for words here, because again, this is a very innocuous, have a conversation, look at some metrics, how do we move forward, resolution, and it shouldn't inspire this level of ire and anger and finger pointing.
Point of information, Mr. President. Point of information, Mr. President. Point of information, thank you, Councilor Morrell. Point of information, Councilor Scott-Pelley. The intent of the resolution was fine, but to respond that people and social media responding to our fellow colleagues and saying even that I'm masked, that's a joke, that's hypocrisy. Thank you. Thank you, Councilor Scott-Pelley. Councilor Marks. Mr. President. It is on now. One second.
Mr. President, did you not meet or was the Board of Health Director not in this chamber and gave approval to this set up, Mr. President? Yes, correct, correct. So if I may really quickly- Mr. President, if I could. Can you not go to a restaurant, indoor or outdoor, and sit six feet from someone else without plexiglass, Mr. President?
Have we not been told, Mr. President, that we can't exceed 25 people in this chamber, Mr. President? Correct. Do we exceed those numbers, Mr. President? Have we adhered to all the rules and regulations, Mr. President? If my colleague wants to stick his head in the sand, but meanwhile attend every rally possible,
Everywhere, we've got hundreds of people gliding in and shaking hands. Then so be it, Mr. President. It is the height of hypocrisy, Mr. President, to stand there and say that someone would be in danger attending this meeting, Mr. President. Shame on whoever's spreading that around, Mr. President. Yeah, Mr. President. Thank you, Counselor Marks. Counselor Knight, and then Counselor Behrs. Counselor Knight.
Mr. President, I just want to say this. Now, we've been doing this Zoom thing now for what, since St. Patty's Day? Yes. All right, so that's going back to March 16th. March 17th, we've been doing the Zoom. Almost six months. I don't like Zoom at all. I think it's awful. I have a terrible setup for it in my home. I got two young kids. I can't put them on lockdown for seven and eight and nine hour long meetings and tell them, don't say a word in the house, guys. I got a Zoom meeting going on. All right, it doesn't work for me.
But I will say this, and I don't think anybody can shake a stick at it. The last two meetings that we've had in this chambers have been the best run meetings that we've had since St. Patrick's Day. And I'll be happy to say that, Mr. President. The reason why is because we're in these chambers and we're doing business where business is supposed to be done. And that's why when the governor issued his executive order, bodies public were exempt. Thank you, Councilor Knight.
So just to let everyone know, you know, before we, Councilor Pierce. Thank you, Mr. President. I believe when you walk in the building, it says you have to keep your mask on. So again, you know, if we're talking about following all rules and regulations, that's fine. That's not what this resolution says. It says, I'd like to check on that. It says that we should have not, not that the process that has gone through approval now,
is at issue here, Counselor Marks, through the Chair, it's that if things change, do we need to make a different decision and how are we having the information to make that choice? That's what it's saying. I'll be completely honest. The reason I proposed a B paper is because I've been wearing my mask this whole time and showing you the courtesy of doing that and I would like that to be returned to me. And if it's not, then I will attend in a way that makes me feel safe.
You know, if my counselors don't want to do that, or they don't feel that wearing a mask is necessary, that's fine with them. I'm going to make a decision to make myself feel safe. I think that to Counselor Knight's point, to the integrity of the body, do we want President Falco trying to call on me on Zoom and call on you in here? It's already hard enough with the two of us in these back seats without a signal. So I ask for that reason, that everyone wear a mask, and I'll feel okay being in here. But to say that it's not everywhere we go, I don't go to restaurants.
Well, then maybe we should meet on Zoom. Then maybe we should meet on Zoom. I don't know what to say, Council Marks. I can understand it. I think the public can understand it.
Thank you, Mr. President. And again, I would ask that my colleagues respect the courtesy and the rules of the building and wear their masks. And if they don't, then we'll have to make the choices we make. And I guarantee you, it won't be as an effectively run meeting if some of the council are here and some of the council is not. So that's why I proposed the B paper. And quite frankly, I'm disappointed.
Okay, thank you, Councilor Behrs. We have Councilor Morrell. Thank you, Mr. President. I continue to be dismayed by the health decisions trying to be made by other people. You do not know people's medical histories, their underlying conditions, their level of safety in being here. And I'm just so dismayed by other people trying to make health decisions for people this entire time.
I was only here for an hour until a fellow counselor asked that I be removed. I've been here for what, six and a half hours? Because there is no safe option. There is a safe option for these council meetings. There is a safe option for these council meetings.
There's not a safe option. There's not another option for people to vote. And I stand by my decision to protect democracy. Thank you. And you also endorsed candidates that you were passing off ballots to. Point of information, Mr. President. That's enough, okay? That's enough.
Okay. Point of information. We've debated this, I think everyone's had three times by now. What I want to say is this, and I'll be the final word on this, and that is that I have met with
We've gone back and forth all over the phone with Marian O'Connor, with Kimberly Scanlon, and we're doing everything that we should be doing, okay? I have made sure of that, okay? So what I will be doing now, and I'll tell you this much, is I will be meeting with them again because maybe we'll have a committee in the hall about it. That's what we need to do. But I mean, I have gone.
spent a ton of time going back and forth with each of the department heads, making sure that plexiglass goes up, making sure that everybody's seated in the right spot, working with Patrick Gordon to do all the technology piece. This has not been an easy task, but
If I go back at the past meetings, everybody was pretty much on board with getting back in chambers. So what we have been doing is we've basically been following the rules that have been put in place. So with that being said, to get us all on the same page, we can meet with our department heads again. But to tell you the truth, there are some cities and towns that are meeting, actually, and having the public here as well. Now, I've been told by our city solicitor that we can't do that.
Okay, the room.
I do have that, and I can send that to you. But with that being said, the opinion was that the room's got 25 people in it. If 30 people show up to the meeting, we can't kick people out of the room. And therefore, we would be limiting speech and be limiting participation. So it would be a violation of the open meeting law. And that's why we're here tonight, and the public is coming in through Zoom. That is the reason I got from the city solicitor.
So with that being said, that's where we are with that, okay? So we have a number of people that want to ask questions on this. I will call on that now. William Navar, name and address for the record, please. You have a minute and a half. Thank you, President Falco. William Navar, 108 Medford Street, apartment 1B.
I'm quite disappointed with the vitriol on both sides of this issue. And I wish we could take a problem-solving stance. And I've seen different city councils do this in different ways, et cetera. But just as a matter of practicality,
I think there's probably a way to meet safely and perhaps a safe mess or not, I'm not sure. But just as I see on my screen, you can't actually see the counselors. I can see you, President Falcone. I can see Claire Curnaby, but the other counselors I can't actually see, which is actually sort of worse than when everybody's at home. And also nobody's in the chamber, so it doesn't really provide access for people who can't do Zoom.
But mostly, I just hope we can get back into a problem-solving, problem-solving kind of thing, rather than this material is pretty frustrating to me. Thank you, Mr. President. Thank you. We'll see. We have Jean Nuzzo. Name and address for the record, please. Hi. Thank you. Jean Nuzzo, 35 Paris Street. Give a minute and a half. Just a few quick thoughts. First of all, you're in a space with 20-foot ceilings. You're distance beyond 10 feet.
and a room that typically holds between 200 and 250 people, you're currently at between two and two and a half percent capacity. As for public participation, City Hall is quite large. You could do an inbound pathway and an outbound pathway with some staged areas, six foot distancing dots and monitors in the hallway, and citizens and residents of Medford
and speak in front of that chamber. And if you need some help, let me know. I've done a million square feet of this at this point. So again, I applaud you being on site. I recognize that people are concerned about masks, but right now in this moment, you're roughly at 2% occupancy, which is lower than what's required. Thank you for letting me speak. And again, if you need my help, let me know. Thank you very much. Okay, up next we have Joanna.
I'm sorry if I'm saying that wrong. Yes, name and address for the record, please. Can you have a minute? I just think that yeah, I whatever you whatever the decisions were made to me in chambers is one thing. But during a global pandemic, you can't tell anybody individually what they shouldn't, should not do or what they're comfortable with.
As far as the other counselors, yelling and screaming at other counselors, it's so ridiculous. And President Falco, it's not your fault, but I would take better control of that room, because it wouldn't be happening, not on my watch. It's not right. They shouldn't be doing it to each other. Thank you. Thank you. Rick Caparo, name and address for the record, please.
I would just like to let Councilor Morrell and Councilor Bares, if they're so concerned about everyone's health and everyone in the council in the room, then they would be very concerned about the children they plan on having at a rally on Saturday. So they should stop being hypocrites and respect the city. Thank you. Thank you. Point of information, Councilor Morrell. One second. Councilor Morrell, one second.
Put your microphone on. Through the chair, I'm not having a rally on Saturday. I just want to make that clear. Thank you. Thank you, Councilor Morrell. Let's see, we have Laurel Rummel. Laurel, name and address of the record, Laurel. Oops, sorry. Trying to unmute you. Laurel Rummel, 149 Burgett Avenue.
So it's very disrespectful the way that everyone is acting, and I think you all know better, and to have counselors shout over each other and call each other names is outrageous. You're there as all representatives. I understand this is a heated debate, but everyone has to do the best practices possible to keep everyone else safe. It's just very disappointing and ridiculous that we've come to this.
Two, the Zoom meetings are fantastic. More than 100 people are online. Probably 10 people are watching through the feed. We need to kind of keep this participation and interest and people just being exposed to how the city does business going. And I have to tell you, you've got to be more welcoming than shouting and arguing this constantly.
Lastly, I'm not sure what the devil in the room is with the social media and the negativity. All I'm seeing on social media is a lot of people trying to figure out how to make Medford the best place it can be for as many people as possible. And, you know, everyone is quite heated right now. But let's just kind of step back a minute and take a breath. And I really appreciate that we're not calling each other hypocrites. Thank you.
Thank you. Okay, I believe that is everyone. Okay, so on the B paper offered by Councilor Beers, on that B paper, that was seconded by, does that have a second, Councilor Morrell? Okay, on the B paper. Clerk, could you please read the B paper back? I believe the B paper was to have the Council President
Mandate masks behind the rail during council meetings. Is that correct council bears? Correct. Mr. Clark That is correct amend the paper to amend the council rules to mandate masks behind the rail
for the duration of the COVID-19 state of emergency. We want to amend the paper. Amend the council rules. Do you have the language on that paper? I'm trying.
All right, let me read this back. So the B paper is to amend the council rules to mandate masks behind the rail during council meetings for the duration of the COVID-19 emergency. Yes, as issued by Governor Baker. What was the last part? The COVID-19 state of emergency as issued by Governor Baker. Okay. Did I clear everybody? Got it.
Councilor Beers made a motion and Councilor Knight has asked that that be moved to the Rules Subcommittee, where that can be discussed. Because to be honest with you, Councilor Beers, I don't even know if I have the authority to do that. I mean, I can't tell. So I think it probably needs to be discussed. So on a motion of Councilor Knight to move that to the Rules Subcommittee, was there a second there?
Seconded by Councilor Scott Kelly. Clerk Urtubis, please call the roll. This is to move it to the Rules Subcommittee? Yes. Councilor Behrs? Yes. Vice President Caraballo? Yes. Vice President Caraballo? Yes. That was a yes. OK. Councilor Night? No. I can't hear Councilor Night either. No. He said no.
And that's a no. Correct.
Four in the affirmative, three in the negative. The B paper has been moved to the Rules Subcommittee. On the main motion offered by Councilor Behrs, and that was seconded by, was there a second on that? Second. Seconded by Councilor Morrell. Clerk Urtubis, please call the roll. On the main paper, Councilor Behrs. Yes.
Vice President Caraballo. Yes. Vice President Caraballo. Yes. Yes. Councilor Knight. No. Councilor Marks. No. Councilor Morrell. Yes. Councilor Scarpelli. No.
Yes, 4 in the affirmative, 3 in the negative, the motion passes. Okay. Mr. President, when do you plan on meeting with the Board of Health? We'll see, I've got to find time. We'll figure it out. I have to meet with Mary Ann and Kim Scanlon sooner than later. I talked to them today. We will be setting up some time and we can
work on that issue as well, so. So you'd be meeting with just the Board of Health and the solicitor yourself behind closed doors and then coming up with a plan? No, I just talked to them today and I told them I wanted to speak to them more about what we're doing here and how we're doing it. Just want to make sure everybody's on the same page. Because where it's, as a result of a council resolution, you might want to be careful meeting behind closed doors. Absolutely, so that's fine, we can do that. Thank you.
20-537 offered by Council of Mayors, whereas residents of Meffitt requested that the city of Meffitt hang a banner stating Black Lives Matter at Meffitt City Hall as a statement of solidarity and support to begin to address the history of racism and discrimination in our community. And whereas the Supreme Court of the United States and Rosenberger versus Rectors and Visitors of University of Virginia established
The government speech doctrine recognizing that a government entity is entitled to say what it wishes and select views it wants to express. And whereas the government speech doctrine has been affirmed and reinforced by Supreme Court decisions including but not limited to Russ versus Sullivan, Johans versus Livestock.
Marketing Association, Pleasant Grove City v. Summum, Walker v. Texas Division, Sons of Confederate Veterans and Matal v. TAM, and whereas placing a banner on Memphis City Hall meets the multi-factor test defined in Summum and Walker of, number one, historic use of building
including banners to convey government messages, two, the public's close identification of messages and signage placed on Medford City Hall with the city government, and three, the city of Medford's maintenance of effective control over the messages conveyed, and whereas in 2018 the U.S. District Court for the District of Massachusetts in Shirtland versus the City of Boston denied the request for injunction
of a plaintiff requesting the flying of a specific flag on Boston City Hall using the government speech doctrine and multi-factor test defined in Summum and Walker. And whereas in 2019, the U.S. Court of Appeals for the First Circuit affirmed the decision of District Court of Shurtleff with a three-judge panel deciding unanimously to reject the plaintiff's appeal. Now, therefore,
Be it resolved that the Memphis City Council, that the city administration provide a summary explanation of the opinion regarding banners on Memphis City Hall and how it is possible that such an opinion can ignore the U.S. Constitution's government speech doctrine as decided and affirmed by decades of precedent of the Supreme Court of the United States. Councilor Beers.
So this same resolution has been offered two weeks in a row. So when the council rules, I have to rule this out of order because it has been two weeks in a row. This is verbatim, the same exact resolution as a prior meeting.
Now, so with that being said, the matter basically has already been disposed of because I was ruled out of order in the previous week. There was a doubting of the chair. But with that being said, what I did do today is I made a phone call to Chief of Staff Rodriguez.
And he was busy all day meeting, so I did have a conversation with the mayor regarding this very issue. So what I wanted to let you know is during our conversation, what she said is the response is on the way, and that the council should receive it within the next few days.
She also went out to say that the administration is also working on a policy with regard to banners. There's no timeline on that, but there is a policy that they are working on. But she said that we will be getting a response, because we haven't received an official response. But we will be getting that in the next few days, okay? Thank you, Mr. President. Thank you. 20-53, an offer by Councilor- Can I ask why it's taking a month?
What's coronavirus? Mr. President, the paper's out of order. Yeah. Yeah, the paper's out of order. I do not know why the administration's taking as long as it's taking, but that is what I was told and I wanted to pass that information on to my colleagues. I think a month is
I would agree, but you know. 20-53, an offer by Councilor Morrell, be it resolved that the Memphis City Council request that a representative from the administration provide an update on COVID-19 metrics for Memphis in any policy changes related to the pandemic at each forthcoming regular City Council meeting so long as deemed necessary to city operations. Councilor Morrell? Give me one second.
Councilor Morrell. Thank you, Mr. President. Yeah, this is pretty self-explanatory. I've had a few residents reach out about this. I know we have the dashboard. The dashboard is beautiful, but it does seem like there's a real opportunity at City Council meetings to hear from the administration, just a brief update about perhaps any changes, any different metrics, or how things are impacting things because I know we have, you know, it's seemingly every day that state unveils some new color map and what it means and, you know, the goalposts keep on moving.
and changing so I think it would just be an opportune thing to have a representative from the administration just explain kind of where we are and any necessary updates. So I move approval. Thank you. Second. On the motion of Councilor Morrell. On the motion of Councilor Morrell, seconded by Councilor Beers, Councilor Knight. From an operational standpoint, through you, through the author of the amendment, so does this feel like a standing
COVID-19 updated every single council meeting by someone from the administration? I mean, I'm just concerned about posting, you know, I mean, we've talked about suspension of the rules. We've talked about how we're not bringing items under suspension of the rules. We have posting requirements through the open meeting law. So would this be like a standing invitation? Is it the first meeting of every month? Is it whenever the administration feels fit or is this gonna be one of those things where every month we say, okay, is anybody here from the administration that wants to come and give us an update on Corona? Okay, no, all right, moving on.
Yeah, I mean, I have the same question procedurally. My intention was just to get a response from the administration first and then understand how it might be introduced by them if it's something they're willing to do. I understand it's, yeah, procedurally it's something strange, but it's strange times. Mr. President, point of information.
Point of information, council appears. I mean, it could be a weekly communication from the mayor that ends up on the agenda, something like that. I'm interested to hear what the administration has to say. It could be that. That says one or two. Like, could it be like a report for marrying an honor? Yeah. Yeah. That's, yeah. I would ideally, yeah. Putting this to the administration, seeing how they would like to deliver it via communications from the mayor, communications from the administration. That could be added if they see fit, if it's something they agree to.
So it wouldn't be that they're necessarily appearing before the council and are on the agenda. The request would be that they give us a weekly report as to the status. I mean, my intention would be to have someone to actually speak from the administration because there is stuff online. There is stuff already in report form and this would just be kind of anything that's worth addressing that week, that needs to be addressed that week. Under council purview or just in general?
I see it in general as this being, you know, we have X number of people on the call right now, it just being that these are well attended and as opposed to having to hunt stuff down on the website and try to parse out data, just getting an update to say, okay, here's the numbers and here's how it impacts anything, or maybe it doesn't, or maybe there's not an update that week. Maybe it's not possible procedurally, but I think it is, it's information that's being asked for in the community and it's, this is a vehicle to provide it.
Councilor Caviello. Vice President Caviello. Councilor, I didn't, I couldn't understand what you were saying because I am hearing impaired and I just, if you could repeat what you started with, I just, I just couldn't, I couldn't understand what you said.
I'm just hoping because we do have the dashboard and there are numbers there, but sometimes it's a certain amount of parsing out and trying to understand, you know, looking at one screen and seeing what the state metrics say and how we're supposed to behave based on those numbers. And if we could get an update directly from the administration as far as our metrics and if it's changing any policies that week. But I do understand it's procedurally as far as being introduced as an agenda item, it's a little bit tricky. So my intention is just to deliver this to administration and get a response from them as far as how they might
if they would be interested in delivering such a thing and how they might want to deliver it, whether it's communications from the mayor or something like that. But I do think there is a benefit to having a representative from the administration when possible to briefly address this. So this would be on a weekly basis or a monthly basis? I mean, weekly would be nice, but I think I also, I'd be happy to amend the paper to have the administration at a frequency they deem necessary.
Thank you. Is that an amendment? Yeah. If we could add the language at a frequency that the administration deems necessary in the form of an amendment. So we're going to strike the language at each forthcoming regular council meeting? Yes. You can strike that language. We can strike that language. I'll second that amendment, Mr. President. Any other questions for the council? Any other questions? Okay. Seeing and hearing none.
On the motion of Councilor Morrell, seconded by Councilor Night, as amended by Councilor Morrell. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Behrs? Yes. Vice President Caraballo? Yes. Yes. Thank you. Councilor Night? Yes. Councilor Marks? Yes. Councilor Morrell? Yes. Councilor Scarpelli? Yes.
President Falco. Yes, seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative, the motion passes. Councilor Beers, is your resolution the same as the communications from- Withdrawn. I'm sorry? I withdraw the resolution. Okay, that's 20539 has been withdrawn.
Communications from the Mayor. 20-541, September 3rd, 2020. The electronic delivery to the Honorable President and members of the Memphis City Council, City Hall, Memphis, Massachusetts, 02155, regarding the proposed ordinance historic district. Dear Mr. President.
and members of the city council, I respectfully request and recommend that your honorable body approve the following amendments to the city of Medford revised ordinances entitled historic district commission, article three, section 48 through 51 as described below. The amendments clarify the ordinance to delineate the previously approved districts and at the request of the method historic district commission create new single parcel district at 16 Foster court.
By way of background, section 48-51A presently states, under the authority of Mass General MGLA C40 section 3, there is a hereby established Hillside Avenue Historic District and Marm Simmons Historic District.
bounded as respectively shown on the map entitled Historic Avenue Historic District in Marm-Simons Historic District, which are on file in the city clerk's office and made part of this article by reference.
Pursuant to Mass General Law, Chapter 40C, Section 3, the attached report and request has been transmitted to the Community Development Board for their concurrent review. The matter is scheduled to be taken up by the Community Development Board on September 16th, 2020. Thank you for your kind attention to this matter. Sincerely, Brianna Longo Kern, Mayor. Mr. President, motion to refer to a committee of the whole for a presentation by the Historic District Commission, the owner of the property, before the City Council.
On the motion, I'm counseling tonight to refer to Committee of the Whole for a presentation from the owner of the property. Is that OK? Yes. From the Historic District Commission, I think, would be the ones that are imposing this, presenting this. So the Historic District Commission can present it. We'll have the owner of the property there, as well as a representative from the mayor's office, Mr. President. Today, I had the opportunity to speak with Mayor Lungo on a number of issues. And this topic came up. And she suggested that we meet in the Committee of the Whole, and she'll have a representative from her staff available.
To sit down with us and go over the paper as well as representatives from the Historic District Commission there, okay? Mr.. President well on the motion of console night seconded by Council Scott Pelley we have console morel. I believe had her hand up yep console morel and that consoles bears and
So the motion was to refer to committee, the whole seconded by Councilor Scott, followed by Councilor Morrell. Thank you, Mr. President. I'm curious if we could amend that to add to a date certain, because this demo delay expires in October. So we would probably want to meet before the expiration to actually have this conversation. So make sure we do that in due time. And on to that point, Mr. President, I spoke with the mayor and she said that she would make someone available next week. She said she'd be willing to do that, but it would have to happen next week. If I may, we actually do have
You can blow up my meeting. You're taking it Wednesday, right? It's OK. I understand. This is timely. So it'll be either Tuesday or Wednesday next week, OK? Just to let everyone know. So we'll get it scheduled sooner than later. OK, so Councilor Morrell has amended the paper. Councilor Beers? Yeah, that was the same thing. So if it's happening next week, I'm fine with that. OK, thank you, Councilor Beers. Any other questions or comments from the council? Mr. President?
Quick question, so Councilor Morrell is offering an amendment to a date certain, is that correct? Well, I think, I don't formally have a date yet, so I'm aiming for next Tuesday or Wednesday. No less than 10 days. No less than 10, within 10 days, right? We'll meet within 10 days.
Okay. Let's see, so, Councilor Morrell, did you have another? No, I just had, okay, speak on that. Okay, so I'll thank you. Okay, perfect. Okay, so. So there's no amendment, is that correct? Is the amendment to meet within 10 days? Yeah, the amendment is to meet. I'll second that amendment, Mr. President. To meet within 10 days. You are correct. Okay, let's see, so,
We have a hand raised here. I believe it's one minute, please. Okay. Chris Bader, name and address. Yes, I just want to be, this is Chris Bader. I'm the head of the historic distribution. I, oh, I cannot mute myself. No, we can hear you. Okay. I just want to make sure.
We're running out of time here. And this is a historic house that should be preserved. And I just want to be sure that bureaucratic people made a lot of comments about how slow everything moves with historic district commissions and the historical commission and so on. But this is exactly the same thing. OK. Thank you, Chris.
Okay, any other questions? Okay, hearing and seeing none. Oh, I'm sorry, we've got Jean Nozo has her hand up. Jean, I'm unmuting you now. Jean, name and address for the record, please. Jean?
Okay, I don't see Jean. Okay, I don't see Jean. Mr. Clark, do you, she's disappeared off my screen. I tried unmuting her. Okay, any other questions from the council?
I just, I think I just unmuted Jean. Okay. Jean, name and address for the record, please. Mr. Clerk, I have, she's unmuted. Jean? Alright. Okay. Mueller?
Okay. Okay. So it seems like Jean's not with us or she, I think there's a technology issue, but she's been unmuted, but we cannot communicate with her. So on the motion of, let's see, on the motion of Councilor Niter, furthest to committee the whole, seconded by Councilor Scott Pele as amended by Councilor Morrell. Clerk, please call the roll.
Councilor Behrs. Yes. Vice President Caraballo. Yes. Councilor Knight. Yes. Councilor Marks. Yes. Councilor Morrell. Yes. Councilor Scarpelli. Yes. President Falco. Yes. Senate affirmative, adjourn the meeting until the motion passes. Let's see.
Councilor Scarpelli. Is he back? Let's see here. Clark-Carnaby, do you have five?
Mr. President, did you ask me a question? Yes, do you know if Mohammed Anwar was logging in, or if you've seen him? I didn't see him logged in. OK. I don't see him either. So that will stay on the table. Clerk Carterby, did we dispose of everything? I think you have records of public participation.
Let's see, public participation, did anybody want to speak? Dude, this is like a cast iron pot pan. It's gorgeous. Okay, let's see. Thank you, Laurel. Okay, it looks like, okay, so we don't have anything on community participation that I can see.
I believe we are on to the records. The table records of the meeting of July 28, 2020 were passed to Vice President Caviello. Vice President Caviello, I'm not sure if you got through those yet. I think they're about 75 pages. Hang on. Vice President Caviello. Mr. President, after an exhaustive review, I find the papers to be in order. Okay.
Do you move approval? Move approval. On the motion of Vice President Tom Yellow to approve the record, seconded by Councilor Knight. Clerk Urbis, please call the roll. Councilor Pierce? Yes. Vice President Kerrio? Yes. Thank you. Councilor Knight? Yes. Councilor Marks? Yes. Councilor Morrell? Yes.
I think that was a yes. Yeah, that was a yes. Thanks. Councilor Scarpelli? Yes. President Fevella? Yes. Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative. The motion passes. The records of the meeting of August 25th, 2020 were passed to Councilor Knight. Councilor Knight, how did you find the records? Motion to table. Motion to table. On the motion of Councilor Knight to table the records, Director Enobis, please call the roll. Is there a second on the motion to table? Second. Councilor Behrs? Thank you. Councilor Behrs? Yes.
Vice President Caviello. Yes. Council Knight. Yes. Council Marks. Yes. He said yes. Council Marks. Yes. Yes. Thank you. Council Morrell. Yes. Hang on. I can only have four microphones because I have to be on at once. Thank you. She said yes. Councilor Scarpelli. Yes.
Yes, 7 in the affirmative, 0 in the negative. The records from the 25th of August have been tabled. Councilor Marks. Mr. President, several months back I put on the agenda that we asked that a crosswalk be painted at the intersection of Everett Street and Salem Street. Can we please get an update from DPW or the Traffic Commission regarding the crosswalk at Everett and Salem?
Okay. Anything else? Nope, okay. Is there a motion? Motion to adjourn. A motion of Council appears to adjourn the meeting, seconded by Vice President Carabiello. Clerk Urneby, please call the roll. Council Paris. Yes. Vice President Carabiello. Yes. Vice President Carabiello. Yes. Yes. Thank you. Council Knight. Yes.
Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
Yes, and tomorrow's committee, the whole meeting has been canceled. We resolved everything tonight. So that's been canceled. Thank you everyone for tuning in tonight. Stay safe, stay healthy. Thank you. Meeting adjourned.