[SPEAKER_07]: Greetings, seniors.
[SPEAKER_07]: This is Superintendent Edward Vincent, and I'm really happy to be here this evening to recognize you on this special scholarship awards night.
[SPEAKER_07]: As you can see, I'm holding in my hand the Mustang mask.
[SPEAKER_07]: I am Mustang proud, just like all of you.
[SPEAKER_07]: I am also Mustang strong.
[SPEAKER_07]: Today, I'm speaking to you because schools are closed and we're not able to meet in person.
[SPEAKER_07]: But I want to congratulate all of you for your wonderful achievements.
[SPEAKER_07]: Why are we here tonight to celebrate you?
[SPEAKER_07]: We're here because you worked hard and you're being recognized.
[SPEAKER_07]: You're being recognized for your great achievements, but you're also being recognized financially.
[SPEAKER_07]: Some of you are going to receive scholarships tonight because you excelled in certain academic areas or maybe in sports or maybe in the arts.
[SPEAKER_07]: Others of you are being recognized because you wrote an essay
[SPEAKER_07]: for community service and you were selected because of your excellent persuasion skills and your ability to express through written word what it is that you do on behalf of the community of Medford.
[SPEAKER_07]: It doesn't matter the reason why you're being recognized.
[SPEAKER_07]: The fact is you're all being recognized with scholarships tonight.
[SPEAKER_07]: I want to congratulate you for your hard work
[SPEAKER_07]: As a Mustang, these 12 years, you're going on to college.
[SPEAKER_07]: You're going on to bigger, better, and a brighter future.
[SPEAKER_07]: And you have scholarship award money to support you with that.
[SPEAKER_07]: I encourage you, when you are in college, to continue to write for scholarships, to not give up, to continue to be dedicated to the community and to doing service learning projects, continuing to make your community a better place.
[SPEAKER_07]: I am so proud of all of you.
[SPEAKER_07]: Congratulations on your wonderful accomplishments this evening.
[SPEAKER_07]: whether it's for academics, whether it's sports, whether it's the arts, whether it's community service.
[SPEAKER_07]: Congratulations for your hard work.
[SPEAKER_07]: You deserve these scholarships.
[SPEAKER_07]: I wish you great success as you start school next year.
[SPEAKER_07]: And don't forget, we are Mustang strong and we are Mustang proud.
[SPEAKER_07]: Go Seniors!
[SPEAKER_09]: I'd like to congratulate our seniors of the class of 2020 for being awarded these scholarships.
[SPEAKER_09]: This is just another mark that shows how hard this class has worked and how much they deserve.
[SPEAKER_09]: For all the seniors that have been selected, I know that you've put a lot of effort into all your work and these scholarships are attainment for exactly what you have done.
[SPEAKER_09]: I hope that you use this to move your education in a forward motion so that you are continuing your achievements and becoming lifelong learners.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hello Medford Mustang graduates, class of 2020.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's Miss Lavin, your director of guidance.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wanted to kick off this year's scholarship award by first saying thank you and congratulations.
[SPEAKER_00]: It truly has been my pleasure to step in as acting director of guidance this year.
[SPEAKER_00]: and see how much you've grown up through the years.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've had so many of you since elementary school, into the Andrews Middle School, and now at Medford High School.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this year, we're gonna start the award ceremony off with the Medford Police Patrolman's Association Award.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are four $1,000 awards that they raised money during the No Shave November event that they held.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the winners are,
[SPEAKER_00]: Evelyn Garcon, Karen Adams, Margaret Tseng, and Emma McGlynn.
[SPEAKER_00]: Congratulations to you all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Have a great summer and keep in touch with us.
[SPEAKER_00]: We want to know how you're doing and what your future looks like.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you so much and have a great day.
[SPEAKER_08]: Hello from the Medford Kiwanis Club.
[SPEAKER_08]: I am Mike Hayes, chair of the scholarship committee.
[SPEAKER_08]: We are proud to announce this year's scholarship recipients.
[SPEAKER_08]: Ibn Asa, Emily McDade, Bobby Norton, Melanie Dematia, Noah Light, and Brenna Christensen.
[SPEAKER_08]: They're all $2,000 scholarship recipients.
[SPEAKER_08]: As the chairperson, I create the facts about the applications without identifying people's names.
[SPEAKER_08]: There's a committee of six voting members.
[SPEAKER_08]: Recipients are picked on the following criteria.
[SPEAKER_08]: Medford residents, financial needs, academics, community service, and character.
[SPEAKER_08]: At least one recipient must be a Key Club member.
[SPEAKER_08]: One recipient is from the Tufts-Curtis School.
[SPEAKER_08]: We'd like to have many applications, so next year the seniors should definitely reapply.
[SPEAKER_08]: Medford Quantics Club thanks you.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hello Medford community.
[SPEAKER_05]: My name is Katie Fumara and I am a school adjustment counselor at the McGlynn Elementary School here in Medford, as well as the president and founder of 4INC, a 501c3 nonprofit organization located here in Medford.
[SPEAKER_05]: 4INC is an organization that raises money for cancer research and patient care.
[SPEAKER_05]: We hope to help those in need and inspire those willing to help.
[SPEAKER_05]: When I was 18, I lost my father to lung cancer.
[SPEAKER_05]: My father was a lifelong Medford resident, a Medford High graduate, and an avid golfer.
[SPEAKER_05]: This organization started as an annual golf tournament, and it quickly transformed into a group raising money to support families going through a recent cancer diagnosis.
[SPEAKER_05]: as well as inspiring the community to know what they stand for.
[SPEAKER_05]: This is the second year that 4 Inc.
[SPEAKER_05]: is awarding a scholarship to a Medford High senior.
[SPEAKER_05]: Medford is so important to us, particularly to our story where my father was a lifelong Medford resident and now that I am working in Medford.
[SPEAKER_05]: My board of directors really looks for a graduating senior who is excited about their future endeavors
[SPEAKER_05]: and how that connects to their passion about what they are advocating for in the community.
[SPEAKER_05]: We had numerous amazing senior candidates for this scholarship, and I want to sincerely thank each and every one of them for applying, as well as congratulating them on their recent graduation of high school.
[SPEAKER_05]: This year, 4INC would like to award the $1,000 scholarship to Jacqueline Madigan.
[SPEAKER_05]: Jacqueline is attending Salve Regina in the fall to pursue a nursing degree and we wish her the best of luck.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you so much to everyone who applied.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hello, my name is Tori Glasser.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm a guidance counselor at Medford High School and I'm going to be announcing some of our world language scholarships.
[SPEAKER_03]: The first is the Munoz Lepore scholarship.
[SPEAKER_03]: It is awarded to a student who has achieved the highest level of Spanish competency at Medford High School while demonstrating a passion for learning and a constant pursuit of excellence.
[SPEAKER_03]: The recipient of this scholarship will have demonstrated a desire to push the academic envelope, resulting in strong speaking and writing skill and ability to grasp difficult concepts.
[SPEAKER_03]: In addition, the student will have brought to the classroom a strong appreciation for the cultural elements that strongly enhance the study of the language and will plan to continue the study of Spanish in the future.
[SPEAKER_03]: We have two lucky recipients of this $1,000 scholarship this year.
[SPEAKER_03]: They are Nicholas Hollings and Michael Wu.
[SPEAKER_03]: Congratulations, gentlemen.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now we have the World Language Club Scholarship.
[SPEAKER_03]: They are awarded to Medford High School students who have achieved excellence at the highest level in the studies of French and Spanish.
[SPEAKER_03]: Judgment was based on exemplary speaking, reading, and writing skills, while demonstrating a keen sensitivity to the cultural components that influence their respective languages.
[SPEAKER_03]: For French, in the amount of $400 each, we have two lucky winners, Katie Stefani and Shruti Sood.
[SPEAKER_03]: And Spanish, one winner for the amount of $800, Catherine Brosnahan.
[SPEAKER_03]: Congratulations ladies.
[SPEAKER_10]: Hi everyone, my name is Jason Massimino.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm a school counselor here at the high school, and I'll be presenting the Michelina Petrangelo Scholarship.
[SPEAKER_10]: Michelina Petrangelo is a very dedicated and passionate teacher of the Italian language at the high school for many, many years.
[SPEAKER_10]: Unfortunately, her life and career were cut short due to a long battle with a leukemia-related illness.
[SPEAKER_10]: The Petrangelo Fund has sponsored several key cultural events over the years, trips to Italy, in addition to giving out scholarships each year.
[SPEAKER_10]: Our library is actually named after Michelina Petrangelo.
[SPEAKER_10]: You can see the plaque right when you walk in.
[SPEAKER_10]: to the library.
[SPEAKER_10]: The scholarship is awarded to high-achieving academic students who completed the fourth level of Italian and have demonstrated exceptional leadership qualities as well as a deep appreciation for the Italian language and culture.
[SPEAKER_10]: The award comes in the amount of $2,000 or $1,000 and for a total of about $9,000 this year.
[SPEAKER_10]: This year we have six winners, and those winners are Lang Cheng, Ching Cheng, Audrey Soley, Nick Corrado, Olivia Framini, and Maria Robbins.
[SPEAKER_11]: Hello, my name is Tony Zickney, and I am Director of Fine Arts for the Medford Public Schools.
[SPEAKER_11]: It's my pleasure to announce the recipients of our annual Music Ensemble Scholarships.
[SPEAKER_11]: The Medford High School Band Scholarship goes to an individual who was a seven-year member of the group, including several years as drumline captain.
[SPEAKER_11]: Congratulations to Connor Parry.
[SPEAKER_11]: The Medford High School Chorus Scholarship recipient was a chorus member for many years and a section leader of the alto section.
[SPEAKER_11]: Congratulations to Alyssa Gould.
[SPEAKER_11]: And finally, the Medford High School Orchestra Scholarship recipient has been a member of our string program since elementary school, playing first violin in the high school orchestra all four years.
[SPEAKER_11]: She has been accepted to Gordon College to major in music education in the fall, and that student is Isabel Vizera.
[SPEAKER_11]: Congratulations and best of luck to all three of you in all of your future endeavors.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hi, Miss Normandin here.
[SPEAKER_04]: I would like to present the Crystal Campbell Medford Strong Spirit Award for 1500.
[SPEAKER_04]: This award goes to a student athlete or band member who is active in the community.
[SPEAKER_04]: Congratulations, Jackie Madigan.
[SPEAKER_14]: Hi, my name is Wendy Horn, and I'm a guidance counselor at Medford High School.
[SPEAKER_14]: And I'm here to present the Medford Chamber of Commerce Cheryl White Scholarship Award in the amount of $2,000.
[SPEAKER_14]: This scholarship was named for Cheryl White, former director of Medford Chamber of Commerce.
[SPEAKER_14]: who prize community service and commitment to helping others.
[SPEAKER_14]: It is these qualities along with an essay, a record of community involvement, a strong high school transcript and financial need that the scholarship committee considered for this award.
[SPEAKER_14]: This year's winner of the $2,000 Cheryl White Scholarship is Jacqueline Madigan.
[SPEAKER_14]: Congratulations, Jacqueline.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hi, Malika.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm John Feudo, the Vice Chancellor for University Advancement at UMass Lowell.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you and I actually have a lot in common.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're from Medford.
[SPEAKER_01]: I grew up in Everett.
[SPEAKER_01]: You like music and want to study music.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I studied music in college, too.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you and I were both the recipients of valuable scholarships to help us achieve our success.
[SPEAKER_01]: So congratulations on being a recipient of the Hoff Scholarship for 2020.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, Charlie Hoff happens to be a good friend of mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I know there's nothing that Charlie likes more than trying to help our students achieve success, not just while they're here at UMass Lowell, but throughout your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Charlie wants to make sure that students like you don't have the financial burdens that so many others have.
[SPEAKER_01]: And while you're here at UMass Lowell studying business marketing and entrepreneurship, you're going to be right here in this building behind me, the Pulcino Tong Business Center, part of the Manning School of Business.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where you're going to find out
[SPEAKER_01]: who you are, and I read your application.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I know that you want to be somebody in this world, and you are definitely somebody in this world.
[SPEAKER_01]: And coming to UMass Lowell is not only going to help you find out who that somebody is, but it will help you find out where your place is in the world today.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're so excited to welcome you to our world at UMass Lowell, and we look forward to welcoming you to campus.
[SPEAKER_13]: Hello, I'm Guidance Counselor Joel Menasha.
[SPEAKER_13]: Bunker Hill Community College provides the Presidential Scholarship to a Medford graduate who shows financial need and a dedication to continue their education.
[SPEAKER_13]: The scholarship covers all tuition and fees for their freshman's fall semester, with the opportunity to cover the spring semester as well if the recipient earns the required GPA.
[SPEAKER_13]: We are proud to award this year's Bunker Hill Community College Presidential Scholarship to Kelly Doan.
[SPEAKER_13]: Congratulations.
[SPEAKER_06]: Medford High School Medford Vocational Technical High School PTO is involved in a variety of activities to improve the well-being of our vibrant school community.
[SPEAKER_06]: Throughout the year, we are involved in fundraising activities that allow us to sponsor supplemental events to enhance the lives of students, teachers, and administrators.
[SPEAKER_06]: These include the Up All Night party after the junior prom, the purchase of mid-year school supplies for teachers, an all-staff appreciation breakfast each spring, and many other activities peppered throughout the academic year.
[SPEAKER_06]: Part of the PTO's funds are set aside to fund senior scholarships, each valued at $500.
[SPEAKER_06]: Seniors were invited to submit a brief essay that were reviewed and rated based on their thoughtfulness, organization, and readability.
[SPEAKER_06]: On behalf of the entire PTO, it is with great pleasure that I offer my congratulations to this year's recipients.
[SPEAKER_06]: Ebion Abshir, Brenna Christensen, Alex Myles, Kieran Adams, Jacqueline Madigan,
[SPEAKER_04]: Once again, congratulations.
[SPEAKER_04]: The next scholarship is the Medford High School Alumni Association for $1,000.
[SPEAKER_04]: This award is given to a student who is able to show through an essay how Medford High School shaped their future plans and goals.
[SPEAKER_04]: This award goes to Dorothea Villot.
[SPEAKER_04]: Congratulations.
[SPEAKER_13]: Middlesex Federal offers three $1,000 scholarships to Medford High and Vocational Technical High School graduating seniors in the memory of John Champy, a long-time member of Middlesex Federal Savings Board of Directors.
[SPEAKER_13]: These students have been accepted and plan to attend an accredited institution of higher education.
[SPEAKER_13]: The 2020 Middlesex Federal scholarship recipients are Ava Urasitz, Frances Flood, and Katherine Sherburn.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hi, everyone.
[SPEAKER_02]: My name's Alana Bruno.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm a guidance counselor at Medford High.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm announcing the scholarship for East Cambridge Savings Bank.
[SPEAKER_02]: Supporting educational and enrichment opportunities for Medford High graduates is a core value of East Cambridge Savings Bank.
[SPEAKER_02]: They believe that an educated community is a powerful one.
[SPEAKER_02]: With this in mind, they're delighted to award a $1,000 scholarship to both Evan Liao and Frances Flood.
[SPEAKER_12]: My brother Matt was a 2012 graduate of Medford High School.
[SPEAKER_12]: He passed away from cancer at the age of 19.
[SPEAKER_12]: Matt was a member of the high school cross country team for three years.
[SPEAKER_12]: He received the unsung hero award his senior year and was proud to serve as captain under coach Lou who Matt admired as a leader and a friend.
[SPEAKER_12]: As a member of the team, Matt met some of his best friends and learned the meaning and value of dedication, teamwork, and the importance of simply enjoying the moment, whether it finished in a race in the first place or last.
[SPEAKER_12]: From reading their essays, it's easy to see how this year's recipients of the Matthew Soros Sorelli Scholarship exemplify so many of the characteristics that define who Matt was.
[SPEAKER_12]: A good person and friend with a kind heart and gentle spirit, who you could always trust and count on to be there when you needed him.
[SPEAKER_12]: took pride in anything he did, especially his work with kids with special needs and always remembering to pay it forward.
[SPEAKER_12]: It is our honor to present this year's scholarships for $1,000 each to Jacqueline Madigan and John Falco.
[SPEAKER_03]: We are so grateful for the community support our students receive every year.
[SPEAKER_14]: Class of 2020, we honor you.
[SPEAKER_10]: And we know you'll put these scholarships to good use.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's been a pleasure working with each of you.
[SPEAKER_04]: watching you grow and realizing your dreams for the future.
[SPEAKER_13]: Now go out and make us proud.
[SPEAKER_13]: Congratulations.