[SPEAKER_06]: Good evening, everyone.
[SPEAKER_06]: Can you hear me all right.
[SPEAKER_06]: I can hear.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_12]: Right.
[SPEAKER_06]: Hey, thanks.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thanks everybody for joining us.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm just gonna make sure that we don't have anybody else in the waiting room here.
[SPEAKER_06]: So,
[SPEAKER_06]: My name is Adam Bardosky.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm the attorney for the project.
[SPEAKER_06]: We're here tonight to talk about Salem Place, which is a proposed development at 290 Salem Street.
[SPEAKER_06]: With us tonight from the architectural team is Jacob Levine and Nyree Stewart, as well as the developers, Fernando Bento and Sal Parisio.
[SPEAKER_06]: So at the outset, I'd like to thank you all for joining.
[SPEAKER_06]: It looks like we have about 20 something here.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I'd also like to thank the city
[SPEAKER_06]: in putting this together.
[SPEAKER_06]: Victor Schrader, I believe, is here somewhere.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'd like to say thanks to Victor for putting out a few calls and just kind of helping to facilitate this whole thing.
[SPEAKER_06]: So this is gonna be, this is an exciting project.
[SPEAKER_06]: We've been waiting to have an opportunity to talk with members of the community on this project for some time.
[SPEAKER_06]: This is really gonna be the first opportunity to see the project.
[SPEAKER_06]: There's been nothing filed with the City so far.
[SPEAKER_06]: We anticipate that we'll have this meeting and at minimum we'll have to go before Planning and Development for site plan review and likely then next to the Zoning Board of Appeals for the zoning relief that's needed on the project.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we're really just here tonight to tell you a little bit about the project, what's in store, what it looks like, share some of the plans with you,
[SPEAKER_06]: This is a mixed use development so it's going to be, it's proposed to be three stories, nine units in total with parking and a commercial unit on the first floor, there will be residential units on the second and third floor and a roof deck.
[SPEAKER_06]: With that, I think I'm going to pass it to the architectural team to share their screen and walk through some of the actual plans.
[SPEAKER_06]: And we'll have an opportunity to have you folks ask questions and really stay as long as you'd like.
[SPEAKER_02]: So let me see.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, is it going to be Jacob or Nyree that's going to walk through the plans here?
[SPEAKER_02]: Good evening, everybody.
[SPEAKER_02]: It just says host disabled participants screen sharing right now.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm gonna sorry, I'm a little new to the hosting.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I'm going to make you a host.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, for a moment, Jacob, let's see if you let's see if you can handle it.
[SPEAKER_06]: If I do that.
[SPEAKER_06]: All right.
[SPEAKER_13]: Now the hosts.
[SPEAKER_13]: Okay, everybody.
[SPEAKER_13]: So hopefully y'all can see my screen here.
[SPEAKER_13]: Good evening and thank you all for joining us.
[SPEAKER_13]: We're the architecture team myself Jacob Levine is the project lead, and I have by my side Nyree Stewart, the project architect.
[SPEAKER_13]: We are representing SL Haas Group.
[SPEAKER_13]: We are a local firm here in Boston.
[SPEAKER_13]: So, I'm going to run you through some images of the project.
[SPEAKER_13]: This is obviously the new building on the left right here, just a little rendering, showing our new proposed design, looking down Salem Street with Park Street on the left.
[SPEAKER_13]: we can come back and view some of these images as soon as we kind of run through some of the numbers on them so everyone can understand what we're trying to achieve with the floor plans themselves.
[SPEAKER_13]: So right now we're looking at a unit with two bedroom units.
[SPEAKER_13]: It's a need for it's important to have a mix of one beds and two bedrooms.
[SPEAKER_13]: So in total, our building is 3000 square feet of square footage on the first floor here on the left, you can see Salem Street is on this side down here.
[SPEAKER_13]: So we would propose about 1400 square feet of commercial space on this first floor.
[SPEAKER_13]: That would be an excellent opportunity to activate this corner on Park Street and Salem Street, give that space back to the town.
[SPEAKER_13]: In the back, we want to do parking off Park Street.
[SPEAKER_13]: Right now, we're showing eight parking spots, but we're going to try to get nine parking spots.
[SPEAKER_13]: That would be one per unit.
[SPEAKER_13]: Depending on how the final structural system lays out, we're pretty confident we can get nine parking spots.
[SPEAKER_13]: But right now, we're just showing eight parking spots in the back.
[SPEAKER_13]: not pull in through Salem Street as that's the busier road.
[SPEAKER_13]: We're going to have the parking come and go two-way parking from Park Street.
[SPEAKER_13]: You can enter the building if you are a resident from the back on one of these two entrances, one right here by bike storage and the other through these main doors in which you'd go up the stairs or an elevator.
[SPEAKER_13]: We have one unit on the first floor that would be either a one bed with an office or we can make it a two bed.
[SPEAKER_13]: Dumpsters will be on the right side back here for ease of access to get them in and out for trash.
[SPEAKER_13]: As we work our way up, we're going to have in total, we have three two beds and eight one beds in the whole project.
[SPEAKER_13]: So what I'm outlining here
[SPEAKER_13]: you're going to have a central stair corridor as shown here.
[SPEAKER_13]: You come up through a hallway and you are going to have excellent views in all the units with plenty of natural light.
[SPEAKER_13]: We have a large two-bedroom unit, which is 1,500 square feet, with a balcony overlooking Salem Street and Park Street to activate that corner, along with a typical one-bedroom unit is totaling about 800 square feet.
[SPEAKER_13]: So the two-bedroom units are 1,500 square feet, and the one-bedroom units are about 800 square feet.
[SPEAKER_13]: The floor plan duplicates on the third floor as you continue up the stairs with one common hallway.
[SPEAKER_13]: making everything structurally work accordingly.
[SPEAKER_13]: We're trying to work with some of these bump-outs to, if you go back to the rendering, capture the essence of this project, which is a great model example of classic architecture in Medford, using the bump-outs here.
[SPEAKER_13]: The color scheme at this point hasn't been finalized, but we wanna do something with a lot of detail, similar to the ornate style across the street.
[SPEAKER_13]: As we work our way up to the last floor, we're proposing a roof deck for all the tenants.
[SPEAKER_13]: This roof space is still being developed.
[SPEAKER_13]: We think it would be a great opportunity to look over the street and add some activity to the roof.
[SPEAKER_13]: We would love to try to have sustainable features in our buildings, such as solar panels or maybe rainwater collectors in the back end.
[SPEAKER_13]: Lastly, I'm going to show you here, we're going to try to reuse some of the foundation of the existing facility, depending on the condition of it.
[SPEAKER_13]: You would either put a gym or mechanical space back down in that basement, but trying to be sustainable and use as much of that foundation as possible and not dig more than we have to.
[SPEAKER_13]: On the right, you can see our proposed site plan.
[SPEAKER_13]: We can get into a little bit more detail.
[SPEAKER_13]: with the proposed building.
[SPEAKER_13]: The building gross square footage on all floors is 13,000 square feet, so it's broken down into 3,000 square feet on the first floor and 5,000 square feet on the second and 5,000 square feet on the third floor, outlined by this red ring you see here and this red ring you see here.
[SPEAKER_13]: Lastly, our elevations.
[SPEAKER_13]: It's a very tricky site when I say tricky, you can see the site plan here how it's a really hard angle, so they, it's
[SPEAKER_13]: very difficult to try to work with that angle.
[SPEAKER_13]: So the elevations might be a little bit confusing, but I'll try walking you guys through them.
[SPEAKER_13]: This would be what you would see from Salem Street side.
[SPEAKER_13]: So this would be the entrance to the commercial street down below.
[SPEAKER_13]: These would be the bump outs that we were showing to represent the bump outs across the street.
[SPEAKER_13]: This would be the view from the Park Street side of things.
[SPEAKER_13]: So this is where the parking would be, under here.
[SPEAKER_13]: So you would park actually under the building.
[SPEAKER_13]: And this would be a very beautiful facade to see from Park Street.
[SPEAKER_13]: Everything is balanced, equal with a lot of thought and detail that goes into it.
[SPEAKER_13]: And these are the other two, not as visible sides, but still have some character to them.
[SPEAKER_13]: And that is where we are at with the design right now as we're continuing to explore color options and materials.
[SPEAKER_13]: We certainly want to use some brickwork that tries to match the existing brickwork from across the street.
[SPEAKER_13]: We're trying to use, excuse me, sustainable and durable materials that will last.
[SPEAKER_13]: more so than just vinyl siding.
[SPEAKER_13]: And we want to stay away from any sort of metal panels that was used down the street that has the really modern rustic look.
[SPEAKER_13]: So right now we're looking at maybe fiber cement board or something in the durable aspect, but that's still being decided.
[SPEAKER_13]: So that is our presentation right now and the drawings as they stand.
[SPEAKER_02]: Great.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thanks, Jacob.
[SPEAKER_13]: Adam, would you like me to make you host again?
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you, everybody.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm going to take my brother when I joined the is one of our partners to you want to join the meeting.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you can let him in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure, you can foster rental.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's an issue the computer so computer like.
[SPEAKER_02]: Alright, so everyone from the waiting room should be at this point.
[SPEAKER_02]: see if you show up.
[SPEAKER_02]: All right.
[SPEAKER_06]: Fernando, Sal, did you want to, I mean, that's essentially the presentation we had from the design side.
[SPEAKER_06]: Did you want to add anything before we start hearing from folks in the neighborhood?
[SPEAKER_14]: This is Sal Caruso.
[SPEAKER_14]: I'm on the development team also, the developer.
[SPEAKER_14]: I mean, I want to thank Jacob.
[SPEAKER_14]: Jacob did a great job in filtrating what we'd like to do there and
[SPEAKER_14]: try to make the building more of, not like the buildings, like you said, down the street with the panel, the metal panels and all that.
[SPEAKER_14]: We'd like to do is maybe some, you know, like siding, body plank siding along those lines and the brickwork and make it a little bit more appealing and not have to worry about one year or three years down the road and not start looking like the building's falling apart, because it is down the street.
[SPEAKER_14]: But no, I think Jacob's done a great job in designing this.
[SPEAKER_14]: This is, I think, our fifth time around on design on this.
[SPEAKER_14]: I think we got it down pretty patently now, as long as the neighborhood agrees or likes it, or if there's any changes they would like us to make, we'll get thoughts up.
[SPEAKER_14]: Great.
[SPEAKER_14]: Thanks, Sal.
[SPEAKER_06]: So with that, I mean, is there anyone from the community or on the Zoom right now that wants to ask any questions or have any comments about the proposal?
[SPEAKER_06]: potentially you could just raise your hand or send me a message in the chat function.
[SPEAKER_06]: Barbara, I see you there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thanks.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I'm not sure that I'm entirely understanding how many residential units there are versus how many commercial units there are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, ma'am.
[SPEAKER_13]: So it's one.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thank you, Barbara, for your question.
[SPEAKER_13]: So there's one commercial unit on the on the ground floor.
[SPEAKER_13]: And then there's nine residential units.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, and do you have any expectation of what type of a commercial unit would go on the ground floor?
[SPEAKER_14]: Sal, you want to jump in there?
[SPEAKER_14]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_14]: We, we're not at that, that stage.
[SPEAKER_14]: We don't know.
[SPEAKER_14]: We want to see what the neighbors would like.
[SPEAKER_14]: I mean, one of the, one of the, the, the city members had said, they said, you know something, because of the school, the parents, they want to wait for their children coming out of school.
[SPEAKER_14]: So, obviously a coffee shop would be nice.
[SPEAKER_14]: So, something that's catered to parents where they can sit and wait while their children are coming out of school.
[SPEAKER_14]: That was a suggestion from one of the city staff.
[SPEAKER_14]: But we're not sure.
[SPEAKER_14]: It's still open in the air that we haven't figured it out.
[SPEAKER_14]: We don't know what we're going to do with that space.
[SPEAKER_14]: If there's any suggestions that somebody would like to admit, we'd love to listen to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I just saw the parking would be for the residential units, but not for the commercial unit.
[SPEAKER_14]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_01]: OK, so just to be clear, I'm fairly confident that that stretch of Salem Street from Park Street to
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know, probably that brick apartment building that's past where like the little laundry mat is is 15 minutes apart like that is 15 minute parking.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I mean, that is just something for you all to keep in mind, like, and I know that's the same across the street where like Eddie's places and the hair salon.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's very, that's short term parking.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I live right on Park Street on the other side of Salem Street.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all day long, we are, you know, we have a lot of that commercial parking.
[SPEAKER_01]: People are going to Eddie's place or going to the hair salon, or there's now a daycare center in that building that they're parked.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can come out of my house in the morning and people are literally blocking my driveway.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I guess that that would be my concern that whatever commercial unit goes in there, or if somebody moves into the residential unit and has more than
[SPEAKER_01]: one car, like where are those people going to park?
[SPEAKER_01]: And are they then going to end up on Park Street, which is already brutally hard to find parking because it's only parking on one side.
[SPEAKER_01]: So just some things to keep in mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those would be my concerns.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would love to see that corner, like something done with it, but parking is a huge concern.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: No consideration, Barbara.
[SPEAKER_12]: And I live at
[SPEAKER_12]: 208, which is right across.
[SPEAKER_12]: And that would be my only concern really too, is just like my driveway comes right out into where the parking lot is going to be, where all the entrances are.
[SPEAKER_12]: And then they shut down the road at like three o'clock when the school comes out.
[SPEAKER_12]: And yeah, the only thing I would be somewhat interested in seeing is just, you know, the traffic that is going to be coming and going.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you and part and part of the, as you as you might know part of the site plan review process before the planning and development board, there will be a traffic and a parking component to that so that's the.
[SPEAKER_06]: the developer is going to have to go and get a traffic study done and we're going to have to present it as part of that.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that that's definitely something that we've all talked about that we know is an issue that needs to be addressed.
[SPEAKER_06]: And it's not going to be something that we're really guessing.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's not really going to be guesswork.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we'll have a traffic study done as part of the initial approval process.
[SPEAKER_12]: And not even with the building, but like a lot of parents who come to pick up their kids, they don't even have any like
[SPEAKER_12]: they don't care where they park, they'll park in my driveway, they'll park in front of my road, like, it's like, okay, so it might be, you know, for some of the residents who would live there, a little concerning, but you know, what can you do?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, totally understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: Eunice?
[SPEAKER_08]: Hi, yeah, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_08]: I have two questions.
[SPEAKER_08]: First one may or may not be for developer or the city staff, I'm not sure.
[SPEAKER_08]: But I see 22 people on this zoom.
[SPEAKER_08]: And from my count, I'd say probably a full third of them are either affiliated with the developer or the city.
[SPEAKER_08]: Um, how well was.
[SPEAKER_08]: Was this meeting noticed to the neighborhood at all?
[SPEAKER_08]: Um, in any fashion, other than just, you know, a simple, um, You know, posting on the city website, um, you know, was, was the general.
[SPEAKER_08]: neighborhood vicinity personally noticed at all, because it's a bit concerning.
[SPEAKER_08]: It's very concerning, actually, that, you know, there's about 14 people on this Zoom that are not somehow affiliated with the project or the city, and that's not really representative of
[SPEAKER_08]: people that might be concerned with this development.
[SPEAKER_08]: And my second question is, you talked about parking, and you said that you had eight parking spots
[SPEAKER_08]: in the back at the moment, but we'll probably be able to squeeze out nine for the, I think somebody said for the amount of units that you have, one per unit, but then you say that you have 11 units.
[SPEAKER_08]: So do you have nine units or do you have 11 units?
[SPEAKER_08]: Do you have eight parking spaces, nine, 11?
[SPEAKER_08]: The numbers aren't adding up.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_13]: Sure, let me just clarify on the architecture front.
[SPEAKER_13]: We have nine units, and right now the proposed amount of parking spaces are eight, but we are trying to fit nine parking spaces.
[SPEAKER_13]: So the goal is to get a one-in-one parking spot per unit.
[SPEAKER_13]: So there's nine units.
[SPEAKER_13]: Our site plan is showing eight parking spots, and we're gonna try to fit nine parking spots in total.
[SPEAKER_08]: Okay, but I think you said something about you had eight one-bedrooms and three two-bedrooms.
[SPEAKER_13]: Um, we have in total, uh, three, two bedrooms and, um, Uh, six, sorry, one bedrooms.
[SPEAKER_13]: I misspoke.
[SPEAKER_08]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_08]: Cause I think the little blurb that you had down the bottom there on what you put up, um, different.
[SPEAKER_13]: It's nine units in total.
[SPEAKER_08]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: And thanks Jacob and Eunice to your question.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we sent mailings out to, we obtained an abutters list from the city and sent mailers to all abutters within 400 feet.
[SPEAKER_06]: We had posted this on the, the city had posted this on their website and I had provided notice to various departments in town.
[SPEAKER_06]: I believe that
[SPEAKER_06]: the town conduct or the city conducted a reverse 911 on this.
[SPEAKER_06]: I personally, I was on the flyer.
[SPEAKER_06]: I received probably about a dozen emails with people saying that they couldn't attend but wanted more information on it.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we shared the plans.
[SPEAKER_06]: We're also recording this meeting, which I believe will be posted on the city's website.
[SPEAKER_06]: And as I mentioned at the outset, this is really the first meeting with the community.
[SPEAKER_06]: We will have at least two
[SPEAKER_06]: public hearings before city boards on this, and there very likely will be other opportunities to review our plans and comments so I wouldn't, I wouldn't look at this group as indicative of everyone that at least was notified about it, and there certainly will be other opportunities for people to attend.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_09]: Adam if you don't mind I can jump in on that Victor Schrader, economic development director I'm sorry I'm not on video my internet's unstable but yeah reverse 911 call should have gone out I did ask the communications department to do that and we were.
[SPEAKER_09]: Remind me, Adam, we were targeting 400 feet, 300 feet with the notice?
[SPEAKER_06]: 400 feet, yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: The reverse 911 should have been the same.
[SPEAKER_09]: So just for folks that are in the immediate area, you absolutely should have received notice of this.
[SPEAKER_09]: But please let us know if you didn't.
[SPEAKER_09]: We want to know about that.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you, Victor.
[SPEAKER_06]: Appreciate that.
[SPEAKER_06]: Cheryl?
[SPEAKER_10]: Good evening.
[SPEAKER_10]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_10]: I live on Park Street.
[SPEAKER_10]: I was in the waiting room and I only got let in when you said, and that concludes our presentation.
[SPEAKER_10]: So that was really helpful.
[SPEAKER_10]: But I didn't get any notice.
[SPEAKER_10]: And since the section of Park Street that you're planning to build on has maybe six parking spaces, and I'm on the next block, your overflow cars will 100% be in my block.
[SPEAKER_10]: So it's pretty important that my neighbors know about it.
[SPEAKER_10]: We have a lot of multifamilies in my section that don't all have driveways.
[SPEAKER_10]: So this is going to be a big impact on our lives.
[SPEAKER_10]: And Park, I'm wondering who is letting you believe that one parking space per unit is even feasible in this area because it's not?
[SPEAKER_10]: Our ordinances are for two per unit.
[SPEAKER_10]: So one is a really deep dive.
[SPEAKER_10]: And will one of these units be affordable because you're adding nine dense units to our area?
[SPEAKER_10]: So I'm just wondering if there's a benefit to the community, to the school.
[SPEAKER_10]: School supply donations every year.
[SPEAKER_06]: I mean, yeah, I don't know if Fernando or Sal want to speak to that at this point.
[SPEAKER_06]: I mean, I don't know that they've determined what the configuration is.
[SPEAKER_06]: But certainly, I mean, parking, traffic, all those things are going to be part of the approval process.
[SPEAKER_06]: I mean, I don't know, Cheryl, if you heard the comments of two of the other folks that were on before, but certainly, you know, parking,
[SPEAKER_06]: it's absolutely understood that it's something that needs to be considered as the project's developed.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, because I'm just wondering why people would feel that that was an appropriate variance to ask.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's a 50% reduction in parking in a very dense area.
[SPEAKER_10]: And you're going to blot out the sun on that area of Sound Street.
[SPEAKER_10]: We have two mature trees there that I'm sure you're going to tear out.
[SPEAKER_14]: No, there are no trees on the site right now.
[SPEAKER_14]: There are no trees whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_10]: No, they're on the city sidewalk.
[SPEAKER_14]: But we're not touching them.
[SPEAKER_14]: We can't touch those more.
[SPEAKER_14]: Number two, if I'm correct, I think the zoning has just changed or it's in the process of changing one car per unit.
[SPEAKER_14]: And it's not the two per one any longer.
[SPEAKER_14]: It's one car per unit.
[SPEAKER_14]: Most of our bedrooms, most of our units are all one bedrooms, not all two.
[SPEAKER_10]: It hasn't changed yet, and it's not going to be one.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's going to be one and a half, maybe, but it hasn't gone through yet.
[SPEAKER_14]: Jacob, how many two bedrooms we have?
[SPEAKER_10]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_13]: Right now, we have two two bedrooms.
[SPEAKER_14]: Two bedrooms, OK.
[SPEAKER_14]: So our study that we have, there's more and more people taking bicycles on the public T now these days, and not necessarily driving.
[SPEAKER_14]: You, myself, maybe majority of these people still drive, but all the new professionals, young professionals, single families, no children, don't, a lot of them don't drive any longer.
[SPEAKER_14]: A lot of them just have the car, they leave the cars, they look at cars in the parking lot.
[SPEAKER_14]: But that's what we considered.
[SPEAKER_14]: That's how we came to determination of one parking spot per unit.
[SPEAKER_14]: Some of these people won't even have cars.
[SPEAKER_14]: I've done enough developments knowing that we've always had more than enough parking, but there's always empty parking spots in the driveway, always in the garage.
[SPEAKER_14]: always.
[SPEAKER_14]: So with that said, we, we, we tend to do our parking study.
[SPEAKER_14]: We intend to do all that.
[SPEAKER_14]: We're not going to leave it out there saying, let's, well, let's see what happens.
[SPEAKER_14]: And if it goes from there, we, that's one of our assignments that we're going to be doing.
[SPEAKER_14]: We have to do that for the zoning board.
[SPEAKER_10]: So would you be willing to deed restrict on no cars from that building will be allowed to get permits and park on the street.
[SPEAKER_10]: that they're doing that in South Boston when they're short of parking.
[SPEAKER_14]: It's a good point.
[SPEAKER_14]: Do they have permit parking over there?
[SPEAKER_10]: They will once you come.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I mean, it's not out of the question.
[SPEAKER_10]: Sections of sections of our Medford does permit parking currently by street.
[SPEAKER_10]: They're looking at doing it by zone and
[SPEAKER_10]: Intentionally shorting your parking, rolling the dice that your units won't have cars, then you should bear the burden and not the neighborhood.
[SPEAKER_10]: You should deed restrict your tenants owners from ever getting permit parking.
[SPEAKER_10]: The express bus here.
[SPEAKER_10]: So a lot more people are getting cars because the T cut our bus.
[SPEAKER_06]: Victor.
[SPEAKER_06]: I see, I see your, your, your hands raised.
[SPEAKER_06]: Do you want to comment?
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, I just wanted to clarify on the zoning.
[SPEAKER_09]: Cheryl's right, the new zoning ordinance is not in effect yet.
[SPEAKER_09]: I think it will be when this project applies for relief.
[SPEAKER_09]: The current zoning ordinance or the new zoning ordinances as drafted is 1.5 parking spaces per unit.
[SPEAKER_09]: So the project will need to seek relief.
[SPEAKER_09]: It'll be by special permit, not variance, but that'll be part of the relief that they'll need to seek from either the zoning board or community development board.
[SPEAKER_06]: Great.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thanks, Victor.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm just trying to go in order here.
[SPEAKER_06]: Alex,
[SPEAKER_06]: Your hand raised.
[SPEAKER_00]: Alex?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm sorry I'm not on video.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm holding a baby, so kind of multitasking here.
[SPEAKER_00]: All right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I actually was just going to kind of bounce on one of the comments that Cheryl said, which was my main question or thought about this development is for affordable units.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just would strongly, strongly encourage you all to do whatever you could to
[SPEAKER_00]: add some units potentially so that we could be past the 10 unit threshold for inclusionary zoning.
[SPEAKER_00]: That new law went into play, it's still pretty new in 2019, and really hasn't been taken advantage of at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I would really, really like to see more developers taking advantage of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So personally, parking, your comment about
[SPEAKER_00]: you know, young folks taking bus and bike definitely resonated with me.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, I have a young family, we have two kids, we're a one car family, we have a cargo bike, we love it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I do think that that is
[SPEAKER_00]: you know, becoming more and more of a thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I'm really happy to see that too.
[SPEAKER_00]: So parking is not my number one concern, but I would think for, you know, for Medford as a whole, uh, really, really wanting to see that inclusionary zoning be taken advantage of more so we can provide more below market rate units as well as market rate, because they both, you know, that's a benefit to the city of Medford, um, just as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's, that's my, my biggest thing.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: Great.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thanks Alex.
[SPEAKER_06]: We appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Uh, Jamie.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, I was just going to sort of go off some of that.
[SPEAKER_12]: I mean, I don't know the ordinances and like if 10 units is better than nine or what that means.
[SPEAKER_12]: I mean, ideally, if people, everyone takes bus, you know, buses and cars, and that's great.
[SPEAKER_12]: I mean, not less, but I don't know necessarily if more is something I want them right across the street.
[SPEAKER_12]: But I will say that
[SPEAKER_12]: you know, the parking is the biggest issue, obviously, but that area was sort of an eyesore for a long time.
[SPEAKER_12]: So I'm hoping that this does sort of boost up value and does do good for a lot of the people who live around here.
[SPEAKER_12]: So, you know, do I want to see construction all day and stuff like that, but that just comes with it and the parking, but hopefully it benefits us in the long run with increasing the value of the area.
[SPEAKER_12]: Great.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thanks, Jamie.
[SPEAKER_06]: Appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Navar?
[SPEAKER_07]: Hi there, William Navar.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah, I wanted to say something similar to what Alex said.
[SPEAKER_07]: I think it's really great that
[SPEAKER_07]: the city's going to be able to welcome five, sorry, nine new households as neighbors.
[SPEAKER_07]: I think that's a wonderful thing.
[SPEAKER_07]: I think one of the wonderful things about building housing here in the city as opposed to out in, you know, Billerica or something is that's going to give people the chance to live without a car, which is something that people really value nowadays.
[SPEAKER_07]: And a lot of people,
[SPEAKER_07]: feel they're forced to own a car because they can't afford housing close to the city.
[SPEAKER_07]: And this, I think, is going to be a real benefit to us if we have more people living here in the city.
[SPEAKER_07]: Because people that live out of the city drive their cars through our city.
[SPEAKER_07]: We're what's known as a cut-through town.
[SPEAKER_07]: So when we send people to Billerica, they come back and drive through.
[SPEAKER_07]: As for the amount of units, I think it would be really great, and I think it's important to note that the City Council really did, one of the reasons they're settling at 1.5 spaces per unit,
[SPEAKER_07]: is because there's going to be a provision that you won't need a variance to reduce the parking.
[SPEAKER_07]: You'll be able to use special permit.
[SPEAKER_07]: And that's one of the reasons they're OK with leaving it even so high as 1.5, is that it's easier than it was before to knock that down.
[SPEAKER_07]: They were thinking to do a 1.2, and they said, OK, let's do 1.5 with the understanding that a special permit knocks that down.
[SPEAKER_07]: And that's deliberate.
[SPEAKER_07]: That's not a loophole.
[SPEAKER_07]: As for the number of units, I would love to see more.
[SPEAKER_07]: It would be really good if you could get inclusionary zoning, 10 units or more, put another floor on there, welcome a couple more neighbors, one of them affordable.
[SPEAKER_07]: I would really love to see that.
[SPEAKER_07]: And if if there are certain reasons regulatory why you can't do that.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'd be open to open to hearing about that because you know our our City Council and everything really wants rules that make it so people can do this community need so just as a helpful thing to the community and it can be really great if if there's a good if there's a reason that's not possible because the rules are something just let us know that we can learn from that going forward and advocate for things to make to make that situation better going forward.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thanks.
[SPEAKER_06]: Great, thanks so much, appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Anyone else with any questions, comments?
[SPEAKER_14]: If I may, the idea of the fourth floor did come across our desk at the time, and I think in that particular zoning, I think we have the right to go four stories, but I thought, and we had a long discussion about this, I think the majority of the neighbors would know
[SPEAKER_14]: like that idea of going four stories.
[SPEAKER_14]: I mean, we don't mind inclusionary housing.
[SPEAKER_14]: I mean, you know, this is what we do it all the time.
[SPEAKER_14]: And the nine units we have there now are just the right size.
[SPEAKER_14]: I mean, if we went another story and, you know, Jacob, can you tell us, what are your thoughts on another story and how many units you can put in there?
[SPEAKER_14]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_13]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_13]: I mean, obviously, one issue with going higher is there's the height limit in Medford.
[SPEAKER_13]: So that'd be some relief you'd be asking for there.
[SPEAKER_13]: So the current 35 foot height limit is being achieved with this design.
[SPEAKER_13]: So by adding another story, we'd probably do a similar floor plan and get another, you know, maybe four units in there, which we have per floor.
[SPEAKER_13]: So you would go, you know, maybe 45 feet, which is going to be taller than the building across the street.
[SPEAKER_13]: But there are some taller buildings in the area.
[SPEAKER_13]: But having said that, you could add another four units if you just added another story on top.
[SPEAKER_13]: But it would be something we would want to look at also the shadows that would be cast
[SPEAKER_13]: And that's another parking concern where if you add another four units, you know, one of the reasons we were trying to hit nine units was because of the parking issue.
[SPEAKER_13]: So we've been the goal has been a one in one.
[SPEAKER_13]: And we think that's a good ratio.
[SPEAKER_13]: I know it's a really challenging site.
[SPEAKER_13]: So having one in one is beneficial.
[SPEAKER_13]: But if you add another four units in there, it's going to be hard to add more parking.
[SPEAKER_13]: You're going to start shrinking that commercial space on the first floor if we want to start adding more parking.
[SPEAKER_13]: The next thing you know the whole building is going to be up on people say, and you're going to lose the entire corner there on Park Street and Salem Street, so we could try to go up to, you know, to be at another for you.
[SPEAKER_13]: option for maybe go back to rooms and try to expand the floor plate in that realm.
[SPEAKER_13]: But talking to the town earlier, we thought it was a good mix of having two beds and one bed is really a need for the city in the sweet spot.
[SPEAKER_02]: Great.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thanks, Jacob.
[SPEAKER_06]: All right.
[SPEAKER_06]: Any, any, any other thoughts, comments, questions.
[SPEAKER_06]: About, uh, uh, any, anyone from the city, Victor and anything before we wrap up here.
[SPEAKER_09]: No, Adam, thanks for presenting today.
[SPEAKER_09]: I mean, the purpose of these meetings is to hear from neighbors before an application is submitted.
[SPEAKER_09]: So thank you all for coming out.
[SPEAKER_09]: And we hope that the developer will take your comments into consideration.
[SPEAKER_09]: And please, you know, continue to show up as this project goes through the process.
[SPEAKER_09]: And thank you for your time.
[SPEAKER_06]: Great, thank you, Victor.
[SPEAKER_06]: I appreciate that.
[SPEAKER_06]: Looks like we have one hand raised from Ann Sullivan.
[SPEAKER_11]: Hi, I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_11]: I also did not get to see the presentation.
[SPEAKER_11]: I came in a little bit late and was not able to get on right away.
[SPEAKER_11]: So I can't really comment because I have not seen the design.
[SPEAKER_11]: But the building across the street from it, the corner of Park and Salem, I believe it's called the Potter building, is very unique.
[SPEAKER_11]: You drive down Salem Street and you notice it right away.
[SPEAKER_11]: It's a three story building.
[SPEAKER_11]: It has
[SPEAKER_11]: an interesting roofline and whatever and is there any design element that takes a look at what is offered on that side of the street so there's almost like a balance rather than putting up a modern you know very different kind of building and then across the street you have this lovely brick building with you know a sort of a angled entrance and all of that I mean
[SPEAKER_11]: I didn't get to see the design, so I have no.
[SPEAKER_13]: yeah can you can you make me host again at a really quick door.
[SPEAKER_11]: That'd be great.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_11]: And I apologize.
[SPEAKER_11]: No problem, Anne.
[SPEAKER_13]: We absolutely love the Potter building across the street.
[SPEAKER_13]: So it's been a huge influence on what we've been designing.
[SPEAKER_13]: So I just need to wait to become host.
[SPEAKER_13]: And I'll show you kind of our rendering in 3D view here.
[SPEAKER_13]: We think that building is absolutely gorgeous.
[SPEAKER_13]: And compared to some of the things that have been being built down the street, we want to definitely play off our neighbor across the street with the detailing, the window trim, the bump outs, the brickwork.
[SPEAKER_13]: That's yeah great.
[SPEAKER_13]: That is absolutely gorgeous.
[SPEAKER_13]: I'm the host now so just give me a quick second here I'm going to share my screen, and hopefully you can see this rendering we've been working on.
[SPEAKER_13]: So, if you could see the trim here in all this detail, we want to do something very similar.
[SPEAKER_13]: to the Salem street side where we have these bump outs and even on the park side we want to do these.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_13]: We want to the brick work on the first floor we want to do our best to try to match the combination of the yellow brick on the lower end and the higher red brick light brick on the top do some sort of blend on the lower end.
[SPEAKER_13]: We want to keep the same kind of rough opening scale on the first floor, that is, on the second floor.
[SPEAKER_13]: We want to play with the banding that they have on the roof deck and on the middle part too, as you can kind of see here.
[SPEAKER_13]: I'm going to take you to these axons really quick so you can kind of see a little bit more 3D.
[SPEAKER_13]: That building is a high influence on us, so it's definitely something we're taking in consideration.
[SPEAKER_13]: I mean, we're still early in the project, obviously.
[SPEAKER_13]: But 100%, we love that.
[SPEAKER_12]: And these aren't the finished color schemes or anything, right?
[SPEAKER_12]: This is just sort of your initial design.
[SPEAKER_13]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_13]: By no means are these the finished color schemes.
[SPEAKER_13]: We're just trying to show the idea is going to have a contrast of colors and play on what's across the street.
[SPEAKER_13]: It's a little challenging.
[SPEAKER_13]: They used this green there.
[SPEAKER_13]: So we don't want to really match that.
[SPEAKER_13]: Right.
[SPEAKER_13]: And we still want to have a little bit of modern, you know, we don't want to look like something we're trying to copy from the past.
[SPEAKER_13]: So this corner in the front, which we're still working on, is going to be a huge opportunity for us.
[SPEAKER_13]: I got a little bit of background noise there.
[SPEAKER_13]: I hope that answers your question a little bit.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, thank you.
[SPEAKER_11]: I missed the beginning, so thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_11]: I have one other question for you.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm listening to some of the abutting neighbors talking about parking, and I noticed that on number 237 Park Street, which is almost two doors down from this building, it is up for sale now,
[SPEAKER_11]: which might be a tear down and which might be another proposed development.
[SPEAKER_11]: And has anyone been aware of that, that the house further down the street?
[SPEAKER_06]: And I think we lost you there for a moment.
[SPEAKER_11]: OK, I think I was muted there.
[SPEAKER_11]: 237 Park Street is up for sale right now.
[SPEAKER_11]: And it's I'm listening to the neighbors talking about parking, which is right across the street from the school and how difficult it is.
[SPEAKER_11]: And it looks like it might be a teardown and it might be another multi multi use spot.
[SPEAKER_05]: Has anyone
[SPEAKER_11]: you know, looked at the timing of, of developing that property while this was going up.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thanks.
[SPEAKER_06]: And if you're still with us in, I don't know that that particular property is, I mean, it's certainly on our radar, but I don't know that there was much consideration to what could be developed there currently, considering it's current use.
[SPEAKER_06]: Although if that's incorrect, Fernando or Sal, if you have anything else to add to that, please feel free.
[SPEAKER_06]: I was gonna say you could make a parking lot out of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: We did try to purchase the other, talk to the neighbors on the side of the property to buy the other properties and try to enlarge the building or get more units or get more parking, but that didn't work.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that's pretty stupid, the same play that we have.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: All right, great, thanks.
[SPEAKER_06]: Uh, well, yeah, and just to echo, uh, Victor's comments, I do want to say, you know, thanks so much for everyone who came out.
[SPEAKER_06]: Um, this is the beginning of, of, of a conversation relative to this, um, this proposal.
[SPEAKER_06]: And, uh, you know, my, my contact information was included on the, uh, the handout, uh, and the poster, but my email is ARB at R I W.com.
[SPEAKER_06]: But I think that everyone here will certainly be hearing from us as things progress.
[SPEAKER_06]: And thank you again all for your comments.
[SPEAKER_06]: And with that, have a great night.
[SPEAKER_06]: We'll all speak soon.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you, everybody.
[SPEAKER_06]: Really quick.
[SPEAKER_13]: Adam, everybody, this meeting was recorded.
[SPEAKER_13]: So if you didn't make it to the beginning, you have an opportunity to go back and look at us walking through this.
[SPEAKER_13]: And thank you, everybody.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you, everybody.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you.