Hey, Medford Bites listeners. Today's episode includes an interview with Mayor Brianna Lungo-Kern. This interview is full of information about the mayor's current work and upcoming plans for the city. I hope you enjoy the interview. All right, thank you so much for joining me this morning. If you don't mind just introducing yourself with your name, pronouns, and your role here. Sure. I'm Brianna Lungo-Kern, Mayor of Medford, and I use the pronouns she and her.
Great, thank you so much. And congratulations on winning your next term, your current term. I was hoping to chat with you a little bit today about kind of any reflections you have on the election and stuff that you're sort of looking forward to, your kind of priorities for this term. Yeah, no, I think with the election, I'm glad it's behind us. It was a tough six months, but I
really excited to work with the school committee and the city council that was elected. And we have so much work to do, but I feel like we have two good groups along with all of our great employees that really can get a lot of work done. So I'm excited. Awesome. Great. Yeah. And what are some of the things that you're sort of your priorities for this, this term? There's there's so many things we're working on, but I'll, I'll just name a few. I mean, I'm excited to collaborate with the council on
the zoning reform, which hopefully will be passed in the next month or two. We also sent the city council a housing production plan that the city worked on along with volunteers and employees within our community. And I'm excited to work with the city council to start implementing some of those initiatives so that we can work on our, obviously our housing crisis, our food crisis. We have a,
Great news is yesterday we posted for a diversity, equity, and inclusion director. So we hope to have somebody on board helping with that within the next 30 to 45 days, which is really exciting. This new council recently approved the CAF for the human resource director. So we're able to move forward and now hire a diversity director. It's just very exciting steps that we know
works for several, several months. We have some hiring we've been doing on the police and the fire side, we are restructuring our Department of Public Works, and we made some changes there, but we have a wonderful acting director and Tim McGivern who worked very well, especially in the last snowstorm and is really trying to
implement planning and organization and management goals for the department. So those amazing employees that work hard every day just have structure and we can get even more done than we ever have before. We have our parking director who is completely in the weeds because we, the contract with Park Medford ended on January 6th.
So like I said, in my inauguration speech, we're asking for patience while we just work through the next month. We have about nine or 10 individuals who are hired in that department and currently getting trained, currently out assessing and documenting our private ways and our streets and getting ready to start a warning system, which we wanna do first, which will probably take place in the next, start taking place in the next couple of weeks.
So those are a few of the many climate change we're working to implement our climate adaptation and action plan. We are working on trying to get some movement in Medford Square, we're going to be.
Applying for a grant to do a design on the waterfront in the square, and then at the same time also trying to start drafting an RFI on Memphis square lots to get some mixed use development within in the square so our economic development directors working hard on those two initiatives.
Yeah, I don't know if you have any questions, but I can probably keep going. Yeah, no, that's a lot. So I do have one question about one of the first things you mentioned, the diversity, equity, inclusion, and the human resources director. Is that where that situation where they were combined initially as one role, and did you split them? And I've been hearing from some of the other city councilors about the budget for that position and sort of shifting the priority there a little bit.
Yeah, it was always when I first came in I we did not have a human resource department so I just asked Mr Osborne who my transition team thought was fully capable of just working on both those roles, and it was always our plan to hire.
human resource director and a diversity director. When we had to cut a million dollars from the budget, he stayed in those two roles, always knowing that once we recovered from what we were going through, we would be hiring a human resource director and a diversity and inclusion director. And the council wanted those budgets split, which we did. We did that in June fiscal year 22 for the fiscal year 22 budget.
budgets are completely split, and this was always our goal to hire, you know, both, both directors and we're finally at, at the point where human resource directors jobs been capped, and we can just thankfully move forward with a human resource department, and then separately diversity and inclusion.
Um, director is what has been posted now. So awesome. Yep. Great. Cool. And, um, I did notice the skating rink is up at car park. And so those are some exciting stuff with the parks. It's, uh, um, I mean, that seems like really good timing this year, right before it's getting really cold. Um, so also from, for some cold weather, we didn't put them up last year because of COVID. And then the year before we put the rinks up.
But we never had the three, never the whole winter, never had three straight days for enough for it to freeze. So here's a crossed. Cause I drove by to car park and my son's like, what is that? I'm like, that's a hockey rink. We just needed to, so I can take you. We're excited. So just need a few cold days and hopefully get that up and running. And then we also hired a director, you know, a manager of the rink.
La Conte rink and Hormel Stadium. So our goal is to try to go as close to year round as possible. And we're going to kind of pilot it this year. And I know the cost of utilities is expensive, but if we can keep that operational almost year round, maybe just a one month shut down, that's our goal. So that we can enjoy it year round for birthdays and parties, reskate and rent it for an hour.
clinics, all types of different things. REC is really involved. That position falls under our REC director, so it's exciting. We have some beautiful art murals that were just designed by artist Jamie Chan that we'll be publicizing soon, that hopefully will be painted at La Conte in April.
Nice. Cool. And what about school committee? I know it probably you're the last two years have been pretty full up with things addressing COVID, but anything that you're particularly excited about for the school committee? Yes. The school committee is a group of hard workers, and we have a lot of things we're working on. But for me, my goal is to really try to get a diverse vision committee implemented within the next
two, three months to start our vision for the new high school or completely rehabbed or type of high school we need to put serious time and energy into updating that facility or completely
fingers crossed getting an MSBA loan so that we can give our students a facility that they can be proud of. And that is my main goal right now. So I have a meeting with our superintendent next week and I know the school committee's on board to really get that off the ground. That was the committee that sort of had formed and then you kind of be like disbanded to sort of hope that there would be a more, it would become a more diverse group. Right. Okay.
Right, yeah, we implemented it with the applications that came before us prior to my being mayor. So we disbanded it and we really, then COVID, we've been so entrenched in trying to get our students and staff back safely and all the testing we've been doing. And the nurses, obviously, we have a lot on their plate now, but we need to, whether it's COVID or not, we need to
work to get that implemented. And that's a goal for the next several months. Awesome. Um, I did want to ask about the, the ways that like school committee, or you were thinking about some of the stuff we heard about kind of before the winter break around some incidents of violence in the school. And so students, um, you know, sort of acting out violently towards each other. Yeah, I, I, um, that's been a,
definitely a topic of conversation and something that I know that the superintendent and the administrative staff, as well as the school committee, have really taken a good look at. A lot had to do with trying to hear from students, hear from staff, and I know the administration did a good job bringing people together and doing what they could.
it was very concerning the amount of violence that was happening at one of our elementary schools and our high school. And some of the activity that was going on on our buses, whether it was COVID and mental health and social media, some of this TikTok and challenge type activity is just so concerning.
for students from across the country to be throwing these challenges out and for our students to be taking hold of them was something we had to get a handle on. So I was involved behind the scenes, you know, just making sure that we were doing the right things, you know, should have cell phones in school, you know, make sure we're listening and doing whatever we can to make sure everybody's, our administrative staff, principals, vice principals are on the same page.
because what happened is not okay. And we just have to, it's something we have to continue to work on. So it was exciting to have our first behavioral health committee meeting at the police station with, it's a committee of at least 11 social workers and psychologists and the police chiefs, the veterans director, Penny from prevention and outreach.
And Pat Brady, who's a local psychologist, really our focus needs to be on mental health and how we can help our students because they're not only dealing with their own stress, they're dealing with their family stress and what they're going through at home and what their parents are going through or grandparents. And we need to do all we can to help each and every student, you know,
be on the right path, make sure everybody's safe and feel safe. So there's a lot of work that still needs to be done. And I thank that committee for the role they're taking. I thank the admin for continuing. I don't wanna just have been reactive based on what happened that month. We just need to continue to work at it. And I know Avery Hines is working her butt off trying to make sure every student has what they need to be successful and to feel safe.
And I know that Pat Brady, even from the city, she's willing, she's reached out to Avery and they're collaborating on having mental health, you know, sessions to help our students. So just to have the community and the staff and everybody working together, it's a work in progress, but I feel confident we can get there and make sure, you know, everybody's on a better path than they were in December.
Yeah, it was certainly shocking and and I think it's hard to, you know, I think the way that kids engage with like social media is.
I think it's just like changing so rapidly that it's hard to sort of keep up with what they're seeing and exposed to. And like, I think that sometimes there's this approach of like almost like abstinence, like, well, we won't, we won't let them use it, but that there's like, there has to be some middle ground of like, how do they use it responsibly? How are they talking about what they're seeing? And I wonder if there's like any opportunity or if it's already happening to sort of include that in like a health curriculum or some sort of like the way in which like when I was in high school, we talked about like drug use that maybe there's some like,
overlap with like social media use or, and the mental health aspect of that. Absolutely. I, I'm not sure if it's in the health curriculum, but I'm almost positive that the students do have, you know, seminars. I know my daughter is at the McGlynn Middle School and Nick Tucci, you know, is very on top of these issues. So
We just want to make sure it's uniform across the board, and I know they're working hard, all the administrators, to do all they can. But yes, education for the students, it's a must. Sure, yeah.
I mean, it does feel like with the transition back to school with COVID that there has been like a much more of an emphasis on mental health as a necessity, but I think it's encouraging to see that that's being responded to so well. So for you, anything that you want to talk about that like constituents, like voters could get involved in or anything that you want to hear from residents for, you know, sort of support in your second term?
I, I think it's important for, you know, everybody in the community to get involved, whether, and everybody has different time constraints, but there's open positions in some of our boards and commissions. There's a number of positions that will be open in the spring as well. But if that's too much of a commitment, you know, we have our comprehensive master plan where you can do on your own, you know, you can take a look on our city website on your own time.
and kind of just outline things you think should change or where you think different types of zoning should fit or more green space. So that's just like a couple minutes on the computer. I just think it's good to get involved. If you see a survey come out, you know, I know we did a parking survey and we've done a composting survey. We've had 900 to a thousand people responding to those surveys. So the simple things like that, staying involved, staying active, reading the Medford patch,
you know, knowing what's going on in your community, I think it's important. You know, when the community conversations are going to come up and just get involved. I said it at the end of my inauguration speech, like get involved and learn and grow with me in 2022. We all have growing to do and me included. And if we're going to try to start offering trainings for not only staff, but our residents,
jump on a call and get involved, you know, always learn and grow and be more accepting and understanding and inclusive. That's our main goal. And my goal is, I know it's ambitious, but to not only offer staff those supports, but our residents too. No, no, I just, we're all more alike than we know. And I, I think we're,
If we could just show that somehow, it would be a better place. Sure. Yeah, I appreciate that stance of sort of like open to growth and including the community in that growth and understanding. Are there any specific things that you want to mention about that sort of those goals of inclusivity? Yeah, actually, we just we did a press release this week and we're forming two
task force type planning committees, we really want to have a multicultural events, sometime, you know, sometime in 22.
we want people involved, not only just to volunteer, but to tell us like, what's the, about, you know, a number of different cultures and how best to reach out to everybody and really form a committee so that we can be as inclusive as possible and do it the right way. And then we also want to have a pride event in June. So we are asking people if they wanna be involved in that, the more the merrier to help us plan that.
So there is a one page form that you can just grab on our boards and commission web web page and fill that out say you're interested and we're going to be forming the pride. committee, you know, within the next couple month or two and then the multicultural event i'm assuming would be after that.
Great. I can definitely link that in our show notes so people can maybe access it a little easier there too. I know we posted it on social media, but I can also send you the press release as well. It explains the trainings that my staff
are going to take on cultural awareness. And then at the end, just asking people to get involved in the events, but anything we have, you know, when we do our next holiday celebration, we, we want people involved. We want to do it right. You know, our goal is to be inclusive and we got it wrong this year on a, on a point, but we, that was, that was a mistake. And we, we want to.
have everybody involved that wants to be involved and just do it the right way. Because our goal is to be more inclusive and get the community together, all together.
Yeah, thank you for mentioning that. It sounds like you're sort of reflecting on some of the things that you and your staff have took away from that incident and how you can kind of learn. And I think some of the feedback that I was hearing was like how to take away, what you can take away from that experience to sort of create like a plan moving forward. So like being, like you're saying, like learning what you can do more proactively rather than having to be reactive when there's like mistakes like that. That sounds great. Thanks.
We learned, but we'll be better for it, and more inclusive for it. And we've built great relationships just even since the incident. And it's very hopeful, and I'm excited to have the partnerships now that we formed. Great. Awesome. Was there anything else that you wanted to mention today before we wrap up?
No, I can't think of anything. I mean, I'm sure I missed a ton of what we're doing. You know, I didn't even talk. The rec department is getting ready for their winter and spring and summer catalog that will hit in a week or two. They're working hard on that. There's just so many great things going on. Catch a game if you can. I know it's COVID, but I just went to the
girls varsity hockey game and then stayed for some of the boys varsity hockey games. So that was, people think, you know, they can't go out at all, but it was very safe. Everybody was socially distanced. So take a look at the link and catch a game, you know, just be part of the community. And yeah, so many other great things going on, but I appreciate the time and you letting me explain, you know, some of it.
Yeah. And also, um, I know the last time we talked was, uh, in the fall, but we did get a chance to go to the girls on the run race, um, that you all were organizing and that was an awesome experience. So, um, thanks for doing that. And, uh, yeah, that's, um, this is also our first summer of having to figure out summer camp. So that's something that I, the rec department seems like it'll be helpful with too. Um, yeah. Yeah. That's great programming. And my six acres has a camp and then my, my children went to the Medford
summer fun camp, um, up at the Columbus. They loved it. They're already asking if they can go again. They talk about their counselors nonstop. So, um, there's a lot of great opportunities out there. Absolutely. We have, um, the girls in the run is hopefully going to be in Medford again in June. So we're excited about that. And then we also have a big race plans. Um, I'll let you be one of the first to know, hopefully sometime in
September we're working with Dave McGovery, who organizes the Boston marathon to do, you know, just a really big race weekend here in Medford. So we're excited. Cool. It sounds fun. Awesome. Well, thank you so much for joining me again. And, uh, hopefully we'll get to connect again soon. Yes, absolutely. Thank you for having me. Yeah.
Thank you so much to Mayor Lungo Kern for the conversation. More information about some of the topics mentioned, including open positions on boards and the planning committees for pride and multicultural events, the comprehensive master plan, updates to the parking plan, and the mayor's inauguration speech are included in the show notes.
Thanks so much for listening to today's episode, and as always, if you have feedback about this episode or ideas for future episodes, you can email medfordpod at gmail.com. You can also subscribe, rate, and review the podcast on Spotify and Apple Podcasts. Thanks so much for listening. Guys, what's the name of the podcast? Medford Bites!