city council committee of the whole may 7 2024 mr. Kirk please call the roll present present
present five present two absent the meeting is called to order there'll be a meeting of the Medford City Council committee the whole 6 p.m. the Medford City Council chamber second floor Medford City Hall 85 George P has to drive Medford ma and via zoom to submit written comments please email a her to be set Medford dash ma dot gov the purpose of this meeting is to discuss paper 2 4-0 0 9 the community development block grant action plan for fiscal year 2025
This is for community development and planning. The action plan contains the proposed use of community development block grant funds for the program year, which extends from July 1st, 2024 through June 30th, 2025. CDBG is a program of the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development that began in 1974. Fiscal 2025 will be the city of Medford's program year 50 of CDBG funding. Happy 50th birthday to CDBG. And Councilor Collins has joined us as well. So with that, I will turn over to our CDBG manager,
we'll see. All right. Thank you so much. So yes, we're presenting the figures for the coming year and the proposed use of funds. Interestingly, we actually got the final figures a couple of hours ago from HUD. They were expected to come out tomorrow. So all the figures in the plan that I had provided you were estimated funds. But the actual allocation for us, fortunately, is a little bit higher than the original estimate. So the total actual allocation that we're going to get is $1 million
$384,050 from HUD. So our cut for this year, it's still a reduction from the present year, but it's only a 2.8 reduction versus the 12% that we had been anticipating. Just if I could ask, do you know what that's going to bring us to for the public services funding?
Absolutely. So we had projected $187,922 for public services, and the actual will be $207,607.50. So that's an increase of $19,685.50. Great. Thank you so much.
Anything else you want to say before we hear from some of our applicants? No, no. So we've, yeah, we've invited our applicants to participate tonight. So we are going to start with Megan Fidler-Carey from the schools to talk about their afterschool program. Great. We recognize Megan Fidler-Carey. Hi, Megan.
Hello, thank you, thank you, Laurel. Thank you for the opportunity. As always, we've been the fortunate recipient of this grant for several years and we put it to very good use in my opinion. My title is the Director of Family and Community Engagement for Medford Public Schools. And one of the departments I oversee is the before and after school program. And this is a tuition funded program. We do not provide free before and after school care for families, but we do provide
the care and we do offer financial assistance to families who need it. So we use the income verification forms that are provided through the CDBG application process and we determine need based on that. And with that, families can get up to 70% discount on their before or after school tuition.
So we use these funds, we request the full amount of the $10,000, which I understand, you know, has been depends on how much the state gives us or the federal gives us. But we request $10,000 to contribute towards our scholarship program, which this year and last year is upwards of $45,000 in financial assistance that we have been able to give to families.
because we realize that like many families won't be able to keep their job if they can't afford child care. So we want to make sure that as many families in the Medford Public Schools have access as possible. The afterschool programs are in the four elementary schools and we offer every family the opportunity to apply for financial assistance. We just give a blanket application along with when we request their, you know, emergency contact details, for example. So it's a really
It's a really, it's a private way to talk to families about their need, addressing their need. And we also offer it if we, if families kind of confide in us that they're having financial struggles in any way, we remind them that financial assistance is available. And we're really grateful to CDBG that this funding exists. And we think that's a great way to use it. Thank you, Megan. Any questions for Megan, for members of the council?
Seeing none, we will go to our next applicant, which is the Welcome Project. Sarah Lodgen, if you could give us a summary of your request.
Yes, hi, thank you for having me. I'm the director of multilingual programs at the welcome project. We are a nonprofit organization that's been operating since 1987 in Somerville, but we work with immigrant populations in Medford and other cities around really anybody who can make it to us and have been doing so.
In terms of education and advocacy work for the last 40 something years, 30 something years. So we're requesting CBG funding for the 1st time from Medford. We have been receiving funding from Somerville for several years, but with changing demographics of where immigrants are living in our area, we have seen a really.
sharp uptick in the amount of constituents of ours that are living in medford now as opposed to somerville which was more typical in the past so this funding would specifically be for. English for speakers of other languages program called the english for parents program or pp we've actually been running this for the last seven years in somerville but we expanded into medford
Um, a year and a half ago, and have been running this program in collaboration with Medford public schools, although we haven't received funding from the schools or the city before, which is why we're here requesting that the English for parents program is specifically designed for immigrant parents with children in Medford public schools of any age.
And it's an English for Speakers of Other Languages program, as I said, so they learn English in two different classes. There's a morning class and an evening class. And they're learning English with a focus on helping them navigate the school system and understand who to go to if their child needs help academically or socially or
if there's like any issue that comes up and they might not understand like how the school system works and how to best really support their child through their children's education. So this does a lot to kind of teach about the public school system as well as teaching English to parents, which also then in turn will help their children as
you know, studies show that parents who are more involved in child's education, which you're more able to do when you speak English at a higher level and understand the school system, that means that, you know, children are typically more successful with fewer dropout rates when they're older as well. So, that's really our goal to have immigrant parents in Medford really take more of an active role in their child's
educational development and have the skills to be able to do that. And as I mentioned, we've been running the program for the last year and a half. And our previous funding, which was from a private foundation, has run its course of like a three year grant that we had. So we're hoping to be able to continue the program. We've enrolled about 75 immigrant parents as students each semester. So we're really having a pretty large reach in this. Yeah, that's that's pretty much it. Thank you. Thank you so much.
Do we have any questions for the applicant from the Welcome Project? Seeing none, Laurel, I do have a question. For the folks who did not receive, who requested money but were not recommended, are we expecting them to make a case for themselves? They were invited to participate if they wanted to, but I don't believe that we have anybody attending from those organizations right now. All right, great. Do we have anyone from Community Family? Yes, we have Stacy. Great.
I'll recognize Stacey. Stacey, welcome. If you could tell us a little bit about your application request for CDBG funds for the community family. Yes, good evening, councilors and city officials. Thank you for all your previous support. So I am the brand new executive director of community family. We operate the state's first dementia certified center in Medford. It's an adult day health center for older adults.
Not specifically all older adults, because as sadly to report, there are some younger folks that are showing early onset dementia or cognitive abilities. And we're very appreciative of the CDBG funding because it allows us to gap
the start dates for folks that may not have long-term care insurance policies, may not be eligible for MassHealth, and we use the funding to provide scholarships for folks to start in our Medford Center. It's located at 121 Washington Street. I'm sure you're familiar with the old train station.
community family has been in business since 1978. We purchased it from the city. And I have to tell you, we operate a great program and it's nice to see that we're able to take care of Medford's older citizens. I welcome you to come visit us anytime and check out the facility. And I just appreciate this offer. Thank you. Great, thank you. Any questions for community family?
Stacey, I just wanted to say thank you. I was, as a Medford public school student, volunteer in community service at the Buddy Cohalen Center and Alzheimer's has affected my family. So really appreciate it. Thank you so much. I appreciate it. Thank you. All right. Next, we will go to Megan Transport, LLC. Right behind you, Laurel.
No, actually, I can just grab the mic. I can sit right here. It's fine. Hi, everyone. My name is Nima. Can you guys hear me? Okay. You might need to get a little closer. We're working on upgrading the system. You can grab the chair behind you, too. No, it's okay. It's not going to be too long.
Hi, everyone. My name is Nima. I'm the program director for McGinn Transport. We are, for the people who don't know, based in Medford. I was raised in Medford, live in Medford. Our business is based in Medford. So really, McGinn Transport likes to, or we strive to work to serve our community.
So we are here today trying to request an extension of these grants that we've been receiving in order to support senior transportation needs in Medford. Every single person currently registered for our service is low to medium income, so 100% of our participants are ridership. 75% of them are low or very low income.
Our program fulfills the objectives of CDBG, especially in three ways, improved access to health care, enhanced food security and financial relief. Many low income seniors struggle to access medical care due to transportation barriers. A lot of times, you know, it's like a last minute, like a last minute MRI and they need to go in the next two days and they don't have
They can't book a transportation service that might take a week or two to book. So we're really demand responsive. Non-emergency demand responsive is our most important core. And yeah, we also provide our second most important issue that we're tackling is providing
affordable and nutritious food options to our seniors by traveling with the seniors to Market Basket or certain areas that they prefer to buy groceries from because it will make their dollar stretch farther. So we are applying this grant to extend what we've been working on. We have been hearing such a positive feedback from our community, both through Pam Kelly at the Senior Center,
through our friends at the Medford Housing Authority. Everyone is very excited and really thankful for our program. It really has done a lot to support the seniors of our community. So thank you for supporting us in the past, and we look forward to working together in the future. Thank you. Any questions? Thank you so much. Any questions?
Oh, sorry, Vice President Collins. Thank you so much for being here. I always appreciate hearing the rundown of the services that you provide in the community for our excellent partners at the Council on Aging and the MIJ. I noticed that this funding would mostly go towards supporting your existing services through the first quarter of FY25. I was just wondering... The first quarter, you said? Is it just that the CDBG funding would enable continued service through the first quarter of FY25, or would it be year-round?
well because of the limited funding um we were speaking to laurel about this and we're also uh justin counselor justin's not in person here today but we have a transportation brainstorming group with laurel and alicia um to try to see how we can continue to fund projects like this in the future but as of right now we do know that we
we don't have, we won't have full access to the money that we requested. We are trying to see how we can supplement that, you know, so it can fulfill us through the end of or, you know, July 2025. We're looking at different avenues right now with Alicia and Laurel and our transportation brainstorming group.
Um, but we want to fund this as, you know, as long as we can, because every appointment is just so important. Um, every meeting that we take our seniors to, it's all like necessary. It's all essential stuff. It's not like, I'm going to go see my friend or something. They're all really need this transportation. And they always tell us like, you know, I would have skipped this really important MRI or CT scan. If I didn't have anyone to take me, I just kind of ignore it.
So we're looking to use whatever funds we can get to try to fund this for as long as possible. And then supplement, we're looking at more stuff to supplement it through the second half of the year. Great, thank you, that's helpful. And I know that a lot of minds in this room, including Councillor Senghap and working on those ongoing conversations about kind of filling out the transit network. Right, right, yeah. Just kind of reimagining for the Councillors who don't know, we've been talking about reimagining what transportation in Medford is going to look like past this year, especially since CDBG funding is
slowly dwindling and it is, you know, federal funding, so that tends to happen. So we've been in the talks, so we're hoping to maintain this program for as long as we can and looking at different creative ways to problem-solve the financial kind of, you know, funding at that end of it. Great. Thank you. And I know we're eager to support that extension. Thank you. Thank you. All right. We will go to our next
Applicant the Medford Council on Aging will go to Pam Kelly and give us a description of your request, please. Good evening, everybody.
Our Council on Aging is looking to extend the CDBG grant again this year for many programs that we offer that are not funded through other financial means. For example, we have a handy person maintenance program. The gentleman goes out to people's homes who need to be able to stay in their homes with safety. For example, changing light bulbs,
Also changing out any smoke detectors, batteries, tightening handrails, helping with doors, anything that's going to make their life easier while they're staying in home. So the handy person is only covered under the CDBG grant.
Also, recreational transportation, which allows us to offer discounted trips, day trips for our seniors to have social events. If we didn't have this funding, we wouldn't be able to offer our day trips at a discounted rate for many of our Medford seniors.
Our social worker has been able to have an extended time working with us. She is part-time and this fund helps her to outreach to more homebound Medford seniors so she's able to get to them.
for those who cannot come to our office. And as well as our Mystic Valley Elder Services Title III match, that grant affords many Medford senior population with Meals on Wheels, with in-home care, and other funding services.
This match through the CDBG and our municipal grant, not grant, our municipal budget is quite a help for us to keep that service going. Also, our volunteer outreach coordinator does many things each and every month, so this provides her with an additional funding to keep her part-time salary going as well. We look to
continue reaching out to the demographics. As you know, we have a very large senior population with over 12,766 seniors. So this just helps us continue with what we do at the Council on Aging. Thank you, Director Kelly. Any further questions for Director Kelly and the Council on Aging?
Seeing none, thank you, Pam. We will go next to Mystic Valley YMCA, Mystic Community Market. And we have Debbie Amaral available. Wonderful. Hi, Debbie. Hi, everybody. First of all, thank you for all your support that you've given to us in many different ways. I'm sorry for my lighting at my house.
but I truly appreciate all of you. Our CDBG is being used to support operations at the Mystic Community Market located at 291 Mystic Ave. And we have been serving from Medford through CDBG 5,000 individuals. And those are the low,
And moderate very low, low and moderate income individuals but that's not all Medford individuals if people are aren't confirmed I don't want to share income. There's even more individuals from Medford that we do serve.
but there's still more to be served. Recent data shows that one in five individuals in Medford is, are food insecure and so that there's much more to be done. We also, we presently deliver to about 80 seniors or homebound individuals. We
bring food twice a week, twice a month to the senior center and includes proteins and fresh vegetables and the seniors pack bags there and distribute for us. Thank you, Pam. We also will offer Lyft rides and Uber rides to individuals who can't get a ride to come to us. I think a lot of people don't realize that we have that service available, but especially at the high school,
We find it easier for people who don't have a ride for their family, sometimes to do that rather than trying to carry their bags on public transportation so we can make that available.
We've also have the in-person shopping that the person can come in and pick what they need. We also support the food policy council for the city of Medford, not only through the resiliency hub funds that the city has, but we've also written for the local food council grant through the Massachusetts Department of Agriculture.
So we've been trying to support food security work throughout Medford. We're happy to do that. We're very proud of the work we do. And we thank the city for the support. And we're always looking for how we can do more and make sure that services are available to all Medford residents. Thank you so much, Debbie. Any questions for our Mystic Valley YMCA Mystic Community Market applicant?
Seeing none, next we'll go to SCM Community Transportation. And we have John Keegan here in person. Welcome.
Hello, folks. I'm John Keegan. I'm the executive director at SCM, aka door-to-door. We've been providing senior transportation for just over 40 years, primarily to medical appointments and also food shopping. We're grateful to have our friends at McGann. As you know, the demographic is increasing. We could never serve everybody that needs support out there.
Also to Laurel and Alicia for the group that's recently come together to talk about the future of transportation. It's definitely a conversation that we have to have and to look for ways to collaborate, to do whatever we can to figure a way to deal with that. We provide approximately 3,000 rides per year. We do a couple other things, adult day health programs, put those on under CDBG.
We mostly serve seniors. We also serve some folks with disabilities, sometimes both, a mix of things. We're a free service, although I never know how long I can maintain that concept, but we've been able to do it for quite a long time, so we keep our fingers crossed. Let's see, what else did I want to tell you about?
In terms of shopping, we sort of divide the city up into quadrants, and we take people from different quadrants on different days to different shopping locations. We make sure we hit Market Basket and a couple other places that people want to go.
Our drivers help people with five bags, and we try to keep them to five bags. That's not always possible. So that's a service that people really appreciate. As you all know, the ability to get to medical appointments and to get food are just key to people having a decent
Seniors in particular having a good quality of life allows them to participate more in the community. So we sort of see ourselves as having that as an ancillary benefit of what we do. We don't think that we just drive the clunky vans around and get people places.
We've been doing it, I think I said, for 40 years. The M in SCM means MedFed, so we were originally formed by the three cities back in 1983. They came together to say we need to do more for senior transportation, and that's how SCM was formed. I'll stop there and see if you want to ask more questions. Great, thank you so much. Do we have any questions for SCM Transportation?
All right, okay, seeing none, we will go next to the West Bedford Community Center. And unfortunately, I'm not currently seeing anybody from them online. So if we can move on to the others and see if perhaps they join. Sure. So next would be ABCD and we have NEFI participating from them. Yeah, and if we could just before we go there, could you explain the difference between the CDBG and the CDBG-CB?
Absolutely. So in 2020, we received a separate grant from CDBG, which was the CV coronavirus funding. And so that is a separate grant, separate pot of money. We have a small portion of that remaining.
It's intended to prepare for and respond to the coronavirus. And so these programs are good programs to fit into that box, because while we're largely past the pandemic at this point, there are still ongoing impacts, particularly for housing. And so there is still a tieback on these housing programs to the impacts of the virus. Great. Thank you. So yeah, we'll go to ABCD first.
Good evening, everyone. My name is Nefi Dahoo. I am the director of ABCD's Housing Department. ABCD's Housing Department provides a variety of housing counseling services, mobile homeless outreach services, as well as rental and utility services to residents of Boston, Malden, Medford, and Everett. In years past, we have received Medford CDBG funding to support our mobile homeless outreach efforts.
So we operate a van that goes out into three communities, one of them being Medford, and provides services to folks at risk of homelessness or folks that are homeless. So providing assistance with applying for shelter, receiving hygiene kits, food, water, things like that. Recently, when I joined the department in May of last year, we received CDBG-CV funding to support
our housing counseling services, as well as our rental and utility assistance programming, and that's what we are requesting support for this year. In response to COVID, the pandemic, in 2020, ABCD established an ongoing rental and utility assistance program that has become a vital effort for the department, and so we appreciate your consideration to support that program.
Thank you. Any questions for ABCD? I have one, Mr. President. Councillor Scarpelli. Thank you. I appreciate your...
description. The question I have is something that comes up every year. With the Action Boston Community Development, the ABCD program, I think we had a problem, if you remember, that focused on making sure that this money was spent in Medford. And again, if you could just make sure that that happens, to approve this money. I know in the past, they weren't very clear that if it was going to Boston, if it was going to other communities, but
Boston and other communities have different avenues, and I think this is, you know, when we talk about Medford, we just want to be clear that this money is earmarked for Medford residents and Medford concerns. Thank you. Absolutely. If I may speak to that, CDBG funding may only be used to serve Medford residents. So this funding for ABCD through CDBG will only serve Medford residents. Thank you for the clarification. Appreciate it. Thank you, Laurel. Any further questions?
Thank you so much. And we will go next to Housing Families. And we have Jaina from Housing Families. Great, Jaina. Hi, everyone. Good evening. Thank you for having me. We're so appreciative of the support in the past and hoping to look to the future and continue to collaborate and work together moving forward. I wanted to be there with you in person tonight. Unfortunately, I have picked up some kind of respiratory virus, so I'm staying well away, keeping everyone safe.
So I wanted to talk a little bit about housing families in general. We offer a variety of services, all really geared to the prevention of homelessness. So we have family and individual shelter. We have winter warming centers. We have homelessness outreach. We have a community resource hub. We have clinical mental health and youth programming. And then we also have the homelessness prevention and legal services, which is the project that I am here to discuss.
So our program started in 1991. We are the only legal services entity located in the Tri-Cities. We offer brief advice, referrals, advocacy, and representation. I think of it as a continuum, so all along that line.
of from a very early on issue or question that someone might have, such as my landlord might sell next year all the way through to the constables coming tomorrow to move me out. And even sometimes beyond that, where we have families that are experiencing homelessness. So we work all along that and we put together legal services and homelessness prevention tools to be as effective as possible in preventing or ending homelessness.
I think that is about it for me. We were very successful last year in Medford. We exceeded our goal by the number of people that we wanted to serve by quite a bit. We had a good success in achieving some raft awards for Medford residents. And like ABCD, all of our services that are paid for through CDBG would be for Medford residents.
Thank you, Dana. Could you just share what your goal was and what you exceeded it by? That would be just helpful. Sure. So our goal is 155 individuals and we serve 200. Great. Thank you. Thank you. Any questions for housing families? Vice President Collins. Thank you, President Behrs. Not a question, just a comment. I know for myself and many other councilors and city staff members.
You know, we hear month in and month out how meaningful it is to have these service providers operating in our community. And it's kind of interesting to talk about this topic and many others in sort of a numerical way, but you know that blowing past that 155 community members goal into 200, you know, 200 people served and supported and coached and housed.
is so meaningful when you think about that on the basis of individual people, individual households. So no question, just thank you for the good work that you do on behalf of our community and working to fill and expand our supportive safety net here in Medford. Thank you very much. Any further questions for housing families?
Seeing none, we can jump back to West Memphis Community Center. I don't know that anyone's popped on. Unfortunately, I'm not seeing anybody from the community center on right now. Would you be able to share their
information, or is there another thing that you guys would like to do for this process? So, I mean, certainly, you know, I can read a bit from the summary. This is a program that we do currently fund. And so this would be continuing funding for their elder services program. And they say that they provide opportunities for Medford elders, need for diversity inclusion,
engagement, community conversation and celebration through consistent and complementary social, educational, arts and cultural events and activities, allowing participants to grow and learn from one another. These events bring an awareness of the value of the senior to younger generations as well as the whole of Medford.
The program is directed by Terry Carter and is supported by many collaborations in and around Medford, including City of Medford Public Health Nurse, Jillian Hertig, who has partnered with them to provide COVID vaccines, flu vaccine clinics, blood pressure clinics, and relevant presentations on health prevention topics.
Mystic Valley Elder Services provides weekly healthy nutritious meals and educational materials around making healthy meal choices. Melrose Wakefield Hospital provides additional blood pressure clinics, relevant health education materials and activities to the program monthly as well as 20 grocery bags per month.
Brookline Bank provides experts and assists in locating experts around financial health, like estate planning, home equity, money management, and cybersecurity. So that's essentially a summary of the various programs that they are providing to seniors through the community center. Great. Thank you, Laurel. All right.
Well, we've heard from everybody on the list. Is there anybody who has any further questions, or is there any member of the public who would like to comment at this time? I have Councilor Sang.
I just wanted to thank everyone for coming in today and presenting their projects. I know it's not easy to come before the city council. A lot of these projects we have heard before, but we also have new folks here, and I wanted to welcome everyone to the city council. Hopefully we're not as scary as we might seem. I think that's what they're saying.
Any further questions, discussion, comments by members of the public? Seeing none, we'll go to member of the public, Eileen Lerner. Name and address for the record, please. Eileen, I'm asking you to unmute.
There should be a button popping up on your screen that will ask you to unmute.
Yeah, she just raised her hand though, so. It looks like we're having some technical difficulties. There will be another chance to comment at the public hearing. I don't know, Laurel, if you want to go through what the rest of the process is here.
that we've just received these updated figures will be going back to review Director Hunt and Mayor and I and other staff will go back to review our allocation of funds, both for the public services and the other projects in the annual action plan will be back before you next Tuesday, May 14th for the formal hearing to approve the annual action plan, which then gets submitted to HUD for approval.
So we have a public hearing at our May 14th meeting. Correct. And then the final will go to, but then that will be our last role in the process. Exactly, exactly. And then the plan is also currently open for public comment. It was published as of May 1st. That public comment period will close on May 31st. So our plan is to submit the plan on, that is a Friday. So we'll submit the plan the following Monday, June 3rd. Great.
Is there anything else? I know that public comments tend to be a good thing. In this sense, for the CDBG program, I know we've definitely solicited them in the past. Could you just say a little bit more about how folks can make their comments?
Absolutely. So they can submit them to our office through the OCD at Medford-MA.gov email address. They're also welcome to call our office, 781-393-2480. Just double checking I have everything right. If they have any comments that they want to convey to me individually. Great. Well, thank you so much. Any further questions from members of the council?
Is there a motion to refer this out to the regular meeting? Council Vice President Collins. There certainly is. Just thank you so much for coming for us, providing this update, this information. It's great to hear that the change made to the overall allocation after this meeting will be in the positive direction. But always appreciate these overviews. It's a great chance to just revisit all of the good work that is being done in the community by CDBG grantees. And I would motion to report the paper out favorably.
Motion to report the paper out of committee and adjourn. Second. Seconded by Council Vice President Collins, seconded by Councilor Lemming. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. And we are joined by Councilor Callahan as well. Councilor Callahan? Yes. Vice President Collins? Yes. Councilor Lozano? Yes. Councilor Lemming? Yes.
Yes. Yes, 70 affirmative, none negative. The motion passes and the meeting is adjourned. Thank you.