The runners were through.
The first bomb explodes just a few yards from the finish line.
A big part of Crystal's life was Medford High School and the activities that she participated in with the band and softball at Medford High.
She loved the team and the girls have been loyal to her from day one.
They have spent a lot of time
raising money for scholarships so that children can continue after high school on to their college career.
They have put together this tournament in memory of Crystal.
When we first heard about the tragedy we were shocked and felt like it was our obligation as Crystal's fellow Mustangs and softball members to do something for her legacy.
So we decided to dedicate our softball season to carry on her spirit not only in our hearts but also in our community.
Mustangs on three.
One, two, three.
Mustangs!
The Crystal Campbell Scholarship is awarded every year to a deserving Medford High School senior who exemplifies the qualities of school spirit, sportsmanship, and community service.
Crystal Campbell's legacy will live on through the annual softball tournament, the Medford Strong t-shirts, and the scholarship fund throughout Medford.
do