Did everyone have a minute to look at the minutes? I have. I'm good. Everyone has had a chance, I can make a motion to approve the minutes. Is there a second? Aye. All right. It looks like Sue seconded. All in favor, raise your hand or
Say aye. Great. Any? It doesn't look like any abstentions. Any nays? Any nos? Great. The minutes have passed. If there's any lags, I'm trying to keep up with the notes so that I can have those out sooner this time rather than later. Yeah. Do you want me to take notes while you chair the meeting, Gabby?
It's totally up to you. I think if we, do we want to fill the secretary role? Is that something that we can do or we can put on the agenda for the next meeting maybe? I think we can do it for, well, I'm thinking the next meeting just when we have everybody present. Yeah. Yeah. Seems like a good idea.
In the meantime, if you're able to help with notes, that would be great. I'll still keep my rough notes off to the side here, but if there's anything that's more than a few sentences, if you'd be able to capture it, I would really appreciate it. Yeah, we can combine our notes and that should be a good finished product. Okay. And I'll add for discussion of secretary for our next agenda. Okay.
So do you know if Shanine will be, it doesn't sound like she'll be joining us this evening? You know, I'll text her. I texted her this morning and I didn't hear back. Okay. So why don't I text her for now? Do you, I don't know if you want to get started with the next agenda item while I do that. Yeah, and was Susie also someone that you haven't heard back from yet?
I think it's Sue Fowler-Finn. Is that you, Susie, with the GBIO low-income and disabled housing? I think you might be muted. You're on mute. It does say Susie K, so I'm not sure what that means. You're still on mute.
Can you hear me? Can you hear me? There you go. Yep. Oh, Tom. You can't hear me. We can hear you now. Oh, good. Okay. So I was wondering. Can't hear you now though.
Is Frances not coming today? I don't believe so. I think she's she's on vacation. So she's been kind of doing some background work for us to get the Zoom meeting set up. Okay, so what happened was I sent a message because somehow I got involved with planning about bowling coming out disabled because
I try to talk to people that are running for office in the city of Denver, council people and so on. Really, not just say, I'll vote for you because you have my support, but I'd like to know you a little bit. And anyway, it evolved into me presenting at a, I'll explain that in the initial GPIO on December 12th, but I said that,
Frances was, I don't feel like, I've only been on for a year, that we've talked about housing for disabled and talked about other things, but I really haven't heard housing come up often. And it's a huge part of a disabled person's life. And anyway, I presented and she asked me to read what I presented.
and also talk a little bit about it. So do you want me to do that? Yes, please. Okay, it's gonna take me 20 minutes. So I'll give you a little bit of background because when I started the commission, I was very cloaked about saying that I wanted to respect his privacy.
And I didn't want to feel like my role was based on that, because I also have many other passions. I taught special ed forever. Very impacted kids, blah, blah, blah. I still teach a lot of special ed through the direct department and through, I'm a ski instructor, and I teach a lot of special ed through that, blah, blah, blah. So it wasn't just about that, the reason why.
It's also, it was mainly because when I walked through Medford, I see horrible sidewalks, or I see somebody who I can tell has a mental illness, or whatever, that Medford didn't feel friendly to me if I had any kind of a non-enabling situation. So in any case,
I got involved with CBIO, which is Greater Boston Interfaith Organization. And what it is, I still don't know that much about it. I probably got into it because I talked to a candidate who went to CBIO.
Um, really local started, um, I want to say around and it involves 58 congregations and they could be, they could be community center. They could be churches. Um, the one that I was, um, you know, um, but anyway,
The 58, or how many at the time, groups of those people that decide they'll be on the board for it, think of a common interest they all have. So you're talking about a large stance of people, and what they think is important for Massachusetts, or for Medford, or for whatever. And they want, I guess,
two years ago, and I haven't looked into it that much. I haven't had time. This all happened like in December, which is a crazy month for everybody. And what they did a couple years ago was the whole organization focused on health care in Massachusetts. And then after a couple years working on that, they decided they looked at
affordable housing, safe and dignified affordable housing. So there's affordable housing and then there's safe and dignified and I like the way they said that.
and- Excuse me, Susie. Yeah. There's something, it's either your microphone or something. Okay. You can't hear me? I wasted all that time? No, we can hear you, but the volume is going up and down or something. Okay. I don't know. Tell me how it is now. I can hear you. I think maybe when you look down to your notes, maybe it fades a little bit. Look up. But when you speak straight ahead, it's pretty clear. Okay.
So tell me when, just give me a thumbs down somebody when you can't hear me. So in any case, when they decided on affordable housing, it was like 1400 people went to Mayor Wu and said, we need to talk about affordable housing. And then she did X, Y, and Z steps. And then it went to the governor.
and they're gonna have a big meeting, I wanna say in January 3rd, where another huge group is gonna go and rally about affordable housing. But it's not just that, it's also people that have been recently let go from being incarcerated. So a man spoke who said he was incarcerated not properly, he shouldn't have been convicted. And they're talking about,
getting IDs when they're still in prison and also the whole process because of course they're on the quarry and so on and so forth. And then another person spoke who got evicted because his landowner of his apartment or condo or whatever wanted to redo it and get a higher rent from it.
And then he couldn't find anything. I think he was in Somerville or Cambridge and now lives in a, not a great place in Medford. So anyway, they also talk a lot about mental health and those kinds of issues that people with
that need affordable housing have problems with. A tenant doesn't want somebody who looks and acts like they have mental health issues. In any case, it really was an astounding thing for me because the people that came, it was well over 100 people, and they were only representing probably another 100 people.
And our state senator, Pat Jalen was sitting on the stage and two other people that represent, I don't know where, close by on the stage. And anyway, so that's, does anybody have questions about any of that yet?
You can ask me any question, I might not know the answer because it's very new to me. Sue, I was going to say, I live and breathe that stuff. All of the disability work I do is through MassHealth, and so there is new federal policy that says we can spend money on things like housing.
for people on mass health, things like eviction support, tenancy rent deposits, all of that. And then what you're saying about, we're calling it justice involved. The Medicaid program has historically never been used to cover folks that have been incarcerated. Right.
Progressive states have asked the federal government to waive that, and now folks can receive up to two months of pre-release services, which are intended to help them get set up in the community, so that when they're released, they have a source of care, they have support, they have all of the resources to be successful.
It would be great to take all of that and figure out what we need to do for Medford to be really effective.
There are other organizations in, I assume there are other organizations in Medford that deal with housing, low-income housing. I don't know, I'm not sure what they are. It sounds like it might be good to partner with them. Yes, Medford Housing is ours, but I've never seen it. It's a senior center, it's on White Avenue, I want to say.
There's a lot of people, am I, yes, who a lot of different questions. It needs more of a focus. And it has to encompass, like the gentleman just before, it has to encompass mental health. It has to encompass, especially, it has to encompass mental illness. And even homeless, like in Denver, do we look around and see who's homeless? How do we tell?
How many shopping carts are in their hands? Are they in a port-a-potty for 30 minutes because they want to get out of the wind? There's a lot of things I think, I don't know whether it's up to the board or what, can look at in Medford, besides the sidewalks, which I still think need a lot of help, to help the rest of our community. We're the lucky ones.
I don't know. So I'm going to read it really quickly. I'll try not to look down and then I'm going to be done. Okay. So my son is right. Everybody can hear me. Yes. Can you hear me? Nope. Can you hear me? Yes, I can hear you right there. Okay. My son Wes is a bright, socially engaging,
44-year-old college graduate. He has cerebral palsy, which impacts his reflexes, mobility, and multitasking. He gets easily fatigued. Wes can't drive despite many years of specialized training. He commutes an hour and a half to and then from work daily, often getting home at 9 or 10 p.m.
He makes an average of $17 an hour as a hospital transporter. Wes does not want to be defined by his disability. When Wes moved with us from out of state, we converted our lower level into a private studio apartment. We began looking to section eight housing for disability and income status, a place of independence nearby, but not attached to his parents.
He eventually moved to a Medford Housing Authority apartment, where he lived for about five years until November of 2014. The rent was based on income and was submitted each year for examination and determination. He qualified under disability status. It was a small one bedroom with a tiny living room, a very tiny kitchen that had no countertops, which made cooking very difficult.
The building was bug-ridden, but when management eventually called exterminators, drawers were dumped randomly, making a mess out of the preparation that Wes and I had done. The carpeting was threadbare throughout. There were also many smokers in the building, which led Wes to develop a smoker's cloth that continued for a couple of years after living there. We worried about the clientele and their unregistered guests.
In general, the whole place was very depressing. His parents, siblings, relatives, and Wes all felt uncomfortable. Why were there not basic amenities and comfort provided in Section 8 housing? Wes now lives in a two-bedroom condo in a converted school building. Families, couples, and singles live in the 15 units, two of which are subsidized. That means Wes pays half the taxes
half the condo fee, utilities, and half the price of this wonderful residence. There's an occasional extra fee if a major upkeep project is needed. West has two good-sized bedrooms, a decent kitchen, living room and dining room areas, a laundry room, plenty of closets, and communal outdoor space. This unit was obtained through the state.
Applications are accepted based on low income need, low mortgage need. We fronted Wes the down payment and he pays the monthly mortgage, which will be paid off in 12 years and other fees, taxes and utilities. This transpired after I contacted Medgar City Hall and explained what we were looking for, including proximity to our home for our ongoing support and
A few months later, we were contacted. My husband submitted the paperwork immediately, and Wes qualified. I'm sorry, I'm getting teary. We are all incredibly lucky, all feel incredibly lucky. Wes feels a part of the community. He often shovels out condo owners' driveways, get baked goods from a woman there, and watches football with a gentleman who has become a dear friend.
He feels like he's living in a clean safe place and has enough space to cook meals, have friends over and walk to her home without difficulty. He feels respected and dignified in his residence, which spills out onto his outlook of life. His friends and family love his place. Life is good. So that's it. But what I wanna say is, I want that for more residents
everywhere, but in Medford. And I don't know whether that's really part of our role in the disability board or not. And I think people need to weigh in on that.
Thank you so much, Sue. Yeah, I agree that these perspectives and these stories are extremely important. We need to be able to, when we can, use our voices to advocate for change that we think, as a group, is important in our community, and I agree that this definitely is important.
As far as the meeting that you went to, did it sound like there was any, you know, future meetings coming up that we wouldn't be able to attend? Or do you have any suggestions on how we could potentially learn more to get involved? So I know there's a meeting January 3rd at the big valley somewhere.
I will look it up and send it out. Cause I don't have it all written down. Cause I didn't get it until December 12th and I've had relatives and a lot of stuff going on since then. I will send it out. That's all I can say to you, but I think it's one way to put our voice there.
Yeah, I'll get it to you in the next couple days. That sounds great. Thank you. Yeah, you could email that around. I won't be available January 3rd, but if anybody is able to attend and kind of get some, do they have a website or anything like that to you? Yes, and that I will get to you. I'll get it all to you.
Great, thank you. And then I'm thinking that maybe if we have the chance to kind of learn more and check out the website, maybe we could add some items to our agenda for the January 24th meeting, I believe is our next one. So we could connect all by email once you have that, if that works. Yep. Oh, thank you. Can I ask a question? Of course. Suzy, is
You shared that story, you heard that story at the GBIO event. Is that correct? It was at the First Paris Unitarian Church in Cambridge. Oh, okay. First Unitarian Church in Cambridge, December 12th. And that's where representatives all came from the 58 or whatever different
groups throughout greater Boston. And they were doing it because Pat Jalen said she'd be there and the other representatives would be there. And they wanted them to hear some personal stories. And I actually couldn't stay, I just got off a plane like an hour before.
and said, I'm going to present and I've got to get home after that. It went on until I don't know what time at night. So I'm not sure about the details, but it was definitely saying to the representative and the senator, will you, you know, they did that. Will you go back and vote for this? Will you go back and vote for this kind of thing? Anyway, that's all I know.
A follow-up question, I think, is that process that Wes went through to secure housing. Right. Is that a current process? Like, could other people go to City Hall? Or it sounded like this might have happened back in 2014 or 15. Yes. So it's just that we knew we didn't want him to stay in public housing.
And but he was lucky that we could support him in purchasing it. But I just found somebody in City Hall and said, this is what we're looking for. We want him to be independent. We want him to have a place, blah, blah, blah. And she listened. And the reason why I made that call was because like a week before, I looked at a beautiful, luminous
over near metal blend wall. It went in, in like 2013, all these condos or apartments or whatever, and they said affordable, affordable housing. And they were not affordable housing. And I regularly check when new places, when they call it affordable, I check how much they cost, the condo fees or their rent or whatever.
And it's not affordable for somebody like one person on December 12th who makes $7 an hour. It's not affordable. Or my son who makes $17 an hour. It's not affordable. And when I called City Hall, I said, these places are not affordable. This is what we're looking for. And then it came up about this, you know, certain subsidized,
listing, which I didn't know anything about until then. Most people don't probably. Yeah, I was just wondering if there was a way to share this information with more people. Well, I can talk to the person if she's still there or whoever's there now about how she would define that whole process. But I know it goes to the state
Massachusetts State that says when you convert, when you build whatever, you have to have a certain amount that are subsidized. You know that. Cambridge is very strong on that. I know that. Anyway. I'm not even aware of what department to talk to in City Hall. I don't know. I'll do it. I'm writing notes down on this. I'll do it the next day.
Yeah, that makes me wonder if there's something like a like something we could put on our website, like some way to connect folks with that type of resources, since we're a city commission. And if it's connected to City Hall, it certainly would be nice if we would be able to think of if someone's looking at our commission. Yeah, he is that they know that this is a resource at City Hall. The other last thing that I'll say is that
When you're in like a housing authority place, you're much more in contact with things like fuel assistance or if you're, just a lot of different things. But if you're in a separate place like subsidized housing, two out of 15 units, you're not in that link, I'm finding out. So there's a lot of different little things
I don't know how else to explain it. I'm glad you're eating, because I'm eating. Yes, please always feel free to eat. But Linda, I agree, that's a good idea. Maybe we could start to pull together some helpful links and things like that so that
I know sometimes the city's website you have to dig a little bit. But if people are looking for disability related services, it would be great to have like a helpful links. I think we have some links on our page, but they might be outdated. And there's definitely things that are missing. So we can put that on our radar to be updated. I think that Francis is the one that has to request it through somebody that
works in an IT-related department. I'm not totally sure, but I know it can be done. Yeah. So that really can be done. It's the communications focus, the communication director. Yeah, yeah. And when the website in the last, I forget, it's been a few months now, but the website got migrated over to a new platform. And so as part of updating the website, our little web page,
I did go through and get rid of all of the links that were at least broken. And then we did review them to see if things didn't make sense to have them on there. So hopefully, that's all to say that hopefully what's up there at least works. But yes, reviewing those every so often would be good. And obviously, adding to them whenever possible, I think, is also a good idea. And it doesn't take much to get them up there.
that making a request as often as we need wouldn't be a big deal. Great. I know we need to add Cam, our new commissioner, onto the website. When maybe when that's done, we can have the links updated. I'm going a little bit out of order now, but I did want to congratulate Cam on joining us as officially being a member of our commission. We're very glad that you're here and we're excited for the perspective that you'll share.
Susan, did you have anything else that you wanted to add at this point or were you planning to follow up by email? No, I'll follow up with their agenda and I'll follow up on City Hall stuff. Perfect. That sounds great. Did anybody have any last thoughts, comments, questions before we keep moving through the agenda? No? Okay. I'm going to go
back out of order. I think that, yeah, Shanine, would you like to, I don't know if you're here just to observe or if you'd like to talk about Carr Park? I really thought that the last time we met was in December, so it was completely not on my radar that you would even be meeting again this month, so I apologize. I have less prepared. Sue, I also owe you an email. I have been waiting for the city to get the link tree up, but I have that link now for all of you, which is the updated
Medford Park's kind of quick list of things happening right now. So there's a link to all the McGlynn documents, so you can see all of the inclusive elements at McGlynn, and you can see what's happening with Car Park. So that took us a little while to get up and going, but that was one of the things. And then also, Sue, thank you for sharing the stuff about the Medford Adaptive Programs. I've been pretty involved, at least in this initial setup, and then have not been so involved since Kate's taken over.
This body helped us create the Medford Recreation Program, helped create the questions that the rec department asks for inclusion services. So we modeled those off of the national best practices and a couple of the parks departments that are doing really great work in inclusion, and then this disability commission actually
helped us approve those questions in the process that the REC department uses to do intakes for new participants and make sure that there's the right supports in place. So thank you for that work previously. We talked about a lot of things. So I guess I want to know what your questions are, what you've been hearing about CAR or McGlynn or any of those things and see what I might be able to answer for you or what you've been thinking about since we last talked.
We do not have a one-pager. I think one of the members asked for a one-pager, and I wanted to get clarification on what that is. It was a request for a one-pager on how for you to use as you're talking to people, I believe, with disabilities out in the community. But what kind of information would you like to have on a one-pager to talk about parks projects or ask the kinds of questions?
You're saying one of us asked you that question? If that would not be helpful, that's also fine, but. Hello, I'm sorry, but as far as the one pager, I think. As we're just the key points or changes that are happening and maybe the expected delivery point,
on those changes that may be happening, and also, you know, contact information in case someone else has questions. And hopefully that can be, you know, email or telephone, email and telephone.
So, if someone has questions on park projects, as you're talking to people out in the community, so you would have, like, McGlynn is supposed to be done at this date, and Carr is happening at this date, and this is when we expect these to be done, and if you have questions, then you can ask these people. Is that correct? Correct. And if you have, if it's already written up, like, if it's on the website somewhere, you know, maybe even putting that link underneath that subtopic
you know, McGlynn, what you plan on doing, and then where more information can be found. That way if a person, if we're talking to people, I was on the bus and, you know, the only way I could have shared something is possibly taking a picture with my phone and then sending that document to them so that they would be able to read it on their own. So just, you know, okay.
I think that I get that. You know what? I will get your email address. And tell me your name again. Yvette Wilks, W-I-L-K-S. Okay. I will get your email address. Okay. And I'll send you a draft and make sure that it's on the right track of what you're looking for. Okay, then. And then, Tom, I should run that by you and Francis.
I guess it would be Gabby and Francis. Oh, Gabby and Francis. Okay. Yeah. I was going with that finger on the nose, not it. I'm stepping back from my chair role. Oh, okay. Because with Gabby as the new chair, she should be involved in those. She should take that position. Okay, then. Okay, Gabby and Francis.
One of the things I did not hear back from that I did the next day was the idea that your request that you be more, that this body be more involved in, get more communication from the planning department. And so the planning department has a newsletter, but I don't believe that there's one email address to send that would go to all of the current commissioners.
It seems like an easy thing to do to have, like, every time somebody rolls on and off, you'd have, like, a list serve of current commissioners. Does that exist right now? And could we put it? No, it doesn't. It doesn't. I don't remember if Linda or Tom or some commissioners that have been around for a while. I know we asked about that.
And the answer was just kind of, no, we don't do that. But I'm wondering if it's worth asking Frances again, even if it's like an email group that should be easy to set up. I think that would be extremely helpful because I think things do get lost in the shuffle. And it is difficult to get in touch with all of us. Right. And then how do we take it off of Frances's plate so that she's not responsible for forwarding everything that she needs to forward?
Let me follow up with her. I think it was I think that initial decision predated Francis. So let me check in with her. And I'll just add to that. I think one of the one of the.
Um, is is if email, you don't want to email you don't want to have a conversation with more than 2 people, because then it can create a public meeting. On email, and so we've had that happen a few times where we just share information, but then a conversation ensues and then we have to cut it short. So, what we've been trying to do.
of it alluded to earlier was to just email a few people and then Francis or the chair will then have to pass along that information. It's not, it's difficult, acknowledging that it's difficult to work together that way. You know what, let me talk to, I might be able to get this answer out of Roberta too and see how they navigated at the CPC.
She also works for Somerville, so it might be interesting how other communities are dealing with that too.
Yeah, what I was thinking was more of having like a group. I don't know how it works, what service the city uses as far as email, but I know like in Outlook you could create a group that just would all get filtered to the same place, but it wouldn't be having one conversation with one big group. So maybe there's workarounds or maybe there's not, but we can
we can definitely troubleshoot and see if there's any other solution. But in the meantime, please feel free to use my inbox for anything and I'm happy to move forward as needed. I put two links in there. The first one is the parks link and the second link is the newsletter sign up for the Planning, Development, and Sustainability Office. If each of you individually would like to click that link, quickly sign up, then you will, at least individually and beyond your time as a commissioner,
the parks update. So I'd highly encourage you to do that now, especially so that we don't have to, like that Gabby doesn't have to be responsible for making sure she gets all of that information to you in a timely manner. And Yvette, I will include that link, these two links in my email to you. Thank you very much.
Thank you very much. Oh, yes. Were there any questions about park accessibility? And I saw that I saw cams note at the beginning of when I signed in about.
Yeah, we were going to make you a spreadsheet. And the reason I didn't, no, no, no, the reason I didn't was I wasn't a commissioner yet. But now that I am, I think I can get started. There was just a little she asked me to pause. And then so I'll get that for next meeting. And we can look at that together. Okay, and tell me what was gonna because I also started a spreadsheet, a similar kind of parks thing. So maybe you and I can like what
What constitutes work that a commissioner can do that's not, like, if there are two of you in the room, that's fine, but if there are three of you, then it's public meeting? Yeah, that is not clear to me at all, but I figured if I, like, tried to spearhead it and make it a little bit smaller just to get it going, you know, I'm happy to partner with you.
Yeah, I think that that's my understanding.
she improved by the? Be public, yes, okay. So there is a like a public meeting law presentation that was given to us about a year ago. Cam, I will send it to you and maybe I'll just include everybody else in case anybody wants a refresher, more so I need the refresher. But yeah, so that's my understanding is that it would need to be public if it's more than two.
Well, good. I was going to say, I think it has a lot to do with, like, decisions that are being made. So, like, even if 2 people are.
working together, if there's decisions that people are making, even the two of them, then that really should be a public meeting. So it's kind of complicated. It's like information can flow up. If I'm reporting to Tom, if Tom was like, hey, you said you were going to do X, Y, and Z, where is it? Or like, hey,
Just checking in on something like I can feed information up to Tom or now Gabby. So I can feed information up, but there can't be like decisions and discussions and anything like that. Got it. So then. And this can be my last point cam. If you could send an email to me with the categories that you have been thinking about, I'll make sure that they're on there. And maybe you and I can find a time to kind of flesh that out. I am going to be.
So I'm going to be proposing this as a project. This is part of a larger project to audit and kind of get a database going of the playgrounds that we currently have. So I'm going to be proposing that in the coming weeks to the planning department. So it would be great to have those categories in advance to say, you know, the Disability Commission would like this. And some of the things, if you want to run off a quick list and then the rest of you can add what you would want to know.
the document that I have really quick and I'll take only two more minutes and then let you guys get on with your... Let's see. So some of the things were... I'm going to have to do it this way.
Medford Playground Master List. There it is. We're proximity to public transportation, kind of if they meet the ADA. We need to do an ADA audit, an accessibility audit on each. Okay, great. I see this. CAM has parking, size, small, medium, large playground, location to public transport, to public housing, and make it a goal to have an inclusive park in each Medford quadrant.
I'll say that again. Other members, please add other things. So we want to know if there's parking, how big the park is, kind of an approximate how big the playground is, location to public transportation and to public housing, or I guess proximity to, and then to have a goal be to have an inclusive park kind of in each section of the city.
I'm sorry, I have a question. All of these parks, will the restroom facilities all be ADA accessible? So, currently, there are no bathrooms at any parks in Pittsburgh. Tufts Playground, I suppose, is an exception because in the summer, the pool is open, and so the bathhouse is open. And Wrights Pond also has a bathroom.
and a playground, but is also only open seasonally. So our aquatics facilities have bathrooms, but none of the other playgrounds, parks at all, have bathrooms. Occasionally there are porta-potties, which are usually funded by the youth sports organizations. I would love to see all of you make an ordinance that those need to be accessible porta-potties when they put them in and they need to be on an accessible pad. That's work that you guys can do. Yeah, Sue.
I guess Gabby's probably supposed to call on you, sorry. No, it's good for you, Sue, go ahead. Thank you. Sue, can you move right toward the center of your screen? What we really need to do is have a ballot issue that says all parks need to have, not quarter parties actually, they actually need to have
bathroom facilities, and they need to be for wheelchairs also, they need to be part of the parks and that it should be part of X amount of extra taxes, I'm sorry, that we have them because going to the bathroom and also going to the bathroom as a disabled person could be a human right in Medford.
And nobody, it's all, as you said, it's up to whether there's a sport going on. I mean, really, that's what we're doing in Medford? It has to be a valid issue in Medford. That's a great idea. Well, I mean, Medford is also, as I mentioned, Medford is only one of
for communities in Massachusetts that's never actually put a Prop 2.5 override on the ballot. So there's not a lot of political will to do so.
But putting it on the ballot is one way to do that. And there's also, you know, I mean, letting the mayor know that that should be a priority in all parks designs and all of that. And I will certainly raise that to the planning department as well about what conversations have been happening around that. And if we did put in bathrooms, they would have to be accessible bathrooms. Most park bathrooms are usually like, there's like a men's and a women's, and they're both just like the single stall accessible bathrooms.
like when I'm in other states looking at those facilities. Sometimes there's a couple of different stalls, and then all the ADA rules do apply there. So if there's only one stall, it has to be an accessible stall. Okay, and then there's, in the chat, are we thinking parking would include accessible parking?
Cam says the original current concern is car park has accessible parking, but it might not be the smartest choice for an inclusive playground. Because go ahead cam. Well, I was just repeating what we said last time, which is, you know, we might just want to think about it holistically. And if there are other options in the heights where.
Um, there may be fewer tradeoffs. Maybe there's parking and it's easy to get to or or it might be that. This is 1 where it has accessible parking, but it's a lot further from the metro and it might not meet our other sort of, um, principles, but it might be the only way to sort of get an accessible park in that quadrant. So.
I think we're thinking all of the data will help us make a really informed decision and even one that might have a repercussion of like, oh, like add something to it, bathrooms in the future, stuff like that. I do want to share the last thing and then I will.
just send this out to the rest of you, or I'll touch base with Cam on that piece. That link tree that has the, that's in the Medford Parks page, there is a community survey. I'm going to put the link in the chat right now so that you don't have to do any extra clicking. So please, please fill this out.
to send this out to your networks. We want as much input as possible on this last survey. I believe this is the last survey for Car Park. Thank you. We can have that distributed. And Cheney, do you know if we could get this up on our website, like on our city webpage, would it be okay with you if we added that to our page, if we can do it timely?
Yeah, absolutely. And then just remember to take it down once it's down. Like, so somebody put a note up on January 8th to take it down. It's open until January 7th, so.
Perfect, thank you so much and please whatever needs to be distributed. If it's easier to. Email to me, that's that's totally fine. I think Francis is still technically out until the 4th. So, to save her any extra emails, feel free to to send to me and I'll can take it from there. Can you put your email into the chat and then I will email you as well to get that's email.
I think I might have it, but I just would rather get it now. Perfect. I think Tom emailed you and I. Oh. So he sent us an email. I do have one quick question or a statement about earlier you mentioned how we had asked to be part of like being aware of when they're making decisions or when that particular group you work with, you know, having them work with us. I think the bathroom issue is just
one of those examples, right? For us to be on the front end of that conversation, to us, you know, a bathroom would have definitely been part of it, right? And then some of the other things that Sherry was saying, you know, we would also think about, but that gives people a chance. So what this group has to say is definitely helpful to everybody to reduce the workload.
100%. I will, just to put on your radar, the city undergoes a process called the Open Space and Recreation Plan every seven years. The last one was done, it was the 2019 through 2026 plan, so I think we did it in 2017 to 18.
So that time is coming up. In the next year or so, the city's going to be starting to think about their next open space plan. It's like a 300-page book of all of, it's available online if you want to take a look at it, if you go to the planning department. And it allows, it's a comprehensive survey of all of our open space and what the priorities should be, et cetera. And it allows us to be eligible for certain funding pieces, but I think that it would be wise to have
to ask for a representative from this group to be on that planning board. So it's the Open Space and Recreation Committee or something like that. So that would be a wise decision to have someone saying, no, really, we need to put bathrooms on the radar as a priority for our community.
Great. Thank you for that information. I'm hoping that maybe you can send that link to where it's located, the current one. But also, I don't know if you have the link for the PATH report, you know, that was submitted. So if you, it's all on this main planning
So I can't get any more specific on the link than the one I'm about to put in the chat. But if you scroll down here, you will be able to see where it says, it says parks and open space under their projects and resources. And then it has the open space plan.
which includes the final open space and recreation plan. Do not open this on your phone unless you're on Wi-Fi because it is the biggest file you have ever seen. Not the link that I just sent, but don't click on the open space plan unless you're on Wi-Fi or have unlimited, very fast data. How do we get all of these links? I'm on my cell phone. I will email you every link that I sent tonight. Okay then. Thank you.
But yes, the final open space and recreation plan, which is 2019 through 2026, is available online for viewing as well as presentation and community feedback summary. And there's, I think there might be an executive summary. There's previous open space reports as well. And that helps you kind of see what the working priorities are.
and get a sense of where we are right now and what the document, the next document will probably look similar, but we'll have updated parks. Okay, I'm going to sign off because I have, well, not sign off, I'm happy to listen and it's always good information, but I don't want to take more agenda time. So thank you. Thank you so much, Janine. We really appreciate it. All of these links I've saved and we'll send around. So thank you so much.
Okay, let's see. I know that now we still have a quorum, yes, without Linda. One, two, yeah. A quick item on our agenda which we should have a good amount of time to get through was to kind of go through some of the commission goals for 2024. We talked about kind of an overview of the expectations for the kind of work that we should be engaging in.
in kind of how we hope to focus our advocacy efforts for this year. I think parks is definitely a big one. I think the open space planning is also very important.
And I think that there may be some ways that we could brainstorm to, whether it's drafting letters in support of things, whether it's to the mayor or to the city council, maybe those are some areas that we could focus our effort. I know some of our more recent meetings, we talked about wanting to be involved in more community events and organizing different community gatherings.
I feel like we have a good amount of momentum from this spring, and we'd like to keep that going. I don't know if anybody had specific items that they would like to either talk about as goals or talk about adding to our agenda for our next meeting. Whether it's small action items or big picture items, your feedback is welcome.
Yes, go ahead. So, I was, I'm wondering this, we could talk about is.
you know, building our membership and maybe setting goals for like, like numbers, like every month we want to at least bring on two new people. And maybe those things could happen through, you know, this community engagement. The thing that Tom had mentioned, you know, like last year, getting, having some kind of monthly or every other month.
that meeting so that like the information we received today, we know we have a place where we're going to be able to share it with people that may not go on the internet or even check out any of these meetings. So maybe just trying to set a goal to increase our meeting numbers or something by X number.
And, Yvette, are you referring, so our commission can only be, can only have, I think it's nine commissioners, and so you're referring to a separate type of meeting? Well, I guess what I'm thinking about is how do we really be intentional about building our base, informing our community about stuff, right? So I was out,
And I was on the bus and this man got on the bus, you know, he's in a wheelchair and he had so many things to complain about. And I was just thinking about what you had talked about, Tom. I wish I could have said, hey, you know, the city of Medford, we have a commission, we have group meetings every other month. So this may be someplace you may want to come and check and talk about what's going on with busing.
If we built that, then maybe even these meetings that we have, it may be nine commissioners, but maybe we at least bring more people to the table or to our meetings because I think someone had mentioned the event we did in October, they were looking for a different type of person to present. That's what I'm thinking about.
Yeah, I think and so you may be referring to the events that we did a couple of them last year where we had tables at events in Medford, like.
Harvest Your Energy Festival and then Arctic Oktoberfest last year. And so I think building our community. So whether it's events like that or whether it's just listening sessions, as you mentioned, like we could have a meeting at the library or something, but just to try to access, connect with people that, like you said, may not be able to do it via the Internet, but in person is a better option.
And then build that list that we currently, Linda is keeping track of a list per week. Well, it's electronic. We can reach people via email, but we have other contact information for them to keep them aware of what we're doing. Yes. Great. Okay.
Yeah, I think just to add on that, we did a few, maybe it was the beginning of the pandemic or maybe mid-pandemic, where we sent out kind of an online questionnaire where people could provide their contact information. So whether it was, it was majority email, but there were a few people who preferred whether it was telephone or text message or standard mail.
And we do still have that list and we did for a while invite and encourage people to attend meetings and we didn't get a huge response, but that is something that we could and probably should continue to implement. Even if it gets one person into a meeting that shares a perspective that maybe none of us were aware of, it's still huge.
I know the Facebook group for a while was pretty active. And I think, Tom, do you know if it's currently being moderated by anybody? Not so much. So I'm actually the new moderator. OK, great. So the prior chair, not the prior chair, a few chairs ago, I connected with Rachel and she passed over
admin, I guess, to me. So yes, you're right, there's not much activity on it.
I mean, it's still a good source to use. I'm wondering if the city, which I can look into, sends out any regular mail newsletters. I know Marsha before had talked about getting actual paper flyers into the senior center and into some of the affordable housing buildings in Medford. I'm not totally sure I could send her an email where she was looking because I think
Sending emails and digital outreach is great, but we do still need to be able to cater to people who don't use the Internet or don't have an email. So those are all things to think about. So thank you, Yvette. I can bring back that Google Drive. I don't remember if it was a Word doc.
Um, that had different outreach, um. Strategies, but I will look for that and I will reshare it with everyone. Um, even if we send out. Even if it's like a monthly.
like little update on what we've been doing, and then just a reminder of our upcoming meetings could be really helpful. And then that way you would have something, Yvette, that if people, you know, out and about you're in conversation with that you think that they would benefit from coming to our meetings, you would be able to point them in the right direction.
Yes, yes, and we would benefit as well. I do have a quick question for Tom, though. So I ended up on Facebook and then I saw this webpage and somebody was asking someone to take over the page because they were stepping aside. Is that the same page, Tom? Yes.
Oh, that's great. I didn't even, okay. I did something wrong where I didn't know that that was there. So that's a great place for us to share all of this stuff. Yes. Okay. Do we have an Instagram page as well? Uh, not that I'm aware. I don't believe so. Um,
but if that's something that you think would be helpful or you wanted to start, I think, I don't know if it could, would it maybe something to check with Francis about, I don't know if it could be like a commission official Instagram page, but if it's just like a disability related Instagram page for Medford and sharing resources, that's always an option too. Let me see what.
Yeah, I think the Facebook is great. Anything else, nobody needs to add anything to their plates. And so maybe, you know, maybe, like you mentioned the seniors, and you mentioned the MHA areas, maybe those could be some of the first places that we host a little
sit in, right, where people can come down and meet X number of people from the Commission on Disability and we can at least show them the website. And then that group of people can maybe think about other social media. But I think Facebook is great for right now. Yeah. Sorry, go ahead, Susie.
It's a little hard to hear you. Oh, there's a over. We have the farmer's market. And why can't we have a table there that one person sits at each week, one of us? Because it's easy. It's every whatever Wednesday or Thursday. Once a week from April to October.
I was just going to chime in and say, I like focusing on building the commission and getting it full strength and then all of us connecting with community members and hopefully bringing them to events and to track that, to grow our activity and who we touch. And Gabby, maybe try to measure that
in some way over the year to Yvette's point to make sure that we have goals that we are striving for and then we can track our performance against those. Yeah, I think that's a great idea. I'll kind of
Update what we have going what we had going with on Google Drive before and we can kind of see where we're at now and build on that. That list, I think it's a great idea. The farmers market is a great idea. Also, any community events that we can go and have a table that.
If people want to just drop their email or their phone number or whatever it is, so that when we do have updates like community events or if we're looking for surveys to be filled out, to be able to send those off to people would be great. I'm writing that down as a goal. Circle the square. Thank you, Shanine. That's also a really great one. I think also the library does some,
I don't know what.
Exactly, I get their newsletter occasionally. They have a lot of events going on. Some of them are like, you know, sensory related. I think maybe it's through the Medford Family Network. Maybe it's more child focused, but I think that there's still a good amount of, oh yeah, Puffs Community. Okay, I'm writing all of this down. These are all great ideas. But anything that has a community presence would be great for us to go out and chat with people.
Even if we just reserve a room at the library and have a listening session for an hour, just to say, hey, meet, you know, meet members of the commission. Come share your concerns. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Maybe we can add that the library space as an idea.
I've been in the library a few times in the evenings recently and there seems to always be something going on. So even to just be there and maybe get people floating by that pop into chat would be great. So okay, we can maybe talk about setting a date at the January meeting.
If that works something like that, okay, that's what I'm going to tentatively. Right so community outreach is a big 1. does anybody have anything else that. And obviously, we can add to this to our list of goals. It doesn't need to be right now. Um, but is there anything that anyone has been thinking about recently that they would really like to see.
I'm sorry, you just said I'm going to put a date down. What are you referring to as far as a date?
Sorry, I meant just to write for our January meeting to pick a date for, I'm thinking a community event at the library, just kind of like a meet and greet where people can come in and maybe we could have a piece of paper with our website and some contact information or useful links.
Okay, but is that like one of the locations or are we thinking that maybe we could do our first thing at the senior citizen home in, I don't know what it's called, but right there in Bedford Square, maybe that's like our first place because then they don't have to get out and travel. Totally.
would you like to spearhead reaching out to the senior center in Medford to see if they would be willing? Great. In any time that works, if you could get a date or just a rough timeframe of when that may be possible, if you want to send out an email to all of us and whoever is available can chime in, that would be great.
Okay then. Or I'll at least bring it, make sure it's on the agenda for the next meeting. Perfect. So I don't get any issues, right? Yeah. Yeah. No, no, no rush at all. And I'm sure that with the new year and everything, they'll be busy and everybody here will also probably be busy. So definitely no rush. But that is something to get started with early on in the year. Yes. Great.
Okay, I'm just gonna see if there's anything else specific. Yeah, Francis added, how do you plan to acquire the training and information that could assist you in your role? I know I for one definitely need a refresher on the open meeting laws. So I will send around the PowerPoint that was sent to us. I think it was probably more than a year ago at this point, but I did find it very helpful.
just to get a little bit of a refresher. But obviously, if anybody has any specific questions, feel free to reach out to me or to Frances, and we can reach out to me first. If I can't answer it, then maybe I'll pass off to Frances. But anything related to open meeting laws and things like that, we can, the information is there. It might not be readily available, but we can find it. Yeah, aside from that, was there anything that anybody wanted to add at this point?
A couple of things I wanted to share. So I think one of the things that we had talked about last time, I don't know if you're ready for it, but is the Mass. Office on Disability, they offer to join a commission meeting like ours and just go over, hey, this is what commissions do, or maybe they offer trainings. So if we identify something specific, they're probably worth reaching out to to see if they could help address that.
Just kind of in general, like, okay, you know, we know this 1st step I agree is building our community. What what happens next? Right? What happens after that?
The other thing I wanted to add was I think it would be helpful to kind of have a point person for each of these different topics, like a point person for inclusive playgrounds, and maybe we have a couple point people for community stuff. One thing that I have not gotten back to is the West Medford Commuter Rail Station and making that accessible. And I'm happy to be the point person on that.
So, yeah, I guess that would be my. My thought on, you know, we can look at the list and I know that already volunteered to set up the senior center meeting, which is great. So, if we have people assigned, I think that would be helpful. Yeah, I think that's a great idea. It especially helps with. When we're kind of going through updates at meetings to have 1 person be able to share a few quick updates on 1 topic.
Yvette, if you're going to be working on reaching out to the senior center, and Cam, you're kind of our park spreadsheet person at this point, if you don't mind that being your kind of role at this point, I can commit to getting the community outreach, like the contact form and everything set up. Susie, yeah, go ahead.
Sorry, could you say that one more time? And I'll do, I work on a portable housing table. Perfect. And of course, these are not, you know, hard deadline tasks that you're expected to come to every meeting with an update, but just kind of things to keep. Oh, and healthcare, perfect. Thank you, Kim.
just to keep monitoring generally and keep your eye on things if you see any updates online, whatever it may be to send it around so that we can all be involved. Yeah, I think that's a great idea, Tom. Were there other commissioners currently on the commission who received the, there was training on playgrounds and I can't remember specifically what it was and who was trained.
I believe that Susan was. I know that she did the ADA training and I believe she did a park training. Is that through the Mass Office on Disability?
That was something that could be added to our, our planning for the new year. I personally would love to attend a training or 2. And if we have more than 1 person, or a few people interested, that would be great. Go ahead. I believe they will come to your meeting.
Yes. Okay. Maybe. I know that there was something that was scheduled with, I think, a few commissioners a few years ago went to a school, and they, like, did an in-person, like, a site type of training. Interesting. Or at least that was my understanding of it at the time. I know that Susan attended. Okay. They also have their community access monitor, their CAM training. Okay. Which is an online, there's a kind of, there's a level one and level two.
There's basic community access monitor training, which is kind of an ADA, an overview of the ADA so that you know what you're looking for in your communities. And those are free. And the other thing, I was just, since you've been talking so much about community outreach, I did just do an introduction between you, Gabby, and Anna Callahan, who's the new city councilor whose expertise is in reaching marginalized communities. So I suggested in the email that maybe she come to the January or February meeting
and talk to you all about how to reach out to people, like what are the best practices as well as just like you telling her what you do and kind of introducing yourself. But I made that introduction already. Thank you. Yes, that would be great and a very welcome introduction. So thank you. I'll make a note to to reach out to her as well. Yeah. Great. Yeah, I can look into some of the CAM trainings that I can send around a link to everyone.
I want to say that the trainings that were a few years ago now were free through whoever did it. I will do some looking around and I can also follow up with Frances. But if anybody is interested, please, or I'll share the information and then if you're interested, you can let me know. That would be a good thing to do. Because you never know what insights we might get as far as the parks.
Great, okay. I know that, does anybody have anything else that they'd like to add on those points for now? No, okay. It looks like there are a few updates from Francis on upcoming community events. On the 15th, the West Medford Community Center is gonna be hosting a Martin Luther King Day. Sorry, my eyes.
at St. Raphael's Parish in Medford. And on February 10th, the Human Rights Commission is going to be hosting the Year of the Dragon Lunar New Year celebration, and that's at 12.30 to 2.30 p.m. at the Medford Public Library.
And on February 17, the Human Rights Commission is going to be hosting an annual reading of Belinda Sutton's petition from 1pm to 3pm at the Royal House and Slave Quarters. And those I can also send, well, they're on the meeting minutes, but I can also send that around in my email update that will contain a million links.
Does anybody have any questions or anything that they would like to add? We can wrap up a few minutes early here if there's nothing else. Go ahead. Okay.
Do we need to put on our calendar to talk about. The maybe annual events so that we could possibly, like, reserve the library, like, what happened October? It was like, coming out the week we did our. Our resource fair.
So maybe there are dates that we want to recognize, like there was a woman that passed away last year who was very instrumental to the fight for individuals with disabilities, right? So maybe that becomes, who was that again? Judy Heumann.
Yes. Maybe we want to do something where we want to have a day at the library. I don't know if that's something we need to put on the calendar for January that we talk about maybe some upcoming events where we want to reserve space now.
Yeah, that's a great idea. I can send a Google Drive link that people can add to with the screening of Crip Camp. It's definitely something that we should get on. And maybe we can get the library now because they're always looking for things. And yeah, that'd be a great thing.
Yeah, that would be great. I know that the library also has a decent reach in the city as far as their mailings and their flyers and things like that. So that would be a really great idea. What we can do is we can start to brainstorm what we want as kind of tentative plans for the next meeting. And then at our January meeting, we can kind of go through and pick, okay, we'll prioritize these three
events as our first ones of the year and take it from there to get things on the calendar in advance? Does that? Well, I just meant from January to December. What are the key things that happened throughout the year? Maybe there's something that when Ms. Human passed away, maybe that's something that it's a special day. Well, we may want to reserve the library to do a screening or we may want to do something, but we want to reserve it now.
That's all I'm saying is to look at the full year and see if there's any activities that we want to try to get a space now. Sure. Yeah, that sounds great. We can have a working Google Doc that people can add to and then we can start to reach out.
Yeah, and I guess I could maybe look at our past meetings to look at the events that we did do this past year. Is that it? Look at, review all of our meeting notes and then find out. Okay then. Yeah, that works. If you want to take that on, that sounds good. I know the city calendar also might be a good way to filter through if you go back to previous months to be able to see what events were.
or on the calendar for the city. No, I'm talking about events from our commission. No, go ahead. Sorry. No, I was just talking about events that we have done. I think the previous meeting minutes are agendas, but also I think the city calendar, you should be able to filter. I could be wrong, but I think you should be able to.
commission of persons with disability filter to our events. Okay. I'm looking at it right now. Sorry, one sec. Maybe it's just
that headings, yeah, maybe the meeting minutes is the, I was hoping there was a way for you to be able to do that without having to scroll, but it looks like maybe the city website is a little bit clunky. But if you want any help with that, feel free to shoot an email. Yeah, I guess I could reach out to Cam since he's doing spreadsheets, the Excel, and that could just be another worksheet page or work page, right?
Yeah, yeah, that works if you want to have a couple of different working documents. Okay. Okay. All right. Anything else from anybody before we wrap up? No. Okay. Would somebody like to make a motion to adjourn? I second that motion.
Great, thank you so much and thank you so much for being here and cam. Thank you so much for joining us. I'm very happy to have you here. And please, if any questions, concerns, comments, ideas come up, feel free to shoot me an email so that we can add them to the agenda. I believe our next meeting is January 24th.
So, I hope to to see you all there. You're welcome to join if you'd like, don't feel like you have to remember. I know I'll talk to the planning commission about to see the planning department to see if it would be wise to have a representative. Sounds good. Thank you so much for you.
Happy New Year. Happy New Year. Thank you, Gabriella. Good job. Yes, thank you.