Okay, 6.05, let's get started. So we have an application from 15 Hillside. Why don't you tell us what you wanna do? Oh, by the way, we have a quorum. Did everyone get to see the photographs that I sent?
I did not circulate it, but why don't you, why don't you just tell us what you want to do, Joe? Okay, there are three windows on the north side of the house, which is facing my neighbor's house. There's like a six feet away from the property line. So it's not quite visible, not much visible from the street, but it is somewhere.
HAB-Michael Leccesereeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeee
I want to make it a straight run. So when it. It's going to take up that North wall. And the intersect these windows. I want to. Replace one window.
It's towards the front corner of the house. That'll end up being in a shower. So I want to take the same kind of window, same size and everything, and move it a bit further to the east so that there'll still be a window on that face of the house. So there'll be a window above the staircase? Is that right? No, no. That whole, you know, I might be able to,
Okay. I was going to try to share the screen. I might be able to have a picture. Go ahead and share the screen. Dennis, are you still on? Let me. He's all set. Okay. Yeah. Why don't you go ahead and share your screen, Joe? I thought I had it set up for it, but I don't. Do you know how to share a screen?
It's a little icon on the bottom. Yeah, I have all the windows that are open. Not the right one. Let me see. I have to find it somewhere else. Okay, hold on a second.
Of course, when I had that open. I'm afraid if I get out of the. Maybe I should just get out of this and then out of the zoom and then come back in. Let me let me.
Let me see if I can, let me see if I can find it here. Yeah, it was attached to an email, I said. Yeah. Sorry, everybody. Okay, well, sign in. Sorry about this. Yeah, that was my fault too.
Okay, just a second here.
What email did you use, Joe? Hillside John at Outlook. Yeah. It's not coming up.
Okay, can you look around for it and we will discuss 54 South Street for a little while? Is that okay? Thank you so much, I'll take care of that. Okay, sure. Okay, so Attorney Desmond, are you there? Yes, I am. I'm sorry, I was having trouble finding my video button.
I'm here and with me is Chris Mulhern, the project architect, the developer, Ron Buck, and also Ben Minnix, the project engineer. We asked for this meeting to discuss the plans for the property in the hopes that we can all arrive at an outcome that will work for everyone.
Yeah. So I can have Chris run through the plans, if you like, to introduce the changes that have been made to the project. OK, just just for your information, we we our role in in in in this house is not not currently in a local historic district. Right.
We are actually seeking, as I told Mr. Mulhern earlier, we're actually seeking to put this into the proposed House South Street historic district. And we would like your support for putting this house into that district. But otherwise, our role is purely advisory. And we understand that.
In terms of the project and the project that was put forth originally, there was a serious attempt by Mr. Buck and the development team to do something that would preserve the project. And we spent a lot of time trying to bring it to the Zoning Board of Appeals to make sure that we could deal with the fire department and concerns they had about access to the back of the property without having to
demolish any portion of the existing structure. So it's always been our intent to try and work with the historic committees with the understanding that this has historic significance to the city. And I think I made the point at the Zoning Board of Appeals, and I'm only to say that this is a 16,000 square foot lot, and if you looked at it,
strictly from a zoning perspective, this property would support in the vicinity of 10 to 12 units. And that's never what the developer came in with on this project. So we're here in an attempt to work and to do something that will make everybody happy if we can. Sure.
OK, so I guess the next step is just to tell us what you have in mind. OK, great. Hi, everybody. For the record, Christopher Mulhern for Harrison Mulhern Architects. I'm going to share my screen if I can. Let's see. My screen is telling me that sharing is disabled. Oh, dear. Dennis, are you still there?
Oh brother. Okay, hold on a second. If you hit the green share screen button at the bottom of your control. The green share screen. Only one share, let's see. Advanced sharing options, all participants. I gotta set it to all participants can share.
Okay, can you try it again. Well now I got it. There we go. Okay. Okay, so can you see my screen now. Yes. Yeah, so.
This is the proposed plan for 54 Church Street. The orientation is Church Street. Sorry, South Street is what I'm talking about is on the right side of this image, the existing house is at the top.
And the proposed addition is down below. The footprint of the proposed addition is very similar to what we had before. But as you can see, it's set well back from the plane established by the existing house. So we were able to move the entire mass of this proposed addition back and to reconfigure it so that
It has a townhouse at the front, which is marked here as unit four. And then it has two stacked flats at the back, which are units three and units five. The historic house is proposed for two units. Unit one at the front, which would consist of the original, what I view as the original piece of the house.
and then unit two in this back area. So the way these units would work, well, so this is the ground floor plan. The parking is in the back. We'll come back to that in a second. And the way this works is that we're taking better advantage of
the basement footprint in order to get good apartments here. This is the basement level plan. You can see that unit 5 has two bedrooms and two bathrooms on this level with a large area way that's outdoor space below grade at the basement floor level. Unit 4, which is a townhouse, has a storage area and a family room at the lower level.
This is the main level plan. Unit 4 at the front is the townhouse that's similar to what we showed you before. This is the living level, if you will, of Unit 5. Unit 5 is a three-bedroom unit, so two down below, and then this bedroom with a bath on the main floor with kitchen, dining, and living as well. This unit is accessed off of
the vestibule space here and has a sliding door that leads out to the backyard. Looking at the existing house, it was very easy, relatively easy to get this to work as two units by closing an existing opening that lives here to make an L-shaped kitchen with a seating area and the existing fireplace, and then tucking a powder room under the stair,
and making a back door out of this study. This has a front parlor slash living room, an eat-in kitchen, and then a stair leading up to the bedrooms. The back unit would have its front door here off the drive with a large living area, fireplace, living area, study, back mudroom, powder room, and then kitchen with an eating bar.
Moving upstairs, unit one, which is in the front portion of the house, has two bedrooms and a hall bath, with some new closeting along the dividing wall here. Unit two has a big bedroom and a laundry and a walk-in closet. The link building connects to
the front of the living portion of unit three, which is stacked on top. Let me just interrupt you here, Mr. Mulhern. We're actually not interested in what happens to the interiors of these buildings. We're only interested in the exteriors. Okay. Well, then we'll move on. Just to finish this out, there is a living space at the
third level as well. So from the street, this is the proposed elevation with the existing home on the right side here, the existing fortune screen enclosure, and then this gable ended new bit with a link in between.
John Gerstle PB – PB&I Coordinators): and garden space on the left hand side, this is the long side on the left side of the property, you can see that the existing home existing House is. John Gerstle PB – PB&I Coordinators): Forward of the new proposed work, this is the rear with the existing backdoor and the existing House here the new link element.
and then the new residential piece here. Here are three views of the proposed development with the existing house in the foreground and the new portion set well back. Here, you can see that in this view, it's also set back and then at the back, they're more or less in the same plane.
That's the layout. The site plan looks like this with the drive coming in, two parking spaces in the existing garage, which is unchanged, an area for the bins next to the garage, four additional parking spaces towards the building. Here you can see the area way, the new construction, and the setback from the front of the existing house. That is basically the story.
So what will be the materials used in the siding and the windows? So what we're proposing is a left siding, probably a composite. That is to say it's either Boral, which is a fly ash product, or a hardy type left siding, which is a cementitious based product. The trim would probably
The borel product, that's the one that looks the most like wood. And then, can you still hear me? You're cutting out. Hello? You're cutting out. Can everybody see and hear Mr. Mulhern?
When I go sideways for a second there, I think I'm back now. Were there other questions, Mr. Bader? Let me turn it over to other members. Charlotte, do you have any questions?
Are you muted, Charlotte? Charlotte, do you have any questions? OK, well, how about Fred? Fred, do you have questions?
Okay. Thanks, Chris. Yeah. I'll turn my video on. Hopefully you can see me there. So my, my question is, is, is a variant still required for this? Are you seeking to change?
I'm going to defer to Catherine. We haven't submitted the new plans to the building department but but this would bring us back. I don't, I don't know if you're familiar with what occurred at the last meeting but there was an issue with regard to the townhouses and and the definition of single attached versus multi.
We've stacked the units in order to bring it within the frontage requirements of the zoning. So we believe that this will require minimal relief and mainly related to the existing structure. I believe, and I don't have it in front of me, but I believe the setback on the,
if you're looking at it, the right hand side is only 14 feet. So for a portion of about seven feet due to the bump out, it does not comply with the 15 foot requirement. Other than that, I believe there may be one more variance that we may need as to... Actually, I think that's the only variance that we'll need at this point. There was some confusion
about the aisle width, and I think we've resolved that issue. If it is an issue, it would relate to the aisle width of the parking area. And it's literally three or four feet, I think. Okay, so it's not a question of number of units or anything on that. No, as I explained to
Chair Bader, when we first came into this, this is a 16,000 square foot lot. And we haven't configured a building based on the square footage, but an apartment one is a multifamily district. I think that this lot would support at least 10 units to 11 units. And that was never my client's intent.
Um, in this regard, he, you know, he came in with a project that would preserve the existing structure. Um, and, and also, you know, one, one item, which I believe is important, uh, is that, you know, when we were speaking with the fire department about this project, um, it also will sprinkle that existing structure, um, so that you would have an added protection to that, that structure, which doesn't exist at this point. Um,
it would be updated with sprinklers so that, you know, you have a better chance of preserving the building in the event of some issue were to occur. Yeah, okay, that's helpful. Well, my concern is the addition's bigger than the house, basically, is my, I think it's overwhelming, the little Greek revival. And I appreciate you're gonna restore that and bring it back and upgrade it and all that stuff.
But even on these images that are here, particularly the upper right-hand corner, it seems like it's overwhelming this, you know, it's a nice little house. It's a beautiful Greek revival. And I'm not sure that using clapboards and the same materials myself, whether that's the correct approach or not, whether a more modern,
type appearance that would really allow the Greek revival to come through as a historic property and the other can be more contemporary and all that. So I'm thinking, as always, if you could reduce the roof lines of the proposed addition or other units, whatever you want to call it,
I think it's, it's larger. By far. There's a little house on the right. That drawing you just have there.
comment and request that if we could just downsize things a little bit or reduce the scale somewhat. Thank you. And maybe possibly change materials as well. Let me, before you say, respond Mr. Mulhern, why don't we go to other members of the commission? Charlotte, do you have any comments, questions?
You're still muted, Charlie, you gotta unmute. Okay. Melanie, comments, questions? I don't have any questions. I just kind of agree with Fred. I think the new addition kind of overpowers the historical part of the original household. That was just my original thought. Okay. Joe, comments, questions? Is that me?
No, Joe, Joe. The commission member. Yeah. And Joe you're muted as well. Okay. Right.
Uh, you know, I'm a member. Uh, so my own opinion is that, um, I, I, I'm also inclined to agree with Fred. Um, and, uh, um, what, uh, what would be, um, Uh, and I'm just wondering, and this is really a commitment, you know, that I have to get from, uh, the owner is, uh,
whether you would commit to working with us and coming up with a design that would... So supposing that the building were in a historic district today, you would be bound to work with us in coming up with
uh, in coming up with a design, uh, and a list of materials that was, uh, that was acceptable to the commission. Um, if you're willing to make a commitment to us to working with us, you know, we're, um, we're pretty easy going guys. Uh, uh, we all, we've all expressed concerns about the size of the building, but, um, uh, what we would be, what we could be looking for from you is a commitment
to work with us until the historic district is approved, and we would also be looking for your support in inclusion of this house into the historic district. So that's really a question for the owner or the attorney. I understand exactly what you're saying. The issue is that my
The client has requirements with respect to the size of the units that he's trying to build. And so I can't commit to reducing the footprint or the volume of the building such that it would be smaller than the existing Greek Revival house. That's programmatically not going to work. So the question is whether this commission is willing to work with us to
try and find materials and details and design solutions that work with the program that's been established by my client. Well, I mean, we're certainly willing to work with you. I guess what I'm saying is that if the starting point is that the building has to be smaller than the Great Revival, then we don't have a starting point.
And that may be the case. I mean, we are non-binding here. I'm not trying to lock anyone into it. If you want our comments, I think that's the main thing, the materials. We had a house built in another part of the district at the hillside, which is a completely brand new construction. And the owner opted for a very contemporary modern look. And we approved that because it was not trying to look at,
you know, manufacturing a historic replicas and things. So I would just consider that. And I mean, I've run into this before where, you know, the, in order to sell it, it has to be a certain size. And I, I don't necessarily agree with that, but we could look at the massing of it and maybe reduce things towards the front into the back, but you know, it's overwhelming that house. So I don't know if there's any way around that for our point of view.
I would rather see a freestanding standalone building next to it, I guess, than an addition that's larger than the house. But that's just me. So I don't know how to resolve that and how we go ahead forward with that. I understand. I think with respect to the materials, our take was that
using a different palette of materials was going to call more attention to the new work.
And that that would be to the detriment of the existing house. Reasonable people can disagree on this topic and have for years. So I agree completely. It's a, it's a, and I'm only one person in this commission and I know other members of this commission feel very strongly in other directions. So I agree. It's there's no easy or one solution that fits all for them. So.
But anyway, so design gets all the things that you need in there, but I, you know, I'm just afraid that it's not heating the historic property next door or on the lot, that's all. Okay, so Mr. Mellon, we are, again, our role is purely advisory here. So I think you've heard from everybody.
And, uh, you can see if Joe weigh in or put an opinion on this joke. Go ahead, Joe. Can you hear me? Yes. Oh, excellent. We can't see you though.
I guess I can only do one thing at a time with that. That's fine. I mean, I actually see it from both ways. I mean, I agree it is overpowering the original house, but I also can understand that going through all the effort, you need to have it large enough to have what people are looking for to purchase it in the end.
I guess I don't have a strong opinion either way, I guess. I guess my only other comment is like, how is that gonna look with the house next to it? Because there's another kind of, I think sideways frequent, some type of historic home, the purple one that sits right next to that lot as well, right? So. Yeah, yeah. Yeah, this is really the centerpiece of the whole proposed South Street historic district.
And as Melanie points out, there's another beautiful house right next door. So Attorney Desmond, I guess you've heard from us. Well, if I could just ask, in terms of a more contemporary
structure which has kind of been tossed about but hasn't really been explained or perhaps as examples and the same with regard to how a second structure would fit on this. I think I'd like to at least hear what those are and if there are examples of contemporary structures that the committee thinks would work in terms of an addition. Fred, can you send,
where we have other stuff to discuss this evening. Fred, can you send Mr. Mulhern some examples of what you might have in mind? Yeah, I have pictures of the house. It's on Governor's app. I forget the numbers, 10 or 15 on the end. I mean, that one was in the commission. And again, the architect selected the palette of materials and wanted a contemporary thing. It was driven by
By their designer and we're okay with that for them. It's a lot of glass and, you know, roof and all that sort of thing. And I could send some other examples, but I think Melanie's point is if we were to have some design review, we'd want to see it in context along South street, because it is a house of these. You know, a lot of shipbuilding history in Medford and a lot of.
Um, and then we, uh, have a lot of, um, pre 1855 buildings, which admittedly were a lot smaller than they are now. Um, so if we were to be involved in the design, I'd like to see, you know, The house with some context of the houses next door. Crosses feet and that sort of thing, which I think. Um, you know, the historical commission or whomever might have some. Design review on this might, might be interested in looking at that.
Yes. We'd accept contemporary or not. I mean, the. The guy who was on governor's have the, the applicant. Originally got some pushback from members of the commission that it shouldn't be a modern thing. I sort of was able to. Clear people a little bit direct some path that it might be an option worth considering. So.
So. It's a little bit more. Imposing than, than some of the images, even if it's set back a little bit. So. I have your. Kathleen, I have your, I have your email. I think it's some correspondence. So I can send you some images and you could distribute them to. Wherever you want. And again, it's not binding. It's just some ideas. And I'm sure if you Google modern architecture, you could.
I mean, is there a place to get to yes if if if something if if something that sent along. You know, makes makes sense is is that something the Commission, because I think part of the the issue we had when we originally received correspondence from chair beta and yourself was there seemed to be a dichotomy of opinion as to whether it was traditional.
or contemporary and kind of left us in a situation where, you know, we have no direction and, you know, it isn't a market where you can sit on a property in terms of, you know, in terms of development, you know, market conditions have changed such that the carrying cost is much greater than they were originally when this project started. So there's some immediacy to this as well. And, you know, so those are issues. So here's where we are.
You've heard our, I think we've fulfilled our advisory role here. We obviously do, are not particularly keen on your current design, and we will welcome you coming back with a design that address the concerns that Fred expressed and other members expressed. And just a reminder that if you want to demolish
Any portion of the existing house, you need the permission of the historical commission, not us, because they have demolition delays, and that includes partial demolition. So you should consult the historical commission on that. Basically, you can't demolish anything, any portion of the existing house.
the existing building without the approval of the historical commission. Yeah, our plans don't contemplate any exterior demolition and more removal of any chimneys. Um, anyway, um, we would, uh, we, you are known we, there is a proposed South street historic district. Uh, it will probably be passed by city council in the next few months. We would very much like your support. Um, and, um,
We, of course, would work with you if it were part of a historic district. And, you know, if you were willing to support the inclusion of this house in the proposed historic district, I can't imagine that would do any harm to your application to the zoning board.
We are not in a position to actually make a recommendation to the zoning board. But if you did, if you did write a letter, if the owner was willing to write letters expressing support for inclusion of this house in a local historic district, I think that might be using good. Thank you for your input.
Okay, so I think we need to move on here, Attorney Desmond. All right, thank you so much for talking to us. You know, let's keep this dialogue open. Okay, Joe, let's go back to Joe Murphy. Okay, it's John Murphy. Oh, John, I'm sorry.
Okay. One, two. Share the screen. Ah, perfect. This is my house. So this is standing on. The railing of the lower right is. For the roof, my garage.
This is kind of the side of the house. Well, anyway, I X'd out on the north side where the fence is on the left-hand side of the picture. You see, there are three windows I put X on. They're the ones I'd like to remove. And then I drew in between the two X's on the first floor, I drew in another window. So in effect, I want to take the window that's right on the corner of the house and move it about six feet to the left.
So that'll be at kind of at the foot of the stairs. The stairs are going to start at the back where they currently do actually. The second floor back rear of the house, that's the far left. And then he'd come down along the back wall, along this wall and end where that X is by the fence post. So then the window that's,
at the corner of the house on the first floor, there's gonna be a bathroom there and that window will be inside a shower. So I'm gonna take that window and just move it, make it outside of the bathroom and I'll make it into a window in a hallway at the foot of the stairs. So that's all part of, I'm gonna be doing the kitchen renovation and the bedrooms upstairs.
From basically the flat part of the house, the flat roof, it's all going to be gutted on the inside. New insulation, new wiring, and new plumbing for kitchen, bathroom, and laundry. And the only thing that impacts on the outside that you can see from the street are these three windows. Personally, I don't think they're part of any
ensemble of windows that you can see around the bay window and everything. It's a whole array of windows. These are, I don't know, way off to the side. I don't think it impacts the effect of the house. At least I'm hoping you agree. Yeah. So Fred, questions, comments? All right, let me unmute there.
I, are you putting an actual stairway with railings and things that go up here and into like a doorway into that? Is that the intent? It's an interior staircase. Now that's a windings. It's a winding staircase in the back of the house. That's that starts in this upper second floor bedroom and goes down into the kitchen area. And I want to make instead of having a winding staircase that I want to make it. So it'd be an enclosed staircase.
walls on left and right with railings and bring it up to the code. And that gives me an extra three and a half feet in the kitchen. So I enlarged the kitchen that way. Why is it necessary to remove the second floor window up there? Because that's two feet above the floor.
And I think that that'll be cutting into the headroom of the stairs as you go down. And you couldn't, I mean, I'm not averse to moving the windows right and left and that sort of thing. I'm a little, it doesn't really thrill me to remove that window on the second floor and just have a sea of clapboards going down that whole wall. And I'm wondering if you could find a place, even if it's a new location for that window to survive.
Yes, I could move it towards the front of the house and it would be in a laundry. Let me see. Oh, it would be in a closet. Yeah, so I could move it, say, two feet to the front, to the street side. In the picture, that would be two feet to the right.
That would clear the stairwell. And it is going to be inside a closet then. Yeah. I mean, I'd prefer that than just have a blank wall there that. Yeah. 20 Feet long. And I don't mind personally. Relocating on the first floor, one of them and eliminating the second floor. So I would. In my opinion, you could.
You still have at least two windows on that facade. That's my opinion. OK. I can do that. The second floor, I think, has four different cladboard styles. I don't know if you can see it in this picture, but four different shingle styles.
Well, it's what I queen and so that's what they love doing back then, right? Yeah. So that's what I have to work with. I don't need to make it any, but you'd have to be patching that siding anyway, even to remove the window. So you're, you know, that's clever down below. That's a piece of cake. Yeah, I was just
in the store, a fellow was telling me that a box of shingles now costs, I think he was, might be exaggerating, he said $600 for a box of wooden shingles. Well, I'll be honest, I repaired my garage, which was cedar shakes, and I paid for just a box over $100 for just one box of shingles. I'll sell it to you, it's sitting in my garage. If you need some cedar shakes, I've got them here for you. Thanks, I'll keep that in mind.
Okay. Anything else? Well, I can leave it to the commission to chime in. So. Let's see. Charlotte. Questions, comments. How about Melanie? No, no additional comments. Okay.
Yes, we can. Oh, excellent. Okay. Yeah. I think Fred nailed it. Um, I agreed. I didn't, I think it's going to look better to have, um, the window moved down on the second floor as opposed to just all siding there. I think, I think that's, I think that'll look great. Um, and I have, you know, obviously on the first floor that that'll work out fine as well. So I would go ahead with that. Sure. Okay. Um, yeah. And, um,
I'm in agreement with Fred as well. So can I have, Fred, can you formulate your proposal in a motion? I can, I make a motion to approve the application with the following modifications of maintaining the window on the second floor and relocating it to an appropriate location.
I think, cause you've already, you've already submitted to eliminate one on the first floor and relocate one of those on the first floor. So I think that is covered in your application. And I would just say the modification of the second floor would be approved. So that's, that would be the motion. Okay. I'll second that. Okay. Thank you, Joe. Okay.
Let's see. We need Charlotte to vote. Charlotte, are you there? You're on mute, Charlotte. You gotta learn to unmute, Charlotte, if you can. There's a little button on your image there. Can she just give a hand signal or something? Yeah, thumbs up or thumbs down.
Yes, so let the record show that Charlotte voted thumbs up for to approve Fred's motion. Let's see, Joe? Yes. Okay, Melanie? Yes. Okay, and I also vote yes. So the motion carries unanimously and we do have a quorum. So John, you're all set.
Thanks so much. Okay. Thank you. We are, are we out of time? No. Okay. So thank you, John. And let me just fill in a couple of details. Chris Skelly is working hard on creating the preliminary report.
And he, I will circulate that when I get it from him, I will circulate that to everybody. And we don't have Chris Donovan or Sharon Guzik here. So we don't have an update on how outreach to South Street is going.
I think it's appropriate and not in violation of open meeting laws for Sharon and or Chris Donovan to send us an update and we can discuss the outreach plan next time.
I'm sorry that neither Sharon or Kristofferman is here. As far as guidelines to historic districts, there's been a snafu, which ultimately I'm responsible for, regarding the website. The bill has been paid. My apologies for the website being down for nonpayment.
I thought City Hall was taking care of it, but I obviously should have checked to make sure that was the case. Anyway, I think that is all in process. The website should be up in the next day or so. And once it's up, I will ask the website provider who actually designed the website to create an additional page with the guidelines that we adopted last time.
Um, and Chris, uh, um, I hope, uh, I think I just sent you the guidelines. I don't know if we wanted to. Yes. No, I think we voted on them. I think we voted on them, Fred, and I don't intend to make any. No, and I agree with that. I don't know if everyone would get a chance to look at it, but what about sending it to the city solicitor? Should we just give it
Um, well, I would love to do that, but, uh, I don't think we have a city solicitor yet. Let me just, let me just check in. MedfordMass.gov. Um, when I checked last time, there was still no, there was still nobody that, that, uh, let me just check law department here.
The position of city solicitor is still vacant. That is obviously not good news for us because we need the city solicitor to have our back on lots of issues. But I think we just need to proceed on our own. Does everyone agree? Anybody disagree?
No, I'd agree. And maybe I should send them to the mayor's office or something, just so they're like on file somewhere. And we can always say, well, we send them to mayor's office or something, even in the absence of a solicitor, just to be a little proactive. Okay, you want me to do that? And just ask the mayor's office for comments? Or say when you hire a solicitor, you know, make sure this is the first thing on his or her desk sort of thing. Okay, well, I can contact the,
Janice Spencer, who was listed as the office manager of the law department. And just ask her to have the, whenever the city solicitor comes in, there will probably be a mountain of work for that person to do. But somewhere down the list, that person should also review
our guidelines. Does that sound okay? Yes. Okay. All right then. So we are out of time. I will normally, I will put together the, I guess John has dropped off.
Um, I will put together the certificate of appropriateness for John Murphy and, uh, I will see you guys, uh, next month, hopefully with, uh, with more information about the outreach campaign. Excellent. Okay. Thank you everybody.