[SPEAKER_10]: How are we doing?
[SPEAKER_10]: Is everybody online?
[SPEAKER_10]: Is everyone able to hear each other?
[SPEAKER_09]: Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_09]: I can hear you.
[SPEAKER_09]: Hi, Charlotte.
[SPEAKER_09]: How are you feeling?
[SPEAKER_09]: Good.
[SPEAKER_09]: How are you?
[SPEAKER_01]: I think just Chris is waiting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Chris Bader is just waiting to unmute.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think my dog wants to.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why Sharon.
[SPEAKER_05]: sick my dog is trying to join the meeting.
[SPEAKER_01]: To grow over there.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm going to read Chris Bader's lips in case his microphone doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_10]: Chris, you can just talk now.
[SPEAKER_03]: This way.
[SPEAKER_03]: Looks like he's dialing in on his phone.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you, Chris.
[SPEAKER_01]: He must be having technical difficulties there, so.
[SPEAKER_10]: Chris Kelly, thank you for coming last week.
[SPEAKER_10]: We had a walkthrough of the South street district last week with Chris Kelly.
[SPEAKER_10]: It was a nice to be out in the street and see some, see it in person.
[SPEAKER_10]: We looked at some other additional sites after Sharon's great work pulling together district boundaries and there may be some additions to that, but that was last thing we we did out in the street on president's day.
[SPEAKER_10]: Some victories, a couple of defeats.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was good.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's good to talk through it with everybody and get a feel for what is over there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can I ask what people's impressions were?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I'll go first, I. I like the district we have, with the exception of maybe a couple of other things.
[SPEAKER_01]: I thought, you know, the idea of trying to really protect the shipbuilding properties with heritage to the river, I think was a pretty strong narrative.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a lot of beautiful homes over there, not all of which are part of this era that we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's part of the debate I guess we can have tonight as to whether we should expand or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but I thought there's a lot of,
[SPEAKER_01]: nice potential properties out there that are deserving of protection with the district.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I thought it could hang together pretty well myself.
[SPEAKER_10]: And of course, one of the things we're dealing with is the low hanging fruit, easy things to get done.
[SPEAKER_10]: And then those that may be more difficult.
[SPEAKER_10]: So the expanding it may cause more difficulty, but we're looking at them house by house and trying to find some value of which ones could be admitted.
[SPEAKER_10]: But that's the rub.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_10]: Chris Bader, are you with us on audio?
[SPEAKER_10]: You're muted.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'll see if I can unmute you.
[SPEAKER_10]: You're muted on your phone as well, Chris Bader.
[SPEAKER_10]: OK.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can you hear me now?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, boy.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, boy.
[SPEAKER_10]: Oh, boy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, boy.
[SPEAKER_10]: Oh,
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no echo, please.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Just a minute.
[SPEAKER_07]: Oh, I love it.
[SPEAKER_07]: It's science fiction sound effects.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hey, honey, buddy.
[SPEAKER_05]: Can I have a headset real quick?
[SPEAKER_02]: I might have to put that on the record.
[SPEAKER_10]: Honey bunny is going to have to go on the record.
[SPEAKER_03]: Next time, you got it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Look, speaker is on the right hand.
[SPEAKER_10]: Do we need to cite open meeting law terminology at the beginning of this meeting?
[SPEAKER_10]: I don't think we've done that.
[SPEAKER_10]: And just as the recording secretary, I'm just wondering if we need to say that language at the front end, which I may not be comfortable understanding of at the moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, people, people do.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can, I can, I have, I have the
[SPEAKER_00]: The info here, I can say it, but I'm not sometimes when I'm at home and my audio is so bad, it sounds model.
[SPEAKER_00]: So if you could, if you could state that just for the record, that would be great.
[SPEAKER_00]: On July 16, 2022, Governor Baker signed into law an act relative to extending certain state of emergency accommodations, which, among other things, extends the expiration of provisions pertaining to the open meeting on March 31, 2023.
[SPEAKER_00]: Specifically, this extension allows public bodies to continue holding meetings remotely without a quorum of the public body physically present at a meeting location.
[SPEAKER_00]: and provide adequate alternative access to remote meetings.
[SPEAKER_00]: This act does not make any new changes to the open meeting law other than extending the expiration date of the temporary provisions regarding remote meetings from July 15, 2022 to March 31, 2023.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: OK, can people hear me now?
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Still a lot of echo there, though, Chris.
[SPEAKER_11]: OK, I'll mute when I'm not speaking.
[SPEAKER_11]: Or can I do that?
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: We have two things going.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just cancel out something, one of the two.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's better?
[SPEAKER_11]: Is that better?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I guess not.
[SPEAKER_11]: Oh, brother.
[SPEAKER_11]: Damn it.
[SPEAKER_11]: Hold on.
[SPEAKER_00]: What the hell?
[SPEAKER_00]: Chris, can you mute your laptop or computer?
[SPEAKER_00]: If you do that, that shouldn't fix this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm just going to.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, let me just close out for a second.
[SPEAKER_11]: OK, can you hear me now?
[SPEAKER_07]: Can hear you can't see you.
[SPEAKER_11]: All right.
[SPEAKER_11]: You're not going to be able to see me.
[SPEAKER_11]: That's OK.
[SPEAKER_11]: You don't need to see me.
[SPEAKER_11]: My ugly mug.
[SPEAKER_10]: Chris, can we call the meeting to order?
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes, please.
[SPEAKER_11]: Let's call the meeting to order.
[SPEAKER_11]: It's 614.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thanks to my technological incompetence.
[SPEAKER_11]: Right.
[SPEAKER_11]: And yeah, so Chris Kelly, Chris Donovan, you want to read the minutes from from the last meeting?
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes, I sent them for the first time early.
[SPEAKER_10]: But I'll read them so it's in people's email, but let me just sort of read them for the record.
[SPEAKER_10]: But it is part of the email that they sent out to everyone.
[SPEAKER_10]: So this is February's meeting.
[SPEAKER_10]: It was, we reviewed last month's meeting notes, was approved, and then we dealt with 309 High Street, Ben Coy, K-O-O-Y.
[SPEAKER_10]: dealing with this chimney replacement application.
[SPEAKER_10]: They'd replaced two chimneys and restored them, and they were looking to restore the next two with the same exact process.
[SPEAKER_10]: We reviewed that.
[SPEAKER_10]: One chimney needed a chimney cap, so the motion was to approve the replacement of the two additional chimneys and the chimney cap.
[SPEAKER_10]: Motion for Fred was to motion to approve four to nothing unanimous.
[SPEAKER_10]: Tim Matt to whiskey spoke from the Commonwealth energy regarding solar energy for historic homes.
[SPEAKER_10]: He made a presentation to us.
[SPEAKER_10]: Fred soul presented the district guidelines presented for review.
[SPEAKER_10]: We talked about the South street walkthrough plan with Chris Skelly for February 20th.
[SPEAKER_10]: And that was our meeting a meeting adjourned just before seven.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's our meeting notes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, sounds good.
[SPEAKER_11]: Can I have a motion to accept?
[SPEAKER_05]: I make a motion to accept the minutes from the prior meeting.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, second?
[SPEAKER_01]: I second the motion.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, Charlotte?
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Fred?
[SPEAKER_03]: Melanie?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Joe.
[SPEAKER_11]: Joey there.
[SPEAKER_11]: OK.
[SPEAKER_04]: And.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes, yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: OK, great.
[SPEAKER_11]: Chris, Chris.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_10]: And Melanie.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, great.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: And Melanie has to respond as well, Melanie.
[SPEAKER_10]: Oh, she did.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: So next on our agenda is how to proceed on South Street.
[SPEAKER_11]: Do we... Recording in progress.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, just a minute.
[SPEAKER_11]: Let me get rid of my audio.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is going on here?
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, I'm just going to leave.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know how to fix this.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Right.
[SPEAKER_11]: We have a draft of the boundaries for the South Street historic district.
[SPEAKER_11]: We reviewed those, we toured that area.
[SPEAKER_11]: I think those boundaries are pretty good.
[SPEAKER_11]: There are clearly some houses on Manning Street that should be incorporated into a future historic district.
[SPEAKER_11]: I would say there are half a dozen very well-preserved Victorians.
[SPEAKER_01]: I put the map up here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hopefully everyone can see that.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, Fred.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, thank you.
[SPEAKER_10]: So this has been proposed.
[SPEAKER_10]: We passed the motion to accept this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_10]: And that's where we stand.
[SPEAKER_10]: We did a walkthrough with Chris Skelly to check that over, maybe to find some additions if they're notable, but this is what we have in play right now.
[SPEAKER_10]: So question is, what do we do next?
[SPEAKER_11]: Right.
[SPEAKER_11]: So
[SPEAKER_11]: So Chris Skelly, can you remind us what the next step is here?
[SPEAKER_08]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_08]: No necessarily clear flow chart that says you do this, then you do this, then you do this in this case.
[SPEAKER_08]: You're still at the point where you're thinking about the investigation of a local historic district here.
[SPEAKER_08]: And so there's going to be back and forth in terms of what that boundary should be.
[SPEAKER_08]: So you have options.
[SPEAKER_08]: You could just stick with the proposed district that you've got right now.
[SPEAKER_08]: So this is my first time just walking around that district.
[SPEAKER_08]: And I mean, it's a significant area.
[SPEAKER_08]: It was a really wonderful, wonderful collection of historic resources there.
[SPEAKER_08]: I wasn't really familiar with the whole shipyard aspect of the neighborhood until we walked around.
[SPEAKER_08]: And I think just being next to the river like that and seeing
[SPEAKER_08]: 19th century houses there, you could really get a sense that you were in a special place and the shipyards were right there.
[SPEAKER_08]: It was really amazing to think about.
[SPEAKER_08]: Okay, so you've got a wonderful district boundary right now that you could go with.
[SPEAKER_08]: Our walk around the district a couple of weeks ago definitely showed that there's lots of other significant resources as you make your way down some of those residential streets.
[SPEAKER_08]: They certainly are for the most part later properties.
[SPEAKER_08]: So they're gonna be later 19th century properties as you get away from the river, but certainly significant properties there.
[SPEAKER_08]: So as was said just a few minutes ago, your options are you could look at a larger local historic district right now, or you could stick with the boundary that you have for the proposed district and keep a larger district
[SPEAKER_08]: heads further into those neighborhoods at some point in the future.
[SPEAKER_08]: Lots of towns, cities do that where they'll expand.
[SPEAKER_08]: I mean, I've seen some where they expand every few years, basically.
[SPEAKER_08]: So that's definitely a possibility there.
[SPEAKER_08]: I think, well, okay, so then just finishing up there.
[SPEAKER_08]: So how do you decide whether you should stick with what you have or go a little further?
[SPEAKER_08]: into the neighborhoods.
[SPEAKER_08]: And that's where I really think public outreach, talking to property owners here, gauging the interest in having their neighborhood, their streets better protected, it would be really part of that process.
[SPEAKER_08]: And that can be a bit time consuming to think about, you can't rush that.
[SPEAKER_08]: So there's a number of things that you would have to do to really talk to the property owners here, their interest in a local historic district.
[SPEAKER_08]: If you kind of already bet it out that there's interest in the current district from property owners in knowing that this is going to better protect their neighborhood, well, that might be the better approach.
[SPEAKER_08]: It's certainly going to push things off quite a bit if you want to do an outreach campaign into those other streets.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, so Chris, Donovan, and Sharon, can you fill us in on any outreach activities that you've been doing in the neighborhood?
[SPEAKER_07]: Well, we haven't really gotten much farther than we had been.
[SPEAKER_07]: There's three definite yeses and a handful of probabilities.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, so what are the yeses?
[SPEAKER_10]: So Sharon was good enough to create a little list of all the properties in play and a little check off of how we go check out those people.
[SPEAKER_10]: So that's what we're kind of working off of.
[SPEAKER_10]: And Sharon has some relationships with some of these people as well.
[SPEAKER_10]: So to respect their neighbors, we've got a little start on that, but Sharon, any suggestions on what you think we may be able to do next, but she's done a lot of great work to set up a platform to identify them all.
[SPEAKER_07]: Well, I was hoping to run into people, but that's not working.
[SPEAKER_07]: So I'm going to have to go knock on some doors.
[SPEAKER_11]: OK.
[SPEAKER_11]: Oh, well, who have you who have you mentioned?
[SPEAKER_11]: A couple of people have said yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Number 48 and Marie McAllen, McAllen, 48 South Street.
[SPEAKER_07]: 48 South Street.
[SPEAKER_07]: It's the beautiful purple farmhouse.
[SPEAKER_07]: She's definitely into it.
[SPEAKER_07]: And 114 South Street, grandfather's house, they were into it.
[SPEAKER_07]: I think my, well, I know the people at 9 Toro and I'm pretty sure they'd be interested.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah, their kids are living there now and they're on the Cape, I think.
[SPEAKER_07]: I never see them anymore.
[SPEAKER_07]: So I have to call them or something.
[SPEAKER_07]: The neighbor behind me, number 15 Walnut, is likely.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_07]: And you would think the people, I don't know the people at 21 Turo, the Gates house.
[SPEAKER_07]: But as far as I know, they're the same people that bought it from Tufts.
[SPEAKER_07]: And at that point, they were interested in it.
[SPEAKER_07]: I don't know if that's changed.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, certainly a few years ago, they were in favor.
[SPEAKER_07]: Number, I just wanted to point out, number 12 Walnut, that shouldn't be included.
[SPEAKER_07]: That's not a significant house.
[SPEAKER_01]: This one down here?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe, let me see what I got.
[SPEAKER_07]: I think you and I talked about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I got the wrong one.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's 12 Maple, not 12 Walnut.
[SPEAKER_07]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we have to,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, just OK.
[SPEAKER_11]: Is that the one we're looking at right now?
[SPEAKER_07]: No, this is this is a pre 1855 house on Maple Street, but he just got the 12th confused.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have to fix that one.
[SPEAKER_01]: So.
[SPEAKER_01]: All right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a great picture.
[SPEAKER_11]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: But do we want to, I don't have the thing.
12.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we could, I have to revise this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Map, which I'm willing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I guess we'd have to then revote on.
[SPEAKER_01]: The boundaries of it just to get.
[SPEAKER_01]: Approval for us as a committee.
[SPEAKER_01]: So.
[SPEAKER_11]: That's correct.
[SPEAKER_11]: Let me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me see.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't think there is a sheet for it.
[SPEAKER_07]: So I don't believe so.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah, 1912 Walnut was built in 1955.
[SPEAKER_07]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, yeah, I see that, right.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, so shall we strike that from, we would have to vote on that of course, but.
[SPEAKER_01]: We can vote on it now and then I could just redo the map with like today's date or something if we want.
[SPEAKER_11]: That sounds good.
[SPEAKER_11]: Do you, okay, do you want to do that right now, Fred?
[SPEAKER_01]: I think so, unless anyone is proposing, I did some more research myself and there are some lovely homes as we identified when we were out there, but only a handful are sort of the pre-Civil War shipbuilding era.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I don't think there's no,
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no form Bs for the properties that I thought might be significant out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And without the form B, it's really hard to know if there is any significance to the building.
[SPEAKER_07]: So- Which ones were you thinking?
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me just... Let me get my Zoom up back here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, now I'm having technical difficulties over here.
[SPEAKER_10]: So these are some homes that we thought may be additional to the proposed district as we walked the streets.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, now I can't find my.
[SPEAKER_10]: So they made some notes about someone's that had had the right, you know, architectural the right look to fill in the district.
[SPEAKER_10]: And that's what we're probably discussing now what things may be additional to add if it's appropriate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, and so let me go back to the map here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, now I'm back again.
[SPEAKER_01]: 12 Maples, the original shipbuilder's house.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this was all an empty lot.
[SPEAKER_01]: And she, the widow of the property, sold it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all these were added in the 1910s.
[SPEAKER_01]: But across the street, it's 15 and this one here, which is... 21.
[SPEAKER_01]: look like they are vintage from the 1840s, 1850s construction era based on, they're very severely compromised though.
[SPEAKER_01]: So for that reason, I'm a little reluctant to add them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it was really only these two.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then down here, 45 Metcalf Street is a original shipbuilder's house that is 1845, I believe.
[SPEAKER_07]: But that's a two family.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's it's now like a boarding house apparently.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that one is available on macros.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me see if I can get the sheet to that one.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that would be an outlier from my district would be hard to sort of connect the dots for that one.
[SPEAKER_07]: 58 is a nice house as well.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah, that was made into condos.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I'm inclined to sort of not, and it's also been compromised somewhat there.
45.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me see what the short it is here.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's 23 Walnut.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you see it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is this on the screen here?
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah, it's not, the address isn't 23 anymore, Walnut, but yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: The alternative there was 58 Metcalf Street.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that was an old shipbuilder's house.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you read the whole narrative here, and I won't go into the end of it, it is lumped in with all the other shipbuilding homes of this era that we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think this one would be a good,
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, there's no.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, possibility for that, except that it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's some other pictures.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's been pretty heavily compromised.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's an outlier.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just is sort of way out.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it would hide.
[SPEAKER_01]: Be hard to bring the boundaries in.
[SPEAKER_07]: I actually.
[SPEAKER_07]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know
[SPEAKER_01]: All these other ones in here are nice homes, but they're not of this era.
[SPEAKER_07]: That's why I didn't include it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'd love to include it, but yeah, it was hard to connect.
[SPEAKER_01]: I agree.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I'm willing to forgo that and stick with the boundaries with the exception of removing 12 Walnut and sticking with the boundaries as we show here.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hello?
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, what do other people think?
[SPEAKER_11]: Charlotte?
[SPEAKER_05]: Pardon me?
[SPEAKER_11]: What do you think about including 58 MedCap?
[SPEAKER_05]: I wasn't able to hear a lot of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: My dog is acting up and barking behind me.
[SPEAKER_05]: But what I did hear, I approve.
[SPEAKER_07]: Wait, wait, you're asking to include it now, Chris?
[SPEAKER_07]: Mm-hmm, yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm asking what people think.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm willing to go with whoever.
[SPEAKER_11]: I have no particular opinion on.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, I just want to know what people's opinion are.
[SPEAKER_07]: It's just that it would be hard to connect it.
[SPEAKER_07]: It would be sort of an island unto itself.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_11]: I mean, it fits in with the shipyard narrative.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe Charlotte, are you agreeing with the fact that we won't include it?
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's what I'm taking from Charlotte's comment that she agrees that we would not include it in the district.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, you're muted though, Charlotte.
[SPEAKER_11]: We have a you Joe.
[SPEAKER_11]: It obviously is a pre-Civil War.
[SPEAKER_11]: It fits in with our narrative, but it's kind of been altered a lot.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a beautiful look at home.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, I can go all the way on it.
[SPEAKER_04]: If the homeowner wanted to go with it, I'd have no problem, you know, including it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: There's at least three.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think it'd be hard to get their approval to do that.
[SPEAKER_07]: Change anything.
[SPEAKER_07]: I don't think so.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'm not sure that they would object.
[SPEAKER_07]: It's just that, how do you connect it to the other houses?
[SPEAKER_11]: What do you think with Melanie?
[SPEAKER_06]: I think it's a nice house, but I think it's hard to connect everything.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: How about you, Chris Donovan?
[SPEAKER_10]: I think it's part of the narrative, but I like what Chris Kelly was saying was let's kind of start with something.
[SPEAKER_10]: It doesn't mean we can't expand story, tell the story in the future.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I think we leave it off for now to try and get some of the things that we've already discussed.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I say, leave it off.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Is that, do other people agree with that?
[SPEAKER_05]: I think that's good reasoning, so I will go along with it, Chris.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: And it doesn't mean we can't loop back, but just for right now.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's true.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, my opinion would be to move forward if we want to make it forward easier than fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if they, if the owner said that they wanted to be part of it, I would have no objection to making them part of it.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, well, let's leave it off.
[SPEAKER_11]: I suggest that we leave it off for the moment and rethink it if as part of our outreach, we discover that they're interested.
[SPEAKER_11]: How about that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yep, sounds good.
[SPEAKER_11]: All right, so do we have any other issues with the boundaries?
[SPEAKER_07]: Well, you were going to vote to exclude number 12.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: All right.
[SPEAKER_11]: So, yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: So can I have a motion?
[SPEAKER_10]: And have we included anything new, Fred?
[SPEAKER_10]: Is there anything that we thought may have merited that and we could run it by Sharon to vet?
[SPEAKER_10]: Was there anything additional that we were looking to include?
[SPEAKER_10]: Fred.
[SPEAKER_01]: At this time.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I like the idea of maybe trying to expand on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: We'll get it through and then we can expand houses.
[SPEAKER_01]: As people get more on board.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Chris would be to amend this map.
[SPEAKER_01]: By removing 12 Walnut street.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I will prepare a new map dated today's date of March 9th, 2023.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I vote that we vote on that now as a commission.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: You're making a motion, Chris.
[SPEAKER_10]: So the motion is to take 12, number 12 Manning?
[SPEAKER_00]: 12 Walnut.
[SPEAKER_10]: Walnut, 12 Walnut.
[SPEAKER_10]: Understood, 12 Walnut.
[SPEAKER_10]: We're taking that off the proposed district.
[SPEAKER_10]: Everything else continues the way that it was in the proposed district we had before, but we're taking 12 Walnut off the list.
[SPEAKER_01]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, can I have a second for that motion?
[SPEAKER_10]: I second the motion.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, all in favor, Charlotte?
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Fred.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Melanie.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Joe.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Chris.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: And I vote.
[SPEAKER_10]: So we have new district boundaries.
[SPEAKER_11]: That's correct.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: We should probably try to go forward and do some more stuff with outreach.
[SPEAKER_10]: So Chris, excuse me for interrupting Chris.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I just sent everybody on email the list that Sharon had created of all the names that are on there.
[SPEAKER_10]: 12 Walnut may still be on that list.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm not sure.
[SPEAKER_10]: So it's a list of all those homes that are in the district and the owner's names.
[SPEAKER_10]: If anybody knows anyone who wants to reach out to them, but we've had some success as Sharon mentioned earlier, but everybody has a list of those names and addresses on their email.
[SPEAKER_07]: About half of them are absentee landlords.
[SPEAKER_07]: So that's, I know two of those, but the other ones I don't, you know.
[SPEAKER_10]: So Chris Skelly, Chris Bader, do we make an official awareness to them at some point to say that this is happening?
[SPEAKER_11]: Well, I think we should, the answer is yes, of course, but I think it should be done in the context of a general outreach.
[SPEAKER_11]: uh, to not only to the, to the owners, because this is not, it's not just the owners that are, that are relevant here.
[SPEAKER_11]: It's also the residents.
[SPEAKER_07]: Uh, are you talking about doing that now, Chris?
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Um, do you think that's not a good idea?
[SPEAKER_07]: Well, I think we should get the buy-in of the owners first because you don't want,
[SPEAKER_07]: Oh, right.
[SPEAKER_11]: You don't want to talk to the residents first, right?
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_11]: OK.
[SPEAKER_07]: I mean, it's fine once we talk to the owners and get, you know, assess them.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: Talk to everybody else.
[SPEAKER_11]: OK.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: So let's reach out to the owners.
[SPEAKER_11]: And let's see, we guess we reached out to about two or three.
[SPEAKER_11]: We we.
[SPEAKER_10]: So, Chris, does 18 have been told us 18 homes in total?
[SPEAKER_11]: Does that sound right, Fred?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there might be 17 now, if we take one off.
[SPEAKER_01]: Was Walnut on that list?
[SPEAKER_10]: No, this is Sharon's list that she generated.
[SPEAKER_10]: I don't see 12 Walnut on it.
[SPEAKER_10]: So 18 homes in our district.
[SPEAKER_10]: And we could loop back on that to be sure, but I think 18.
[SPEAKER_10]: Do you want to go over them right now quickly?
[SPEAKER_10]: Call up the map and we'll go right down the list.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can share Sharon's spreadsheet if that's all right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you want to do that?
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: Sounds good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_10]: The one I just sent you Fred.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, this is the one you just sent me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_10]: Sharon, if you could just overview that, there's anything that's.
[SPEAKER_10]: You think is.
[SPEAKER_10]: Not correct on that, but.
[SPEAKER_07]: No, these are correct.
[SPEAKER_07]: So yes, my notes didn't make it in terms of who's actually living there and who isn't.
[SPEAKER_10]: Oh, I may have chopped it off when I created a PDF.
[SPEAKER_10]: There's a couple of notes to who we actually did contact.
[SPEAKER_10]: So the question is.
[SPEAKER_07]: The ones in the yellow are all yeses, are all pro.
[SPEAKER_07]: The ones in the blue.
[SPEAKER_03]: What are the ones in the blue?
[SPEAKER_10]: So the question is, should we reach out to all of them and some continuous, everyone gets the same respect of being notified with a postcard?
[SPEAKER_07]: No, I think we should talk to them if at all possible.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes, I agree with you.
[SPEAKER_07]: Personally.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: I don't think a postcard is we postcard you weren't in on the, the, the force group yes but we're still open but postcards is definitely not the way to go.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think it was officially announced that they've been notified, what would it would be the term the thought of that situation they've all been notified everyone's been.
[SPEAKER_10]: they should have it on the record that they've been notified.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's my thought, but I understand.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's a time for that.
[SPEAKER_08]: Under the state law, you're going to be required to do that with an official notification to all the property owners.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, I think we're there.
[SPEAKER_08]: You want to do something that goes way beyond what the state law actually requires.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, I agree with that.
[SPEAKER_08]: Ideally, that's something face-to-face if you can just really make it personal that way.
[SPEAKER_10]: What if we actually rang the doorbell and thought that that was considered the outreach that we actually, because I like to go through each one of them.
[SPEAKER_10]: I like to, there's only 18, it's very finite.
[SPEAKER_10]: What would be the thought of that?
[SPEAKER_10]: Because I'd like to get some accomplishments on this.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah, Chris, why don't we talk offline and make a plan?
[SPEAKER_08]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_08]: So if you do anything door to door,
[SPEAKER_08]: I mean, you're really kind of putting people on the spot to make a decision, and that's going to be challenging in a lot of cases, because they're not quite sure what you're talking about, and they might have follow-up questions.
[SPEAKER_08]: So, I mean, I think having something in hand, like a letter or a one-page fact sheet, maybe even something personal about the significance of their house, but just a one-pager about a local historic district would be great to leave with them, and then
[SPEAKER_08]: either something like a survey or some way that they can send something back to you at a later time with what their questions are or what their feelings are in general about the proposed district.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, sounds good.
[SPEAKER_10]: I like the personalization of that, Chris Kelly.
[SPEAKER_10]: I like the personalization of that's a little bit of work.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm not sure who's going to do that work, but we do have some form B's on some things, but Chris, Chris Bader, do we have information on every single property?
[SPEAKER_10]: I know there's a bunch of form B's out there, but do we have to and where are we holding that?
[SPEAKER_10]: specific form Bs or information about each house, do we have?
[SPEAKER_10]: We can probably post those.
[SPEAKER_07]: I thought you posted those, Chris, in Google Drive.
[SPEAKER_10]: I do have them in a Google Drive, just wondering what's the official format for collecting them.
[SPEAKER_08]: I've done a lot of that already, so I could actually get you what I put together so far for a PDF.
[SPEAKER_08]: Love it.
[SPEAKER_08]: Not all of these have form Bs.
[SPEAKER_08]: Some have nothing for an inventory form.
[SPEAKER_08]: And then some are included, but only included because they're within an area form.
[SPEAKER_08]: And so there's really nothing there on the area form about that individual property.
[SPEAKER_08]: So it might have a number MDF.175, but it's what MHC calls a no form.
[SPEAKER_08]: It's got a number, but there's no form attached to it because it was like, it was on an area form.
[SPEAKER_08]: So it didn't get that specific.
[SPEAKER_07]: Well, but there is a little bit of information in that area form.
[SPEAKER_08]: Sometimes, yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: Except for the 1974 one that has 30 and 31 and 23 on it.
[SPEAKER_07]: That has very little information.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, that might be the one I'm looking at right now.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, sometimes there's a little bit of information.
[SPEAKER_07]: But the one on Manning Street-Turrow has information on each one.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'm not each one, but most a lot of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this map, if you go on here, I've included in this PDF that I sent to everybody.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you click on the little box there.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is available on macros will come up for each property I had.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you get the scan sheet and all the all the pages are here.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we could this is this is what's available on macros.
[SPEAKER_01]: There may be some other things that are not available, but the whole form B.
[SPEAKER_01]: This, for instance, is 21 Truro we've been talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think we could print.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm happy to print it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we could hand the ones, at least when you talk to the homeowner, the actual Form B that's been prepared for their property.
[SPEAKER_01]: They may or may not even know of its existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: That sounds great.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that might be the jumping off point for a discussion.
[SPEAKER_07]: This is a great map that you put together.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's really cool.
[SPEAKER_01]: All those little flags are the Form Bs.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's great.
[SPEAKER_11]: That's very helpful.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm trying to make it easy for us people.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I've listed the ones here that we that I can't find much information on but so okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: Sharon, if I could ask, maybe you have a little bit more research on this.
[SPEAKER_10]: If we ask the Historical Society, you know how they do the campaign with the signs on it?
[SPEAKER_10]: Are they going to the same places that you may have tried in Fred and this database?
[SPEAKER_10]: So they go into the same thing?
[SPEAKER_10]: Have we exhausted?
[SPEAKER_10]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: So there's really no more out there than you probably already tried to dig up on some of these places.
[SPEAKER_07]: There's no official thing out there.
[SPEAKER_07]: But yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Some of these things are mentioned in other forms, but there's ways to quickly get a little information.
[SPEAKER_07]: You look at maps, you look at feeds.
[SPEAKER_07]: I've done a lot of that for some of these.
[SPEAKER_10]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_11]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know
[SPEAKER_01]: Properties like this one, if you go down to the bottom here, this whole section here is the narrative for our district.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all about a well-defined area centered on South Street, extending on and on with several prominent shipbuilders and shipwrights, and they get the names and the addresses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's the narrative that's already been prepared by John Clemson, for instance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think, so,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's already there.
[SPEAKER_10]: What I was thinking was just trying to call a little bit of that to be just a little bit, maybe a paragraph, but I'll maybe take it upon myself to read them and pull out some of the substantive pieces.
[SPEAKER_10]: Some of a little bit more difficult to read, but that one looks pretty tight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and John Clemson, he includes this paragraph in almost every one of these houses that is relating to a shipbuilder.
[SPEAKER_01]: So he, this is like a piece of boilerplate that he puts in all these form Bs.
[SPEAKER_01]: that we're trying to build on by making it an actual district.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think that we could have a cover sheet that gives the big umbrella picture of why we're doing this, and then the specific house attached to that.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_07]: This is in there, in that paragraph.
[SPEAKER_07]: Pretty cool.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just rambles on and on and on.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it could break it down and
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do we have, do we have budget for someone to kind of go do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: I know we're all kind of busy and we're all trying to add something.
[SPEAKER_01]: We do.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes, a budget with a reason is not a problem.
[SPEAKER_10]: So could we assign that as a project to kind of do an overview of what the district is sort of all about, and then try and bring up some of those narratives, whether it be the universal one, then the smaller one for each of those 18 houses?
[SPEAKER_11]: Well, I think that will be part of Chris Kelly's report.
[SPEAKER_11]: Am I right, Chris?
[SPEAKER_08]: It definitely will be.
[SPEAKER_08]: So part of the report will be the
[SPEAKER_08]: the history, history of the area, significance of the area.
[SPEAKER_08]: And then, um, I I'll, I'll send this to you, the PDF, but it's going to have, it's going to have a list.
[SPEAKER_08]: The, the property index itself is going to have a little bit of information on each of the properties.
[SPEAKER_08]: And I'm going to grab that whenever I can from the inventory forms.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Now, um, do we know how many houses do not have foreign bees, Chris Kelly?
[SPEAKER_08]: I think so, yeah.
[SPEAKER_08]: I don't know, I'd have to go add them up right now, but I think so.
[SPEAKER_08]: It might be like five, five or so.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: And what do people think?
[SPEAKER_11]: Do we want, do we want, we can, we can commission form Bs either from Chris Kelly himself or from Claire Dempsey or from John Clemson for these houses.
[SPEAKER_11]: Do we want to do that or do we not think that's necessary?
[SPEAKER_08]: It's not necessary for the purposes of submitting a study report for a local historic district.
[SPEAKER_08]: You do not have to have inventory forms for each of the boxes.
[SPEAKER_11]: But as a practical matter and part of our outreach, what do you think, Chris, Kelly?
[SPEAKER_08]: I mean, obviously having more information is better.
[SPEAKER_08]: So yeah, if you have the ability to send us out with some more individual form Bs,
[SPEAKER_11]: We have the resources, we have the resources for that.
[SPEAKER_11]: Assuming that, so what do other people think?
[SPEAKER_10]: I think we need that scholarship.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think we need that detail because that just makes it easy for us to sell it to everybody else.
[SPEAKER_10]: Something very succinct.
[SPEAKER_10]: So yeah, provide that for us.
[SPEAKER_10]: And that's a lot.
[SPEAKER_11]: Well, it wouldn't necessarily it could be for Skelly if you have time to do this, Chris.
[SPEAKER_11]: But would you have time to do this in the next month or two, Chris?
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, you might want to see if John Clemson's available first, just because he's he's informed form B's in this area already.
[SPEAKER_11]: Right.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_11]: OK.
[SPEAKER_11]: And Claire Dempsey also has worked in this area.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, and she's just got more skilled at the architectural history than the descriptions.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm more of a planner.
[SPEAKER_08]: I can do them, I just can't do them as efficiently as they can.
[SPEAKER_11]: So Charlotte, what do you think?
[SPEAKER_11]: Do we want to get, from the standpoint of outreach, do we want to get Form Bs for each of the, for every property in this district?
[SPEAKER_05]: How difficult do you think that would be?
[SPEAKER_05]: What kind of time would we build?
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm guessing, I'm guessing, I don't, the short answer is I don't know.
[SPEAKER_11]: We can find that out and I can report back at our next meeting.
[SPEAKER_11]: But let's assume that it can happen in a three month time frame.
[SPEAKER_11]: Would that help?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: I think that I would say yes, let's call that rule.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Fred, what do you think?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm happy to have the four Bs, but I don't think it should slow us down.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think we should keep going with the ones we have and the narrative we have.
[SPEAKER_11]: Well, maybe we can start reaching out to the people who have the, you know, so there are only less than half a dozen that don't have Form Bs.
[SPEAKER_11]: Maybe we can just start reaching out to the people who do.
[SPEAKER_11]: And, you know, if we have the Form Bs in time,
[SPEAKER_11]: You know, to, to, to be meaningful to this process, then, then we can, we can pull that in.
[SPEAKER_11]: But I think we should get, I would suggest getting started on the form Bs.
[SPEAKER_11]: And we'll just see how fast we can do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, do you need a motion to contact?
[SPEAKER_11]: I do.
[SPEAKER_01]: I do.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I'd make a motion that you reach out to John Clemson for the, for the omitted properties and we can find out what they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm asking him to give us a quote for it.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, great.
[SPEAKER_11]: Do I have a second?
[SPEAKER_05]: I have a second, Charlotte.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: So Charlotte, you're in favor?
[SPEAKER_05]: I am.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, Fred?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, Melanie?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, Joe?
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm sorry, I lost all audio at about five minutes ago, so I haven't been able to hear anything.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, sorry.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which device?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_11]: So the motion, the motion is to get form B's for the half dozen or so properties that, uh, that don't have form B. So yeah, I'll go with that.
[SPEAKER_11]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Chris Donovan.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, and I vote yes as well.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, we have the resources for this in the budget.
[SPEAKER_11]: So I think we should definitely go forward with that.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: All right, so motion passed.
[SPEAKER_11]: We're running out of time.
[SPEAKER_10]: Chris, if I could just interject, I just sent an email to everybody about the Google drive and the password.
[SPEAKER_10]: So it has a lot of those form Bs, has a lot of pictures on it, has a lot of stuff on it, but it's a way to access some of that.
[SPEAKER_10]: But Fred, I think your map, and it may have come from Sharon, that has all the PDFs, so the form Bs connected to it, that's our official proposal, correct?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's our official map, and I'll revise it, but I will include
[SPEAKER_01]: It will still have the tags for all the properties that I confirmed before.
[SPEAKER_10]: That sounds pretty all-encompassing to that one document.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's the idea.
[SPEAKER_07]: Chris Donovan, it's easier to go online and share the Google Drive with other people than it is to have them sign in.
[SPEAKER_07]: Because if it's shared, they can get into it.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'll do that right afterwards.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you, Sharon.
[SPEAKER_11]: I also think a webpage would help us.
[SPEAKER_11]: So we could put the map up on our webpage where you can click and actually get to the form B right there.
[SPEAKER_10]: Who has access to that, Chris?
[SPEAKER_10]: And who knows that web?
[SPEAKER_11]: I can take care of that.
[SPEAKER_07]: I think we should wait on that.
[SPEAKER_11]: Oh, really?
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_07]: Well, just until we, you know, get it all nailed down and everything, yeah.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, sure, okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: What do other people think?
[SPEAKER_11]: Sharon, Fred, what do you think?
[SPEAKER_01]: Should we- Well, Sharon, would taking like the 12 Walnut Street off and having a new map or waiting until we do some more outreach to property owners and things like that?
[SPEAKER_07]: I'd like to talk to the property owners or at least most of them, or let's say more than half of them to be, you know, once, once it's like out there, then yeah, let's put it up there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, whenever that is, I I'm in favor of sort of putting it up as soon as we can on the website, but yeah, I, I think there are transparency issues, Sharon.
[SPEAKER_11]: We don't necessarily have to advertise the existence of the website, but
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's already part of the public record in this recording, in this Zoom meeting, so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: That's exactly right.
[SPEAKER_07]: I mean, if people wanted to watch the Zoom meeting, they'd know about it.
[SPEAKER_10]: And how could they access our district proposal through the public?
[SPEAKER_07]: Well, that's what they're talking about is putting it on the website.
[SPEAKER_10]: So Fred, the map that Fred has, can we give that a title?
[SPEAKER_10]: Can we give that a name, Fred?
[SPEAKER_10]: But that document has those clickable forms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's another good point, Chris, is that right now it's just South Street Historic District.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm wondering if we should officially name it the South Street Shipbuilding Historic District or add some little piece that makes it a little more evocative than just South Street.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: Well, there's already, you know, a national register historic district called the ship.
[SPEAKER_06]: I think it's called Shipbuilding District.
[SPEAKER_07]: It's over by Riverside, Pleasant Street and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I think we could build on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the Riverside Shipbuilding District.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the South Street Shipbuilding District.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think they can complement each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: eventually we should try to claim that for a local historic district, right now it is not.
[SPEAKER_07]: It should, yeah, you're right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that, I just think adding more than, you know, the other districts are named for people and whatever, Grandview Ave or whatever, sorry.
[SPEAKER_08]: Just a thought on that is that if you do want to expand this in the future,
[SPEAKER_08]: just a more general name called South Street might be useful.
[SPEAKER_08]: I mean, this area is significant not just because it's shipbuilders.
[SPEAKER_08]: I mean, its growth is really interesting the way it went away from the river and later architectural styles kind of go up the street like that.
[SPEAKER_08]: There's significance here that goes beyond just the shipbuilders, but I think it makes sense what you're doing is just to focus on the shipbuilding property now.
[SPEAKER_08]: But yeah, it is a problem if you started thinking about adding in lots of more later 19th century properties and they're post-shipbuilding.
[SPEAKER_07]: That's exactly what I was thinking, Chris.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would still go for it, but that's all right.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'll defer to the- You would still go for what, Fred?
[SPEAKER_01]: The South Street Shipbuilding Historic District.
[SPEAKER_11]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I would love my house, even though I'm not a shipbuilder in my house.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I was in the neighborhood, I'd happily be part of that with my 1880 Salonia or Victorian shingle style house or whatever it is.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_10]: Even some of those lumber operators came out of that shipbuilding industry, even if not was directly shipbuilding.
[SPEAKER_10]: It seemed to have a legacy of that money, of that wealth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, so I think Sharon, you have, you don't think a website is a webpage dedicated to the ditch is a good idea at that point, is that correct?
[SPEAKER_07]: I would wait on it.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_07]: In my personal opinion.
[SPEAKER_11]: Can you, so we have to have an alternative to that.
[SPEAKER_11]: Can you and Chris Donovan come up with a concrete plan that you can present at our next meeting that exactly how to do the outreach?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: And, you know, I think you should consider at what stage, and there should be a webpage at some point.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, yes, I agree.
[SPEAKER_11]: And, you know, if you could make, you know, make a recommendation in your proposal, exactly what, at exactly when that should happen.
[SPEAKER_07]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'm leaning towards more where it's required.
[SPEAKER_11]: To do outreach.
[SPEAKER_11]: No, but that is, can you and Chris Donovan come up with a concrete proposal?
[SPEAKER_11]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_11]: With steps and dates and yada yada.
[SPEAKER_07]: Well, you can't do dates, right?
[SPEAKER_07]: But yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Chris, what do you think?
[SPEAKER_07]: Donovan, Chris.
[SPEAKER_10]: I want to do it tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_10]: I want these 18 homeowners to know, if they know, then I feel like that's one more check off the list.
[SPEAKER_10]: And then there's the awareness campaign of the neighborhood.
[SPEAKER_10]: So step one is the 18.
[SPEAKER_10]: Step two is the neighborhood.
[SPEAKER_10]: And then we take it to the public, but we're waiting for information of the neighborhood is the public.
[SPEAKER_10]: Right.
[SPEAKER_10]: So, I mean, for me to be honest, I like the historical society involved.
[SPEAKER_10]: I like the mayor involved.
[SPEAKER_10]: I like everyone to know that this is something we are shining some light on.
[SPEAKER_10]: So the sooner we get, uh,
[SPEAKER_10]: eyes dotted to make sure that everyone is notified, the more we take it public.
[SPEAKER_10]: And I know we're trying to get something passed, but I don't want to pass it under, you know, I want to see it with the sun on it.
[SPEAKER_10]: I want to see it shine.
[SPEAKER_10]: So whatever you think, Chris Bader for Sharon and I to do something and just trying to get some finite, you know, timelines on finishing that component, which is the website.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: So why don't you guys talk and,
[SPEAKER_11]: see if you can come up with something you agree on.
[SPEAKER_11]: And if you can't agree, just give us your own personal recommendations as to what the steps should be.
[SPEAKER_07]: I think we can reach an agreement, don't you?
[SPEAKER_07]: Okay, good.
[SPEAKER_11]: Good, good.
[SPEAKER_11]: Just checking.
[SPEAKER_11]: All right.
[SPEAKER_11]: So Sharon and Chris Donovan are going to come up with a concrete outreach plan before our next regular meeting.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm gonna reach out to John Clemson and or Claire Dempsey about doing Form Bs as expeditiously as possible for the properties.
[SPEAKER_11]: We didn't get to Fred's revised, I'm sorry, Fred's proposal for guidelines.
[SPEAKER_10]: District guidelines.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, but please, everyone do have a look at that.
[SPEAKER_11]: I sent out my proposed revisions.
[SPEAKER_11]: You know, again, we can talk about that.
[SPEAKER_10]: And Chris Bader, is that something we take before council when we do sort of finish?
[SPEAKER_11]: No, no, we adopt that as our on our own.
[SPEAKER_11]: But we need to take a vote on it.
[SPEAKER_11]: And once is once we take a vote on it, then we put it up on the website.
[SPEAKER_10]: Can we plan on doing that next month to try and let's let's aim for that.
[SPEAKER_11]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you, Fred.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, thank you for it.
[SPEAKER_11]: This is great.
[SPEAKER_11]: And thank you for the interactive math too.
[SPEAKER_11]: This is above and beyond.
[SPEAKER_01]: All technology within our reach here.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I'm looking forward to everyone's data on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll try to do my best to consolidate everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's great.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: I think we all have our work cut out for us for the next, for the next month.
[SPEAKER_11]: Why don't we meet at our regular date in, in April, which is.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you, Chris.
[SPEAKER_11]: Just a minute.
[SPEAKER_11]: April 13th.
[SPEAKER_10]: April 13th.
[SPEAKER_10]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_07]: So do we have to wait for them to get these guidelines?
[SPEAKER_11]: I, I would prefer to wait, I want to, I would, I would, you know, we're all busy people and I don't,
[SPEAKER_07]: I mean, that would be important to have that in hand when we go to talk to people.
[SPEAKER_11]: And if we're talking to people, I mean, the thing is, we have to vote on the guidelines.
[SPEAKER_11]: We can't just... Do you want to have a meeting before that?
[SPEAKER_07]: It's not up to me.
[SPEAKER_11]: Right, exactly.
[SPEAKER_11]: What do other people think?
[SPEAKER_10]: So the idea was to have reviewed it, to have looked at it, to make any notes or changes, additions, subtractions on that.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I think we can do that on our own and be prepared for the next meeting to move that forward.
[SPEAKER_10]: It sounds like a plan we could do it on our own to look through it and then be prepared to talk on it and then pass it.
[SPEAKER_11]: And vote on it, yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, I think that's reasonable.
[SPEAKER_11]: Fred, what do you think?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I was trying to just share it on my screen here.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have a copy of it open, but I can't seem to find it.
[SPEAKER_06]: I have read it before the meeting and read your comments.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if everyone wants to do it, I'm happy to make the changes and we could have an interim meeting or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: If we if we're able to get it together and people can respond in the next week, I'm happy to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Review those things, digest them if we can.
[SPEAKER_11]: You want to have a brief meeting in two weeks?
[SPEAKER_10]: I don't know if it's a subcommittee meeting.
[SPEAKER_11]: Well, it would be a meeting of the full of the full commission.
[SPEAKER_11]: We don't want to.
[SPEAKER_11]: We don't want to get into the weeds.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's really the guidelines of the historic district.
[SPEAKER_10]: And Chris Kelly, have you seen that?
[SPEAKER_11]: I only said that, you know, I don't think Chris is doing it.
[SPEAKER_10]: No, no, just to review that nothing's either out of bounds or something that's common sense that we're missing out on.
[SPEAKER_10]: Just an overview is what I was wondering.
[SPEAKER_08]: I opened it up.
[SPEAKER_08]: I mean, I took a quick look at it.
[SPEAKER_08]: I mean, I'm not contracted to look at, to review your design guidelines.
[SPEAKER_11]: Right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_11]: So, actually that is another point.
[SPEAKER_11]: We want Chris Kelly to look at those.
[SPEAKER_11]: Can we delegate, can the commission delegate to me the ability to approve a reasonable
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Do we have a motion?
[SPEAKER_11]: Fee from Chris Kelly to review the gut and design guidelines.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Sean, is that okay by you?
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes, let's make it a motion.
[SPEAKER_11]: So I will, you are, you are the commission is delegating to me.
[SPEAKER_11]: The ability to approve a reasonable.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Melody?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Joe?
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Let's see.
[SPEAKER_11]: Charlotte?
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: And did I get you, Fred?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, but I'll vote yes to that.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, so I'll vote yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, so yeah, so Chris Kelly and I will work out a reasonable fee for that and hopefully we'll get- Chris Bader, can we still meet in two weeks?
[SPEAKER_10]: So anyone that's interested in doing that to kind of put some final notes on that before we send it to Chris Kelly, we'll kind of just do a final overview on that in two weeks and then you can- Well, no, we want his input before that.
[SPEAKER_10]: OK, OK.
[SPEAKER_10]: Oh, I wanted to put I wanted to put a stamp on it, make sure it was legal with the one with the stamp.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_11]: OK, so let's tentatively propose plan to meet on on on March 23rd.
[SPEAKER_11]: That's in two weeks.
[SPEAKER_11]: And does that work for people?
[SPEAKER_11]: And we're just gonna have a brief meeting to discuss the guidelines and approve them.
[SPEAKER_11]: A brief meeting, yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Does that make sense?
[SPEAKER_01]: You can try, let's try for it.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, right, I think that's it.
[SPEAKER_11]: Does anybody else have anything else you wanna bring up before we talk again on the 23rd?
[SPEAKER_05]: I'll ask a question on the 23rd.
[SPEAKER_11]: What time so I can set it aside 6 o'clock 6 o'clock 6 o'clock for people.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, so let's meet briefly on the 23rd to discuss to finalize the design guidelines because I think Sharon is correct that that this is an important part of outreach.
[SPEAKER_11]: And please, everyone, please, please, please do review them.
[SPEAKER_11]: Please make any changes you think.
[SPEAKER_11]: Please don't wait to the meeting to propose your changes, just send them to the group.
[SPEAKER_11]: And, you know, we will just hammer out what it's gonna be and that will definitely help our outreach process.
[SPEAKER_06]: It did make sense to put that up on a Google Doc too so it's easy for everyone, because if you're just doing in a Word document I make my comments and someone else makes their comments at the same time.
[SPEAKER_11]: I know I agree, I agree 100% have we figured out what the case are there Fred.
[SPEAKER_10]: Melanie, I just put the Google Doc password in there.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'll send everyone a shared document.
[SPEAKER_10]: Fred, I'll put your document in there as well.
[SPEAKER_10]: So most of the Form Bs are in there.
[SPEAKER_10]: There's a ton of information in there.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's all kind of random.
[SPEAKER_11]: Can you just put a specific, just for those of us who are technologically challenged, can you just put a specific link to the specific document that we want to be editing?
[SPEAKER_10]: I'll do that, Fred.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'll do that.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's not Fred's document that he put in the email.
[SPEAKER_11]: And it will be shared.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: That was great.
[SPEAKER_11]: I think we're set.
[SPEAKER_11]: I think we have our place full.
[SPEAKER_11]: Does anybody else have anything else they want to discuss?
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Can I have a motion to adjourn?
[SPEAKER_09]: Motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Charlotte.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Fred.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Melanie.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Joe.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: And Chris Donovan.
[SPEAKER_09]: Motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: And I vote yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: So we are adjourned.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you, everybody.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'll talk to you guys in a couple of weeks.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you, Chris.
[SPEAKER_10]: All right.
[SPEAKER_07]: Bye.
[SPEAKER_11]: All right.
[SPEAKER_11]: Bye now.