Okay, well, let's get going and this will be quite brief.
Okay.
So basically, the revised application, so I'm not sure I filled everyone in on the details here, but when we submitted the application last time for the South Street Historic District,
They didn't just ask for a few corrections or additions.
They actually rejected the application, which surprised me and Chris Kelly.
But anyway, we have to pick up the shattered pieces.
We revised the application and Chris just submitted it today.
And I will send everyone a copy of that.
So given that we can't hold the public hearing in September as we had previously thought we could, but we can still hold it at our regular meeting in October.
And our regular meeting happens to fall on October 12th.
Charlotte, can you make it to a meeting on October 12th, our regular October meeting?
We can't hear you, Charlotte.
Hey, Charlotte.
Can you, Charlotte, can you make it to our regular October meeting?
All right, well, I'm going to assume.
OK.
Ah.
Yeah, so I would like to have the public hearing at the time of our regular October meeting, October 12th at 6 p.m.
Can you make it, Charlotte?
Well, we can't hear you again.
Anyhow, can you make it, Melanie?
Yeah, I don't have any.
I don't see anything on my calendar as of now.
So as of now, I can make it.
Great.
It'll be good to have as many commission members there as possible.
Is there a reason?
So you're saying it's going to take too long to have something at the next September meeting, is what you're saying?
No, there's a 60 day requirement.
Oh, it's a 60 day.
OK, thank you.
OK.
Yeah.
So the fact that they rejected it and then we cut it too close last time.
In fact, we're cutting it pretty close this time, but so hopefully they will accept it.
means that we couldn't do the hearing in September, and we're going to do it in October instead.
Got it.
The earliest possible time where we can do a presentation for the city council is probably mid-November.
Chris?
Yes, your Charlotte.
Can you hear me now?
Yes, I can.
Okay.
Great.
Can you make it to the regular October meeting?
October 12th.
Yes.
Correct?
Correct, yes.
Yes, I can make it to that meeting.
Okay, good.
We're actually going to be holding the public hearing then for South.
Okay.
And the meeting will be a live meeting at the main city council chamber upstairs at City Hall.
At what time, six o'clock?
Six o'clock.
Okay.
However, we will be meeting in September.
At that time, we need to approve versions of the trifold, which I'm hoping that Melanie and Fred will be able to punch up.
uh, so that it's appropriate for sending out not only to residents, but also to anyone lives who lives within a few hundred yards or say a hundred yards of any house in the district.
Um, and I will write a letter, a carefully worded letter.
Uh, and maybe you can help me with that too, Melanie.
Um,
Again, the goal is marketing, not just informing them of a public hearing.
Yeah.
Going back to the trifle for one second.
I think I had done a lot of copy and it was cut back because it had to be cut back because of the front and back.
I wonder if that revision is somewhere because that would be a good place to start.
Absolutely.
I save everything.
for it.
So I'm sure I can, I can, I'm sure I can fight it.
Um, yeah, so we're gonna punch up the, the trifold.
We're going to draft a detailed letter and, um, and those, uh, uh, uh, I'm hoping that, that that Melanie and Fred can have, uh,
the trifle ready, say, in a couple of weeks.
And I will have the letter ready in a couple of weeks.
And then we can approve it at our regular September meeting and then mail it out immediately to residents and owners of the district and to anyone who lives within 300 feet.
That sounds like a reasonable plan.
Yeah, just so you know, I will not be here.
When's the September meeting?
Let me see.
Just a minute.
Our September meeting is September 14th.
Okay, I will be out of the country that week.
Oh, okay.
Just so you know.
the meeting the week before?
Well, that's in August.
And I don't think- No, no, no.
The week before is September 7th.
Oh.
I will be here September 7th if people want to move it to that time.
That works for me.
If you're looking for a quorum, otherwise,
I trust you guys to make the right decision if you still want to have it on the 14th, okay?
Okay, sure.
Yeah, let's just bear that in mind as a possibility.
Okay, so that's it for- Chris, do you want to move it to the 7th?
We are considering moving it to the 7th.
Could you do that?
Yes, I can do that.
Okay, that's just for a regular Zoom meeting.
Right.
Okay.
There's a second matter that I was hoping to have a quorum for, but I think needs to be addressed right now, which is that Chris Donovan has not been doing the job of secretary.
We need to do something.
I think the best thing is to
ask the mayor for an executive secretary.
We've discussed this in the past.
A lot of towns have executive secretaries and it's basically a member of city hall staff who attends the meetings, prepares the minutes and posts them.
and generally speaking handles the paperwork for the commission.
Does that seem appropriate in this circumstance?
I think you're looking in the right direction, Chris.
Okay, great.
What do you think, Melanie?
Yeah.
I mean, these meetings are usually pretty short.
I don't, I think it's a, it's not what I would consider a really heavy lift for someone in the staff.
So, I mean, they, they don't, they don't tend to go over.
They rarely go over 30 minutes to an hour, you know?
So I think that's, yeah.
Okay.
Good.
All right.
Well, uh, I will talk to Alicia Hunt about it.
She's the head of the office of community development and, um,
We've already talked briefly about this to the mayor, so I think that will not be a problem.
That's all I have.
Anybody have any, Charlotte, Melanie, do you have any other business?
No, I do not.
Okay, great.
Well, let's adjourn then.
And thank you both for attending.
All right, well, thanks, Chris.
Our next meeting, Chris, will be the 7th of September, correct?
Yes, that's right.
Okay.
All right.
Great.
Thanks.
Bye-bye now.
Bye.
Good night, Chris.
Good night, Charlotte.