The public meeting of the City of Medford Liquor License Commission for 11-20-24 will come to order. We do have an agenda to follow. There are no minutes from last month, so we're going to move right on to the first item on the agenda, which is event, and I see Brian here.
So, Brian, tell us a little bit about what's going on. Great. Actually, I have two applications, and one is a collaboration. Is this the collaboration with Cuisine and Locale, or is this the... Yes. Great. So... We can do yours first, the event, then one, and then Cuisine and Locale after, second. Great. Sure. So, let's see, Friday, December 6th, if I'm correct.
beer and board games. We basically, we do games here. We've done this before and basically we invite the community, local businesses, people to come to a free event and they can play games and the bar would be open for beer and wine. We did it, I think around, maybe around this time last year and it was really good. We set up a bunch of tables and yeah, it was just something for people to do and come out for. So we're actually doing,
3 gaming events that weekend, um, the, uh, the Saturday and Sunday, we will not be serving alcohol. Um, but we thought the Friday 1 would be good. Uh, the, the Friday and the Saturday and Sunday are video game. And so those don't really, um. It's not really an interest in it, so the Friday we would be interested in it for the beer and board games. Okay.
That sounds good. You always do a good job. I'm sure we've got the insurance on file. Do you have just like an annual insurance for this? We do, but I usually pull a one day additional liquor liability on it. So once we get the application, I usually just send it over. Yeah, if you can send that over to Daria, that'd be great.
Okay, and we know where you always serve your alcohol. It's always the same, so same layout. Allen, do you have any questions for Brian? No. No, Mr. Chairman. I was going to say the same thing. I remember this event last year, and Brian has the insurance on record in the diagram, so we're good. I'm comfortable with this. I don't have any questions for Brian. Great.
And I'm here for most, pretty much 90% of any event that we do that has alcohol, so. I'll take it any chance. I know it's in good hands at that point. Okay, you want to make a motion? Yeah, I'll make a motion. I motion to approve the one-day license for Event Dam to be held on December 6th from 7 to 10 p.m.
All righty, and I'll second that motion. All those in favor? Aye. Aye. All those opposed? Hearing and seeing none, the ayes have it. You're all set with that one, Brian. Great, thank you. You're welcome. Yeah. Let's go to the next. That's for... Jean. JJ Gonson. Yep. Correct. We do collaborations with JJ. She,
She owns, she has, what am I trying to say? A catering business, also does production. She used to own one, so she still does, which is in Somerville. Yeah, she knows some great artists, and we've done collaborations with her in the past. This is actually the same artist we had, I think it was back in May. And basically, she's a singer-songwriter, piano player, almost like,
I want to say like dueling piano style, but I don't know what to call it because there's no other piano player. But, uh, yeah, just a real heartwarming, uh, event, like tells like, it's like a storytelling thing. It's really great. It's one of my favorites that we've ever done here. And so he'll be returning, um, in December for a more holiday themed event. Um, and yeah, that was actually one of our.
the best sales night for, for, for beer and wine that we've had here. Um, again, we're not like, no, because we were over serving anybody or anything, but just this, you know, it's just, it's just applied to the crowd. So it was, uh, it was great. It looks like you have a good size crowd to 30 to 50, which is, yeah. Yeah. Again, you never know at that time of year. Um, I'd rather play it safe. Sure. Uh, but you know, I mean, people have conflicts that time of year. So absolutely.
Brian, I think I heard you say this, but will you be attending this event on December 14th? I'll be here as well. You'll be there also. Okay. Honestly, because I typically, again, try to be here for any event that we have alcohol for. Yeah. Okay. But honestly, I want to be at this one. I feel like it's a great event. I think so. Yeah.
Yeah, and I see the Mr chairman, I see the insurance that I can see a million dollars and then a 2 million dollar aggregate. So the insurance is in place and it's current. So, and we know the layout, so I don't have any other questions other than good luck. You know, very good. Very good. Yeah.
Okay, Al. Yeah, I motion to approve the one-day license for the event to be held on December 14th for cuisine and locale for J.J. Gonson and event them. Okay, very good. I second that motion. All those in favor? Aye. Aye. All those opposed? Absolutely none. The ayes have it. Motion passes.
Good to go, Brian. Very good. Brian, good to see you. Happy holidays. You too. Everybody have a safe holiday. Bye now. Happy events. Have a good Thanksgiving. Bye now. You too. Okay. Next on the agenda, do we have a representative from NN Liquor Co-op, DBA Main Street Liquor?
That's you, the one raising your hand. You gotta take your thing off of mute. Yeah, off of mute and the camera, I see more sailing than you. Okay, I got it. You got it. There you go. Okay, yeah. How you doing? Would you be able to just state your name and the address of your business for the record, please?
Yeah, my name is Kusum Latha. It's 395 Main Street, Laker. OK. Yeah, we just want to change the hours there. OK. It was 8 to 11, and we want to do like 10 to 10, like 10 AM to 10 PM. OK. And that would be for, OK, and that's for seven days a week? Seven days a week, yeah.
Okay, same hours. Same hour. Okay. And, um. Let me just take a look at the paperwork that was submitted. I know you sent that over.
I see that you have the corporate vote, which is completed and fine. You have a letter stating to this commission that you're looking to change the hours for exactly what you said. The only thing that you're missing here is
Let's see. It's a no fee transmittal form. Gary, I can, I don't know if you've got one handy, but I can send one over to you. If not, can you be able to send it over to her?
I can send it over to her, yeah. Yeah, you've got one? I'm looking on the website now. Okay, I'll send one over to you. I have it on my desktop. Actually, I can probably do it right now if we want to wait a second. Okay. Let's see. Okay. Yeah, that has to be filled out and
No fee. There's no fee for it. It's just got to go over to the ABCC with the paperwork. Let me clear that. Add the attachment. So Chairman, were you thinking of tabling that or moving forward with that subject to the completion of that form?
Yeah, I think we can move forward with it. I don't think it's a big deal. Yeah. You know, because it's we've got the letter. It's all pretty much set up. If she could just get it over to Daria as soon as possible, you know, and I'd say Daria.
I'm sorry, Mr chairman and Derek, can you let us know when the completed form arrives? So we know. Uh, consumer fulfilled that that request. Yep, because I'm just going to make a. A conditional approval on that or. You know, it'll be subject to the completion of that form.
Bobby, you're on mute. I know, I just saw it over there. Okay, yeah, that'll be good. That way they can get on with their new hours and stuff and we won't be holding them up. But if you can, get it over to Daria as soon as possible, hopefully by the end of the week, and you'll be all good to go, okay? Okay.
Alan, you want to make a motion? Please. I motion to accept and approve the application for change of hours for Main Street Liquor Mart subject to the completion of the no fee transmittal form. I'm hoping that'll be done immediately within 24, 48 hours so you can get that off your desk and Daria can take care of the package and we can get moving with ABCCs.
Information. Okay, that'd be great. I will 2nd that motion. All those in favor. Hi. All those opposed hearing and seeing none. The eyes have it. You are all set. Just get that over the area as soon as you can. Okay. Okay. All right. Nice holidays. Thank you. Thanks. Bye. Bye. Bye. Bye. Bye.
Okay, let's see. Next on the agenda, we have, do we have a representative from 116 Riverside Catering, which is, what's that, the Hyatt? Yeah, we did it last month. I don't know why I have to, that's all. I kind of saw that on there and I'm saying,
But I, yeah, I'm like, did they fire him already, or did he quit already? Yeah. Okay. Oh, I wasn't here last month. No wonder why I don't remember it. I was away, right? Yeah. Yeah, you were, you were, yeah. You were away, yeah. That's, okay. Oh boy. Sorry about that. No, you're fine. Let's see. I'm gonna just X that one out.
Okay, do we the same thing go for the ocean state job? I don't think I don't see anybody on here, but I did email them. Okay. And they said that somebody was going to come. So I don't know. Okay, well, maybe after. Yeah, maybe they'll catch up at the end. Yeah. Yeah, we can after we after we talk to Peter, if they're on, we can we can take them on.
Okay, Peter, I know you're the representative for Desisto Enterprises. You're doing a change of category application for your location on 313 Mystic Ave, Medford. Yep. Do you want to just kind of give us a little description about what's going on, where you're going to be serving the liquor, where the bar's going to be set up, is it all going to basically be the same, you know?
Yeah, it's pretty much all going to stay the same. We're just adding a little bit of liquor to the function room bar. In the future or not, if I'm going to do anything in the restaurant, the actual restaurant, I might do a small menu and just run out of the function room possibly. Mostly for the function room because we get a lot of
The clients that come in, they'd want something more than beer and wine. So, it's like we find that it's kind of, yeah, it's a little bit of a struggle sometimes. I even have people like back out because they're realizing that the full lick is not in play. So, they just try to... So, it's kind of costing us a little bit right now. So, I mean, again, like a small menu, just something to offer and, you know.
Now, I've been to a couple of functions there, and it's a good size room. Do you know what the seating capacity is in it? I think we hold 100. Okay. Licensed for 100 at the time, but we never really get a crowd that big, to be honest with you. Okay, so you're over the 60. 70, 75 is probably the biggest that come, yeah. Okay, cool. And now, is there going to be...
liquor available in the other part of the restaurant as well. Do you have that now? That's what I was just saying. If we do a small menu, I'll just run it out of the service bar in the function room. Yeah. Okay. Yeah. If that's okay. If that's okay. I mean, if somebody wants a beer, for instance, like say I come in and I get a, I don't know, a pizza or a sub or something, and I have a cold beer with it, is it the norm for you to take the beer from the function room into the- A lot of times.
A lot of times we do, but we do have a small stock in the restaurant as well. The only thing I was trying to get at is that the pizza, let's call it pizza restaurant section of your restaurant, is on the original plans of where alcohol could be stored and served, correct?
Yes. Yes. You originally opened. Okay. That's all I wanted to find out, uh, just to make sure that you weren't bringing the alcohol into a place that wasn't already, um, set up for us bringing alcohol in. So if you're doing that already, it's, I'm sure it's on the original plan. So Alan, I was on, uh, then I, I'm not sure whether you remember. I do. I do. It is on the original. I think Guy was on back then. Yeah.
I remember all of that. Yeah, it's fine. He can do it. Yeah. Okay, good. Good. I saw everything. I looked at all the papers. Everything seems to be in order. Did you do this yourself or does the lawyer do it?
I did it. Wow. Wow. You got to go into business here because you hit the nail on the head with everything. Let me tell you, compared to the City of Somerville, you guys are like...
Well, you know, you go on the ABCC website, it's very easy to follow. All you do is just point and click. It really is not. It's not difficult to navigate. No, it's wonderful. And it'd be wonderful if everybody was thorough. Yeah, it's organized and efficient. Absolutely.
Yes, so I just want to congratulate you on that. Alan, do you have anything? No, no, no. I went through the package. I see the certificate of good standing, the tax compliance. Yeah, no, this is great. This is great. That's awesome. Yeah. Yeah, no, I went through it a number of times, and everything seems to be fine. So I'm good with it.
Let me make a motion to accept and move forward, approve and move forward with the change of category application for Desisto Enterprises. Okay, and I'll second that motion. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Hearing and seeing none, the ayes have it.
Congratulations, Peter. You guys are awesome. Thank you very much, everybody. Have a happy Thanksgiving to all of you. Thank you. Peter, I know Rotary will be happy when we have our scholarship night. There you go. And take this young lady out for doing a good job. Thank you. I like you. Maybe Avelinos. No, not Avelinos. Go someplace a little fancier. Thank you so much. All right. Happy holidays. Happy holidays. Thanks again. Bye-bye.
Okay, let's see. I think that clears us up, correct? Yeah. Yes. Okay. With 116 Riverside, I just found a couple of things, but I mean, if it's already been pushed through and stuff. Yeah, well, we approved it.
Okay, I mean, it's if it comes back from the ABCC, we'll get in touch with him and I saw that the vote of the entity board was missing. Um, yeah, that that was supposed to be part of it. And, um, Harold, you're willing to send the whole page. Yeah. Yeah, it wasn't even on it. Um, I see 116 Riverside.
You had the change of manager amendment, which is the transmittal form. And then you had the amendment change of manager.
which gave the business information, Harold Jones, blah, blah, blah. And he said, resume attached. But he was- And there's nothing attached. Yeah, he was supposed to sign it, not Susan, whatever her name is, I can't read it. But she signed it instead of him. You talking about this function's middle stage or no? No, first page. Nevermind.
Yeah, that's the payment for it, the one you just showed me. But the first page is the- This one? It's the monetary transmittal, yep. It's that one there. Yeah, it's on here. I wonder if it's scanned in. Well, they got that. Then the next page was the change of manager.
The amendment and it said the address and the person that's in charge of the licenses and permits is Sean Nault. And then the proposed manager name is Harold Jones and gives his information, email, all that good stuff.
And then it says resume attached. And then it says at the bottom of that page, I hereby swear under the pains and penalties of perjury that the information I have provided in this application is true and correct. And it's signed, it says manager's signature, which is supposed to be him, not Susan. Oh, yeah, I see that.
Then she did the applicant statement, Susan Schultz, she signed it. She signed again, yep. You do all of that stuff, that was correct. But then she, then the query was fine. And then, I don't know where they got this page, it says number 12, manager application. It's basically got the same information on it.
that the one that he didn't sign has, only this one he signed. I think they took it out of a new application or something. That would make sense now that you say that. It kind of like cut and paste it, I think. Yeah.
So I, you know, I just, it's not a big deal. I'm just letting you know in case the ABCC kicks it back. Well, they will kick it back to them. So yeah, we'll have them corrected. Yeah. I mean, it was fine.
I wonder if they realized they made a mistake, and that's why they did that page again and had Mr. Jones sign it. He could have. He could have. I wonder. Yeah. I was just going to suggest that if they were here today, because I didn't know what went on last month. I wasn't here, but if they were scheduled to be here today, I was just going to tell them to just correct the papers and send the whole packet out to Daria.
instead of just the one page, because I know it's a pain for Daria to try and rescan everything and take stuff out of a PDF that's got five, six pages. It's craziness. So when we have people correct stuff, I'm going to start telling them, send the whole package corrected. Do you usually get them on a PDF, Daria, with all the things on one page? Or do they just mail them to you?
Sometimes it really depends. Some people are very top-notch, get everything together for me. Yeah.
once everything is ready. Some give me pieces by pieces and that's where it becomes a pain in the butt because then I don't, I just don't have time to. Yeah. So they don't drop, they don't come to City Hall and drop off? Sometimes they do. It depends. Some of them do. And some of them just scan it in and send the whole PDF? Yeah, most of them do send me the original and I'll ask, I will tell them, can you send me the original please? But they will also send me the emailed version. Okay.
Yeah, that'll be good. Just so you don't have to go crazy if you got to do any corrections and if they got to do any corrections and stuff. Yes, so I was going to email Ocean State job lot.
And I said, hello, no one appear in front of the Liquor License Commission for a change in manager application today. The application will be tabled. Should I tell them the next meeting, special meeting, or should we just have them come for December? Come for December. That's fine. Just to change a manager. I mean, it's not a big deal. Because I confirmed twice. I emailed, I followed up because nobody responded to me.
I just want to make sure that they received it and then they applied and said that Ralph Kimber, which I think is the proposed manager, will be in attendance. Yeah. But that was November 6th. We can push that to December. I think that's fine. I think our special meeting is going to be long.
And I spoke with Ralph today because I had a couple of questions.
He said, they notify, he says, you folks notified them that there are four different incidents, four different violations. I says, I'm not sure how we notified them, to be honest with you. I know we notified them to appear. And he says, yeah, he says, you gotta notify them that they have to appear for four separate violations.
He says, each one of them, you're going to read individually. When you read them individually, at that point, if you want to set what they're going to have to have for a violation punishment, you got to do it for each one.
And he kind of explained to me basically the way that it works and how we progress every violation, the next violation. He explained to me how it should progress. He also said before we send out the notification that we're going to be
hearing all four violations at the same day, we've got to put times in. If it's noon, first violation, 12 o'clock. Second violation, 12.15. Third violation, 12.45. Fourth violation, 1 o'clock.
And it got to be hand-delivered by Rory to make sure he gets it. He said, also, you want to run it by KP law to make sure we get the right language in there in case it needs to be polished up a little. I told him about the signage for the window.
And he said just, he says, that's beautiful, that's good, you wanna do that, he said, but run that by KP Law too in case it needs to be polished a little bit. And what was, just remind me, what was the signage? The signage in the window is just basically telling them that, telling the public. Consumer, yeah. It's gotta be displayed eye level,
on the inside of the glass so people can read it from outside. I can basically read it without the name. Name of the business is prohibited from selling any products containing alcohol per order of the Method License Commission.
from such-and-such-a-date to such-and-such-a-date due to liquor license suspension for violation of Mass General Law, Chapter 138, Section 34, sale, delivery, or furnishing of alcoholic beverages to persons under 21 years of age. And then in small letters down the bottom, I put, the store may resume normal hours of operation on December 1st. I shouldn't, such-and-such-a-date.
He also advised me on how we should, you know, we can have the hearings and after each violation hearing, we can set the, not the fine, the punishment for it. And
Once that's done, we get into the next one and then we set.
the punishment for that one. And we get another one. And that way, it progresses. Because it's, as you can see in our things, it goes in steps. First violation, you know, warning, second violation, one day suspension. And these are all major. They're not, they're all major. So it sounds like what you're saying is that we have to treat each infraction individually. That is correct. Okay. And so we,
We know what occurred, and we hear their side of the argument, and then we ask questions, and then we come to some resolution with that one, and then we go to the next one. Do we give each one
20 minutes, 30 minutes, because you had mentioned there has to be a timeframe on the agenda. Yeah, I mean, that's what Ralph said. He was saying, yeah, the first one could be 12, then 1230, then Monday. But I don't think we need a half hour for each one. No, no. Some might be quick. Some might be longer. Yeah.
You can do them 10 minutes apart if you want. If it goes a little longer, it goes a little longer. It's not a big deal. It's just kind of like a
a couple of little tweaks that he wanted, which were good. I'm glad I gave him a call because the reason why I called him was because of the incident with the porch that we're having. I don't know if you are aware of it, Alan, but the new owners that are going to be going into the porch,
can't get in because the porch never surrendered their license. The license, I'd heard that, yes. So there's options. Ralph gave me two, three different options. Can't they wait for the end of the year till it expires? That is the best option for them. Only he says, if it's extreme and they really want to get in there any, well, not any earlier,
but they can withdraw their application. So now they're not applying for a Section 12 license, so they can get a one-day license to have in there, and because they already have the lease secured. But he says the bad thing about that is, is if
Um, he says they're going to have to re-advertise to all the abutters when they reapply. They won't have to pay the $200 fee again, but they're going to have to re-advertise. They're going to have to put it in the paper. And I'm saying, that's going to take them longer than just waiting. He says, yeah, he says you only got another 10 days in the license. It's not going to be renewed. You know, the only thing that could,
mess that up is if they try and renew the license, the porch. And at that point, they probably wouldn't have all the required documents because of the circumstances. So, I mean, it's
He says, and he said the other thing, too, is there was one other thing, and I forgot what it was. I wrote it down, but I made so many notes. You're right. I think letting it expire makes the most sense. I don't like the one-day license because we don't allow any entity more than 30 one-day licenses. Right.
No, we'd only give them one day. Right, but wouldn't he want a one day for the remainder of the year for each day to stay open? Just one day? One day for this party. It must be an important party. It's done. But remember, it's done, Bobby. It was like the 16th or something like that. Oh, it's already over? Yeah. OK. I don't know what they did, but I don't know that. Yeah.
So, yeah, it's passed. The quickest way to get it through is just to let the license lapse. And at that point, the ABCC can move forward on it. And that's really about, you know, the easiest and the best way to do it. It's only going to tie them up a month. That's not the deal. And other than that,
What else was there? I think that was. Yeah, I think that was it. Could Bobby, can I ask you a Daria? I. I, I'm going crazy trying to find.
the email link with the control compliance checks that had the liquor store in question for Tuesday's special hearing, can that be sent to me so I can read the police reports with that? I just can't find that one. Because I know that was in Fraction 1. That was the minor one. Yeah. Which one are you asking for? The one that we just got last week?
No, wasn't there one before where we put them on? Oh, from... Was that June? Yeah, was that June that there was a police report on that? Yeah, that's when they were doing the compliance checks. Yeah. Yeah, I got that.
I'll send it to you, Alan, because I'm looking at it. So I just want the one, because I wanted to read that one, because it's the same owner, same manager. Yes. And that same manager did get TIP certified. OK. Those are some questions I had, because Daria sent me the copies of the TIP certification I asked for. So I wanted to make sure it was. Yeah.
I just wanted to refresh my memory with all of that. I remember how we handled it. But again, I wanted to read the police report on that particular package store. Yeah. It wasn't too impressive. No. The first time around in June. No.
what kind of ticks me off, and I'm sure it ticks you off. And I mean, the city itself, it shouldn't be having to deal with this. The city doesn't want this type of behavior. This place is known to the miners in the city that this is where you go to buy your booze. It's got to stop. It has to stop. That's right. So that's why we want to be prepared.
That, you know, we're going to have to be prepared if he comes with a lawyer and be prepared and, you know, what the lawyer may ask for and, you know, we got to be able to.
uh, be able to stand strong on certain things. So, um, you know, like I said, I, I gotta, I get a lot of good information today. Um, I didn't know if I was going to make the meeting. Yeah, I've been on the phone so long. He just got back from Aruba and it was kind of like, okay. And, you know, and I, I just called him like a half hour before the meeting. So it was,
He gave me a lot of information. I try to cram down on a couple of pieces of paper, but yeah, so that's where we are with it. What I can do is, you know, I'll probably, when's a good time for me to touch base with you, Dara? Are you going to be there today, tonight? Yeah, so. Or tomorrow, better? No, no, today's fine.
I'm just trying to think this through. So for the violations, we have to do a letter, right, that should go to him too? Just the agenda. Just an agenda. We have to break down the violations. I was going to reach out to Lieutenant Lockowitz and see if he actually sent them anything with the violation. Lieutenant Lockowitz?
What's that? You said Lieutenant Lockovitz? Yeah. No, because I remember you said it just had to be mailed. OK.
No, but I mean his police reports that he sent them to the, uh, you know what I mean? Yeah. And what we have to do is the, I guess, I don't know what to call it, a summons that we're sending him. Um, we did that. We just corrected. Um, we're going to have to redo that stating, um, the four violations and, um, four separate hearings on that day and the times of each hearing.
and we'll do the hearing and then go to the next hearing. We can do the hearing, discuss it, make a decision on it, set the penalty, and then go to the next hearing. That's the way Ralph suggested to do it. He says either that or
He says, even, you know, you're going to correct it anyways, he says, because, you know, you know, you got it that they're coming in, you can only kind of really do one at a time if you don't specify that you're doing all, you know, all four hearings, they're separate hearings, one for each violation. So, and he, I believe with that one too, he said, you might want to,
just run that by KP law to make sure that the wording is okay. Ask if he sent that license a copy of the charges and hand deliver the new notice of the hearings, hand deliver the new notice
of the four scheduled hearings all the same day. So we've got to have Rory handle it. Along with the police report? We've got to ask Rory. I believe he said they've got to be notified on what the charges are. I thought he said. So why he's appearing before the commission.
So it could be you're appearing before this commission because of violation number one, November 1st, such and such, so many hours for violation of Mass General Law 138, section 34. Violation number two is going to be at 1215 for violation number one,
violation of Chapter 138, Section 34. 1230 is going to be a hearing on violation of Chapter 138, Section 34. I don't know if that's good enough.
I think Rory can kind of give us, I'm going to reach out to Rory anyways just to see what he thinks, the way to handle it. Maybe if he's a little sketchy on it, he might be able to run it by KP law just to make sure the language is good or whatever. Are they aware that there's two a pair before us on the 26th? Do they know that? Yeah. Yeah. Good. Okay.
Yeah, I mean, that's kind of where we are with it. Are those other people coming to the meeting? Are they going to be hybrid? That's why I didn't want to issue the thing.
Yeah, okay. Yeah, we can knock them out of the way. Yeah, that's okay. I'm putting them first anyways, and then getting them done. And then why don't we schedule the, uh, the meetings 15 minutes apart starting at 1215. Okay. And we can take care of business the 1st, 15 minutes, get them out of them, get them out of there. And then we can conduct the well, because remember, one of them is a.
Transfer so that one might be longer than 15 minutes. Okay, if you include. License transfer license, and then the 3, 1 day licenses. Okay, the 1 day license is a quick, but I don't know how long to transfer. You know, I mean, we can do like, 1220. Yeah, 1220 minutes is pretty much the paperwork all in order for the transfer.
Yeah, yeah, it's all set. I'm going to send it to you guys today so you guys have it for... Okay. And if I see anything or you see anything in it, Alan, that might need correcting, we'll just shoot Daria a quick email. She can reach out to them, get it corrected before the actual meeting. So once the meeting comes, we'll have everything in order. We can just kind of
Push it through if it's all good, you know. And of course, add Ben to the email string also. Yeah, I always add, I try to add you guys all together, unless I know you're not going to be there. So for the establishment,
Bobby, I forwarded you the email from the attorney. Okay. I don't know if you saw that or not. I don't think I did. Attorney Began, you might have not because he emailed me. Did you just do that? No, I sent it 1154.
Yeah, I don't know. I might not have read that 1 already. Yeah, but he's basically asking if there's an any update on our end. Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. That's the 1 you're going to send it run it by KP.
Yeah, do you want me to run it by KPLR if there's anything else we can do or just... I kind of mentioned that to Ralph and he says, what do you want to do that for? He says, he's going to charge you for what I just told you for free. Yeah.
Well, I just want to make sure that like, I just want to make sure we're good because obviously. No, Ralph Ralph put a pretty clear that as long as their license has not been surrendered for that property.
whether he has a lease or not. There's nothing we can do. No. Okay. So until the license expires, they're knowing it. And at that point, January 1st, they're good to go. I'm sure we can, what was his name? The ABCC inspector. We can send him.
What was it? Sean Walsh? Yeah, you can send Sean probably just an email for us to December. He said, so I asked him, I did ask him about that and he said that we actually have to vote on it. So in December when we vote on it.
is when I will notify that they didn't sign or whatever. It has to be voted on by the commission. They asked him the same thing. He said, no, you got to wait till you vote. But he said they'll push it along anyways. We're going to vote on the same thing that we did, just the application all over again? Yeah, and all the renewals. Yeah.
on all the renewals because it's part of the renewal so if they don't sign it's not the application it's just the renewal for the porch if they're not signing then we'll have to vote on them not signing on it or renewing whatever not renewing okay we do that in december yes we do yeah because right now i don't have any of the right they're still coming in so that'll be december um our next meeting okay
Yeah, so I don't I don't mean to be kicking the horse, but.
So is the establishment, are they in there, in the premises at all? Is the license on the wall and just nobody has taken it off? Or has the whole place been stripped out? I have no idea, honestly. I don't know. From what I understood or assumed was that they're walking into a turnkey restaurant. Everything's there. They're just going in and starting to do business.
Yeah, that's what I thought, too, that it's just they able to go in there because there's nobody else in there. Right. But I don't know. Like the license, they'll be up on the wall or. Yeah, but I don't think we can just go in and take it. It's got to be surrendered by. Yeah. And by the license holder, is that is that the catch? OK. Yeah, that's what I mean. I drive down to the porch there and yank it off the wall and confiscate it. But we're out of the way. OK.
Ralph said, he says, you can't get in touch with the guy. I said, no, Daria's tried. She's got his phone number. She sent him emails. I says, the even second person in charge, she reached out to them. She had a number, but she just couldn't get nobody's responding. There's nothing you can do. He says, somebody of authority and that license has to surrender it, or just send you a letter stating that they're surrendering the license.
As long as it's in writing, he says, that's all you need. Yeah. It's something on record. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Unless, uh, unless we can get that, which it doesn't look like we're going to get, um, we got to go 30 days till the next meeting and vote on it. Like Daria said that, uh, you know, they did not renew their license and there's a license available now and yeah. Move forward. Um, okay.
Yeah, and I don't know, Deshawn said that, did he have, did the establishment have to come before us again, or no? No, no, no, no, no, no, no, he just said that. So just we get a vote. We'll just do the revision or whatever on top of the LLA local licensing authority certification form. Okay. They just receive it and push it through. Okay. So he said the only thing, I think the only issue is the fact that there's,
an active license, basically. Right. Until the end of the month, right? Yeah. Yeah. They don't expire until December 31st. Yeah. Okay. Yeah. Okay. So how are we going to know that? Oh, yeah. Because they didn't do it by November 30th. Okay. Yeah. They don't do it by November 30th. That's right. Then we know. Okay. That works.
Okay. Anything else? Do we end the meeting? I think that might be it on my end. I know, Bobby, when you maybe at some point, maybe five-ish or something, if you have availability, call me. Okay. Just let me know whenever.
Yeah, and I'll reach out to Rory in the meantime to see what, you know, get his input on it. Yeah, because I want to make sure that I get this letter done today then. Yeah, I'll get on with him shortly after I get off this call and we'll see if we can get that squared away. And yeah, I think that's the best way to go. Okay. Sounds good.
That's all I have. Alan, anyone else? Daria, no? No, I'm good. I'll motion to adjourn. It's 1.52 p.m. I second that motion. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Hearing and seeing none, motion's been accepted. That's what Jim used to say, you know, that's why I started saying that. Hearing and seeing none. Hearing and seeing none. I feel like Jim. I look like him with my little, you know,
Get on here and, you know, look back. Okay. All right. We'll see you guys have a great week.