Welcome to tonight's meeting of the method committee development board. I'll call the meeting to order. Let's begin with some obligatory procedural matters 1st.
This hearing of the Method Community Development Board is being conducted via remote means. No in-person attendance of members of the public will be permitted, but every effort will be made to ensure that the public can adequately access the procedures as provided for in Chapter 2 of the Acts of 2023. A reminder that anyone who would like to listen to or view this meeting while in progress may do so by accessing the link that was included on the meeting agenda posted on the City of Method's website. If despite our best efforts, we are not able to provide a real-time access,
We will post a recording of this meeting on the city's website as soon as possible. A reminder that given the remote nature of this meeting, tonight all votes from the board will be made by roll call. Please note that the project materials for all projects before the board can be viewed at the city's website, which is MedfordMA.org. And you can click on current city board filings, which you can find the link in the chat. I'm going to do roll call attendance. Sally Akiki.
Can you hear me? Present. Present? Yes. Thank you. Peter Kautz? Present. Sabrina Alpino? Present. And myself, Jackie McPherson. Danielle, can you introduce any city staff on the call? Flying solo tonight, just me, Danielle Evans, senior planner. Okay.
All right, well, the first item on agenda for this evening is 1416 Mystic Valley Parkway. It's a special permit for a detached ADU. This is a new public hearing, and I'll read the public hearing notice. The Memphis Community Development Board shall conduct a public hearing on August 7, 2024, after 6.30 p.m., remotely via Zoom, relative to an application submitted by Nancy Russa, for a special permit for a detached, essentially dwelling unit, ADU.
The applicant is seeking to legalize and renovate an existing ADU and an existing detached garage structure on the same lot at Lot J-01-9, 1416 Mystic Valley Parkway, Mayford Mass 02155, which requires a special permit for Chapter 94, Section 8.2.2, City of Mayford Zoning Ordinance. Danielle, can you please provide any introductory comments?
Um, yes, so, um, this, um, as the legal ad, uh, described, this is an existing, um, detached garage, um, has an existing, um, ADU or some kind of living space that's there. I think that predates their ownership.
And I believe that this came to our attention when they applied for a building permit to do some work in there, and then learned that they needed to actually have a special permit for this. So they are now here before us. And I'll turn it over to Ms. Woosa. I'll unmute you.
Great, yeah. So I have some pictures. I've just introduced my husband, Alex Moot. And my sister, Betsy Rosa, is on the call. She is, fortunately for me, an architect who has done a lot of work for us. So I have some pictures that I can share with you of the plans, the neighborhood, so on and so forth, if that would be helpful.
Yeah, I can make you a co-host so that you can host the stream. I think that's the only way to do it. Oh, yeah, I'm disabled. You should be able to do so now. OK. Yes, great. Now, how do I get to my? Give me a minute and I will get to the pictures. No, that's.
There you go. Yeah, there we go. So it's the ADU presentation right there. Right there. Perfect. OK. Is that shared? Can everyone see it? Oh, OK. To make it active. Oh, got it. OK. I'm glad you're here. OK.
Yay, there we go. So this is a picture of the property. It's this large red roof structure in the middle left-hand side of the picture. And on the right-hand side of that is the garage apartment dwelling unit. Yeah, that is. So we bought the property in October 1998 and have lived there very happily since.
Let me go on. How do I go to the next one? You scroll down. Okay. Oh, there we go. Great. It's the small red roof is the garage with the apartment above it. Then that's a picture just of the streets in the neighborhood and our lot is in obviously the yellow. This is a plot plan, again, the house and the two-story garage.
going down. So the house was built in 1910. At that time, it was common to have a detached garage, and we believe that the dwelling unit over the garage was probably used for a chauffeur or servant or something. This is the floor plan of the garage, the first floor. We've added new
hardwired smoke detectors and heat detectors and insulation, which were requirements from the building department, and they've approved that. So that's all done, I think.
Oh, back to the neighborhood too. I have reached out to all the abutters that the city provided a list of all the abutters within 400 feet. I've emailed with all of the 15 households that I knew. And then I sent hand-delivered letters to the 25 or so households that I don't know. I know that the immediate neighbors that I've spoken with are all in agreement with this, have no trouble with it.
Okay, so there's the garage again. And we have off-street parking for two cars in that garage, obviously. So this is the floor plan for the dwelling unit. You can see on the right-hand side of the picture are some existing stairs. So you go up those stairs to the main door, and then there's a little, you know, tiny kitchenette and bathroom and living space.
On the top of the picture, you can see that we've added a new door, which was, again, a building department requirement for a second egress in case of fire. So that new door is now in there as some pictures will make clear soon. So this is, again, just a picture from the street. We have taken away all that ivy, but that's the two-car garage and the unit above and the steps to the right. Keep going.
This is, again, just another view, the pictures, yeah, just the view from the whatever side that is. Keep going.
And this is a picture of the side facing our house. The picture above is the old view, and now the one below shows the new door with a new patio. Through this process, we've had a lot of interactions with the building department, and they've told us what we need to do, and I think we're in compliance with all of their regulations. That second egress was really the one thing that was very important to do.
Okay, so go on. And that's just the other side. Again, most of that ivy is gone, but it does grow pretty ferociously, so I won't promise it's going to stay gone. So we think that we've met all the requirements for an ADU, and we hope that you'll give us approval. Does anybody have any questions about any of this? Thank you, Ms. Rosa. I appreciate it.
I will open it up to the board for questions. One of the things for clarity that I want, Danielle, can you please just quickly go back to the, I didn't hear the second ingress as part of the requirements that have been met. What were the things that were in compliance already? So it's all brought up to meet building code and we did an analysis of all the conditions to meet
for detached accessory dwelling unit, it meets the size thresholds. It's already a building that's in existence. The only condition or criterion that you all need to cite upon is there's language in the ADU ordinance that says, let me see where my phone is.
Okay, so it's criterion number seven, which is that there should be sufficient and appropriate space for no more than one additional parking space when necessary and feasible. It shall be accommodated on site by the owner to serve the accessory dwelling unit. So there is not an additional parking space being added. It's preexisting. So, I mean,
There's some discretion that your board has on whether you think an additional space is necessary, or if it's feasible, there are some topography challenges on the Sagamore side. So I don't know what the parking pressures are on that street. As staff, we generally don't want additional parking spaces if we don't need them.
but ultimately I defer to this board to make that decision whether you think that criterion is satisfied. How many parking spaces are included as of right now? There's two in the garage. There's no surface parking on
We do have a little bit of space. I mean, if you go back to the basic street plan, the garage unit is right on the street. But there is a little bit of a setback that's wide enough for a car there. So when we have to clear the street for street cleaning, we can fit a car there. I tend to park there all the time. We've never parked our cars in the garage.
So where do you park on? On the street. There's a lot of parking available. Yeah, for really the entire our side of Sagamorav from the garage north to our neighbor's house. There are, there's never any other cars there. So, we could probably fit 10 cars along the street there if you wanted to. I'm not, I'm not sure exactly where our property line ends on this map, but we just always parked in the street.
But there are two parking spaces in the garage. Yeah, within the garage. And so the requirement for a single family is two spaces. So you're conforming for the single family use. And it's the AD ordinance that says that an additional space should be provided, but if it's necessary or feasible.
Based on topography, it's not feasible. It'd be more of a hardship than anything at this point for adding the unnecessary parking. Yeah. I think based on what they've said about that surface space that may not be a formal parking space but functions as one, then that would theoretically satisfy the condition anyway of an additional parking space as part of the AD ordinance. I think that shouldn't be a problem.
Yeah, I definitely agree and with that, I'm going to open it up if if the board has any questions for the questions. I don't think so. I think figure that out and that's. That should be that satisfies the parking questions. Yeah. And I think that's the only thing that we were really weighing on if it meets all other building codes, I'm actually going to.
ask for a motion to approve the special permit for 1416 Mystic Valley Parkways ADU. So moved. Second. I, Sally, second. I'm going to do roll call. Sally Akiki? Yes. Peter Klaus? Yes. Sabrina Alpino? Yes.
and myself, Jackie McPherson. Actually, I have to back up a little bit. I jumped the gun, and this is a public hearing, so I am going to open it up in case there's any public comments. Although we voted ahead, I do have to give the public a chance to speak. So I'm going to go back and open up the public comment period, and those who wish to provide comments can use the raise hand feature or message Danielle in the comments.
You can also send an email to OCD at MedRate-MA.gov. Before providing your comments, please state your name and address for the record. A reminder to all meeting participants to please refrain from using the chat function to provide comments as it is not part of the public record. However, if a participant is having audio or other technical difficulties, this may be entered into the chat to alert myself or staff.
Danielle, can you please manage the public comment queue and read any previously sent emails or letters that you may have received? Madam Chair, I don't see anyone in the participant list with their hand raised. I'll also add because it's a public hearing, we did mail out notices to the abutters. So everyone received that legal notice.
Seeing no public comment and hearing that there has not been anything received, I'm going to close the public comment period for this meeting, and I'm going to revert back to the original vote with Peter Kalbs making the first motion and Sally Akiki seconded. I will do the roll call to make it complete. Sally Akiki. Aye. Peter Kalbs. Aye. Sabrina Alpino. Aye.
And myself, Jackie McPherson. Thank you, Mr. and Mrs. Russo. You're all set. Thank you so much. I really appreciate it. I appreciate your time and thank you guys for doing what you do. Yeah. Thank you. Have a great evening. Thanks. Bye-bye. Bye-bye. Our second agenda item is approval not required for 98 to 100 Magoon Ave.
I have, I'm sorry, I do not have the applicant's name readily available. Oh, yeah, because it's not a public hearing. I don't have that in there. Apologies. Leave it Angelo, correct? Yes. I have to pull up the application. Mr. Angel, Angel is your last, your surname?
No, first name is Angelo, last name is Sterianos. Mr. Sterianos, thank you for being here with us this evening. I'm going to have the city lead us and give us a brief discussion, a brief overview, and then we'll have you introduce yourself and the project, okay? Yes. Yes, so we received this application for an approval not required. Basically, that means that
as part of the subdivision control law, if it meets the frontage requirements, and if it meets the other standards, which are, if both lots will front on a right of way, and if they, yeah, minimum frontage, and is there vital access to the lots? So if it meets those, then the board is required to endorse it. That's why they call it the approval not required.
Neighboring cities have opted out of subdivision control law, so they don't do these. It would just be something that the planning director would sign administratively. So it's sort of a perfunctory exercise when they're straightforward like this one is. So I can show the plan unless
Mr. Stariano, did you want to share anything or would you prefer that I share the plan? You're muted. Yeah. No, I think it's pretty straightforward. We purchased a home with a lot. We've used it for many great times. I promised my wife when
My youngest graduated last year that we would divide the lot instead of moving out of the city that we like to build a small one family home on that lot so that we don't have to leave the city. And that was the reason of going forward. Can folks see my screen? Yes.
What are the dimensions on this, Danielle? So this is in the, hold on a second. Let me just confirm the zoning district. I did check all this initially, but now I don't.
Yeah, this is in the single family two zone and the required frontage is 35 feet. So it exceeds that. It exceeds it?
Yeah, I just did a quick measure on Google Maps. It looks like there's a little over 60 feet on the Magoon Ave side and approximately 90 feet on the Washington Street side. Yeah, and if you can see the, I guess I can't, am I sharing the ANR plan? So you can see, maybe it's too small, but you can see the dimensions.
Oh yeah. The new lot is 102.57 feet. And it's the minimum lot size. And then you've got 60 on the Laguna side, so that's well over 35. Yep. And so it fronts on a right of way, and in my opinion, has vital access.
So it fronts on the right of way, has vital access, and it exceeds the minimum frontage requirements. So those are the three requirements to remind the board that an A&R needs. So without further ado, if the board has no questions, I am going to ask for a motion to approve the A&R, although it doesn't need an approval. Yes, so the motion is to endorse. To endorse the A&R.
I second the motion. Do I have a second? I'll second. I'm going to do a roll call. Sally Akiki? Yes. Peter Kautz? Yes. Sabrina Alpino? Yes. And myself, Jackie McPherson. I'm a yes.
Thank you so much, Angelo, for being here. I apologize, because I blanked on your surname that quickly. No, not a problem. Have a great evening. Thank you for being with us. Thank you so much. Yes, sir. Our planning director will be back in the office on Monday, and she can sign the MILRs. So they'll be available to pick up probably on Monday. So just give our office a ring.
for when they're ready, and then you can bring them down to the Registry of Deeds to have them reported. Thank you so much. You're welcome. Thank you. Thank you. Have a good evening. So the third item on our agenda is approval of minutes, but they don't appear to be ready. Yeah, Gabe had prepared them, and I'm not sure where he put the final draft. I saw some
A rough draft, and I imagine it's going to be somewhere. And so I was like, I could redo these, but that's probably not the best use of time. So next meeting. Next meeting will take so many minutes to approve.
And so number four is zoning overhaul updates. Danielle, do you have anything for us? I'm assuming that may wait for Alicia to return or do you have- Yeah, so we've kept that as a standing agenda item to keep you all in the loop of what's going on. A few weeks ago, maybe it was two weeks ago, City Council had a permitting and planning subcommittee meeting and it was more of like a working session
And they had a bunch of maps out and a lot of questions. And there was a lot of staff. And the consultants were there. And I think there were some members of the public and elected officials that kind of marked up the maps. And so they've been going through those and will be reporting back on some of those comments. But right now, they are working on the Mystic Ave
corridor and the Salem Street corridor to put together some new dimensional and use regulations for those areas. As we are getting a lot of interest in properties on both of those quarters and as our zoning doesn't match our comprehensive plan or revision, we really need to
get the zoning in place so that we can get the kind of development that we want. So that things can be just a site plan review and not coming in for a bunch of variances in order to get what we want. So the next city council subcommittee meeting will be next week, I believe Wednesday.
So as always, you're welcome to attend those. Or they're also recorded and put on the Medford Community Media website if you ever want to catch up and see what was discussed. That's all I have for now.
Thank you so much. And just quickly to touch base, speaking on updates to zoning and so forth, Daniel, you were mentioning earlier about the housing bond bill that passed the new ADU law. And I'm not sure if you'll need the board to sort of help with that or if it starts in the planning office and what you'll be overruling. I do know that KP Law, this attorney from KP Law, is actually going to do like a lunch and learn to try to figure out what the
the law, the new law says, does, what's effective. So to try to kind of put it in layman's terms for us planners. That would be good because we knew it was coming down the pipeline, which is OK, we're going to have to change our zoning to align with the new state law. But I have a lot of questions. I don't know if this is just detached or within the same structure. So we're going to have to update our ordinance to
at a minimum, align with it. But we could be, I think, more permissive if we want to be. I'm hoping, usually KP Law, which is the legal counsel that we use, usually they issue a memorandum when something changes that they send out to all their clients. So I'm also hoping that we get something like that. But do you know if EOHLC will be
um, issuing any like regulations or guidance for this or. So Chris Clutchman, um, actually, uh, who's already doing the MTA laws has mentioned something about, uh, something coming down the pipeline, but I have not heard anything official. And now that we're two separate secretariats, I, I don't have that information real time. So, um,
I'm in a separate secretariat now, but I'm assuming that that's being worked on now. And I can get you all, I mean, you'll probably get the information as fast as I get the information, or maybe even sooner, because it's going out to municipalities as soon as possible. And I think it goes into effect, I think it's 180 days, I think.
When I have not again, I have not digested even the bridge version of what was sent out by one of our not not all heroes wear capes and there is a planner out there who actually digested this information and put it into like a little compact document. I haven't even had a chance to read that. So.
All right, I didn't want to drag on on that. I just wanted to know if there was anything that the board was going to have to do differently. And if that was, I know it's going to come down the pipeline because we just approved an ADU. And I didn't know how that was going to look going forward. Yeah, so that one was still, what they wanted to do is not by right. I'm not sure if it would be by right under the new law or not. But it's not in effect yet.
They could have waited it out, but. And then just are. The 2nd item is how do we get these?
to an administrative process with your office. That's a good question. That's a good question. I don't know about the rest of the board, but... That's just gonna be a waste of time. Yes, it's just, it's one of those things where it's like, we rely on you, you guys, to give us the information for those three requirements that we hit. So if you know that they hit them all at that point, it's a waste of the, it's not the best use of the client's time, your time or the board's time.
It's more of, again, not trying to put more on your plate, but how do we get those quick things? That's a good question. Yeah, because the two other cities that I've worked in, in Massachusetts, Somerville and Watertown, both have that as an administrative process. They opted out of subdivision control law. I don't know if that's something that we can do, or I don't know.
It does seem kind of like busy work. I think there have been A&Rs in the past where the access question has been more subjective. And I think that maybe the city board has declined to endorse an A&R on tasks. I didn't think it met that threshold. But yeah, the trickier ones, I think, should be the ones coming before the board, not the ones that are
pretty obvious, rubber stamps. Yeah, rubber stamps, perfect. Okay, and with that, there's no other items. If no one wants to share anything, then I will ask for a motion to adjourn. Okay, your turn.
I second. I second. OK. OK, Sally Akiti? Yes. Peter Kaufs? Yes. Sabrina Alfino? Yes. And myself, Jackie McPherson. I'm a yes. Thank you all. Have a great evening. Thank you. Bye. Welcome aboard, Sabrina. They want to be the CZ. Thank you. Give you a nice short one. Yes.