[SPEAKER_00]: Good evening, friends and neighbors.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now I know what you're thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Great, another person with a microphone and a dream.
[SPEAKER_00]: But don't worry.
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't come here to sell you a timeshare and convince you to join a pyramid scheme.
[SPEAKER_00]: I came here to talk about something even more exciting, local government.
[SPEAKER_00]: I stand before you today, not as a politician, but as a resident of Medford.
[SPEAKER_00]: Someone who believes in building bridges, not walls.
[SPEAKER_00]: Someone who believes that when we see something wrong, we speak up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when speaking up isn't enough, we roll up our sleeves and do something.
[SPEAKER_00]: I entered this race because I saw firsthand how the Charter Committee was treated in its early stages.
[SPEAKER_00]: How the City Council dismissed its purpose and its people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let me be clear, the Charter was created to protect our budget, not inflate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was meant to serve the people, not politics.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not my father's Oldsmobile.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not here to run Cruise On Legacy or Nostalgia.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm here for change.
[SPEAKER_00]: The residents of Medford are not asking for miracles.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're asking for solutions and I'm here to deliver them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here's what I propose.
[SPEAKER_00]: A world-class fire department.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's purchase land on Mystic Ave and build a fire department that reflects the excellence and courage of our firefighters.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just functional, world-class.
[SPEAKER_00]: Affordable housing for veterans, seniors, and disabled.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's knock down the old police and fire station and transform that space into affordable housing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a win-win.
[SPEAKER_00]: We address the crisis and we do it at that location with direct bus access and nearby medical offices.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's smart, compassionate, and long overdue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Revitalize the Mystic River.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's clean up the Mystic River, not just for the environment, but for opportunity.
[SPEAKER_00]: I propose we work with the MBTA to launch a commuter boat service to Boston, which stops at Rose Wharf and the seaport.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's time we rethink transportation and embrace innovation.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to be part of preparing for a future comprehensive infrastructure program that our city so desperately needs.
[SPEAKER_00]: Zoning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lastly and most importantly, we have enough work to do revitalizing all the squares in Mystic Ave.
[SPEAKER_00]: We don't need to put energy at this time into residential rezoning.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to ensure that all residential zoning is not infringed upon.
[SPEAKER_00]: This campaign isn't about me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about us.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about Medford.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about compromise, even when we don't agree on things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's build a city that works for everyone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's build bridges.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's come together and get to work.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have any questions, you can reach me at DonatoForMedFed.com.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'd like to thank my family, my friends, and my supporters for all you have done for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Paul for all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.