Good evening, friends and neighbors.
Now I know what you're thinking.
Great, another person with a microphone and a dream.
But don't worry.
I didn't come here to sell you a timeshare and convince you to join a pyramid scheme.
I came here to talk about something even more exciting, local government.
I stand before you today, not as a politician, but as a resident of Medford.
Someone who believes in building bridges, not walls.
Someone who believes that when we see something wrong, we speak up.
And when speaking up isn't enough, we roll up our sleeves and do something.
I entered this race because I saw firsthand how the Charter Committee was treated in its early stages.
How the City Council dismissed its purpose and its people.
Let me be clear, the Charter was created to protect our budget, not inflate it.
It was meant to serve the people, not politics.
I'm not my father's Oldsmobile.
I'm not here to run Cruise On Legacy or Nostalgia.
I'm here for change.
The residents of Medford are not asking for miracles.
They're asking for solutions and I'm here to deliver them.
Here's what I propose.
A world-class fire department.
Let's purchase land on Mystic Ave and build a fire department that reflects the excellence and courage of our firefighters.
Not just functional, world-class.
Affordable housing for veterans, seniors, and disabled.
Let's knock down the old police and fire station and transform that space into affordable housing.
It's a win-win.
We address the crisis and we do it at that location with direct bus access and nearby medical offices.
It's smart, compassionate, and long overdue.
Revitalize the Mystic River.
Let's clean up the Mystic River, not just for the environment, but for opportunity.
I propose we work with the MBTA to launch a commuter boat service to Boston, which stops at Rose Wharf and the seaport.
It's time we rethink transportation and embrace innovation.
I want to be part of preparing for a future comprehensive infrastructure program that our city so desperately needs.
Zoning.
Lastly and most importantly, we have enough work to do revitalizing all the squares in Mystic Ave.
We don't need to put energy at this time into residential rezoning.
I want to ensure that all residential zoning is not infringed upon.
This campaign isn't about me.
It's about us.
It's about Medford.
It's about compromise, even when we don't agree on things.
Let's build a city that works for everyone.
Let's build bridges.
Let's come together and get to work.
If you have any questions, you can reach me at DonatoForMedFed.com.
I'd like to thank my family, my friends, and my supporters for all you have done for me.
Paul for all.
Thank you.