I wrote a letter to South Street owners, just to give them a heads up that we're going forward. I didn't say much, I didn't defend, I didn't say what's involved in. I wanted to say as little as possible, frankly, except to get to say that we're considering this.
Yeah, I looked at that, Chris. I mean, I thought it was fine. I like Melody's edits to it. My question was whether we should link, are we gonna update our website? Are we gonna have a link? We are gonna update our website, but I don't have, I'm working with the website, the guys who built the website, and I haven't put the new content up yet.
Okay. And so I want them to create a web page. Oh, there's Chris. Okay, good. Yeah, I want them to create a page for the guidelines that that that we approved. Yeah. And, and a separate page for for South Street.
you know, with the map and the proposed map and the, as soon as possible, the preliminary report. Yeah. And the new Form Bs and, you know, all the, you know, all the Form Bs and so on. That's something has to be done by the web guys. Yeah, there's a, there's, we have a big, there's a big web design development and
hosting firm in North Carolina called AppNet and they're the ones we use. Okay. And they seem to be pretty responsive. So I'm hoping they will get the content up and running as quickly as possible. Okay, excellent. I mean, just as an aside, I've been using Wix for the website at my job and for my personal site and
I, I do all the editing myself and you just hit, it goes live and it's really easy. Is it, is it compatible with, uh, whatever that thing is that, uh, it's probably not compatible with WordPress unless they less, you know, you can export it in some web format. They have Wix, they have lots of templates and things, and you could, you can create things from scratch.
The only reason I mentioned it is because it's really easy to do yourself. You don't need to sort out stuff. Yeah. Might be worth it. Do you know how to use WordPress? You ever tried WordPress? Yeah. We started with WordPress for my office and hated it. And I said that I got on Wix and I don't know, my daughter said, go to go to Wix. And I figured that out in half of getting it all up and running. Well, I will definitely look into that.
Let me write that down. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. All right. Well, that's my comments on the, on the letter to the neighbors. Okay. And maybe yeah. Link to the web page is definitely a must. Yeah, I agree. Okay. Anybody else have any comments?
Okay, uh, so Chris, uh, what's up with the trifold? So I just sent that over just now. Okay. I, uh, I have a flu. I'm like just burning up. I know the lighting looks.
like crap. But um, I get the flu. I'm just burning up since I talked to Fred yesterday. I haven't had a bed. But the trifold I just sent it to everyone in the email. I apologize. But let's uh, it's got the front of them. If you want to look at your emails right now. I don't know if I can make it through this meeting. I'm like 101. Oh my god. I'm just burning. I first time I stood up all day today. So I'm burning up. Oh, wow.
So I sent the trifold, it's kind of just straight about what is a historic district. Would it just look at your emails? There's a which one is the best one to pull up, Chris, the PDF, the trifold handout. I fold him. OK, let me just open that up and maybe we can I'll pull it up on the screen here. We could look at it in. All right, there it is, can I call it up on the screen?
HAB-Michael Leccesereeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeee
These get cut into thirds, right? You know, get cut into thirds. It's a trifle. So the basic thing is how to tease them into the front. What is it? It's not really much information in the front, but it's kind of a turn it over. Fred, if you can tilt down our page down the second pages on the bottom of it. So there you go. So it's the same thing on all three, and it's kind of generic, but that's we were talking a little bit about maybe just trying to keep it simple, but Fred was kind of saying maybe we should have the South Street District
issues and line items in there. But this is just saying, hey, this is what a district is all about. This is what you may be seeing. This is why we use it. So it's generic. It's pretty straight ahead. But this grandfather's house, a couple more pictures here in the back that are South Street ish. But the pictures all can be replaced easily. The text can be replaced easily. But that's the idea is having something that's simple. So it's not really deep, but it's something that's OK.
PB, David Ensign — He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-He Him, He-
make some comments. There's three things in that, in that email. One is this PDF, but you should change it. The other one says dot pages. That's, that's, that's the one that you format that in. So you can't touch the PDF, but the pages one in there is the second. And what's the third thing on the third thing is the listing of each house. Great work that Sharon did to put together the lineups. Can you, what do you want to do Chris Bader first things first, but
There's a listing that Sharon had put together. Those are the three things that are in the email that I just sent. OK. I think I can write comments on a PDF in Adobe.
I just think that maybe, I think this is really good. I love the pictures and stuff. I'm just thinking maybe cleaning up the copy a little bit. And I think sometimes when it's centered, it's hard to, the front page I think is going, I think you have a lot of paragraphs. It's hard to read it when it's centered. So I can make just a few comments and send that over. Perfect. Perfect. I love it. Just, it's just a way to kind of look at something in your hand, right? All these little handouts that people get. Thank you, Melanie. Okay.
And it's going to be a trifold so. Oh, when I say trifle those should be cut into into third into thirds that should just be a single almost like a long business card that was. back.
And front and front and back right so you. Okay, I didn't know if you got like a trifle that we could take a height and a half by 11 you know how you can fold it into. So that's so that's eight and a half by 11 sideways right and then, when you print it front and back you cut that into thirds and you get. Out of every sheet. Unless you want. Chris bader a trifle and each one of those panels.
was details, more details. I thought it would just be soft, it's a nothing burger, but something to hand almost everyone that there's something in the thing, but the historic district, the South Street one is specific. So I didn't know if you wanted to include both of them in this thing or the separate letter. Well, we need some copy that actually pertains to the historic district.
Well, this on the back is really just saying, this is what a district's about. So just to educate people what it's all about, not necessarily say 1850 and this house is under that form B. I just didn't know if I wanted to get into that, but there's no wrong answers. I'm happy to change anything. It's just the beginning of a format to get, you know, to see it with sustenance. Can we look at the pages document, Brent? Let me see. Let me stop the share.
The pages will just it's that same form, but that's the one you can modify and change. It's a Mac, so it's pages, but it's PowerPoint. Let me see if I don't know if I have power, I can open a PowerPoint, let me just click on the pages, if it's applicable, it will open up in a comparable application. Do you have Mac bread? I do not know. I could be able to open that.
Okay, let me- And that's the pages. I can put it in some other format, but it's basically just those three, a couple of pictures and some generic text. Okay, hold on a second. Let me try and open it. Yeah, it doesn't- No, no. Get to it. Hold on a second. I can open it and share. Wait a minute. It says.pages.
Hold on, search app store. What the heck? Okay, give me a second here. I don't, I seldom use pages, so I haven't sort of new Mac. Just give me a second here. All right.
and open the pages, continue. Let's download. Okay, here we go. Yeah, it's just the same thing. It's exactly the same thing. Okay, well, the thing is,
But you can modify that template, but we need we need the actual copy to be on the printer. Right. You don't have the copy inside the template when you open that up. Well, I see what you what's in the PDF. But. Yeah, pages is a Mac thing, so it might be I can.
I mean, I'm seeing it right here, but there's not, there's no reason for me to share because it's, it's exactly right. Correct. Correct. And Chris, you and I can deal with a little bit of that later on if you want that. Okay. The layout of that. I had in mind something a little more, a little less generic and a little more specific to the South street historic district, you know, like talking about grandfather's house and, and, uh, um,
Well, my original thought was that was a handout, that something's going on, and the other thing is the more detailed thing, but that doesn't have to be. So if you want them both in thing, as Fred suggested that as well yesterday, I just didn't get a chance to kind of throw that in there. Yeah, I think we could just keep the generic language and then just move over to some, either out of Chris Skelly's report or make some up for ourselves that is specific to South Street and the ship building and all that.
Okay. I have a question and then I have to go. So when you send the letter, I guess my question is, I know we're trying to communicate things to certain people about the historic district. And to me, and I'm just putting on my marketing hat here, like who is the audience and who are we trying to communicate what to? So there's obviously going to be, um,
You're gonna send out the letter. Were you planning on putting something in that letter to talk more about the historic district? I wasn't planning on it, no. Okay, so then what Chris worked on is really just a handout, and that's to inform not only the people in the area, but also others within the city? Is that what we're trying to do?
Yes, we want this to be we want this to be accessible and targeted toward anybody who's going to pick it up. So we really want to talk more about.
We really want to talk about them that the South Street, that historic district and some of the important things so we might, given that we might want to make it instead of just a front and back more of a trifold. Yes, no. Okay, so I think if we make it into more of a trifle we can think about what those different panels are we could actually get add more copy and definitely some more photos.
And then I tried looking for the thing that Chris Kelly did, and I couldn't find it. If you could re-forward it to me, because I think what Fred said, you could probably pull in some of that copy. So I'm happy to, I don't know if I can do it right in Pages, but I'm happy to try to do something like on a Word document, like what we might want to communicate. Do you have a Mac, Melanie?
And this doesn't have to be Mac. We could redo it on PC base. Just who's going to own the. No, no, no. I have both Word and Pages, so I can import and export it. It's not a question of the format. But Melanie, do you have a Mac? I do have a Mac. I do. Yeah, it's older, but I do have one. OK. What I'll do is I'll just change this to Word format, and I'll send it out to everybody. OK.
But yeah, I think we want something much more specific to set the South Street historic district. And we want, we don't want, I think we want to use all six panels, right?
Yes, we do want to use all six panels. We want to use, I think in the, yeah. And, you know, we definitely wanted to use all six panels. The back doesn't necessarily need to be, maybe it just has something about the historic district, you know, historic district commission, what we are, who we are, that type of thing. And the website on the very back of the panel, then the front of the panel is, you know, maybe a really nice picture about South street. And then when you open it up, you know, you have two more panels. So I think there's,
You know, and then we could even do like a whole spread across the middle of the eight and a half by 11. So if you send me that in Word, I can try to think about some of the layout. I'm not a designer, but I can definitely think about some of the communications that we wanna do. And send me the stuff from Chris Kelly. I will absolutely do that. Okay. Okay, so I'll convert this to Word and I will send you Chris Kelly's stuff in Word format. Okay.
Yeah. And so I spoke with the wheelers, Chris Bader, and they're all excited to see us come on that day. So we do have a place to launch. I got to go, guys. So I'll be in touch. Thank you. All right. Right. OK. Yeah. So why don't we hand this over? I mean, Melanie is gone. It's very easy to delegate work to her then. But
He volunteered, so I think we can do it. Yes. Well, now that I know we want more text in there, it's kind of easy just to drag and drop a couple of things and I'll do that. I'll send Melanie another one. She has everything I have right now. We just sent that. But if that's what the idea is to make it useful of using all three panels, I'll put some Chris Kelly stuff in there and some of the stuff that guidelines. OK, can you work with Melanie and please
You know time we've only got let's see can I check with you tomorrow Chris let's let's let's do this. i'll check in with you tomorrow. that's excellent. Because i'll drop a bunch of stuff. Okay. All right, so I don't think we have much more to discuss this evening.
I'd like to make one comment that I went to Somerville Porch Fest Saturday. It was raucous. What a crazy event. Just out of control. People, bands, the crowd, huge crowds. It was a huge success. So hopefully Medford can rub off a little stuff for us.
So Fred, if you were going to go, how many people do you think, like, I'm just thinking we can draw on your experience to think about how many copies of the trifold we should print. Yeah, I don't know. I have no idea how many people are going to show up to Medford's port. I mean, literally, you could have had 10,000 copies for Somerville if you wanted to hand one to every people. It was mobbed. But I think a
We probably don't need more than 100 or something, you know, I think that would be more than adequate to hand out to people. And I think, Chris, we wouldn't be handing out to everyone, but to have the booth off to the side is to try and invite the neighbors.
and talking about it before and after as a campaign to say, hey, this is a place to maybe talk a little bit about this. That was, I thought, the original thought. Not to engage everyone in, hey, what we're doing, but just the neighbors, the people in that area. I'm beginning to think more like 250, because these are not that expensive. Yeah, and we can always use them later on. Yeah, yeah. OK, so Chris, can you work with Melanie? Can we check in with you? Do you have any time tomorrow or this weekend to look at this stuff?
I want to have a full six panel trifold that is unique on every page. Not overwhelming people with information or text, but has a lot more content than it is in there now.
Does that make sense? We can do that. We get the content. It's just a matter of pulling it all together and adding it and putting it in. OK, I full format and all that. What's our next meeting, Chris Bader? When's our next meeting? Boy, it's probably after June 3rd. Oh, yeah, it's it's June. It's the it's the it's the Thursday of that week.
So do you want to just talk about just a second about if we can have anyone wants to go down for that booth and I'm happy to go there. The scheduling of it, PorchFest, Fred, did PorchFest work like this? You were at one place and then everybody moved to the next place and everybody moved to the next place. And it was chaos. Every band playing simultaneously just.
heard a song, and if you wanted to find it, you'd just walk a few houses down and it'd be somebody else playing another song. They had a website with all the acts or addresses, but it was so popular, it was overwhelmed and you couldn't get into it. They had like...
You know, it overlaps. I just wonder, Chris Bader, if we can at least make some announcement that we're going to have a table there and from, you know, one to two or one to three, we'll be taking, you know, commentary from anyone in the community about this, this facet of it. What do you think? I can put something on next door. Because it's going to happen before our next meeting. Just trying to figure out how we're going to let people sort of know. Yeah. Do you know what next door is? No. It's a it's a.
social media thing for neighborhoods. And there are a lot of Medford residents on it. I can put something on next door. All right, I can put something on Reddit and my wife can put something on the Medford Facebook page. So once we go, we could probably broadcast it out. Yeah. To at least those things.
Any comments, questions, concerns, please come and see us on June 3rd, PorchFest. We'll have a booth at the Real Fathers House. We'll give you some insight to the South Street Historic District that's being proposed, and we'd love to hear your input. Yeah. Okay. Yeah. Yeah. So let's do something like that. Okay. Well, we've still got a lot of work to do.
in my opinion. So let's, let's get, let's get going. You want to just Chris beta Fred, put Charlotte in, but I want to just convene Monday went for a phone call, check in on Monday and get an update. I'm available. What about you, Fred?
Yeah, it's okay. I'll just make a call, give an update, see where we stand. Yeah, might be. I could impress you with something. Let's see. I'd like to let's get this stuff pulled together. And then, yeah, if it seems to be happening, then a quick. Why don't we, Chris, why don't we email first? Why don't we schedule this by email? Sounds good. OK, that's great. OK. All right. Thanks, everybody. Anything else?
Nope. Okay, well, yeah, we've got a little ways to go before we're ready to go to press, so to speak. I like where we are, Chris. The good news is that Staples has 24-hour turnaround. So if we take it down, if we even email it to the, I'm sure they want a PDF.
And if we email a PDF to them, uh, they can probably print, uh, you know, like 250 copies and, and, uh, and we can pick it up in time for the porch fest. Yeah. And a lot of them, we, we use staples a fair amount. You can get it in by like 11 in the morning, a lot of times. So it's ready by five o'clock that day. Yeah, exactly. Yeah.
Thank you, Charlotte. Okay. All right. All right. Very good. Thank you, everybody. Thank you. Right.