[SPEAKER_00]: It's my distinct pleasure to welcome all of you to the Medford Public Schools.
[SPEAKER_00]: My name is Dr. Marice Edouard-Vincent, and I am so honored to be the superintendent of the Medford Public Schools.
[SPEAKER_00]: Medford is a welcoming community, and in our schools, we thrive to be inclusive and offer so many educational and athletic opportunities for our students.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Medford Public Schools has always encouraged our parents and caregivers to collaborate with us to benefit your students' education.
[SPEAKER_00]: We know that it takes all of us, parents, caregivers, teachers, administrators, the Medford School Committee, and the community at large to work together for the betterment of our students.
[SPEAKER_00]: Medford is one of the oldest communities in the United States, settled in 1630 and established as a city in 1892.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is a community rich in diversity and history.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a district, our guiding pillars are achievement for all, collaboration for all, equity for all, and support for all.
[SPEAKER_00]: As Maya Angelou once said,
[SPEAKER_00]: We should all know that diversity makes for a rich tapestry, and we must understand that all the threads of the tapestry are equal in value, no matter what their color.
[SPEAKER_00]: I look forward to us working together.
[SPEAKER_00]: In closing, I welcome everyone to the home of the Mustangs.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you ever see me out and about,
[SPEAKER_00]: When I say Mustang, you say Pride.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mustang Pride.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is your proud superintendent.