We're good to go in the chamber.
Give me the sign, Rich, and we'll go.
All right.
Medford City Council, Medford Community Development Board Special Joint Meeting, May 27, 2026.
We do not have a quorum of the City Council or the Community Development Board right now, because as we announced at our last meeting, we are planning to continue the public hearing of this meeting to
June 3rd at 6 p.m., Wednesday, June 3rd at 6 p.m.
So we will be having the public hearing on the Boston Avenue Neighborhood Corridor District on Wednesday, June 3rd at 6 p.m.
I believe Chair Carr, if you could also note that you don't have a quorum of the Community Development Board, then we can move from there.
Great, thank you, Councilor, President Behrs.
We do not have a quorum, so we are going to agree to continue the public hearing to June 3rd as you described.
Councilor Lemming, go ahead.
Motion to... There's no motions because we don't have a quorum, so the public hearing is continued to June 3rd at 6 p.m.
and the meeting was never called to order and therefore we do not need to adjourn in the
meeting for tonight's special joint meeting, Medford City Council and Community Development Board is concluded.
We will be having a city council committee of the whole at 6.15, a budget meeting.
Thank you.