Now for this week's Mustang report.
Hello, we're back here again with Tea Time with Dora and Haley with our second guest, Lydia. So Lydia, we have a few random questions to ask you. So what would you say your favorite movie is? It's definitely Lilo and Stitch, the first one. We heard you're on the gymnastics team. How's that going for you? It's rough, man. Gymnastics, I don't know if it's my calling, but I'm going to work hard for this team in this season. And it's a great group of kids.
If you could have any superpower, what would it be? Oh my god, I'd be invisible. Or maybe I'd fly. No, I'd definitely fly. That would be pretty sick. Last question. What's your favorite season and how do you feel about the snow today? I love winter because I don't like being hot in the summer. But summer is definitely my favorite season because we don't have to go to school. Awesome. There you have it. Thank you very much, Lydia.
belongs on a knee. But I found a boy who I love more than I ever did you before. So stand beside the river I cry and let your
I also, again, would like to thank superintendent Roy Belson for getting my school tomorrow. I thought I was going to be walking to school tomorrow with blue lips. Yeah, blue lips. You know, up next we have Alida Brenton singing Blue Lips by Regine Spector. Let's give her a round of applause. Stood up beneath the knowledge tree And they chopped it down to make my bed
Okay, and on that note, we have Beatrice Gonsalves singing Love Yourself by Justin Bieber.
And if you think that I'm still holding on to something, you should go and love yourself. Cause it's tickling me. If I were a boy, I think I could understand.
And we miss the love of God, I swear I'd be a better man I listen to her, cause I know how it hurts
when you lose the one you wanted, cause he's taken you for granted, and everything you had I've destroyed. I'd like to give it up for Raquel Darachi and Julia Mara singing two songs, The Way You're Looking Tonight by Frank Sinatra, and one of my personal favorites, If I Ain't Got You, by Alicia Keys.
Yes, you're lovely With your smile so warm And your cheeks so soft There is nothing for me but to love Some people want it all But I don't want nothing at all If it ain't you, baby
I got you, baby. Some people want diamond rings. Some just want everything. But everything means nothing if I ain't got you. But I remember when I moved in you. The holy dust was moving too. And every breath we drew was hallelujah.
Tell me, what is your position here at MHS? I work in the main office. I'm one of the admin
And I work alongside Ms. Lisa Bowler and the headmaster, Dr. Prowler. I like to think that both, well, the whole main office crew itself creates a welcoming and safe environment so that we try to nurture and harbor any kind of student that needs our help throughout the day. Obviously, these students go to their academics, to their teachers, but sometimes they just need that extra support during the day, and we always try to provide it. How do you come to be here at Medford High? Why did you come back?
So when I originally went to school, I actually went to Bridgewater State University, I went for an English degree, thinking that I wanted to teach. When I came here, I started studying, I kind of was in the classroom, made me a little nervous, wasn't really my thing, but knew I wanted to stay within the school, and so I kind of came and found my little niche here.
of the directors and founders of Spotlight Productions and I'm a balloon artist so I have gone to different kinds of events and twisted balloons. If you could be any animal what would you be? I could be any animal.
Yeah!
I'm here with Ms. Mack and the question of the week is who do you think is going to win the Patriots game, Patriots or the Steelers? TV 12, baby. That's all the way. What do you think the score is going to be? 28-14, Patriots. Steelers! Patriots! The Patriots, obviously. 28-21. I'm wearing a Brady shirt. I think that's the answer enough for you. Patriots 31.
The Patriots definitely. 28-13. The Patriots. Hands down. Obviously it's the Pats. 27-24. Obviously the Patriots. I calculated it out. It's gonna be 28-23.
Go Pats, baby. Pats, 42. Pittsburgh, 13. What's up, Metro High School? This is Nick Hennessy with the Mustang Report, and I'm here at the Metro High School pool where last night the swim team defeated Summerville in their meet. In sports now, first for the boys basketball team, their team has been very strong this year.
uh... led by captain mckay collins as well as a uh... other captains tyree strata conor frasier they've jumped out to a pretty strong record this year specifically sunday be stonem and last night they beat arlington catholic by twenty three points and they also contended with ever for three quarters and that they have led but they've been led this year by not only the captains but big also big man justin kelly as well as incumbent sophomore guard tyla wholeness
Additionally, for the track team, the track team has been very strong this year. However, they have definitely been suffering from, as being a winter sport, they've been suffering from lots of sickness. Definitely the flu bug is going around. However, they've had two pretty close meets. Additionally, their sophomore contingent of middle distance runners have been outstanding. Specifically, Julia Gailback, Willa Driscoll, Megan McGilvery, Lauren Brown,
Zoe Salvato-Cutter, as well as sophomores Haley DiPietro Antonio, freshman Jada Hamill, and Joelle Brown. And also, they've had strong leadership from their captains, such as Amber Harbison, captain Alexa Normyle in the shot put, and they've also gotten some strong outputs in the shot put from junior Tess Morrow.
now for the girls basketball team uh... recently they have deftly also caught the injury bug a little bit where ryan and arnold and carmen diario both of torn their ceo and i've done for the year however they've read responded pretty strong as they beat pope john last week
and they are looking to contend for the GBL championship. If they can beat Malden one more time and Everett one more time, they will win the GBL for the last time. As this year, they will then go into the Northeast Conference with 16 teams. For Girls Hockey now,
they've started off this is definitely a rebuilding season for them however they have come on strong as of late with a two-game win streak led by strong goaltending from trisha mcclain as well as strong play from their uh... from their star abby abby vigliotti additionally another note for girls hockey uh... one of medford high school's alums britney lanzilli uh... was elected to the women's unit united states national women's university team this is a huge
Huge honor for Lenzilli. And a couple of other notes for Lenzilli. She's the third female to score 300 career points in state history. Additionally, in her junior year, she led the entire nation in goals and in points.
She did break Sean Bates' school record for goals and points. To boys hockey now, they have had a strong season so far, led by goaltending from seniors Matt Santos and Jonathan Haley. Additionally, they have had some strong play from juniors Ryan Donohue and David Welch. And that concludes our Mustang Report for this week. This has been the Sports Report from Nick Kenniston, and back to you.