so
do
Music playing
so so
you
It's gonna be hard to do.
It doesn't matter.
Because what happens...
Peace.
Bye.
so
Yeah.
I am Paul DeLeva, Medford Vocational Technical High School Complex.
At this time, I would ask that you please stand for the Pledge of Allegiance recited by the voice of Medford High School, Elijah Fortune, and remain standing for the singing of our National Anthem sung by the voice of Medford High School, Katherine Brosnahan.
Hello everyone, I'm Elijah Fortenay, here to give to you the Pledge of Allegiance.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America and to the republic for which it stands, one nation under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all.
Class of 2020, this year has been a whirlwind.
And it's crazy to say that we were born in after 9-11 and we are graduating during a pandemic.
Just know that this means we are meant to succeed during difficult times and never forget that as you pursue your future careers.
gleaming, whose broad stripes and bright stars through