Hey listeners, this is Danielle. And Shelley. Shelley is a radical Dravidian and racial equity activist. And Danielle is a community mobilizer and changemaker. And this is the Medford Bites podcast. Every two weeks, we chew on the issues facing Medford and deliver bites of information about the city by lifting the expertise of our guests. Join us in discussion about what you hope for the future of Medford. And as always, tell us where you like to eat.
Thanks so much for being here with us today. Shelly's back. We've missed her for a while, but she's here today. I missed you guys too. Good to be back. All right. So the rest of you, if you don't mind introducing yourselves, just with your name, pronouns, and who you are.
Yeah, my name is Nicole Morrell she her, I am the chair of invest in Medford, which is the ballot question campaign in favor of questions, six, seven and eight. I'm also a former city counselor and mom in Medford, and that covers it.
Hi, I'm Christina McCourty. I am a volunteer with the Invest in Medford campaign, mostly focusing on the comms, so I might be coming to your door soon to Canvas. I am a currently substitute teaching in the Medford public schools and was a former teacher before that. And I'm also a parent of two kids in the Medford public schools.
Hi, I'm Jessica Parks. I am also a volunteer with the Invest in Medford campaign and a mom and longtime resident in Medford. All right, thank you all. So I'll just prompt the question of the podcast that we ask everybody, sometimes the hardest one. If you could just share your favorite place to eat in Medford and what you like to eat there.
Yeah, I'll go. I've been on before, and I gave the same question before, the same answer before, but I'm going to get into specifics. So we'll go with Chili Garden. I like the super spicy stuff, but I also like the bamboo shoots and sesame oil. And they've been extra good lately because my son is a huge fan. So that's just a win because he's a toddler. So anything he likes and will eat, it makes it extra good. Thanks.
It is very hard to pick, but I'll say one of my favorite things is the carnitas torta from Tenoch. Nice. And I'm going to go with peppermint stick ice cream from Colleen's. Yeah, we have a frequent one. Nice. Yeah, that's a good one.
haven't heard about Colleen's in a while so it's nice to hear about it again. So I'm hoping that you can describe for us kind of what the Invest in Medford campaign is. Sure I can kick it off and then I'll let other folks join in. So the Invest in Medford campaign at its most basic is a ballot question committee for people who are in favor
Of question 678 which pertain to a debt exclusion for the new fire headquarters and to overrides for the schools and our streets and sidewalk. The campaign is like most local campaigns is made up of your
your friends, your cousins, your neighbors, people in Medford who are invested in investing in Medford and wanna see these campaign, these ballot questions come to fruition and have Medford be funded in the way that it deserves. So the ballot measures cover a number of different needs for the city and ask Medford residents if they're in favor of investing in the city in the form of a fixed dollar amount of tax increase to make these things happen. And I'm happy to go in more detail or if anyone else wants to jump in.
And I think that's great Nicole, and maybe you could expand on what a vote of yes on 678 would mean for this.
Yeah, so I'll break them down into each question. So I'm just in sequential order. So by voting yes on six, voters are approving a debt exclusion, which would increase taxes for residents and commercial to fund the design and construction of a new fire headquarters that would cover the cost of the project as they are outlined today. Any kind of like small changes for timing of project or slight adjustment would be covered, but we're looking at roughly $30 million.
And what makes it a debt exclusion is this is a tax increase over a set period of time. So once the bill is paid for that project, that amount of tax increase is going to come off everyone's bills.
Seven and eight are overrides, which are permanent, but like the debt exclusion, they're a set amount. So it's not a percentage increase. It's a set dollar increase to your yearly tax bill. They total $7.5 million together. And question seven helps to stabilize our school district and avoid cuts to our school system, as well as fund a permanent street and sidewalk crew in-house instead of always contracting out.
for the huge amount of work we need down in the city. And question eight really helps the schools reach beyond just stabilizing and making sure everything can stay as it is and reach for things that would really benefit our students and our community through a number of different things that are outlined that I can talk about later or let someone else talk about.
Thank you. Yeah. So I think, you know, Christina and Jessica, you guys are also here as parents in different roles in the city. So I want to hear from you in a second. But one thing we did do in preparation for this episode was to reach out to residents to see kind of what their support or lack of support was for the override. We didn't receive any messages that conveyed that people did not want this. So they were all messages in support. But I want to read a couple and then and sort of see
How these resonate with you all if you have anything that you would add or agree with here. So, a resident named Michelle and said right now made for public schools have already had to cut valuable valuable positions and services due to budget issues last year. If these tax overrides don't pass 35 to 45 more positions will be cut along with services such as behavioral support staff.
paraprofessionals, advanced courses at the high school, and the arts throughout the district. This means teachers will take on more work, have less time and energy to create engaging lessons, and certainly less time and energy to spend with students individually as class sizes throughout the district would rise. To have less than adequate funding makes teaching near impossible. The added burdens of inadequate funding make what should be a joyful job a miserable one. These difficult working conditions will directly affect
Our students in Medford, please don't ever forget that teacher working conditions are student learning conditions. If teachers are struggling and unhappy, students will be too. I want my children to go to a school in a district where teachers are happy and supported, and I hope that district can be Medford.
Another person said that they're in support of 6, 7, and 8 because Medford's needs can't be met as is. The value to our community of being able to do more instead of figuring out how to do less is worth way more to me than $37 in my pocket a month. Honestly, I would have gladly supported a bigger ask because these three initiatives are only scratching the surface of what our community needs. Prop 2.5 has not made
was not made to never be broken. The majority of our cities and towns have passed multiple overrides, which is why our surrounding communities have more resources and amenities than we have. I have two young kids and hope to stay in Medford for their childhoods, but the decision will certainly have to be revisited if there's no broad community support for our schools. I'll pause there and see, you know.
Yeah, I mean, I feel like one of the big things there that runs through is like that Medford Public Schools always tries to do as much as they can with the budget they're given, but that's really not okay for our kids and for our teachers. We are supposed to meet
each child's needs. We're supposed to figure out each child as an individual, get to know them, figure out their needs, and that can't happen the way things are now. So class size came up, and we are feeling the effects right now of the cuts that already happened last year. We have large class sizes, and you know,
is when you have like 24 second graders, which I am subbing right now in a class of 24 second graders. And you're trying to get to know them and figure them out as learners and give them what they need. It is impossible. Education has come a long way from what it was decades ago. And I feel like the expectations are higher and they should be. But it is not a sustainable job when your class sizes are
are large. Another thing that didn't come up in what those comments, but that comes up for me is like how the underfunding in our schools has created inequity. And if there are further cuts, it just furthers the inequity. Because it's so hard to get, for example, a child on an IP and get kids the services they need.
What happens is that it's the parents who are the most in the know, the parents who have the money for lawyers and the parents who have the money for advocates that can fight hard for their kids. A lot of people know the easiest way to get things for your kids is when the parents initiate it.
what I would like to see is a funded school where teachers can feel comfortable like bringing up kids and not being brushed off and where parents can bring up concerns and not be brushed off the way that often happens in Medford because we just don't have the funds to really give the kids what they need. So the equity piece is really big for me. There's a lot of inequity in Medford and you see it in the schools.
And to me, when there were cuts, it concerned me because I felt like the larger classes with the needier populations is really hard. And if there are more cuts, I don't know how
just to be honest, I don't know how we could have more cuts. So I'd like us to fund the school so that we don't have to make the cuts, but then we also can actually provide what the kids need and the teachers. That was another thing they spoke to. We want to keep our teachers. And honestly, financially, people can go, paraprofessionals too, everyone that works in the schools, they can go somewhere else nearby for more money.
So we wanna make their job doable and keep the class sizes smaller and have the support staff we need. I heard guidance, we need so much social emotional learning support and guidance. So part of this too is helping to increase salaries hopefully for teachers in Paris. So yeah, a lot of that is big.
Another thing that I heard in those comments, which is tied into the inequity piece, I think somewhat, but just the reality of what happens if they don't pass is, I think one of the people said that they could potentially leave Medford if they don't pass. And that's troublesome. We've been here for,
13 years, we're not going anywhere. The cost of houses in this area are ridiculous. So we're not moving anywhere. We're not in a position to move anywhere else. And if it doesn't pass, then is it that people who can move elsewhere to other districts where they're investing in their children,
then those children have the opportunities. Or people who can't afford to have their children go to private schools, their children get those opportunities. And then the children left in the Medford schools are left with what the Medford schools end up becoming. And so that worries me personally for my own kid and all the other kids who will be left in the Medford school district if it doesn't pass.
And I did hear that from a few other people, like how this decision is going to affect their decision about if they stay in Medford or not. And that's, yeah. Yeah, you can't blame people because if a community says we don't want to invest in this, we don't care about our public schools. That's, you know, that's really jarring.
Chrissy, I just wanted to key in on an important point you made, sharing that you're already feeling the weight of larger class sizes. It is September 20th, right? And so I wondered if you might speak to maybe some of the, you know, you've got years of expertise in teaching some of the ramifications of what larger class sizes mean in so far as learning, not to mention the kind of individualized support that all our kids deserve, but maybe some of the kids, you know, navigating learning stuff. But yeah, what are the classrooms feeling like?
So it's just, I mean, as simple as it sounds, it's just like having all those like bodies in the room and then trying to manage them takes a lot of energy. So, you know, you're here to teach and learn and, you know,
talk about how to be kind and good people and all this stuff, but you get bogged down sometimes with trying to get 24 people ready. We had to just do this assessment that we have to do on the Chromebooks, and it took 10 minutes to get everyone set up. There's just a lot of time wasted.
it takes kids longer. Everything takes longer. When you're teaching something, you want to be able to assess their background knowledge, see where they are, and meet them where they are. You want to be able to
rotate around the room and feel like you've checked in with each student. See, okay, who's got it? Okay, I need to check in with like these kids, they really don't have it. You know, and when there's so many
children. It is really hard to go around, especially because of all the things that come up, like children are children. There's kids who are just having a hard time paying attention or there's kids chatting. There's all these behaviors that you have to manage. And
So, you know, that, that becomes hard. And then also, like, if you have kids that you want to bring up that are concerning, you know, it's just hard because, you know, when I was a teacher, I always felt like I had, you know, I couldn't bring up
all the kids because there were so many. You have to make all these decisions about who's the most neediest and things like that. It's just like the more kids you have, the harder all that is. Last year I happened to be in a class, I know it's ideal, but there were 15 children and it just
It was wonderful. Like, I did feel like I could check in with everyone. I did feel like we were a nice family, like a community. It's just hard when, yeah, like the more of them there are, the harder it is to give them the individual attention that they need.
Thank you, yeah. And there was one other person who wrote into us that said that if there's no vote on these questions that Medford will continue to be in a worse state year after year and that it almost guarantees that we'll be passed over for the new high school. So I don't know if, yeah, I think that like the new high school was sort of the reason that I started thinking about this or hearing about overrides or like a budget increase. And so I wonder if there's any thoughts about that.
Yeah, Nicole, I don't know if you know more about the the heist. Um, so yeah, so part of this is, none of us can see the future. But I think what that person is getting to is that we have something on the ballot right now that's asking people whether or not they want to invest in our public schools. And if they say no, that's going to signal to the MSBA that covers part of a new high school. It doesn't cover the entirety of the community has to cover for part of it as well.
And that requires another debt exclusion down the line. If we're already saying now we don't want to invest in our public schools, they're not going to likely want to go through the process with us to continue towards a new high school. If they think that the next time it comes up to invest in our public schools in the form of new high school, we're going to say no again.
So it's kind of them reading the tea leaves of what we're telling them with this vote. So it's really important in that sense, too. And I know there's some confusion, understandably, that people think that what does this vote have to do with the new high school? It's its own separate vote, but it definitely does have an impact in a different way. Absolutely. I think when you spend money, you're showcasing your values, and this is an opportunity to showcase our municipal values. Absolutely. Community values, rather. Right.
So I don't want to frame it that everyone was writing to us about the schools because there was another person who was talking about streets and sidewalk repair maintenance and saying that those things are projects that have been kicked down the road by many mayors and city councils in the past. He said that there's 95 miles of roadway in Medford and in 2023 one street that was 1300 feet long was replaced.
At that rate, we'll have dirt roads in 10 years. And we need more funding for infrastructure, lead pipes, burst pipes, sidewalks that you trip over. I think this is a good example. I think even when we talk about the school budget, we talk about teacher salaries. But I think you all did a great job of illustrating all the other things that we don't maybe think about every day if we aren't in the schools. And I think this person does a good job of talking about, we hear complaints about the roads all the time. This is a way to start addressing
fixing them, but also all of the other things that maybe we need to fix. And I think one of the arguments I was hearing along the way was like, we don't need to raise taxes because we're going to be getting more revenue from businesses in the city. And I think if our roads are a mess, no one's going to want to drive through here to get to different places. But yeah, any other thoughts about the road maintenance projects, the infrastructure impacts of these overrides?
Yeah, I mean, I think it's an essential part of it. I mean, this allows us to bring a crew in-house, allows us to be that much more agile, allows us to have people, you know, in our DPW that this is like the sole focus of their job as opposed to contracting out every single time we need work done, which not only is, of course, a cost, but it's also, you know, a scheduling challenge. So it's something completely different, allows us to be much more agile and allows us to
chip away on that backlog of street and sidewalk repairs that's been talked about so often. And I think, yeah, I'll stop there. But it's another equity issue though, too, right? Because we're all using the roads, whether we're walking, we're driving, we're biking. And this is something that asks for a smaller collective investment rather than someone repairing their car every time they hit a pothole or, you know,
Investing in a different mode of transportation because the roads do not allow them to travel in the way they need to travel for their own mobility constraints. So I think it's, it's all part of a whole of just a collective investment in a city which may be, you know, it's going to be
$40 give or take every month. But you have to compare to what if you address those issues out of your own pocket through expensive transportation, through tutors, through all of these things that a large amount of people don't have access to, don't have the funds for. But $40 to get them that is something completely different and something game changing. 100%. I feel like I'm sitting here thinking about the breadth of time that has to do with how important this vote is, and this seems
to a certain extent to be about visioning and being able to think about where Medford could be, where we want it to be and what are the necessary steps to take now in order to ensure that. But then a different part of me is thinking about the sort of question of how did we get here and pulling in some equity pieces around knowing that for a very long time, Medford was run by men, run by white men. It's hard for me
And I'm also very much ignorant to a lot of the sort of nuts and bolts, but it's hard for me to place this larger moment at the feet of like, you know, current leaders or like folks who've been only part of the conversation in the last 10 years, because we know that these sort of like property revenue conversations have been in motion for decades. So I wondered maybe Nicole, if you might kind of speak to how we got here in Medford, maybe some of the larger choices that have happened that are kind of creating this moment.
Yeah, definitely. So we got here because of Prop 2.5 that was passed in the early 1980s. What is the simplest way to explain this? But it basically limits, a city may increase its total property tax by up to 2.5% of the value of taxable property per year plus an additional amount for new construction, commonly referred to as new growth.
So any increase beyond that must be approved by the majority of voters in the term of an override or a debt exclusion. So this was passed in the 1980s. People that were alive then and making financial decisions then can think about, you know, the financial landscape that we were in at the time. Perhaps it was passed with good intentions, who knows. But basically any time inflation goes up more than two and a half percent, it's essentially, it's going to be a cut to your city budget.
This was definitely a constraining statute that was established, but it was also set up with a tool of an override or a debt exclusion that allows the majority of the voters to say, hey, we want to collect a little bit more taxes because we want these things in our budget. We want to do more with our budget. We don't want to have our budget essentially cut little by little every single year. And I think part of how we got here is it's a,
I think it's a fairly well-known fact. Well, it's a fact that we had the same mayor for a very long time in Medford, and I think it's a fairly well-known fact that he was against bringing an override to the voters.
you have the same mayor for 28 years, that is a long time of little cut, little cut, little cut, little cut. And we know things like healthcare, healthcare costs that we cover in the city for our employees go up much, much faster than 2.5%. If we want to pay our workers what they deserve, it's going to be more than 2.5%. Look at the contracts that are being settled. If they're getting more than 2.5%, we have to sit and think, where else is that coming from?
So that's kind of how we got here. I think a lot of cities you'll see that maybe the first time they tried an override, sometimes they pass, a lot of times they pass in the first, sometimes they don't. Sometimes it's just getting it out into the lexicon and people realizing that this is a thing, this is a tool we have in our toolbox. We are pushing so that this passes, our first attempt at override passes because it's an absolute need.
If it doesn't, hard decisions will have to be made. Cuts will come. It will be not good. But I know for one, I will try again. And we will get an override passed, ideally this November.
And I do. But I think, you know, it's kind of like the the genies out of the bottle, you know, we've said we are Medford, and we can do an override. So these conversations are happening, it can be a little uncomfortable for some folks. But for so long, we wouldn't even say it. And for 28 years for for, you know, for
40 something years since two and a half was passed, that's how we get here. And that's how it can feel like how, you know, people are saying like, how did we suddenly get here? It was cut by cut by cut by cut every single year. Um, and then the, the ARPA funding and ESSER funding that came with the pandemic kind of gave us a little bit of a lifeline. And it also let us see some things that we could have in Medford that are really nice to have in Medford that we really should have in Medford. And now some of those things and some very basic things need to go away.
unless we find another funding source. I love that. I'm wondering if any of you have any thoughts about what you might say to somebody who's sort of on the fence or worried about maybe how this would, their ability to pay for an increased tax rate.
Yeah, absolutely. And I understand our, I think it's, we're lucky and we're also a little bit cursed about these home values. So as home values go up, our assessments go up and our taxes go up, but of course our tax rate comes down. So we're within those prop two and a half limits, but I know we're all in different scenarios for how, what our income is in our homes. So as far as folks that are affected, just number one,
This is just an investment in the community, and it will absolutely pay dividends in our roads and in our students and in our community as a whole, but for the actual dollars and cents of it, there are a number of programs for seniors on fixed incomes that
Medford mandates that are not mandates that Medford operates that are really opt in programs to the state. So we have our work off program where seniors can work, put in some hours for the city to offset their bill. There are a number of exemptions. And then there is also the tax deferral program, which allows you to defer the entirety of your real estate bill until you either sell your home or the owner passes away.
And there is, I believe, a 5% interest on that. So the interest does accrue on that and that bill does have to be paid at some point. But I think understanding that a lot of our longtime residents may have paid a small amount for their home relative to what it's worth now, I think that's an option that may work for some people. So there are things out there to help folks with real estate taxes in a number of ways. And those are available on the city website, as well as the Invest in Medford website can tell you more about that.
We'll make sure to put links to those in our show notes so people can read more about that.
I wanted to add too that if people are wondering how much this actually impacts you, there's a calculator on the Invest in Medford website and I think the city website too, where you can put in your address and see what the actual impact would be around. Because although there are, for some people on a tight budget, those programs Nicole mentioned are really important, but for others, they might be surprised like what the actual impact is.
I was definitely surprised. I put my house in there. I was surprised by two things. One, the low cost per month that I assumed it would be much higher, but also the assessed value of my home has changed. So lots of good things to know there.
It's worth noting that that calculator is powered by the Department of Revenue for the state. So it's not some magical equation we made up, like this is the state that's saying, you know, here's how your tax bill is gonna be affected. It is based on this fiscal year. So it's, you know, it will change a little bit, but this is our best guess, you know, from the Department of Revenue of how it's gonna impact, what that total bill is gonna look like. Okay. Shelley, were you gonna say something?
No, just that with very high property values, folks are going to expect to have a certain level of municipal service. And this is one of the ways that we can get there. So zooming out, it doesn't seem complicated. Right. We have taxes for a reason.
Yeah, I do like the framing around the community aspect. I think one thing that most folks that I talk to in the city agree with is they care about their neighbors, they care about people in the city, and this is a way of doing that, of paying a little bit of extra money or a little bit more money than we were paying to make sure that people are taken care of or that we're moving towards the city that I think everybody would agree that they want.
Yeah, I think that is a really helpful framing. So yeah, it seems like a vote no would have some kind of grim impacts, but I'm wondering if these measures do pass, when we would expect to see like the increase in our taxes and then the like revenue for the city.
Absolutely. So this will impact our next fiscal year budget. So if these don't pass the fiscal year in June, July, well, not what goes into effect in July, what's being established by June, that's where the cuts are going to come in if these don't pass. If they do pass, we can avoid those cuts. We don't have to have this conversation in June and people will see the impact on their tax bills actually in January 2025. So very quick turnaround.
Question six actually is a little different. It won't go into effect right away because that project needs to move on a little bit further is my understanding. But we do have the calculator just for simplicity. It includes all three questions. So that's the total amount. But seven and eight, if they pass, will go into effect in January 2025. And question six will be a little bit later, depending on how that project advances.
It's really helpful to know, thank you. Anything else anybody wants to add or mention before we wrap up? I wanted to add, because I don't think we went over this, but because some people with the funds that are coming in want more detail about where they'll go, but if they look on
the wording for question eight. There are there are some things that are very specific like last year when there were cuts to with band and things like that one of the things that came up was they said well a lot there weren't a lot of people who chose band or color guard or those and it
brought up the problem was like that was because of the way it was scheduled and there were scheduling issues. And so question A, which is like the expansion of the school budget, is going would be part of it would be going to like changing the schedule so that more students can choose the arts.
I know Medford always prides itself in investing in the arts, and I do think we have some good programs. Last year, my daughter was on Color Guard just for the year, and watching the band in the Color Guard, I was moved, and I was like, this is Medford? This is amazing. I was so proud of it.
you know, having more kids be able to be a part of that and the community that comes from being from that is amazing. And the other was expanding the vocational program, because we are lucky to have a vocational school, but sometimes they don't offer things and kids have to go to other schools like Minuteman. So increasing that helps them to, you know, stay in Medford and have those opportunity. So I just wanted to mention those, because I think they're both really important. And I know sometimes I focus on elementary,
Because that's my world. But those are, you know, those are high school initiatives. Yeah. And to jump on your point, Christine, about the vocational school, too, is one of the ideas I've seen is because there is such an interest in the vocational programming, some of the different offerings have waitlists and making sure every student that's interested in a specific offering can actually get into that class and get into that program. Yeah.
Thank you. And if anyone wants to be more involved in your campaign, is there a way that they can reach out or a way they can get more involved?
Yeah, so we are investinmedford.com. That is great for FAQs, the calculator, just going over the questions that say, here's what it's gonna say on the ballot and here's what this means, because there is specific language you have to use on ballots, which is sometimes not the way we all talk. And then you can learn how to volunteer or donate or just spread the word. Thank you.
Are there any upcoming events or? Yes, well, this weekend is like the canvassing kickoff. There's a whole list. I think all the weekends coming up or having their be canvassing events. And then in addition, there's a number of house parties that are going on to in different neighborhoods just to be able to talk for the folks working on campaigns and just have conversations with your neighbors. So if you reach out on that contact form on the website and say, hey, I'm
interested in the house party or I'd like to attend a house party, we'll make sure we can connect you with one in your neighborhood that works for your schedule. Or you can always host one. Yeah, so hosting an event to learn more, going to an event to learn more, also looking out for canvassing opportunities and canvassers coming to your neighborhood to talk to you. Great. And if you want a lawn sign there on that contact tab on the website too, there's a link or
we can click to order a yard sign. We need to get out more signs. There's so many out, but in certain parts of Medford, we could use some more yes signs. Perfect. Awesome. So get a yard sign through the website as well. Yeah. All right. Well, this was very informative. Thank you all for being with us. And people can vote on November. People can vote on November 5th. Great. Well, thank you so much.
Thank you. Thanks y'all for being here this opportunity.
Thanks so much for listening to today's episode. The Medford Bites podcast is produced and moderated by Danielle Balacca and Shelly Keshaman. Music is made by Hendrik Idonis. We'd love to hear what you think about the podcast. You can reach out to us by email at medfordpod at gmail.com, or you can rate and review the podcast on Apple Podcasts. Thanks so much for listening.
Guys, what's the name of the podcast? Never Bites. Never Bites. Good job.