[SPEAKER_02]: The seventh regular meeting in the Medford City Council will now come to order.
[SPEAKER_03]: Motion by Councilor Knight to suspend the rules, seconded by Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_03]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_03]: The rules are suspended.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mr. President, the reason why I request that we suspend the rules is to take up paper 19071, a petition by Shower Rodriguez relative to the Medford Elementary School Citywide PTO announcing the Harlem Wizards game on March 13th.
[SPEAKER_05]: OK.
[SPEAKER_03]: Petition's presentation to similar matters 19-071, petition by Cheryl Rodriguez, 281 Park Street, Medford, Mass., to address the Medford Elementary Citywide PTO announcing the Harlem Wizards game on March 13th.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mr. President, before you turn the microphone over to Ms.
[SPEAKER_05]: Rodriguez, I do want to make sure that we preface this with the conversation that I had with Ms.
[SPEAKER_05]: Rodriguez and the agreement that we came to was that if I suspend the rules for her to go first, that she would be playing in the game.
[SPEAKER_05]: March 13th.
[SPEAKER_05]: So she's gonna buy a new pair of sneakers and she's gonna be down there on the 13th.
[SPEAKER_03]: If we could please have your name and address for the record, please.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hi, Cheryl Rodriguez, 221 Park Street.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'll see Adam Knight, we'll be playing one-on-one before the start of the game.
[SPEAKER_01]: We'll warm up, yep.
[SPEAKER_01]: So let's all get down there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I'm here tonight representing the Medford Citywide Elementary PTO.
[SPEAKER_01]: which is a collaboration of the Brooks, Columbus, McGlynn, and the Roberts Elementary School.
[SPEAKER_01]: A group of parents got together over the summer and decided to try to work on projects to benefit all of the PTOs.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this is our second community event, and it will be the Harlem Wizards versus the Medford All-Stars.
[SPEAKER_01]: So each elementary school has gathered a team of administrators, staff,
[SPEAKER_01]: teachers that will be playing against the Harlem Wizards.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we're going to have our own little March Madness on March 13th.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wednesday we'll all be in the brand new renovated MHS basketball gym.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doors will open at 6, the game will start at 7, and you'll be able to purchase tickets at harlemwizards.com.
[SPEAKER_01]: This event is open to the entire community and we hope to see a lot of people out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It'll be
[SPEAKER_01]: fun event for everyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: We'll be serving pizza for sale, things like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it'll just be a great time to see members of the community come out.
[SPEAKER_01]: and check out that new gym.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just wanted to thank a few of the people that helped us to make this event possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Hyatt here in Medford is providing the lodging for the Wizards.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bill Blumenright presents the Chevalier Theater, sponsoring our t-shirts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wegmans and McLaughlin Masonry and Boston Sports and Wellness is also helping us to make this event possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And anyone that buys tickets this week will be entered to win this fabulous basketball.
[SPEAKER_01]: So go to hollandwizards.com to buy tickets and help support your local PTOs.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thanks.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Cheryl, if I may, is the only way to purchase tickets through the website?
[SPEAKER_01]: We do have a limited amount of paper tickets, so people can contact the individual PTOs or myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I'm sure they can, if they contact the council, someone can get to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we can sell paper tickets.
[SPEAKER_01]: The general admission tickets are $15.
[SPEAKER_01]: We'll have some available at the door if we're not sold out, and those will be $18.
[SPEAKER_01]: Great, thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: What time is the game?
[SPEAKER_01]: The game's at 7 on Wednesday, March 13.
[SPEAKER_09]: Second.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion of Councilor Dello Russo to approve, seconded by Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_03]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_03]: Motion's approved.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Scarpelli, I apologize.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not lit up.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: Just, this is a great event.
[SPEAKER_10]: I know it works and other communities have done a great job.
[SPEAKER_10]: Just a heads up, Cheryl.
[SPEAKER_10]: In a neighboring community, the first alley-oop broke the backboard.
[SPEAKER_10]: And they had to play half-court, three on three.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I know Mr. Maloney's at the high school.
[SPEAKER_10]: I know we have the portable nets that maybe just have one available just in case.
[SPEAKER_10]: I didn't expect it, but it almost ruined that night.
[SPEAKER_10]: But it was an amazing event.
[SPEAKER_10]: They had about 3,000 seats sold, so, and it's a lot of fun.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's a great family event.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's really fun.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's like, it's now the better version of the Column Globetrotter, so it's a good time.
[SPEAKER_08]: Right here in beautiful Medford.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Vice President Alongo-Kern.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you, President Falco.
[SPEAKER_08]: I was going to mention the price of the tickets, because Bichero mentioned it at the end, $15 a ticket.
[SPEAKER_08]: That's for general admission seating, and I think any way you sit, you're going to have a good seat, because it is a small arena.
[SPEAKER_08]: So I want to thank Cheryl and the PTO from all four elementary schools for getting this community event together.
[SPEAKER_08]: It's going to raise money for the kids' schools.
[SPEAKER_08]: It's the second event that has been put on.
[SPEAKER_08]: The first was the lottery that everybody knows of, the $5,000 for a Disney World Trip that one of Medford's own won.
[SPEAKER_08]: And that raised a great amount of money for the schools.
[SPEAKER_08]: So anything we can do for our kids is fantastic.
[SPEAKER_08]: And thank you to the PTOs for all the hard work they
[SPEAKER_08]: they do.
[SPEAKER_08]: It's going to be a great night and hopefully a lot of Medford residents show up and support the schools.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Cheryl, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you to all the PTOs that are involved.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_03]: While we're under suspension, Consular Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_10]: If I can go to table
[SPEAKER_10]: items, item 19-037, Victor License for 711-69 Fellsway West Mass.
[SPEAKER_10]: I know the petition has been here for a few weeks and had some questions.
[SPEAKER_10]: We had some issues.
[SPEAKER_10]: I know that one of the concerns is a permit for 24 hours.
[SPEAKER_10]: He's taking that off this evening.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, on the motion of Scarpelli that we take
[SPEAKER_03]: 19-037 from the table, seconded by Councilor Light.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_03]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_03]: It is taken from the table.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_10]: Apologize for jumping the gun, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_03]: No worries.
[SPEAKER_10]: But I know the petitioner's here this evening.
[SPEAKER_10]: He's here tonight just asking for the petition for crime and victim license for the location, not the 24-hour extension.
[SPEAKER_10]: So that is gonna be something separate.
[SPEAKER_10]: Is that correct?
[SPEAKER_10]: That's correct.
[SPEAKER_12]: Office is already, you know, processed to filling, getting... If we could please have your name and address for the record, please.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_12]: Nadeem Shakur, 69 Bell Sway West, Medford, Massachusetts, and I'm the area rep.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay, so at the time, Mr. President, we've reviewed and gone over all of the requested information.
[SPEAKER_10]: Everything seems to be in order.
[SPEAKER_10]: I move forward with this portion of the request.
[SPEAKER_10]: In favor.
[SPEAKER_03]: So on the motion of...
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Scarapelli to approve the common vigil license 711-69 Fellows Way West, Medford, Mass.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion of Councilor Scarapelli, seconded by Councilor Caraviello, Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mr. President, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'd request that a 90-day review be placed on this paper by way of amendment, and I'd also ask that
[SPEAKER_05]: It's a convictual license, not a special permit, correct?
[SPEAKER_05]: That's the 90-day review we placed on the convictual license.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you'd like to amend for a 90-day review?
[SPEAKER_05]: Just based upon the nature of the business, Mr. President, that we can take a 90-day review on it.
[SPEAKER_03]: OK.
[SPEAKER_03]: So on the motion of Consul Escarpelli, seconded by a Consul and I, and amended by a Consul and I, for a 90-day review.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mr. Secretary, would you please call the roll?
[SPEAKER_13]: Councilor Caraviello?
[SPEAKER_13]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_13]: Councilor Dello Russo?
[SPEAKER_13]: Affirmative.
[SPEAKER_13]: Councilor Knight?
[SPEAKER_13]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_13]: Vice President Lungo-Koehn?
[SPEAKER_13]: Councilor Marks?
[SPEAKER_13]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_13]: Councilor Scarpelli?
[SPEAKER_13]: President Falco?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative.
[SPEAKER_03]: Motion passes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Motion to revert to the regular order of business by Councilor Knight, seconded by Vice President Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hearings 19-016.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is notice of a public hearing.
[SPEAKER_03]: A continued public hearing will be held by the Medford City Council and the Howard F. Alden Memorial Auditorium, 85 George P. Hassett Drive, Medford, Massachusetts on Tuesday evening, February 26th, 2019 at 7 p.m.
[SPEAKER_03]: on a petition from Carlos A. Alcantara of ALC Auto Sales Incorporated of 407 Rare Mystic Ave., Unit 36A, Medford for Class II Used Auto Sales Use Special Permit.
[SPEAKER_03]: in accordance with Chapter 94 Zoning Ordinance of the City of Medford, Section 94-148D, Table of Use Regulations, Automobile Uses 27A, for permission to operate its Class II second-hand motor vehicle sales at 407 Rare Mystic Avenue, Unit 36A, Medford, Massachusetts, a Commercial II Zoning District.
[SPEAKER_03]: The public hearing is a continuation of a public hearing begun
[SPEAKER_03]: in a City Council meeting on January 15th, 2019.
[SPEAKER_03]: The hearing was referred to the Committee of the Whole for a meeting on January 23rd, 2019, and a further meeting on February 13th, 2019.
[SPEAKER_03]: The Committee of the Whole referred the hearing back to City Council on February 13th, 2019.
[SPEAKER_03]: Petition and plan may be seen in the office of the City Clerk, Medford City Hall, Medford, Massachusetts.
[SPEAKER_03]: Call 781-393-2425 for any accommodations
[SPEAKER_03]: Indoor Aids, TDD 781-393-2516.
[SPEAKER_03]: The City of Medford is an EEO-AA-504 employer.
[SPEAKER_03]: By order of the Medford City Council, Adam L. Hurtabese, City Clerk.
[SPEAKER_03]: At this point I declare the public hearing open.
[SPEAKER_03]: The public hearing is now open to those in favor of the petition.
[SPEAKER_03]: Anyone in favor of the petition, could you please step forward and give your name and address for the record.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, who hasn't already spoken in favor yet.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hearing and seeing none, I declare this portion of the hearing closed.
[SPEAKER_03]: Anyone in opposition to the petition, please step forward if you have not stepped forward already.
[SPEAKER_03]: Could we please, at this point, we just need your name and address for the record.
[SPEAKER_12]: Sure, it's Bill O'Keefe, Kilgore Ave, Method Mass.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Mr. O'Keefe.
[SPEAKER_03]: Anyone else?
[SPEAKER_03]: that has not spoken previously that is not in favor of this petition.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hearing and seeing none, this part of the hearing is closed.
[SPEAKER_03]: At this point, I'll call upon the chairperson of licensing, Consular Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_10]: I know that the petitioner isn't here this evening.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think we have
[SPEAKER_10]: We have reached out to different departments.
[SPEAKER_10]: There were some questions that were brought up in a subcommittee meeting in regards of the licensing departments, the approving departments, giving the proper information needed to approve.
[SPEAKER_10]: We've talked to both FIRE and Mr. Moki in the building department.
[SPEAKER_10]: And they were under the impression that this
[SPEAKER_10]: request was only for a used car dealership for the outside of the premises, not on the inside.
[SPEAKER_10]: So at this time, I would declare this to be a petition that's not in good standing in the fact that what's being asked now is to house
[SPEAKER_10]: automobiles with gasoline tanks in the facility.
[SPEAKER_10]: What we were told is that Mr. Mulkey himself told me that what would be needed would be
[SPEAKER_10]: retrofitted walls that are fire safe and so many other variables that he wouldn't have approved that scenario.
[SPEAKER_10]: And so I know that other council might have talked to the fire department, but with that said, I think this should go back to the petitioner and refiled with the proper documentation.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Scott Belli.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mr. President, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_05]: With the petitioner is not present this evening, I don't feel as though it would be appropriate for us to take a vote with him not here.
[SPEAKER_05]: So with that being said, I'd request that this matter be moved to the 3-12 agenda for a council vote on the special permit, with notice being given to the gentleman that he's requested to appear.
[SPEAKER_05]: Failure to appear will result in the council voting for his permit without him present.
[SPEAKER_05]: But at this point in time, the gentleman's not here.
[SPEAKER_05]: So I'd ask that we continue the matter for three weeks and allow the gentleman the opportunity to come here and be available to us when we take this vote.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion of Councilor Knight to move this to a date certain, which would be March 12th, 2019.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_10]: I second that, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_10]: Supporting Councilor Knight, I think that's appropriate.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think Mr. Akutera is very confused with this whole proceeding.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I think that we wait for him to explain and move forward with it.
[SPEAKER_10]: OK.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you, Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_08]: Vice President Longo.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you, President Falco.
[SPEAKER_08]: And in the meantime, if we could just get a written update from
[SPEAKER_08]: Building Commissioner Moki, I think that's very important information and information that we didn't have at last week's meeting.
[SPEAKER_08]: I know there was questions with regards to the fire department as well, not knowing the logistics of the license request.
[SPEAKER_08]: And one of my two concerns was housing vehicles in the building, although it was dissuaded a little bit because
[SPEAKER_08]: other unit owners at times have a vehicle here and there in the building.
[SPEAKER_08]: So, you know, I was just confused on that matter.
[SPEAKER_08]: But hearing from the building department and possibly the fire department on the logistics of the application would be very helpful in determining, especially where there's a safety issue involved.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'd appreciate that.
[SPEAKER_08]: Vice President Longo, I just want to make sure, do you want to get a report back from the building department?
[SPEAKER_08]: Just, yeah, there was mention of Councilor Scarpelli doing his due diligence and speaking to the building department.
[SPEAKER_08]: I just also would like to see that in writing, because I didn't speak to the building department.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's a great point brought up that if we could get a report back from Mr. Moki.
[SPEAKER_10]: I believe the difference, the question was, I think that Councilor Langley-Curran brought this up a few times, that if there were propane, why couldn't there be the gas?
[SPEAKER_10]: That was the big question.
[SPEAKER_10]: what he was explaining to us, it's two totally different scenarios and requirements.
[SPEAKER_10]: So if Mr. Moki can just share that with us so that's on the record, that'd be perfect.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: And if I may, just... Yes, Vice President.
[SPEAKER_08]: I think that is important because if you have... I know there's churches in that building and a number of other people that work there day in and day out.
[SPEAKER_08]: And to have any exhaust, whether that's propane or gas or anything that's...
[SPEAKER_08]: worrisome in the building, it would be nice to know the difference of why propane is maybe okay, and why gas isn't, for the council to, in case we ever have to examine this specific petition in the future, or any others that have to do with any type of vehicles in the building, that's concerning in general.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Vice President Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion, Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_06]: Mr. President, is there a reason why the petitioner is not here this evening?
[SPEAKER_03]: I have not received any notification.
[SPEAKER_06]: Was he notified to be here this evening?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_13]: Was he notified?
[SPEAKER_13]: Yes, he was notified he was going to be here this evening.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion of Council and I, seconded by Councilor Scarapelli, that this hearing be moved to a date certain, March 12, 2019.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_03]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Knight and Councilor Caraviello, please mark in opposition.
[SPEAKER_03]: I apologize.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Marks and Councilor Caraviello, please mark them in opposition.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Dello Russo.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'd just like the record to be shown that the microphone system is still in disrepair.
[SPEAKER_03]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_03]: That was actually on one of our priority lists that we did not get to tonight, so that will be at the next Committee of the Whole.
[SPEAKER_04]: because in the winter they can't be, the wires don't fix as they would in the springtime.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Motions, orders and resolutions.
[SPEAKER_03]: 19-060 offered by Vice President Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_03]: Be it resolved that the administration update the Medford City Council regarding negotiations with Tufts University
[SPEAKER_03]: Vice President Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you, President Falco.
[SPEAKER_08]: With regards to Tufts University, there's been, I believe, two or three agreements since I've been a city councilor over the last several years with regards to money, agreements with regards to money in lieu of taxes that has been given to the city.
[SPEAKER_08]: And I believe that the administration is
[SPEAKER_08]: negotiating currently.
[SPEAKER_08]: That is what I'm under the understanding.
[SPEAKER_08]: So I'd just like to see if that negotiation is complete, if anybody has any information on that.
[SPEAKER_08]: We haven't been apprised.
[SPEAKER_08]: I know negotiations sometimes are not involved, but it is important.
[SPEAKER_08]: People ask me as a Councilor all the time, and I'm sure my colleagues, you know, what is Tufts doing for us?
[SPEAKER_08]: And if you go online or do any research, you'll see all the different things that they do help the city with.
[SPEAKER_08]: Community Day,
[SPEAKER_08]: going into the schools and doing certain programs.
[SPEAKER_08]: They give donations back to the Royal House, the Brooks Estates, Chamber of Commerce, Historical Society.
[SPEAKER_08]: But my resolution really has to do with the lump sum that has been contracted to be given to the city from Tufts University pretty much since early 2000s that I'm aware of.
[SPEAKER_08]: So I want to know what is the administration doing to make sure we continue that
[SPEAKER_08]: And has there been any discussion what has been discussed?
[SPEAKER_08]: And when should we expect finality of a new agreement?
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Vice President Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mr. President, I thank Councilor Lungo for bringing this forward.
[SPEAKER_05]: And I think that payment in lieu of tax agreements is something that are very important for us here in the community because it allows us the opportunity to capture non-tax revenue and to capture that revenue in a reoccurring fashion.
[SPEAKER_05]: So with that being said, Mr. President, I'd like to amend the paper and also request that
[SPEAKER_05]: the city administration report back to the council.
[SPEAKER_05]: If they have identified any property owning non-profit tax exempt properties, they can also approach to discuss whether or not we can implement a payment of lieu of taxes program with them as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion of Vice President Lungo-Koehn, seconded by Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_03]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_03]: Motion passes.
[SPEAKER_03]: 19-061 offered by Vice President Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_03]: Be it resolved that the administration update the Medford City Council with regards to the details of the lawsuit filed against the Sackler family.
[SPEAKER_03]: Vice President Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you, President Falco.
[SPEAKER_08]: This press release came out February 11th with regards to the city filing a public nuisance lawsuit in the United States District Court against pharmaceutical drug manufacturers.
[SPEAKER_08]: And it's a one and a half page
[SPEAKER_08]: press release, which is just something that I'm interested in learning more about as far as the budget's concerned, as far as the specifics of the lawsuit.
[SPEAKER_08]: I know breach of their duties to detect or report suspicious orders of prescription opiates is part of the complaint, but I would like to see if we could get a copy of the actual complaint that was filed.
[SPEAKER_08]: and also just get any other information such as what has been, if this is a contingent fee or have we given a retainer to the law office that is handling this for the city, and if so, how much is that retainer?
[SPEAKER_08]: How much do we expect this to cost?
[SPEAKER_08]: What do we expect to be the outcome?
[SPEAKER_08]: Will we be helping Medford families get reimbursement?
[SPEAKER_08]: I just would like to know the logistics of this.
[SPEAKER_08]: People are asking me,
[SPEAKER_08]: Since the press release has gone out since February 11th, and I don't have the answers except for what's in this press release, because I think something was out a year ago that spoke of it, but not much more detail than what's in the press release.
[SPEAKER_08]: And as a Councilor who will be voting on the budget in June, I want to know how this affects, you know, how this affects the budget.
[SPEAKER_08]: Are we talking a $5,000 retainer or $50,000?
[SPEAKER_08]: relevant to the budget, and I want to know more about it on many different levels.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Vice President Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Dello Russo.
[SPEAKER_03]: I've changed my mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Dello Russo.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion of Vice President Lungo-Koehn, seconded by Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_03]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_03]: Motion passes.
[SPEAKER_03]: 19-069.
[SPEAKER_03]: Offered by Councilor Caraviellola.
[SPEAKER_03]: Be it resolved that the Medford City Council have the Code Enforcement Officers send literature
[SPEAKER_03]: to all retail establishments, informing them of the signed ordinances in time frame for enforcement.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_06]: Mr. President, you know, as we get more and more visitors coming to the city with the Chevalier Auditorium and other things happening here, one of the complaints I hear from many, even our own residents, is our signed ordinances is just not even been enforced at all.
[SPEAKER_06]: More and more stores, the windows are just totally full, signs everywhere.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I think it's about time that, and as I said, I know that our enforcement department is cut thin as it is.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I think it's about time that we send out literature to all these business owners throughout the city, letting them know what our sign ordinance is.
[SPEAKER_06]: give them some type of time frame for when we'll be able to enforce them.
[SPEAKER_06]: I mean, the good weather's coming out and people are going to be starting walking the streets again.
[SPEAKER_06]: The windows of these stores are deplorable.
[SPEAKER_06]: They're just full of literature and signs.
[SPEAKER_06]: Not that we want to be anti-business, but the curb appeal of our city is going down.
[SPEAKER_06]: I think it's about time that we step up and start cleaning up the windows
[SPEAKER_06]: and making them look a lot better than what they are.
[SPEAKER_06]: So they say, if I could ask the building department to send it out and give them 60 days, 90 days to conform.
[SPEAKER_06]: If they don't conform, then I think it's about time that we find them.
[SPEAKER_06]: Because you go out throughout the whole city, there's probably 90% of the businesses are in violation.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mr. President, I'd like to request that the Code Enforcement Officer also visit Lawrence Memorial Hospital for compliance with the sign ordinance.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's been brought to my attention by a number of neighbors that a temporary sign has been erected that's in violation of our sign ordinance.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's causing blight and eyesore for the residents in the neighborhood, and they've requested that the Code Enforcement Officer make a visit over to Lawrence Memorial Hospital and remind them of the criteria that's included in our sign ordinance, one of them being a special permit from the City Council for a sign that is outside the scope of our ordinance.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion by Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_09]: Just if I could, on line with Councilor Caraviello, I would just ask also if we can send a letter to the Chamber of Commerce and maybe we can work through the Chamber of Commerce to have them alert their business owners regarding the sign ordinance.
[SPEAKER_09]: And if anyone needs
[SPEAKER_09]: to be enlightened on what the current, because the sign on ordinances is rather lengthy and new businesses may not be that familiar with it.
[SPEAKER_09]: So I would ask as a first step that we also send a letter to the president of the chamber asking that they contact their membership also about adhering to the local sign ordinance.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sounds good.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion of Councilor Caraviello, seconded by Councilor Knight,
[SPEAKER_03]: as amended by Councilor Knight and Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_03]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_03]: The motion passes.
[SPEAKER_03]: 19-070, offered by Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_03]: Be it so ordained, Medford City Council adopt the following ordinance.
[SPEAKER_03]: Tree preservation, protection, and replacement ordinance.
[SPEAKER_03]: Findings, intent, and purpose.
[SPEAKER_03]: The City Council has determined that many trees are being lost without replacement.
[SPEAKER_03]: to demolition of existing buildings in order to construct new buildings and lot clearing in connection with the construction of new buildings on previously undeveloped land.
[SPEAKER_03]: The city council has further determined that trees have been lost, severely damaged, or disfigured.
[SPEAKER_09]: Mr. President, move to waive the reading and if a brief synopsis could be given.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion of Council Marks to waive the reading for brief synopsis.
[SPEAKER_03]: Given by council and I. Proposed.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mr. President, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_05]: We're picking up where we left off last week.
[SPEAKER_05]: I had put forward a resolution requesting that the city solicitor draft an ordinance of similar fashion that would be considered a tree preservation protection and replacement ordinance.
[SPEAKER_05]: The council had expressed some concern relative to the devil being in the details.
[SPEAKER_05]: As such, it was a very long meeting as well last week.
[SPEAKER_05]: I think we didn't get out of it until about half to 12 o'clock.
[SPEAKER_05]: So as such, I decided that it was in the best fashion for the deliberative process to withdraw the paper and to put forward some language, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_05]: So here before us, we have this evening is going to be a launching pad to start a discussion on the regulation of private trees in our community.
[SPEAKER_05]: And if we go through the ordinance briefly, we'll have section one, which would be definitions defining, you know, the parameters of applicability, certain exemptions for individuals who'd be exempt.
[SPEAKER_05]: In applicability, it would be for, right now in the draft proposal, lots that are equal to or greater than 10,000 square feet, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_05]: Those would be lots that are
[SPEAKER_05]: large enough to be developed for multi-family homes if three families or larger.
[SPEAKER_05]: I've also included in this some language relative to an 18-month rolling review period, which would be in line with our demolition delay.
[SPEAKER_05]: We have a second section related to applicability and the requirements that are going to be asked of individuals that do not have an exempt property.
[SPEAKER_05]: Also, there's certain protections in there relative to change of ownership.
[SPEAKER_05]: If a lot is clear-cut but the trees are not replaced or the tree farm hasn't been contributed to,
[SPEAKER_05]: There's restrictions and requirements relative to change of ownership.
[SPEAKER_05]: We also have the third section, which would be the process and how a permit is going to be issued.
[SPEAKER_05]: Activities not requiring a permit, Mr. President, exempt activities that wouldn't require a permit like pruning and emergencies.
[SPEAKER_05]: Ultimately, what this ordinance does is it defines what would be a preferably protected tree.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then it establishes a criteria to remove it.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's a launching pad, as I said before.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not the final product.
[SPEAKER_05]: And I'd like to ask my council colleagues to indulge me by allowing this paper to be referred to the zoning subcommittee for us to have further deliberations with Go Green Medford, the Forestry Department, and legal counsel for us to come up with a draft that we can all live with, debate, and discuss.
[SPEAKER_05]: Ultimately, this paper right here would not be ready to be voted on this evening.
[SPEAKER_05]: I've had discussions with our code enforcement officer and there are some areas that are lacking relative to safety concerns.
[SPEAKER_05]: For example, last night we had a very windy night.
[SPEAKER_05]: A lot of trees were damaged in private residences.
[SPEAKER_05]: If a tree is on a private residence on lot A and it's caused damage to lot B based upon the decision of our tree warden or our arborist, then appropriate steps need to be taken to protect that individual's property.
[SPEAKER_05]: We have no control in this proposed ordinance to do that.
[SPEAKER_05]: I've had discussions with Mr. Bavuso.
[SPEAKER_05]: I've had discussions with Ms.
[SPEAKER_05]: Tudin.
[SPEAKER_05]: I've had discussions with Mr. Rumley.
[SPEAKER_05]: I've had discussions with Mr. Campolis from the Forestry Department as well.
[SPEAKER_05]: And they think that this is a great starting point for a discussion.
[SPEAKER_05]: But in terms of applicability in Medford, there will need to be changes.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's why I make the motion to have this sent to the Zoning Subcommittee and then ask my council colleagues to indulge me and such.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Dello Russo.
[SPEAKER_04]: Mr. President, I welcome Councilor Knight's
[SPEAKER_04]: effort in this matter, he's clearly, as he always does, as he always does, researched this subject matter and placed necessary hours in working on this, and also reaching out to people who are pertinent to these matters, all wonderful qualities of a city councilor.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so I equally regard his wisdom to move this to an appropriate committee so that we might have more fruitful and detailed discussion
[SPEAKER_04]: because bogging down such discussion on the council's floor might become tedious and burdensome.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'd also like to point out that there are so many items in this that I'd like to discuss in great detail with regards to legalities, appropriateness, life, liberty, the pursuit of happiness.
[SPEAKER_04]: that I look forward to having a robust and rich discussion on this matter so that people's interests might truly be protected, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I want to, again, express my gratitude to the councilor for the outstanding job he's done in the preparation of this document.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Dello Russo.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_09]: And I, too, want to thank my council colleague.
[SPEAKER_09]: Last week's motion was to have the city solicitor draft language
[SPEAKER_09]: around a city ordinance, but the language wasn't clear.
[SPEAKER_09]: There really wasn't any language, just a direction.
[SPEAKER_09]: And clearly we have something to work from now.
[SPEAKER_09]: So this was very helpful and I appreciate the fact that Councilor and I did that.
[SPEAKER_09]: As I stated last week, and I'll state again publicly, Mr. President, on private property of homeowners, I believe homeowners should have the right to remove a tree on private property.
[SPEAKER_09]: If we're talking about development with large developers that are coming in and declaring land and so forth, I think that's worthy of an ordinance to protect our shade trees and our trees that might be endangered.
[SPEAKER_09]: And I would support that, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_09]: I also want to state an ordinance is great, and we can follow an ordinance.
[SPEAKER_09]: But we also have to put our money where our mouth is.
[SPEAKER_09]: And in the last several budgets, there is a pittance of money to replace shade trees within our community.
[SPEAKER_09]: And Aggie Tudin was good enough to respond back.
[SPEAKER_09]: I believe it was the next day from the council meeting regarding something that Councilor Caraviello brought up about the, if someone buys a tree, the city will match the tree.
[SPEAKER_09]: And Aggie Toonan came back right away, our tree warden, and said, that's a great program, and it's working.
[SPEAKER_09]: I mentioned the Back of the Curb program, which I believe at the time, and don't quote me, but there's been a dozen or so trees this year planted on private property that the city will purchase a tree for $500, $600, $700 at the request of the homeowner and plant a tree on private property in areas that
[SPEAKER_09]: You probably couldn't put a tree because the sidewalk may be too small.
[SPEAKER_09]: It may be a tough intersection to put a tree.
[SPEAKER_09]: And I think that's an important program too that we run, but needs to be funded.
[SPEAKER_09]: So as part of the ordinance, I'm also going to push in budget time that we increase our funding for our public shade trees within the community too, Mr. President, because I believe they go hand in hand.
[SPEAKER_09]: And I want to thank my colleague for bringing this up tonight.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_03]: Point of clarification, Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mr. President, one of the key reasons why I brought this thing forward was basically just because of what Councilor Mack said, that we're having a lack of investment in the shade trees.
[SPEAKER_05]: And one of the key components of the tree replacement zone, the zoning amendment would be that we have a tree replacement fund.
[SPEAKER_05]: So if private homeowners that take down a preferably protected tree are unable
[SPEAKER_05]: to replace it on property, they'll pay into a tree fund to the city and the city will have a revolving account and a funding mechanism to actually purchase shade trees to be used in public lands and as part of the back street, back of the sidewalk program.
[SPEAKER_05]: So yeah, it's right on the ball.
[SPEAKER_05]: I think these are some of the issues that we need to vet out, but I think we're really all on the same page in terms of some of the important aspects that we need to put in there.
[SPEAKER_05]: So I thank Councilor Marks for his kind words.
[SPEAKER_05]: And it was the right course withdrawing and bringing forward language from last week's meeting.
[SPEAKER_05]: So I'm glad that we had the opportunity to debate that and discuss it and bring this measure forward.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion of Councilor Knight, we have name and address for the record, please.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_07]: Curtis Tootin, 38 Early Ave.
[SPEAKER_07]: And I'm here tonight representing Medford's Energy and Environment Committee.
[SPEAKER_07]: So first, thank you, councilors, for making trees a priority.
[SPEAKER_07]: Medford's tree canopy has been in decline, so protecting significant community trees is more important than ever.
[SPEAKER_07]: Knowing how critical trees are to public health and ecology,
[SPEAKER_07]: A subcommittee of the Medford Energy and Environment Committee has worked on a report about local tree protection and other aspects of the proposed resolution.
[SPEAKER_07]: It will be completed soon, and the group of volunteers who have spent months working on the draft looks forward to seeing this through.
[SPEAKER_07]: Again, we need to grow our city's tree canopy and not just protect and replace what we have left.
[SPEAKER_07]: Tonight's proposed version of a tree ordinance should be improved on and passed at a later date.
[SPEAKER_07]: So we look forward, overall, to being part of the process when that report is available soon.
[SPEAKER_07]: So again, thank you tonight.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion of Consul Knight, seconded by Consul Scarpelli, to move this paper to the subcommittee on zoning, which is chaired by Consul Scarpelli and members Consul Knight and Vice President Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_03]: With notice to legal counsel in the Forestry Department.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_03]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_03]: Motion passes and the paper is moved to the zoning subcommittee.
Motion to take papers in the hands of the clerk.
[SPEAKER_03]: Second.
[SPEAKER_03]: Motion by Councilor Knight to take papers in the hands of the clerk, seconded by Councilor Dello Russo.
[SPEAKER_03]: Offered by Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_03]: Be it resolved that the library capital campaign be discussed.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'll take that title, Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'll take that.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'll take any title.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_09]: It was about two months ago we had a person from the Library Foundation Committee appear before this council.
[SPEAKER_09]: It was at the request of I think it was Councilor Lungo-Koehn at the time.
[SPEAKER_09]: And the advisor that was hired by the Library Foundation with the mission of raising private funds
[SPEAKER_09]: to help with the capital campaign towards a $34 million public library.
[SPEAKER_09]: As we all remember, the city of Medford was awarded a $12.3 million grant from the Mass Board of Library Commissioners to construct this $34 million library.
[SPEAKER_09]: And the advisor that appeared before the podium stated, based on their
[SPEAKER_09]: recent outreach and discussion among the Library Foundation group and their different outreach, they anticipate to raise about $3.5 million.
[SPEAKER_09]: The reason why I bring this up, Mr. President, and I mentioned it two months ago that we have a Committee of the Whole meeting, this is a very vital financial economic issue in this community.
[SPEAKER_09]: And the reason why I bring it up is at the time when we were building a new library, or plans to build a new library, it was mentioned that a $34 million library, based on $12.3 million grant, would leave us paying over $18 million for a balance.
[SPEAKER_09]: And at the time, it was Mayor Burke that mentioned that she was going to raise privately
[SPEAKER_09]: the amount of the grant.
[SPEAKER_09]: So she was going to go out and raise $12.3 million privately, the amount of the grant.
[SPEAKER_09]: And this was stated.
[SPEAKER_09]: This isn't just off the top of my head.
[SPEAKER_09]: It was stated on two occasions publicly, one during November 2017, that Mayor Burke said she was hopeful donations would be able to match the funds from the state.
[SPEAKER_09]: And this is her quote, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_09]: We're very optimistic from those that have already been interviewed and people that we have reached out to that we'll be able to parlay the state grant, double it with foundation money, and then be left for the city to put up a piece of about $5 million, which is our goal.
[SPEAKER_09]: We had the foundation advisor appear before us stating $3.5 million was probably an aggressive figure.
[SPEAKER_09]: But that was what they were looking to raise.
[SPEAKER_09]: And I asked Barbara Kerr, the library director, when she was at the podium, I stated to her unequivocally, where is the $12.3 million that you're going to raise privately?
[SPEAKER_09]: And Barbara Kerr, who has been involved with this library planning from day one, said, oh, I never heard of that figure before.
[SPEAKER_09]: Where did that figure come from?
[SPEAKER_09]: And I said, well, it came from the mayor of this city that it was going to be raised privately.
[SPEAKER_09]: So that's why I keep on raising the issue, Mr. President, because as time goes on now, and we have yet to hear back from the Library Foundation, and I'm sure they're doing yeoman's work, reaching out to people, trying to gather money, but as time goes on, there's going to be a rather large commitment outstanding for the taxpayers of this community.
[SPEAKER_09]: And I, as one member of the council, can't turn back to taxpayers and say, you know what?
[SPEAKER_09]: They may have made a commitment, but the $12.3 million they may have said they were going to get, they only got $3 million.
[SPEAKER_09]: So guess what?
[SPEAKER_09]: You're going to pay the difference.
[SPEAKER_09]: That may have been a game changer, Mr. President, at the time.
[SPEAKER_09]: So when you look at the figures, $12.3 million grant, the foundation money that they're saying, just say $3.5, it may be more, it may be less, who knows?
[SPEAKER_09]: Maybe they'll raise the whole amount.
[SPEAKER_09]: I don't know, but I don't get a warm, fuzzy feeling to date regarding the private funds.
[SPEAKER_09]: So that's $15.8 million.
[SPEAKER_09]: You take that from the $34 million, it leaves you a balance of $18.2 million.
[SPEAKER_09]: We have to start discussing this.
[SPEAKER_09]: We should be having, if not weekly, monthly meetings with the library, with the administration, saying, how are we going to pay for this?
[SPEAKER_09]: And I don't want to hear, well, year one, we're all set for year one.
[SPEAKER_09]: There's year two.
[SPEAKER_09]: There's year three, four, five, six.
[SPEAKER_09]: There's other projects in line, like the fire department, Mr. President, like the high school, like the police station.
[SPEAKER_09]: The fire station, the plans that were made with the fire station were made based on the fact that private funds were going to be garnered to support this project.
[SPEAKER_09]: Now, if that doesn't come through, does that push the fire station from year 2024 to 2029, 2030?
[SPEAKER_09]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_09]: And no one's talking about it.
[SPEAKER_09]: But I'm going to continually bring it up, Mr. President, because it disturbs me when the director of the library that's been involved from day one never recalls a commitment made by the administration of $12.3 million being raised privately.
[SPEAKER_09]: How do you overlook that as the library director involved from day one?
[SPEAKER_09]: That's not a small little fact that you can overlook.
[SPEAKER_09]: That's huge how you're going to pay for this.
[SPEAKER_09]: So again, Mr. President, respectfully,
[SPEAKER_09]: I asked that we have a meeting with the library foundation group that's set up and the library commissioners, I think they should be part of this also.
[SPEAKER_09]: I've spoken to library commissioners regarding this and they're eager to find out what's going on as well, to be quite honest with you.
[SPEAKER_09]: And we have yet to get an answer from this administration other than the fact, in my opinion, that the mayor is hiding from her original commitment.
[SPEAKER_09]: Now, if the mayor thinks she was too aggressive at the time, happened to be during a city debate for office, and maybe she was being a little overly aggressive to Ghana support.
[SPEAKER_09]: But now if that's the case, Mr. President, we still have to make ends meet with this project.
[SPEAKER_09]: And according to my figures, there's an $18.2 million balance in this project.
[SPEAKER_09]: So I would ask that we sit up.
[SPEAKER_09]: I know we have a lot of Committee of the Wholes, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_09]: We joked about it tonight while we were in a Committee of the Whole meeting with the administration.
[SPEAKER_09]: But we really need to sit down as a council.
[SPEAKER_09]: because it was the council that took this vote.
[SPEAKER_09]: This was a very difficult vote regarding public safety, regarding a new library, which I don't think anyone feels that we didn't need at the time.
[SPEAKER_09]: But we were sold a bill of goods.
[SPEAKER_09]: This is what's going to happen.
[SPEAKER_09]: This is how we're going to afford it.
[SPEAKER_09]: And now if this is not how it's going to happen, and this is not how we're going to afford it, we should know how it's going to work.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Caraviellola.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_06]: Being a member of the Library Foundation, I could shine a little bit of light on what's happening in the last couple of meetings.
[SPEAKER_06]: That 3.5 number that Holly Sargent spoke about
[SPEAKER_06]: The last time she did it was a few months ago.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's changed a little bit.
[SPEAKER_06]: She's had some discussions with some other people that were involved with fundraising and different projects, and I think the expectation of the money raised is going to be different.
[SPEAKER_06]: I think she'll tell you that when you want to have it for her next report.
[SPEAKER_06]: They've met with the people from the Museum of Science.
[SPEAKER_06]: who have been involved with the Bloomberg Foundation, and they've asked us, they've told us that the recommendation was to increase your expectations.
[SPEAKER_06]: That number is not a number you should be looking at.
[SPEAKER_06]: If you're looking at a much higher number, then you should be asking for a lot more than what we're asking for.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I think with that, there's been a little bit of change in the foundation, and you may see some different strategies coming out.
[SPEAKER_06]: We've also,
[SPEAKER_06]: fine-tuned the list of local donors from the business community.
[SPEAKER_06]: The list that was generated before might have been a little generic.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that's been fine-tuned down to people, you know, real sort of more legitimate sources, you know, taking people off that just came off a general list.
[SPEAKER_06]: And certain members of the foundation are contacting, you know, people to start bringing, to start, you know, developing this.
[SPEAKER_06]: And probably, maybe in May, if everything goes as expected, they may be able to do their first presentation to some people.
[SPEAKER_06]: Again, I know the mayor has requested a 3D slide presentation to have.
[SPEAKER_06]: Like I say, a lot of these are one-time acts, so if you're first time out of the box, it's not a good one.
[SPEAKER_06]: You're not gonna be able to go back.
[SPEAKER_06]: The foundation is doing a lot of work behind the scenes that people don't know about to hopefully get ready for a May ask of some local people to start on the giving program.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you, Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_06]: And if you'd like, we can invite Holly to come back at one of the next few meetings, whatever, and say, just give me a little bit of notice, because she lives up in Maine.
[SPEAKER_06]: And she has to go, so she can make the appropriate plans.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can have her at that committee in the hall.
[SPEAKER_03]: We can invite her to that.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_09]: And I want to thank Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_09]: If people aren't aware, Councilor Caraviello was one of the first people to start
[SPEAKER_09]: speaking about the poor condition of our public library where our students go.
[SPEAKER_09]: And I think he was one that first raised many of the concerns with the leaks and so forth.
[SPEAKER_09]: So I want to thank him for his efforts on this.
[SPEAKER_09]: I just, I don't want people to think for a second that I don't want to see funds raised.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm hoping that we raise the full amount.
[SPEAKER_09]: I just think we should have a contingency plan.
[SPEAKER_09]: And if that doesn't work out, how are we going to pay for this?
[SPEAKER_09]: And it's unfortunate when the mayor can sit back and say, well, if that doesn't work out, we have 60,000 people out here that are going to pay for it.
[SPEAKER_09]: That's not the way we should operate government, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_09]: And there should be, if there's none established now, like they're changing the rules on how they're going to raise money and so forth and different ways of raising money, then we should have a contingency plan on how are we going to afford this if the expectations
[SPEAKER_09]: of what the mayor stated, the 12.3 matching private money doesn't come through, how are we going to gather that money to pay for this library?
[SPEAKER_09]: And if we can't afford it, what are we going to do, Mr. President, moving forward?
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_03]: Vice President Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you, President Falco.
[SPEAKER_08]: I want to thank Councilor Marks for bringing this up.
[SPEAKER_08]: I asked for an update on this a couple months ago due to my concern as well.
[SPEAKER_08]: with the two commitments to raise 12 plus million dollars by the administration and not seeing that happening yet, although I know it's in the works, I am concerned because of the other projects that we also want to get done.
[SPEAKER_08]: The fire station, the fire station improvements, we have the police station bond that we are going to have to start paying back.
[SPEAKER_08]: There's a lot of things that this city needs and
[SPEAKER_08]: I also want to make sure we're on track.
[SPEAKER_08]: I want to make sure that the library moves forward in a timely manner and that it's funded accordingly, like we were promised November 2017 and when the mayor was before us at the council meeting when we agreed to move forward with the library.
[SPEAKER_08]: If I could, Councilor Caraviello, I want to thank you too for all your work on this.
[SPEAKER_08]: I know you mentioned a first presentation in May, but then you also mentioned a new list where we started asking people for money.
[SPEAKER_08]: Has anybody on that list been contacted?
[SPEAKER_08]: Nobody's been contacted yet.
[SPEAKER_06]: What we've done is they have a generic list of a lot of people in the community.
[SPEAKER_06]: And a lot of the people that were on that list
[SPEAKER_06]: were just  they weren't good people to ask.
[SPEAKER_06]: The list has been really  not that they weren't good people to ask, but they shouldn't have been on that list.
[SPEAKER_06]: So the list has been really torn down to some
[SPEAKER_06]: you know, businesses that are larger in size that can afford to make the larger donation.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, and, you know, Barry Sloan is, you know, he's making a lot of the calls to those  to the bigger people that, you know, because, you know, he's got that ability that, you know, we don't have.
[SPEAKER_06]: And other people who  new people on the list.
[SPEAKER_06]: So the goal is to hopefully have something  hopefully in May, later in May, before the summer,
[SPEAKER_06]: to get a feeling onto where we are with this.
[SPEAKER_06]: But I said, when you have Holly come back, I think she'll explain to you what the reasoning was, why the expectation for RASC has gone up from that original number that we had.
[SPEAKER_08]: And we had the original number of 3.5 million that Holly gave us a few months ago.
[SPEAKER_08]: Is there a new number that is out there?
[SPEAKER_06]: We don't have a new number, but there's a different thinking
[SPEAKER_06]: on the amount we should be asking for.
[SPEAKER_06]: Rather than asking for 3.5, we should be asking for a much higher number.
[SPEAKER_08]: And since that meeting, has the commission now understood that the administration's commitment is the 12.3 million?
[SPEAKER_06]: Are we hoping to?
[SPEAKER_06]: The administration isn't really involved in this, other than that that hasn't been discussed.
[SPEAKER_06]: The mayor's, whatever comment the mayor has said or didn't say, that's not part of the foundation.
[SPEAKER_08]: Will the library commission be bringing in the administration to hopefully abide by that commitment?
[SPEAKER_06]: It's not the foundation's job to do that.
[SPEAKER_06]: They're here to raise as much money as possible.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's a private organization.
[SPEAKER_06]: It doesn't answer to the city.
[SPEAKER_06]: Its sole function is to raise as much money as possible for the Medford Public Library.
[SPEAKER_06]: Again, we don't fall under the auspices of the mayor or anybody else.
[SPEAKER_06]: Anne-Marie Irwin is on the commission for a little bit of guidance.
[SPEAKER_03]: It sounds like a lot of these questions probably, which are great questions.
[SPEAKER_06]: But it's a private organization, and their goal is to raise as much money as possible.
[SPEAKER_03]: What information, Councilor Marks?
[SPEAKER_09]: I appreciate you being so candid with us,
[SPEAKER_09]: If it's a private organization, why is our treasurer collector, Anne Marie Irwin, sitting on the committee?
[SPEAKER_06]: She's part of the committee also.
[SPEAKER_06]: She's been asked to be part of the committee.
[SPEAKER_09]: Right.
[SPEAKER_09]: So someone from the administration, a city employee.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm a city employee, so I. Right.
[SPEAKER_09]: Is sitting on this committee, but the mayor has nothing to do with this.
[SPEAKER_06]: Not really.
[SPEAKER_06]: I mean, if she wants to come, she can come.
[SPEAKER_06]: But again, this is.
[SPEAKER_06]: Right.
[SPEAKER_06]: We don't answer to the mayor.
[SPEAKER_06]: Anne Irwin does.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's what Ian Irwin does.
[SPEAKER_06]: But again, the goal of the foundation is to raise as much money as possible.
[SPEAKER_09]: And I hope you do.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I say that the thought process has changed from the last time Hawley was here.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_03]: Vice President Lungo-Koehn has the floor.
[SPEAKER_08]: I appreciate the comments, and I understand that the commission is a separate body that doesn't, you know,
[SPEAKER_08]: But what I'm hearing is that the administration and the commission are not working together, not communicating, not... I'm not hearing that.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm hearing that... My hope... It's sounding like there's no communication to me.
[SPEAKER_08]: But if there is communication, that's what I'm hoping for, that this commitment by the administration to raise $12.3 million
[SPEAKER_08]: is communicated to the foundation, and obviously the administration is helping the foundation raise this money, whether it be everything on top of the 3.5 or that new number, or they're raising the 12.3 and the commission's raising the 3.5 or that new number.
[SPEAKER_08]: We need to make sure those two groups of people are working together, and obviously the council is apprised of what's going on so that we don't get a bond request, like Councilman Marks said, for $20 million in pushing back the FIFA headquarters.
[SPEAKER_08]: back to 2030.
[SPEAKER_08]: I just don't want to see that happen.
[SPEAKER_08]: So I think it is important that we have a meeting on it.
[SPEAKER_08]: I think it's important that we, maybe every few months, we have, when this representative is here from Maine, that she come to a council meeting.
[SPEAKER_08]: Every three, four months, come to a council meeting.
[SPEAKER_08]: Even more than that, if possible, when the ball starts rolling, to give us quarterly updates on where we're at, where we're going, how we foresee things.
[SPEAKER_08]: I understand maybe nobody was solicited yet, but I have talked to a business or two that has been solicited.
[SPEAKER_08]: A business owner contacted me.
[SPEAKER_03]: Vice President Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_08]: Point of information.
[SPEAKER_03]: Point of information, Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_06]: They've been solicited by the Library Foundation, the Alliance here, because no one has been solicited.
[SPEAKER_06]: There's been no solicitation going out there.
[SPEAKER_08]: A reputable business told me they were solicited.
[SPEAKER_06]: Whether or not that's true, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_08]: They didn't solicit my business.
[SPEAKER_06]: Listen, I'll give you one information.
[SPEAKER_06]: There was a company that was hired in the beginning that went out there to get a feel in the community.
[SPEAKER_06]: They didn't ask for any money.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yes, I was interviewed for that.
[SPEAKER_06]: They were interviewing people to see what the response in the community was.
[SPEAKER_06]: Nobody from the Library Foundation has asked anybody for a penny yet.
[SPEAKER_06]: So if anybody says that the Library Foundation has contacted them, they haven't.
[SPEAKER_06]: I can also assure you that the administration is working with the Foundation to make sure that we all work together.
[SPEAKER_03]: Good.
[SPEAKER_03]: Vice President Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Council.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Vice President Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mr. President, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'd request that we amend the paper.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm actually amending the paper by filing an amendment right now, requesting that the Medford Public Library, or its fundraising arm, file an application for determinative eligibility for community preservation funds with the Community Preservation Commission under the funding opportunities for recreational or historic preservation.
[SPEAKER_05]: Ultimately, we have a library there with a number of historic artifacts in it that have been locked up in an attic.
[SPEAKER_05]: We're looking to get these artifacts out of the attic and be more visible and accessible to the public.
[SPEAKER_05]: And also, I can't think of any better recreational facility in our community than a library, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_05]: So I think that these two avenues might be available for us to pursue additional funding.
[SPEAKER_05]: I know Councilor Marks has expressed some concern in the past about using CPA funds to fund municipal projects.
[SPEAKER_05]: However, based upon a need for a contingency plan, I think that it only makes sense for us to see whether or not the
[SPEAKER_05]: public library would be eligible for these Community Preservation Act funds by filing a determination of eligibility with the CPC.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then if, in fact, we do need to come up with a contingency plan, maybe that can be part of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion of Councilor Marks, as amended by Councilor Knight, seconded by Vice President Lungo-Kirk, a roll call vote has been asked for.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_11]: 7 in favor, 0 against, motion passes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_11]: If we can report to committees.
[SPEAKER_03]: If I may, we have one more.
[SPEAKER_10]: Sure, go ahead.
[SPEAKER_10]: Under suspension.
[SPEAKER_10]: I apologize.
[SPEAKER_03]: Offered by Councilor Caraviello, be it resolved that the Medford City Council have the mayor or the appropriate department report to the council regarding the safety of gear worn by Medford firefighters.
[SPEAKER_03]: Be it further resolved that a report on who makes our gear and what materials are the gear comprised of.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_06]: I don't know if, I think probably some of our members
[SPEAKER_06]: saw the report on television this evening on Fox 25 in regards to the chemicals that the firemen's gear is made out of.
[SPEAKER_06]: And there was some concern about the fire retardant material in them has been linked to cancer.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I think it's called
[SPEAKER_06]: PFAS.
[SPEAKER_06]: And like I said, we don't want to alarm anybody in our community, but I'd like to get a report back from the mayor or whoever on who makes our gear and what materials our gear is comprised of.
[SPEAKER_06]: And also there's a bill at the state house currently going through that would reduce toxic chemicals into protective gear for the firefighters.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I request that our state delegation support that bill HD3590.
[SPEAKER_06]: Currently, only Representative Barber has signed on to that bill.
[SPEAKER_06]: So if we could ask Representative Donato and Gobley to support that also.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can you repeat the bill number again?
[SPEAKER_06]: HD3590.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion of Councilor Caraviello, seconded by Councilor Dello Russo.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_03]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_03]: The motion passes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Offered by Councilor Scarpelli, reports of committees 19-007.
[SPEAKER_03]: February 19th, 2019, Transportation Subcommittee Report.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_10]: I know this is, if I could just indulge everyone without reading through the whole meeting.
[SPEAKER_10]: It was a very important meeting.
[SPEAKER_10]: We met with representatives from DOT to discuss a very dangerous intersection here in Medford, our corridor of South Street and Main Street.
[SPEAKER_10]: the lack of working lights, and the safety concerns for pedestrians, bicyclists, and drivers trying to traverse that area.
[SPEAKER_10]: We had a very productive meeting.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think our state delegates were here.
[SPEAKER_10]: Christine Barber and Representative Donato were here.
[SPEAKER_10]: They lent some very, very important feedback.
[SPEAKER_10]: We learned a lot about that intersection.
[SPEAKER_10]: whether it's under the method privy, under the state privy.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I think we are moving forward to a very important meeting in three weeks' time, I believe.
[SPEAKER_10]: I know that Mr. Blake from our traffic department has done a remarkable job in the last week.
[SPEAKER_10]: He's gotten back to me with seven different correspondents back and forth.
[SPEAKER_10]: He feels that there is going to be some
[SPEAKER_10]: short-term solutions to this issue and a long-term vision to what needs to be done, especially with the building of the police department.
[SPEAKER_10]: So it's very important that when the meeting is called that if anybody is interested to attend, we will be having a subcommittee meeting again.
[SPEAKER_10]: I believe we'll be calling that with the clerk.
[SPEAKER_10]: in due time, but this paper notes all of the questions that were brought up by Council Marks and Council Del Russo and reiterated by the members in our gallery that were frightened of what they've seen in that area.
[SPEAKER_10]: So it is something that I've gotten emails and phone calls from residents.
[SPEAKER_10]: One resident challenged me saying,
[SPEAKER_10]: It looks like nothing will ever happen until somebody passes on in that area, and it's a challenge that I take seriously.
[SPEAKER_10]: And I know that my colleagues support me when I say we will work tirelessly to make sure this, especially this corner, this corridor, is put through every safety precaution to make sure everybody that traverses that area is safe.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I think that's very important.
[SPEAKER_10]: So thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion of Councilor Scarpelli, seconded by Councilor Knight to accept the committee report.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_03]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, Councilor Dello Russo.
[SPEAKER_04]: Very briefly, Mr. President, I want to thank Councilor Scarpelli for his leadership in this matter.
[SPEAKER_04]: Though we were primarily focused on the issues of Main Street and South Street, that intersection, we did dive in a more broader approach to that whole systemic interaction of streets, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I thought it was a very fruitful discussion.
[SPEAKER_04]: representatives of DOT, our state delegation were with us, as well as, again, Todd Blake, our traffic engineer.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I must say, the day I walked out of that meeting with optimism, and partly because Councilor Scarpelli has done such great work on bringing people together in this matter and holding people to the fire, and that's important.
[SPEAKER_04]: But we had very thoughtful discussions in that meeting.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I also want to say that I received a very pessimistic email, and I will with delight see it not to come to fruition.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Dello Russo.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm looking at the wrong button.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_09]: I, too, want to go on record thanking Councilor Scarpelli,
[SPEAKER_09]: It was under his leadership calling for this meeting, getting the players at the table, having DOT sit around the table, having the district office there, not just the people that are responsible for the day-to-day activities, but the engineers from our district, from DOT were present, and people that can make decisions.
[SPEAKER_09]: So it was very helpful to have them there.
[SPEAKER_09]: I think it was insightful, which was offered by Councilor Scarpelli,
[SPEAKER_09]: The fact that DOT kept on stating to us they have to adhere to
[SPEAKER_09]: state and federal guidelines and regulations regarding signage, regarding traffic lights, and much of which prevents them from doing what we would like to see them do, which is provide some pedestrian safety in that area.
[SPEAKER_09]: And it was under Councilor Scarpelli's motion that within the next, I think it was 30 or 45 days, that we reconvene with some short-term fixes for that area.
[SPEAKER_09]: And I believe they're going to come back with a number of short-term fixes, whether it's a raised crosswalk, whether it's additional signage, whether it's changing that just blinking light to a steady light for the time being.
[SPEAKER_09]: They're going to come back with something, Mr. President, in my opinion, that's going to improve that section.
[SPEAKER_09]: And I would just put out a challenge to my colleague that that is one intersection.
[SPEAKER_09]: I have about another 75 on a list that we need to look at, and I'm sure he'll be eager to take them one at a time.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_10]: I don't want to forget, I think that the work of one person in this room that
[SPEAKER_10]: it gets quickly forgotten, is our clerk, Kurt Abese.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think he worked tirelessly with getting back to me and who exactly the people and the parties we needed at that table.
[SPEAKER_10]: And when we walked into that room and we had every single division
[SPEAKER_10]: of transportation there to answer our questions.
[SPEAKER_10]: A lot had to do with our city clerk who worked tirelessly making sure that everybody was represented.
[SPEAKER_10]: So credit where credit is due.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm taking a lot of credit for doing nothing.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think... Yes, it was.
[SPEAKER_13]: So... Can I answer that?
[SPEAKER_10]: I don't make enough money for him to switch.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'll definitely take it.
[SPEAKER_12]: I don't know if he wants it.
[SPEAKER_12]: The city clerk should be seen, but not heard.
[SPEAKER_12]: I'm going to make an exception to that tonight.
[SPEAKER_12]: Council, I very much appreciate the compliment, but this was your work.
[SPEAKER_12]: And I made a couple of phone calls based on expertise and experience I had back at DOT and the T's.
[SPEAKER_12]: This was your work.
[SPEAKER_12]: And again, I appreciate the compliment, but that was a team effort.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Motion to receive the report successfully.
[SPEAKER_03]: First of all, I'd also like to say thank you to Councilor Scarpelli for your hard work and everybody on the Transportation Subcommittee.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know this is a very important issue, a very important public safety issue.
[SPEAKER_03]: We receive calls on this all the time.
[SPEAKER_03]: So thank you for your hard work on this and your continued work in the future because I know this issue is going to be continuous.
[SPEAKER_03]: So thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion of Councilor Scarpelli, seconded by Councilor Knight that we adopt the Transportation Subcommittee report.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_03]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_03]: Report adopted.
[SPEAKER_03]: Report is adopted.
[SPEAKER_10]: Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_10]: If you can just indulge me for one topic.
[SPEAKER_10]: I know that along with this, we had a meeting last week.
[SPEAKER_10]: with the T, and they came to us about adding a few bus stops and moving on to additional traffic due to moving bus routes through our neighborhoods.
[SPEAKER_10]: We've called for a meeting.
[SPEAKER_10]: I believe that next week the representatives from the T will be here again.
[SPEAKER_10]: A reverse 9-1-1 is going to go out to the residents of the College Ave, George Street, Main Street areas and the crossing streets.
[SPEAKER_10]: The residents that live, I believe, on Albion Street, where they're going to be adding that bus stop, which will be losing three parking spots.
[SPEAKER_10]: and across the street they're going to be notified.
[SPEAKER_10]: I just wanted to make it public for tonight's meeting that just look out for that.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think it's important that we have representatives that are here to discuss some concerns.
[SPEAKER_10]: I know I've already gotten some feedback and some very shocked neighbors that didn't realize that all that T traffic, all the traffic now
[SPEAKER_10]: is going to be coming through that congested area anyway.
[SPEAKER_10]: So it was enlightening.
[SPEAKER_10]: They've had some concerns that I'll share next week with the representative, but I just wanted to make everybody aware of that meeting.
[SPEAKER_10]: Next week we'll be here in a regular meeting here at the council, and they'll be looking for us to vote on
[SPEAKER_10]: I believe additional bus stops.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's what we have the control of here at this council.
[SPEAKER_10]: They can do whatever they want with their bus routes, but it'd be important that we express our concerns, especially those neighbors that live in that area that have to exit their driveways from that main street and understand that things are going to be a little bit slower and there's going to be a lot more waiting around because they moved
[SPEAKER_10]: I believe, 11 stops instead of moving it through Somerville, which would have only affected one street.
[SPEAKER_10]: So it's very important.
[SPEAKER_10]: I just want everybody to know that that meeting is going to be here next week if they want to be heard by the T. So thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mr. President, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_05]: I think it's also important to point out that because we're diverting buses through College Avenue that are going to go past Tufts University, but we're not diverting them.
[SPEAKER_05]: The T is diverting them.
[SPEAKER_05]: The administration signed off on it.
[SPEAKER_05]: that they're asking us just for the temporary bus stops.
[SPEAKER_05]: But ultimately, if you look at the area in front of Tufts University on College Avenue, historically, you'll see a large number of buses that are parked there, buses for whatever team Tufts University is playing at Spicer Field, for whatever team Tufts University is playing at the gymnasium.
[SPEAKER_05]: So with that being said, Mr. President, moving forward, I'd like to see if we can put some contingencies upon it, where as long as this is the temporary bus route, the buses are not able to park on College Avenue.
[SPEAKER_05]: They'd have to be required to park inside the parking lot at Spicer Field.
[SPEAKER_05]: in the interest of public safety, in the interest of the environment, idling, so on and so forth.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Dello Russo.
[SPEAKER_04]: Mr. President, the issue really isn't a bus route being added to a street temporarily.
[SPEAKER_04]: The issue is that a large amount of traffic that travels over Broadway is going to be diverted through city streets to reroute itself.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the major issue.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so the efforts of DOT in planning for this for nearly a year have been to bring that perimeter further and further out so people are diverted out and stay on the highway rather than come through the neighborhoods.
[SPEAKER_04]: The communication plan was supposed to have been undertaken by now and I think it's beginning.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you notice on the city's website, the announcements are up and DOT
[SPEAKER_04]: explained to us at one of the committee meetings some month or two ago, when we were talking about this, that based on their experience of doing major disruptive projects over the past several years, vis-a-vis bridge work, the bridge work down over in Austin-Brighton, over the Mass Pike, that Commonwealth Ave.
[SPEAKER_04]: bridge, there were a couple others, and also the
[SPEAKER_04]: What did they call it, the quick 14 or whatever it was they did here on 93?
[SPEAKER_04]: Fast 14.
[SPEAKER_04]: Was it the fast 14?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_04]: Fast 14.
[SPEAKER_04]: That they found that doom notifications further out, at a greater distance of time from when the project commences.
[SPEAKER_04]: was less successful, it kept it fresh in people's minds that they did it three weeks before the project started.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that was part of the rationale for that.
[SPEAKER_04]: But as far as I lament, as Councilor Scarpelli did, that they didn't do the footwork to tell people that there'd be a bus dump in front of their houses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, the other day they had Hobbit Street shut down for a day, working on some of the gas mains and traffic and parking was diverted to people's houses with limited notice.
[SPEAKER_04]: There's been an ongoing for seven months now, repair of a road going on to replace the street to all the pipes.
[SPEAKER_04]: In fact, they have a trench down the street that's about 10 feet deep right now.
[SPEAKER_04]: So there are disruptions that we all encounter.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Dello Russo.
[SPEAKER_03]: Records.
[SPEAKER_03]: The records of the meeting of February 19, 2019 were passed to Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Marks, how did you find those records?
[SPEAKER_09]: Mr. President, I reviewed the records, find them to be in order, and move approval.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion of Councilor Marks to approve the records, seconded by Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_03]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_03]: The record's a pass.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion of Consul Dello Russo to adjourn, seconded by Vice President Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_03]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_03]: Meeting adjourned.