It's a shell that, when it bursts in the sky, it has 35 of these gold-glittering comets in them. And the glitter kind of looks like if you ground up 18-karat gold and pixie-dusted it into the sky, and it twinkles when it descends.
It ignites the burst charge at its full apex up in the sky. That burst charge also ignites the stars. And just as you think that the comet is going to extinguish and go out, it then splits again and it creates this dust effect at the tail end of the burn. It's something that's special to me and also the rest of the family when you see that shell. It's also a tribute and a remembrance of my dad.
Jimmy Guzzi once told me about making fireworks, that an accident was always vaguely in the back of the mind. You live with it every day, he told me, sort of like knowing that nuclear weapons are pointed at you.
My second great-grandfather started our business in Bari, Italy in 1850. They immigrated to Ellis Island in the early 1900s and they set up a factory literally six, seven miles from where we're sitting here today on Long Island.
And they operated their factory until about the late 1920s, 1929. My grandfather, he opened his own factory in 1929 right in this very village, Bellport Village. So he had three children. He and my grandmother had three children, which was the fourth generation. And my father was the oldest. And he was somewhat the innovator at that time. I remember the days of being at Coney Island at five, six years old.
And it got into my blood. I mean, I was with my dad. The show would go off. All the people would come up, clap, you know, tell him, have a great job. And it's addictive. And that, to me, at five years old, the energy, the camaraderie of being with a group of people, the ability to create something and see so many people enjoy it, it's addictive. And at that time, I knew from as long as I can remember that this is what I wanted to do.
And then in 1983, unfortunately, we had the explosion. On a Saturday of a Thanksgiving weekend, the Gucci's plant exploded. Debris from this blast drifted down on townships 10 miles away. Jimmy Gucci had been working on the big shells he loved to make, big eight-inch color shells, though he was always a bit anxious about them.
He and his cousin, a pretty dark-haired girl who was Jimmy's assistant, were instantly killed only a few feet from the shop where they were working on the big shelves. Something must have happened in there.
We lost everything, you know, we lost two loved ones and lost our entire facilities. There was a lot of activity, there was a lot of shoes to fill, there was a lot of space to fill because there was a big gap that was caused by losing him. So I kind of took the role of trying to fill his shoes and still am trying to fill his shoes. Good morning, fireworks by Gritchy.
Favorite firework would be a brocade Camaro. It's a large, breaking, big willow type Camaro that would descend all the way down to the ground. And with the music and a large volley of them, it just fills the sky. It's a beautiful show.
I like the spectacle of the Niagara Falls. You know, you have some pictures around here that you'll see the Niagara Falls coming off the entire bottom part of the Brooklyn Bridge, from the bottom of the actual bridge itself, hitting the East River down below. So I'll never forget firing that shell, that exact effect. And it still brings shivers up my spine now, thinking about it.
I love the giant willow ones. They're just so pretty when they come down like a waterfall. It twinkles as it's coming down, and then it slowly dissipates, so it makes it really pretty. Kind of magical, I guess.
When somebody asks me what's my occupation, I generally would say we're in the firework entertainment business, as well as manufacturing of explosives business, because the other half of our business, about 50% of our revenue, is in manufacturing of explosives for the Department of Defense. We make a tremendous amount of training devices, hand grenade simulators, ground bomb simulators, trip flare simulators, and things like that, as well as some components that go into live munitions.
So, I say we're a fireworks performance company as well as a manufacturer for the Department of Defense.
This New Year's Eve, we're in the heart of the design process right now. A project of this size has about 40,000 different cues and circuits that have to be initiated over an eight-and-a-half-minute period. Do you get a sense of the aerial drone, but it's still unknown? Sure. You absolutely have a sense. If everything goes perfectly, what this is going to look like.
But there's always so many variables in a live performance. One, rehearsal, you can't fire this whole show and then look at it and make changes in real time out in the field.
So this is the countdown towards the launching of the world record show. So these are digits, sky-etching digits that are fired with a series of comets that are fired in a very tight pattern to create the digits. Now you notice it's not one digit every second. It's slow in the beginning, but now you'll see it picks up. And it's intended to be very quiet as far as nothing in the sky.
And then you'll see this long tail. This is the launching of the shell now. You see this long tail. The music will be playing also with it. And then when it reaches its apex... Now each one of these...
These small trails will be one 5-inch in diameter, 5-pound comet that's loaded inside of the shell. And it's designed to burn long enough for it to come all the way down to the water. So when you see that...
Lawrence LaPore. LaPore. Councilor DelaRusso has nominated Lawrence LaPore. Any further nominations? Motion to close the nominations, Mr. Clerk. Councilor Knight has closed the nominations. Madam Clerk, please call the roll. I present DelaRusso. Lawrence LaPore. Councilor Franco. Lawrence LaPore. Councilor Knight. Lawrence LaPore. Councilor Burnett. Lawrence LaPore. Councilor Marks.
Lawrence Lapore. 7 in the affirmative for Lawrence Lapore. Congratulations.
. . . .
to rules and regulations of the Constitution, the laws of the Commonwealth, and the ordinances of the City of Memphis. Congratulations. You want to say a few words now?
All right, the chair declares a quick recess at what time is it? It's 7.10? Okay. We'll reconvene with the gradual chair.
I thought he thank you. He's gonna late night tomorrow.
I stood straight up the whole time. It was so cool.
C. We thought that the. We first. It's a race. I think eleven maybe early. No way.
Michael.
Yeah, I started What
I know you're after bus stops, you're after bus stops for sure.
Motion to reconvene. All right, everybody. Good evening, everyone. 18004, offered by Councilor DelaRusso, be it resolved that the standing committee rules be adopted as the standing rules of the City Council insofar as they are applicable. Move. Vice President DelaRusso. Move approval, Mr. President. Second. On the motion by Councilor DelaRusso. Seconded. Seconded by Councilor Knight.
All those in favor? Aye. Motion passes. 18-005, offered by Vice President Donald Russo, be it resolved that the City Council transfer all papers and committees are on the table from 2017 Council to the 2018 Council. Mr. President, I move approval. Second, Mr. President. Seconded by Councilor Ney. All those in favor? Aye. Motion passes.
motions orders and resolutions 18 zero zero six up by councillor mox Be it resolved that the best that the city of method recognized long time public servant and 30-year veteran of the school committee leader the giant amaso for her dedication in commitment to the children of our community councillor mox
Thank you, Mr. President, and it's with great honor and great pride that I rise tonight to honor, in my opinion, someone that has done so much for this community, not only in the capacity as a member of the school committee for three decades,
but also as someone very involved in many, many organizations throughout the community, and someone very instrumental in leading the path on many, many initiatives in this community, of which I will mention some here tonight, Mr. President.
I personally had the opportunity to serve with Lena DiGentimaso for six years as a member of the school committee. It was my first time elected in this community back some years ago and when I first got on the school board it was
kind of intimidating. I was new to the process, new to the system, and Lena was one of the first people to put her hand out and welcome me to the school committee and really took me under her wing for a period of time.
to show me the ins and outs. And I can remember my first few times being part of the negotiations when we used to have to negotiate with the teachers. And this would be a lengthy six, seven hour night. We used to get in there at five o'clock, no breaks. And you can always count on one thing.
and it wasn't to settle the contract. It was the fact that Lena would cook a homemade lasagna and make sure that everyone was fed. That was the type of person she was. She was very considerate and always thinking of others. Her one goal that I found out early as a member of the school committee, she taught me, she said, Mike, no matter what happens,
We're here for the children of this community. We're here to make sure they get the best education possible. And she said, my votes are always predicated on whatever is good for the children. And I learned that early with Lena that she was very dedicated, she was very loyal, and she meant what she said. She didn't go back on her word. If Lena gave you her word, her word was as good as gold, Mr. President.
You know, another thing too, Lena attended every single meeting, not just with the school committee and other meetings we had, every single function that happened in this community, Lena Degentamaso was part of it. And I think that says a lot about a person's character and their commitment to doing the job that they're in.
Lena served, like I said, for three decades on the school committee. Never ran or never intended to run for any other public office. Her commitment was to the kids of this community. Never had any political aspirations other than to helping the kids of this community. And that's what she did for three decades. Lena was also the longest serving member of the Meffitt School Committee.
She was a strong advocate for the Meffitt Vocational Technical High School back when the school was, to be quite frank with you, lacking the technology and shops
And Lena was one of the key people that stood up back some 20, 25 years ago about improving the vocational school. So she was a leader in that aspect and now we see a school that is really state of the art and one we can all be proud of.
The Curtis Tufts High School. Lena realized early on when that program came about that not every child has the opportunity to go on to college, not every child does well in high school, and this was an opportunity that was given to students that may not get their diploma if the Curtis Tufts did not exist.
And you can count on Lena being there at every Thanksgiving meal that they had, and she was a strong advocate of the Curtis Tufts Alternative High School. She was a big supporter of the fine arts department, in particular the high school band. She was the past president of the Friends of Chevalier.
She was instrumental in the building of the new schools. I served with Lena when we built the new schools. And if you think that wasn't a tough time, that was a difficult time going from neighborhood schools to having centralized schools. And Lena was one of the educational leaders in this community that led the charge, Mr. President.
She also served with distinction as PTA president for a number of years. She was selected by the directors of the Mass Association of School Committees, Incorporated, and received the association's Lifetime Achievement Award. Lena received the Woman's Achievement Award from the Human Rights Commission. She was a recipient of the Tip of the Hat Award from the Salem Street Business Association. She received the Golden Mustang Award for supporting the students of the Mustang athletic programs.
She was instrumental in the planning and development of the Gene Mack Youth Center. She received the Veterans of Foreign Wars Post-1012 Award in appreciation of leading the charge to have the McGlynn School Auditorium named in honor of the veterans.
She was honored at the Curtis Tufts Alternative High School graduation for many years of continued support. She received the Tony Lucci Golden Mustang Award for being an outstanding athletic program supporter. She served as past president of AARP, the method chapter 1132.
And the list goes on and on and it really does. And I'm not going to mention everything. I would be remiss at this time because Lena's late husband, Al, as we all know him as affectionately, was a big part of
uh, Lena, uh, during the years that I served with her on the school committee, and he was a recognized Purple Heart recipient, uh, from the Korean War, and, uh, along with their three children that were all graduates of Meffitt High School, uh, she raised a beautiful family, Mr. President, along with her role as an advocate
in this community, and not just with the schools, with many, many organizations that I mentioned here tonight. And it is with great pride, Mr. President, that I offer this resolution to Lena as an outstanding member of the school committee.
and I can attest to that, serving with her for six years, but also an outstanding member of this community and, in my opinion, a very, very good friend to many people in this community. And I would ask, as a resolution here tonight, that the school department dedicate, in her honor, something within the public schools to show the appreciation of her service, 30 years of service,
One quick story I remember when I first got on the school board, when we were looking to do the new schools, they invited the school committee to go around to the buildings to see the condition of the buildings. And I'll never forget some of the meetings I attended and some of the buildings we went in, seeing Lena climb up to the roof of the Franklin School was quite an interesting sight.
And it was one of the many things that she took her job so serious, she could have easily said I'm not interested in going to the roof of this old rickety building and standing on the top of the roof. And there wasn't a staircase leading up there, by the way, it was a ladder. And she found it in herself to get up there because that's how interested she was and how dedicated she was to making sure that her vote was predicated on
doing the right thing, and making sure that she had first-hand knowledge. And I learned a lot from her in that spirit of time that I served with her. And I would ask that something be named, Mr. President, with the school department, to honor Lina DeGentimaso for her three decades of service to this community. Outstanding. I, for one, I've known Lina since I was probably 13, 14 years old in Upper House many times, because I was very friendly with her daughter.
And good woman, I still see her occasionally. And remember, Lena worked at the hilltop. He never waited in line when Lena was working. He always went in and saw Lena, and she got you right in. Those were the old days when you had to wait for days to get in. On the motion. I think we have a few people, Mr. President, that would like to say anything further.
Name and address of the record please. Figure it might sound. They might sell.
First of all, congratulations, President Caviello and Vice President De La Rosa. And Happy New Year to all of you. I had the pleasure of working with Lena on many, many community projects. As Councilor Mark said, if there was something happening in the city, you can be sure that Lena was gonna be involved in that. And although she has
over time received quite a lot of significant recognitions. I wholeheartedly support your proposal and I think one of the
most prestigious awards that she received was from the Massachusetts Association of School Committee when she was given the Lifetime Achievement Award. I don't believe any other person in this city ever was honored. And also, I believe she was the first woman, now that women are in the newspapers these days, she was the first woman to receive the Golden Mustang Award.
And my working with her very, very closely during the founding and development of the Friends of Chevalier and Gene Mack Gym, Lena was just amazing. I mean, if she decided she was going to do something, she was actually the driving force behind our fundraising efforts.
And over the years, I would say, I know for a fact, that's where she headed that up, every one of the fundraisers were hugely successful. And without a doubt, she raised in excess of $100,000 through the fundraising campaigns. And all of that money was given
She raised over $100,000 for both the theater and the Boys and Girls Club. And all of that money has been given to those operations. So City of Medford can be very, very proud that Lena was a part of us. And I certainly, as I say, I certainly would
like to see something happen to give her an honor from the city. Thank you. I also was contacted today by some friends who worked alongside of Lena and myself and that couple was Bruce and Amy Folk.
They are currently in the process of moving from Cotting Street to Melrose. But she sent me an email and asked me if I would read this on her behalf. Bruce and I have known Lena DiGiandomaso for many, many years. First got to know her through the Friends of Chevalier and GMAC Gymnasium. We worked together on various committees and many fundraising ventures.
Lena's dedication and devotion to the City of Medford and the young people of the City is a tribute for us all. Her strength, her enthusiasm, her hard work, her eagerness,
always to be there whenever anything or anyone had a question or needed anything. Lena would always be there to listen and help whenever possible. Lena always insisted on doing and getting the best for our city of Medford, and especially the young people of the city. Thank you.
I along with Michael had the honor and privilege of serving with Lena on the school committee and I think one of her greatest accomplishments was when we decided to beef up the vocational school and do a few things that were unconventional at the time.
I said to Lena, why don't we see if we can institute a culinary arts program? And through a lot of arm bending and work behind the scenes, it became a fruition. And just last month, Council, you and I had the opportunity to see what that program, how it started, and where it is today with their brand new cafeteria. Lena and I were fortunate enough in 2010 to be granted life membership in the Mass Association of School Committees.
And during my tenure on the school board, I think there was no person that offered more help, more insight, and had some great ideas. And like people have said, she was always there for the kids. That was her first priority, even long after her own children were gone from Medford High.
and I would hope that you would pass this on to the new school committee and see that they act with due diligence and name something respectfully after Mr. DeGentomaso. Thank you.
for your years of service to the children, similar to Lena, over 26 years of service, Mr. Skerry? Yes. As a school committee, I thank you for your years of dedication to the children of the Memphis office. I'm just wondering where the time went. On a lighter note, when I first ran for the school board back in 1985, Lena and I were battling out for the sixth seat on the school board. Election night, I won by one vote.
She had a recount. I ended up losing by one vote. Came back the following time, was elected, and I had a great run. Best to you all. It was a pleasure serving with Michael and all my former colleagues. I wish Mrs. DeGentimaso well. Thank you.
Good evening. Name and address of the record, please. Thank you. Ken Crouch, 50 Mystic Street. I'm a member of the board of directors of the Friends of Chevalier. I got to know Lita when I started to get involved with the Friends, probably around 2004 or so. And it's been a few years since she stepped down from her active role with the Friends.
Also the school committee, but it's never too late to say thank you to somebody for all their contributions to the community. And I think it's especially fitting this year for a couple of reasons. One is the 25th anniversary, 2018, of the founding of the Friends of Chevalier.
As was mentioned, Lena had an important role. I don't know if she was a founding member, probably was, but very instrumental in bringing the theater back from a condition that was, you know,
deplorable and perhaps, you know, in jeopardy of the theater remaining as a viable venue. And, you know, look where it is today. You know, she was an advocate for the city to invest in the building, well, to save the building, first of all, and also invest in the building.
For the state legislature to approve significant funding for the renovations and was instrumental in the fundraising on behalf of the Friends as well. So, you know, she really believed in the theater and its viability as a
venue that would bring economic vitality to the community and be a place for outstanding performances for the arts. So working hand-in-hand with the commission, they brought really Chevalier to the point where we see what's happening with it today. You know, a lot of the naysayers said, oh, it's too big to be successful.
No company would ever come in here and run it without, you know, being paid a fortune. And no company would ever come in and essentially pay the city for the opportunity to use this venue. And look what's happened. Bill Blumenreich presents, entered into an agreement with the city this fall and is investing
his own money, putting in a sound system, putting in new lighting, putting in new box office facilities, improving the sight lines, putting up money to bring in top-notch shows that are selling out this theater. Today, the fifth performance was added for comedian Gabriel Iglesias in February. So there are numerous shows that have already sold out and additional shows have been added.
The work of people like Lena, others on the Friends, others on the commission, really brought the theater to the point where it was able to take this leap to the next level. And I support whatever could be done.
to recognize Lena, particularly something at the school, and not only to thank her, but if there's something visible at the school, I think it would inspire future generations of public servants that will learn about Lena and what she contributed to the community when they pass through those halls. So, thank you.
On the motion by Councilor Mox. Roll call vote, Mr. President. Seconded by. Councilor DelaRusso. By Councilor DelaRusso. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Vice President DelaRusso. Yes. Councilor Falcone. Yes.
motion passes. Motion by counselor night to suspend the rule seconded by council Scott Kelly also favor.
Did Mr. President see the president motion to waive a reading of the paper and have a brief synopsis given by the president? On the motion by counselor night for a brief synopsis in it. Maybe name and address of the record, please. Good evening, counselors. Alicia Nellie Benjamin, finance director for the city of Medford. Roberta Cameron, chairman of the Community Preservation Committee.
Daniel Evans, Community Preservation Coordinator. Thank you. Okay, who wants to go first? Okay, I'll go first. Okay. Paper 18-010 is actually the fiscal year 17 revenues. I know the council did vote fiscal year 18, but you didn't get to see fiscal year 17, as that was our first year, so I automatically had to reserve it, and then it had to go through DOR before it could be appropriated. That's what this paper's for.
Thank you, the purpose for this is to reserve the minimum 10% as is required under the CPA legislation in each of the program areas, and the remaining balance is to be, can be appropriated for any of the program areas. Thank you. Do you want to speak? Do you have anything to add?
Mr. President, so it's my understanding that annually 10% needs to be appropriated to each program area where the CPA was up and running, but our ordinance wasn't in place until a little bit later on in the year. I believe what happened is we were able to address fiscal year 18, but fiscal year 17 money was not appropriated. So it's my understanding that by approving this appropriation will be in compliance with the community preservation.
On the motion by Councilor Nays. Seconded by Councilor Falco. All those in favor, we'll call vote. Mr. Clerk, roll call vote, please. Vice President DelaRusso. Yes. Councilor Falco. Yes. Councilor Nays. Yes. Councilor Long-Term. Yes. Councilor Maxwell. Yes. Councilor Scott-Billings. Yes. President Campbell. Yes. Seven in the affirmative, none in the negative, motion passes. Thank you.
We're under suspension, Mr. President. We have paper 18-011 also on the table. 18-011, dear Mr. President, city councilors, I respectfully request that you and your Honorable body approve the recommendations of the community preservation committee to appropriate up to
$300,000 from the Community Preservation Act funds for the purpose of funding phase one of the Harris Park Rehabilitation Project in order to meet the deadline for committing the matching funds for the anticipated federal land and water conservation grant and is identified in the community preservation plan as a high priority recreation project. This appropriation will be allocated to the open space category in the amount of $100,000.
$23,281 and funded from the General Reserve category in the amount of $176,719. This project will be tracked in the Community Preservation Fund. Roberta Cameron, Chair of the Community Preservation Committee, and Daniel Evans, Community Preservation Coordinator, are present to answer any questions that we may have. Name and address for the record again. Roberta Cameron, 12 North Street.
Daniel Evans Community Preservation Coordinator. Thank you.
Any questions? So the Office of Community Development submitted a request for us to consider an off-cycle application for a project to match a federal grant rehabilitating Harris Park.
And their purpose for the off-cycle application was because the OCD anticipates that the city will have to commit the funding to complete the project during the month of January at some point. So imminently, the city is going to have to commit the resources in order to be able to accept the federal grant.
So the community preservation funds would have to be committed before any other city funds could be committed to the project. So they asked us if we would support the use of community preservation funds for this project.
We felt that the project, so the community preservation application process allows for an off-cycle applicant where it is a high-priority project that has a substantial purpose for urgency that needs to be considered outside of this cycle.
And we felt that this proposal, this request, met both of those criteria, that there's a reason why the funds would need to be committed before we consider the other applications in the pipeline, and this is a high-priority project.
According to the plan that we carried out over the past six, seven months, we identified community needs through a public process, through coordinating with various departments and boards and committees and community organizations to get input about what the needs are. And some of the goals and priorities that were identified were to
commit funds to serve underserved neighborhoods and populations, which this proposal does, to leverage funding from other sources, which this proposal does, to, I don't have all of the goals, but we had given previously when we came to the city council a summary of our goals and recommendations
or the goals and priorities that we identified in our process, and specifically pertaining to open space and recreation. Improving access to open space and recreation resources and providing diverse recreation opportunities, serving residents of all ages. So this project...
fulfills our goals and the priority to improve access, safety, and function of our existing recreation resources, which this project does. So we felt that this project meets the criteria to be considered a high priority for CPA funding.
The amount of city match that was requested, I believe was $516,000 to match a federal grant of $300,000. And given the fact that this is coming before we've had the opportunity to see what other projects are in the pipeline, we wanted to be conservative in the amount of CPA funds that we committed to the project. So we elected to match the federal grant
and ask that the city find funding from other sources to match the remainder of the needs for this project. And that represents
We're only for the first round of funding That we intend to recommend in May to the City Council We are looking at the FY 17 revenues that that you've just approved the reserving
the program areas for. That's $1.2 million in total funding. So to evenly allocate that funding between each of the three program areas would be about $400,000 for each program area. So our offering or recommending $300,000 toward open space and recreation for this project
is still leaves some funding available for other open space and recreation projects and to provide an even amount of funding for the three program areas altogether. So that's a long synopsis of how we got to make this recommendation. Thank you. Thank you. Daniel, Mr. President.
Do you want to say anything? No, she pretty much covered it. But I just wanted to add that about the equal distribution of the funding, I think based on the forms, the eligibility determination forms that we've received, I believe that it's not going to be very heavy on the recreation open space projects. So I do think that there will be price-efficient funds to go around for any recreation open space projects that were coming down the pipeline.
as well as to fund this at $300,000. Mr. President, I think that the intricacies and the inner workings of the CPA are very interesting, but people, if we're going to be spending $300,000, want to know what that $300,000 is going to go for. In our packet, we have a letter from our economic development planner, Clodagh Stoker-Long,
And this is a two-phase project, Mr. President, to rehabilitate Harris Park. And phase one will include new play equipment for children ages two to five and five to 12, a rope climber, a water play area, a nature play area or a swing alley, a community garden, site furnishings, plantings and signage, and accessible parking improvements. Phase two will involve the rehabilitation of the fields to provide a new softball field, space for three junior soccer fields, an area for a farmer's market or a similar community use. It will also include a rain garden,
and additional accessibility improvements and streetage improvements and plannings along the edge of Middlesex Avenue. Mr. President says here that the total cost of phase one, including design and construction and construction oversight is estimated at about $817,000. The $300,000 which would be reimbursable through the Land Water Conservation Fund.
And it looks like, Mr. President, if in fact this appropriation is made this evening, there'll be a $217,000 balance to complete the requirements of phase one of the project, and the city will continue to seek land and water APOC grants to fund.
Phase two of the project. Mr. President seems like it's a quite an endeavor, but having been down Harris Park all fall long My kid being enrolled in soccer for the first time in his life It's a park that needs a little bit of TLC. It needs a little bit of love and it's a I think a highly trafficked park Mr. President actually has a lot more access and a lot more involvement down there than most of the other parks that we see in the community so on this is an endeavor that I think needs to be
examined thoroughly, but it's certainly a worthwhile cause, Mr. President. So with that being said, I rest. Councilor Kern. Thank you. I'm President Carviello. Thank you for your hard work. I don't know if my questions are for you or for the city, but with regards to the 300,000 that potentially will be used from CPA, is there a certain match? What's the percentage of the match for the grant?
The land and water grant is $300,000, so the committee elected to recommend that CPA funds match the land and water grant one-to-one, so to match $300,000 for the land and water grant.
So how are we going to be paying? This isn't a question for the CPA, but for the $217,000, what is our plan? I think maybe the city. I don't have it in. I may close. Thank you. Office of Community Development.
I will give you a direct answer and then I will go backwards. I spoke to the mayor today about how we would look to fund the balance of $217,000. When we get the official confirmation from, we get it through the state of the land and water funding, we will come to you like we come again and again with a presentation asking you to accept the funding, accept the grant and to appropriate the funds
the whole lot of the funds for the park. That's the way these grant systems work. At that time, we will ask you to appropriate the additional $217,000. I spoke to the mayor today and she said it's very likely that we will ask you to appropriate that from free cash. That isn't definite, but that's what she said is likely.
So either bond or free cash, is there a potential that we'll request part of the next funding from CPA to put in another application? Is that a possibility? Yes, I would anticipate that this is a source of funds for open space and I would anticipate that generally we will ask CPA to help.
with important recreational projects.
The open space plan is due to be updated.
It's been five years. It's actually now seven, but we've gotten to the seventh. So by August of this year, we need to have a new open space plan. So we need to do the whole process of information gathering and getting goals and objectives, as well as assessing the value, the state of the various parks.
create a new list of priorities. We usually just move down to the priorities that are set by that planning process. And of course the CPA has also done their own planning process, which in fact, obviously the people say the same things.
So very often the priorities in the open space plan are quite like those in the community preservation plan. But the city would be applying for any parks that are city owned, the city would be applying for the CPA and we don't have any plans in the next year or two besides Harris Park phase one and phase two until we do the open space assessment in August, which isn't going to really lead into if there's another park that's
designated as needing rehab, that would not even be until the 2019 cycle. So potentially we could put an application for the CPA funds for the second cycle.
I think this is definitely a project that needs to be done. This is exactly where I envision CPA monies going. My question, putting this project aside, is how did the vote go down with regards to taking something out of cycle?
Our committee members voted, I believe there were eight people present at our previous meeting, all but one. And there was one person who voted in the negative, everyone else voted for it. And his concerns were about taking this out of order, not, he felt that this was a good project, but
felt uncomfortable with the very first project that we do being taken out of order or being accelerated. Felt that if the timing were otherwise, he would get behind it very easily. So that was a difficult decision for the committee to wrap our heads around because we want to maintain the appearance that this funding is available for anybody in the community who needs it.
and that's what drove us to find an amount that we felt comfortable with leaving funds available for other applicants. So can you tell the council when was the application given to the committee originally, and was a full application provided from the city? Yes, we had a full application received by CLODA. And when was that? The 19th?
It must have been the 19th. Yes. Oh, really? So very recently. Yes. And that's time-wise because this application for the grant is due? The grant application that was submitted originally goes through a strange sort of process. Submitted to the state, who decide whether they're going to support it or not. And then they send it to the National Park Service. And the state, so it was submitted to the state last February.
They decided by about, let me say, August 2 to submit it to the National Park Service with a recommendation to fund it. And they tell us that they're 99% sure that we will refund it, that they have never been turned down. Of course you can't, no. It's in your hands, not mine. I expect in the next month, I can't forget, absolutely not, to get a letter saying, congratulations, you've been awarded the funding, now please go to the council and get your acceptance
Sure, yeah.
I think I understand why you had one in the negative. So it is a difficult decision, but I think this obviously needs to be done. So it's a hard vote, obviously, for the committee, I think, is ultimately the ones that are doing all the work and putting their time and effort and sweat and tears into how much you do is commendable. I see an issue with
Taking applications out of order, but I you know, I see both sides I just want to I want to just voice that concern. Yeah doing that often I don't I want to make sure that even though we have so, you know, two million come very very soon in this fund I just feel like everybody should have a fair shot. It should be obviously I asked for an extension on the application process and I just think we're walking a fine line and I hope hopefully
I appreciate that and it is also I think important to have as we wrote in the application process the opportunity for applicants to come in off cycle as this application was because there are opportunities that will be very important
down the line. Meeting a grant cycle is one example of the kind of project that might not align with what our timeline is, and if we wanted to acquire property, perhaps for open space or for affordable housing, property acquisition is often something that needs to be done.
on a very fast timeline that doesn't match. So there are reasons why that can happen. It was a little bit uncomfortable that this was our first application. So even though we anticipated that we were going to need to be able to consider applications out of order, we weighed very carefully this particular one.
In my last question, I guess, or point, has the committee discussed, like you just mentioned, a few scenarios where you'd have to take them out of order when you have a grant or you have a land acquisition. Have you discussed or created a checklist of why you would take
an application out of order, just so it's something to follow. And when you come back to us next time, we know, oh, you know, you're trying to acquire this piece of land, or there's a grant that needs to be written in time. I mean, just so we can feel better about this decision as well, confirming your vote.
At the moment we have, and perhaps it's a little bit informal and we could improve on the procedure, but we did specify that it should be a high priority project and that there should be a defensible reason why it needs to be considered off-cycle. Those were the only two criteria that we considered at this point, but we would take suggestions if there are further criteria that we ought to include in our process.
I would just think maybe at your next meeting you designate 10-15 minutes to discuss it. I think anything given to you by the mayor's office or anybody, any organization, their project is going to be high priority. High priority by the standards that are established in our plan, not by necessarily the urgency felt by the applicant.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you, Mr. President. And again, thank you, your team doing a great job with this. And we all know how Harris Park, the work it needs. I know that I receive phone calls right away. People, you know, what about car park? What about the baseball fields? And this is this is great because that's a dialogue. And we express to people that I believe the deadline is coming up soon for the new round. The 15th, correct? January.
for the sixth, fifth, this Friday for the eligibility determination forms for the first round. And for the second round of funding, which will also be recommended in 2018, but in the fall, the project eligibility deadline, I believe is in April. I think it's April 13th. Yes, April 13th. One of the big pieces, I know, being part of the recreation committee that we put together,
I think we should really pay close attention to making sure that part of these projects in the parks have inclusionary equipment for our special needs students. Is that spelt out in this? I don't know if the city can address that. I know the water is nice, but one thing that we talked about at the recreation meetings, we're trying to make more inclusionary parks and accessibility for our children.
This is a preliminary design, it's a concept plan, but any design we do is fully accessible. I mean that has been for many, many years. Right, but it would be what was expressed in those meetings more of adaptive equipment. So a child with a wheelchair with special equipment. When we get the grant we will be coming to you. Great.
You will have an opportunity to have that input, just like last year. It was the same funding source last year for Riverside Plaza. We came to you, made comments, we tried to see if we could do some adaptations to make things work. Similarly, when we get this, we'll come before you and we'll have the same interactive process.
But thank you. And again, I think this is what people were looking for when we, Roberta, started the dialogue with community preservation and looking into such important projects like this. So thank you very much.
Thank you. Thank you, Mr. President. Roberta, you mentioned about other projects that are in the pipeline. At what point will this council see other projects that are in the pipeline?
and be able to see, in my opinion, to be helpful to see a comparison of what funding is available, what projects are in the pipeline, because it's great to get these projects piecemeal, and everyone supports, Harris Park is around the corner from my home, I know it needs work, everyone supports this.
but I also think it's important that we know what's out there, and there may come a time when you appear before us that we'd say, you know what, we realize this is important, but I also think creating more affordable housing in the city is equally as important, and maybe I'd like to pay more attention to that at this particular point. So at what point will we see as a council the total picture? Do you have the full timeline?
We have in the
We have a timeline laid out of when all of the applications are due and when we anticipate bringing our full slate of recommendations for the first round and the second round of funding to the city council. So we can keep you updated as we've received the applications as to what's in the pipeline and there would be a public process and hearings that occur with our committee
prior to our sending the recommendations or committing the recommendations to you. Is this the only application that you received from the city so far for the first round?
This is the only full application that we've received. So far the eligibility determination forms are just more or less an intent to apply. We initially had the deadline for the eligibility forms due prior to when this application was discussed by our committee. Now the eligibility determination forms are due in the end of this week.
So before we meet again, we'll know what applications are potentially in the pipeline. My question, Roberta, is on behalf of the city, is this the only application you've received so far on behalf of the city as a city entity? This is the only application that we've received because the deadline is not until March.
but for eligibility termination forms, we were free something. No one else asked for early acceptance? No one else said? No, no, because I don't think anyone else is on a timeline where they have to get a match before their grant is awarded. I'm not sure what the other funds that are being leveraged for the other projects, but we have received forms from the Community Garden Commission for four different gardens. I don't believe that they're gonna apply for all four, but they wanted to,
make sure that they want to get it out there first, make sure that it's eligible, and then decide later which ones to apply for. So they applied. We have the Historical Commission has submitted, I think,
was seven or nine eligibility termination forms. They also don't intend to submit full applications for all of those, but they, for planning purposes, to get all their ducks in a row, to have several month lead time to know which ones are worth filling out a complete application form to know what's eligible. And we also are expecting one from the mayor's office for the condon shell.
But those are the ones that I know offhands that are City of Medford projects. As Council Longo Kern mentioned, knowing that there's a set amount of money.
Do you think that we're opening the floodgate to other recipients or potential recipients saying, you know what, we don't want to sit back and wait. We want to make ours as urgent as everyone else, get in there early, do what we have to do to be ahead of the curve. Do you think we open ourselves up for that by accepting something before?
My sense from talking with other committee members is that they feel very conservative about considering an off-cycle application, that they want to see a very
defined legitimate purpose for the off-cycle application, that the reason why the funding would need to be committed prior to when everybody else's funding is committed, there's a hard outside
deadline, externally imposed deadline that drives that early application. It's not just that they thought of it before everyone else, but it's because something else from outside is causing them to have to make that commitment now as opposed to later. And as I said, it's only something that we would consider for something that meets the high priority as defined in the planning process that we undertook.
So the possibility is there, but I think that unless that external deadline applies to a project, they're going to be asked to get in the regular stream on cycle with the other applicants.
Councilor Russo. Mr. President, I think we need to be certain of our intentions here because we're committing ourselves to a portion of this project needs and there still remains a balance of $176,000, $177,000 nearly.
I'm correct in reading this 217 that we've been informed by someone
who may or may not be authorized to inform us of that, that it's going to be asked for from free cash. So I hope when it comes time to make that expenditure that we'll go through with it. Secondly, I wonder sometimes if, since there's been such a call in the past to not pass these proposals that are sent to us for the first time,
why that concern isn't being raised, but I am in favor of this, Mr. President. Thank you.
Thank you, President Carviello. One question about the applications. The applications or the forms that do come in, are those gonna be public, go public? Are we gonna be able to check them out online before you discuss them? Yes, it's all public information, so I was waiting until the deadline this Friday to aggregate everything and put it at least on the preservedbedford.org website. Oh, on your website, okay. Yes, we would host it and have them all there.
And then just through the chair.
I'm not sure the city said we were definitely gonna be taking this out of free cash. It sounded like we, it's possible. But will we be putting in, I guess, will we be putting in another application for CPA funding for the remaining? Not for this project. I mean, not for phase one. Not for phase one, but for phase two, potentially, for the 217,000. At that stage, we should be on time because
We should not be out of cycle, although we won't know if we're likely to get a grant. For instance, if there's a funding cycle, we'll say from the park program in March.
I wouldn't get the decision from the park program, you know that the CPA couldn't make their decision with all the other decisions and then when the park program came through we could put it all together.
I think that this will be the only major off-cycle application because I think they will be anticipation rather than having a very good idea if you're getting matching funding. But for instance, I could, for instance, make an application for park funding in March, also make a CPA for the following October, and usually park funds, you're told about October and November if you're getting them. So it would line up in a different way than this. This is an exceptional circumstance.
Because this is the first year of the CPA All that Okay, I think thank you. I think I read it wrong. I thought both phases were the 817 and you wouldn't need the 217 till phase two, but I guess it I Look at the sentence again. So phase two. Do we know how much that is gonna cost? I
There's a concept plan, and again that looks at the moment about $600,000, but that's phase two. We have to deal with phase one first. That's what we're pursuing at the moment.
When we did the, last February when we did the concept for the whole park, then we realized we'd have to divide it into two pieces because the grants that are available generally are in the $300,000 to $400,000 range, and also they're reimbursable usually, and park grants,
Land and water, which we're hopefully getting for this, is a 50% reimbursement. So for instance, to get 300, you need to spend at least 600 of what they call eligible expenses. At the moment, park is 60% reimbursement, so the figure is related. So to answer your question, I think this is phase one.
817,000 is phase one. But that also includes design and construction oversight. Very often when we come to, we have already funded design or we've started the design, and very often when we get to a stage, and it's usually a major problem for us, when we go into construction, we have no money for construction oversight, and we have no contingency, and we are really in a bind. The proposal is to properly fund this so that we can actually do the project.
Councilor Mox. Clota. In previous grants that we've received, matching grants, we always had to show where we're gonna get the funding from, correct?
That's what happens when we come to you, when we get the letter saying we're awarded. We come to you and when you do the vote, you will vote to accept the grant and to appropriate the funds. And that's one vote and that has to be sent to the state before they will actually sign the grant contract.
But I just want to make sure we're talking about the same thing. When you say accept the funds, that is from the matching grant? So we have to vote to accept the matching grant? But we also have to take a vote to approve this tonight, right? And when you go back to apply for the matching grant, all you're going to have at that particular time is what we're voting on tonight, and that doesn't cover the full project.
Yes, so when we come to you, we'll say in a month or six weeks, we will be asking you for another $217,000. Correct. I understand that, but are you going to be, between now and then, are you going to be applying for the... No, I've applied for it. You put in the application, and then you wait till they say, here we are, we're going to award it to you, and then we come to you, because there's no point in asking you for money if we don't know we're getting a match, because you've got to say no.
So that's the way when we know we're getting the money then we come to you to say please accept the grant and front the total amount. So what's the urgency of voting on this tonight then? The CPA money has to be allocated in advance of us coming to you with the grant application because once
Once the city allocates money, then it cannot be replaced with CPA money. And that's why you have to get the CPA in place first. What happens if the other $200,000 doesn't come to fruition? We're in trouble.
We need the project, the council is basically the body who controls whether this project will happen or not, because they approved funds. And you're saying phase two is another 600,000, so we're looking at about a million? At the moment, that's not designed or anything. We'll be looking to come maybe next year for phase two. This is hypothetical at the moment, but I'm trying to be as direct as I can, telling as much as I know.
So why aren't we being asked to vote for the free cash tonight also? I mean, if you're going to get a commitment to use funds for CPA, so that means this body supports the concept, why wouldn't we be asked to... We could have done that, but you might be reluctant to do that when you haven't got the grant in your hand.
You know, when you appropriate the money then, you've appropriated on the off chance, I don't believe this for a second, we didn't get the park grant, sorry it's land and water, then you would have allocated money. It gives you a sense of security that the project is definitely going to happen before you allocate the additional funds.
And if we don't get the grant, that money just goes back into the CPA? I don't believe for a second that we won't get the grant. I've been told by the coordinator of the state that she's 99% sure, but she cannot absolutely say it until she gets the letter.
I just wanted to answer, if the funds, if CPA funds are appropriated for a project and not used for that project, they can be returned to the pool that's available for other projects. Shall be returned, yes. You can always vote to rescind back to the category in which you programmed the money.
Thank you, Mr. President. Councilor Falco. Thank you, Mr. President. One quick question on what you just mentioned. So does that money automatically go back in? Does it automatically go into that same bucket that it came out of? Yes. OK, perfect. Thank you.
That's actually why we specifically tell you which bucket it's coming out of, so that we know which bucket to put it back into should it ever occur on this or any future project. That's fine. I just wanted to get confirmation, just because it seemed, the way you said it, it just seemed funny. But I just wanted to make sure. So it goes back into the same bucket it came out of, and it can be used.
the future for that purpose. Yes. Thank you very much. I mean, this is I mean, I've been down to Harris Park a number of times, and I think it's definitely a park that needs some work. We have a lot of parks that need some work, but I know that that park does need a lot of work. And I think it's definitely a worthy project. So thank you. Councilor McGrath. Thank you, President Carviello. I just want to check in on this $817,000 figures. Is that what you're submitting to the state?
Can that change at all? I mean, could it go down or could we reduce the project at all? What we applied to the state for, let me see, something like,
I think it was $667,000. You can only get $300,000. The maximum grant available in this cycle is $300,000. So you have to apply for at least $600,000. And it has to be eligible. And there are things that are not eligible that you need in a project. For instance, construction oversight. The Clerk of the Works is not an eligible expense.
Police details are not an eligible expense. So if you spend that, you have to have money for that because the state will not reimburse that. And that's why the money is more.
Councilor Nye. Mr. President, I as one member of this body, very excited to see that the CPA is moving forward. I think that when the CPA ballot question was put on, put to the test for the voters, that this is what they envisioned happening. It's what I envisioned happening as well, where the community comes together and they put together a plan and work together to come up with a goal. And I really think this is a great plan. I think it's a bold plan.
It's an expensive plant, but I think it's worthwhile, and I think it's a project that deserves to be funded. It has great merit. So for those reasons, Mr. President, I move for approval on the paper. On the motion by Councilor Nice, seconded by Councilor DelaRusso. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
18-012, dear President Caraballo, members of the Memphis City Council. Recently, the city was informed that Medford will be the site of the filming of certain segments of a television production called City on a Hill. Yes, we are.
Location Manager Ryan Cook and his staff have been in contact with various city officials regarding these filming activities. At this time, it is anticipated that one of the filming days will be January 16th. The production staff has advised Director of Public Health Department that it anticipates having a food truck preparing food for its crew in the parking lot of the VFW. I respectfully request that the council endorse an approval of food trucks for this production as it has done in the past year. Thank you.
On the motion by Councilor DelaRusso, Councilor Nyeth. Yes, Mr. President, just my understanding that this is a food truck that's going to be not open to the public, but just open to the staff of the crew that's working on the film. That is correct. With that being said, I second Councilor DelaRusso's motion. On the motion by Councilor DelaRusso, seconded by Councilor Nyeth. All those in favor? Aye. Motion passes.
Motion by Councilor Knight to revert back to regular business. Second by Councilor Falco. All in favor? Motion passes.
18-0-0-7, offered by Councilor Mox, be it resolved that the sidewalk on the corner of Bradshaw and Honeywell be replaced in the interest of public safety. Councilor Mox. Thank you, Mr. President. This particular sidewalk panel has been an ongoing problem for a number of years. There's a small shade tree that is pushing up
The panel, one of the residents actually tripped and got seriously hurt on this particular sidewalk. So I would ask that DPW immediately go out there and review the issue in the interest of public safety. The motion by Councilor Mogg, seconded by Councilor Scarpelli. All those in favor? Motion passes. 18-0-0-8, offered by Councilor Falco.
Whereas resident students are forced to walk in the street when traversing city-owned sidewalks during and after snow storms. Be it resolved that the City of Medford purchase a trackless plow or snow removal apparatus to remove snow from city-owned sidewalks and property during inclement weather
You give our DPW department the tools that they need to succeed. Councilor Falco. Thank you, Mr. President. This is an item that I have brought before the council before in the past, and the council supported it unanimously in the past and has not been included in past budgets, and it's something that
I've strongly advocated for before, and I continue to do so. We expect our residents to clear their sidewalks after it snows, and the city should be doing the same thing with regard to city properties and sidewalks as well.
You know, we see our students, you know, they walk to and from school, residents walk when it snows out, and it's important to keep our sidewalks clean of snow. And it's basically a public safety issue. And now when you bring the Chevalier Theater on board now with running shows during the winter and whatnot, you know, we're asking people to walk from the parking lots here at City Hall
to Chevalier Theatre, and that's another reason why we should have a piece of machinery like this that can clear the snow. And it's important that we give our city workers, the DBW workers, the tools that they need, and I'm happy to say that we received a paper tonight
from the mayor's office, and I'll read it. It's in response to the resolution that I offered, and it's from, let's see, it's from Brian Kerentz. It's a commissioner of public works, and it's in response to Councilor Falco's resolution.
18-008. After meeting with Mayor Stephanie M. Burke on Thursday, December 28th, regarding the purchase of a trackless plow for the Department of Public Works to better clear sidewalks during the winter months, we will be purchasing one for $130,545. The machine is called the Holder, and it is made in Canada. The local dealer for this machine is in Chelmsford, Massachusetts.
The machine will have a snowblower attachment, a power reversible plow blade, and a dump body and a sander unit. So happy to say that this issue sounds like it's being addressed. Mr. President, if you wouldn't mind, if we could get just a further answer with regard to the timing on this, when we should actually see this piece of machinery here in our city and when we could actually see, may possibly see it in service.
Thank you. Council Member Kern. Thank you, President Carviello. I want to thank Councilor Falco and second the resolve. Definitely need this piece of equipment sooner than later. He brought up a good point and we all discussed it at our meeting regarding the Chevalier Theatre.
And the last several weeks, our sidewalks haven't really, they're doing the best they can, but I think it's really, they're definitely shoveled out, and I see our DPW out there working hard, but with regards to this apparatus and having a sander on it, it's something that we so desperately need, and it will definitely help everybody traverse our sidewalks.
having the shows coming in, that's important, but we also have everyday customers and business owners traversing our sidewalks in the squares, and they need to be shoveled and sanded, and hopefully this will go a very long way and help out the department of the DPW to make sure we clear every square and sidewalk that we can, especially those two that are, the children that are going to school,
I've got complaints already with regards to children heading to school, having to go onto the street, putting, obviously, their safety in jeopardy. So this is extremely important and hopefully it will go a very long way in every snowstorm. Thank you. Councilor Nye. Move approval, Mr. President. Councilor Scott Pelly.
Again, thank you, Mr. President. Thank you, Councilor Falco, for bringing that up. And I know that Kent Krause is in the crowd tonight. One thing we've all worked on is working with the school system, especially. Kent traverses the Brooks area, and that's one of the hot spots that we always get phone calls from. And I think that what we really need to make sure that there's a collaboration and there's
discussion, both the city and the school side, in making sure that these areas are done and there's a line of communication open between both departments. Not to say there isn't, but sometimes they do fall through the cracks. We're expecting, and I know that even this Thursday, they've increased it to 12 to 15 inches.
for this Thursday and getting those areas taken care of as soon as possible.
work on a plan for this upcoming storm to make sure these common areas are taken care of. I know that, unfortunately, probably won't be here by Thursday, so I just wanted to make sure that that was out there. So, thank you.
Name and address of the record, please. Yes, thank you again, Ken Krause, 50 Mystic Street. I wanted to speak in support of this resolution. I'm pleased to hear that the city has responded so quickly. I think the need has increased recently, and particularly, as you've heard, we're doing a lot of investing in our parks.
Our squares, we have a very active Walk Medford community. We have a very active bicycle commission. The Mr. Grover Watershed Association is putting a lot of emphasis behind completing the Mystic Greenways network. Some of those trails that we're seeing come online are
responsibility of the city, some are not. So this will be helpful where we need to use the device at the parks and the trails that we're responsible for. But we're just going to be seeing a lot more people using the sidewalks and using the trails where this will be used.
I'm glad to see this is brought forward. And also, I know from my past experience with the transition team on the recreation subcommittee, we got a tour of all the parks from Mike Nestor, the park foreman. And he had said at that time that for a number of years, he has been strongly advocating for this type of a machine as well. So I know it'd be very welcome.
One of the things he pointed out, in addition to its value and utility, currently the city has to, or at least when we spoke two years ago, use a bobcat primarily for removing the snow from sidewalks and places like this. And that requires another truck and a trailer to take it and deliver it to the site to be used. Whereas this type of machine is completely independent. It can run on its own and doesn't require the need for the truck and the trailer.
The last question I had, and this kind of goes along the lines of urgency for this. I'm glad we're thinking about it for next year's budget, but perhaps it could come even sooner. And my question would be, is this something that could be possibly eligible for linkage fee money to be used on?
We hear a lot about linkage fees when they're required for developments and a lot of developments are residential and they bring into the community a lot of people that use the sidewalks and use the paths, a lot of younger people, a lot of people that are bicycle users.
All kinds of people. And the linkage process is sort of mysterious to me. It's just a resident who, you know, tries to pay attention to what's going on. I rarely see, if ever,
Any kind of meetings where they talk about the linkage money you'll see on the Zoning Board of Appeals meetings This is this project requires linkage money But we never really hear how much came in and where it goes and what it's what it's used for I think maybe correct me if I'm wrong that the council might even have a seat on the linkage committee that decides to
point of information. Point of information Councilor Dela Russo. The president of the City Council is ex officio, a member of the linkage committee. And during my two year tenure as president, we met three times in properly noticed meetings
do we call the minutes? Yes. I'll investigate. It's good to know. And I think under Mayor Burke, we, no, I never met, maybe I met once under Mayor McLennan. I've had a couple. Under Mayor Burke, we've probably spent a good portion of it down on this type of stuff, the type of stuff of parks, public safety. It's parks, public safety, and one more.
Infrastructure related to the development that comes in. So my point was that. I think I've had a couple Ken. It could be eligible. I would like to know as a citizen what kind of money is available and if this is eligible because if we don't need to put it in next year's budget, then perhaps that money could go toward additional personnel for the DPW because perhaps this will be utilized a lot and can't be used for people.
Yeah, no, I'm saying that this, if we buy the machine with linkage money, we could use the budget money for personnel. I know we can't use linkage money for personnel, so just wanted to raise that as a possibility to expedite, hopefully getting this machine sooner than later. So thank you, Councilor Falcone, for bringing that up. Councilor Locren. Maybe just as a side paper, we can get an update of how much money is in the linkage account currently.
On the motion by Councilor Falco, as amended by Councilor Lungo-Kern, seconded by Councilor Neistat. All those in favor? Aye. Mr. Clerk, roll call has been requested by Councilor Falco.
Vice President Dela Russo. Yes. Councilor Falco. Yes. Councilor Knight. Yes. Councilor Allen-Curran. Yes. Councilor Mach. Yes. Councilor Scott Pelli. Yes. President Caprio. Yes, seven in the affirmative, none in the negative. Motion passes. 18-009, offered by Councilor Falco and Councilor Scott Pelli, be it resolved that the Memphis City Council extend its deep and sincere condolences to the family of Joseph Pace on his recent passing.
Councilor Falco. Thank you, Mr. President. Just this past Christmas Eve, we lost a good friend, Joe Pachi. He was a one-time Metro resident, lived up on Doonan Street for many years with his family, and owned Joe Pachi and Son grocery store. And just overall, just a great guy. I mean, good friend, great guy, and someone that was always there to help.
For many years, I mean he you know when he had moved out of Medford, he always found time to donate time donate money Give to charitable organizations throughout our city. So he will be Missed greatly in thoughts and prayers to his family. Thank you council Scott belly Thank you. I know council Falco not to repeat but I
Joe deserves it. Joe Pace was a wonderful Italian-American, often the strongest voice in the North End while they were going through the big dig, and a person that loved his job and loved his family. I know Angela and Joe and Joey and
You know, I spent a lot of time and donated a lot of time and effort in St. Francis Parish at the time. And they were, Joe's passing, Wilhurt, he was one of those individuals that left a mark. And I think everybody that you talked to had a positive story about Joe Pace. And I can say a few from my personal, but I'll leave that with the family and myself.
We'll miss him and send our condolences to the family. Thank you. All rise, please.
18-013 offered by Councilor Knight, be it resolved that the Memphis City Council request the City Administration provide a cost estimate for the implementation of an annual diversity training program for all employees within the City of Memphis. Councilor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much.
number of new personnel that are coming on here in the community and this council's commitment to diversity and to inclusion in the city as well as that of the administration and the hiring of a new director of Diversity I think that it only makes sense for us mr. President to continue building upon the positive progress that we've made in the past When Diane McLeod was the director of the office of diversity she did have annual trainings for our city employees whether it was
a training module on the computer or a presentation, Mr. President, but I think it was very beneficial. And I think it's something that doesn't, that should be pushed by the wayside. So I'm asking the administration to take the appropriate steps to provide the council with a cost analysis as to what it costs to provide an annual diversity training for the city employees. And then we can take appropriate steps to determine whether or not we want to codify this as an ordinance. I request that it be done by executive order to ensure that it continues, Mr. President. So I'm asking my council colleagues to support this endeavor.
so that we can get a little bit more information about what it costs for us to be able to implement an annual diversity training for our city employees.
On the motion by Councilor Knight, seconded by Councilor De La Russa, all those in favor? Motion passes. 18-014 offered by Councilor Knight, be it resolved that the Memphis City Council request directed patrols to enforce resident access restrictions on Hastings Lane with particular focus on the morning and evening commuting hours. Councilor Knight.
Yes, Mr. President, unfortunately the Waze app has found Hastings Lane and there are many vehicles that would come from Winchester and cut right down Woburn Street and follow Woburn Street all the way to the end and then cross over to High Street and go right down Hastings Lane even though it says resident access only between 7 to 9.
It's becoming a problem in the neighborhood. There are many young families that live in the neighborhood. It's not an easy street to get up and down. Portions of it are unpaved. Portions of it are paved. Certain portions wouldn't allow two cars to traverse at the same time. And this lack of conscientiousness by certain commuters is causing an issue in the neighborhood, Mr. President. On Christmas Eve, I had the opportunity
to visit a family friend over there, like I do every year. And the conversation that I had with every member of the family revolved around the number of cars that are going down the street during the hours that they're not supposed to be going down there, never mind the speed. So I'm asking, Mr. President, for the Traffic Division to do a directed patrol at Hastings Lane, either at the top at High Street or at the bottom down on Parkway, while the restrictions are in place, to see if we can catch some people going through the Do Not Enter sign.
If a person goes down a restricted access street like that, when they go down that street, that is a moving violation. It's a surchargeable offense. It goes on your registration. It goes on your insurance, Mr. President. So for individuals that want to save five minutes cutting down a street, they have to realize that that five minutes that they're saving could cost them $700 a year for the next seven years.
I think that, you know, there's a lack of conscientiousness and just ignorance, Mr. President, when it comes to some of these signs. And I think we're all guilty of it. We've all gone down a sign that might have said, you know, resident access only before. I know I've done it on rural ave before. We've all done it. But ultimately, it's causing an issue in the neighborhood. It needs to be addressed. And I'm asking for some help from our police department.
If I can amend that to ask if the police department has a way of contacting Waze to have them come down and put them on notice of the signs on different streets. I don't know if Waze has a... I would certainly be open to amending the paper as a B paper. I just don't want them to say that we can't contact Waze so we're not going to do the directive patrol. So as long as it's a B paper and they have two separate tasks to move on, I'd be happy to do it, Mr. President.
Thank you, Mr. President, I was just gonna mention that I know he has
some sort of contact or some way to reach out to ways he's done it in the past. And this is definitely something that I think we should definitely push in his direction, have him look into. It definitely needs to be addressed. It's amazing what that app has done to our city streets in our neighborhoods. And while we're on the topic, just to mention really quick, tomorrow night at the Lawrence Memorial Hospital School of Nursing is our next
community police meetings. I just wanted to bring that up, but I thought it was appropriate to bring it up now, since we are talking about this issue here, and a lot of issues like this here are discussed during that type of meeting. The Lawrenceboro Hospital is right down the street from Hastings Lane, so if anybody in Hastings Lane wants to go down to the hospital, let the chief know. On the motion by Councilor Layton, on the B paper, that we contact Sergeant Hartman, contact Waze, and see if they can update their software.
seconded by the councilor falco all those in favor right on the original paper offered by councilor night seconded by councilor falco all in favor all right motion passes president motion take papers in the hands of the clerk motion by councilor night to take papers in the hands of the clerk seconded by councilor scarpelli
18-015, offered by Councilor Scott Pelley. It's the resolve of Memphis City Council to send their deep and sincere condolences to the family of John Bob Conner on his recent passing. Councilor Scott Pelley. Thank you, Mr. President. The Conner family, well-known in the Spring Street area. Mr. Conner was a loving member of his community. He loved Medford.
He was a member of the Mustang Association. He was also a past board member of the Wellington Club with Little League. I grew up with his son, Sean.
Mr.. As of yesterday's wake had some great stories how mr.. Connor up until last week watched our program on Tuesday nights and made sure he always Sent message and what he thought This council should be doing so and I appreciated that he's a great person great family Great Mustang, so he'll be missed
Thank you. And we have another one here. Offered by Councilor Knight. Be it resolved that the Memphis City Council send its deep and sincere condolences to the family of Dante DeFranco Sr. on his recent passing. Councilor Knight. Mr. President, yes, thank you very much. For any of us from West Medford, we'd all know Dante DeFranco. He'd be the best dressed guy walking around West Medford Square, Mr. President.
construction work that was always impeccably dressed and always someone that was willing to sit down and give you a hello and ask how you were doing down in West Memphis Square. So with that being said, Mr. President, he suddenly passed away just over the past week and I'd like to have my council colleagues join me in offering my condolences and our condolences to Mrs. DeFranco and Dante Jr. and Danielle and Dean as they go through this difficult time, especially during the holidays, Mr. President. Thank you. And we have one last one offered by Councilor Knight.
January 6, 2018 marks the 7th anniversary of the passing of lifelong resident of Medford, Vietnam veteran, community activist, and Governor's Counselor, Michael J. Callahan. Be it resolved that the Memphis City Council hold a moment of silence in his honor, and be it further resolved that the Memphis City Council dedicate the 1-2-18 Council Meeting in memory of Michael J. Callahan, former Governor's Counselor, Counselor Knight.
Mr. President, thank you very much. Michael and I were very close friends. Michael was a mentor to me. He taught me a great deal about how government works. And I think when you look at Michael Callaghan and his career in government, especially as a resident here of Medford who's been credited with the legend of saving Wrights Pond from development, his slogan in the 2005 Senate campaign summed up Michael Callaghan. And Michael Callaghan helped people. He helped people.
That's what Michael did, and I sadly miss Mr. President. I'd ask my colleagues to join me in a moment of silence and to dedicate tonight's meeting in his memory. Please rise. Records. The meeting of records for the decisive meeting are passed to Councilor Mox.
excuse me, December 19th, we will pass to Council of Mox. Council of Mox, how did you find those records? On the motion by Council of Mox to approve of the record, seconded by Councilor Scott Kelly. All in favor? Motion passes. On the motion by Councilor Scott Kelly for adjournment, seconded by Councilor Knight. All in favor? Motion passes, meeting adjourned.
you
the smog and the fog and the pollution has gripped the airport and not many people have been getting in and out of the city so not a great new year start I'm afraid to say. No indeed I do worry for your health when you join us on Business Matters Rahul because I know you go out to the street because you get a better signal to be able to broadcast but you do have to breathe in all of the fumes of the traffic.
I know, but it's now the cold air here, I'm afraid. It may be 20 degrees, but I have to say, quite a comical sight in Kolkata at the moment. It looks like a convention of bank robbers, as everybody's wearing these monkey caps, balaclavas, shivering in 20 degrees, I'm afraid to say here.
Sounds terrible, as we're about 15 degrees colder. Talk to me about one of these stories that you've been looking at, which is to do with Indian doctors not very happy with the government because it is offering, or considering offering, a short kind of bridging course to homeopaths and others trained in alternative medicines that would allow them to become doctors. It's being called sanctioned quackery.
Yes, indeed it is. And you know, this is not the first time the idea has been considered. And whilst a lot of doctors of yesterday went on a strike in private hospitals, others in public hospitals were wearing black armbands to say, look, what a ludicrous idea this is, what the government and actually some other people involved in the medical profession say is, India has a huge problem. It does not produce enough doctors.
And not only does it not produce enough doctors, but if you go into the rural sector of the country, many doctors don't want to go and stay there because they say the facilities aren't good enough for their children in terms of education, etc. So what's going to happen to the health needs of these people? You can't suddenly create, you know, double the number of doctors overnight. So you have to find some sort of interim solution. And that's what this idea has always been, that you take people
who practice medicine, these sort of quacks that exist up and down this country, and give them a little bit more professional training. Look, they're operating anyway, a lot of people say, so, you know, give them some medical skills so that they're able to cope with basic emergencies, so that people in those areas can actually have some sort of medical
treatment when they need it in those situations. I mean doctors on the other hand say look you know this is just not the right way to do it but I have to say you know when I go to rural India you see quacks performing there. They are being used by a lot of people there. I think there is a lot of critics and a lot of others who say you have to give some sort of medical facilities to people so let's try this method out because at the moment you have millions and millions of people in India who have no access to health care.
Indeed. Another story which is in the Times of India today. The number of visitors to the Taj Mahal is to be capped at 40,000 a day. Why is that? I think it is just the damage that the sheer number of people who are visiting the Taj Mahal, you know, cause. I mean, I've been there on public holidays to India's most famous monument, one of the greatest monuments in the world.
You know, and you can have 60, 80,000 people who are turning up. And there's been a long debate about how do you protect, you know, India's iconic building. And I think now this is why they've decided that at least for Indians, there's going to be 20,000 in the morning, 20,000 in the afternoon. Once they cross that figure, you just won't be able to go in. The good news for all the foreign tourists is no restrictions on them, but obviously they pay far more than Indians.
Anyway, and I think it's part of a much wider debate whether you're talking about India's, when India's looking at tourism, about how to protect it. I mean, the tigers are another thing here. I mean, how do you protect the national parks from the huge number of people who are coming in? And I think India's looking at a much more long-term vision when it comes to tourism now, because it's not about getting people in over the next 10 years. It's about the next 50, 100 years about how you develop it. So I think we could see more things like this at other sites in India as well.
Is this controversial with many people that Indians are going to be restricted in numbers visiting an Indian monument, yet foreigners won't?
I think that once it comes in, it probably will be. And I think it's about communicating that information accurately to people, because often when you go to the Taj, you know, you'll see people who come from miles and villages, a lifetime's moment to go and see it. And if they turn up and find out that it's shut or it's going to be shut to them, I'm sure they are going to get pretty angry.
I think it's about getting that information out. A lot of people still turn up at the Taj Mahal, foreigners and Indians, on a Friday, even though it's closed. So I think it's getting that information out. But certainly, if you've spent a lot of money getting there as an Indian, and you're restricted to get in, and you see foreigners going in, well, you may get annoyed. But there is a little loophole there. If you do want to go in, if you pay the foreigners' rate, whether you're a foreigner or not, you will be allowed in. The problem is, for many Indians, that's just going to be way too expensive.
Indeed. Interesting. Thank you, Rahul. Get back indoors. Get out of all that fumes. Clearly got the back of your throat a bit earlier. Good to talk to you as always. That's the BBC's Rahul Tandon there in Calcutta in India. And they called it puppy love. How much is that hound dog in the window?
I do hope that fleabag's first.
We are going doggy crazy on Business Matters. Various songs, I'm sure you'll recognise that. I won't ask Andrew People and Bridget Bodnar to name every single song, that would be unfair. But we are going to discuss something called Paternity Leave. We've discussed over the years on Business Matters the various pet-friendly policies that companies
have brought in, but this is a new related trend. Lots of employees of course take maternity, paternity leave when they have a baby or adopt a child, but now many companies are offering paternity leave for pet owners. It is where employees are allowed to take time off when they get a new dog. It started among US technology startup businesses, but it seems to be spreading.
A brewery in Ohio has introduced the policy. It's the appropriately named Brew Dog USA. I've been talking to the boss, Tanisha Robinson, and I asked her about her own four-legged friends. I actually have three dogs. We have a pit bull hound mix, a chihuahua, and a pomeranian. So about 90 pounds of dogs, but in the form of three creatures.
And so why did you decide then to introduce Pawternity? Was this because you yourself wanted some time off? No, I don't have any new dogs on my horizon, which is now post the introduction of Pawternity Leave, but we feel that it's a great benefit to offer our team when they introduce a new family member, whether it's a human or canine member of the family, so that people can take time to bond. It's not just because you've got the word dog in the name of the company.
Well, I mean, our company was founded by two humans and one dog ten years ago, so that is certainly an important component of our business. What is the benefit of doing this? Because you don't offer it for people who get a new cat or a new rabbit or something, do you? So why have you decided to introduce it?
We want to be the best place to work on the earth ever. And, you know, dogs have a special place in the history of our business. And certainly, you know, someone who's horribly allergic to cats, you know, I think dogs are truly a man's best friend. How much time then can people take off? People get a week off. They bring a new dog into their family. And it's paid? Yes. How many people have made use of this then so far? So on our US team, we've had four people take paternity leave so far.
What do the colleagues of people with dogs make of this? Because if you don't have a dog, of course, you're not entitled to it. Well, they certainly have the opportunity to be entitled to it if they adopt a dog or bring a new dog into their family. But we also are a dog-friendly office space, so there's a lot of love for dogs in our business.
Do you think it's only a certain type of company that does and will offer this kind of leave for employees? Because some people still grumble they get too few holidays, never mind being able to take time off to look after a pet. At BrewDog, it's really important for us to take great care of our people. Our two most important things in our whole business are our people and our beer. And for us, that means letting people spend some time bonding with a new puppy if they get one.
You said you also let people bring dogs to work. Do they not cause a nuisance in the office, wandering in during meetings or demanding they go for walkies when you're on a deadline or something?