21-301 and 22-047 committee.
The whole meeting Tuesday, January 3rd, 2023 at 6 p.m.
is called to order.
Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Mr. Chair.
Present.
Councilor Kerrio.
Councilor Collins.
Present.
Councilor Knight.
Councilor Fevella.
Present.
Councilor Sanz.
present to absent.
There will be a meeting of the Medford City Council Committee of the Whole on Tuesday, January 3rd, 2023 at 6 p.m.
in the Medford City Council Chambers and via Zoom.
The purpose of this meeting is to address the application of BJ's Wholesale Club for a flammable storage license for a proposed fueling station including two 20,000 gallon and one 24,000 gallon underground fuel storage tanks at 278 Middlesex Avenue, Medford Bass, 02155 in an industrial zoning district
shown on Assessor's Map P17, Lot 5, and Maps O16, Lot 1.
The original application is part of Council Paper 21-301 for April 13, 2021.
This meeting will begin in open session.
As this is an ongoing legal matter, BJ's Wholesale Club, Incorporated versus City of Medford City Council, the Committee of the Whole may vote to enter into executive session pursuant to General Law's Chapter
30 a section at 21 purpose three of the Massachusetts Open meeting law.
If the chair so declares that discussion is open in open session may have a detrimental effect on the city of Medford's litigation position.
The city council has invited Attorney General Janelle Austin of K. P. Law to attend this meeting.
For further information, aids and accommodations, contact the city clerk at 71 3932425.
Sincerely yours,
Nicole Morrell, Council President.
So as this meeting notice has stated, this is about the litigation facing the City Council.
There will be, it has been posted that this hearing has been remanded to, there'll be a public hearing on this once again on the 17th.
So this is a meeting for the City Council to get an update of where we stand.
Attorney Austin is online.
Second.
On the motion by Councilor Carvillo to go into executive session for the reasons listed in the meeting notice, seconded by Vice-President Behrs.
Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Yes.
Six in the infirmary zero negative one absolutely motion passes the council executive session which will also include moving to a breakout room on zoom with just the council and legal.
Bye-bye.
Thanks.
Mr. Clerk, can you hear me?
I just wanted to confirm whether or not the council was going to reconvene or exit from executive session.
Sorry, we're going to go into executive session.
We're not we have to vote to go into executive session.
So we're going to do that right now.
We're just trying to set up a breakout room.
We're just figuring out the.
how to make sure we hear everyone on Zoom, but don't broadcast the TV.
Oh, sorry.
I guess, I mean, we'll probably, I don't know, it depends what we talk about.
We may go back to open session.
We may convene from executive session.
Okay, we'll go back to open session just to close.
Thank you, Council President.
I have a motion to adjourn.
Do you have something?
Just to say that if there is anyone watching that we will be holding the hearing on the 17th.
Yes, there will be the remand hearing is scheduled for the 17th, January 17th.
So on the motion, Councilor Carviello to adjourn, seconded by- Seconded.
Vice-President Ferris, Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
vice president bears.
Yes, Councilor Caraballo.
Yes, Councilor Collins.
Yes, Councilor night is absent.
Councilor Scarpelli.
Yes, you're saying?
Yes, President Morrell.
Yes, six in front of zero in the negative one absent motion passes meeting is adjourned.