[SPEAKER_06]: Please be advised there will be a meeting of the Medford Comprehensive High School Elite Committee held at major 489 at Medford Vocational Technical High School, 489 Huntsman Street, and via remote participation for the community.
[SPEAKER_06]: Meetings can be viewed live on the Medford Public Schools YouTube channel, preventative community media, and or with the cable channel, Comcast channel 98422, Verizon channel 4345.
[SPEAKER_06]: Or 47, the meeting will be recorded log in by using the following information to do meeting ideas.
96020419196.
[SPEAKER_01]: Um, just like editorial that they sort of feed that description for everybody to know.
[SPEAKER_01]: What meeting is that thing, which is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You all know why you're here, but some days, but you might watch this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so I'm going to do a quick roll call.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mayor Mungo Kern.
[SPEAKER_01]: Present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dr. Burk Vincent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dr. Lucey.
[SPEAKER_01]: Present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dr. Cushing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Artic Brau.
[SPEAKER_01]: Present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cindy Brown.
[SPEAKER_01]: Marissa Desmond.
[SPEAKER_01]: Present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hi, Marissa.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_01]: How are you doing?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm good, thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Christine.
[SPEAKER_07]: Present.
[SPEAKER_07]: Emily Lazzaro, present.
[SPEAKER_07]: Nicole Morell, present.
[SPEAKER_07]: Aaron Lopate, present.
[SPEAKER_07]: Larry Brown, present.
[SPEAKER_07]: Bob Dickinson, not here.
[SPEAKER_07]: Anna Max, not here.
[SPEAKER_07]: Joe Bowen, here.
[SPEAKER_07]: Tom Dalton, here.
[SPEAKER_07]: Shannon Salad.
[SPEAKER_07]: Lori Hodgson, present.
[SPEAKER_07]: Adam McLaughlin, not here.
[SPEAKER_07]: Oh, so yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: Oh, I'm joining us.
[SPEAKER_07]: Okay, so yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: I asked him to show me bread.
[SPEAKER_07]: So the meeting is called over.
[SPEAKER_07]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'm hoping that we won't need the full two hours tonight.
[SPEAKER_07]: I know everyone probably definitely wants that to be true, so we'll see what we can do.
[SPEAKER_06]: Marissa, if you have any questions, feel free to raise your hand.
[SPEAKER_06]: You can all see your square, so that might just help us know that you want to get an award each at twice.
[SPEAKER_06]: The next thing on the agenda is what we call a consent agenda.
[SPEAKER_06]: And it's essentially a place where you put items that have to be initially approved by the committee, but to which there's probably no conversation really to have.
[SPEAKER_06]: So the three items that are in there that we need to approve tonight are our meeting minutes from our personal meeting, from our lead and onboarding subcommittee meeting, from our communications and community engagement subcommittee meeting.
[SPEAKER_06]: If you take a look at the meeting minutes, you will see that they are very late.
[SPEAKER_06]: That is because those meetings, by and large, did not have a lot of action in terms of motions and votes and things to approve or deny.
[SPEAKER_07]: We also, in the electronic version of this, you can click a link to the YouTube channel and see the actual recorded meeting there.
[SPEAKER_06]: We try to err on the side of slimmer,
[SPEAKER_06]: minutes.
[SPEAKER_06]: These are still totally permissible under the OPA law, but the more detailed they are, the more like you have to read and recount and say, was it accurate?
[SPEAKER_06]: Did I say that in the right way?
[SPEAKER_06]: And you just find that that sort of leads to just a lot of work that I can try to avoid again.
[SPEAKER_06]: So the consent agenda is basically approving the meeting minutes.
[SPEAKER_06]: And the meeting minutes also include several documents that we'll actually talk about in detail.
[SPEAKER_07]: But the first thing is for somebody to make a motion to approve the consent agenda.
[SPEAKER_07]: So motion by Mayor Wendell Kern, seconded by Reese.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_06]: If there was something that you were like, I want to talk about this thing separately, you just let me know and we will sever that, we'll pull it out, we'll put everything else through and then pass the conversation.
[SPEAKER_01]: In general, we're going to try to drop the Robertson's order without boring you all with like lots of financial about Robertson's order.
[SPEAKER_12]: So like the general thing is if you have a question and you don't know how to do it, just ask.
[SPEAKER_12]: the people at the table actually know what we're going to include.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, is that right, colleagues?
[SPEAKER_04]: Is that done on the fly?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: No, yeah, it can be done right at the meeting.
[SPEAKER_06]: And the other thing that's worth noting about OPD Law is that there are people, it is a hybrid meeting in terms of participants.
[SPEAKER_07]: We do a roll call.
[SPEAKER_07]: So, I'm going to do a roll call so that we can vote this through.
[SPEAKER_07]: There was no other questions, right?
[SPEAKER_07]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_07]: Um, so on the motion to approve the consent agenda, they have the longest term.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, 15 in the affirmative, zero at the negative.
[SPEAKER_06]: The minutes are up.
[SPEAKER_06]: For three.
[SPEAKER_06]: One of the things that we charge the rules and onboarding team to do is provide a set of operating rules for this committee and give some thought to onboarding both for all of you as well as for people who may join this committee over time because that's sort of inevitable when you talk about a seven, six, seven year project.
[SPEAKER_06]: So if you flip through your packet,
[SPEAKER_06]: What I wanted to do was just go through these rules and ask you all, like, what questions do you have?
[SPEAKER_06]: If you think anything's missing, this is a place where we can certainly amend these rules.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then when we're done reviewing the rules, we will take a vote to adopt them.
[SPEAKER_06]: So the rules committee met.
[SPEAKER_06]: for about an hour, so they were incredibly efficient.
[SPEAKER_06]: We did a fast job of trying to create a set of rules and an onboarding checklist.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we'll start with the rules.
[SPEAKER_06]: The first thing that we have in here is essentially that we will simply use SBC as the acronym for this, because if you add all of the Medford Comprehensive
[SPEAKER_06]: high school building committee it's a lot of letters so we will adopt SPC as our sort of common acronym.
[SPEAKER_06]: Item number two we had some discussion about so if you watch council meetings or school committee meetings everyone is member so-and-so Councilor so-and-so we sort of
[SPEAKER_06]: Landed on a slightly different approach.
[SPEAKER_06]: We are residents and neighbors, and as such, we will refer to each other by our first name unless somebody requests.
[SPEAKER_06]: Otherwise, the mayor of Medford will be referred to as mayor and the superintendent will be referred to a superintendent.
[SPEAKER_06]: But otherwise, we're gonna be friends and neighbors 1st and committee members 2nd.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that's item number 2.
[SPEAKER_06]: Members of the SBC are urged to speak for themselves using I statements.
[SPEAKER_06]: Allow for one speaker at a time.
[SPEAKER_06]: Be present, engaged, and prepared.
[SPEAKER_06]: Engage in honest and open conversation.
[SPEAKER_06]: Assume the best intentions and understand and acknowledge intent and hold themselves and one another accountable.
[SPEAKER_06]: Item number four, public comment will be limited to three minutes per individual and will be limited to those matters on the agenda.
[SPEAKER_06]: The chair may limit comment to two minutes based on the number of individuals wishing to speak.
[SPEAKER_06]: The chair will announce the timeline before any public comment period at every meeting.
[SPEAKER_06]: The public will also be encouraged to submit their comments in writing by emailing the SBC account.
[SPEAKER_06]: Those emails will be auto forwarded to all members when they come in.
[SPEAKER_06]: Item number five, the SBC will operate following Robert's Rules of Order.
[SPEAKER_06]: And what we try to do here is give you like the ones you need to know in order to sort of function in a basic way.
[SPEAKER_06]: So voting happens when a motion to do something is made and seconded after debate.
[SPEAKER_06]: Under the open meeting law, voice votes are allowed when everybody is physically present.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that's where we say all those in favor, all those opposed.
[SPEAKER_06]: and you just say aye or nay.
[SPEAKER_06]: However, when any voting member is remotely participating, a roll call is required.
[SPEAKER_06]: Any voting member may request a roll call vote.
[SPEAKER_06]: So if we were all here in person and there was something sort of squirrely going on and you're like, no, I really want to know where everybody stands, you just say roll call and then we will do an official roll call so everyone has to register their vote.
[SPEAKER_06]: Any voting member may suggest an amendment to the motion.
[SPEAKER_06]: The chair will guide and support members in following Robert's rules during the meetings.
[SPEAKER_06]: Members may speak twice on any debatable motion for up to three minutes.
[SPEAKER_06]: And once voting begins, no member may speak other than to indicate how they are voting.
[SPEAKER_06]: If a voting member of the committee believes a mistake was made with a motion that passed or failed and that member was in the majority for that motion, they may make a motion to reconsider to do so by speaking to the chair on how to proceed.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, in other words, if something happens really fast and
[SPEAKER_06]: It was sort of a split vote, and somebody that was on the winning side says, wait a minute, I don't think we all know what we just did there.
[SPEAKER_06]: There's a process for us to reconsider, as long as that is raised by somebody who was in the majority vote.
[SPEAKER_06]: And if that happens, just say, wait a minute, I have a question, and we'll work through the mechanics of how to do that.
[SPEAKER_06]: Um, and then if items on the agenda will be taken out of order from how they are presented on the agenda, a voting member must make a motion to spend the rules and take them specifically out of order.
[SPEAKER_06]: Item number six, the chair will create the agenda and place certain items within the consent agenda item.
[SPEAKER_06]: Item number seven, all SBC meetings and or any SBC subcommittee shall operate according to the open meeting law.
[SPEAKER_06]: The SBC shall to the best of its ability ensure its meetings are reported by Medford Public Media and broadcast live to the district YouTube channel.
[SPEAKER_06]: Media requests for comment from the SBC will be directed to the chair of the SBC.
[SPEAKER_06]: Number nine, non-voting members will be called during the roll call at the beginning of the meetings, but their presence will not be counted towards a forum.
[SPEAKER_06]: I did that sort of while I was calling the roll.
[SPEAKER_06]: Non-voting members will not be called for the adjournment of meetings, as this is just simply a vote to adjourn the meeting.
[SPEAKER_06]: And our non-voting members cannot be counted in that group.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then item number 10, new members of the SBC will be onboarded following the checklist, which will be maintained by the responsible committee.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's sort of our proposed set of rules.
[SPEAKER_06]: So the subcommittee both created and considered these rules and is bringing them here tonight for discussion.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I will open the floor if anyone has questions, comments, thoughts, anything they want to change, like this is the time for us to do that because we will adopt those changes as we go.
[SPEAKER_06]: Mayor?
[SPEAKER_06]: Quick question, thank you.
[SPEAKER_12]: chair did you discuss giving everybody three minutes and then limited it to one first one time per topic yes um and the limit to one time per topic did not
[SPEAKER_06]: Because make it in here and that actually completely mirrors how we do public participation at school.
[SPEAKER_06]: So people are welcome to speak on any item that we're discussing, like, members of the public could be weighing in on the rules right now.
[SPEAKER_06]: But, yes, we generally do limit to 3 minutes, 3 minutes per person and you can't.
[SPEAKER_06]: Just get back in line and come back up again and talk for three more minutes.
[SPEAKER_06]: And if there's a lot of public participation, we sort of can make those adjustments on the fly under our rules.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we would, yeah, so we would add one time to that item.
[SPEAKER_07]: Can I see somebody's question?
[SPEAKER_07]: Luke?
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't know if that's something that we can all collectively decide to do without having to partner with that school.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, I think we can.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, yeah, we can do that for the next meeting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Emily?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are we following all of the rubber-toothed order and this is just a reminder of the basic ones that are most common?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, and I think they're hopefully for our purposes, the ones that will need to be used here.
[SPEAKER_06]: You know, there's a lot of like other things that happen when things get wild, and I'm hoping we can navigate through those without having to have y'all go by the 200 page book and read about parliamentary procedure.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that's sort of the goal, and if things get out of hand, we'll adjust.
[SPEAKER_09]: approval as much.
[SPEAKER_06]: Are there any?
[SPEAKER_06]: Is there anything missing?
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, um, so motion to approve as amended by Mayor Lungo-Koehn second seconded by Nicole.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's my list.
[SPEAKER_06]: Mayor Lungo-Koehn?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Dr Edouard-Vincent?
[SPEAKER_06]: Dr Glusi?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Dr Cushing?
[SPEAKER_06]: Marta?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Libby?
[SPEAKER_06]: Marissa?
[SPEAKER_09]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Maria.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Brian.
[SPEAKER_06]: Tracy.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Emily.
[SPEAKER_06]: Nicole.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_09]: Aaron.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Luke.
[SPEAKER_06]: Jenny.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: 15 in the affirmative, zero in the negative.
[SPEAKER_06]: The rules have been adopted.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, item number four is, oh, sorry, also under item number three is the onboarding checklist.
[SPEAKER_06]: So on the next page, what we tried to do was just create like a little checklist of like the kinds of things that we're going to want to remember to do when somebody new joins this committee, which is somewhat inevitable, and things that we want to make sure this group has,
[SPEAKER_06]: has done and is comfortable with.
[SPEAKER_06]: So open meeting law training, for those of you who were here last week, you went through open meeting law training.
[SPEAKER_06]: We will send you like a little thing to attest that you did it just so we can put it in the file and move on.
[SPEAKER_06]: If you missed it, there is training offered by the Attorney General's office and we'll get the presentation from Janelle at KP and make sure that you all have what you need just so that you understand sort of the role open meeting law plays.
[SPEAKER_06]: our SBC rules, which we just adopted.
[SPEAKER_06]: We would want to make sure new members get an overview of the MSDA process, which we did in the last meeting.
[SPEAKER_06]: Everyone will get an email address.
[SPEAKER_06]: I think we're still working on that.
[SPEAKER_06]: Is that right, Dr. Cushing?
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, so you all, if you don't already have an MPS email address, you will get one.
[SPEAKER_06]: Again, highly encourage that all communications about the SBC happen via that email.
[SPEAKER_06]: If you use your personal email to do this, sort of open up your personal email to records requests, so it is not
[SPEAKER_06]: recommended.
[SPEAKER_06]: Just one quick question.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know Emily previously worked for the district.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yep, we will.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is there, and Larry, your email is still active?
[SPEAKER_03]: It's still active.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you're good.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is there anyone else that previously may have not met to publish this email with us?
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, just need to know.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: We'll make sure people have access to the MSBA website and our School Building Authority website.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that is a bit of work in progress, but I'm expecting we'll be able to look at it at the next meeting.
[SPEAKER_06]: We talked a little bit about that at our communications meeting, so more on that in just a second.
[SPEAKER_06]: Obviously, we'll provide people a meeting schedule and add people to our distribution list.
[SPEAKER_06]: Robert's was an order, an email to everybody else to introduce a new member so that everybody knows who to expect.
[SPEAKER_06]: This acronym listing is obviously quite short, and I'm sure it will get much, much longer before we're done.
[SPEAKER_06]: And so that's sort of like our brief onboarding checklist.
[SPEAKER_06]: The other thing that we talked about was
[SPEAKER_06]: Collecting up exemplar documents from other districts, so we can start to look at, like, how other people are navigating this process stone and Belmont Arlington Somerville Winchester.
[SPEAKER_06]: And possibly Mohawk as a vocational school are some places that we would like to go out and sort of collect that information and make it available, not just to the members of this group, but to other members of the community who might be interested in sort of taking a deep dive into the phase that we're at or what we're up to and how other communities are handling these documents.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that's our onboarding checklist.
[SPEAKER_06]: Any questions, thoughts, Tom?
[SPEAKER_03]: Just to offer one correction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Scrivener's error, I think, Jenny.
[SPEAKER_03]: But under important websites, I think we mean to say BedfordSBC website as opposed to SBA website.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_07]: Other questions, comments, thoughts?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: We sort of felt like this would be a living document rather than something to get through.
[SPEAKER_05]: As we move through this process, like, you know, when we've got shovels in the ground, some of these things may be irrelevant, which is our fault, but we want to make sure that this, it's not overwhelming, but actually appropriate for something to be completed.
[SPEAKER_05]: seats.
[SPEAKER_05]: And so I don't know if that was actually written somewhere.
[SPEAKER_05]: It is at the bottom right.
[SPEAKER_05]: But we would just modify it as we did.
[SPEAKER_05]: So anything that you think should be there should let Jenny or me or somebody else add it.
[SPEAKER_05]: It has to be a meeting conversation.
[SPEAKER_05]: Right.
[SPEAKER_07]: Other questions, things that look
[SPEAKER_07]: Maria?
[SPEAKER_07]: Just a question about that list of exemplars.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: Is there a limit on how many years since they built their buildings that we should limit it to within the last five years?
[SPEAKER_07]: You know, anything like that?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: I mean, I think ideally, they would be close in time.
[SPEAKER_06]: Winchester, I think, is a little bit further out.
[SPEAKER_06]: But I think the thing that intrigued me about Winchester was like, they're like,
[SPEAKER_06]: Their overhaul of the building was maybe possibly something that would be similar to what happens here, where the facade changed and they did it in state.
[SPEAKER_06]: So there might just be something interesting there.
[SPEAKER_06]: But I think they were a little bit further back than some of the others.
[SPEAKER_06]: But I think Stoneham's right in the middle of their process.
[SPEAKER_06]: Arlington is.
[SPEAKER_06]: Belmont is.
[SPEAKER_06]: So the rest of them are all very recent.
[SPEAKER_06]: But Winchester sort of jumped out at me because it's a building I know with my eye that
[SPEAKER_06]: has gone through like sort of started out looking a little bit like our building and has gone through that restoration.
[SPEAKER_06]: Luke?
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: Adelbert on what?
[SPEAKER_04]: Admit it man.
[SPEAKER_01]: Have a question to Jane.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is the idea that they're in close proximity?
[SPEAKER_01]: I know Alvaro change that the idea that they're in close proximity or ideally?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes, but they don't have to be.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's like, we know of a district that has gone through this and like.
[SPEAKER_06]: Particularly the ones where it went smoothly, maybe, like those documents are the ones I want to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I know, obviously, to me, Fuller River went through where they kept their field house.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's something that may be relevant to us.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they just opened, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, probably a year ago.
[SPEAKER_12]: Nattleboro was around the same population.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: OK.
[SPEAKER_06]: Other thoughts about this checklist?
[SPEAKER_06]: The other thing that I think might be helpful is it's not as easy as you might think to find some of these exemplar documents.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, Tom, I think we started creating a folder.
[SPEAKER_06]: I don't know how far we got.
[SPEAKER_03]: I would have to check.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's been a couple of weeks.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, I'll check.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: If there's anybody who's willing to take on one of these communities and go find their documents, that would be amazing.
[SPEAKER_06]: Because I think the quicker we can sort of pull all these into some place, the more accessible it will be for everybody.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I don't know if there's any volunteers to take on going to track down Luke.
[SPEAKER_04]: I have a silhouette.
[SPEAKER_06]: OK.
[SPEAKER_06]: Right?
[SPEAKER_06]: So if you can send those my way, I'll get them dropped in the, I'll get them to Tom.
[SPEAKER_06]: We'll get them to Tom so they can be shared.
[SPEAKER_06]: Anybody else?
[SPEAKER_06]: Aaron?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: All right.
[SPEAKER_06]: Aaron will go digging, for example, our documents.
[SPEAKER_06]: Does anybody want to sign on to help Aaron?
[SPEAKER_09]: All right.
[SPEAKER_06]: Which documents?
[SPEAKER_06]: I think for right now, what I'm particularly interested in is their eligibility documents, right?
[SPEAKER_06]: So the same documents we're going to have to send it in, like, they, they have to be in the public records somewhere.
[SPEAKER_06]: But I think if you look at a project, that's just about done, those documents are going to be.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's already well varied, I'm guessing.
[SPEAKER_06]: So it might just take a little bit of digging to find.
[SPEAKER_06]: But I would be interested in what did other people put in their educational profile?
[SPEAKER_06]: Because that's a pretty meaty document, and I'm interested in what all goes in there, because that could give us good inspiration when we start reviewing our educational profile.
[SPEAKER_06]: The same thing with the Chapter 74 form.
[SPEAKER_06]: Those are the two big ones in the eligibility base.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: I spoke with the OPM Watertown.
[SPEAKER_05]: They were remarkably like- Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: They reached out a whole bunch of other projects they were involved with and other OPMs they do.
[SPEAKER_05]: And I was looking for rules, so I didn't ask about any of the documents.
[SPEAKER_05]: So do you want to show me on the list?
[SPEAKER_05]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_05]: dialogue going on.
[SPEAKER_06]: I would assume they have access to them.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Great.
[SPEAKER_06]: Other questions about onboarding?
[SPEAKER_06]: No?
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: So then we'll move on to item number four, which is review and amend proposed communications and community engagement strategy for the eligibility phase.
[SPEAKER_06]: So the communications and community engagement team met and actually I thought we had like a really fun discussion of some of the opportunities that we have.
[SPEAKER_06]: particularly sort of focused around the eligibility phase.
[SPEAKER_06]: So the first thing is like first draft of the website.
[SPEAKER_06]: Our website will be connected to the MPS website.
[SPEAKER_06]: So it's not a standalone thing with a separate architecture.
[SPEAKER_06]: It'll be connected.
[SPEAKER_06]: We have a dedicated domain.
[SPEAKER_06]: All of our sites are secure.
[SPEAKER_06]: So all of that should be fine.
[SPEAKER_06]: The basic structure that we landed on was like,
[SPEAKER_06]: A welcome page like welcome and why, like, why are we doing this?
[SPEAKER_06]: And we'll so Tom and I will work on pending something for that page.
[SPEAKER_06]: We'll have a meetings page where, like, you can go get all the meeting doc agendas and minutes and all that good stuff.
[SPEAKER_06]: A news page where like when we submit documents, where we're doing press releases, that all of that can sort of live.
[SPEAKER_06]: We'll have a documents space so that as we finish and complete documents, they can be posted.
[SPEAKER_06]: Bios for all of you will also be available on the site.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then finally, FAQs, which we'll talk about in just a second, but you know, ultimately sort of an evolving list of
[SPEAKER_06]: Answers to questions people want to know about what we're up to some extent so far.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that's the website sort of broadly and then we did talk about, like.
[SPEAKER_06]: some of our community engagement opportunities in the eligibility base specifically, because I think people are really excited to be part of the things that are going to happen a little bit further down the line, like focus groups with students, focus groups with teachers, focus groups, community members, but like it's going to take some time for us to get there.
[SPEAKER_06]: And so in this eligibility phase, we talked about a couple of things.
[SPEAKER_06]: One was a community survey
[SPEAKER_06]: um where we would collect um some information so the questions that we have on our list is um you know we want to answer your question so tell us what questions do you have about the building committee itself and what questions do you have about the eligibility process um we want to know what kind of features are important to you so tell us like what do you see in a reimagined bedford high school just to like
[SPEAKER_06]: get everybody sort of thinking and excited about that.
[SPEAKER_06]: And what suggestions do you have for the building committee?
[SPEAKER_06]: Tell us who you are.
[SPEAKER_06]: Are you a caregiver, a student, a resident, MPS faculty?
[SPEAKER_06]: What neighborhood are you from?
[SPEAKER_06]: And are you a Medford High student, past, present, or future?
[SPEAKER_06]: Just to sort of get an understanding of like, is there a set of questions that's coming from primarily students, primarily faculty, et cetera?
[SPEAKER_06]: And tell us how you want to be involved in this process.
[SPEAKER_06]: I want to take surveys during the process.
[SPEAKER_06]: I want a tour of MHS.
[SPEAKER_06]: I want to know about your meetings in advance.
[SPEAKER_06]: Just the highlights, please.
[SPEAKER_06]: Tell us how you want to know and be involved in this process.
[SPEAKER_06]: So one proposal that we have is to send out a community-based survey to collect some input that will help inform those FAQs and start to get people thinking about the fact that this is
[SPEAKER_06]: a community-based project for everybody.
[SPEAKER_06]: We did talk about scheduling some tours of MHS, probably not before the end of school this year, because I don't think there's like a single extra minute in the schedule.
[SPEAKER_06]: But, you know, really thinking about like, as we give people a tour, I think that would be very, I think that would be very appealing to people who don't spend any time in this building or don't have kids in this building yet to be able to come in and see like,
[SPEAKER_06]: What are we talking about here?
[SPEAKER_06]: They know what it looks like outside.
[SPEAKER_06]: Maybe they know what the pool looks like, et cetera.
[SPEAKER_06]: But is there some sort of curated tour we can provide people so people start to get an understanding of what this building is?
[SPEAKER_06]: And frankly, what some of the challenges are.
[SPEAKER_06]: I think that needs to be baked into any sort of tour that we're doing.
[SPEAKER_06]: We did talk about being willing to do more staff meetings with your team.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, if there is another staff meeting coming up for the end of the year, or even next year that you want us to participate in, you can do that.
[SPEAKER_06]: We did talk, we had this, Luke had this great idea.
[SPEAKER_06]: There's apparently a video from this back in the 70s when Medford High opened.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that it would be really cool to do some sort of like then and now of like what these spaces look like and how they've aged since the 70s.
[SPEAKER_06]: And Maria is also in the middle of digitizing yearbooks.
[SPEAKER_06]: So she has some history of the old, old MHS.
[SPEAKER_06]: And so we talked about this as, like, maybe a program for, you know, potentially our vocational students to get involved in creating something that would be available.
[SPEAKER_06]: for us for really marketing purposes as we go.
[SPEAKER_06]: So again, nothing that has to be done before the end of June, but these kinds of cool creative things obviously take time.
[SPEAKER_06]: So really thinking about how do we start to create some energy around what's happening in the building and what the potential is.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we did talk about developing a roadshow presentation.
[SPEAKER_06]: And Nicole and Marissa Desmond volunteered to work on a draft of that.
[SPEAKER_06]: We think that content will change all the time, but we do anticipate a lot of reasons to go tell people what's happening here.
[SPEAKER_06]: And so whether it's at school committee, whether the council wants to be briefed on a regular basis, whether we're talking to community groups,
[SPEAKER_06]: We want there to be some common set of talking points so that any member of this committee could say, yes, I'm available on that day.
[SPEAKER_06]: I can go do that talk and sort of carry forward before the committee.
[SPEAKER_06]: A couple of other things we talked about, certainly including some periodic updates in the superintendent's weekly update, but also investigating some sort of like, register your email to subscribe to this particular kind of news, which will be important for people who maybe don't have kids in MPS right now and aren't seeing the superintendent's weekly updates but might be interested in this.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then we also talked about for the website, creating a roadmap that's visual, that demonstrates like, where are we in the process and what steps have we already completed and what's next?
[SPEAKER_06]: So that's something that we'll work on.
[SPEAKER_06]: Maria is going to collect some info for us so that we can start to have tables at some of the community-based events like the Farmers Market, Family Concert Series, Circled Square, those kinds of things.
[SPEAKER_06]: And so once we get there, we may want to have some poster boards of what NHS looks like.
[SPEAKER_06]: You know, something visual about our road map and where we are, but really just to be there to answer questions and create interest in the community and encourage people to to be part of this process.
[SPEAKER_06]: Any questions about that in terms of our, like, communication plan and strategy and the eligibility phase.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, the event tables, I like that a lot.
[SPEAKER_05]: I do think there are a number of businesses that get a lot of foot traffic where we can put things up as well, like Colleen's.
[SPEAKER_05]: CB Scoops.
[SPEAKER_05]: To be fair, yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: But there's probably others as well where we can be very supportive and have a lot of foot traffic.
[SPEAKER_05]: I mean, I'm shocked.
[SPEAKER_05]: My daughter works at Colleen's.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm shocked how many people are in and out of that place.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's wild.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, I think that's a great idea.
[SPEAKER_06]: Luke?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, I think that's a great idea.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I think some of the youth sports organizations will have a vested interest in what becomes of the property as well, because they rely on the fields and that kind of thing.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that's actually a great idea.
[SPEAKER_06]: We can add that.
[SPEAKER_06]: Tracy?
[SPEAKER_08]: One thing that stuck out that I want, also internal but external, is this reimagined improvised school.
[SPEAKER_08]: collective determination of how the committee is going to talk about it during this phase.
[SPEAKER_08]: Is it re-imagined?
[SPEAKER_08]: You know, we don't want to go out and start out and say we're building new or things like that.
[SPEAKER_08]: And so that, I underline it as I was reading it, say re-imagined gives you a lot of possibility.
[SPEAKER_08]: And if we as a community, when we're communicating or however we're putting it out there, we're using a certain term, whether it's re-imagined or something else that we can come up with.
[SPEAKER_08]: So we're all speaking.
[SPEAKER_08]: same language when we're talking about the process that we're in now?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, I think that's a great question.
[SPEAKER_06]: Our website is building MHS because building can mean like all of those things, but I think reimagine is the other word that I like to use when I'm talking to people because
[SPEAKER_06]: What it's going to be is not decided yet, right?
[SPEAKER_06]: And I think when people say, well, what's it going to look like?
[SPEAKER_06]: Are we going to do this or that?
[SPEAKER_06]: I typically say, we don't know that yet.
[SPEAKER_06]: But part of this process is really an imaginative process.
[SPEAKER_06]: Some of us got to see Arlington High School.
[SPEAKER_06]: And we went into a room, and it was called the discourse room.
[SPEAKER_06]: It was like a classroom, but it was a little bit more like a college classroom, but it was intended to be big enough for multiple classes to be in there at the same time.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that you could like, co teach a lesson and there could be like.
[SPEAKER_06]: A debate happening in the room was structured for that right and so that's it like an imagination like point, we don't have anything like that here today.
[SPEAKER_06]: But it's possible and not only is it possible it exists right and so really thinking about like.
[SPEAKER_06]: What is possible, I think, is hard to do when you are tied to a building and how it functions, right?
[SPEAKER_06]: You can say, I want the windows to open, or I want the lockers to be bigger or smaller.
[SPEAKER_06]: But to really think about what isn't here does take a lot of imagination.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I think reimagining is a good word for us to think about using.
[SPEAKER_06]: I don't know if others have thoughts about that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Tom?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I completely agree.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think reimagined has been a really attractive and salient message.
[SPEAKER_03]: When we're talking about this project, I also think that when we're engaging with folks in the community, and they're looking for more specificity, that's where we say, well, look, the two big buckets are rebuild or renovate, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: Those are the two kinds of MSBA projects.
[SPEAKER_03]: We're hoping to do one or the other.
[SPEAKER_03]: So there's still space to be more specific.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I do think that
[SPEAKER_03]: especially in this early stage, there's so much value in it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's an imaginative process, like you were saying, Jenny, it's really talking about what is here that we care about and want to preserve, and the things that we do like about the space, as much as we talk about the things that need to be remedied, there are things about this building that we like and that the community values, but then also thinking bigger about, you know,
[SPEAKER_03]: do we change programming?
[SPEAKER_03]: Do we expand certain programming?
[SPEAKER_03]: Do we move things around in a different way?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, those are all imaginative questions.
[SPEAKER_03]: So yeah, I would certainly be in favor of emphasizing that reimaginability.
[SPEAKER_04]: Luke?
[SPEAKER_04]: So there's also the bureaucratic aspect of the public space where we're like a bureaucrat.
[SPEAKER_04]: We're creating tools where
[SPEAKER_04]: is a big snowy, which is truly, I think, where creative juices get tapped, and have a professional design and planning team that's brought on board, that's put on retainer, given the job of locating that what's here, in terms of acreage
[SPEAKER_04]: And then what levels of replacement or renovation, and that's where the imagination really kicks in.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So I totally agree with it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Reimagining is a good catch-all for the general process, but there is a sort of bureaucratic aspect to it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, and I think what I tell people about eligibility is like, we've got to get through this in order to get on to answering the questions you really want to know about.
[SPEAKER_06]: And so we're going to move as quickly as we can through this eligibility phase so that we can start the real engagement and the imagination about what this could be.
[SPEAKER_06]: Other questions?
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you for that.
[SPEAKER_05]: One of the things that I worry about is the people who are like coming at us with stuff about the feasibility of reimagining they want to do now is, you know, when we get through that gate, we'll get through it.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, we will.
[SPEAKER_05]: We're getting through that gate.
[SPEAKER_05]: It isn't the time to then start engaging the community to start thinking about reimagining because like the race began.
[SPEAKER_05]: And catching all those people in their reimaginings and interests, even though we can't do anything with them right now, so that on day one of that process, they're all queued up, ready to be balled.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because, well, I mean, it is just a lot of paperwork right now.
[SPEAKER_05]: We don't, like, hook them and keep them, because frankly, none of them are probably interested in paperwork.
[SPEAKER_05]: on day one, you know, I mean, I know, like, when I run for office, like, for two full years, I had people contact me, and they support me, and then time to start my campaign up, and I'm like, who are all those people again?
[SPEAKER_05]: And I just don't want us to, I mean, I don't know if we create a shared document where we just add names of people who have interests, maybe a little note, how did you meet them, what was their interest, so that when we have a reason to meet them,
[SPEAKER_05]: We're not all just, like, digging through our memories of this long process of reading a bunch of books and documents.
[SPEAKER_05]: And I know that my own, like, intent to do that every day falls flat.
[SPEAKER_05]: So I think about that as a committee, something to formalize.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm too formal.
[SPEAKER_06]: We did talk about creating a mail list, essentially.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I think that's the place for capturing those folks, because we can create the list in such a way that you can tell us what you want to know about.
[SPEAKER_06]: And also, what else do you want us to keep in mind about you?
[SPEAKER_06]: And then we have that running list, and people can self-subscribe.
[SPEAKER_06]: Luke?
[SPEAKER_04]: So I mean, since you want to serve it, you would need to add a question.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if we were to talk about a survey, that's kind of part of our work here, but certainly identifying specific people and affirming that they want to come back with us and are still willing to share.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, I think that's a great suggestion.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I will, I've got that on my list to add.
[SPEAKER_06]: Other thoughts about the community engagement piece so far?
[SPEAKER_06]: Maria?
[SPEAKER_07]: Back to what Luke mentioned about sports teams.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_07]: My mind jumped to the PTOs because it's not only they're a powerful group, but it's a way to reach everyone who's in schools.
[SPEAKER_07]: but also the Catholic schools, the private schools, the local charter schools, because if we want to bring people back, they're the ones that have less of what we deserve.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: I will put that on the list.
[SPEAKER_12]: Just feel free to tap into the city side as well, because of course it's important for
[SPEAKER_12]: families to want to be involved, but I think we need to build excitement amongst the entire community.
[SPEAKER_12]: And I'm not going to help robocalls, newsletters, start building that excitement.
[SPEAKER_12]: So I need everybody's support, but hopefully we'll be there.
[SPEAKER_12]: OK, we can do that.
[SPEAKER_06]: Speaking of the city side of things, we also talked about how best to engage our boards and commissions, because there's a huge number of boards and commissions across the city, some of which have lots of obvious touch points with this school building committee, and others maybe not as obvious, but maybe there are some that we're not thinking about.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we will build a separate survey for them, for the boards and commissions, to say,
[SPEAKER_06]: Does your board or commission have an overlapping and or aligned interest in our SBC?
[SPEAKER_06]: If so, please describe at what phase in the process.
[SPEAKER_06]: Should we reach out to you?
[SPEAKER_06]: to your board and commission for that sort of integration, what's the best way to reach you, and do you have any questions for us?
[SPEAKER_06]: And then also offer to hold informal sessions for those boards and commissions.
[SPEAKER_06]: Like they may say, can you come speak at a board meeting?
[SPEAKER_06]: So we'll have this little roadshow presentation that we can bring with us, and somebody can go and speak to them and sort of bring back to the group what they talked about.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that's the idea of how to make sure we're casting sort of a wide net across our boards and commissions.
[SPEAKER_06]: I would also, in my mind, I know REC has a board now, but we would also be trying to tap into the folks at Medford REC because they obviously have sort of another vested interest in what's going on there.
[SPEAKER_04]: Luke?
[SPEAKER_04]: third-party candidates, because there are organizations that are possibly outside of our community.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right.
[SPEAKER_04]: That rent, the building, the fields, on a regular basis, on a regular basis.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And in terms of engagement there, is there already a concept for how to sort of see their thing there?
[SPEAKER_04]: that goes out to our community, or is there a certain issue?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, I think there might need to be some sort of slightly different survey for them, much like there's something different for the boards and commissions.
[SPEAKER_06]: So maybe we can talk about that in our next, we have another communications meeting coming up, but we can talk about that in our next meeting and just figure out how do we properly get them into the fold as well?
[SPEAKER_06]: Because I think you're right, this building is never quiet, ever.
[SPEAKER_06]: Right?
[SPEAKER_06]: So even when school's not happening, something's happening in this building more than likely.
[SPEAKER_06]: So just, you know, I think that is actually a really good point.
[SPEAKER_04]: Do you have a list of all those things?
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, I'm aware of some, but just an idea of who all the schools are.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, I'm sure we have a list.
[SPEAKER_06]: We'll have to work on whether it's an actual list or if it's
[SPEAKER_06]: a lot of things all over the place that we have to pull together, but yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Questions?
[SPEAKER_06]: Larry?
[SPEAKER_02]: This may be stupid, but get used to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I've all seen the cooking shows where they give the guys a grocery cart, and they have to use certain ingredients to make the best thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It seems to me what would be helpful early on, and I don't know that this has particular application to your specific comments today, but I would like to know what we have to work with in terms of sites in the city.
[SPEAKER_02]: I would like to know specifically, I have some questions about this building, having been in it now for 10 years.
[SPEAKER_02]: Peter and I have discussed it on a couple occasions.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think I gave a superintendent a paper maybe a year or so ago,
[SPEAKER_02]: But I think that idea you mentioned earlier of the tour might be good for this group as well.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, I think that's a great idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: And let's just be honest with the good, bad, and young.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, what do we have here, really?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I don't have most of the answers, but I think I have a few things that I'm certainly concerned about.
[SPEAKER_02]: One being subterranean groundwater in the fells, which is caused, I believe it's exacerbated a lot of the structural settling.
[SPEAKER_02]: So let's just kind of leave that there for now.
[SPEAKER_02]: But maybe it can be remediated.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I just think if everybody's kind of up to speed on what we have here, and there are some environmental, shall we say, things that we can stay in this building,
[SPEAKER_02]: But additionally, like the other pieces of property that could be available can, you know, be squeezable out of the bells, that we have a loop around and maybe integrate, particularly if we're going to have a lot more sports things here and somehow
[SPEAKER_02]: have access to the soccer fields below the synagogue down there.
[SPEAKER_02]: What about Playstead Park?
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, there's just, and then what about the whole thing of Hormel Stadium?
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, that's a big, nice piece of valuable property sitting there that doesn't get used very often.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that is worth a lot of money, a lot of money, because potentially it can help finance some other things we're doing elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think of the tax revenue perspective.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you had a bunch of people, say, in high-end condos, not that I'm suggesting, I'm just trying to, like, what are we dealing with here?
[SPEAKER_02]: What do we have to work with?
[SPEAKER_02]: What are our options?
[SPEAKER_02]: And thinking outside the box.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe this site, maybe not, maybe a couple sites.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, I want to know what ingredients we have to make the recipe.
[SPEAKER_06]: I like that.
[SPEAKER_06]: So two things.
[SPEAKER_06]: We have a meeting on 6-4.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I think having a tour of this building during that meeting makes a lot of sense.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I'll put that on our agenda.
[SPEAKER_06]: We do have a finance subcommittee meeting before that.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I think the finance subcommittee includes more of the city staff, like Bob and Fiona, et cetera.
[SPEAKER_06]: And so my goal for that meeting is for us to be talking about the sort of
[SPEAKER_06]: getting to a place where we understand better what kind of funding needs to be set aside for feasibility study and for what, so that we can be ready to work with the council to do that.
[SPEAKER_06]: But I think the other question we can put on their agenda is like, what are those possibilities across the city that this group needs to know about and start to be able to think about?
[SPEAKER_06]: I can do that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Luke?
[SPEAKER_04]: So with respect to the feasibility, is there
[SPEAKER_04]: formal RFP process or collect the bids so that we know what it costs.
[SPEAKER_04]: We'll only know if somebody's delivering the bids.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hopefully in the spring.
[SPEAKER_04]: Is there something else?
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, people are chomping at the bit for this project.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, so once we get through this, the first thing that we do is we put out an RFP to bring on our OPM.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that OPM has to be done by competitive bid.
[SPEAKER_06]: They're also chomping at the bit to be part of this.
[SPEAKER_06]: But what we have to do before we can even get there is demonstrate to MSBA that we have a pot of money set aside that is reasonable to cover
[SPEAKER_06]: what will be the feasibility study.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that includes the OPM and then ultimately the feasibility study.
[SPEAKER_06]: So the mayor will need to send something to the council that says this is how much money that we're going to set aside and this is where it's going to come from and then the council will need to take a vote.
[SPEAKER_06]: How we think that's going to happen is that that money will be moved into the newly created stabilization fund.
[SPEAKER_06]: So there'll be an earmark of like this is money for
[SPEAKER_06]: The feasibility study for MSBA and it will get moved into the stabilization fund.
[SPEAKER_06]: So it's there and it's ready for us when we are ready for it rather than waiting for free cash to come all the way back around sometime around now next year.
[SPEAKER_06]: That has to be in place before MSBA will move us on to the next step.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we're working through the mechanics of that and we've been in touch with the president of the council.
[SPEAKER_06]: So he knows it's coming.
[SPEAKER_06]: Um, but, yeah, we have some flexibility because there's not a vote required.
[SPEAKER_06]: There's not a city wide vote required to fund the feasibility study.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that will that will come from our free cash reserves.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that's been our plan.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, regards to feasibility studies, I've had some limited experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Most of them, of course, have been in free enterprise.
[SPEAKER_02]: So they have to do with, is this going to be profitable?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can we sell it?
[SPEAKER_02]: That makes a lot.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a big part of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a little different.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I'm not saying we shouldn't have a feasibility study.
[SPEAKER_02]: We really should.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I think we can do a lot of the initial homework ourselves.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nobody knows what's more feasible than the people in this room.
[SPEAKER_02]: And nobody knows, like I was saying about the ingredients, what's available to us.
[SPEAKER_02]: And let's get it as far as we can before we turn it over to them, because all they're going to do is ask us all the same questions we're asking each other.
[SPEAKER_06]: So MSBA requires
[SPEAKER_06]: a certain process and that process really is like you can't sort of jump the line through their steps so our goal needs to be to bring those feasibility folks on as quickly as possible and be ready to hand them something.
[SPEAKER_06]: I think that's a really important idea but more importantly like we need to get them on the bus as quickly as we can so that they can make progress because
[SPEAKER_06]: We could hand them a whole thing.
[SPEAKER_06]: They're still going to do it again because they have to.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's part of the prescription of the MSBA process is that there's no jumping the line, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or we can pre-think through things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I just feel like as a communications professional, like we're going all over the place a little bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think we're helping to find out what questions should maybe be on the website that people want to have answers to.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I would think just for like folks following along at home or just all of us trying to follow along to make sure, are we still on the communications?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are we just kind of like going a little bit here, there, just with general questions, which I totally get as far as.
[SPEAKER_01]: bring it back to the communications and community engagement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_06]: I think we probably veered off track a little bit, but that's okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: We're back.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then the other thing that we did talk a little bit about is that there is a question on the educational profile that does say like, what is your communication strategy during this time period?
[SPEAKER_06]: And so we have a couple of
[SPEAKER_06]: We have a couple of thoughts there about how we are going to answer this question.
[SPEAKER_06]: And we'll certainly make this outline of what we plan to do a little bit jazzier and more cohesive.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that will go in there, as well as describe some of the topics where we're expecting school committee engagement.
[SPEAKER_06]: So for example, at our next meeting, which is on the 20th,
[SPEAKER_06]: Mr. Fallon will be bringing forward a conversation about expansion of certain vocational programs that they'll be seeking support from the school committee, like sort of to green light those ideas.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's important for us to do and for us to take a vote on at school committee so that then it can be incorporated into our chapter 74 profile before it goes in.
[SPEAKER_06]: There's also a conversation tomorrow, is it tomorrow?
[SPEAKER_05]: No, it's Wednesday.
[SPEAKER_06]: Wednesday.
[SPEAKER_06]: So there's a special education subcommittee meeting of the school committee on Wednesday.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that group will be talking about the possible inclusion of the Curtis Tufts program to the campus through this project.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I think, you know,
[SPEAKER_06]: we are all feeling like the time that there's an opportunity to create increased educational opportunities for our students at Curtis Tufts by co-locating them here and they're in in a way that still like meets their needs because they do have a particular like a sort of a different set of needs than being in a gen ed setting so how do you sort of do both of those things is an important question
[SPEAKER_06]: And we've asked the special education subcommittee, which is chaired by Paul, to explore that with students and members of the staff and come back to the school committee with a recommendation.
[SPEAKER_06]: Because if that group sort of recommends that this is not a good idea, we should not pursue this, then we would not put it in our educational profile.
[SPEAKER_06]: But if they confirm that there is broad agreement, then we would make sure that that programming is in here as well.
[SPEAKER_06]: We actually have a Medford resident who runs Somerville's sort of similar program and he happened to be at our meeting last week when we put the need for that meeting to happen on the agenda and he had just a million amazing things to say about
[SPEAKER_06]: the benefits for students in the Somerville program, how the program has expanded, how this student participation in athletics has increased, and all the rest.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I think we're all thinking there will be like a pretty favorable outcome from that, but that is another place where we're asking the school committee to get engaged in something.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then the last thing is we'll have, I think it's next week,
[SPEAKER_06]: a meeting, a school committee meeting about our capital planning process, and that has to be sort of tightened up and in good order before we put in our maintenance documents.
[SPEAKER_06]: So all of those things are happening at the school committee, so we'll wrap all of that in as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: Luke?
[SPEAKER_09]: Sure, we can do that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Paul?
[SPEAKER_05]: The very stuff is not just part of the ISP.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it seems different because it's a separate program.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's got its own name and it's in a different location.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it's part of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So I think that's how we're going to dodge that.
[SPEAKER_05]: I hope it won't be a problem.
[SPEAKER_06]: And the program today is how many students, Lori?
[SPEAKER_12]: On the rules, 15.
15.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we're not talking about true consolidation that many communities go through.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: OK.
[SPEAKER_06]: Other questions about the communication and community engagement plan?
[SPEAKER_06]: Is there a motion to approve the communication and community engagement plan as amended by our discussion?
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, motion to approve by Mayor Lungo-Koehn, seconded by Emily.
[SPEAKER_06]: Let's see, Mayor?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Dr. Edouard-Vincent?
[SPEAKER_06]: Dr. Galusi?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Dr. Cushing?
[SPEAKER_06]: Marta?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Libby?
[SPEAKER_06]: Marissa?
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Maria, yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Brian, yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Tracy, yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Emily, yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Nicole, yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Aaron, yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Luke, yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Janet, yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: 15 in the affirmative, zero in the negative.
[SPEAKER_06]: The plan is approved.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, we're making good time at 7 o'clock.
[SPEAKER_06]: The last thing on the agenda was just to give you all a first draft look at 1 of our deliverables.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, as, you know, there's.
[SPEAKER_06]: There's 5 deliverables that we need to submit.
[SPEAKER_06]: The 1st, 1 is an agreement that has been submitted.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's complete.
[SPEAKER_06]: The 2nd, 1 is a list of all of your names that will be done before we meet next.
[SPEAKER_06]: The 3rd, 1 is the educational profile and that 1 really sets, like, sort of the vision for, like.
[SPEAKER_06]: What do we do in this building and how do we do it?
[SPEAKER_06]: Both today and how do we want to do it in the future?
[SPEAKER_06]: And then because we have such a big vocational program, item number four is this chapter 74 viability program document.
[SPEAKER_06]: Fifth one is the authorization to fund the feasibility study.
[SPEAKER_06]: The reason that we're sort of, I won't say we're out of order, but we're starting with vocational first because this document is the most complete.
[SPEAKER_06]: The vocational programs have
[SPEAKER_06]: sort of the luxury, I guess, in this process of having already customized things happening in each of their programs.
[SPEAKER_06]: So where on the comprehensive side, on the sort of traditional side of the high school, there's sort of big, broad questions about, like,
[SPEAKER_06]: how are we teaching and how might we do things differently, the vocational programs all have that customization sort of implicit in their programming.
[SPEAKER_06]: And a lot of it is driven by what chapter 74, which governs all of our vocational programs sort of requires.
[SPEAKER_06]: So what this document requires us to do is give them some information about our program.
[SPEAKER_06]: So on the second page, what you can see
[SPEAKER_06]: here is a list of programs that we have that are existing.
[SPEAKER_06]: You can also see that we have our current enrollment for 23-24 listed.
[SPEAKER_06]: So this is our current enrollment in the program for each program.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then a column for proposed capacity.
[SPEAKER_06]: So there are a handful of programs where we believe that after our school committee meeting next week, that we will be seeking some expansion
[SPEAKER_09]: of certain programs because there is wait there's a wait list that's for
[SPEAKER_11]: We are going to be talking about Monday.
[SPEAKER_11]: um and what the staffing commitment would be to um
And.
Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_11]: Oh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh.
I'm going to go ahead and open it up for questions.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm going to open it up for questions.
And I think that's what we're trying to do here.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_11]: But there's an area that I just want someone to educate me on.
[SPEAKER_08]: into their own space.
[SPEAKER_08]: We're not often.
[SPEAKER_08]: How does it?
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, if we are offering that offer, does that change the scope of this doctor didn't send before to lift it up or I think you're going to expand.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes, we have done it before, right?
[SPEAKER_06]: So we have had students from other schools tuition in to our program, but the demand here is that we don't have the space for that anymore.
[SPEAKER_06]: Can you talk a little bit about what is the right mix of accounting for that possibility?
[SPEAKER_06]: That's a question for this group to really think about.
[SPEAKER_06]: I mean, trying to build capacity for a revenue generating program is going to come at a cost, which isn't necessarily a bad thing, but it also, there's not super clear pipeline of like,
[SPEAKER_06]: could how many tuitions could count on in a year.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we don't know that we necessarily like really land anywhere but just to say that our first priority for this group has to be like our students and and half of that half of every class is deciding to go into a vocational program and I think that's in part because it's not
[SPEAKER_06]: the vocational programs are not what you think of as the vocational programs from when you went to school.
[SPEAKER_06]: They're quite different now.
[SPEAKER_08]: And there's just a tremendous number of them.
[SPEAKER_08]: All you know, I'm building a new building, and it's coming with all new bills and lists.
[SPEAKER_08]: And everybody is talking, can we rent it?
[SPEAKER_08]: Can we get into it?
[SPEAKER_08]: What can we do?
[SPEAKER_08]: And when I see this data that there was one time an opportunity for our district
[SPEAKER_08]: that has the latest model, whatever equipment, and Arlington people find out about it, can we come over and use that equipment?
[SPEAKER_08]: I just want us to think about, as we think about how big this department is going to be, this part of the building is going to be, that there is going to be that desire to keep one up.
[SPEAKER_06]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_06]: I knew you were going to have something to say.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, this goes way back, but
[SPEAKER_02]: When I first started teaching here, it was my understanding it would cost $56,000 a year for us to send a kid to Minuteman to have plumbing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So if we go down that road, it should be nice if there was some sort of standardized fee schedule.
[SPEAKER_13]: And then I think also, Chad, there is for the state.
[SPEAKER_13]: It's all done.
[SPEAKER_13]: Minuteman's sold $30,000 right now for the capital expense.
[SPEAKER_13]: I don't really know how the calculation works, but a sending count, sending a kid here for $10,0017, that's it.
[SPEAKER_13]: And we have 20 to 25 extra kids.
[SPEAKER_13]: I sure did bring kids in, and it was nice.
[SPEAKER_13]: Keep in mind as we're doing this work, there are 15,000 kids statewide who don't get into any CTE spot.
[SPEAKER_13]: So it's fun to think about if we were in a spot where we could bring in 10 students a year,
[SPEAKER_13]: They can't get into the Northeast.
[SPEAKER_13]: So yeah, I think that's something to think about.
[SPEAKER_13]: But to your question, Larry, yeah, it's all covered by the state.
[SPEAKER_13]: It's all calculated.
[SPEAKER_13]: I'm not really sure how, but... Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just a quick question.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_04]: This past weekend, I was talking to Mr. Christie about robots, and he indicated that there was a pretty substantial
[SPEAKER_13]: So we'll have to feed all of that back into this before it's done.
[SPEAKER_13]: Paul, the other thing about having space for kids to other communities, and I believe this happened with Everett, I don't know if this is for your time, but we have Everett students coming.
[SPEAKER_05]: And Everett is like, wow, we're sending, I don't know, 10 kids over to Medford.
[SPEAKER_05]: Maybe we should have our own program.
[SPEAKER_05]: They start their own program, and then suddenly we don't have those 10 kids all at once.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like this year, we no longer have them.
[SPEAKER_05]: So it's not a risk-free thing to build capacity for surrounding communities, especially if they have any capability to actually do it themselves.
[SPEAKER_05]: If they don't have a vocational school at all, obviously the risks are very different.
[SPEAKER_05]: But when they have something, or it's a program where the upfront costs are not exorbitant, just need a teacher, those I think of as more risky because they just, they would want to keep their money too.
[SPEAKER_05]: So yeah, there's no easy path, but like, I don't know if plumbing is one of the ones where there's easy places.
[SPEAKER_05]: There are opportunities, but they're not all risk-free.
[SPEAKER_04]: So there's also this cyber security, which I'm sure you're thinking about this, too.
[SPEAKER_04]: So one part of the IT systems, I think, might be bad for cyber.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's already on the closing trajectory.
[SPEAKER_04]: But is the internet a thing to surround us?
[SPEAKER_04]: There's got to be some ways to respond to these questions.
[SPEAKER_04]: So I would just say, I think the reply to Catherine Klosko,
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, you can do that.
[SPEAKER_06]: Questions, thoughts, things you're wondering about in terms of our vocational programs?
[SPEAKER_06]: One of the things that was sort of interesting is like this does
[SPEAKER_06]: there's a completely separate track that we would have to pursue with DESE to be approved to have these programs, which is sort of separate and apart from having the space to have the program, which is what MSBA is here to do.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that's sort of a different work stream that would have to sort of move alongside of us, but more on the administration side.
[SPEAKER_06]: But the other thing that if you look at section C, if you're adding new programs,
[SPEAKER_06]: It does ask a series of questions to make sure that what you're adding
[SPEAKER_06]: is in alignment with what your area requires.
[SPEAKER_06]: So if you were like, well, I have an agricultural program, and you look around the immediate area, and there's no call for that in the field, then MSBA and DEFI, because DEFI will review and approve this as well, will say, no.
[SPEAKER_06]: You can do that, but we're not going to pay for it, right?
[SPEAKER_06]: Chad did look at the regional blueprints in terms of like getting to this, cultivating this list of programs that we're going to potentially seek to expand because these are the ones that are supported by our regional blueprint.
[SPEAKER_06]: And so there's sort of a straighter line there in terms of what we might be able to offer.
[SPEAKER_06]: Other questions, thoughts, comments about this form.
[SPEAKER_06]: the easier of the two.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I thought we'd start here.
[SPEAKER_06]: If any of you have questions or thoughts as you're reading this, as you're thinking about it, can they send them to you, Chad?
[SPEAKER_06]: OK.
[SPEAKER_06]: So Chad will take your individual questions and comments.
[SPEAKER_06]: On Monday at the school committee, Chad will be presenting about this, about the potential expansion of the particular programs.
[SPEAKER_06]: And you all are welcome at the school committee meeting all the time.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm sure it would be another lively meeting.
[SPEAKER_06]: We'll try to schedule the agenda such that Chad doesn't have to be there all night.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we'll look at that.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then, you know, my ideally, the presentation will go well, and the school committee will.
[SPEAKER_06]: take a vote to approve support of Chad's plan that he's going to outline for us and then we can include that in this before you all see it again when we finalize.
[SPEAKER_06]: Peter?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is there a specific MSBA language for how a vote should be?
[SPEAKER_06]: No, it just says that they need to provide a copy of the meeting minutes which include the language and outcome of the vote.
[SPEAKER_06]: And it does say to be studied as part of the feasibility study for the proposed project.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I'll craft a motion that wraps all those buzzwords in.
[SPEAKER_06]: Other questions about this document?
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: Feel free to reach out to Chad if you have any other thoughts.
[SPEAKER_06]: Steve Allen at medford.k12.ma.us.
[SPEAKER_06]: Once you all have your email addresses, you'll be able to find him in the directory.
[SPEAKER_06]: Our next meetings.
[SPEAKER_06]: Our next full committee meeting is on June 4th here so we will plan a tour of Medford High.
[SPEAKER_06]: We will hopefully approve our chapter 74 form for submission and we'll do a first review of the educational profile and I will do my level best to make sure you have that a couple of days ahead of time so you don't have to speed read on the fly.
[SPEAKER_06]: So all of that to come for June 4th and then
[SPEAKER_06]: Our subcommittee, we have another communications and community engagement subcommittee.
[SPEAKER_06]: Now that we have the support of this group, we'll get working on some of the surveying and that kind of thing so that can get ready.
[SPEAKER_06]: Then also before our next full committee meeting is a finance subcommittee meeting.
[SPEAKER_06]: For those of you who weren't here the last time, if you are interested in being part of any of the subcommittees, you can just let me know and we'll add you to the list provided that there's not
[SPEAKER_06]: Too many people on the list.
[SPEAKER_06]: Folks are welcome to join any of those subcommittees.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, so far we have rules and onboarding, communications and community engagement and then finance.
[SPEAKER_06]: Any other questions?
[SPEAKER_06]: Or we make a motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_06]: Motion to adjourn by Dr. Edouard-Vincent.
[SPEAKER_03]: Second.
[SPEAKER_06]: Seconded by Aaron.
[SPEAKER_06]: OK, roll call.
[SPEAKER_06]: Mayor?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Dr. Edouard-Vincent?
[SPEAKER_06]: Dr. Galussi?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Dr. Cushing?
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Marta?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Libby?
[SPEAKER_06]: Marissa?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Maria?
[SPEAKER_06]: Brian?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Tracy?
[SPEAKER_06]: Emily?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Nicole?
[SPEAKER_06]: Aaron?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Luke?
[SPEAKER_06]: Jenny?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: 15 in the affirmative, 0 in the negative.
[SPEAKER_06]: The meeting is adjourned.
[SPEAKER_06]: Have a good night, everyone.