[SPEAKER_02]: What do you get when you put 12 high schoolers in a media technology class?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a Mustang report.
[SPEAKER_03]: What do you get when you mix eggs, bacon, and seniors?
[SPEAKER_03]: The senior breakfast.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's the most wonderful time of the year.
[SPEAKER_05]: Why does the track team always run in circles?
[SPEAKER_05]: Because the basketball team plays on rectangles.
I'm not going to take over right now.
Good.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you hear when Santa passes over Medford High?
[SPEAKER_02]: The AP Spanish class singing Cascabeles.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hey, Cascabeles, Cascabeles, ta-la-la-la-la.
[SPEAKER_05]: Que alegría todo el día, ta-la-la-la-la.
Hey, Cascabeles, Cascabeles, ta-la-la-la-la.
[SPEAKER_03]: What do you get when you mix the Boston Latin High School girls basketball team with the Medford High School girls basketball team?
[SPEAKER_03]: A win for Medford.
Who can do ten backflips, two back walkovers, and a somersault all at the same time?
The captain of the gymnastics team, Renee Stoudy.
[SPEAKER_01]: I showed him all the things that he didn't understand And then I let him go Now there's one in California who can curse my name Cause I found me a better lover in the
[SPEAKER_01]: One, two, three, they're gonna run back to me Cause I'm the best baby that they never gotta keep One, two, three, they're gonna run back to me They always wanna come, but they never wanna leave
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you love supporting your boys basketball team?
[SPEAKER_00]: And do you love the Boston Celtics?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, we've got the best of both worlds for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Come support the boys basketball team as they face off against Arlington Catholic Boys Basketball at 7 o'clock on January 24th at the Good Sports Invitational here at the TD Garden.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hope to see you there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Come support your Mustangs.
[SPEAKER_05]: We are Mustangs!
[SPEAKER_02]: One, two, three.