Hi, I'm Mrs. Miller.
I teach programming and web development.
I think the highlights of the shop include what the name implies.
We learn to program, we make apps, we make programs, we do web development, we create websites.
We are a creating kind of shop, but we're creating with code.
What interested me originally was really just web development, when I saw that, and how you can just really control what you want to do, like through your print and all these various things.
Now, I would say it's really just like the problem solving aspect of it.
I always like problem solving, puzzles, and really the creativity, which
many different fields of programming included.
For programming, we learned Python and Java.
Those are our two main programming languages, although we use C Sharp in Unity game development.
For web development, we learned HTML, CSS, and JavaScript.
My favorite aspect is definitely the teamwork.
All of us talk to each other, help each other out with our projects and our daily work.
I think probably the most interesting project recently has been creating the district website.
I would recommend this shop to other people because in this shop you have the best community out of any other voc class.
I can promise you that.
We have the best, most supportive teacher in the school.
After high school, I plan to work in this field in college and, you know, in the field of computer science.
Hopefully some type of coding for game development.
But yeah, definitely utilize the skills I find in this shop in high school and in college.
Here you can really do what you want when it comes to computers, like you can really pursue any field.
Our teacher will definitely help you excel in that field, whatever it may be.
This is the place to be.
We have a lot of fun, we try to create a great atmosphere, and I think it's a great shop.