[SPEAKER_17]: Greetings and welcome, Andrews Middle School Class of 2023.
[SPEAKER_17]: You are about to embark on a three-year adventure that will not only prepare you for high school, but will give you lots of opportunities to shine in and out of the classroom.
[SPEAKER_17]: I'm a proud alumni of AMS and a soon-to-be grad of Medford High School.
[SPEAKER_17]: As I head to the University of Rhode Island in the fall, I'll be taking with me many valuable academic, artistic, social lessons, and tools that I learned from AMS.
[SPEAKER_17]: enjoy your time at the Anders Middle School because it's truly a special place.
[SPEAKER_12]: Hi future AMSers.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's my pleasure to introduce to you some of our amazing faculty and staff that are going to be incredibly dedicated to you during your time here and you know we're all just so excited for you to come and join us in the AMS family.
[SPEAKER_12]: So welcome to the school.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hello to our incoming sixth graders and their families.
[SPEAKER_03]: My name is Miss Santos.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'll be one of your guidance counselors next year.
[SPEAKER_03]: At the AMS,
[SPEAKER_03]: All of our faculty and staff are dedicated to support and guide all of our AMS students.
[SPEAKER_03]: We're really looking forward to seeing you all in the fall.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hello, everybody.
[SPEAKER_02]: My name is Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Xu.
[SPEAKER_02]: I teach sixth grade math.
[SPEAKER_02]: I would like to share with you what makes Andrews Middle School a special place to learn and grow.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you come to Andrews Middle School next fall, you'll soon discover that it is a place where students find compassion, kindness, and caring from staff, teachers, and students.
[SPEAKER_02]: One piece of advice I would like to give to incoming sixth graders is that you should take advantage of talking to your teachers.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you have any questions on homework, classwork, quiz or test, talking to teachers after class or after school is a good way to get personal attention and to get help from your teachers.
[SPEAKER_02]: I look forward to meeting all of you and hope to see you soon.
[SPEAKER_02]: Bye.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hello incoming Andrews Middle School 6th graders and families.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hi, I'm Mr. Gallagher.
[SPEAKER_01]: Welcome to the Andrews Middle School.
[SPEAKER_01]: Today I just wanted to give you one tip on making the transition to middle school, and that is take your time, be patient, expect new things to happen, expect new people to do new things,
[SPEAKER_01]: in new ways, but know that it's still school, like it's always been.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a safe place for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a place for learning, a place for new experiences, and a place for growing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the main point, you growing, becoming more of who you are.
[SPEAKER_22]: Hi everyone, this is Mr. Michi.
[SPEAKER_22]: I'd like to welcome every sixth grader and their families and all new students to Andrews Middle School.
[SPEAKER_22]: I teach Italian and I give you my warmest and most cordial welcome in the Italian class.
[SPEAKER_22]: So, welcome.
[SPEAKER_22]: This is a song.
[SPEAKER_22]: It's called Felicità by Albano and Romina Power that means happiness.
[SPEAKER_22]: Felicità, è un bicchiere di vino Con un panino la felicità E lasciar camminare dentro al cassetto la felicità
[SPEAKER_22]: I don't like this at all
[SPEAKER_21]: Hey everybody, my name is Mr. Lam, I teach 6th grade at the Andrews, and one of the things that I think makes the Andrews such a special place to go to school is all the supports that we have as students and teachers.
[SPEAKER_21]: We've got a great custodial staff at the Andrews, we've got great cafeteria workers, an incredibly dedicated group of paraprofessionals, great librarians, guidance counselors, school psychologists, all sorts of folks that are here to make your 6th grade and your whole middle school experience great.
[SPEAKER_09]: Hola, I'm Ms.
[SPEAKER_09]: Kammerer.
[SPEAKER_09]: Kitchajian.
[SPEAKER_09]: And we are the Spanish teachers at the Andrews Middle School.
[SPEAKER_08]: Should know if you ever have any questions or you're confused about something in class, you can always ask either of us to stay after with you.
[SPEAKER_08]: We're both willing to stay after if you have any questions.
[SPEAKER_08]: If you need to review something you didn't understand something or you just need help with your homework or project.
[SPEAKER_08]: So don't be afraid to reach out and ask us after class.
[SPEAKER_08]: If you need some extra help.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm seniorita Cameron.
[SPEAKER_09]: I am so excited to meet you guys in the fall.
[SPEAKER_09]: We hope that you have a safe and healthy summer, and we're so excited for the new year.
[SPEAKER_26]: Adios!
[SPEAKER_26]: My name is Mrs. Baptiste, and I'm the band teacher at the middle school.
[SPEAKER_26]: Middle school is going to be a wonderful phase of your academic career, and I can't wait to see my future band students on week one.
[SPEAKER_26]: Until then, take care,
[SPEAKER_26]: stay well, and keep practicing those instruments.
[SPEAKER_23]: Bye!
[SPEAKER_23]: Hello future sixth graders of the Andrews Middle School grade six.
[SPEAKER_23]: My name is Mrs. Boost and I'm an ELA teacher on side 6B.
[SPEAKER_23]: I love the Andrews and I know that you're going to love it too.
[SPEAKER_23]: If I had to give you one piece of advice for the new year,
[SPEAKER_23]: is to come in with an open mind.
[SPEAKER_23]: We promise to take care of you and guide you.
[SPEAKER_23]: There's really nothing to be nervous about at all.
[SPEAKER_23]: Welcome to the Andrews, everybody.
[SPEAKER_23]: I can't wait to get to know each and every one of you.
[SPEAKER_23]: See you in the fall.
[SPEAKER_25]: Hello Andrews Middle School's incoming sixth graders.
[SPEAKER_25]: Just wanted to wish you all a wonderful virtual open house.
[SPEAKER_25]: You are coming into a really, really great atmosphere at the Andrews.
[SPEAKER_25]: Teachers work very hard for you.
[SPEAKER_25]: The kids work very hard for each other.
[SPEAKER_25]: We have a really awesome motto.
[SPEAKER_25]: It's called excellence through responsibility and respect.
[SPEAKER_25]: And we abide by that in all of our facets of our school.
[SPEAKER_25]: I hope you have a great rest of the school year and summer.
[SPEAKER_25]: Look forward to seeing you guys in the fall.
[SPEAKER_15]: AMS offers many after-school clubs and activities, including the CCSR, Builders Club, Drama Club, Boston Shakespeare Project, Art Club, GSA, Diversity Club, Dodgeball, Movie Club, Outing and Environmental Club, Yearbook Club, Soccer, and Basketball.
[SPEAKER_15]: There will be a club and activity fair in the fall that will give you the opportunity to explore and sign up for these great activities.
[SPEAKER_16]: Hello, I'm Sarah, president of the NJHS.
[SPEAKER_14]: And I'm Lindsay, vice president, and we are very excited to welcome you to the Andrews Middle School.
[SPEAKER_16]: We can't wait to tell you all about it, but first, here are some messages from the NJHS talking about what to expect and a little advice.
[SPEAKER_16]: Make sure you stay kind to all peers, teachers, and other school staff.
[SPEAKER_16]: Form good studying habits.
[SPEAKER_16]: Don't stress studying for a test or quiz.
[SPEAKER_18]: Be friendly to one another.
[SPEAKER_18]: We're all in this together.
[SPEAKER_18]: I hope you all have a great time here at the Andrews.
[SPEAKER_15]: Hey guys, it's really important that you do your homework, because homework helps you prepare for tests and quizzes.
[SPEAKER_18]: Make sure you're always going to class prepared with a pencil, necessary books, and materials.
[SPEAKER_13]: Don't hesitate to ask teachers for help.
[SPEAKER_13]: They're here to help you.
[SPEAKER_13]: Most teachers stay after school to help with classwork or homework to better understand the topics you're learning.
[SPEAKER_14]: Use your agenda and write down assignments.
[SPEAKER_14]: It will be your lifesaver.
[SPEAKER_18]: It is very important that you stand on top of all the chapters and pages that your teacher signs for a certain book so that you do not get confused or behind on any of the homework and assignments.
[SPEAKER_00]: Always listen to your teachers because they will provide helpful information that you don't want to miss.
[SPEAKER_17]: Keep your blockers, notes, and everything else organized.
[SPEAKER_19]: Don't be scared to make new friends and talk to new people.
[SPEAKER_19]: You shouldn't fall behind or reward your schoolwork if it is not good for you or your grades, and it will add up in the end.
[SPEAKER_18]: To all the incoming 6th graders, have fun in middle school.
[SPEAKER_18]: It goes by super fast.
[SPEAKER_20]: Hi, my name is Ms.
[SPEAKER_20]: Van Doyen.
[SPEAKER_20]: I am one of the CCSR advisors at the Andrews Middle School.
[SPEAKER_20]: I am also one of the physical education teachers, so I am looking forward to meeting you all next year.
[SPEAKER_20]: CCSR is a project-based group that focuses on giving back to the community, and we welcome anyone to come and join us.
[SPEAKER_20]: So I hope to see you guys join next year.
[SPEAKER_05]: I joined CCSR in fifth grade because it was on the list of clubs and I decided to try it out.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm still in CCSR to this day.
[SPEAKER_04]: I look forward to doing CCSR in the future because it is a place where I can do good things for others and great things for the community.
[SPEAKER_11]: Hi, I'm Sophia.
[SPEAKER_11]: For CCSR, my group did a fundraiser for an animal shelter called Skylands and basically we made it so that they could get some extra money for the proper food and shelter for their animals.
[SPEAKER_10]: I joined CCSR because you can do really fun projects in a great environment and help out your community at the same time.
[SPEAKER_27]: I joined CCSR because I want to be part of the community and have fun and donate money for good causes.
[SPEAKER_19]: Our project was to find ways to decorate the school to make it a happier and more cheerful place.
[SPEAKER_19]: We did this because we feel that kids who are happy will learn better and be able to feel excited about learning in different ways.
[SPEAKER_24]: Hi future Andrews students!
[SPEAKER_24]: My name is Mr. Zizzo and I am a 7th grade social studies teacher here at the Andrews.
[SPEAKER_24]: In the 7th grade in social studies you'll be learning about world cultures and
[SPEAKER_24]: You'll also have the opportunity to take part in a program that's called Global Scholars.
[SPEAKER_24]: In Global Scholars, you get to connect with students from all around the world through a digital classroom, Skype chats, and so much more.
[SPEAKER_24]: During this program, you'll have the opportunity to learn about environmental issues and ways to solve those issues.
[SPEAKER_24]: You'll also have the opportunity to create some wonderful digital projects and share them with those international classmates in the eClassroom.
[SPEAKER_24]: I am very much looking forward to meeting you all, and can't wait to see you soon when you join the Andrews community.
[SPEAKER_24]: Have a great day.
[SPEAKER_07]: Hey there, future AMSers.
[SPEAKER_07]: This is Miss Grant, your music teacher.
[SPEAKER_07]: And I'm really looking forward to meeting you all and singing the Andrews Middle School anthem, Hey You're OK.
[SPEAKER_06]: The differences between us can make each other stronger Unexpected friendships last much longer We can help each other shine much brighter If we band together, we'll reach much higher You won't ever learn anything new If you only talk to people who are just like you See you in the fall!