We have a emergency public meeting for the City of Medford Liquor License Commission today on October 1st, 2024, and the meeting will come to order. I don't believe we have an agenda. It's just the one issue that we're going to look at, and I don't think there'd be a
and need to review the notes from last month. We'll wait till the monthly meeting to do that, too. That's not a big deal. Sounds good. And it's just the Medford Public Library. Joey, is that what you're here for? Yep. All righty. Can you tell us a little bit about what's going on? I appreciate you meeting on this issue.
I'm the director of the Medford Public Library Foundation, and we're having an event, a private event at the library to celebrate the first chapter of the library with the founding donors who supported the building efforts to present to everybody about the reception of the library and celebrate some of the key milestones that have happened since the opening in 2021.
And it's going to be a two-hour event on Saturday, October 5th, from 6 to 8 p.m. There's going to be catered food from Baker's Best Catering based in Needham. They have a food permit in Needham that was transferred to Medford via City Hall. And we'll have bartending services from Premier Bartending, who is a company that Baker's Best works with to provide bartending services.
And I made a map so you could see, oh, I can't share my screen, but basically when people enter onto the second floor from the parking lot of the library, they'll come into what we call Brookline Bank Gallery and Cafe, which is where I'll meet them. And that'll be the opening reception room. And then people will be able to take a tour of the library by some of the trustees.
And then we'll move into Bonsignori Hall, which is just a hallway away from that gallery space. The bar will be set up in the cafe space, in like the back of the cafe as people enter. And then through the hallway to Bonsignori Hall, there will be a presentation by library leaders. And that's where the food will be set up.
Okay. You had mentioned October 5th. Is that the date of the planned event? That is the date of the planned event. Okay. Because on the application, I see it's 927, but obviously, that date's passed. Terry, you can just jot in 10-5-24.
And 1 of the question I had Joey was, you mentioned that. You're going to have. Baker's Baker's best as a caterer, and they bring in a, um.
a bar company, somebody who's going to handle the liquor. Are they a licensed caterer through the state? Yes, they are. From this point forward, if they're a licensed caterer, you don't need to get a one-day license with us.
Okay. If they've got a Section 15 license. Okay. I believe it's Section 15. Yeah. You're right. That's the secret. If they're a licensed cater, that's the whole secret. Section 15. Yeah. Because they register with the state, they're licensed by the state, they're licensed to transport, they do it all.
The only thing you need to do is when you hire them, it's actually their responsibility, but you need to just send Daria some information as to when the event is going to be. I don't have it in front of me, but I believe we have to notify this commission and the police department. Chief of police, that's right. Brian, I believe.
I see. Don't think you're going through this all the time. Because if you're going to use them, and they're licensed by the state, you don't need to come through us. OK. That's great to know. Sorry for wasting your time today. No, no, no. No, no. It's a teachable moment, as they say. Like I said, the whole thing is, as long as they're licensed, if they're a licensed caterer, then you don't. But usually, from talking with Barbara, you'll have Medford Brewery or Hillside Brewery. Right.
then you have the place in West Medford that would cater. I forget the name of that, the caterer in West Medford. But I guess what I'm driving at is the chairman is right. If it's piecemeal, then yes, you've got to come before us for a one-day license. But if it's a licensed caterer through the state or the Commonwealth, then you really don't. They'll take care of it. And the chairman's right. You just notify us of the event and the chief of police, and then you're good to go.
OK, so do I notify the chief of police or do you?
It should be the caterer, I believe. You can have your caterer just reach out to the chief of police and to Daria. And it has to be at least 48 hours in advance. So I mean, if you want to do it a week in advance, that's fine. At such and such a date, we're going to be having this event. And normally, I believe it is the caterer that reaches out to the city chief of police and the license commission.
But like Ellen had said to something else, if you do with Medford Brewery or any other type of event, just give yourself at least a 30-day leeway. This way here, we don't have to have emergency meetings and stuff. It can all be taken care of. We meet on the third Wednesday of every month.
you can schedule it that you'll be able to come in at one of our monthly meetings before your event and just make life easier that way. Okay. Thank you. I'm looking it up here on the state. Yeah, you have to notify the chief of police, the LLA, which is us, Local Licensing Authority. Decatur has got to provide their license to the police chief in to us and proof of insurance.
Got it. Okay. Proof of insurance and then the caterer's license to us and the police. Okay. Got it. Okay. Awesome. Anyways, since we went through all the motions and everything else, we may as well just grant the permit as well. Yeah. I don't think there'll be an issue, just something you'll have. You've got the insurance on file.
If you like, Alan, you want to make a motion or would you like? Yeah, no, I'll make the motion. I motion to approve the one day license for the Metford Public Library for the event to be held at the Metford Public Library on October 5th.
uh, for, uh, the hours of 7 to 10 I see in the application, um, for estimated, uh, guests of between 40 and 50, hopefully more come. I don't know. I know I RSVP'd early on, so, uh, so that's my motion. Okay. I, uh, I second the motion. All those in favor? Aye. Aye. All those opposed?
Hearing and seeing none, the ayes have it. The motion is passed. Joey, you're all set. All right. Thank you very much. All right, so I'll see you Saturday, Joey. Take care. See you Saturday, Alan. Take care. Bye-bye. Bye-bye. Oh, you're going to be an attendee, huh? Yeah. Yeah, Imri and I are one of the founding whatever they call it. Yeah.
Is that why they named the room after your bank? Well, that's separate. But Amory and I made it individual. We were involved in it individually also. Good. Good for you. All right. Well, that kind of went pretty easy. Too bad we didn't know it beforehand and we could have.
Yeah. But that's all right. I had nothing going on. I just had to get a haircut.
Daria, anything else going on? I mean, we just received those reports from the police to do with the Great American Beer Hall. To me, it's just a police matter. We'll stick them in their file, especially when Officer Smith said that there were no illegalities or anything that may affect the license. So I think we're good with that. Yeah, I think so.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, I read it too. You're right. Those two incidents, it doesn't come under our authority, I guess. But yeah, I agree, Mr. Chairman. Just put them in the file, and we'll deal with anything that does impact their license with us later on if anything ever occurs. Yeah, it looks like they're starting to progress, I believe.
Well, I didn't see it. I think my wife saw it as we were driving by the other night. There were people on the second floor patio. So if that's the case and they got their elevator inspected and they're full occupancy now, we just got to make sure that he comes to the meeting and just gives us an update. And we can okay the full occupancy and then he doesn't have to come anymore after that.
Did you happen to notice if he was there for the compliance meeting? I didn't see him. Brian was there. Brian was, yeah. Yeah. Yeah, I talked to him. Yeah. Okay. He came in right at the, I think, like, right when we started. Okay. What about the other gentleman, Mr. Greer? Was he there, the new, taking over the porch? I don't think so. I don't think so. I don't remember seeing him. Yeah, I don't either.
Yeah, well, just just kind of cute. We had a great turnout.
I think everybody was pleased with what went on. And I think it's, I know Ralph was saying something about next year, they're gonna be having more new stuff like violence in the workplace between the help and the customers and all of that stuff, along with some other things. I know Sophie Greenbaum was very impressed by it.
She asked if we could share some information so she could reach out to some of the other communities. I told her, yeah, no problem at all. I gave her Ralph's number. I said, talk to Ralph, tell him I had you give him a call and I'm sure he'll help you out. If you need anything as far as the letters and stuff that we sent out, we'll help you in that area where we can as well.
Bobby, I did get a little feedback from some of them, and I think you hit it on the head. If this is something that we plan to hold every year, it's got to be new, so they don't think they're getting here on the same stuff, because if they think they're just going to get the same information, then they may find ways to sidestep the actual meeting.
I'm encouraged that you're saying that Ralph understands that and he'll add some different parts to the presentation.
Yeah, yeah, I kind of brought it to his attention with the one with Tim Tamper or something that went on Boston Ave. Right. And he says, you know, this kind of a hardship, only two people running the place and this and that. And they were here last year. And I says, I could see with a small business like that, he can't close his business down to come to the meeting. I says, that's understandable. And we told him, don't worry about it. I says, but, you know, do you think we should be doing this every year? Or should we think about it every year?
And he says, yeah, he says every other year is good too. He says, I already got some new stuff for next year, but if you want to do it every two years, that's fine. So maybe we'll skip a year and go from there. See if we can get some bigger and better fish to fry.
Well, it's definitely worth the conversation so the three of us can kick that around. I picked up some information I didn't hear the last time, so I thought that was good. But yeah, let's kick it around and let's see whether it's something we need to do every year or every other year so it's a newer presentation rather than the same thing.
Yeah, yeah, he had a couple of new speakers too this year. The DOA was there, which was good. It kind of explained the minimum wage and all that stuff. And they, what was the other thing? I think one of his associates, or the lawyer, the lawyer there, he explained some stuff. The little question and answers, he had that pretty good. But yeah, I think overall it went really good.
Um, the other thing I just wanted to touch real quick on was, um, with the license renewals, um, Debbie, you think we should be sending out just kind of like a heads up email to all the licensees that, um, their licensory would, what it entails license renewals are going to start November 1st. Um, and just to kind of a easy reminder and then,
Maybe with that, we could remind them what they're going to need, the building department inspection, the fire department inspection, their insurance, and whatever else is required of them. I'm kind of hung up on this.
on this Carmen Vitula thing. It just bugs the crap out of me that the lady in the clerk's office showed me a folder this thick of people that have Carmen Vitula's license that never renewed them this past year. And it's just like, well, why are they still in business? Or how are they still selling food or whatever if they haven't renewed them?
That's out of our lane. What I think I'd like to do is possibly not this year, but next year have the common vigilance license submitted with the paperwork for us.
to process the new liquor license only because the city of Medford, you can't have liquor unless you have food. And you can't have food unless you get a common vigilance license. So if they produce that every year, even if it expires December 31st, they're producing it to us November 1st. So from November 1st to November 30, it's still valid. And that'll also give us,
Their hours of operation, and we can check it against what area has, um, and make sure that we've got the correct hours of operation on our license for that establishment. Um, and then, you know, I think for this year.
What we could do just to wake up the clerk's office just a little bit is I can go in and talk to them and say, you know, we're handling the license renewals a little different.
what we'd like from you is we'll send you a list of our licensees. And after the first of the year, when you renew January 1st, would you be able to check out this list and tell us who did not renew? And at that point, if we've got two or three that didn't renew, we can send them out a letter.
something with some legal talk, you were aware that you are unable to be selling alcoholic beverages unless you sell food. And in order to do so, you need to have a current common vigilance license. And then we can say, you know, there'll be a grace period until January 31st for you to give us a common, a,
a valid common vigilance license, if not, whatever. You know, you have to come in for a hearing or you gotta do whatever. I don't know, maybe we gotta figure out how we can word it that you don't have food, you don't sell booze, in a nice way. You know, I mean, it's basically, I mean, I guess they all have food, but I mean, if they don't have a common vigilance license, they're not being inspected by the Board of Health.
And are they serving food illegally? Is somebody going to get sick? You know, maybe they're not even served. I don't know. Everybody's input, I think.
You know, we should get all of our input on this and that's right. It's a plan for the next the next year or the next fiscal year. Yeah, exactly. But just kind of fire a warning shot across their bow. You know, I can go in and just casually talk to the woman that I spoke to a few months ago about it that showed me the stack and.
I'll ask her if it wouldn't be too much problem if we provided her with a list of our licensees just to check it off to make sure each one renewed their license and that'll kind of okay well since changing you know and I don't know shake them up a little.
Um, and like I say, it's out of our lane to go telling them they got to enforce whatever they're supposed to enforce. That's not us. We just work the license commission, right? Yeah. Go from there. Uh, other than that, I think we're good. Good. And, uh, uh, then I make a motion to adjourn. Absolutely. Derry everything with you.
Yeah. Okay. I'll second that motion. All in favor? Aye. Our emergency meeting has ended. It's nice seeing you. Thank you.