Meeting of the Medford School Committee will now come to order. The secretary will call the roll. Mrs. Grignano. Present. Mrs. DiBenedetto. Present. Mrs. Kratz. Here. Mrs. Mastone. Here. Mr. Skerry. Present. Mrs. Vanderbilt. Present. And her. Present. Seven present. None absent. All please rise and salute our flag.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America, and to the republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all. Prior to the commencement of the meeting, under the open meeting law, the chair must announce to all attendees in the audience that this meeting is being filmed, and I just want to make you aware of that. Thank you.
Approval of minutes of March 20, 2017. There's a motion on the floor for approval by Ms. Disceri, seconded by Ms. Kretz. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Motion carries. Approval of bills, transfer of funds. Motion for approval. Motion for approval by Ms. Disceri, seconded by Ms. Kretz. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Motion passes. Approval of payrolls. Motion for approval by Ms. Disceri, seconded by Ms. Van de Kloot. All those in favor?
All those opposed? Motion carries. Report of secretary. Report of committees. There's an item for community participation, I believe.
Good evening, Medford School Committee. My name is Joe Villione. I reside at 59 Garfield Avenue, Medford, Mass. And thank you for hearing the public. Again, education. Over at Somerville TV, we're now taping my TV show inside my radio show, so we have a TV program and a radio program. My goal for Medford, of course, is to expand access TV for all the residents so that we're not restricted to certain times
at the high school, and I believe, as Arlington has, we need to have a satellite station somewhere centrally located, as Mayor McGlynn's tribunal suggested, and I want to help the school. I want to help the mayor. I want to help the community in this endeavor because I started in Access in 1979, and I think it's unarguable I have more experience and more memberships in Access than possibly anyone in the entire city of Medford. I want to help my community.
So my question to the city school committee is, what is the hard date for opening? Is it the end of April? Because I was talking to Mr. Belson and Ms. Vander Kloot, and they informed me that it would probably be finished by the end of April. I want to know when we can implement this for the community, when we can bring in the educational component so that citizens can learn computers, be it Adobe Premiere or Final Cut Pro,
whatever, this is the amazing thing we've been missing. We've been missing it in Medford for the entirety of the time we've been paying for AXS TV because at the old station it was never properly taught. And now with the station being shut down from around July of 2014, I believe,
We've now had three years in limbo where our football games, our athletics, our political speech, everything has just been kind of in the dark. I want to help open the light, open the door, bring some transparency. So can anyone tell me?
what our next phase is. We do not have a set date when we will be doing our ribbon cutting. However, we do anticipate the contract to be completed at the end of April. However, as people are aware, there's generally a punch list that goes with those. So once we finish off the punch list, then we will determine a date. And can we expand it a little so that we have a satellite? That is not school committee purview. Thank you very much. Thank you. Report of superintendent. Report on SBIRT program.
Mr. Superintendent. Mayor and members of the school committee, uh, Tony Vento, our supervisor of health services is with us this evening for three different reports. This particular report is particularly significant since you may have seen some items in the newspaper today is latest today about opiate issues in Massachusetts. And, uh, Tony has prepared a report based on our initial screening on this pilot program. And I think it should be of strong interest to us with regard to how we're looking at, uh,
screening our young people. Ms. Venter, good evening. Good evening, Mayor, Superintendent, and school committee members. I think I'm one of your main attractions tonight. I'm up for three reports, so I hope you find them interesting. So the SBIRT screening, we know in January of 2016, the governor enacted a law, signed a law, requiring all grade 9 and grade 7 students to be screened.
The law stated that in the school year 2016 to 17, that all schools screen grade nine students and then the following school year at grade seven. The law is called an act relative to preventing adolescent substance abuse by expanding SBIRT. And SBIRT is a screening questionnaire. I've given you information in the past on that. It uses what is called the CRAFT tool.
It's a preventative model looking at identifying students early who are starting to think about or use risky behaviors. So this year was our maiden voyage. We sent out information, a letter home to all grade nine parents. Parents had the option to opt out of the screening. And out of all of our students, only five parents opted out. So we were very encouraged by that. We felt that was
hitting an informational need that parents had. We did the screening in January. It was a team effort between school nurses, guidance counselors, adjustment counselors, and school psychologists. And we screened 316 grade nine students in three days. So all the screenings were done in a confidential place. We used the gymnasium.
We had set up four different screening stations. It was a one-on-one session, and when every student left, he or she received an educational resource about if you're worried about yourself or another student, these are the people within the school that you can contact for help. I did provide a table that summarized the results.
And 316, as I said, were screened. 277 grade nine students exhibited no high-risk behaviors. So at that point, they received positive reinforcement. The screener would say, you know, I'm really proud that you have made healthy lifestyle choices, and we'd like to see you continue that through your high school years. If you need to talk to anybody, this is who you can come talk to.
39 screened had at least one positive response. Of those 39, the most common positive response was that they rode in a car with somebody who had been drinking or using drugs. Depending on, let's see, if you look at the CRAFT tool, there's a number of questions on part B. So depending on their score on part B, that score dictated the next step.
which for 32 of the students was a brief negotiated motivational interview where the screener explored, so tell me a little bit more about your answer on this question. And they would probe, looking for some information on a scale of zero to 10, where do you feel you land? And then did some exploration about likelihood to implement some healthy behaviors.
Seven of the 39 students by their score required a referral to an in-school counselor. And of those, seven too refused the referral. So overall, we felt that our first screening was very positive. We thought that the data we received out of it supported all the data from the Community That Cares survey, which has been showing the last few years a trend for lower
use of substances by our high school population and more reporting of positive protective factors. So I look at that and say, well, the efforts by the team Medford staff, the efforts by the Boys and Girls Club, the extracurricular activities within the high school are all doing their job as protective factors. Excellent. Very good. Ms. Van de Kloot, did you have a question on this? No, I didn't. Thank you, Toni.
Mr. Benedetto. Thank you. First of all, I want to say thank you to you and your staff for implementing this in such a quick way. 300 kids in three days is a lot to go through. I also think that opening the communication with children in this manner is very, very positive. So that way, if something were to come arise, you've already had that initial contact with somebody.
you might feel comfortable going to them, even for other issues that might come about. So I really think that the process is good for all our children. I'm glad so many participated. So out of the 32, my concern was, OK, do we notify parents? How do we do that? I know it's confidential, but especially those seven students that some red flags were drawn, at what point do we? It is confidential, and at the only point
where we would cross the threshold for notifying parents would be if the student demonstrated a potential for harm to themselves or others. So are we going back as confidential employees or nurses or guidance counselors
to check on those students in like a few months and just say, hey, how's everything going? Those students are students that are already, many of them are already followed by staff within the school. So we do have ongoing relationships that are being built and being fostered. And so that connection is there. So we feel that that breeds the follow up. OK, great. Especially for the two students that refuse
the referral. We just don't want anybody to fall through the cracks. And I'm sure that's not happening. So thank you again. And I think that conversation with seventh graders is appropriate. That will be next year. Yeah. So I also think that open that line of communications very early with children. They're mature. They're seeing stuff that we don't even know that they're seeing in middle school. So I think it's good to acknowledge it and talk about it. Thank you for your report. Motion to accept. Thank you.
Ms. Conyo. Thank you. The total screenings that came out was a total of 39. Seven students came forward for you to know who they were, correct? Mm-hmm. Okay. Then the 32, what do we do with them? If they don't come forward, how do we try to help them? Well, see, by virtue of the law, there is no mechanism to place any follow-up in a student's medical record or health record that we keep.
So the basis of the law was complete confidentiality. So no, those seven students, or those 39 students, I do not know who they are. Right, so what do we do to keep on reinforcing what we reinforce? Exactly, exactly. And you reinforce the positive protective factors. You make known who are your supports within the school. You keep building and working on relationships.
that type of disclosure is relationship-based. Right. And it's a very delicate line. I mean, as a parent, yes, you want to know. Right. But we're also trying to get the trust of the student. Exactly. And if you have the seven that have come forward, what we're hoping to do is have the loyalty and the confidentiality. So maybe those seven could hopefully give us, maybe, or have the other students
say, you know, listen, it's working. No one is really saying anything about us. We're going to counseling and we're helping. You know, if you want to go, the door is open. The students had very good feedback. My role during the screening was an escorter, so I made sure I escorted the students from the health and fitness class to the screening area and then back to class. So we knew that they got back into class.
a lot of them had very positive comments to say. That wasn't bad. I enjoyed talking to that person. I never met him before. It was really nice to meet him. So, you know, I heard a lot of nice feedback. And the referrals for the counseling, is it strictly whoever is in our school or is it even outside counseling? Well, if, again, that goes on tiered intervention.
The seven that we referred to an in-school counselor, that was the level that they met by their scores. Had we had students that had an elevated score, we would have referred them to the SAFE project, which is through the Institute of Health and Recovery. And we have a SAFE project counselor that is available to come to the school to do on-site counseling. All right, great. Thank you. And thank you for all the work. I mean, as my colleagues have said, three days to put this together is a lot of work.
Ms. Kratz. Hi. Hi, Ms. Pinto. Thank you for the report. I wanted to know, because I was at the DARE program at the elementary school last week, and it just got me thinking, after reading this report, I wanted to know if maybe with the cooperation with the team Medford, if we could do maybe a similar presentation, maybe in the Cameron Theater, for maybe the incoming freshmen,
in the outgoing seniors to educate them again at the high school level on drinking and driving. I know there's the seminar for driving distracted, but that covers texting, being distracted. I noticed in this report that the most frequently reported risky behavior was ridden in a car with someone who was drinking or using drugs. And I know with the new, how the marijuana is now legal,
I wasn't sure if maybe we needed to do like an upgraded training program to educate the students on, you know, the dangers of, you know, smoking marijuana, drinking and driving. So I, you know, I was just, I was really thinking about that and brainstorming and wanted to ask you about that. Well, all of those components are rolled into the Michigan model health curriculum that Rachel Perry has spoken about. In addition, we, we have actually today,
at our community-based justice meeting at the high school, we were talking with the district attorneys for setting up the pre-prom education seminars. So they come and they provide an assembly to students prior to the junior and senior prom. That reinforces, again, healthy decision making and shares the dangers of all of those things.
Okay. All right. Great. Thank you. Thank you. Ms. Van de Kloot. As I reflect on this, I think exactly what Kathy picked up was the thing that most concerns me, that 32 out of 39 kids reported that they had been in a car where they knew that someone had been drinking or using drugs. Just about two months, within the last two to three months, a young stonem teenager lost her life. And prior, I know many of the kids who were friends or in her class, and sadly,
Prior to that, and fortunately, there were other students in the car who had gotten out before she had her tragic accident. And I think that that's the piece here, we're talking about ninth graders, that we really need. By the junior and senior prom, it's really too late. That's the piece that we really need to target. Exactly. And well, I mean, I said that's, you know, the health and fitness classes are in grade nine and 10. So a lot of that material they're receiving early on in high school.
The Michigan model is going to be used district-wide, K through 12, so they'll be building on those components developmentally as they age in their classes. Thank you, Toni. Mr. Benedetto. Thank you. I remember Coach Perry talking about how different things that they did at certain grade levels, and I know that drinking and driving was part of the health curriculum at this grade level.
And I don't know if it's still the case, but when I was on the Method High School PTO, they used to bring in speakers for different classes and different grade levels. And one of them was yellow dress about dating violence and the other one was about alcohol awareness and driving and those type of things. So we could also check with the PTO and see if that is still happening. We do have, you know, we did receive the grant for the dating violence prevention.
And that has been an active, there's been active initiatives throughout the year that students are involved in. And the PTO used to do the yellow dress. Every other year they would alternate so that kids got different ones. So maybe, through you to the superintendent, maybe we should check with some of our PTOs and see what they're funding throughout the community.
like different programs that we would like to know, you know, because I know the PTO at Medford High, you know, they still do the prom dress shop that was started years ago, like I think we're on the 11th year now. And some of the things, but could we check with them? To see what the high school is offering with their PTO money, as well as our elementary schools, just to see what they're supplementing for us, so that way at budget time we know. Because I did actually get a phone call
this week about how PTOs are paying for a lot of buses for field trips and about them being able to negotiate pricing for those buses and all of those things. So I was going to actually talk to you about that too. But we should maybe invite the heads of PTO to one of our meetings and just talk about what they're doing for our school districts so that we're aware of it and how
We as a district appreciate the work that they're doing and the funds that they're raising, as well as are aware of those programming and let them know how vital we think they are and thank them for their time. So if you could add that to the agenda for maybe either the next meeting or the next, I'll give you time. Before the end of the school year, hopefully.
Thank you very much. Thank you, Ms. Vento. There's a motion on the floor to receive and place this paper on file by Mr. Skerry, seconded by Mr. Benedetto. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Motion passes. Ms. Mustone has made a motion for suspension of the rules to take a paper out of order. Motion for approval on suspension of the rules. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Suspension is granted. It's old business. It's the report on safe routes to school program.
We are really, really proud to announce that the Brooks School has received a $920,000 grant for Safe Routes to School. They have been working on this project for the last, I think, four years, if I'm correct. And they've worked very, very hard to demonstrate the activity in the school, the need to get kids walking, the safety
routes to get to school as well. So they've been really, really busy working on this and we were so very proud to receive the letter from the Commonwealth of Mass, Department of Transportation, that we have been awarded this. I know we have some parents in the audience that worked very, very hard that we would like to come up and say a few words about this and then we can say thank you for all of your efforts. So Liz, would you like to come up? Liz and your daughter?
Your name and address, please, for our record. Elizabeth White, 280 High Street, and Anna. Yeah, we're very excited to receive this news. I also want to thank Sara McGivern, who has been instrumental in this effort as well. She's been great supporting the Safe Routes to School program at the Brooks and I know other schools as well.
If I could, Sarar is the Director of Mass in Motion for the City of Medford, so she gets involved with a lot of walking issues, healthy eating issues. She does a lot of different things in the community, so we're very, very happy for all of her efforts as well. Yes, yeah, so this is, you know, a long time coming, but we're excited about the changes that will be happening and we're hopeful that the other schools as well will
be able to get involved. And I know some of the schools are already active with Safe Routes to School. Sarah has an update. Hi, Sarah McGivern, Mass in Motion Coordinator in the Board of Health.
I've just prepared a little bit of information about what teachers are doing as far as they are participating in Safe Routes to School activities. I know we presented to you about two winters ago just about the Safe Routes to School program and how we're encouraging students to walk and ride more. The Department of Public Health considers this a community level strategy that
affects people's health because oftentimes it involves the entire family, not just the student. Parents and siblings are ending up walking or riding the bikes with the students. It also helps improve our air quality and traffic around the schools as well. So that is why in my position that I'm funded by the state, I'm supposed to be working on this and helping the schools with the Safer School Program. But the other important thing to mention that I know
Superintendent Belson is really excited about too is that when the schools participate in the Safer School activities they're eligible to apply for this funding which is why Liz applied for funding in 2013 and the improvements will be made in 2020 but we really hope that the other schools all the schools in Medford are going to be participating in the Safer School activities soon so that we can apply and get
these infrastructure improvements made around all the schools in our community. So, as you can see from that paper that I passed out, some of the schools are participating, some of them are not as active yet, but they will be soon. I met with Principal DeLeva on Friday and we're going to be doing some trainings, bike and pedestrian safety trainings at his school soon.
So, if you have any questions, I can give you more information. So, Sarah will be reaching out to all of the schools to get them on board, to get them really motivated to take on this task. And you did apply in 14, and we were just notified now. And when the state came out, they did a full assessment of the area of the Brooks School, and literally from Placeton Road, down Placeton, all the way up to the Winthrop Street Rotary. So they looked at a wide expanse of where all the kids are coming from.
And the report is amazing, the detailed work that they put together. But they will be expanding. We're doing the Complete Streets project right at Alston and High, right at the corner of the Brooks. And they're going to be expanding it up to Woburn Street and further down into the square. So they're taking on some of the things that we're not able to do right now. But $920,000 is a fabulous grant. So thank you so much, Liz and your team. Great job.
Maybe you can steal Liz and take her to some of your schools and she can show what she did. I also want to thank Principal Andrews. He was fantastic.
when I, you know, when we worked on this grant and also just supporting the walking program at the Brooks, he was really on board with that. So he was great in getting it started and now Principal Galussi will take it over and get it to completion. Great job. Thank you for coming in. Thank you very much. Do you have any questions? Ms. Van de Kloot. I just think that it's important that we note that the different sorts of things that the money is being spent on, including
five foot wide concrete sidewalk and granite curbs, including ramps, pavement mill and overlay, signs and striping, landscaping, drainage, utility improvements, school zone, flasher, traffic control. And these are the sorts of needed improvements that will make our city safer for walking. So this is really fantastic, and thank you so much. Very good. Mayor Burke. Mr. Benedetto.
Through you to the superintendent, I was reading through this report and participation and goals and needs for each of the schools. Some of the schools don't have someone, a parent that stepped up, but we still see needs at all of our schools for this project. So we need to maybe work with our principals about making this a priority at every school. Also, it says near the Robert schools, they've been very excited about this for a few years. I know that their
walking school bus, was always a favorite of now Councilor Falco, because he used to go with his family and talk to me about it a lot. But I noticed that there is still some question about the crossing guard. Is there any updates on that at all on the Felsway? Well, we don't have anything new. We certainly talked to DCR, but there's no new commitment from them at this point in time.
DCR is not expanding their traffic guards. It's definitive. And through you to the mayor, is there a need for more police officers or someone there in the morning? We'll be reviewing that for the upcoming budget to see if there is room in any of the city-side budget or school-side budget.
Thank you. That's all we can ask for. That's on the school side. That is on the city budget. Yes. Okay. Thank you. And Sarah's going to be going out to the other schools too, to try and motivate them a little bit more. Thank you. Thank you very much. On the motion to Ms. Cuno. Um, actually to Sarah, um, the question was, first of all, congratulations to the Brooks school for all your hard work. Um, that's incredible. It really is. That's what you really should be proud of yourselves. That's a wonderful thing to achieve.
My question is that you were saying that the other schools, would they be able to also apply for this type of funding? And since the Brooks did do it in 2014, you said, 2014, which took three years, do you know if the deadline and the waiting period is the same? So the Columbus also applied in the same year, and they only grant the funding to one school per community per year. So they're eligible to apply again.
Um, there is a new application process that I've inquired about from the state and I'm waiting for them to get back to me. Um, we're hoping that we haven't missed the deadline for next year, but I mean, I think it's rolling. It's, it's always going. So as soon as we find out about it, we're going to try to, um, get the Roberts to apply for the next one. Um, and then we'll go from there. Um, by that time, after, you know, the Roberts does the next one, then whenever the next one is, the Andrews will have been participating long enough that we think there'll be eligible.
I think they'll be a really good candidate for obvious reasons. There's three schools right there. Right. No, that's great. That way, too, they have an idea. As my colleague said, there are some schools that have not participated and do not have anybody. So at least it gives them plenty of time to try to recruit and try to get some more information from you and to try to find out what the process is. I think it's a great idea, and it's a great way of getting some more money for all of us.
I just want to thank you for the report and it was very detailed and a great job to is in to surround. Thank you very much. I just want to mention the point of information for Aaron. So the crossing light at the corner of the Fulton Street in Bell's way. The timing crossing was adjusted in that was done, you know, a while ago. Yeah. Yeah. So that that was the only update. Yeah.
But so that's working and I've crossed myself and it gives you plenty of time to get all the way across. Yeah. Yep, yep. Yeah, no problem. Okay. Very good. There's a motion on the floor to receive and place on file. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Motion passes. Motion to revert to the regular order of business. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed?
We are now back in business. Item two, report on automated external defibrillators. I'm sorry, Ms. Van de Kloot? I was trying to think that perhaps it would have been nice to have our principals of the middle schools come forward so that we could approve their
field trips rather than keeping them to the end of the meeting. There's a motion for suspension of the rules offered by Ms. Vander Kloot. All those in favor? All those opposed? Suspension is granted. We are on item one. We have an addenda to the school committee. Recommendation to approve middle school New York trips. Please see attached report. There's a motion for approval by Ms. Discari. Is there a second by Ms. Vander Kloot?
All those, motion? I did have a question. You have a question? Ms. Vanden Heuvel. Yes. I think that the Andrews told us the cost of the trip, but I didn't see it in the McGlynn report. It's costing $320 per student. OK. And yours, the students go just overnight? One overnight this year, yes. And for the Andrews, it's two? Two overnight. So what time do they leave in the morning? Very early, so about 5 AM on that Friday. OK. And then they return?
about 7 p.m. on Saturday evening. Okay. It's just an interesting difference. Yes. We thought we really needed to make some adjustments to make it affordable for our students, and we were able to get a lot more students to participate in doing so. And they really are not losing anything on the itinerary. In fact, they gained a Broadway show, so they're very excited about that. The only thing that was cut was on Sundays, the only thing we did was go to the Bronx Zoo. So that was cut, and they had some other things they're doing on Saturday.
Okay. Anyway, I think it'll be interesting when you compare notes after the trips to see how it worked out. And how many students do you have participating? As of right now, I have 100. Okay. And you have? About 49. 49. Okay. It doesn't make sense to combine them.
I mean, obviously not this year. So this year, well, let me, our dates are different as well. I know. Ours happened to be because the director of the musical had asked for an extra week due to doing two shows for the high school and then moving to the Andrews. So, you know, over the summer we planned it and went through everything and it seemed like that was a better way to go with the later date. Right. I'm not meaning this year at all. I'm just, and I think that there were pros and cons, but I,
The question needs to be asked. We've done it in the past. That's what I thought. We have done it in the past. I think what happens is every year there's a different shift of interest. Sometimes the McGlynn is higher than the Andrews, and we always have to figure out the logistics of everything and making sure that it all works. But we're never opposed to doing it around the same time and integrating the groups.
Again, more logistically, and Mr. Edwards can also chime in as well. There are certain things that we go to. It's hard to have bigger groups in some things. So what would happen was if we were at a certain area, the McGlynn wasn't too far behind us, or we weren't too far behind them in a different time frame. OK. Anyway, great. Thanks very much. You're welcome. Very good. Mr. Skerry.
I'll throw you to the principals. I believe this is the eighth or ninth year that this trip has taken place. I've moved that it be granted and I know you guys do a great job and I know the kids get a lot out of it. And given the nature of current affairs, I believe
Perhaps, have you worked anything out with the travel agency for contingencies if the trip has to be canceled? Make sure that the trip does take place. We both use the same company. We've been using them for years. Very amenable for things that occur. And I think what your point being is, compared to nine years ago, this wasn't as much of a.
issue as what we're seeing nowadays. So they've been a minimal of, you know, we don't have anything officially in writing, but through phone conversations, they've been, I just want to make sure that the kids get a chance to do what they want to do. Go on the field trip, get to see a Broadway play. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Um, Mr. Edwards, how many students have you had in the past go?
It varies every year. It varies. It certainly has tapered off over the last few years. And that's really due to demographics in our school. So last year you had less than 49 students go? We had one full bus. It was probably comparable to that. I'm not sure what the exact number was. OK. Because I know over the years that we've tried to say, I know over the years it's been together. And we kind of thought that was working. So that way the students felt that
It was like one field trip for everybody. Do we have any students that want to do like a one-nighter in your school that want to go in the McGlynn School? We haven't presented it like that, so I would feel that we had parent meetings and sort of laid out what our itinerary was. And I just wouldn't feel right.
kind of doing that shift this year. But if it's something that we have to do. And it wouldn't be right for the student either. I'm just asking if anybody's asked. Yeah. And Mr. Edwards, you said you're leaving at 5 o'clock in the morning. What time do you get back? It's in the evening, 7 o'clock I think approximately. OK. So you're saying that the only thing that the students will miss out on is the show? The Bronx. Well, they added a show. You added the show? Yes. In place of the Bronx too, I guess. Correct.
All right, I was just curious. Yeah, they're still going to the 9-11 Memorial, Museum of Natural Heritage, out into the water to see Ellis Island, the Statue of Liberty, Rockefeller Center, Times Square. OK. We don't have your itinerary. So if you could provide that for us with the time. And do you also have the same amount of chaperones? We have six chaperones for 49 students.
And 49 students? Correct. And I was just reading. And yourself? I'm not going this year, no. OK, so it's just the six chaperones and the students? Yes, they're all eighth grade teachers that are going, which is really nice for the students. OK. Thank you. You're welcome. Miss Mustone. My eighth grade acquaintance is very excited to be going with the Andrews.
She would not want me to chaperone. So if you need an extra chaperone with the McGlynn, I'll go with you. So have a great time, both of you. I know all the kids at both schools are so excited. Very good. Mr. Benedetto. Do any of the children need medical services that are going on the trip? And how are we handling that? Maybe through you to the superintendent.
This is a careful procedure that starts in October as we start to really get to know our students and identify any students going on any field trips, especially on this field trip. This year, we do not have any medical concerns for the students going. In years past, we have, and we've handled that in a variety of ways. Last year, we had the parents of a diabetic student accompany us.
and be readily available in case the student needed any assistance. Thankfully, she did not and she had a wonderful time. And to reiterate, I have the same scenario this year where I don't have the same medical needs as I've had in the past where we have had parents come.
as well to serve the need that's there. Knowing that, I know this is a discussion that we've had this year greatly, but I think it's something that we're working on to improve through the years. I just want to make sure that everybody has a reasonable chance to go. That's our number one, you know, we would never deny anybody because of some medical reason or even some financial hardship we've been able to.
cover that as well. Right. And we just want to prepare for that in case it were to arise, because it would be the school's responsibility to make sure that we provide appropriate health services for any student that chooses to go on one of these trips. So I just want to keep that in mind when you're planning, and I applaud you for both doing that. As with every field trip, the school nurses screen the lists of students that have signed up for the field trips or that are eligible to go.
This year, as both the principals said, we didn't have any students with needs that required a nurse to accompany them. Parents were offered a chance to go and they all willingly wanted to go. Should they had said no, we would have looked at alternative arrangements.
Thank you very much. And I am EpiPen certified. Defibrillator. There's a motion on the floor for approval by Mr. Skerry, seconded by Ms. Van de Kloot. Roll call vote, please. Mrs. Cunha? Yes. Mrs. DiBenedetto? Yes. Mrs. Price? Yes. Mrs. Costello? Yes. Mr. Skerry? Yes. Mrs. Van de Kloot? Yes. Senator Burke? Yes. 7 in the affirmative, 0 in the negative. The motion passes. Have fun.
Now, motion to revert to the regular order of business. All those in favor? All those opposed? Item two, report on automated external defibrillators. Ms. Vento, I think you already did your intro. No, just a quick thing on this one. Remember, this is a report you asked for. This is a follow-up report of a report that we previously gave you on the AED. So with specific names and
specific discussions of where they're located. So it's a follow-up report to a previous report, but Tony is here to give you more detail. Thank you. So this also follows up another mandate by Governor Baker that was just signed in January called an act requiring automatic external defibrillators in schools, and it's effective of July 2018.
Now we're very fortunate in Medford, this has been a recommendation for many years, and we have met that recommendation for many years. All of our school buildings do have defibrillators in them. Some of the schools, depending on the size of the school, have multiple defibrillators. And the locations are itemized out in the report.
Our AED units are compatible with the equipment that's on Armstrong ambulances. So that if we had to use a defibrillator, we know that we can easily turn responsibility over to the Armstrong ambulance without changing any other equipment. So we're fortunate with that. Every school has staff that are certified.
And I did provide lists. Now those lists change with all of the nurses, the athletic trainer, the coaches, the health and phys ed teachers are required to be certified. Teachers are not. So there's fluidity in the teaching staff who maintain their certifications. But during the school day, we have somebody on site that is properly certified and trained.
And, um, we, we have our unit serviced twice a year through, um, a maintenance contract with life support systems, um, in Dedham. And we're fortunate, um, also that our training has been provided, um, by generous support from, um, the people at Armstrong Ambulance. So superintendent Belson had asked for a demonstration of how, um, the unit would work. And, um, we have, I have Sean Mangan here from.
Armstrong ambulance with a trainer, so we don't have to use it on anybody. But we will show you how. The unit is set, it's a smart unit, so they're set up to give you auditory prompts through the process. Hello, Mr. Mangan. Thank you so much for being here tonight.
So basically this is the Zoll AED Plus. Most of the machines that are in the city are Zoll products. They're brought through life support systems. The machine is pretty simple to operate. It's the same machine that's here at City Hall downstairs. Open the machine up. Any AED that you use or potentially need to use, the first thing you should do is turn the machine on.
All right, that's basically how American Heart Association teaches you, open the machine, turn it on. When you turn on this machine, it'll start to prompt you into what to do next. So if you're not sure what to do, the machine will guide you. So there's a couple of things that ultimately save people's lives. It's early defibrillation and high quality chest compressions or high quality CPR. If both of those things are done in a very short amount of time after we recognize somebody needs those,
The outcomes are typically much better as they get CPR much sooner We used to think a long time ago back in high school when I took CPR that you know Your brain starts to lose after seven or ten minutes of not having oxygen. So we breathe we breathe we breathe into people If their heart stops, we need to circulate the blood. Okay, the blood has plenty of oxygen in it for that period of time So we need to move it around. So those those chest compressions alone will circulate and
perfuse the brain, perfuse the heart, perfuse the major organs until we can get a machine there quick enough to defibrillate somebody. Okay. So I'm going to put the, I'll turn the machine on for you. This is a trainer. The pads are pretty simple to use. There's pictures on the pads. As you can see, take the pads out of the machine and lay them right on the patient's chest and turn the machine on.
Stay calm. Check responsiveness. Call for help. Attach defib pads to patient's spare chest. So once you place the defib pads on the patient's spare chest, the machine will recognize that. Attach defib pads to patients. Don't touch patient. Analyze. So now the machine is going to analyze for up to about 10 to 15 seconds. It's going to analyze the hotbed itself.
So pretty simple to use. We clear the patient, make sure nobody else is touching the patient. So that machine gives you a metronome as to a beat to give when you're actually providing chest compressions throughout that. Every two minutes this machine will go into a reanalyzation process automatically.
What that does is tells us to change out the compressor, because the compressor or whoever's doing the CPR is going to get tired. So that's kind of where we change that position of that person. And every two minutes, the machine will cycle that. So it's either going to deliver a shock, it's going to say the shock is advised, or it's going to say no shock advised. After either one of those, whether we deliver a shock or there's no shock advised, we want to start chest compressions again right away. Okay. So basically it says, check your patient, check for responsiveness. That's a quick, are you okay? Are you all right?
If someone's not breathing normally or responding to just from that or only gasping, that could be a sign of a cardiac arrhythmia that could potentially cause death. So we want to stop compressions right away. That's what AHA recommends.
If we start compressions right away and someone says, please stop pushing on my chest, we would stop. Other than that, we would continue to go. So it kind of gives you, you don't have to worry about hurting anybody or anything like that. We want to stop pushing on that chest right away to get that blood circulating and perfusing those major organs right away.
So do you want to do your song that you taught us at City Hall? Oh yeah, so the song beat is what this one has. We were all trained by Armstrong on how to use this, but there's a time lapse between getting the defibrillator and actually the person that's in the room with them. Yes, so the song that AHA used to use is called Stayin' Alive. So if you sing Stayin' Alive in your head and you keep the beat to stayin' alive and you do good high quality chest compressions and you get early defibrillation, you have great outcomes in patient survival.
So, uh, amongst us just speaking with Tony and speaking with Diane Caldwell, we've, we've also, we have two CPR classes planned. I've also been in touch with Jean Camuso from your office. So we're going to be doing some at city hall. I'm looking at the AEDs from the school and through the service zone plan, what's kind of spaced out throughout the city. There's almost about 50 AEDs in the city.
So, as a community, it's pretty impressive. They're in a lot of locations. We'd like to get them in a few more locations in the parks and stuff with some weatherproof casing. Baseball fields have them as well. So, they are out there and they are available to people.
I want to thank Armstrong Ambulance for also assisting us on any call that we make to them. They're there to help us out. So thank you. Ms. Van de Kloot. Yes, I just had one question. We have the list of where they are in the school system. I'm just sort of curious. Is there one in this? Yep. Right in the front lobby. OK. Just in case, because sometimes passions get pretty heated here. Sure, there is one in the front lobby. I think the library has one. All the schools have one. There's one in the training center at the police academy.
And all the little league fields have them right now. They'd like to get a couple more too, so. Thank you. You're welcome. Thank you both. I want a little bit more on this, because as I said, we are in good shape, but the new law is going to require us to purchase additional units. And that will be to meet the requirements for the presence of an AED during athletic events that are off campus.
So right now, our athletic events, when they're on campus at the high school, we have AEDs available, the trainer is on site, and so we can get an AED to the field very quickly. The new law requires that if a school sponsored athletic event is held at a site other than a school facility, the school officials shall ensure that an AED and an AED provider is on site.
So I spoke with Rachel Perry and Bobby Maloney about what does that mean to us. And for winter sports that are held at the high school, we are meeting requirements, we're fine. It's the fall and spring sports that tend to disperse out amongst the city playing fields. So Playstead, Memorial Park, let's see where else, Columbus Park, places that there is not an AED.
the need to purchase 16 AEDs that the coaches would be able to sign out at the beginning of their season, keep with their first aid bag, and then sign it back into the athletic department at the end of the season. That way, the unit goes with them to every practice and to every game, and it is on site. With purchasing those units, we would also have to purchase
the servicing program that maintains the twice yearly servicing and keeps the software up to date and replaces parts and pads as they're used. Mr. Benedetto. Thank you. Thank you for your report and thank you very much for the demonstration. I hadn't seen that so I found it very interesting and your time to come out tonight.
I think we need to purchase these immediately if our spring sports are underway and our coaches, like say our track team is doing long distance track or something like that. Those coaches should have them with them and God forbid something happened while we're putting this in the budget for next year. So through you, Mayor Burke, to the superintendent, is there any way that we could find a way to get
what we need for our students for this spring season to make sure that they're safe. And training. It would require training. Well, all the coaches are trained. They're trained in this mission, the AED. Yes. It's required of all the athletic coaches. So, Tony, maybe you could explain the different sites that we think, you know, technically, I mean, a coach and a trainer could bring a unit with them to every field and every activity. They don't have to necessarily
Because you see how portable they are. And they don't have to keep it in the car. No, no, they would bring it in their first. They could bring it with them. Right. I think what we're proposing going forward is that we have them actually on site at these places. So in case something happens and someone is not there with it. But since we have trainers and coaches going to every game, I'm not sure we're in a critical stage yet. But in the future, obviously we want to be in a situation where these things are automatically there.
The downside to that is they have to be checked fairly frequently to make sure the battery's loaded. And that means people have to go to these places early to check them in advance. There's a lot of logistical work that's associated with that. So we are working on that as to getting that going forward. Mayor Burke, I'd like to make a motion to have all of our coaches have these defibrillators with them as of this spring season.
So that way they're portable and our children are always provided safe care. There's a motion on the floor. Is there a second? Did you wish to speak on this? First of all, I just want to know, I mean, as far as the coaches having one, at what point do they have to be recharged? Is it like, does the battery go out if you don't use it, or how does that work? The batteries have a long shelf life, so for instance,
The nurses check their machines daily to make sure that that battery is charged. I can't remember purchasing batteries, I mean, through a school year. And then with the maintenance service contract, they're here twice a year, and then they swap out batteries that need to be swapped out. So. How long is the actual battery charge good for, Tony?
two years, two years. So in other words saying it's, you know, generally should be in good shape. But again, you know, we certainly wouldn't want to malfunction to be the outcome of anything. And how much of the units, like how much does it cost per unit per unit? It's just a little bit shy of a thousand dollars. And then the service contract is $285 per unit. So we are looking at a cost. I mean, um,
about $15,000 for the purchase cost and another $4,500 to service them every year. Well, how many coaches do we have starting off in the spring season right now? Oh, I didn't bring that. I didn't bring that with me. But exactly. And they all go to different fields. So the different levels, freshmen, JV, and varsity go to different fields. So we don't have all of baseball at one field. We have them separated out.
It's when, you know, cross-country is running through the fells or whatever. A coach should have somebody with him and keep, you know, training. Offsite. So we should have at least a half a dozen that they could sign up when they're off campus.
There are a lot of spring teams that are off campus. I mean, that's how we added up the 16. There's a motion on the floor that funding take a place immediately if the superintendent can find the funds seconded by Ms. Mustone. Roll call vote, please.
Yes, seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative. The motion passes. Ms. Cuno. I also have another question. Tony, you were just saying that anything that basically off campus, and I know we were discussing our athletes, but I'm curious in knowing what about like when we have our proms? Do we have to find out like where we have our proms? Do we have to find out if those locations, if there's anything going on, because we do have
The proms that are off-site and certain other events that are off-site are banquets for our students. When we have our banquets at the end of the year or after a season, do we need to find out if those places are off? Actually, we spoke about that this morning at the high school. And again, I think the planners of a lot of these events, that needs to be now a question when they're setting up the venues. Do you have an AED on site?
We would have, I mean, I keep a couple in my office as loaners, so sometimes we have to send them on a field trip. And I can give it to the nurses or a phys ed teacher who's certified to take it on a field trip if that's the case. So it would fall under that category, making sure that the venue has them. And if not, then we would loan one out to our staff. They would sign it out and bring it back.
I would propose, actually, even if the site has it, sometimes, even though they might have it, and if you're in a large hotel, you don't exactly know where it is. I think it'd just be better safe than sorry if we do have these that we can check out, that whoever is running the event is actually bringing it with them. So one of the things that we, you know, obviously have to work with our partners, the people that we play sports with and so on and so on, and other school districts, is to have that conversation.
If we go to their school, do they have things in place? If we're at other places, do they have things in place? Just like we're talking about the nurses on field trips and the like. We're going to be asking that question wherever we go. If there's something major going on, do you have facilities on site? So I don't know if you know this, but one of our former nurses used to get paid to go to the theater shows in Boston to sit in the audience just in case a nurse was necessary.
The theaters didn't have their own medical staff, so they wanted someone there who was medically trained to intervene should a situation take place. I suspect we're going to have this conversation since the law not only affects Medford, but it affects every school district and every community across the commonwealth.
It's going to be one of those discussions, do you have the right equipment? The same way with first aid kits, the same way with ambulance calls. We play a football game in a different field, we don't necessarily bring our ambulance, they have their ambulance in the field. So we have to obviously work out a lot of coordination. When I called life support systems to obtain a quote, my contact there said you're one of the first dozen
you know, cities to call about, about this. He said, I'm expecting many, many, many calls because now with this new law and just in the last week I received an email from one of the, you know, a vendor saying, Oh, this is the new law. And you know, are you prepared? So it's out there and people are, you know, we're ahead of the curve right now. People are, um, are starting to look at their needs as well.
Mr. Benedetto. Thank you. Through you to the superintendent, can we get a follow-up report of how many were actually ordered when they became available to our staff and the total cost after you figure out exactly how much you need? Could you add that to the requested reports list at the back? Also, when I read your report, I'm very happy to see that three, four, five, or more people at each of our locations
trained, except for the Curtis Tough School. That concerned me. There's only one trained person at that. And I know that we're close, and Armstrong can be there in moments. I know we don't live miles and miles away, like some of the rural districts. But really, two people minimum should be at every building. As I said, we are opening up training. So that's being offered, too.
starting with the administrators, and then we'll open up more classes. Especially because there's only a nurse there three hours a week. Right. I read another report being presented. That concerns me, and those students, you know, weren't the same. Absolutely. Consideration. So I'd really like to see an upgraded list after the training, through you to the superintendent,
any additional people and making sure that we're starting September with the appropriate number at each building and not less than two people at each school. Preferably more than that. And I motion to accept the report and thank you very much. On the motion to accept the report and place on file, seconded by Ms. Vander Kloot, Ms. Cuneo. Thank you. I was just thinking that since this is something that is hitting now and it is the law, is it possible maybe, I'm not sure if there's any type of discount if you buy a certain amount and if
like maybe we could talk to our surrounding areas, districts, to see if maybe if Somerville, Malden, Everett, or even if like Armstrong is buying some, just to see if that, if you buy, you know, zero to five, it costs a thousand. If it's five to 10, it might cost something else. So, I mean, even if there's a hundred dollar difference, maybe we could buy them together as a package deal and get the cost down.
Yes, we'll look into that, as well as the Commissioner of Elementary and Secondary Education, they're establishing the guidelines on this. They're also looking at getting out information about other grant sources and funding opportunities. That information has not come out yet. So we will have our eye on that, whether we can get some costs reimbursed once the grants come out. Thank you.
Very good, thank you very much. Ms. Vento, on the motion. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Motion is granted. Pre-budget health services. Ms. Vento. Okay, so I thought I'd give you a little overview of the program, and I listed out where our staffing, where our staff nurses are assigned. Our staffing is based on
student enrollment as well as acuity of student health needs. So while we meet all of the guidelines set out by the state for student enrollment, I always look at the acuity within the school and whether additional nurses are necessary at different schools. One expected change is I have one nurse that's retiring at the end of this school year.
So, as we've talked about in many of our pre-budget reports, is the complexity of school nursing that has changed. And there's many advances in pediatric care. Students with chronic illnesses live, they attend school, and they receive a lot of care in school. We have not only students with
allergies, diabetes, but we have students who have had cancer, we've had students that have had organ transplants, and they all require some sort of monitoring or attention by a school nurse. The past couple of years has also seen a growing number of international children coming into the area for care at the Boston Medical Centers. These students usually seek advanced care.
or had very little health care in their lives, so they're coming with many, many needs. And while they're here, they do enroll in the Medford public schools. We're close to the city, and there are community groups that they are linked with, and I think that's why they come here to Medford. And those students require accommodations for their time when they're in school to access their curriculum.
case managers, and not only doing first aid and medication administration, but working closely with physicians and community organizations to make sure that the students are able to attend school safely. We have students who travel with portable defibrillators, we have students who require tube feedings, certainly diabetic care, we have students with seizure disorders, and then life-threatening allergies, and any emergency with
will require one-to-one attention by the school nurse and it leaves the rest of the population waiting until the emergency has been resolved. Some of the other things that have increased the complexity, the demand for student screenings such as the mental health issues have grown and expanded yearly and our most recent numbers are we have about 660
students who have a physician diagnosed mental health condition that may require a lot of additional nursing support. We work in tandem with the counseling staff so that behavior plans can be carried forth in the nurse's office as well, and that we're part of the team to help students get back to class quickly, stay in class,
and access their curriculum. And then we're also trained, we have access to Narcan in case there are any opioid overdoses by either students, staff, or even visitors in the area. The nurses are trained and we have a supply of Narcan available. Last year we had, we did receive funds for,
to fund the contractually mandated professional development and the liability insurance as we grew our staff. Some of the accomplishments. We have maintained a return to class rate of 97% in our district, and that's been consistent for the past three years. So students coming down to the nurse's office are receiving treatments and getting back into class.
We accomplished the SBIRT screening as I mentioned earlier. This year was accomplished at no financial cost to the district. We were able to readjust staffing and we did that without having substitute. The tuberculosis surveillance project was a high priority this fall. We had 205 individuals that participated in screening that took place in October and January.
We ran a blood screening clinic here at the high school for about 120 individuals. A number of other students had skin tests placed by the Medford Board of Health. And other students were followed by their primary care physicians. What that project entailed was a lot of collaboration and coordination by the school nurses with different departments, both at the state and city level.
And then last, another accomplishment is we're continuing our outreach to parents, and I did put a flyer over at the podium about, we have a talk on April 12th by Dr. Ruth Poteet. She's an expert on substance abuse behaviors, and she speaks frequently about the risk factors that teens face because of their brain development during the teen years.
So it's a community forum. It's open to all parents, teaching staff. It's not for students. It's for adults. We've opened it up to the Mystic Valley Public Health Coalition. Some neighboring towns have also expressed interest. So we're very pleased to be sponsoring that with generous support from Team Medford. Pardon me? It's at the high school, the Caron Theater.
at 630 on Wednesday, April 12th. So the request for the budget, the first thing is to increase the service line item to maintain our existing 13 AEDs that we have in the district. Last year, I was able to absorb that cost through grant funding, and that grant funding is no longer available.
Also the funds to purchase the additional AEDs that we spoke about at the previous report. And then some special requests. Replacing the full-time nursing position that we will lose to retirement and increasing the nursing staff by one FTE. I'd like to increase the staff at the Roberts Elementary School so that there is some extra support to the school nurse there since she's a solo practitioner.
And I'd like to place some nursing staff at the Curtis Tufts so that we would have somebody available to attend meetings and be available for the students as they need. Very good. Thank you very much. Are there any questions for Ms. Vento?
Motion to receive and place this report on file by Ms. Cuneo and by Mr. Skerry. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion passes. Thank you. Thank you. Pre-budget foreign language. This report will be given in Italian. Right. OK. We'll do that.
I promise you it'll be much lighter than the previous reports. And before you speak, we do have an addenda that was added in our packet on our desk tonight. If you could add it to this one. So I'd like to begin by giving you an overview of our department. The foreign language program in the Medford Public Schools is aligned with the national Act IV guidelines and with the state
of Massachusetts curriculum frameworks. In the foreign language classroom, students develop linguistics and cultural skills that enable them to contribute in a global society. Students in the Medfit public schools are first introduced to a foreign language in second grade, Italian, and that continues to fifth grade,
and it's a program that's being supported by a grant from CASIT. In the middle school, students can choose to study Italian or Spanish. They have instructions twice a week in sixth grade, and that's increased to three times a week in seventh grade and eighth grade.
Our current program in the middle schools is not ideal and does not adequately prepare most of our students to move into the second year of foreign language at the high school. Ideally, students should have foreign language every day, especially at the 8th grade level.
Unfortunately, the scheduling and the level of staffing needed precludes this from occurring. Adding staff, a .5 teacher at each of the middle schools would help reduce class size, thus increasing a student's acquisition of the language by the end of 8th grade.
At the high school, in addition to Spanish and Italian, we also offer French. The graduation requirement is two years of the same language, but many students choose to continue through senior year, as acceptance to many colleges require three or four years of the same language.
Staffing, the foreign language department has 14 teachers, two at each of the middle schools and 10 at the high school. Highlights, and I did it monthly to be a little bit more organized, so I'll start with September. This past September, our French teachers accompanied a group of French students to the Boston Opera House to see the intriguing Opera of Carmen.
In October, two AP Italian students each won $1,000 and were honored at a gala celebration in Boston. In November, six Medford Public Schools foreign language teachers, including myself, were among the 8,500 who attended the Actful Convention in Boston.
Teachers felt inspired and returned to their classrooms with renewed energy and lots of new strategies to use in the classroom. Subsequently, we held a series of professional development workshops where teachers that attended the conference shared what they learned with the rest of the department and with each other because we made it a point not to attend the same sessions at the convention. In December,
220 students of Italian enjoyed a concert by Italian singers at Everett High School. A group of Italian and Spanish students spent a Saturday at Melrose High School's Immersion Day, where they were able to use the target language outside the classroom settings. Speaking of using the target language outside the classroom settings, in February, students from Ms. Bryan's Spanish 5 class
visited and participated in Spanish classes at St. Anselm's College. In March, the same thing was done with the AP students from Ms. Lepore's AP class, and this time it was at Tufts University. Also in March, the Italian Consulate of Boston arranged to bring Italian culture to Medford High School. They brought two cars, a Maserati and a Lamborghini,
and 100 packets from Italy that contained pasta, canned tomatoes, and a recipe for students of Italian. Finally, that afternoon, they entertained us with a musical group from Italy. A French student in Ms. Smith's French Four of Honors competed in the oratory contest by Club Richelieu,
of Salem and finished second place and won $200. Still in March, about 300 students participated in the national foreign language exams. We just completed them this week. And the results from these tests inform us about curriculum and how we perform on a national basis. To the two middle school teachers from the Andrews School for first time this year also opted to
to have their students take the test. So we're anxious to see the results. In April, actually this coming Friday, a group of 19 Italian students will compete with area high schools at Brandeis University. They will be judged on creativity and language use. During April vacation, Medford High School will take a group
to Italy on an educational trip. And actually, I will be returning on an upcoming meeting to ask your approval for two other trips for the following year. In April and May, the Education Office of the Boston Italian Consulate will introduce Arduino to advanced Italian students. And Arduino is an open source platform used for building electronics projects.
Universities in Italy and MIT are working together on numerous research collaborations using Arduino. And some of these representatives will come to give instructions in Italian to our students. Each student will receive a Arduino kit and will be challenged to create its own electronics project.
In May, 28 students will be taking foreign language AP exams. Our averages from last year were above the national average, and we wish this year's students good luck on their exams. After taking the AP exam, exams, I should say, because the three languages they do it, students will be teaching foreign language to the children in Kids' Corner.
And this is in response to requests from Kids Corner and parents. Funding for 2016-2017 was used to purchase new textbooks, Avancemos 3, to finish our Spanish series, replace lost and damaged books, purchase new sets of easy readers for French, Italian, and Spanish,
Purchase additional AP books since our AP Spanish enrollment was higher this year. Pay for the annual online fee for the AP Spanish students. Purchase sets of headphones and microphones for our middle schools and high school. And then purchase the usual office and classroom supplies. Requests for budget for 2017-2018, I'm asking for a level
funded budget to 2015-2016. Numbers of current staff and anticipated staffing needs. At the high school, we currently have 10 full-time teachers. At the middle schools, there are four, two at each school. And as I mentioned before, I am asking for an additional .5 teacher at each of the middle schools. Goals and objectives for 2017-2018.
improve on our foreign language program at the middle schools, provide professional development for teachers in pedagogy and curriculum, continue our journey to proficiency, and it is a journey, plan a PD series to work on proficiency-based assessments, especially final exams, and support and guide teachers to focus on two of the six core practices from ACTFL, and those are
design communicative activities, and teach grammar as concept and use in context. Non-salary needs for educational materials and supplies. I supplied a table for you, and as I said, I'll be asking for level funded budget to 2015-2016. If you have any questions. Mr. Benedetto. Thank you. Thank you for your report. It's very nice to see you. Thank you.
So I had a question about the middle school teachers. You said the 2.5 people, one for each middle school, would not increase the amount of classes the students take. It would decrease the class size. What is the average class size now? Around 25, I think. 24 to 25. In how many classes a day?
How many classes a day? Do each teacher currently teach? The middle school schedule is unique in a sense that we go a five day cycle. And we also have every exploratory as well. So at the Andrews, we rotate quarterly. So art, music, tech lab, computer, include a full year of foreign language. But in order to make everything work contractually and everybody have what they need,
You pay for Peter to rob the Paul in this sort of kind of way. You know, everybody wants something. You know, there were times where people wanted us all to make sure that everyone's getting help from the Michigan Monocle. You only have 10 periods a day. So in order to figure out how to do that, it becomes a real balancing act. I would love to increase foreign language.
becomes a balancing act and making sure, remembering too, that if there is a 0.5, there's travel that's involved between the two middle schools. So I'm saying 0.5 at each. So how would a 0.5 person lower the class size?
So we can make a section that would help that out and divvy things up. What happens when fifth graders come to select a school, they also select a foreign language. And we do the best we can to honor that, but we can't honor that all the time due to the numbers of kids. So this happens to be an increased number of students that want to take Spanish.
when they come to the Andrews. So that, you know, with one teacher, there's only so many sections I can give that one teacher, and then I have to move it over to Italian, let's say. So presently, what do we have for staffing at the Andrews for foreign language? A full-time Italian teacher and a full-time Spanish teacher. And what's the class size for the Italian classes? Average is 24. Okay, so
How many of those requested Italians? I would say it's usually a 60-40.
60% Spanish, 40% Italian. But that changes. Right, and that varies. You know, we've talked about this, we've had middle school ILDs, we've talked about, you know, what's the change. Sometimes it's the experience that they feel like they've had a little bit of experience in Italian in elementary and they want to make, you know, just a change into Spanish and learn something different.
I'm just curious just to help how it works. Because we used to have foreign language every day in the middle schools years ago, right? Years ago. But again, things, you know, needed things, like everybody needs to take health and we want to make sure that they get the Michigan model. And there's a lot of things that, you know, the needs are there. We just have to make sure everything's balanced. So adding the .5 person, would that enable more children to have
choice. As in get their first choice of which language they want? The way that we're looking at this, if I'm assuming, correct me if I'm wrong, we're talking about one teacher that's going to be shared between two schools?
try to get to teach to save on that. 2.5 teachers. That's even better. Two part-time teachers would be better this way. They won't waste time traveling. Do they just teach one language, or do some teachers teach both? We would teach both. Right. Well, it'd be great if we can get two. Ideally, we would like to have someone that's a foreign language. Right, that would have both. Is that common?
Those are very rare. It's very rare. But just because of what we're seeing with data, it would make things easier with scheduling if you could have someone that could teach a Spanish class and an Italian class as well. And that would help balance off numbers as well. So the new hires that you're going to advertise for, will they be for Spanish or for Italian? We will probably go for Spanish.
Because we have more students selecting Spanish. So my last question is, do we need two full-time Spanish teachers and a part-time Italian teacher? Or has that been looked at? I think based on the numbers, I don't think. Again, and I don't know what the incoming numbers are at this point in time. We're going through that now. We're currently going through that. But I mean, since my tenure as principal, the increase in Spanish has gotten a little bit greater through the years.
I'm just asking so we allocate and we plan for future choice. And the other sense of things too, and I think Mia can attest to it too, I hope. Even though I'm not always able to honor the sixth grade, I do my best if there needs to be some switch. A lot of kids say, oh no, I'm very happy where I was, but there's still a few families that would like to make that switch. I do everything I can in the summer to adjust for that if I can.
Thank you. Thank you very much. Miss Stone. I can attest to that. I can attest to that. I have an Italian eighth grader and a Spanish sixth grader. So they both got their first choice. So they were happy. Thank you. Mr. Scary.
I'll throw you to Mr. Cowell. Mr. Cowell, do you get requests from students to, they may want to learn another language besides what we're offering, such as German, or study Latin, or Chinese, or Russian? Right. We have had that discussion at the beginning of the year with Dr. Perella and Ms. Riccardelli, and we actually conducted a survey. The students gave them a choice of 10 languages. If they were to choose any language, which one would be their first choice?
put them in the order of choice. And so there was no surprise that number one was Spanish, number two was Italian, number three was French, and actually number four is Portuguese that they want. Chinese wasn't there, but I can send you if you want, I can send you the data of the survey.
Is there any possibility of offering introductory Portuguese in the fall or was that some time off? Once we went over the survey with Dr. Ricardelli and Dr. Perella, we decided to leave things as they are for this year and then reconsider. Thank you. Thank you. Ms. Cunha. Thank you, Mr. Keller, for the report. As far as the lost and damaged books, are those numbers rising over the years?
Well, now that we have newer books, so that if a book is lost, it costs a lot more to replace. We have some Italian books that are almost $170 a book. That includes the online component. It seems that more books are lost at the middle schools, but they have old books.
And teachers are using the book less and less, because, in fact, we were looking into buying new books for middle schools, but I'd rather have the extra teachers. And they are making their own units, and there's so much now available online. Because you have replaced lost or damaged books, because the cost of replacing newer books is very high.
So how about the new books that were bought at the high school? Right. Those are the ones I'm talking about. If they lose those books, right, we have to replace them. So has the number of losing books increased? At the high school, I don't think so. It's pretty much. OK. Very good. Ms. Van de Kloop. I just wanted to mention that I really love that after the AP exams, the students are going to go down to Kids' Corner and teach them some
some words and whatever. I thought that was a lot of fun. Some little songs, some words, some colors maybe. I think that's great. I think it would be great for both the students and the little children. Thank you. Thank you very much. Ms. DiCarlo, is there a motion on the floor to receive and place on file? Second. Seconded by Ms. Van de Kloot. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion is granted. Thank you. Thank you. Pre-budget mathematics. Ms. Joy.
Good evening. Good evening, everyone. I'll go through the overview with you. You have the full text of the narrative of the mathematics proposed budget for next year. The mathematics program at the K through 12 is based on the Massachusetts state framework for mathematics, and that is built upon the common core state standards.
And it is currently undergoing a revision of those standards which we will be attending to during the summer and the following school year. The instructional practices and materials are aligned with the program. We have recently bought new programs for the elementary and at the high school levels and our practices
again go on with that program and to offer course pathways for students to make them college and career ready. So you'll see at the high school we have a lot of offerings beyond Algebra II for our students because they do take various routes post-graduation from Medford High School.
Currently, at the middle school, we have 13 teachers, and at the high school, 15 and two-tenths. That little piece is one of the CTE teachers is teaching a section of Algebra I for us again this year. And the highlights of this year
is to support those changes in curriculum and testing. We put in place some professional development for teachers in grades three through eight. Three through five was given predominantly during their professional development days, visits to the elementary schools and workshops that I had at the high school, which they attended. And that was to get them all ready for the next round of testing, which will be
We are entering in that area now. All the teachers on the PD day took the online assessment to see what it was like and experience that firsthand so they'd have better knowledges of the challenges that might face the children with the use of the technology. And then at the middle school, a lot of the professional development was done within our department meeting time.
And again, they were taking the test, giving practice tests to students. We had a new program. This is a first year at the high school for Algebra I, Geometry, Algebra II, and I'd like to thank members of the committee for voting that through. It is making a significant difference to have teachers
like all on the same pace and that is in all the schools and at the special education classrooms are using the same materials as well as the English language learner classrooms. And so that is going well. We kicked off the year with some professional development in how to use the technology associated with the program. And also in the elementary,
Again, we're working on greater use of the technology. So we know that at home, they have access to online textbooks and tutors through those programs. So it's going quite well, but like anything, it's so deep. There are many layers of the technology for the faculty to learn and to be able to share with the students.
The program is integrated, we have co-teaching. Also at the high school now, we extended it to geometry classes in the hopes of expanding it to algebra two. It's working well in mathematics and we just did an assessment on it so if it can all be scheduled, we'd like to continue in that realm. And so it's a co-teach model.
that we're using, and again, it will depend on staffing. And the collaboration and outreach has been with our community members and also higher education. We had an opportunity right now, some of our students are in the midst of taking courses,
through MIT's OpenCourseWare. They invited us into their BeaverWorks program. And we have, let's see, six students who have been granted entrance into the program. They're taking online programming courses and have now applied for a summer program. So we're hoping to get some of the students in this summer program, which will be a combination of
programming and robotics, and it'll be free of charge to our students, so we're very hopeful all their applications are in. We had speakers come from Wentworth Institute and Applied Mathematics to talk to the students about, you know, how are you going to use this mathematics? And so they brought an entire team out.
Tufts University has always been a great partner with us. Um, we have a few programs going with them. One is the STEM Ambassador's Program, where we sit down, um, the director of science and myself with the team from that program through Tisch College. We evaluate the program each year.
And last year we found a need to kind of strengthen our pathway in computer science. And it turned out this year that almost 50% of the ambassadors coming from Tufts had that as a background. So they were able to bring some of the units into the physics class because we're using physics as their vehicle of reaching students. And so they did some programming with them.
And also through that program, I was able to meet a new faculty member in the computer science department, who's starting a chapter of Girl Set Code, and invited Medford students, and we had quite a few, and I believe they've even connected with the Girl Scouts in Medford, to offer Saturday classes. And in turn, one of our teachers, Ms. Faiza Khan,
She went on the TEF Saturday program and spoke about her career pathway because she has an engineering background and programming background and teaches programming at the high school. And on the other side, we had that professor, Dr. Laney Strange, come to Medford High School and speak about her career pathway. So it did work out well. We had a give and take.
We'll be entering into a partnership with Harvard University on strategies for teaching Algebra I. So right now, we're just working out the details of the memorandum of agreement, and that will begin this summer with teacher education. The parent and guardian participation and communications,
held several nights during the school year at the high school. And we have an event coming up for parents of sixth graders. It's Thursday, if you can make it. It's 7 o'clock at the high school, talking about the pathways in our mathematics program. And then at the elementary level, we had teachers open up their classroom and actually model and envision math lessons so the parents could see
just what it looked like in the classroom. So the funding for this present school year, again, the entire textbook budget went to the new high school adoption for Algebra I geometry and Algebra II. Instructional materials to support the program K through 12.
So those were like mathematics specific materials that they needed in the classroom and that included a lot of technology. We're getting up to speed in trying to get document cameras in the classroom and calculators are always a big expense and along with that comes a big expense for batteries every year. So that takes a good chunk of it.
And then the office supplies just for operations for the department. And so my request for next year's funding is pretty much level to what we had last year with a little bump up on the textbook item. And that is so that we can pay our last payment for the textbook program. And then a little bit of extra money
For those senior programs, should we see a shift in enrollment and need to buy some books? Or when you're at a classroom, the teacher materials are quite expensive. But I'm not projecting anything very great. But we do know that our enrollment has been fluctuating. We've been bringing in students, which is a good thing. But we need to kind of look ahead to see
if any more monies need to be put in that direction. So if you have any questions. Thank you very much. Ms. Vandekloot. Could I just ask, what was the date of the pathways? That's this Thursday evening. OK. And where is it being held? It's going to be at the Science Lecture Hall at the high school at 7 o'clock to 8 o'clock. OK. There's so many things that night. There is. And that one didn't get on our list. So thank you very much. You're welcome.
I guess one other comment, I just wanted to, I really like that there's been so much interaction between our students and Tufts and many of the other MIT and whatever so that our students are seeing real world potential jobs in mathematics and what people do with it. So I think that clearly your report listed so many of them and I think that's terrific. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
Is there a motion on the floor for motion to receive in place on file by Mr. Scarry, seconded by Ms. Cuneo. All those in favor. All those opposed, motion passes. Thank you very much, Ms. Joy. Next up, report on personnel hiring September 1st, 2016 to March 29th, 2017. Mr. Superintendent. So this is a report that you requested and it's listing. It's pretty obvious as to what's there. And, uh,
We'll give you updates as they require. Thank you very much, Mr. Superintendent. There's a motion on the floor to accept by Mr. Benedetto. Is there a seconded by Ms. Van de Kloot? All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Motion passes.
a couple of announcements. And actually, if I could just make an announcement from the floor. It's not related to schools. It's the big sweep is starting on Monday. So everybody, check your website. Sign up for the website to get alerts. Please sign up through the website. And just watch for your area when it's going to be covered, because there is ticketing and towing involved. And we know that's very expensive, but it's the only way we can get it done. So a shout out. It's starting next Wednesday. Thank you.
Yep. Did you want to say something else before we throw a couple of quick information pieces out there tomorrow night? I'm at the city council again, seeking matching funds for the culinary arts hospitality project. Um, you've got a breakout here. As you can see, we're putting in quite a bit of our own money and outside money as well as the state grant. Um, so there's 500,000 from the state is 813,000 in kind.
And, um, we're asking the council and free cash for 250,000. So I'll be there tomorrow night. Um, and also, um, because next Monday is Passover, we inadvertently scheduled it for Monday night. We'd like to move it to the 24th. Uh, I scheduled, you know, just tentatively the 26th, but that may have some conflicts with the mayor and other things. So I'll get back to you for a meeting on, on the community schools. We'll get a date that works for all of you. And then we'll,
looking to schedule a date. We'll check with the mayor's office and elsewhere, uh, for a community school and not community schools, a, uh, school council report night. Okay. So we have a committee of the whole on that. So just some of the dates that we're trying to juggle to make sure everybody can be in attendance. And I think we're good. Thank you, Mr. Superintendent. Ms. Vander Kloop. 10th is canceled.
Yes. And that's rescheduled to April 24th. Right. OK. Thank you. I did wonder, when we were given the school council reports, my colleague earlier asked about the PTO representation. And I wondered if we might combine those two, because often the school council reports reflect. We can. The only thing I suggest is that those meetings tend to be very long. That's true.
You might want a different meeting for that, just simply because those meetings are long as it is. OK. Sometimes we hear about them. Sometimes the same people, but that can go for a few hours. OK. Just to follow up on that, I also like it to be here at the chambers, so that way we acknowledge the people that are really doing so much time and service to our community for our students. So I'd rather really have them present to us here.
rather than a committee at a regular meeting. Yes. Okay. Okay. We'd have to schedule as a regular meeting, but it's our special meeting that's put that way. Or added to our agenda. Ms. Cunha. The only thing about having everybody here for the psych council meeting is I know that, um,
A lot of people like to sit at the round table like when we have an open meeting like that and they feel that they could come and be more casual in that. I mean, we could still have it. Oh, the PTO. I'm sorry. Because we were talking about side council. That's what we're talking about. You're talking about the PTO meeting being in council chambers? Yes.
New business. School committee resolution. Be it resolved that the Medford School Committee express its sincere condolences to the family of Stephen Honeycutt. Mr. Honeycutt was an active member of the community who served on the city's disabilities commission. He was a strong supporter of the Medford Public Schools. Be it resolved that the Medford School Committee express its sincere condolences to the family of Stephen DeVoe. Mr. DeVoe was the brother of former superintendent Phillip DeVoe. Mr. DeVoe was a 1964 graduate of Medford High School.
Also be it resolved that the Medford School Committee express its sincere condolences to the family of Frank Loschuto. Loschuto? Loschuto. Mr. Loschuto was a former Medford Public Schools custodian for many years. And lastly, be it resolved that the Medford School Committee express its sincere condolences to the family of Senator Kenneth Donnelly. Senator Donnelly lost his courageous battle with brain cancer this past Sunday. If we could all please rise and take a moment of silence on the passing of these individuals.
Also, there's one other item. Be it resolved that the Medford School Committee expresses congratulations to Director of Pupil Services, Kathy Madaglio, on the birth of her first grandchild, Reese James McMahon. Reese is the son of social studies teacher, Dana McMahon. Congratulations, Ms. Madaglio. We all got to see beautiful pictures earlier, so congratulations. Enjoy every minute of that.
I believe that is the final item on our agenda. There are no negotiations in legal matters. Motion to adjourn.