[SPEAKER_00]: Hi there, my name is Aaron Olopone, and I'm running for Medford School Committee because Medford deserves diversity and progress, and because representation matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because affinity has a huge impact on our sense of belonging, and thus on our learning.
[SPEAKER_00]: When we identify with other humans, when they look like us, and when we share values and experiences, we are more likely to be engaged and enthusiastic.
[SPEAKER_00]: We are motivated and persistent in our efforts when we connect with our teachers and fellow learners.
[SPEAKER_00]: When we share passions and goals with others, collaboration and innovation is more likely.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when we connect with others around shared experiences, there is an emotional connection that builds up community and a sense of trust and belonging.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like it or not, affinity happens with those who share our experiences, cultures, and contexts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everybody, everybody deserves to have curriculum, educators, mentors, coaches, and elected officials who represent them and with whom they can build an affinity.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why representation matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I'm asking for your support.
[SPEAKER_00]: Help our campaign bring my fresh, progressive voice to the school committee.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am the only candidate with the lived experience of being a recent graduate who understands the challenges of missing out on that representation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Donate, host a meet and greet, sign up to Canvas, and check out our website for more details about who I am, what I stand for, and what my top priorities are in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: Visit electaronaldpade.com and let's do this together.