Hi, I am here with Joyce McKenzie, who owns Nelly's Wildflowers in Somerville. Thank you, Joyce, for being here. Hi. Thank you. Yeah, of course. Can you tell me a little bit about Nelly's, when it started and how you started?
We opened in 1990, April of 1990. So we were going to be having our big 30th anniversary in April of this year. That didn't happen. I mean, we still, we have been here 30 plus years and I named it after my grandmother, Nellie. Nellie is not my name. Everyone calls me Nellie and that's fine. And we just specialize in wildflowers and unique things.
We've been here in the neighborhood, and I live in the neighborhood, so I know a lot of people, which is great. A lot of my friends and neighbors come in all the time, a lot of the students from Tufts. So we've got a great, great street. We just love it here.
Yeah, I have to say, you know this, but the viewers and listeners don't, but Nellie's well-forested my wedding. So I have such a warm place in my heart for you guys. Thank you. Yeah, no, thank you. Yeah, so, you know, you obviously, COVID I'm sure affected your business. Can you tell us a little bit about what it's been like and what it's like now?
Well, um, you know, along with everybody else, I mean, we were just completely nervous and thrown and thought we were going to be closing, you know, we really thought this was it. And I thought, okay, 30 years is a good, that's a good round number. And we'll, we'll call it a day. But, um, my partner and I decided to just go on and we've been open ever since we actually never closed.
So we've been just doing online ordering and we do free delivery here in the city. Any amount. We just felt like we wanted to do whatever would make people happy and keep us afloat. And it's been working. You know, I work a lot. I'm really tired. But it's really been working out. So I
You know, COVID has been kind of a mixed blessing in a way, because it's just shown like who our true friends and followers are and supporters. I mean, people have just been so unbelievably generous and kind. And that's just immeasurable for me. So. Great. Yeah.
I'm sure people would love to have flowers for the holidays, to get flowers for their loved ones for the holidays. How can people shop with you?
Yeah, we're pretty accessible. We have online ordering, as I said, and we are open. We've curtailed our hours slightly. We are open 9 to 5, Monday through Saturday. And if you don't want to come into the store, we do curbside pickup. But we are open to the public, so you can come into the store.
And we like I said we have free delivery in Somerville, but we have a wide delivery area to that we do have different delivery charges and things and minimums, but we'll go as far as Wellesley or.
up north to Wilmington. So we have a pretty wide range of where we go. Wow, amazing. Yeah. And what's the website and the phone number? And how can people find you on social media? Yep. It's nellyswildflowers at gmail.com. That's our website.
No, yeah, that's our website. That's the email. Email, sorry. Millieswildflowers.com, is that sound? Exactly, that's our website. And like I said, we have the Bloom Network, it's a network of flower shops throughout the country, and it's very easy to online order. Or you can call, the number is 617-625-9453. And like I said, we're there from nine to five, so it's pretty easy to get in touch with us.
and we'll try to get you whatever you want. Amazing. Yeah. Wonderful. Thank you so much. It's just great to see you again. You're welcome. And chat a little bit. And yeah, have a great holidays. Thanks, Anna. You too. Good luck with everything. Thank you. Bye-bye.