[SPEAKER_02]: Hi, I am here with Joyce McKenzie, who owns Nelly's Wildflowers in Somerville.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you, Joyce, for being here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you tell me a little bit about Nelly's, when it started and how you started?
[SPEAKER_00]: We opened in 1990, April of 1990.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we were going to be having our big 30th anniversary in April of this year.
[SPEAKER_00]: That didn't happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, we still, we have been here 30 plus years and I named it after my grandmother, Nellie.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nellie is not my name.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everyone calls me Nellie and that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we just specialize in wildflowers and unique things.
[SPEAKER_00]: We've been here in the neighborhood, and I live in the neighborhood, so I know a lot of people, which is great.
[SPEAKER_00]: A lot of my friends and neighbors come in all the time, a lot of the students from Tufts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we've got a great, great street.
[SPEAKER_00]: We just love it here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I have to say, you know this, but the viewers and listeners don't, but Nellie's well-forested my wedding.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I have such a warm place in my heart for you guys.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, no, thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so, you know, you obviously, COVID I'm sure affected your business.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you tell us a little bit about what it's been like and what it's like now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, um, you know, along with everybody else, I mean, we were just completely nervous and thrown and thought we were going to be closing, you know, we really thought this was it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I thought, okay, 30 years is a good, that's a good round number.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we'll, we'll call it a day.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, um, my partner and I decided to just go on and we've been open ever since we actually never closed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we've been just doing online ordering and we do free delivery here in the city.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any amount.
[SPEAKER_00]: We just felt like we wanted to do whatever would make people happy and keep us afloat.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's been working.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, I work a lot.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm really tired.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's really been working out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, COVID has been kind of a mixed blessing in a way, because it's just shown like who our true friends and followers are and supporters.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, people have just been so unbelievably generous and kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's just immeasurable for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So.
[SPEAKER_02]: Great.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm sure people would love to have flowers for the holidays, to get flowers for their loved ones for the holidays.
[SPEAKER_02]: How can people shop with you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, we're pretty accessible.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have online ordering, as I said, and we are open.
[SPEAKER_00]: We've curtailed our hours slightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: We are open 9 to 5, Monday through Saturday.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you don't want to come into the store, we do curbside pickup.
[SPEAKER_00]: But we are open to the public, so you can come into the store.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we like I said we have free delivery in Somerville, but we have a wide delivery area to that we do have different delivery charges and things and minimums, but we'll go as far as Wellesley or.
[SPEAKER_00]: up north to Wilmington.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we have a pretty wide range of where we go.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wow, amazing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what's the website and the phone number?
[SPEAKER_02]: And how can people find you on social media?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's nellyswildflowers at gmail.com.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's our website.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, yeah, that's our website.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the email.
[SPEAKER_00]: Email, sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Millieswildflowers.com, is that sound?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, that's our website.
[SPEAKER_00]: And like I said, we have the Bloom Network, it's a network of flower shops throughout the country, and it's very easy to online order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you can call, the number is 617-625-9453.
[SPEAKER_00]: And like I said, we're there from nine to five, so it's pretty easy to get in touch with us.
[SPEAKER_00]: and we'll try to get you whatever you want.
[SPEAKER_02]: Amazing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wonderful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just great to see you again.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're welcome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And chat a little bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yeah, have a great holidays.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thanks, Anna.
[SPEAKER_01]: You too.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good luck with everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bye-bye.