[SPEAKER_01]: Hopefully get a quorum.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know if you can see me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_01]: I knew new computer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So let's show them like we could, but we can't now, or I could, but I can't now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, interesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: It seems like it's trying like holds and pauses.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hey guys, can you hear me?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Cool.
[SPEAKER_03]: All right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hi, everyone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good evening.
[SPEAKER_01]: All right, we have everybody.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm having some trouble, but I'm on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, same, I'm having camera issues, so we'll just gonna, I see everybody's here, so let's get going.
[SPEAKER_01]: Meeting's being recorded.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have our meeting on Friday, July 10th, special meeting approval of updated chapter 74 visibility form.
[SPEAKER_01]: and it's being held remotely only.
[SPEAKER_01]: The meeting can be viewed through Medford Community Media on Comcast and Verizon.
[SPEAKER_01]: Participants can log or call in by using the following link or call in number.
[SPEAKER_01]: Meeting ID is 934-1272-7100.
[SPEAKER_01]: Questions or comments can be submitted during the meeting by emailing medfordsc at medford.k12.ma.us.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those submitting questions or comments must include the following information, your first and last name, your Medford Street address, and your question or comment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Member Ruseau, if you don't mind calling the roll, please.
[SPEAKER_03]: Certainly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Am I unmuted?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Member Graham?
[SPEAKER_03]: Here.
[SPEAKER_03]: Member Mastropone?
[SPEAKER_03]: Member Olapade?
[SPEAKER_03]: Here.
[SPEAKER_03]: Member Parks?
[SPEAKER_00]: Here.
[SPEAKER_03]: Member Reinfeld?
[SPEAKER_01]: Present.
[SPEAKER_03]: Member Ruseau, present.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mayor Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_01]: Present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seven present, zero absent.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're going to go to number two, recommendation to approve the updated chapter 74 visibility form for the new Medford High School project.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I had asked, it might be helpful, I think, if, I don't know what, Jenny, if you wanted to do any framing, and then I had shared with Will, if we could do a little screen sharing, so we could go through it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can set it up quickly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So earlier this week, the MSBA asked us to update this chapter 74 viability form, which for those of you who are on the committee a couple of years back, we had to fill this out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it really goes through all of our chapter 74 programs, our current enrollment, our anticipated enrollment in the new school, and specifically any new programs we intend to add, the timing of those new programs,
[SPEAKER_00]: And just a general check of like, how do these programs sort of line up with our regional labor needs, etc.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, we filled out this form it was unanimously approved like two years ago, they've just asked us to update it with.
[SPEAKER_00]: more current enrollment and waitlist information.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the other like relevant thing that has changed for us is we have more clarity about the opening date of the building, which in some cases will be required for the programs to operate like as in the case of dental assisting.
[SPEAKER_00]: So there's some minor changes to the form that really are about enrollment and timing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so they asked us to update this form, which we have done now and noted that anytime that we change this form, they do require a vote of this committee.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they asked us to get this done before our facilities assessment committee meeting next week.
[SPEAKER_00]: So thank you all for jumping on, on a Friday afternoon, but this should be quick.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the changes are quite, the changes are pretty simple all in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Will, do you mind going back?
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So the first part was just updating the enrollment from school.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, this says school year 24-25.
[SPEAKER_02]: If they want this past school year, we can go back and do that now.
[SPEAKER_02]: But we added the enrollment.
[SPEAKER_02]: That piece was left off from the previous one.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then thank you, Will.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can scroll now.
[SPEAKER_02]: right here, you'll just see through a series of comments, pieces that have been added.
[SPEAKER_02]: So this is talking about how we're expanding some of our programs, how we did it this year by adding additional teachers and or adding additional programs.
[SPEAKER_02]: This right here speaks to the additional staff members that we're adding to these four programs and when that
[SPEAKER_02]: change took place or when it will take place.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you scroll down just a little bit more, Will, right here, these are the four programs that will be new as part of this high school project.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dental assisting, criminal justice, protective services, the HVAC,
[SPEAKER_02]: part plumbing will be in the, the new and then information systems.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, plumbing and information systems is starting next year, as reflected on this for the launch, and then dental assisting and the criminal justice protective services will be starting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Scalia 3031 is the anticipated occupancy.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then if that fluctuates, we can update at that time.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then if you just scroll to the pieces that have been updated that require new votes, just go down a little bit.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you, Will.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: This piece talks about, again, enrollment with the total number of students that we have, and it breaks it down by school year so that you can see.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hold on one second.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is the wait list, I believe.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then the next piece, if we go down to section C,
[SPEAKER_02]: This is general information, so we had to provide just additional pieces about those two programs that are starting in September.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then if we keep, which is, again, plumbing and information systems, those are fully enrolled right now and starting in the fall.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, Will, if you go down to the next section, if there is one that required an update.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nope.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, those are all the pieces that have been updated.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you have any questions, I'm happy to answer them so that we can get a vote on these updates and be able to submit it to MSBA.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you, Dr. Galussi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any questions or is there a motion on the floor?
[SPEAKER_01]: Motion to approve?
[SPEAKER_01]: Second.
[SPEAKER_01]: Motion to approve by Member Graham, seconded by Member Reinfeld.
[SPEAKER_01]: Member Ruseau, if you could please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_03]: Member Graham?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Member Mastromonti?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Member Olapodie?
[SPEAKER_03]: Member Parks?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Member Reinfeld?
[SPEAKER_03]: Member Ruseau?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mayor Leung Okern?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative.
[SPEAKER_01]: The paper passes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you, everybody.
[SPEAKER_01]: Much appreciated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Motion adjourned by Member Ruseau, seconded by Member Reinfeld.
[SPEAKER_01]: Roll call, please.
[SPEAKER_03]: Member Graham?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Member Mastrobonni?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Member Olapade?
[SPEAKER_03]: Member Parks?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Member Reinfeld?
[SPEAKER_03]: Member Ruseau, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, seven the affirmative zero.