Good evening and welcome to tonight's matchup between the visiting Lincoln Sunbury Warriors and your Brockton Boxers. Brockton High School and the MIAA would like to take this opportunity to encourage you to display good sportsmanship. Please do your part by showing respect to everyone involved in tonight's contest. For everyone's safety, spectators are not allowed to stand along the fence in front of the bleachers
on either side of the field. Please note the use of any tobacco or vaping products, including electronic cigarettes or any other burnable substance, is prohibited in the stadium and on all school grounds. A friendly reminder that students, athletes play the game, coaches coach, fans support their team, and officials manage the game, and sometimes make calls you may not agree with. With that being said,
Inappropriate behavior, language, or verbal criticism of coaches, players, and officials will not be tolerated and may result in your removal from the stadium. For your convenience, restrooms are located on the press box side under the bleachers. Please be sure to visit our snack bar in the south end zone where you can get hot, fresh Cape Cod pizza. We'd like to thank our sponsors,
for their support and generosity. McGovern Auto Group, Teamsters Local 653, Woodward's Auto Spring Shop, Madison Food Group, Sign Design, Everett Auto Parts, Evans Machine Company, Torian Associates Real Estate, Everett's Auto Parts, and Copeland Auto Group.
Terry. Terry.
Before they used to stand here. I'm like, get out of the way.
Yeah, there's something over there that I've been driving tonight, the last few nights.
yeah okay yeah
Oh, really? Yeah. Oh, I'm bad. I didn't know. That was a lot.
This is the only Friday night game. All the other games are Saturday afternoon. I think they're just afraid of the problems that happen on Friday nights. Eventually we'll get the huge wave of marijuana.
From the kids beeping. Happens every year.
Mexico.
I have no idea.
They usually put up a good fight. Brockton's having a hard time scoring.
Ladies and gentlemen,
We ask that you bring your attention to midfield as we begin our pregame ceremony. Last summer, our community lost Makai and Terry Boston in a tragic accident.
The Boston brothers exemplify what it meant to be a Brockton boxer. They were dedicated, hardworking, driven, talented, and boxer tough. They also had smiles that could light up a room, even on the darkest of days. As we gather here tonight, we want to let the Boston family know that Makai and Terry will never be forgotten.
They will be in our hearts forever. Even though their time with us was cut short, we are grateful to have been their teammates, friends, teachers, and coaches. It is our honor to give the Boston family jersey number 75 as we celebrate the lives of Makai and Terry. God bless.
At this time, we ask that you please rise, remove your hats, and direct your attention to the flag as we honor America with the playing of our national anthem by the Brockton High School Marching Band.
I'm sorry.
you
Welcome, ladies and gentlemen, to Rocky Marciano Stadium in the campus of Brockton High School. Tonight, 2024, Brockton Community Access to the Brockton Channels. Opening game for us on the air. The Boxers take on the Lincoln-Subbury Warriors. Leo Genitasio, along with the Brockton legend, Orlando Galvao. Orlando, the Boxers come in tonight, 0-2.
And most people, we've talked about this earlier in the season, they had that opening game at Bounstable where they came in, it looked like they had the game won, they had to take a couple knees, they threw the football, they lost. A lot of people around the city talking about the game.
They came back the next week against Franklin. Unfortunately, after the first half, Brockton kind of fell apart in the second half and Franklin ran away with the game. What have you seen early from the Boxers? Well, two things that have stuck out early in the season are obviously what you just said, decision making and a lot of penalties.
Brockton 10 penalties about 10 penalties the first game 10 penalties The second game including touchdowns called back you can't win that you can't win football games that way right and then I'm going back to the first game right you take three knees you get out of Bonstable with a victory and they elected to pass possible ran it back to our 18 and was able to cash in like good teams do and Give Brockton a heartbreaking loss in that first game, and I'm did it go on to the second game where? It might have lingered
We're going to take a short break here and go on to the field.
Hate to see that. As the captains go over the flipping of the coin, going into Lincoln-Subury, they come into the season 0-2. How have they fared early in the season, Orlando, against the competition they faced? Well, they played two tough teams and, you know,
They've both been blogs, but let's go back to the two two meetings against Brockton the Lincoln suburb, right? two years ago Brockton had a big lead and Lincoln Sudbury came crashing back and Almost pulled that game off Brockton won an overtime, correct? I believe they did go on overtime or it would I know Lincoln Sudbury made a game of it last year overtime
Brockton took him into overtime, so I expect nothing but another close game, and obviously Brockton is playing with emotion tonight, right? Their first game of the year, they're back here in Brockton, they're 0-2, and they're probably playing for their brother, Makai Boston. So let's go over the Lincoln-Subbury starters. On offense, their best player, their all-around player, Shavon Harris, a wide receiver junior, running back will be Matt Tasker, a junior.
Ryan Gallagher, a junior, a wide receiver. Ryan Cushin, the wide receiver, a junior. Also another good all-around athlete, Dom Tocanto, a wide receiver. Sean Landry, one of the other running backs they go to. Their offensive line, a mixture of three seniors and two juniors. Kevin Aber at right guard. Adam Ferreira at left guard. Emmitt Dolan at center. Ethan Gordon at left tackle. Max Krauser, the big right tackle, also a senior.
Before we go further, let's not forget also Terry Boston. The younger brother, just about to be a part of the football program. Again, just a tragedy. They were wonderful kids and a nice thing by the whole Brockton community to honor the boys tonight. The Boxers Orlando come in, scoring two touchdowns early in the season. They have a young quarterback.
They have all-purpose running back Luke Turco. What are we looking at offensively for the Boxers? It's funny because Brockton has scored in their first possessions of each game and then haven't been able to score the rest of the game. So the first drives of the game has been good, but going further, you know, a lot of penalties. And so we're looking for the same. Luke Turco to get the ball a lot. It goes around him. So the Boxers have won the toss. They deferred. They'll be kicking off to the south end of the end zone.
The boxer kicker tonight will be number 16.
and that is Daniel DaSilva. And the ball goes deep to about the 10 yard line where Lincoln Subway will return it. He's got a little space. He has some room and he cuts up over the field. He cuts back and he has a lot of open space there. It's a terrific return and they will cash it in about the box of 38 yard line. A couple of missed tackles there, Orlando. Yeah, just like last week, this time Brockton able to catch him, avoiding the return, but not a good start for Brockton here at Rocky Marciano Stadium.
So Lincoln Submarine comes out. The Boxers will have to make a big stand early in this football game in their own side. The quarterback for Lincoln Submarine will be number 15, Sean Landry. The Boxers look like they're coming out in that 43 defense with two safeties back with Luke Turco and Jared Mighty.
possible osculastic safety back there. Yeah, I talked to the Lincoln-Subbury coach, Justin McKay, very young team this year for Lincoln-Subbury. So Landry gets the ball and the pistol and we get a penalty right away that might be an illegal procedure. So Lincoln-Subbury's gonna go back five yards. Well, after a good return, you don't wanna start offensive series that way.
I'm gonna back you up five yards here. So that will put the ball back to the 43 for a first and 15. And we talked about the Brockton secondary. One of the better safety tandems in the state in Luke Turkle and Jared Michaels. Luke Turkle, very special. Give me some Luke Turkle. And I'm pretty sure I'm gonna be saying that a lot tonight. Brockton returns a lot of veterans on defense, including Jaden Lopes-Ribeiro, a corner. Karens Antoine, a corner. Ahmad Wiggins in the middle.
So in the pistol they remain, first and 15. I do not see Ahmad Wiggins out there right now.
So it's an inside handoff, a little bit of space, and Brockton closes that up pretty well for a modest two yard game. Yeah, we gotta get a update on that. I do not see him, I know Ahmad went limping off the field last week against Franklin, and I do not see him out there right now. I see number five. That was the senior Jalen Jackson, a three year starter on the tackle, with a little help from number 88 for the boxers, Nathan Jean-Philippe, the senior defensive end.
So at second in vote, 13, Lincoln-Subber remains in the pistol with one back next to the QB. Same play, hand off and there's nothing going there. Terrific standby boxes.
and the tackle by number 70 for Brockton, who's in the backfield, Jaden Seal, the senior. Running back gets the ball, boxer right in his face to take him down, and two plays, and Lincoln Sudbury going backwards. Jaden Seal, unfortunately, was injured last year, but Brockton expects him to be one of their better two-way linemen. He's very athletic, got good feet. So about third and 16 with the loss of two. Let's see what Lincoln Sudbury has here. They have athleticism at the wide receiver position.
I just gotta report my Wiggins not playing tonight. So the quarterback will remain in the pistol. He comes back. He looks. He's got a man over the middle. It's a terrific throw and it's intercepted. That's Karens Antoine on the tip. He cuts it back. He has room on the right side. He's going backwards and he will go down. So an unspeakable start for Lincoln Sudbury on offense. The tip drill. Antoine ready for it.
able to get to interception and Brockton takes it over. Great play. So the boxers will come out on offense and what do we think of this young quarterback so far this year? Cimetto, man, I like this. I think his future is bright. Obviously there's going to be some learning curves. So baby steps and we'll see what happens tonight. But I do like Mr. Cimetto. Casey Rhodes, the junior, will be in the backfield next to him with the three wide receivers, two to the left.
Samedo gets the naming ball, goes to Rhodes. Rhodes has a little room, nice cut up inside for a modest three yard gain. Yeah, Rhodes is a little shifty there. He likes to do that. You think he's gonna go right and he slashes it in real quick and picks up about four yards. Good vision right there as Brockton's gonna move fast. K.C. Rhodes remains in the backfield. Two receivers to the right of Samedo this time, one to the left. Lopes-Ribera, I think one would be Jayden Wooten.
Samedo back to pass, the ball goes again and he's got nothing there. And he goes down and that will be a loss or two. And we're looking at a third down and eight as a good penetration right there by the linebacker from 51. Yeah that's Devon Harrison, our coach mentioned him at the beginning of the game. Linebacker, go both ways, very special player. Coach really high on him. And Kevin Abad was in there also, number 51.
Good looking middle linebacker. So the Boxers will have third and eight at their own 29 yard line. They're gonna go three rides of receivers to the left of Samedo, and the lone back will be Casey Rhodes again. Lincoln Subber remains in that 44 front with no real safety on the board. So it's gonna be a hitch pass. It goes over to number one. He's got a little room, he's got space, and that's gonna be a first down. Good job, Lopes. Way to follow your blocks. Cut it inside.
picked up about 13 yards and that's good for a Brockton first down. Nice cut by Jadon Los Ribeiro, didn't panic, saw the space, took it and got the first down. So the boxers are gonna move fast with double receivers to both sides. The ball goes to Casey Rhodes and once again, he breaks a tackle.
Yeah, that play's gonna look like it's taken long to develop, snap included, and then that's able to give the linemen a chance to get Rhodes there. Kevin Hebert once again in the backfield, real athletic linebacker, and the Brockton offensive line's gonna have to make some adjustments there. They're massive up front this year. Play callin' comin' in by Coach Barrows.
and we'll see two wide receivers to the left with the H back, Luke Turco in the game. Semedo again in the pistol, and the ball's gonna go right to Turco. Turco tries to get outside, there's not a lot of room over there, he cuts it up inside, and he gains about four yards, and nice game tackling by Lincoln Sudbury. Yeah, Luke Turco should've been tackled in the back for a loss, but that's what he does, he never loses yards, he's always going forward.
So that was a direct snap to Turco, Samedo had his hands in there, maybe it slowed the play down a half a second, which allowed Lincoln Sudbury to get in on the ball. So the Boxers will be looking at a third and seven, the last time a third and long they converted on a screen pass to Lopes Ribeiro. So we'll see number four for the Boxers, Jadon Wooten the senior, along with Lopes Ribeiro, and I believe that is number two Antoine Haught.
Very interesting play, the last play, I don't know. So, that's gonna be a misplay, I don't think. Yeah, he wasn't ready for the ball. Was not ready for the ball, again. And he didn't panic though, Semedo, he gained three yards on the play. I've seen that a lot with the snapper and the quarterback, not on the same page, three games into the season. Brockton faces a big decision here at midfield, and it looks like they're saying stay out there.
So fourth and four, the Boxers keep the offense on the field. We're under seven minutes in the first quarter of a scoreless game. Rocky Marciano Stadium, Leo Genitasio, along with the legend, Orlando Galvao. Yeah, let's not forget Sylvia's first home game as a Brockton Boxer. Shout out to him. So, Boxers will go for it. The snap, he's got a little bit of time, a little bit of space. He looks over, that's a tough play.
and that's just a difficult throw to make. I think they were looking for something easier over the middle, but Lincoln-Subbury defended it well, and Brockton's gonna give the ball back at midfield to Lincoln-Subbury. Yeah, you look at that, they're looking for a pass and finish. That's just a great play by the Lincoln-Subbury defender, and like you said, Leo, that had no chance. So after the interceptions, the Boxers gained one first down, and the ball's turned over and down to about the box of 49 yard line. Lincoln-Subbury will send back out their offense.
as the box's defense was really physical in that first drive, didn't allow much on the ground and intercepted the ball. The Conservative starts again in a great field position across the 50 yard line.
Sean Landry remains in the pistol. He's got three receivers to the right and the lone back. And the pitch goes, he has a little bit of space over there. A good run, that's gonna gain about four yards before the game tackle over to the right there, led by Luke Turco. Yeah, early in the year, that play, defensively, as Brockton has not adjusted to that sweep play. It's giving him trouble. It's giving him trouble, and it's that exact direction that teams keep on running on Brockton, and they gain about five yards.
So we'll go second and about five, maybe a short six. As the boxers remain in that, look like they're 44 front. As Landrieu remained the pistol with two receivers to his right, one to his left, one back with an H back.
Here's a snap, and they're gonna run it again, he has more space to the right, he's gonna get outside, he's gonna gain a first down. Same place, we got a flag here, that's gonna be a hold in, that's gonna come back. So there was some space on the same side there for the eight yard run, but it looks like it's gonna be called back with a hold, we'll wait for the call, it came from the field judge in the back. Yeah, that's a clear hold, I saw that as it developed, so that will cost Lincoln Sudbury 10 yards.
So that will take the first down away from the Warriors and move them back 10 yards. It will be the ball was marked right around the first down marker. So we're looking at about a second and nine as Lincoln-Suburys found something over there, it landed on their right side, running at the Boxers. That's the side I was talking about and until you stop it, teams are gonna keep going that direction. We're at five minutes, 24 seconds of the first quarter, scoreless.
big, good crowd here in Brockton tonight. What a beautiful night as well. Sean Landry remains in the pistol. He's got trips to the right, trips to the left, one to the right with a single back. He's down, he's back, he looks, he's got space over there, it's a great throw. And a catch for a first down. He's gonna gain about 10 yards for the first down. And it was a quick tackle there by Turco. As it was a nice precision play.
throwing to a spot, and they'll get a first down around the Boxer, 36 yard line. Yeah, DeCanto with a good route, good catch, took the hit, great pass, and they move the sticks. So Lincoln Sudbury, deep inside the Boxer's territory here. They remain in the pistol, two to the right, one to the left, H back, and one back.
Here's the snap and it's gonna be a handoff. There's not a lot of room there. It's a good run, he kept moving his legs. Looks like they're gonna gain six. Looked like they had him in the backfield, Lando. Right near him. He just kept on pushing and pushing. Good gain there on first down. So second and five around the 31 yard line as Lincoln Subberry continues to drive.
Box is missing Ahmad Wiggins, a three-year starter at linebacker. That's a huge loss. We're seeing Ty Baker, the senior in the middle, along with number five, Jordan DiPina, the senior. So from the pistol.
second and a long four, there's the run, he's got a little bit of space, he's got space, that's a big tackle right there. So he was about to break that tackle, Luke comes up from the safety position and wraps him up, great form tackling for really no gain.
Luke Turco's like a safety and a linebacker all at once. Orlando, there's not a lot of safeties in the state better than him. He's a really terrific football player. I talked to his father, Greg, before the game. He was looking at Fordham. Any school that gets Luke at a safety position is gonna have himself a real football player. That is very, very true. I've had a lot of people that said the same thing. They love Luke Turco. So third and four from the 31. So Brockton jumps and they're gonna give him a free first down.
We talked about it before the game, just penalties. It's just not good enough. I'm sure it's gonna drive Coach, it drove Coach Jermaine Wiggins crazy last year. You can't win football games with nine, 10 penalties a game. It's the first one tonight. So the Warriors get a first down around the 26 yard line, as Brockton forced a third down. You can't make it easy for your opponents, because it's gonna make it harder for you.
So let's see, they remain in that pistol. They've just been flip-flopping the receivers from each one side to another. They got three to the left, one to the right, one to the H-back, and we're gonna get a timeout. So again, this is Leo Genitasio, along with the legend Orlando Galvao, Brockton Community Access. You can catch us on the Brockton channels. Of course, we got Mike the Postman Simmons on the production, Curtis Reese, and Scott Labossiere on the cameras and production.
We got our new camera here, our new monitor here, Orlando. Can't beat this. Feel like I'm in the ESPN. Feel like we're doing a big time game. So again, a great crowd here tonight at Marciano Stadium. The boxer side almost full. Here to root on the 2024 boxers. Defensive coordinator John Shelby.
I'm sure talking about gap discipline, tackling, stuff that all defensive coordinators, you know, talk about with their linebackers and ends. Don't try to do too much, do your job. So Lincoln Submarine comes right up for the time out to the line of scrimmage. They are gonna, looks like they're under center for the first time tonight. Well one back and looks like an H back and a tight end to the right.
There's a man in motion, there's the box. There's a lot, a little bit of room there, and he'll gain a modest three yards, as it was a good push from the left side right there of Lincoln Sudbury, and a tackle from the boxers. Looked like it was Ty Baker, and we got an injury for Lincoln Sudbury. That's unfortunate. Maybe it's just a cramp, hopefully. And that's number one. That looks like it's number 52.
And that's Adam Ferreira, one of their captains in left guard. And he scores on the out of town docket tonight, Orlando. I was looking at the Everett BC High. BC High's up 32 to seven at half. I know they can't be happy up there in E country. We talk about Brockton football tradition, Everett.
over the last 30 years has been everything Brockton was before Everett came in, so. Well, Brockton plays Everett this year, so it's the battle of the one and two programs historically. That should be a good one no matter what. Who's one and who's two, Orlando? It depends who you ask. It depends on where you are. In Everett, Everett's number one. You ask people in Brockton, Brockton's gonna say two, but if you ask a neutral person, they'll probably say Everett.
I don't agree with you. That's an argument for another day. So, we're looking at Farada down. Brockton has time to go over the sidelines and talk over what they're gonna do defensively.
Again, the blockers come in tonight 0-2. Coach Jilson Silver, a young coach, his first year as a head coach. He's actually never been a coordinator before, but he's been around Brockton football. He played here. I have my son play for him on the freshman team. He's a disciplinarian coach. He doesn't put up with a lot of stuff. I think he's exactly what Brockton needs. He's surrounded himself with guys he trusts, guys that play Brockton football, and we're not gonna judge him on two games, obviously.
Midfield decision. It's a gutsy call. It's a gutsy call, but you know. Sometimes, yeah. I mean, he's a young coach. I'm sure he learned his lesson after the basketball game that you're never gonna throw again in a knee situation. There's times in a football game where he's gonna be challenged to make decisions.
He wanted to be aggressive early in the game, put a little confidence in his young quarterback. So we're at about second and seven from the 23 yard line of Brockton, Lincoln-Subbury in a 0-0 game in the pistol. The snap, and there's a little bit of room to the outside, Brockton trying to close that. And that is closed down really fast.
saying I had enough of that. They're trying to go again, sweep right, and this time Brockton was able to make the play. DePener along with Jared Mighty, the junior safety, who's getting a ton of college looks right now, not only for football, for track. Terrific student, football player, Brockton's lucky to have him. So a loss of five there will make it third and about 11 from the 27 yard line. The last,
Third and long, Everett Lincoln-Subbury completed on a pass. So Landry, from the pistol, he has a little bit of time, time, he looks, he looks over the middle, he has a man open, and that's gonna be a touchdown. A terrific throw. Terrific throw, terrific route, and I don't know about the defensively. Well we talked about this last year, Karens Antoine peeking in the backfield.
He got beat by two steps, and Landry put it right where it was supposed to be, and Lincoln Sudbury on a third and long completes the pass for a six-nothing lead, and they'll send in their kicker to make it seven-nothing at around the one-minute mark of the first quarter. That's just a pitch and catch, simple. I mean, as a cornerback, you have to cover that. We're watching it right here, Orlando.
It just looked like he had him at the line of scrimmage, and as the wide receiver made his move, he peeked a little bit in the backfield to see where the play was going, and he went right by him. So here's the extra point attempt, and the kick is gonna be good. So at the 138 mark, here at Rocky Marciano Stadium, Lincoln-Subbury 7, the Brockton Box is 0. Again, the energy level, I don't feel like it's there yet. And you figure in a game of this magnitude,
Rockford would be more up for so far, I mean we're still early. Well it's something we talked about last year with Coach Wiggins, but he had a young team. This team returns a ton of seniors this year that played a lot of football the past two seasons. There's a little mixture. Really no excuse of not being up for games. Little mixture of young and a lot of seniors, but they do have a lot of young players out there too.
So back deep for the Boxers, we'll see Kasey Rhodes. God, that was just a great play. Great throw by the quarterback Landry. Kasey Rhodes will be back deep along with, that looks like number two for the Boxers, Antoine Hart. Alon Hart, I'm sorry. And. Looks like Rhodes is back to ya.
Ladini-Balouse is back there too. So here's the kick for number five from Lincoln-Selberry. Seems like Lincoln-Selberry has had the ball the entire quarter. That's Marcus Cassell, the senior, kicker. And that's a great boot. That's gonna take him all the way back to, and he's gonna take an ace. So that's a good kick. You don't see that in high school, Robert, it goes all the way to the end zone. And Broxton will get their second possession of the day.
The first one, they got a first down on a third and seven pass to the senior receiver. When you're 0-2, you just can't give teams good field positions. Brogdon has done that in two consecutive series. You just can't do that. That's why I was very iffy about going for it at midfield instead of just maybe kicking it away, pinning him, and go from there. But it is what it is. So Samedo will start out.
In the pistol, two right receivers left with Luke Turco in the backfield. First and 10 at their own 20. The snap and Turco has space. He busts it up inside and he keeps those legs moving for about a three yard gain. As Lincoln Sudbury is giving up a ton of size on the defensive line, but they're just getting in the backfield. Sure don't look like it. You can't tell who's the bigger of the two right now. So Luke Turco gains about three there.
and we'll go second and seven. About the 24 yard line, 23 and a half. Semedo will go into the pistol along with Turco. Two receivers to the right again, one to the left. The snap, and the ball's gonna go to Mighty, Jared Mighty, and a sweep, and he has a little bit of room, and he uses that electric speed to gain about 12 yards. Yeah, once he turns the corner, that speed
Very fast kid, able to get the first down. I believe he was the 400 meter champion in the state, or 200 in the indoors. Just visited Army for track recently. So the Boxers at a first down at around their 32. The snap, the ball's gonna go to Turco. Turco busts it up the middle. And that's gonna be tackled, a game tackle, and we've said his name a bunch of times tonight. That's gonna be number 51, Kevin Abar. Good game by Luke Turco there.
Looks like about maybe four or five. So a game for five by Turco, and Casey Rhodes comes in. And Brockton looking over to head offensive coordinator Derrick Barrows for the call. Semedo talking to his offensive line. Brockton has quads out there, two to each side as the receivers. There's a snap. The ball's gonna go to Rhodes. Oh, it's a keeper, nice play fake. Semedo's got room, and he fumbled the ball.
So he had the first down, he looked like he was extending the ball instead of protecting it, and an uncostly turnover. A costly turnover for the Boxers, and they will give the ball to Lincoln Sudbury at the 45 after a good play call. But Cimino's gotta protect the football. Yeah Brockton turnovers though hasn't really been an issue this year.
If I'm not mistaken, that might have been the first turnover for Brockton for the year, but again, Lincoln Sudbury starts in Brockton side of the field to begin another possession, third straight. So we're at 13 seconds of the first quarter. Lincoln Sudbury leads the Brockton Boxers 7-0. Seeing the replay there, the ball just fumbled away. Sophomore wasn't able to corral it.
So Sean Landry remains in the pistol. The H back is in motion. The ball he missed, looks like it's a missed assignment there and an easy tackle for, is that Ty Baker? It is gonna be Ty Baker. So that will be the last play of the first quarter as we'll enter the end of it here and we're gonna head over to the second quarter with Lincoln Sudbury leaving seven to zero. Not the start we were looking for.
Again, Lincoln Sudbury in Brockton's territory to start all three possessions. Seems kind of flat, I mean, that's how I look at it. The thing that concerns me, Orlando, is you don't mind losing. I don't like it when the teams come in here and they're more physical than you. Right now it looks like Lincoln Sudbury's just being more physical than Brockton. So Coach Silver.
Coach John Shelby, one of the best linebackers in Brockton history, as far as I'm concerned, the best player in the state when he was here. He will coach the defense and I'm sure that's something he talks about with these kids every day at practice. Physical, physical, physical. Out of town scores, we got Nadick leading Milford 14 to seven, that's a big game.
So Lincoln Subway is going to go right to the line of scrimmage. They're at the 45 yard line of Brockton. They're looking at a second and nine. They have three receivers to the right, one to the left, one back next to Landry.
There's the snap, he has room, it's gonna be a screen pass, number 21, that ball might have been a lateral, but they're gonna call it incomplete, so a fortunate play for the Boxers that he dropped out of here, a little bit of space. And we're gonna look at about a third and nine, the second straight series for a third and nine, the last time they scored on a long touchdown pass. So Brockton looking to get the stop here. Yeah, that was a drop, it wouldn't went nowhere anyways, Brockton was right there, they read that very well.
So Landry talks to the coach and he is, they're huddling here. So third and nine, let's see what they do here. They have four receivers once again with one back. And they're to both sides. Got back, he's got back. It's gonna be a quarterback. Keepey's gonna try to get to the outside. He looks, he looks. He's got a man wide open. It's just a broken play right there and it looks like he's gonna score a touchdown on that.
So that was a broken play, Orlando, where the Brockton corner came up to stop the run and he left his man. Yeah, completely ugly. Third and long, that is unacceptable. So. Again, again, you give teams a good field position, it's easier, you know. We're looking at here, Shawn Landry broke the pocket, looked like it was gonna be a design keeper, but the Brockton corner came up to stop him and
You know, it's just an easy pitch and catch. It was known within 15 yards of him at the end of that, and that's again what we talked about, just fundamental football. Yeah, you got a young team like Lincoln Sudbury coming in here right now and just controlling just about everything. This is not good. So there's the point after, and that will be 14-nothing at the 11 minute mark of the second quarter. Not a good start, Leo.
Well there's a lot of football left and it's going to be some tough times early in the season for a young coaching staff.
And I'm looking at the score, 14 and nothing. And I'm also looking at Brockton has only scored 14 points total this year in two games. And then you look at the sideline. No emotion right now. Everybody's head is down and it's almost like we're in the fourth quarter and the other team's about to take a knee and we're about to go shake hands out there, man. This can't happen, Leo.
So the Boxers will send back the same threesome with Casey Rhodes. Alonhart and it looks like Jared Mighty. Lincoln Sudbury kicker will be number five, Marcus Cassell. Got a good leg. That's another terrific kick.
and that ball will go into the end zone for a touch back and the Boxers will take over for the first time this second quarter. You know you don't want to be in a field goal battle with Lincoln Sudbury, I'll tell you that. No you don't. Wow, that kid can kick.
So the Boxers, let's see what Coach Barros, the young offensive coordinator, has right here. He's had some nice plays. I think he's been pretty creative this year. They just haven't executed at times. There's been plays to be made, and sometimes it's up to the kids just to make a play. Coaches can't go out there and do it for them. So the Boxers look like they're gonna bring out the senior fullback, Christian Flaherty, with Luke Turco behind him, and they're gonna try to play smash-mouth football.
Got a good game out of town, Mansfield and Marshfield. Mansfield's up three nothing early. So Semedo was under center. And that's another fumble. He just came out too early. So Brockton will lose three yards right there as Semedo pulled out a little bit too quick. Yeah, that's two fumbles in a row by Semedo and Brockton's gonna call a timeout here. Young quarterback, like, you know. Well, when you got a sophomore quarterback,
you're gonna have to deal with some growing pains. He showed a lot of promise in the early season in the scrimmage games against good teams. So we're not gonna get too down on him, but he's only a sophomore. So Coach Silva's gonna talk to the team. Brockton down 14-nothing. Leo Genitasio along with the legend, you know him all over the city, Orlando Galveo. Mike the Postman Simmons on the production, along with Curtis Reese.
and Scott Labossiere. I'm not gonna forget you, Scott. So that's a good time out there by Silva. So it's gonna be about second and 12 for the Boxers. They'll remain in the straight I. Yeah, it's predictable though. A lot of teams will say that you're gonna run the ball here, right?
Well, they give it to Turco. He's got space, he gets up the middle, and it's a really good game. It's about seven yards, and that's what they wanted on first down. So Brockton's gonna be at about third and about five right here. There was some room there. Brockton opened up the hole.
and they're gonna go fast, they're gonna remain in the eye with two receivers and a tight end, Christian Flaherty the fullback. And the ball's gonna go to Turco, Brock didn't move there, that would look like a first down, but the wide receiver on the right side looked like he moved too quick. It's gonna be an offsides I think, Leo. Or too many men on the field, I think that is gone. Looked like the receiver moved also, let's see what the referees call.
So Brockton's got a break there even though Luke Turco had the first down. They'll add five yards on to the play as the Boxers will get a first down and going into that I right there, there's been some space. Brockton might want to decline that because I think they picked up six. I think, did they change the rule where they add five yards on and penalties like that to the end of the play?
I don't believe so, I think that's only on holdings and stuff like that. I think Brockton might want to decline this, they picked up six yards. So looks like the Boxers do decline it, and they'll get a first down at about the 32 yard line. As they look like they'll remain in that I formation.
And by the way, when I say predictable, what I mean is you gotta give the ball to Lou Turco. You wanna give the ball to Lou Turco, that's what I mean. We won tons of state championships in this offense. It's predictable, but it's tough to stop if you execute it. For the record, that's what I mean by predictable, because you have to feed this guy right here. So the ball will go to Turco. Turco bounces out inside. He gains yards, he gains more yards, and he gains 10 yards. He bounces off three or four tackles for a first down.
That timeout might have been more about give the ball to Mr. Luke Turco, right? So, not a first down, it looked like he came to eat. As Brockton is right around the 10 minute mark of the second quarter, down 14-nothing, they'll remain in the eye with Luke Turco and Christian Flaherty. Good time here for a play action. And the ball will go to Flaherty, Flaherty moves those legs and it looks like he has enough for the first down, and he does.
So the senior fullback, driving his legs forward, gets Brockton, they're back, their second first down of the drive. And Brockton around their own 45 yard line. No change to the formation, they remain in the I. Lincoln-Surrey bears about everyone in the box right here. The snap.
and the ball will go to Turco. Brockton looking, Turco bounce to the outside, he bounce to the inside. Inside, outside, moving his legs. That's just a nice move by Luke Turco. The tackler thought he had him, Luke juked him, was able to get more yards than that. And wow, they're relying strictly on Luke Turco, I believe he asked to come out, Leo. So Luke will go out for a rest, KC Rhodes comes in. That's three first downs in a row, Brockton will remain in the eye, the junior running back giving Luke a breath.
Christian Flaherty, the senior fullback, remains with him. There's a snap, and the ball will go to Rhodes. He moves his legs, and he gains about four yards. I'm surprised Brockton is not trying to do some kind of play action here. You know, set up that run, let the run set up the pass, and kind of take a shot with Lopes.
Sajai Taylor is now in the backfield. Just a sophomore running back. He'll get set his first carry of the game. As Brockton remains at about a second and seven, and the ball goes to the sophomore back, and he hits that, he hit that hole fast, Orlando. Nice run by the sophomore.
I don't know if that was Rhodes that time. That was a 30. Sajai Tyler, that's gonna be a sophomore. Rhodes got a break. So Brockton uses the third back of the drive here. And the sophomore will remain in there. He hit that whole fast. That's a good run. So third down and about two at the 35 of Lincoln Sudbury. And the ball goes right back to him. And he has met, he keeps the legs moving.
and that will gain about a yard. And we might- Yeah, that's gonna get a 15-yard penalty. And that's gonna be on 51 from Lincoln Sudbury. He's been their best player on defense tonight, but that was just a little bit too much. Yeah, that's a little bit too much. I mean, the whistle clearly blew. Kevin Aviar, the senior. You know, and you just can't do that. We've seen Brockton do that the last couple of weeks, and now we see the opponent giving Brockton yards. So that weighed 15 yards to the player. Instead of fourth down and one, Brockton will have a first down.
around the 20-yard line as they enter the red zone. Some place they haven't been a ton this season. Let's see what Coach Barros does here. Brockton's remained in the eye this drive, and they've moved the ball well. But Lincoln Subway has just about everyone in the box. Brockton's gotta punch this in. Jayden Los Ribeiro to the right has man coverage. And the ball will go to the sophomore. He cuts it inside, a nice run. Keeps his legs moving, good vision.
Again, that's what Rhodes does. He looks like he's gonna go outside, then he cuts in. It's a great run. Picked up about five. All runs right now for Brockton. So Casey Rhodes and Brockton getting a lot of help from their sophomore and junior backs here. Both of them moving their legs with good vision. Nice run by Casey Rhodes right there.
using his blockers, getting into space, and lunging forward. So a five yards will give the Boxers second and five at the 15 yard line, their deepest penetration of the night. They remain in the I. And the ball goes to Casey Rhodes, bouncing up inside. He has space, another good move. And he will gain about four. He's gonna be just short, probably about inches. He's gonna set up a good...
He made a man miss there. He was about to get tackled for a loss, and Casey Rhodes used good vision, good footwork, to make a linebacker miss. So we're looking at about third and two from around the 11, and we'll see Luke Turco in the game. He's been battling a shoulder injury this week, that's why he's not in there every other down. And the ball goes to the fullback, but they knew that was coming. They knew that was coming. So they try to be cute there with the fullback,
and Lincoln Sudbury ate that up. So fourth down and one. I understand that play call for fourth and inches, but I don't get that. So they lose two yards there. So Brockton will have. Gotta get the ball to Turkle. Brockton will be in the eye with Luke Turkle, Jayden Los Ribeiro to the right. Big play, biggest play of the game for Brockton so far. We're right around the six minute mark of the second quarter.
There's a snap, the ball's gonna go to Turco. Inside, he tries to bounce it up. Oh, and that's good visual by Luke. Because he was stopped in the backfield. Keeps the legs moving, and he gains a first down. Yeah, that's all Luke Turco right there. He should've been got. Lincoln Sudbury shooting gaps, they're getting guys into the backfield. The blocks of backs are making people miss. Yeah, this is why you can't mess around him. I'm not saying give him the ball all the time, but. So first and goal for the Boxers at about the eight, and Lincoln Sudbury will call a timeout.
I'm not saying give him the ball all the time, but give him the ball all the time. Well, we've seen for the last two years, when he gets the ball, he averages about seven yards a run. So Luke is effective. The difference is, Orlando, like other Brockton backs, had to play one way. Luke's also the leading tackler on the team. He needs a break. He's a physical running back. He's beat up a little bit. It's a long football season. Coach Silva, Coach Barros know what they have in them. They don't want to lose them.
Again, I don't know how much faith they have in Cimetto, but I would like a play, to keep the defense, I would like a play action off that. Just to let them know, we have that arsenal too. You saw him during the scrimmage game, does he throw the ball? I think he can, he's more than capable of throwing the ball. He can make a seven yard pass. I mean, you gotta have some plays out there where you can have space and where you can just get seven yards. It's just like a run, right?
So the Boxers will get some extra time here to talk about the next few plays as they try to cut into this Lincoln-Subbury lead. They'll get the ball in the second half as they deferred. So this is huge for the Boxers to try to get in the end zone here. Henry Hankmore's the center, the senior. And it's a big game out of town today. Zavarian and Springfield Central. And I just got an update on that. 13 and nothing, Zavarian. 55 yard touchdown run by Boost.
Boosa for Severin. Springfield's finding out they're not playing Western Massachusetts anymore. So they're gonna remain in the eye here.
Luke Turk goes to back, the ball's gonna go to him. He looks for inside, looks and there's not much room there. Look at some areas, they are sending everyone in. They're shooting gaps. They may have to because there's not a lot of space there. A little slant there, I mean you just, you gotta keep that defense honest there. You gained about a yard there as the Boxers will go second and goal from about the five. Samedo's working fast.
Gets the ball, and the ball's gonna go to Turkle again. He tries to bounce it to the outside, and he doesn't gain much. So we're gonna go third and goal from about the four yard line, as the boxers work to the left side that time after going to the right a few times. Good game by Luke. So now you got two possessions, two downs, sorry, to get five yards.
They really haven't gained much these first two downs. Like you said, Lincoln Sudbury lost Kevin Abia, their linebacker, but their backups have come in and done a nice job. So the boxers remain in the eye. One wide receiver to the right, one to the left. Everybody pinched in for Lincoln Sudbury right now. Everybody's in the box except for the two corners.
And there it is, there's the play you're looking for. It's a screen, oh, it hit him in the hands, he's gotta catch it. So that's a nice throw, and the ball is dropped by the receiver. Yeah, it should've been caught right in his hands. Maybe a little bit to the side, but if it hits you in the hands, you should catch it. That ball's gotta get caught. So it's a nice throw, so the boxers gonna go fourth and goal. That ball hit the senior receiver in the hands, and I think Brockton might be kicking the ball here. So the boxers just wanna, it's a good drive, you wanna put points up in the board.
Broxton's got a very good field goal kick as well. So I like the call here from Coach Silver. You don't wanna have a long drive like that and come away with nothing. The sophomore quarterback put the ball where it was supposed to right there and simply was not caught. Maybe if it was two yards, but five, six yards, maybe a little bit too much. It's a kick and that ball is blocked.
So unfortunately after a long 70-yard drive, Brockton will turn the ball over after a blocked field goal attempt, and Lincoln-Subbury will take over the 10-yard line. Still four minutes, five minutes left here, Orlando. Get a stop, use your timeouts. You try to get the ball back and put some points up. Even though it was five yards, three points, don't need three points here, man. You need seven, you need touchdowns. The other teams are scoring touchdowns,
Let's see what Lincoln-Subbery had. They have not done much on the ground. They've taken advantage of the Brockton secondary, especially a cornerback, where the Boxer Corners have, you know, they made a few mistakes tonight. Yeah, a little bit on that too with the block kick. Now you get the ball at the 20 instead of, so if you had gone for it, and you don't get it, you get it at the five yard line. So that's, I was surprised that Brockton didn't go for that. That's a good point, Orlando. So Lincoln-Subbery will come out with a 14-nothing lead.
Senior quarterback Sean Landry with two long touchdown pass tonight, he's been the difference. Another score from the out of town Duxbury up on Franklin, 13 to nothing as well. So the Boxers remain in that 43 front as Lincoln-Subury will be under center. I don't think they're gonna try to do too much here, take some time off the clock. Space up the middle, and it's a good run. The Boxer linebacker missed the tackle, and instead of a two yard game, that's gonna be a six yard game. CM playing Leinster tonight. CM's up 14 to six, first half.
So we're gonna go second and two at the Boxer 28. We are at about the four minute mark of the second quarter. Leo Genitassi along with the legend Orlando Galvao. Brockton Boxer Football 2024, they're down 14-0. Sean Landry remains under center with one back and two H-backs next to him.
The ball's gonna be faked in motion, it's on the center, and Brockton is in the backfield right there. And that's a nice play by number 41. Maybean, sophomore, almost took him apart. It was a great stop. And now with a third down and...
We talked about him a ton last year, another one that should be a good college prospect, a good size, a good student too. Terrific play by the young defensive, sophomore defensive end. Yeah, let's call it how it is too, Leo. Third down in five years, you don't stop here. You need to stop, you need to put the brakes on this. You cannot let them get a first down here. I'm surprised Coach Silver not calling any timeouts. So third and five, look at somebody who'll go to the pistol, they'll go three wide receivers to the left, one to the right, with one back next to the Landry.
There's a snap, he's gonna go back. He's looking to throw, he's looking to throw, and that ball, it's caught. Oh, he dropped it. That was... Right in his hands. Right in his hands. It was there. It was there. The Brockton... Jayden Loserbero looked like he just misplayed the ball. The ball...
Again, it looks like he's peeking in the backfield. Yeah, that's a big drop too, because now Brockton does not have to use a timeout, and Lincoln Sudbury's gonna punt it. So after gaining eight yards on first down, the Brockton defense does exactly what they're supposed to do. They get off the field, and it looks like they'll give the offense the ball back with about the three minutes left of the second quarter. Watch out, Jared Mighty, back deep for Brockton. And it's a kick, it's a good one. Mighty gets the ball. He has room up the middle. He gets to the right side, and it's a nice tackle.
Wow, what a tackle by 15 for Lincoln Sudbury or else he would have had at least 15 more yards. And that's their quarterback Sean Landry making that tackle. So the box is still with great field position. We'll take over at the 45 yard line. They're down 14-0. Let's see what Coach Derrick Barrows has in mind here for Brockton. They have skilled the wide receiver this year with some of the scene receivers along with Jared Mighty.
Casey Rhodes will be the back. Brockton looks like they're gonna go trips to the right. And Luke starts on the sidelines in his big possession. Jayden Wooten looks like he's out there with Lopes Ribeiro, Jared Mighty, and Alon Hart. And it's gonna be his room over there. If he gets to the outside, Mighty shows some of that speed. He gets to the outside, and that's gonna be a nice game of about six yards.
Nice call by Coach Barrows, just getting the ball and space to some of the better athletes. So the Boxers will gain six there, they're at midfield. We're at the three minute mark of the second quarter. Boxers down 14-nothing.
Cimino remains in the pistol, DeLone back, looks like it's Casey Rose, just trips to the right. And Rose looks like he's gonna get the ball, cuts up inside. That's gonna be a hold on Brock, didn't have to do it either. Rose had the first down, that was on the other side. Yeah, it's an easy call, it was indeed a hold. Again, another penalty is gonna bring Brockton back. So Rose had enough to pick up the first down, the box is undisciplined once again. We'll lose 10 yards and that will look like it'll be now
The second and 12 from around the 43 if it's marked off where we think it is. Again, Brockton has an opportunity here to drive score. They get the ball to start the second half. So, Boxers are gonna go back to about their 42. They gotta get to the Lincoln-Subury 46 for a first down.
Samedo looking over at Coach Barrows. Kasey Rhodes is the lone back. They got trips to the left, one to the right. That's Jaden Wooten. Watch out for a deep shot here to Lopes. Second and 13, the Boxers need to make some plays. Samedo's back, back, he's looking, he's looking. Doesn't throw it anyway, just didn't.
Looking for Lopes on a screen. No, the quarterback and the receivers weren't on the same page right now. At all, at all. So he was looking to go deep. Jadon Lopes, Ribeiro was blocking. Now offensively. And that's who he was looking for. Brockton on the passing game offensively right now. They're just, let's call it how it is, they're looking like a mess. They don't look good. So the Boxers will go third and 13. They have the athletes to make big plays. Again, it's early in the season. A lot of football left to be played.
And again, this game, still a lot of football left. Let's see if the Boxers can convert a long one here, third and 13. Stick it in here, boys, come on, still early. Semedo remains in the pistol. The Boxers line up again, they're having trouble getting to where they're supposed to be. Four receivers, two to each side. Semedo back, he's got time, he's got a lot of time. He's looking, he's looking, he throws the ball over the middle, it's into triple coverage.
And it's intercepted. Well, there wasn't anyone open. The routes were all down the field. Lincoln knows he's going to throw the ball. There's really no place to throw it. It's like a punt. Yeah, some medals looking for a late hit. I mean, you're not going to get that. But he felt like he got hit late.
No call. So the Boxers will turn the ball right back over. Lincoln-Subbery has time now. They have decent field position. If they wanna go down and really put like a nail in the coffin to the Boxers here. If they think the Broxers gonna score three touchdowns in the second half when they've only scored two the whole season. If Lincoln-Subbery wants to be aggressive here, they could really, really put Brockton in a tough position tonight. Again, get a first down, you get over midfield and the penalty brings you back. Been the story of the season for Brockton. Very undisciplined at times.
So Sean Landry, the senior, junior quarterback will remain, they're gonna go in the pistol this time with two receivers to the left, one to the right, with one back. Brockton remains in that 43 front with two safeties back.
Landry's gonna look to throw, he has time, he has time, he's gonna look to run, now he has a little bit of room. Brockton comes up, they miss some tackles, and he's gonna gain about 12 yards. It looked like he just outran three linebackers, they took bad angles. Well, you know he can run, man. On the punt, he was the first one down and didn't make the tackle, so. It's bad angles by the Boxer backs there, they had chances to make plays and they just, just bad angles. So first down for Lincoln Sudbury at their own 39.
and they're looking to get more points. That's a bad snap, and they should get him in the backfield, and they do. So a nice tackle there by number 36 from Brockton. Jalen Jackson, the senior, he's been a three-year starter. JJ is a really good football player, terrific kid.
When he's healthy, he makes a difference out there. So Lincoln-Subbury loses three. They're gonna go at about the two minute mark. Brockton not using any timeouts. And you look at the score, but again, the same story, Leo. You see a zero. Offensively, Brockton. It's not good enough, Orlando. Scoring points. So they'll go under center this time with an H back and a back behind him.
Boxers put a bunch of guys in the box, and it's a fake. And they throw the ball over, and he's wide open. Great play call. He snuck out of the backfield, and he was, whoa, he fumbled the ball. Brockton's got it. Wow, that is a break for Brockton, because Lincoln-Subbery had a first down. And again, that's gonna be Jalen Jackson, as Lincoln-Subbery, it was a terrific play call. And what a call too, I mean.
That was a great call, but again, the kid tried to get more yards, and then he lost the ball if he had just gone down. It's hard to do, but a big turnover. So a huge break for the Boxers. They'll get the ball back now, right around the 45-yard line, and a throwing situation here. Let's see what Coach Barrows has this series. Brockton's got the ball down deep two series ago, down to the five-yard line. They were unable to punch it in. They had a field goal blocked.
and they remain down 14 points. Wholesale changes from the sidelines. They're not on the same page. So Coach Barrow sending in. Brockton will be in the pistol with Casey Rhodes, three receivers to the left, one to the right.
Samedo's back, he's back. It's gonna go to Jared Mighty in space. He's got a little bit of room. He makes a cut to the outside and he'll gain seven yards. Good play call, Coach Barrows. Get me athletes, the ball in space. It's time to use Jared Mighty, you gotta use that speed. So a gain of seven, we're about a minute 30 of the second quarter. I'd like to see Brockton quicken up the pace. Now that's a football player, Jared Mighty, no gloves.
The ball's gonna go, Mighty's gonna get the ball in a sweep. He's using that speed, he gets to the outside, he cuts it up, cuts it up back, and Brockton will have, I believe, another penalty. And that penalty's gonna go on number nine for holding, and that will be Rommel Johnson, the senior. He didn't need to do it, he just didn't. Brockton, Mighty had the first down, Rommel Johnson, the hold will send them back.
Well, every big play, there's gonna be a penalty, it looks like. All season. It looks like every big play is gonna be a penalty. All season long. As long as you call it the other side, I don't have a problem with it. Well, Lincoln Suburban's had a bunch of penalties tonight, so these refs have been absolutely 100% fair. So Brockton loses 10 on the play. We'll go second and 13 from their own 42.
but that was old. It was old, it was a penalty. It was old. Didn't need to do it. So Semedo gets the play call from Coach Barrows. There's the snap, he's got time, he looks, he looks, there's a throw over to space and a terrific, nice catch. Mighty. Jared Mighty again.
So that's gonna gain, yeah, that's eight yards. The ball will be at midfield for a third down, about five for the Boxers. The ball went out of bounds. I don't believe they need to use a timeout. Oh, they gotta change the clock. I guess they left the clock going. Yeah, that's a metal, it's pointing at the clock. They might've let it run out. So the ref is adding time to the clock.
I think he's saying 104. 108, they'll add 11 seconds to the play clock, which will help Brockton. There you have the ball at midfield, very third and five. Luke Turco's in the game. Let's see what the boxers have here. They're down around the minute 10 mark. They need big plays here. They're down by 14 points. What a nice screen call to Luke. We have Rommel Johnson and
Lucas Andrade, Jared Mighty to the right with Rommel. Samedo back to pass, he's got time, he looks, he's fading over, and he just has to throw it away. So Orlando, it's third and five in, they're running their receivers 30 yards down the field.
I'd like to see him just throw the ball seven, eight yards like they've had, like they've shown. You just can't go all deep. Like I said, you gotta have some seven yard plays, five yard plays. So the box is, there's a flag on the play, let's see what it is. It's gonna be a legal man downfield, over the line of scrimmage. Looked like it was over the line of scrimmage. So Brockton's gonna have to pump the ball, because it's a loss of downs.
This first half has been very ugly offensively. And we talked about this a lot last year when Coach Jermaine Wiggins was here. He had a young football team, but I saw growth offensively with them right from the start, Orlando. Hopefully we're gonna see that from Brockton starting in the second half here. Gotta make sure of young players and seniors, so sometimes you need games under your belt. So we're gonna get a timeout. We're at a minute of the second half. Leo, I'm gonna tell you something, right?
Lincoln sub recall that time out, okay. It was in Brockton. So again we're here at Rocky Marciano Stadium in the campus of Brockton High School. Leo Genitasio along with the legend Orlando Galvao. We got Mike the Postman, Postman Simmons on the production. Curtis Reach and Scott Labossiere on the cameras.
and video help. I'm a Kai Boston Knight here at the stadium. So the boxers will send Mighty out to punt. I gotta say this, be careful for the fake punt. I mean, Mighty, he gave him the ball last. He's had two fake punts, right? You gotta be careful. He's a threat. Well, teams have been scouting that. You just can't do that every game. Good football teams will scout you and they'll take that away.
So Mighty has it, and he will punt it. And that ball goes off the side of his foot. And Lincoln Sudbury will get terrific field position at about 57 seconds of the second quarter. Other than two big pass plays, Brockton's done a nice job defensively, Orlando. Two breakdowns in the secondary. You look at that kick, and you said maybe you should've just went for it.
Well, if we knew he was gonna shake it off his foot, the answer's yes. But he's actually been a good punter this season. He's had a lot of terrific balls. Yeah, he's done pretty good. It turns out to be a seven-yard punt. Actually, yeah, it doesn't look like a seven-yard punt. It looks like a three-yard punt. So, Lincoln Sudbury will take over at the box of 45. They have a lot of time left to put their nail in the coffin. Well, you don't think it can get
That ball went sideways. Worse, it gets even worse. But again, it's still in this game. Brockton giving a ton of cushion over here to the right side. And he's back to pass, and he's got room, he's gonna take a shot, and he's gonna get, oh that should be intentional grounding too, wasn't it Orlando? No? He was out the pocket, but I don't know if that ball went across the line of scrimmage, but. So your MLA beam was there, along with Jalen Jackson. That, I mean, he's,
That ball did not cross the line of scrimmage at all. He just kind of just tossed it. No one's in the area, nothing. So second and 10 for Lincoln-Sarberry. They're up 14-nothing. As we get ready for the Great Brockton. There it is, there's the call. And I was, there's the call. I mean I was shocked that they didn't call it, but now they discussed it and they're calling it.
I mean, that was a no-brainer. You rolled out the pocket and you just throw it on the ground with no receiver there and it didn't even go past the line of scrimmage. So that will be a loss of downs. Lincoln-Sabre will go second and 15. And that was almost a sack where they lost the ball. I wonder if they'll run the ball again. They don't wanna turn the ball back over. Maybe take one big shot down the field and then get into halftime. I don't think, they thought maybe they were gonna come in and be up 14 to nothing tonight. Well, maybe they did.
So the box is defensively gonna have to make a stop here to keep their offense in the game in the second half. We're at- It's supposed to be second down, right? You lose it down, right? If it's intentional ground, it's a loss of downs. We don't know the exact call. What is going on here? Well, the refs are coming over to talk about it. The ball's right at midfield.
Let's see if Brockton brings in some more safety help and try to not give up the big play. Maybe take a linebacker off the field and put some more speed in the secondary. Should be second down. So it is second down. At midfield, Sean Landry's got two touchdown passes tonight. He's thrown one interception. He's been the difference.
He's in the pistol with one back. Looked like they left early, but there's the throw, he's in space, he's an easy pitch and catch. And that will be a seven yard gain, and we'll go third and eight at the box of 42. You know they gotta kick it with a big leg. Just gonna say that, the scenario can play out where they can be playing for three here. So I'd like to see a little bit tighter coverage there and not give up those easy yards. Let's see if Coach Shelby gets up on them here, uses some of that Brockton athleticism to take away the easy pitch and catch.
I mean, I'm pretty sure they'll take seven, but three with that kicker is probably something that they're looking at. So huge cushions to the right side, Landry's back, he's looking, he's looking. Once again, nice easy pitch and catch, and they will gain almost a first down. So it looks like maybe six and a half, it could be fourth and one.
where they're able to do these seven yard plays. We don't seem to have that in our arsenal right now. And the game becomes easier when you can. It's just a simple pitch and catch. There's just a ton of space there. Brockton's playing back. Coach Shelby doesn't want to give anything over the top. But Lincoln Subber, he's taking stuff underneath and just two easy plays to gain 14 yards. And we're looking at fourth and two. Brockton needs a play here.
So we are at 41 seconds. Lincoln-Subbury's gonna huddle up. Let's see what they do on fourth and one. They are gonna go under center. First down will stop the clock momentarily. I'm pretty sure they'll spike it. They've been creative offensively. There's a snap. The ball's gonna go to the back, and he has an easy first down. And more. As Luke Turco comes up from the tackle, and they gain three yards. That's gonna be a penalty on Brock today. That's gonna be 15 yards. Number 70. Yep.
Yep, easy penalty. No doubt about it, I mean he hits the Lincoln Sudbury player right in front of the referee. And that's gonna be 15 yards on the senior Jayden Seales. This is unacceptable. Coach Shelby is not gonna be happy. This has just been a poor night of Brockton football so far. Just not good enough. A little bit of the same things that have been happening on the last couple games with these penalties being undisciplined and it's carrying over here at,
So this 15 yards will give Lincoln Sudbury the ball at the Brockton 17 yard line, 35 seconds which is an eternity in high school football. And he's back, he looks, he looks, another just easy pitch and catch. Five more yards there, they're moving the ball right down the field, the same three plays to the same spot. Karens Antoine on the tackle. Brockton's gotta get up on those receivers. They gotta make it more difficult.
So Brock, so they're in the pistol with three receivers to the right, one to the left. He's back to back Landry, he's got time, he's got time, he looks and he's got a ton of room and he's gonna go all the way down to about the four yard line. There was a flag down, let's see what it was. I think it was, let's see what they call. But Landry got out of the pocket and there was no one there to contain.
It looks like it's gonna be like a legal formation. It's a big call here, because if it's on on them, if it's on on Lincoln, they are moving it back. Lincoln somebody would have the ball at the four yard line. So they're gonna move them back five yards. As we're at 24 seconds, and Brockton desperately needs to play.
Tough physical football here in the last few seconds of the half. Make no mistake, look at some of these guys that shared their penalties too. Imagine what the score might be. They didn't have penalties. They've been the better football team. There's no question about that. They've been more physical, more athletic, better coach, better played. Seemed like they wanted more too. So the Boxers will look at a
second and 15 defensively. Sean Landry has been terrific at quarterback tonight. Let's see what Lincoln-Subbury has here. Coach Shelby's up on the line of scrimmage. They're playing a little bit tighter. Looks like they got another quarterback in there though. Number nine. So I hope Landry's all right. Yeah, that'd be a big loss for them. So he's back, he's got room, he throws the ball up for grabs. It looks like he's open. Oh, that would've been a great catch.
Wobbly throw, and that's what caused the receiver from making that catch. That was a poor throw. If he leads him, that's an easy touchdown. He was open, the ball, it wasn't a great throw, but he was open. Look at it right here, Orlando. You look at it, the throw. Yeah, that's a touchdown if it's a better throw. A nice throw, it's a touchdown, but. So we're gonna go,
3rd and 15 at the 20, Lincoln-Subbury within field goal distance. Their kicker's already kicked the ball out of the end zone, as Brockton will take a timeout here. Coach Shelby wants to talk to his defense. I see Sam Basong down there too. Two great Brockton, so they're getting coached. Those are two great Brockton high linebackers who played on championship teams, who played at a high level. Descendants of Coach Bob O'Neal, former Brockton great quarterback and defensive coordinator.
also a Super Bowl champion coach. So the Boxers, down 14, nothing. There's 19 seconds left in the first half. Yeah, Brockton opponent, they're gonna play it down the line. Everett, final score there, BC High 46, and Everett, seven. No. One thing about Everett, I don't care what their record is early in the season, that team always gets better. Like I said, they are the Brockton of the 70s, 80s, and 90s.
They do. Brock always got better, Everett always gets better. Marshfield at halftime, 6-3 over Mansfield. Low scoring game, surprisingly. So we're looking at a third and 15. It is a new quarterback, number nine for Mansfield, for Lincoln-Sawberry, that's gonna be Mason Tarantino, the junior. He's back, he's back, he looks, he looks, he's got a man open.
Oh, he dropped it. That's pretty good coverage right there by Karens Antoine. Turned around right at the right time. Last moment he turned around. If he did, that was going to be a penalty, but he turned around at the last moment and ended up making a spectacular play. Really good football play by Karens Antoine right there. Turned around at the right time, got his hand up there. We're going to watch the replay right here, Orlando, because he was open.
momentarily he was open, and Antoine was able to turn around just at the last minute to turn his head, and now, here comes Adam Vaninteri out here. It's a big kick right here, this makes it a three score game. Let's see what Lincoln Subrey, looks like about a 38 yarder, 39 yarder. This kid got the leg to do it. There's the bounce, the kick, oh that looks like it's good Orlando.
That's almost a 40-yard field goal to give Lincoln-Sudbury a 17-0 lead at the 2-3 second mark of the first half. Yeah, a half totally dominated by Lincoln-Sudbury. Brockton's offense yet to get it going. They did take one of their possessions to the five-yard line, and one was unable to cash in.
Still got another half to go though. So the boxers will receive this kick right now. I expect it to be a squib kick and Brockton's going to have to get into halftime. They're going to have to have some serious conversations with themselves about how they're going to continue to play because last week against Franklin Orlando, me and you talked about this. The effort wasn't great late in that game. And you look at Brockton again, they've only scored 14 points this season.
and now that you're down 17 to nothing, so to win this game, you're gonna have to duplicate what you already scored and then some. Forget about even winning at this point, it's about playing good football. That's what Coach Silver and the rest of the guys, they just wanna play good football. No penalties, line up the right way, run the right formations, tackle, catch the ball, simple stuff like that. So the kicker will kick it.
That's number five, Marcus Cassell. So Mighty, let's see if he has some space here. He sets up the middle, and he's hit really hard, and another penalty. That's gonna be a penalty on Brock, the legal hit in the back. Just an unnecessary, silly penalty. And it was. It was a penalty. It was a penalty, I mean, right in front of the ref's face. It's hard for him not to take that flag and throw it.
Do we have on how many penalties Brockton's had during the first, gotta be close to six or seven already. I mean they've averaged about 10 a game so far, so now we're probably up to seven. I mean they're right on pace. So Brockton will probably take a knee here. It's been a long first half. And Leo, it's like, these are legit penalties, I mean. Lando, I know if you wanted to complain about those reps you would. When you tell me they're legit penalties, they're legit penalties.
Rockets probably just gonna take a knee here. I would be very surprised if they hand off that ball, yep. So, Orlando, we're gonna head into halftime here at Rocky Marciano Stadium at the end of the first half.
The Lincoln Sudbury Warriors, 17. Brockton Boxers, zero. Yes sir, they marched all the way from Lincoln Sudbury, a long ride here to Brockton, traffic filled, and boy did they come to play.
Get ready for one of the best halftime performances you're about to see.
Yeah.
Oh, my God.
The Rochester High School Marching Band is proud to present their 2024 show, Flare. They share a distinction to the rich musical traditions of a variety of large cultures and colors. The Marching Band is honored to perform for you and to represent your senior champions.
Now please welcome, under the field direction of drum majors Glenn Overstreet, Elijah Roman, and Damian Sampath, the Brockton High School Marching Band.
Yeah, Lenny! Yeah, Lenny!
Woo! Woo!
uh oh
do
Let's hear it for the marching band! One more show for Wingo!
Welcome back to Rocky Maciano Stadium in the campus of Brockton High School. Leo Genitasio along with the legend Orlando Galvao. Brockton Community Access, you can catch us on the Brockton channels. Orlando 2024 home opener. Lincoln-Subbury 17, Brockton zero. Not a lot of people, especially inside Brockton, thought this would be the score at halftime.
It kind of leaves you speechless, right? That you see a goose egg there. Felt like Brockton was gonna come out with a lot of energy today and was able to, was going to take it to Lincoln-Subbury, but it's been the other way around. So Brockton deferred to Lincoln-Subbury on their first drive. Brockton intercepted the ball, had a quick first down.
had to turn the ball back over. Lickett-Subbery turned that drive into a long touchdown pass. Sean Landry hit Shavon Harris. Broughton got the ball back one more time, fumbled it. Cimino, the quarterback, ran over the 50-yard line, looked like he had a first down, turned it over. Once again, Lickett-Subbery turned a turnover into a touchdown in the second quarter. Another breakdown in the secondary for another long touchdown pass.
from Landry. Brockton then Orlando had their longest drive of the day down 14 nothing going to the eye giving the ball to Turco Casey Rhodes in their sophomore back they got the ball down to the five yard line on third down a dropped touchdown missed field goal
make it so he cuts down, kicks the field goal down to half. It just hasn't been good enough. Right. And then you, and then you, again, you, you drive all the way down there. Good drive. And I know you, you're looking for three points, but in that situation, you need a touchdown. Um, if you don't get it, so what you pin them deep. Um, and they start from there. Um, Brockton, uh,
Offensively, it's just nothing's going right. I mean, from how they're running the play or how the play's being called, it's just nothing's going right right now. It's like they don't have an identity yet, what type of football team they want. We know if Luke Turco is 100% healthy, they want to give him the ball as much as possible. He makes people miss, he gets into gaps. Casey Rose has showed some promise from the back position. They got running backs, but offensively throwing the ball, when they get into that,
where they have to throw it, they just don't seem to be on the right page. Remember this though, remember this though, right? All excuses aside, they are missing Ahmad Wiggins out there today, and you look at Lincoln Sudbury, the first thing the coach told me is that they have a young team, but however, they have a senior quarterback, where Brockton has a sophomore quarterback, right? First year starter, I know last year he played in a lot of non-playoff games, but that's just not the same.
So he's taking baby steps, and again, he's gonna make mistakes as you've seen today. Crucial fumble at midfield after getting the first down. And you kinda hope they make the plays easier for him too, right? You can't have a situation where you have a third down and a sixth, and everybody's going deep. Do you have seven yard plays in your arsenal? Do you have six yard plays in your arsenal? Things like that. How about a screen play?
All I'm seeing is a team lining up in the I. Chuck and Duck. And handing off to Luke Turco, which is fine, but then again, you're chucking it down the field when you have to throw the ball. So Coach Silva, the young first year coach, gonna get into the locker room after a first half. The first two games they played quality football in the first half. Both of them, first game obviously they should have won, the second one they fell apart late.
This game was not a great start, so Coach Silva's gonna talk to his team. I'm sure he's gonna get a lot of help from his assistants talking about what we talked about, playing with emotion, playing physical football, playing penalty free. You know, that's a start. Outside of winning football games, you always wanna play good football. All right, they was in the locker room for a very long time. I'm pretty sure they had a very firm conversation with the team, and now let's see what they do here in the second half,
He do have 24 minutes to play in this game. A big part of this game has been Lincoln Sudbury's kicker, Marcus Gassell. He has kicked the ball into the end zone each time. He's kicked a 40 yard field goal to make this a three score game. He's been a difference maker so far. What year is he? I believe he is a, he's a senior. Good kicker. So Brockton will send back. It looks like they have Rhodes back there with Jared Mighty.
Speaking of kickers, Dallas Cowboys. He missed one. He missed one. He doesn't miss many. Man, I mean, they get across midfield. Is there any reason why you're concerned that he missed that one on FanDuel? Was there something on FanDuel that didn't go right for you? Maybe Post Malone, his buddy there, has some money on that game. So, Cassell, we're getting ready to
to get it going here in the second half. Again, Leo Genitasio, Orlando Galvao, Mike the Postman-Simmons, Curtis Reese, Scott Laboussier, they do a terrific job giving you a first rate product at Brockton Community Access. Once again, catch us on the Brockton channels. So Cassell will kick off, the Boxers will have their three deep as they look to start the second half and get themselves back in this football game.
And that's going to be returnable. And it is dropped. And Mighty has room. He gets up the middle. He has space. And that could be a touchdown. He has space and he will not be caught. And what a stop for the Boxers. Jared Mighty, we told you how explosive this guy is. We told you he's one break away from going all the way. And there you see it right now. What a start to the second half. That's exactly what they needed, Leo.
I don't know why I look at somebody kicking in the end zone. But Jared Mighty showing that. Let's see the replay here. Elite speed. Yeah, took a bounce. He was able to pick it up, saw the gap, and then one guy left to catch him and forget about it. Gone. So the boxers are right back in this game. Exactly what they needed. Wow, that was electrifying. That's why you see schools looking at Mr. Mighty.
So the extra point will be attempted, and it looks like it will be good. Yes, sir. So that will be Danny DaSilva, the junior kicker, as Brockton now makes it 17-7, and the defense will try to get the ball back for the Boxers. Well we see, now we see the Brockton sideline there. Different zone there, that's what you needed. And again, now let's focus on defensive stops.
Well it starts with good special team stops. Last week they gave up a touchdown, the opening kick to Franklin. Tonight they gave up a 50 yard return. Now go on down and make a tackle, make Lincoln-Subbury, make plays and try to get your offense back on the field. So it's a lot of emotion here in the stands as they got the Boxer Faithful back into this football game. Lincoln-Subbury will send back.
That return sent this crowd into a frenzy. Looks like Siobhan Harris will be back there. That's Stavon Harris.
So now, again, Brock's defense hasn't really been that bad, it's just, they've started in great field position. I mean, that's that. The run defense has been terrific. There's been a couple broken plays with the quarterbacks, game yards. Defensively, and this happened last year too, there's been secondary breakdowns at the wrong time after playing quality football. Yeah, I know it's 17-7, but I would point my finger offensively. Defense has had two turnovers, you know?
So that kick will go down to about the 12-yard line, and Lincoln-Subbery returns the ball. There's a little bit of space, that's a good tackle. And that's number 13 for Brockton. Yeah, energy, they're bringing energy to the second half here. What a start. Ekamini-Akban, he had a bad penalty on the first half, but he comes down and makes up for it with a terrific tackle right there. So Lincoln-Subbery will start at their own, 22 is Sean Landry, is he back into the game?
We saw him on the bench. Look at this tackle again. He's back in the game. Nice open field tackle. So they'll go in the pistol here. Brockton remains in a 43 front. Let's see what Lincoln Sudbury wants to do offensively. They had some success throwing the ball. He's back, he's looking to throw, he's looking to throw, he's over the middle and he's open.
And that will be a modest five yard game, as Brockton once again giving up the underneath stuff. Yeah, just when you think Lincoln Sudbury's gonna run the ball, slow the game down, no. Come up chucking here. So a gain of six will make it second and four at the Brockton 29 and a half yard line. As Lincoln Sudbury taking advantage of the underneath stuff. That play's been open all day. Yeah, Landry remaining in the pistol.
See Luke Turco now pinching in a little. Under center. And the ball will go to the back. There shouldn't be a lot of room there, and they got him. So not a lot of success running the ball, and that's a nice tackle by the boxers. Number 42, Xavier Colon, the junior linebacker. Good athlete, physical linebacker. Yeah, went exactly for the legs. Was able to chop him down in a short game.
So maybe no game there. We'll go third and four at the 30. A huge play early in the second half for the Boxer defense. Let's see if Lincoln Subbery goes through the air here, Orlando. Not a lot of success running the football. This would be a big start for Brockton here.
Let's see if Coach Shelby gets those corners up at the line of scrimmage. A little bit closer. They've been working them flats all game. In the pistol. He's back. Landry's got time. He has time. He throws it. Ah, he has enough for the first down. A nice pitch and catch in the underneath stuff. That's gonna be a penalty on Brockton. Lucky.
Wow, they missed that one, Leo. He hit that kid after the play. So Landry throws the ball underneath. A nice six yard gain will give them a first down and take a little bit of the momentum away from Brockton. You talk about a big, big, big pass. Just too much cushion. Just too much stuff underneath. Too easy of throws. So Landry will remain in the pistol. They have two H-backs and one back next to him. One receiver to the right.
Now two backs next to Landry. And the ball will go to him. He's got a little bit of space, he runs up the middle, and that's a good run. And he gains five yards. Too much. So Lincoln Sudbury, exactly what they wanted. After that opening, electrifying kickoff by Jared Mighty, will gain five yards, a second and five at their own 42. We're at nine minutes of the second half of a 17-17, 17-7 LS lead.
Landry. Landry has made great decisions tonight at quarterback. I think he's been the best player on the field. So, the senior signal caller in the pistol. He's got two H-backs and one back. Man in motion. Same play. Yep, same play. And they've got a good run, did gain three yards. Spun him backwards, and a tackle there, was that Zatz? Nathan Jean-Baptiste along with Uriel Maybeam.
And the sophomore nose tackle, Wade Mike Myers, or Michael Myers. So third and two, another big play for the Boxer defense. I expect, you know, another handoff. Very short yardage to pick up. Yeah, they're missing a mob weakens tonight in the middle. Watch for the quarterback keeper here. So third and two.
closer to third and one at the 44 and a half yard line. Landry and the pistol. He's gonna look to run the ball, and he has space, and the Brockton comes up and makes the tackle. Luke Turco, he'll stop him. Right, that was kinda like, you made a switch to the quarterback position, and I said, you know what, maybe they're gonna go quarterback keeper, and that's exactly what they did, and they lost a little there. So, fourth and three, let's see what they do. I think they might go for it, Orlando.
Looks like they're keeping their offense on the field. They're talking to the quarterback. Maybe they're gonna try to draw him off the sides. Brockton's gonna have to show some discipline here. On a lot of their third downs, the short passing game's been effective. Let's see what they do here. If they don't make this, they'll give Brockton terrific field position inside Lincoln-Subbury territory. So fourth and two, he's gonna be in the pistol. Brockton got almost everyone in the box. He's making the hard count.
No, they didn't jump. They do go for it. There's a snap. They didn't get it. They didn't get it. They didn't get it. And what slowed that play down was the snap. And I don't know if they were supposed to go on a different count, but it looked like the quarterback was ready for that ball. And once again, junior linebacker Xavier Colon shooting the gap, getting in the backfield.
destroying things in the backfield for a lot less. So Brockton now. Let's see the replay here. The snap, yeah, a little bit low. It was able to make a great play there now. Brockton takes over and a big stop. They have the ball at the Lincoln Cemetery, 45. They're gonna come out with receivers on both sides. With Luke Turco in the backfield. Semedo in the pistol.
And they're gonna go to Luke. And Luke, there's nothing there. There's nothing there. So Brockton will lose two yards there. As Lincoln Sudbury's been undersized, but they have really done a nice job stopping Brockton's running game. Right, I feel like when Luke's in the game, they're running the ball. I mean, you gotta play chess here. You gotta try different things, you know, and come back to that. So a loss of two for Brockton will make it second and 12. The offense still stagnant. They gotta make some plays.
Defense is giving them a chance here. Semedo in the shotgun, pistol with Luke Turco next to him. Man in motion, that ball is faked, it's gonna go to Turco. Turco has room, Turco keeps running, Turco's gonna gain a first down. Good play call, Coach Barrows. That time they sent Jarrett in motion, they've been using that. Faked it. Yeah, faked it and it was able to give it to Luko and it got positive yards, great play call.
So we're gonna go first down, they're gonna move fast. Brockton has the ball at the Lincoln-Subbury about a 37 yard line. Semedo the snap, the ball's gonna go to Turco. The ball, it's just starting too late. The snap isn't great. The snap's too high. Yeah, it's too high. The play's taking too much time to develop. That's happened a lot this year with Snapper and the quarterback. That senior Henry Hank Moss. You can't have a delay, that play has to happen quick.
So that's gonna be no game. We're gonna go second and 10 at the, looks like about the 33 and a half. Clark's running here, 541 here in the third quarter. Must touchdown right here, Orlando. Changes the whole game. Semedo in the pistol. They got trips to the right, one to the left. Luke Turk goes to back. Here's the snap.
They're gonna get the ball in space to Mighty. Mighty with good blocking, and they're gonna get called for another penalty. He's blocking downfield before the play. It's just not good enough, Philando. You can't make those mistakes. So Brockton's gonna be pushed back 10 yards. They called holdin', they didn't call blockin' downfield. I would like to see that play again, though. If his hands are outside, it's a hold.
Let's see the play, let's see the play again. So another big play for the Boxers, call back. He's holding, his hands were outside, we saw it right there, his hands were outside. You're gonna get called for that every time. So second and 16, the big play, call back. Another big penalty off a big play. That's gonna drive the coaches crazy, it's just inexcusable stuff. So trips to the left, one to the right.
Samado back, Samado back. It's gonna be the screen pass. What you were looking for. Turco's got a little bit of space and they'll gain about eight yards there and make it a manageable third down. Good play call. Good play call. I've been calling for that and they finally get my wish. Coach Colombo used to run that play to the fullback in the old days and it always seemed to go for 70 yard touchdown. So third and six here for the Boxers. Looks like it's definitely four down territory.
Semedo getting the call from Coach Barrows. Turco is the lone back, Mighty, Wooten, Rommel, Johnson, and Lucas, Jayden Lopes-Rivero. A lot of time spilling from that scoreboard. So here we go, big play, third and five for the Boxers.
man in motion, the ball's faked, the ball, he's open there, he's got him if he catches it. Moves inside, moves outside, he breaks a tackle! And a great pitching catch to Rommel Johnson. That was a great play call, again, they thought Luke was getting the ball, now I've said this, set up your run, set up your pass from your run, and that's what they did there. I take that back, that was Jaden Wooten, back from Randolph High, good athlete, played quarterback, makes the catch, broke a tackle, got the enough yardage to get the first down.
Brockton in the red zone. So here we go. The boxers with a first down at about the 15. Semedo in the pistol. Luke Turco the back next to him. Now Brockton move. Oh timeout. So you don't want to use those timeouts too much. You might need them later in the game. So I'm sure that's not something
the coaches are happy about. I would love to see them go to the line, Leo, and move faster, just hand off the ball. Lincoln Sudbury look like they're in their heels right now, they're looking like they're a little bit tired. A lot of guys are playing both ways on that side. But there's something we talked about coming into the half that we're happy to see, a lot of emotion, physicality.
That's one thing you see, the kids are playing for their coaches, because they easily could have came out and packed it in, lost this game 24 to seven and got ready for next week. Nice to see the boxers battle back in their second half, win or lose. So Brockton will have the ball at about the 15 yard line, they're down 17-7. We're at three minutes of the third quarter. Leo Genitasio, along with the Brockton legend Orlando Galvao, Brockton community actors, catch us on the Brockton channels.
So Brockton will move right, looks like they're gonna go right to the line of scrimmage. Lincoln Sudbury, defensive coordinator, getting the calls. Let's see what Coach Barrows has here. He's been creative so far in this drive. Samada remains in the pistol, two to the left, one.
Two to the right. Luke Turco's the back, the man in motion. The ball's gonna go to Mighty. He tries to get to the outside. He uses some of that speed. He pumps it in, he cuts back in. He cuts back, I'd like to see him protect that ball. But it's a nice run. Once again, using that speed. Luke Turco lead the way too. And an excellent tackle by Lincoln Sudbury, or else he was gonna go on the end zone. So Jared Mighty will gain about 11? So Brockton will have the ball with the five yard line.
They were stagnant here last time, but they've been a little more creative. Christian Flaherty goes into the game. The big fullback, the senior fullback, we're in the eye. Cimino gets the ball, Turco has a little bit of room, he punches inside, he gets in the end zone! Get the ball to Luke Turco!
So that big offensive line pushes Lincoln's set very back. Luke Turco on a six yard touchdown run with the help of Christian Flaherty. And just like they did when Brockton went for it at midfield, they made Brockton pay. Brockton returns the favor, making them pay for going for that fourth down and not making it. And Brockton back in this game. So Danny DaSilva, the kicker, will come in for the extra point.
The hold down, the kick is good.
So we're at three minutes and nine seconds. Brockton has battled themselves back into this football game. We're at 17-14. Yeah, surprise, surprise. There might have been people out there watching Brockton. You see the replay here, Luke Turco not messing around, taking it right in the end zone with authority. Moving over that left side of that Brockton line right there was really did a terrific job, starting with the center, Henry Hinkboss.
It's number 77, the senior, Nathan Bertheny, 6'4", 365. Cash Pettway, 6'5", 404. Yeah, surprise, surprise. A lot of viewers out there watching probably gave up, turned away from the channel, but Brockton has come out a different team, and this is why we get frustrated, because we know what they're capable of doing. So Brockton will kick off here. Lincoln Sudbury has three deep again. Danny DeSilvo looking to kick.
The boxes are right back in this football game. There's a lot of time left.
And it's a good catch. It's angled to the right. The ball's fielded about the six yard line. Brocklin's got guys down there. There's not a lot of space. These guys are bouncing inside. And that's good tackling. Oh! Looked like that ball came a little loose, but he was able to... He had an outfield like a loaf of bread.
So the Boxers, defensively, have really ignited the Boxers' offense. Well, let's see how Lincoln-Satterbury responds now. Well, they've been successful throwing the ball. Running the ball, not worked tonight for them. Let's see if they go back to it. I want Brockton to pinch Luke Turco. That quick pass has been working a lot today. I'd like to see Luke Turco pinch a little bit in. The Boxer defense has been really solid this half. Spock by Xavier Colon, Luke Turco, and those big Brockton defensive ends.
The crowd is on their feet now. What a different turn of events here in the second half. So Landry will get into the shotgun. He's got one back to the right, three receivers right, one left. He's going to throw. He's locked. There's not a lot of pressure. It's over the middle and he's wide open. And that's going to be a 12-yard gain. Yeah, that's a great hit.
Not a lot of pass rush. No pass rush and just too many yards underneath Orlando. And that play's been working all night. And Lincoln Sudbury's not shying away from it. They're going right to it. So a first down, a 14 yard completion as Lincoln Sudbury calms the Brockton crowd a bit. We are at the two minute mark of this third quarter, 17-14 game.
Landry remains in the pistol. Brock remains in the 43 front with two safeties back. The snap, and he's back. He's looking, he's looking, he's looking, he's looking, and he's, oh, it should be intercepted! It is intercepted! Oh no, it bounced. Looked like Mighty had it, but it bounced. Yeah, you know what? We'll see the replay on that, but that looked like a dip bounce. Wow, that would've been huge. That would've been huge. Let's see in the replay. Both refs came in right away and said it bounced, and Jared Mighty's not arguing. We're gonna see the replay here.
Landry back to pass, steps into it. Get a good shot here, good angle. Yeah, it bounced, it bounced. So, second and 10, the near turnover. Let's see if Lincoln Sudbury will run the ball here. The Boxer defense trying to come up with another big stop, get the ball back to the offense. Lincoln Sudbury has three to the, looks like the right, one to the left.
and a lone back in the backfield. Landry gets the ball, they're looking to throw again, they're looking to throw again, he's looking, he's got the wheel right, he's open, and he catches it. Good play. Good play call, good execution. I'm telling you right now, Lincoln Sudbury's not playing like a team that's very young. And they got the ball to the senior kicker, Marcus Cassell, who took it in, and the tackle by Brock is number five who was beat on the play.
and that's Jordan DiPina, the outside linebacker on the wheel route. Yeah, you gotta give the Lincoln Sudbury head coach, whoever made that play call, credit for that one, because they faked that curl to number 21, and he was able to hit him on the sideline for a great pass and catch. So Lincoln Sudbury's taking back some momentum. They have the ball at the Brockton 40, first down. Two minutes left of this third quarter in a 17-14 game.
And they're still throwing. They're not having a lot. He's looking to throw. He's looking to throw. And he's open again. There it is, 21. He's open again. All right. All right. You've got to put the brakes on that right now. And I'll play it down for Brockton. I know who that is. Jordan Topino. Can't afford to lose him because you've already short a linebacker.
You're a star, Ahmaud Wiggins, a starter out for today's game. So they're just playing pitch and catch right now. Brockton's really not sending many, and they're sitting in the zone. And look at Sudbury just throwing the ball to spots in the zone.
Looks like he got hit in the head and hopefully he's gonna be okay. So Lincoln Sebre has gotten the ball back here after Brockton took back the momentum and has gone right down the field on four plays and has gotten the ball at least into field goal territory for Marcus Cassell. Yeah, this Landry kid is a problem. I mean, he's just making dimes. He's out there throwing dimes out there. Every big play you need, he's answered it. So Brockton's a little thin at linebacker. Let's see what Coach Shelby goes through here.
Looks like number 30 coming into the game for the Boxers. Sophomore, Wilma Perelian, and he'll get some varsity reps here in a big game. Lincoln Subberry, once again, they ran out to a 17-nothing halftime lead. Brockton took the opening kickoff of the second half on a 90-odd kickoff return by Jared Mighty.
Brockton got a fourth down stop in midfield, turned that into a five yard Luke Turco run, but Lincoln Subbury's come right back on four plays and got the ball down to the Brockton 29, as hopefully Jordan DePino's okay. Yeah, he looked like he might've got the wind knocked out of him, Leo. Hopefully that's it. If it's a head injury, he will be gone for at least a week. Brockton doesn't need that. So the sophomore linebacker will fill the spot there. Let's see if Lincoln Subbury tries to take advantage of that.
Well, it looked like he's shaking his head, Leo. You might've been right. I thought... So here we go. First down for the Warriors. Landry in the pistol, trips to the right with one back. He's back, he racks, he's gonna run a little option. The ball's pitched and it's just too many odds. That's a holding call right there. We'll get a hold, but again, just too many odds. Well, too many odds because, you know,
That lineman just pulled down one of our defenders. I mean, are they gonna call it? Face mask on, that's a 15 yard penalty. He just pulled him down now. So the 15 yard penalty will put the ball back to about the...
Is it a 15-yarder, Lando? It should be a 15-yarder. So that's a huge penalty for Lincoln Sudbury. The ball will go back to about the 43, I believe. Wow. About the 43 and a half. So first and 25. Brockton with a huge chance to get off the field here. Maybe get the ball back with a chance to take the lead. Right. Where Brockton was committing these penalties that was costing him some yards, now Lincoln Sudbury is doing the same thing. He's had some penalties tonight, too.
and hopefully Brockton can make this stop here. So Landry will go into the pistol again, no change into the offense. Two to the left, two to the right, one back. Brockton sits in that 43 with both safeties back. Landry with the man in motion. The ball goes back, he's gonna look to throw, he's gonna look to throw, he's got a man over. That ball could be intercepted. So good coverage by Antoine right there. Excellent coverage and a little bit thrown to the,
out of the range of the receiver, had no chance of catching the ball. So Antoine, after being beat once tonight, has had real blanket coverage since then. Showing real mental toughness. So at 2nd and 25, Brockton takes out Jaden Seal and bring in one of the quicker ends, Antoine Hart. Alon Hart, I'm sorry. Watch out for the screen here. Watch out for the screen. So at 2nd and 25, let's see what Lincoln Sudbury has in. Brockton brings the safeties up a bit. Xavier Colon switches sides.
with the sophomore linebacker. 21's been open all day for DeCanto. He's back, he's back, Brockton's bringing pressure, Brockton's bringing pressure. It's caught and there's no game there, basically nothing. So John Shelby, I like what he did right there. Gotta get the quarterback off his mark, put a little pressure on him, quicken him up a little bit. He does that, completes the pass, but it's basically no game. So third down to 25, you wanna see Brockton show a little discipline here, no silly penalties.
Big third down coming up here, and a third down a very, very, very long. Sainties will be back a bit. Let's see what Lincoln Sudbury has in. They try to want to get this ball into field goal range, which for their guy could be anywhere at the 35. I would say yes. Landry's back, Brock is putting pressure, they're bringing guys, he's got hit, there's the ball, that ball's intercepted! Oh, he dropped it. Oh, he dropped it.
Right in... And there was space. Right in Antoine's hands. There was no one there. Couldn't corral it. He might have gone the whole way right there. And that's what he was thinking, Leo. All he saw was open field and unfortunately you gotta catch the ball first. So right here, we're gonna see it on the replay. Brockton bringing pressure again. Landry threw the ball. Look at this. Oh, there was... That would have been... So...
The missed opportunity, still fourth down. Lincoln Sudbury with the punter out there. Brockton will get the ball back with a chance to take the lead. And a dangerous serve and mighty back deep for Brockton. We're at 26 seconds, and there's the kick, and it's a good one. It's angled towards the sideline. I would let it go. I would let it go. And it's out at about the one, I believe. What a kick, what a kick. Oh no, Brockton will get the touch back. Oh, it was a really good kick. Brockton might've caught a break there. It did, it looked like it went out at the one. Wow.
So Brock will get the ball and the touch back. Yeah, I gotta see that again, but it looked like that ball bounced out at the 1. So here we go Orlando, the boxers get the ball back. We haven't said this all night. Let's leave the replay here first on that kick. If we can get a quick look at this. So that kick looked like
Yeah, we don't have a great angle at it. That was a good call. That was a good call. Oh, I think it went out at the one. No, no, no, that ball, that ball. No, they marked it at the one. They changed the call. It went out at the one. That's what I thought. That's a good call. So Brockton at the 1-1 yard line. And Tomato will keep the ball, keep the ball. There you go, there you go. Move his legs, move his legs. Like that. That would end the quarter, too. That was initially called a touchback. And the other ref came in and correctly made the call.
He cornered, he got there right at the corner of the end zone, right at the one yard line. My initial thought, it went out, I thought we got a break and it went out, but we don't get breaks. No. We don't get breaks. So at the end of three quarters at Rocky Marciano Stadium on the campus of Brockton High School, Lincoln Subbury 17, Brockton 14. Brockton calling back to this game.
Third quarter score in Brockton was down 17-0. They took the opening kickoff. Jared Mighty went 90 yards and took it to the house to make it 17-7. Brockton got a fourth down stop in midfield. They marched 50 yards on a Luke Turco five yard touchdown pass. Lincoln Sudbury came back, got to the Brockton 29, but Brockton defense stiffened once again. A great kick resulted in Brockton having second down at the four yard line.
Like I said, Leo, the defense hasn't been playing that bad, but if your offense can generate some scores, keep the defense off the field, your defense can make stops for you. And unfortunately, we're starting deep in our territory. Might wanna get a little room here, get a couple first downs. That'd be nice. So Brockton's looking at a second and seven at the four. Luke Turk goes to back.
You have Christian Flaherty in as Brockton starts in the eye. And Turco will get the ball. He has space, he gets up the middle. There he goes! There goes Turco! He has room! He breaks the tackle! And he will go 45 yards up to the 45! And Luke Sykes feed me the ball! Wow!
He was one tackle away from going 95 yards. When was the last time I brought him back when 95 yards? Yeah, you're looking at Lincoln Sudbury. Richard Johnson. The heads are turning right now because they're clearly seeing a different team here in the second half. So the Boxers will have a first down at the Lincoln Sudbury 48. Yeah, great save and tackle that time too. And we'll see Casey Rhodes in.
Again, Brockton, I would like to see that play right into the line, wasting no time, keeping them off balance. Taking too long. Cimino gets the call, Brockton's gonna go quads again. Casey Rhodes is the lone back. Lincoln Sudbury's got just about everyone near that box. There goes the motion, the ball's gonna go to Mighty. He tries to get it to the outside. He uses that speed, he gets upfield and he gains about four yards. Lincoln Sudbury was ready for that one. Yeah, that was a good play, they stiffed that out, but he still was able to get a couple.
Maybe, maybe. So Brockton gains about a yard and a half. We're going second and nine at the Lincoln-Subbury 47. K.C. Rhodes remains in. K.C. Rhodes remains in. We have four receivers with Semedo back there as he gets to signing.
Talks to the receivers. The one and only Nubia just stepped into the press box, guys. Pretty sure Brockton knows who he is. Semedo, once again, motion. Here's the fake, he has time, he has time, he looks, he's low and deep, he has a receiver! You know, I like that play, I like that play, but... Did he have a chance to dive for it?
The ball looked like it was there, maybe a little overthrown, but a good throw either way. So Brock into the third and nine. I would like to see that play to Lopes. I like that play, but I would just like to see that play to Lopes, because I feel like, you know, Lopes, no knock on Wooten, but Lopes goes out there and gets it, but I felt like that was catchable. Let's see it right here on the replay. The ball was thrown and
Play maybe could have been made. So third down and nine. The box is in the pistol. Cimino back, Cimino back. Throws it over the middle. But not enough. I like that play on second down. That ball on third down. So the box is made punt here. Maybe try to box Lincoln Sudbury in. Don't want to give them the ball back at the 45 at fourth and seven. Yeah, looks like they're gonna punt. Yeah, you punt here. There's a lot of football left. The defense has played well enough.
Hopefully Mighty can do exactly what Brockton just did. So Brockton got out of their own two yard, one yard line, crossed midfield. Looks like instead of Mighty putting the ball, you got someone else putting the ball now, the field goal kicker for Brockton. Danny DaSilva. Give Mighty a break. The snap's perfect. Danny DaSilva.
That's a good kick. It's gonna get down, they're gonna let it bounce, let it bounce, let it bounce. And that is a terrific kick that will stop inside the 10 yard line. Yeah, that's a good kick, good bounce. That's exactly what you want for Brockton if you're gonna punt it. You want exactly that situation right there.
So we're at the nine minute, 20 seconds of the fourth quarter. Brockton Community Access, Brockton Channels catchers, Leo Genitassio, along with the legend, Orlando Galveo. Of course we have Mike the Postman-Simmons, Curtis Reese, and Scott LaBoussiere on the production tonight. As the boxers look to try to make another start here. Lincoln Sudbury, let's see if they throw the ball inside their own tent.
Landry, he's gonna huddle up this time. He'll remain, it looks like, in the pistol with one back. Brockton has got everyone in the box, but one safety. Turco back with one corner. There's the call, he fakes it, there's a good call, that's a great play call.
and that's gonna gain, that's just exactly what you need to do inside your own 20. Great play call, it's a reverse, an option reverse by the quarterback, and it gains about seven yards to tackle by Luke Turco, gain of eight. That's a perfect call, Leland, to inside your own 10 yard line. A lot of plays in their arsenals. They remind me a lot of Franklin on offense, they run their plays, but they run them effectively, they block them well.
So it's gonna be second and two at the 16 yard line, under nine minutes of a 17-14 game. Landry, he's done just about everything for this team tonight. Open field tackles, touchdown throws, runs. He's got one back. Motion. And again, it's the same exact call.
So it's another option reverse for six yards. Yeah, nothing fancy, but it's working. Well, the Brockton defensive end has gotta contain and it's just a good play call. So the first down and Lincoln-Subbury gets out of trouble. They're at the 24 at first down and 10. Two real good play calls by Lincoln-Subbury there. Yeah, two O and O, O and two teams tonight battling it out in the field.
Both teams know this could be a big loss for either team, so. This could have playoff implications, point-wise. So, there's the call, there's the ball in the back. He has a little bit of room, that's a good tackle. Ty Baker, Ty Baker with a little help from, it's good to see Jordan Tapina back in there. So a gain of two will make it second and eight.
Landry gets the call from the coach. That's head coach Justin McKay. He does a fine job at Lincoln-Subbury at school. That's really every sport there just about. Yeah, 25%. Pretty good. Medical kids, they're good at everything. Certainly helps. So, second and nine. They're in the pistol.
from the shotgun, he's gonna throw, he's gonna throw, he's gonna throw. He throws it over the middle. Once again, caught and a mistackle. It's gonna be a penalty. You got a hit in the back, that's coming back. And that was, he didn't even need to do that. Harris didn't even need to do that. Well, the play was wide open and the mistackle would have been a 20 yard gain. So Lincoln-Subbery's gotta go back. They've had just as many penalties as Brockton. Yeah, I don't know what Harris was thinking there.
was completely away from the play, hit in the back. So that play was upfield. It'll be probably the same exact, second and nine, no real change. The ball was caught at the first down marker. Brockton fortunate not to give up 20 yards. Again, that play's been open all game though. I mean, every time you need a bread and butter play, it seems like they're going to that exact play. Defensively, you gotta wake up when it comes to that.
It's been their all-might, they've taken advantage of it. Brockton's stiffened where they've had to many times, but Lincoln Sudbury sees something they like, and they're going to it. So second and nine again, same formation. In the pistol, Landry.
Oh, the ball snapped, it's down! Wow, he's down. He made the play anyway, but once his knee's down, another huge break for the Boxers. His knee's down, he's down. So Brockton will get Lincoln Sudbury down to about a third and 13 here, as we are at the six minute mark. This may be the biggest play of the game defensively. We saw the mistakes happen to Brockton in the first half, and now the tides are turning, and Lincoln Sudbury is making these mistakes.
So the poor snap results in about a five yard loss. That's a third and 15 for Lincoln Sudbury. Climbing under six minutes of a 17-14 game. Brock desperately wants to get off the field and give Semido and company the ball back. Lopes is telling the crowd, let's get loud here. The middle of the field has been wide open. The linebackers are up at the line of scrimmage. Motion.
Back, back, back, the ball's thrown. It's gonna be a wide receiver screen. He's got room, he gets to the outside. And it's tackled well by Brockton. So looking off the field, look at Sudbury, plays it safe. They're gonna trust their defense. As Brockton defense once again makes a stop. As back we'll see Jared Mighty and Casey Rhodes. Yeah, they probably wanna, not wanna kick it to Mighty right there. I think that's why Brockton's got two guys down there.
A lot of teams do not want to kick it to Jared Mighty this year. So we are under five minutes. This is going to be the drive of the game coming up for the Boxers. A chance to go ahead. They've had one already. All you can ask for after that first half. Cassell, he's been good in all might. The kick is a real good one. Mighty gets the ball. He receives it. He cuts back outside. It's just another penalty you don't need to do.
You just, he wasn't even near the play, so another silly penalty by Brockton will take away a good pump return. Just really inexcusable penalties. Again, penalty is gonna damper your field position, which is pretty decent. Robert Moyes, the junior. So special teams, we've talked about it for years now, Orlando, special teams is this position. Yeah, let's see the play again. Exactly what the referees are seeing.
Yeah, he doesn't, it's just, it's just a penalty, it's just. Can't hit the guy in the back. And it's right in front of the ref. So 15 yards lost, about a 20 yard penalty there. As Brockton with the penalty will, instead of having the ball near the 45, will have it at the 24. We're at 433 where Brockton with a chance to take the lead. No one in the backfield yet. So they're gonna go five wide.
They haven't seen this formation, they wanna talk it over. Probably a smart time out. Don't be surprised, they don't send extra pressure too. On the young single caller for Brockton. Semido with a chance for his first game winning drive. Any scores, Lelando on the out of style scoreboard before we get back. It's a good question. This game got, it went from boring to,
to a real good game, so. Once again, Orlando, only one offensive touchdown again for Brockton. So the Boxers at 433 with their, this could be a signature drive this season for them. Let's see what Coach Barrows has in store. He came out with a different formation right there. They gave Lincoln-Subbury a little bit of a different look. They wanted a call timeout. And also this could be a season
a change, right? A season-defining moment here, you know? You might- Big difference between one and two and oh and three. Going on the road at Lawrence next week. So here we go. Again, they go- They don't change. Luke Turco's in the slot. I'm pretty sure he's gonna come across- We're going five wide. Expect him to go in motion here. Nope. There he goes. Good call, Orlando. Turco gets the ball. He gets to the outside. Cuts it back in and gain about four yards.
So, positive yardage for the Boxers. Let's see how fast they move. Is it four down territory here? Semedo looks over, talks to Coach Barrows. Brockton gets to five wide again. Luke Turco and Jared Mighty look like they're gonna flop sides, no. They stay, they both.
They both look like they're right around the edge of the tackles. Both looking in the slot area. Semedo. Back, Turco in motion, he fakes, he fakes, he looks. It's open, he catches it, and it's a good catch and a first down. Nice pitching catch. Yeah, able to take the hit, hold on to the ball. First down Brockton. Nice catch by number 19 for Brockton right there.
Shamir Williams, nice catch. He went up high to catch that one. The senior wide receiver, so Brockton gets a first down at the 35. The clock is moving, we're under four minutes. They're gonna have to stop picking some chunk yards here. The ball's gonna go to Turco. Luke has room, cuts it up inside, gains about three. Yeah, he should've been stopped though. Good game by Luke. So the clock is running. Lincoln-Subbery has a guy down.
Brockton wants to move fast. Let's go, let's go. Samino gets the call. Gain of four by Turco. Still issues lining up correctly. The ball's in motion, this one's gonna go to Jarrett. Jarrett cuts up, Jarrett has room. Jarrett cuts inside, back out, he'll get the first down.
But we're at two minutes and 50 seconds. Yeah, that was all Jared right there. He was able to sniff out a couple yards and extend the drive for Brockton. First down. So the clock starts moving. It's not supposed to start until the chains are set. So the clock does move.
We're at 223, the ball around the 45. Brockton in the pistol. Samedo back, Samedo back, he throws the ball to Mighty. There's some room over there, he makes a cut. He gets outside, he's just held up by that jersey. He keeps moving, he gains nine. But again, they're gonna have to get some big plays. And then that, you know what stopped Jared from going all the way?
The player grabbing him by the shirt, literally ripping it off. So Brockton just getting the ball to Jared Mighty and Luke Turco in space. They're at the Lincoln-Subbury 45 at 2-0-3 in the fourth quarter. Down 17-14. Brockton also capable of kicking a field goal, Orlando. So let's see what they have here. It's second and one. Do they take a shot?
We see it right here, Mighty made, he made a man miss. Actually grabbed him by the leg. And the shirt. The shirt first, then the leg. Yep, yep. Let's make a group attendance. If you're in the green house, make some noise. Yep. Full time.
So here we go, out of the timeout. Brockton is at second and one. They flop receivers. Guterko's in the backfield. 2-0-3 of this fourth quarter. You know who's getting the ball right now. Quarterback sneaks, so they want the first down. Sabino keeps the legs moving. So they're gonna get down to the 38, but the clock is running.
Brockton's gonna go right to the line. Lincoln subber, he's subbing. This is a perfect opportunity here. So Brockton moving a little bit quicker here. Semedo in the pistol. The snap. Turco gaining yardage. Turco gaining yardage. Oh, that's a penalty. And there's no? That's a penalty. Wow.
So first down run by Luke Turco. Looks like a horse caller, no call. He has the ball at the Lincoln Sudbury 25. We're at 139 in the fourth quarter. Coach Barrows, creativity right here shown. Let's see it right here. Do we have the horse caller? Let's see. Or is it the back of the jersey? No, it's the back of the jersey. No, that's a horse caller. He brought him down grabbing
So they got the man in motion, they go to number one, he kicks the outside, there's a little bit of room. Oh, good step out, nice. So they went to Jaden Lopes-Ribeiro there, as we're gonna go around one minute, Brockton's gotta move quicker. Second down at about seven, they gotta start putting the ball up in the air down, as the ball, we're going under a minute. Brockton taking its time, taking its time.
Turco next to Samedo. Brocklin at the Lincoln Subbury, 21. Once again, motion. They fake the motion. He's got time. He throws the ball over the middle. Oh, it hit him right in the chest. Another ball that's gotta be caught. It's a perfect throw. That's a great throw. And I believe you try to, you can't catch balls with a helmet, right? You try to catch it with his body. Just catch the ball with your hands. It's a perfect throw.
Can't ask for a better throw from your sophomore quarterback. That ball would've gave him the ball inside the 10 at 45 seconds. So now we're third and seven. Brockton's got two plays to get a first down or they have to come in for a field goal. That was the one right there. It was there. It was there. So, Semedo in the pistol. Luke Turco's back there with him.
Here's the call, they're gonna give the ball to Luke. Luke moves, but no, that's just not it. They got a call timeout, so fourth down and four. So it comes down to this. This is the play of the game, Brock in 36 seconds, fourth and five. Maybe I'd like to see Samedo get out of the pocket and a little bootleg, try something with a little misdirection and get one of those receivers on one-on-one coverage with the ball.
So Brockton gained about three right there. They had to use one of their timeouts. And what do you think they're talking about in this huddle? Well, he's probably thinking about his best play right now. You talk about redemption, decision making, you can make a decision right here that could potentially win you the game. All right? So, 38 seconds, fourth down and about,
Five, maybe four. Lincoln Sudbury, a stop here, wins the football game. A first down from Brockton. And this is the third straight year it's come down to the wire between Brockton and Lincoln Sudbury. Can't ask for more. You know, you play 48 minutes in football, man. You just don't go by the first 24 minutes. And Brockton has shown why you don't do that. Let's see what Coach Barrows has here right now. The coach is talking over.
Brockton goes to the line of scrimmage. Let's see what Turco's lined up here. He's gonna be in the backfield with Tomato. Lincoln Sudbury thinks they're gonna run the ball. They got four down tackles, three linebackers in at the box. They got man coverage everywhere else. Yeah, this is it right here in a timeout. Yeah, coach. They just wanted to see how Brockton would line up, which is smart to do.
So now that they've seen how Brockton was lined up, now Brockton, they're gonna keep the same thing or? Justin McKay, smart coach right there, looked at Brockton, what's he gonna do? He's gonna make some adjustments. Let's see if Coach Barrows comes out and makes an adjustment. Yeah, we got some scores here. With 9.45 left in the fourth quarter, Central has battled back, 20 unanswered points, leads Zavarian 20 to 13. Duxbury.
up 19 to 14 on Franklin. Siema all over Lemonster, 42 to 14 at the half. Natick, final score there, 28 to seven over Milford. So back here at Rocky Maciano Stadium, play of the game. Leo Giannatasio along with Orlando Galvao, the Brockton legend. The Boxers and the Lincoln Sudbury Warriors coming down to the play of the game right here. Brockton down 17-14. They battled back in this game. They've had a chance.
Two plays ago to get a big first down, down to the five. The ball was not caught, so here it is right here. Brockton in the shotgun. Luke Turco to the left, two receivers left, two receivers right. Let's see what they're gonna do. Semedo in the pistol. There's the snap, he is gonna throw, he is gonna throw. The ball's throbbed over, they got room. Hit him right in the hands.
So, instead of trying to get a first down, it's a low percentage throw into the end zone. You gotta go for the first down, man. You gotta go for the first down. Simple five yard pattern, you extend the game. But, unfortunately, chose to go to Lopes. Lopes, I hope he's okay, he's coming out limping. And unfortunately, Brockton's gonna lose another heartbreaker here in Brockton.
So on fourth down, you know, Coach Barrett's gotta make his, he's gotta make it easy for a sophomore quarterback. That's just a, that's a tough play for the wide receiver. It's a tough throw. Looked like the throw was there.
Looks like Ribeiro may have injured his ankle, but either way Lincoln Sudbury did what they needed to do to win this football game. Brockton showed some life in the second half, but unfortunately it just wasn't enough.
Again, that play call at the end is gonna unfortunately stick out more than this final score. It's gotta be a high percentage throw. You can't throw a corner route on fourth down and five. It's just too hard of a throw to make, especially with your soft ball. You got plenty of time, 38 seconds left. First down, your four plays. I believe you have some timeouts under your belt.
and then you chose to go for it all. So we're going to wrap it up here as the final whistle goes here at Marciano Stadium. Orlando Brockton was down 17-0. They showed life here in the second half.
Stuff we wanted to see, they played more physical football, they were creative a little bit more on offense, but it doesn't matter if you don't win football games. This is Brockton. You are what your record says, and now the record says Brockton's 0-3, and this is gonna be an uphill battle, a climb here for Brockton the rest of the way.
So we're gonna wrap it up here at Marciano Stadium. Leo Gennatasio along with Orlando Galvao, Mike DePostman-Simmons, Curtis Reese, Scott Labussiere on the production. The Boxers are gonna lose this one 17-14. We'll see you again next week. Thank you.