Hello, everyone, and welcome to your show, Method Happenings.
We're going to do a show tonight, and it's going to be a short one.
You know, we just want to take some time, and we've got a lot of people to thank, people I've, you know, been associated with putting together Method Happenings, all the guests, and we've had a lot of people along the way that have helped out.
I also want to say, you know, there's a lot going on in the world.
You know, there's still a lot of good stuff, but there's an awful lot of sad things going on, you know, during the holiday season.
I just wanted to say a little favorite saying of mine, and I think people need to keep this in mind.
Where there is faith, there is love.
And where there is love, there is peace.
Where there is peace, there is God.
And where God is, nothing is missing.
Amen.
So I just had to get that in there.
And I hope you heard it and I wish everybody peace.
So we're gonna begin.
I wanna start thanking some people who have been on the show.
Like I said, there's an awful lot of them.
And I wanna also say that, we started this with very little.
It was just an idea from one person
I got involved, and then we brought on two great guys that joined us, and you'll hear from all of them.
But I got to tell you, the show, it's just been an incredible year.
We've put about 31 shows out.
We've had four or five what we call shorts, 15, 20-minute shows.
We've had business owners.
A lot of the candidates that ran this year came on, told us what they were all about.
A lot of them were the new candidates.
But we really did have a lot of fun.
And our main goal was to get information out to everyone that lives in this city.
And not just any information.
You know, information that's valuable, that you can use.
You know, that's going to inform you about what's really going on in Medford.
There's been a lot of good.
There's been, you know, negative
There's, I mean, I can go on and on.
Now we're dealing with a trash situation.
We're still going on with, it's just so many things.
The zoning, you know, there really is a lot.
We all see all the buildings that are gonna be going up, a lot of apartment buildings going up.
That, you know, some people think it's a great thing and others may not, but it's happening.
So there's a lot going on.
And we just want to continue doing what we're doing, and that's to keep everybody informed.
So the first guy I really got to thank, and that's really the leader.
He's the one who started this.
And that's Paul Geraghty.
He's better known to us as the general, or lovingly known as the general.
Paul is really the person responsible for the idea that got this all started.
And it's been a pleasure meeting him, working with him.
And he's behind the scenes, but boy, he does a lot of good.
And he does a lot of good for the city of Method, and he cares about Method.
So I want to thank you, Paul.
It has.
It's been a pleasure.
I've enjoyed working with you.
I also want to thank Bruce Patterson.
I mean, he's just like, you know, the wizard, I guess.
Technical, and it's amazing what he's done with our website.
You know, he joined us along the way.
And I also want to thank Marco Cronali, who, boy, he's helped out tremendously.
And I want to remind everyone that, you know, this is a show that we do.
You know, we're not paid.
We don't, you know, we're not getting rich doing this.
We're doing it because we love the city.
You know, and we really do.
We enjoy doing the show.
And I tell you, it's a great group of guys.
So I just had to get that all in.
Marco, Paul Geraghty, and Bruce Patterson.
And I tell you, we've all worked hard
putting out 31 shows, and we did some shots and all the rest of it that you do in between.
The things that it takes to put a show together, it's a lot.
But like I say, we do enjoy it, and we've had a lot of fun.
You know, I also wanna thank, you know, the Method Community Media, which is the public education,
and Government Access Television Media Studio, which serves Medford.
So I wanna thank Kevin Harrington.
He's running the studio.
He does a great job.
And I also wanna thank James Corbett.
That's his assistant extraordinaire, we call him.
And a shout out to a few other people, Jonathan, Stevie B, that also have helped up
helped out along the way working with cameras and, you know, we'd be short a person and boy, they'd come through for us.
So thank you guys.
And there's a few others, quite a few, I'm not gonna mention them, but thank you for helping us out on short notice.
So I wanna stress that we are gonna be taking some time off for the Christmas season and New Year's.
You know, we've done a lot and we do need a break.
And I think we've all, you know, Paul, Marco, and Bruce would agree with me.
We really do, we need a break.
So over the next few weeks, this is gonna be our last show until the new year.
So it's been a long year.
So enjoyable, as I said earlier.
But we're gonna take a break and then I guess we plan on hitting the new year really hard.
We got a lot of things planned.
We got a lot of things happening.
So in the upcoming season, I want everyone to know, we are, we're planning some really good shows, exciting shows.
Even though we're taking a break,
We're still working on things for the upcoming season.
We're gonna have a lot of, I consider really wonderful guests.
We got a lot of exciting new features.
I know Bruce is doing a new look for the website.
I love the website he's already put up.
it's getting a ton of views.
I'm going to say this, I believe the show, the website, I think we had a total of like 14,000 views, which to me, if you told me a year ago,
you know, doing this show that we were going to get that kind of views, I would have never believed you.
So it makes us feel good.
I mean, that's what it's all about.
And it looks like our hard work is really paying off.
And I want you to know, you know, we're going to keep covering everything we can in Method.
You know, the good, the bad, and I guess I call it the not so pretty stuff, because there's some of that too.
I'm sure we're going to get into some of those things.
There is a lot going on with the city.
And I also want to make a point that, you know, we have invited Madame Mayor to join us on the show.
So we'll see if we can get her to come on.
I think that would be wonderful to have her join us.
We've also sent out invites to the entire council, the city council, and we're hoping that they will be joining us on the show.
I think they'd make for great shows.
And maybe we'll try the school committee as well, you know?
And I, you know, I want you to know we also got, we've got some
There's a lot of business activity going on in Method.
So, you know, a lot of restaurants we plan on doing some shows with, small business.
You know, we had Method Soap on.
We also, the Rotary Club, and we plan on having, there's a lot of good organizations.
And I'm telling you, they do really good work.
And I don't think they're, I don't think
a lot of people in Method are aware of all the things that go on, all the good things that happen, you know?
I mean, this Christmas, it's been, you know, the city has really come together, the fire department, Toys for Tots, and there's been so many, so many programs helping, you know, people helping people, and that's what it's all about.
It really is.
So, you know, that's what we got,
I'm looking forward to the new year.
I know Paul, Bruce, and Marco.
And what we're trying to do, I'm gonna put it out there, is we're trying to get a few more people to join us.
We can use some help.
Geez, I think it's quite a bit, there was quite a bit of work involved.
I know there was weeks we were doing like, you know, 50 hours a week dedicated to,
keeping everything going, keeping it all together.
So we're going to be looking for some help.
Hopefully we'll get some more people to join us.
And like I said, it's all volunteer.
So any kind of help would be appreciated.
So from all of us at Method Happenings, I want to thank Method.
I think we've been a benefit to the city of Medford, to the people.
And that was our original goal, just to be able to get information out.
One of the other people, I don't know how I forgot to mention them, but got to know Medford.
Another group, three wonderful women that are doing a great job.
with the, I guess you'd call it a newspaper.
It's not a print newspaper, but it's online.
If you haven't checked it out, we've had them on the show twice.
And I tell you that the shows, both shows we did with them did very, very well as far as people viewing.
So,
Just so you know, we plan on having them back.
We're trying to work something out with them, maybe on a regular basis, to focus on certain issues.
But I want to thank those wonderful ladies.
I want to wish everyone, we all want to wish everyone a Merry Christmas.
Really, happy holidays.
And everyone, just have a joyous new year.
You know, God bless you all.
And I mean that.
We all need to find some peace, slow down a little bit.
Enjoy family, friends, neighbors.
It's that time of year.
And it's good to see so much going on with people helping other people.
That's really what it's all about.
So once again,
My name is John Petrella, and I'm going to say this because if I don't, I'll get in a lot of trouble.
So remember, stay informed.
Thank you, everyone.
We'll see you soon.
Merry Christmas.
Hello.
I want to take a moment to thank all of our viewers for joining us this past year at Method Happenings, and I want to wish you all a very
Merry Christmas, happy holidays, and a peaceful and successful 2026.
Hi, I'm Marco.
I'm wishing you a very merry Christmas filled with love and laughter.
May the holiday season bring you peace and happiness.
As we head into 26, I hope the new year is filled with new adventures, great health, and much success.
Cheers to a wonderful year.
E per l'Italiani buon Natale e felice anno nuovo.
Hi, my name is Bruce, and I wanted to wish everybody here a Merry Christmas and a Happy New Year from everyone here at Medford Happenings.
We look forward to seeing you all in the new year.