Announcements, accolades, remembrances, reports, and records. The records of the meeting of March 10th, 2026 were passed to Councilor Callahan. Councilor Callahan, how did you find those records? I found them in order and I move to approve. On the motion of Councilor Callahan to approve the records of March 10th, 2026, seconded by? Seconded by Vice President Lazaro. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Callahan? Yes. Councilor Lemming? Yes. Councilor Maloney? Yes. Councilor Scarpelli?
Yes. Councillor Singh. Yes. Vice President Lazaro. Yes. President Beers. Yes. I'm in the affirmative, none in the negative. The motion passes. Reports of committees 25054 and 26059 offered by Councillor Lemming. Planning and Permitting Committee, March 17, 2026. Report to follow. Councillor Lemming.
Thank you. We went over the latest draft of the vacant building ordinance and pass it to a regular meeting pending a couple of additional conversations needed to have with city staff.
also went over plans for the cleanup portion of the Medford zoning with the Building Commissioner and the Director of the Office of Planning, Development and Sustainability. Motion to approve. On the motion to approve the committee report by Councilor Lemming, seconded by. Seconded by Councilor Sang. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Kellyanne. Councilor Lemming.
Yes. Councilor Malauulu. Yes. Councilor Scott Belli. Yes. Councilor Singh. Yes. Vice President Lazaro. Yes. President Beers. Yes. Seven the affirmative, none of the negative. The motion passes. Councilor, I think that someone's making a motion. We got an accommodation request. Is someone making that motion? So moved.
Yes, motion to take... Sorry, getting to the agenda packet online right now. Motion to suspend the regular rules and take paper 26063 out of order.
On the motion to suspend the rules to take paper 26063 out of order by Councilor Lemming, seconded by, seconded by Councilor Sang. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Callahan? Councilor Lemming? Yes. Councilor Maloney? Yes. Councilor Scarpelli? Yes. Councilor Sang? Yes. Vice President Lazaro?
President Beers. Yes, I'm in affirmative, none in the negative, the motion passes. 26063, resolution to update the ordinance establishing the Medford Commission for Persons with Disabilities. Whereas, the Medford Commission for Persons with Disabilities approved a proposed ordinance change that would remove exclusionary language concerning drug use, modernize terminology throughout the language of the ordinance, and clarify and positively define the commission's role. Now therefore, be it resolved by the Medford City Council that we update the ordinance establishing the commission for persons with disabilities. Councillor Lemming.
Thank you, Council President Behrs. So the Medford Commission for Persons with Disabilities has been very hard at work coming up with and agreeing on new language for their proposed ordinance. I don't want to take
Any credit away from them. I'm simply presenting the work that they have all spent a lot of time on and Want to obviously want to want to see this past
A letter from the Commission is included in the agenda packet, essentially summarizing what the changes are. We also have an updated draft of the new ordinance establishing the Medford Commissions for Persons with Disabilities.
The three essential changes here are removal of exclusionary languages, language concerning drug use, modernizing terminology, so the current ordinance contains words such as handicap, which has been widely abandoned in favor of disability or persons with disabilities.
and clarifying and positively defining the commission's role. The mayor is already aware of these changes and is reviewing the ordinance herself. My only recommendation at this stage would just be for a formal request for legal review, but otherwise everything seems in order and I would like to give
time for the members of the commission to speak and just talk about some of their own work on this and some of the background behind it. And I see that a couple of them are joining us on Zoom and I believe some folks are in the chamber as well. And that is what I got.
So I just would love to hear them talk about this. We have folks here from the commission and from our Office of Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion, both in the chambers and on Zoom. We do have two, seems like two comments from counselors before we go. So I'll go to Vice President Lazaro and Counselor Tseng, and then we will hear from our commissioners and our DEI office team. Counselor Lazaro.
Thank you Councillor Lemming for bringing this forward and to the commission and our DEI officer and director and office generally. I really appreciate especially it happens to be something that I have an interest in as the suggested change from the phrasing currently engaging in the illegal use of drugs and removing that from the
from the phrasing and the legal language is great because it's not necessary and stigmatizing. And I think there's a lot of ways we can scrub things from our local laws and our state laws. They just made a big change at the state level to this effect and the Department of Developmental Services
I can't remember what it's called, but they made a bunch of changes. They took out a bunch of words that were really derogatory, now have developed these derogatory meanings. Ultimately, of course, the hope for the world is that words don't have these meanings because you don't assign those meanings to the way people feel about each other. Then you stop having to change which words we use because
everybody treats each other better and then we don't have to keep doing this. But in the meantime, we can start with taking out some of these words that have these connotations and we can start using words that people choose for themselves and be more open and equity minded and focused on
person first language and lovely things like that. And I really appreciate the work that's gone into this. So I'm very much in favor and would motion to approve once we get to that point, but looking forward to hearing from the folks that have come tonight. So thank you. Thank you. Councilor Sang.
Thank you. Like Councilor Lazaro, I'm very grateful to the members of the commission who have put their work, put so much work into updating the language to reflect what we actually know to be true of the situation, that we shouldn't be stigmatizing drug use or using words that are outdated, that don't reflect the actual experience of what it is to be disabled in our community, to use language, to get rid of outdated language that
creates exclusion rather than inclusion in our community. And I am particularly inspired by the fact that this is grassroots-led, led by the members of the commission.
My only question is that in section 11, the effective date at the very end, there seems to maybe be a typo. It says, this ordinance shall take effect upon passage by the city council in approval by the mayor in accordance with the, and the sentence seems to drop off there. So I'm just wondering if the last few words after mayor are just extraneous or whether there was something that was supposed to come after those words.
Thank you. Thank you, Vice President Lazaro, Councilor Sang. We can hear from our commissioners and our wonderful staff team next. So if you want to come to the podium, I will get our microphone going for you. And if you are from the commission and planning to say something on Zoom, please raise your hand on Zoom.
You're on. Good evening. Good evening. Anthony Antriadola, 75 Lawrence Road, Medford, Mass, Medford High School, class of 1978, and a newly appointed commissioner on the Persons with Disability Commission here in Medford. And I want to, first off, thank Councilor Lemming for coming out to our meeting and bringing this ordinance forward.
You know, I think it's very important for the city to, you know, fix old language and ordinances that really don't reflect who we are now in Medford and what we want to be in the future, you know. The language in the old ordinance is something that I noticed when I was appointed to the commission. I wanted to know what I was getting into. And when I read it, I was very upset to see that, you know, how the language was used to kind
minimize people in our community rather than kind of go to their strengths, what people with disabilities bring to Medford, not what somewhere in the old ordinance it says we will work to solve the problems of the people with disabilities.
Our commission is here to help the city, to help the city remove barriers so people with disabilities can live, work, and thrive in Medford like everyone else.
Our city is 12% disabled. It's a very large number of people living in our community that have a disability. And by age 65, that number rises dramatically when people have an impaired mobility somewhere within 30% to 40% of our population of people age 65 or older. So it's a significant number of people in Medford with disabilities that need support and need to have
a commission that could actually represent them in ways that are significant. One of the main reasons I wanted to bring this forward is because there are a number of opportunities in the city where our commission can help, where, you know, especially in zoning and building, it's real important that, you know, things are done correctly the first time.
it would be a lot more expensive to retrofit our city after, say, oh, you know, this particular building is not accessible or we could have made this ramp this way or maybe we should have asked the people who struggle with getting around Method Square what we're going to do in Method Square. Because, you know, right now I think people with disabilities are the major residents
of Meffitt Square. I think there's more than 400 people living with disabilities right here in Meffitt Square. So they're a majority of the population. So when we look at things like Meffitt Square, it's real important that our commission can be involved and help in the process, help the council, help the administration, the mayor's office, or the DPW. We've worked with the Traffic Commission recently
to try to do something about this. Our major crosswalk in Medford Square is not accessible. It hasn't been for maybe 30 years. 30 years, there's a crosswalk that a person with a disability cannot make it safely to the other side.
And our commission went out and worked with the traffic commission to time the light. And it's not safe. And these are the kinds of things that we want to focus on. And we want to just update this ordinance and to let you all know that we're here. We want to be part of the changes in Medford. And I think we have a lot of experienced commissioners and people who want to give their time and energy
to make a better city. People 65, 40% have impaired mobility and you become 65 in the blink of an eye. This isn't for me or for us, it's for you guys, it's for the future. These changes that we're making in the city need to benefit a new,
new generation of people that have needs. And I'll stop rambling at the mouth, but I just want to thank you for all considering the changes and to thank the other commissioners and everyone that's been kind of supportive of this process. Thank you. Thank you, Anthony.
And I just wanted to thank you and John and Joseph and Cameron and Kate and Susan from the commission and Francis and Nick and their support from the Office of Diversity, Equity and Inclusion. If folks haven't had a chance to take a look, there's a fantastic letter about this ordinance update that you guys drafted as well. So that's available for the public to read on our website.
Is there anyone else from our Office of Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion or from the Commission for Persons with Disabilities? Frances is coming back. All right, great.
All right, Director Nwaje, how are you? I'm good, thank you. How are you all doing? Good, thank you for this. So, Nick was going to speak, but I think he's left me up here by myself. I want to say first and foremost, a huge thank you to the members for
that are currently on the commission. I want everybody to know and understand that it's not always about the numbers. It's about the passion and the effort that people bring. The commission is supposed to have nine people. For a long time, we floated with three. We're now up to six.
And this was really their work and their drive, their language. I just, you know, did the administrative piece, let's say. So I am, I'm truly, truly proud of that.
Something that Commissioner Andrew Toller said is really important. The original ordinance does include the Commission for Persons with Disabilities in so much work that gets done. And more and more recently, people have started reaching out to the commission. And it is important because it allows us to be able to
share the recommendations, which may not necessarily be well received. However, those recommendations are founded and guided by law. So we avoid the huge costly mistakes that we now have to go back to and, you know, fix, replace, or live with and act like we don't see. It is my hope that
the different departments, city council, folks continue to reach out to the commission. It is my hope that of the 400 plus that do live around Medford Square and of the 100 visually impaired members of the Medford community that we will expand.
And we will have people that bring all their unique skill sets, everything from whether you are a late adult amputee to being born with a physical disability or a cognitive disability. So I just want to say that I'm truly proud to work with all of the commissioners.
and proud to work with Mr. Karinge over here, who unfortunately was the one that almost got ran over when we were timing the traffic signals. So this is why those things are important, right? We can use technology. However, you actually have to be out there.
what a white cane user might require to cross the street. It's very different from what a person that is using a mobility device might need. So there I rest.
Thank you, Frances. And Nick, first off, thanks for putting yourself, to be frank, at risk to help make the city a better place. It shouldn't have to be that way. But you do so much for our community. And just really, that's not a great story to have to hear, but it is a story that people experience every day in our city. And that's something we need to change. So just wanted to say that before you have the floor.
And it's empowering, too, because I think it was four commissioners went out with the director of traffic and engineering. So it's actually on site. It's not done virtually or using technology. It's actually a physical exercise that they do.
Good evening, everyone. My name is Nicholas Kadinga. I work with Ms. Frances as the disability specialist here in City Hall. And I don't really have much to add, but I just want to just reiterate
what has already been said. Since I've been working here, I've had the express pleasure of working with this AmeriCorps commission. And truly, the work that they do is definitely something to be commended, to say the least.
I think I have grown as a resident of Medford having worked with them. I've also been able to relate a lot more.
with my own city because of working with them. And I think their work is extremely necessary for us to even continue as a city if we really care about those that live here.
Not to mention the sheer fact that whether you are born with a disability or not, the fact that we are humans made of bone and skin can easily find us in the place of having a disability, even if temporary.
at any given time in life. And so this AmeriCorps commission not only works for those that have been clearly born with a disability, but also whoever will happen upon life's chances for any reason.
With that, I just want to give my support to the commission and my thanks to City Council for hearing us out. Thank you. Thank you, Nick. And I just want to add, you brought up a good point, which is the dangers on our streets and sidewalks and lack of access to our buildings.
may be particularly serious for people with disabilities, but we are all people with bones and skin.
whether it's motor vehicles or whatever else, those dangers are for all of us. And if we can make our intersections safer, certainly focusing on making them safe for people with disabilities in our community, it makes it safer for everyone. And I think that's an important thing to recognize too. So we so appreciate the work that you guys in your office do and that the commission does. And I know a couple of counselors want to say some more, so I'll go to Vice President Lazaro and then Councilor Scarpelli. Vice President Lazaro.
Thank you. I just wanted to highlight something that Nick said that I thought was really important. Talking about crossing the street in Medford Square, something that we have talked about a lot in walking audits,
Last winter, after Dan Dill and Arthur Weber were killed in crosswalks, they were not disabled. They were killed in crosswalks by cars, and now the places that they were hit by cars have been fixed, and they are now both ADA accessible. But we shouldn't need somebody to get hit by a car to have a crosswalk fixed and made to be ADA accessible.
And that's, those are a couple of only, you know, a handful of.
crosswalks in Medford that are actually up to the standards that are supposedly required for crosswalks. And it highlights how interconnected disability services are to every other service in a city. Traffic, maintenance of roads and sidewalks, and something else that Nick said that really made me think is like, anybody, there are disabilities that are very visible, there are disabilities that are very invisible.
mental health, substance use disorder.
chronic pain, chronic illness, lots of things that happen to people that we don't see. And then you temporarily break a leg and then you cannot walk down the street and you can't cross the street, you can't get off of a sidewalk because there are no curb cuts. Or you have an infant in a stroller and you realize how difficult it is to traverse the city because the sidewalks are very uneven, there aren't curb cuts.
When we do walking audits, we talk a lot about like, it's so hard just to walk from one place to another in town. Imagine how hard it is if you're in a wheelchair, you have a mobility device, and it's like a lot of people don't have to imagine. They just don't walk places. Maybe they have to hire a car. It's an additional expense. Maybe they have to take the ride. Maybe they have to add in a ton of extra time every time they go anywhere. It's things that many, many people are not considering.
that it is our obligation as people who are governing the city and leading the city to always be considering. I appreciate the commission for calling it to our attention, but it needs to be at the forefront of our mind all the time. And things that improve, things that make life more accessible and livable for people with disabilities make life easier for everybody. It is an improvement that lifts all ships.
Um, so, uh, again, great appreciation. Um, much obliged, uh, all of us. Thank you, Vice President Lazaro. Councilor Scarpelli. Um, thank you, Mr President. I just want to take a second and just mention how proud I am
of one of my former students and one of my all-time idols in Nick Karenga. I met Nick many, many years ago with him and his mom at the McGlynn. And to see him today as a strong advocate for people with disabilities and standing up for what we should all be working hard to accomplish, I just wanted to just reach out and personally thank him for everything he's done. You make us very proud, Nick. So thank you.
Thank you, Councilor Scarpelli. All right, do we have a, I think we had a motion to express our support and refer to legal review, and then we'll get it back. Does that sound about right, Councilor Lemming? I think, obviously we could just motion to refer to legal review, but I think we all wanna, it seems like we all support this change as well, so might as well say it. Do you mean pass for a first reading and then refer to legal review?
I think just expressing support, like just saying that we're, we look favorably on this and we'd like legal review, but just indicating a little bit that we would like to see this done. Not a first reading vote quite yet, unless you think it's ready for that or I'm just not sure we're in the process. You know, obviously the commission drafted it and you mentioned that the mayor is taking a look at it. So, you know, is it?
And then we want to have the council look at it. So, um, yeah, sorry. I was, I was just trying to clarify the specifics of the, um, of, uh, of what the motion was, but yeah, refer, but yeah, I would, I would go with refer to, uh, refer to legal review with, uh, and, um, and also, and also express our support for it. Um, I would also like to thank,
Francis, Nick, and Anthony for coming to speak today as well as all the other commissioners who are here on Zoom and in person as well. Thank you once again for your work. With that, yeah, I'll make the motion to refer to legal and express the support for the ordinance.
All right, on the motion of Councilor Lemming, seconded by Councilor Callahan. Is there anyone else here or on Zoom who'd like to speak on this draft ordinance? Seeing none in the chambers and none on Zoom, Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Callahan. Councilor Lemming. Yes. Councilor Maloney. Yes. Councilor Scapelli.
Yes. Councillor Hussain. Yes. Vice President Lazaro. Yes. President Pierce. Yes. I have the affirmative, none in the negative. The motion passes. Thank you all for coming tonight on this paper.
All right, petitions, presentations and similar papers, 26060, petition for amendment to a common vixen's license, extended hours, Ho-Win Palace. To the honorable city council, councilors, the undersigned respectfully request an amendment for our operating hours for our common vixen's license to 1130 a.m. to 1 a.m. Monday through Sunday.
Brief explanation, reason, private events, friends and family gathering, regular maintenance, Christmas, Chinese New Year, staff meetings, and reason two, customers stay late after, quote, last call. And we have representatives of Hohen Palace here to speak to this license amendment, and we'd love to hear from them. Raymond, how you doing? Yeah, good to see you. Is that a good thing or a bad thing?
We try to request the extension operation now for the reason. We need some time, we need the area. After work, the staff meeting, we have late for past Chinese New Year, we need the area. And then since we open for grand opening, more than a year.
The people like to hang out a little bit after 11 o'clock, so we send the last call, and maybe light the atmosphere. Just in case, we cover. We're not open for the public business. Okay. Yeah, for a couple of hours, couple up. But you don't have to kick people out, right? I try, yeah. You check my record, and I went a couple times called Jack. Oh, boy.
All right, I'll recognize Councillor Scarpelli, Chair of the Subcommittee on Licensing, Permitting and Signs on this license. Thank you, Mr. President. I think Raymond's done an amazing job anywhere he's gone. He's been very reputable and supportive of whatever the city has needed. I've reached out to our building department and asked if we've had any concerns and issues.
With the establishment, there are none I've, um, um, I would, um, as we've been, uh, what we've been doing, uh, council president is offering, um.
awarding these hours for our businesses. Uh, and I think it's something that is now, um, um, good practice. And again, I think we'll move. I would recommend we move forward with this again with the 30 16 90 day review like we do with all other businesses. And, uh, we award, uh, the opportunity to home and palace to move forward with these hours. Everything is in the water, Mr President. So
Thank you. Thank you, Councillor Scarpelli. Any further questions from members of the council? Councillor Callaghan. I'm sorry, it's changing from what to, I see the hours that's being asked for. Oh, what are the current hours? What are the current hours? A couple hours, one o'clock in the morning. And right now you're at 11? Yes. Okay, so it's 11 p.m., it goes to 1 a.m. Yep. Yep, great. Well, it's not so far, but we try to extend to one o'clock in the morning.
Any further questions from members of the council? Seeing none, on the motion of Councilor Scarpelli to approve with 30, 60, 90 day review, seconded by. Seconded by Vice President Lazaro. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Callahan. Councilor Lemming. Yes. Councilor Maloney. You're muted, Liz.
Oh, sorry, yes. Councillor Scarpelli. Yes. Councillor Singh. Yes. Vice President Lazaro. Yes. President Pierce. Yes. Seven in the affirmative, none in the negative. The motion passes. Thank you. Thank you. Thanks, Raymond. Good luck. Thank you. We'll give those people a little more time at the bar, huh?
All right. Motions, orders, and resolutions 26061 offered by President Behrs, annual budget process for fiscal 27. We just discussed this at 6 p.m., but we have our annual budget for fiscal 27. This is for the city's general fund and the water sewer enterprise fund. Be it resolved by the city council that based on the budget ordinance and discussions with the administration, the city council and city administration will follow the following budget schedule for the fiscal 27 city budget.
By March 11th, City Councilors submit individual budget recommendations for consideration in Committee of the Whole. Just tonight, Tuesday, March 24th at 6 p.m., we had a Committee of the Whole meeting to discuss our budget recommendations. Right now is our City Council regular meeting to submit collective budget recommendation. On April 8th at 6 p.m., we'll have a joint meeting of the City Council and School Committee to receive a financial update and discuss the fiscal 27 budget process.
From April 15th to May 15th, the City Council will hold its preliminary budget meetings with department heads, and by Friday, May 31st, the Mayor will submit the comprehensive budget proposal to the City Council.
Be it further resolved that a draft schedule of preliminary budget meetings and committee of the whole is as follows, Wednesday, April 15th, Tuesday, April 21st, Tuesday, April 28th, Wednesday, April 29th, Tuesday, May 5th, Wednesday, May 6th, Tuesday, May 12th, and Wednesday, May 13th. Those are all at 6 p.m. We may not use all of them, but they are available to us.
That is the motion and schedule. At 6 p.m. we talked about our budget recommendations, and I think really at this point the path forward is, you know, I went through our compiled collective recommendation. It seems like much of what we included last time still has not happened, so we want to keep recommending that the city do those things.
I'll just quickly go over those for folks who weren't able to be in our last meeting. The first recommendation is that we maintain full level service funding for our public schools and city departments. So that means that we do not have service cuts at our schools or our city.
And then the second one is to fund our assessing department to implement the residential exemption. And also I'm going to incorporate a bit of Councilor Scarpelli's recommendation around making sure that we can support our seniors, veterans, people with disabilities, folks who may need assistance in accessing exemptions and other assistance from our assessing department.
Third item is increasing funding for our DPW and facilities for improved street repair and safety, tree planting, and capital improvements. That includes a number of items including funding street repair and safety improvements, additional traffic engineers and transportation planning, more re-striping, patching of potholes, fixing sidewalks, installing and maintaining road safety markings, and bike-related equipment.
Funding our urban tree management plan, enabling volunteers to finally get our volunteer tree planting program off the ground so that we can start putting more trees up in our neighborhoods. And funding to improve snow removal, including priority sidewalks and bus stops moving forward to understand how we can implement a priority sidewalk clearing program. Funding our citywide inclusion specialist.
funding the fire department dive team training and equipment.
And then there were four new items to be included. One was addressing the increase in part-time librarian pay and supporting our library staff, additional funding for arts and culture organizations, and making sure that our Medford Family Network, which is facing a serious funding gap, moves forward with the funding that it needs to continue its amazing work. And then finally, funding our city messenger and council assistant.
So that's the general outline I have I don't have the final document obviously because we just talked about it you know around 615. But I'm interested in hearing from counselors what they would prefer in terms of a process going forward. I could.
take that outline, write it up and have the clerk submit that to the mayor and also share that with members of the council. I could also draft that and have the clerk distribute it for comments by members of the council before we submit it, or I could write a draft and we could discuss that at an upcoming meeting. So whichever of those three options folks would prefer, I'm happy to do. Councilor Scarpelli. Council President, I think that you've done your due diligence having these pre-budget meetings, having the council,
share what our wishes are. I think we discussed that. I think that the sooner that it's in the administration's hands, the sooner we get some answers so we can move this budget process forward. So I would go with your first option. If my colleagues would support that, that's what I would move forward with that assessment, Mr. President.
Great. Thank you, Councilor Scarpelli. Any other thoughts on what option folks would prefer we take? And of course, all of your recommendations will be included along with this collective recommendation memo. Everyone seems to be, oh, Councilor Callahan.
I will second what Councillor Scarpelli is suggesting. I feel quite comfortable. I think we had a great discussion. All of our recommendations will also be included. I think that getting it to the mayor soon would be good. So I'll just second what Councillor Scarpelli said.
on the motion of Councilor Scarpelli, seconded by Councilor Callahan to have me do the work. Any further discussion?
Seeing none, Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. I think that motion is actually to have me write up the recommendations and submit them to the mayor, submit to the mayor through the clerk. And I will put them on an upcoming meeting agenda so that we can, just so that the public can see them next time we talk about the budget schedule as well. So they're attached to the budget documents and maybe we can get it out with the newsletter and whatnot as well. That's not all part of the motion, but that's what I'll do. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Kelly. Councilor Lemming.
Yes. Councilor Malauulu. Yes. Councilor Scarpelli. Yes. Councilor Singh. Yes. Vice President Lazaro. Yes. And President Pierce. Yes. Having the affirmative, none the negative, the motion passes. 26062, resolution to hold a meeting and request an update on hiring an inclusion specialist offered by Councilor Scarpelli. Whereas the City Council had a subcommittee meeting on education and culture to discuss the possible creation of an inclusion specialist over a year ago,
Whereas parents and community members ask for guidance for support for our family members with special needs after high school, whereas the city council has not yet received updates dealing with an inclusion specialist, be it resolved that the city council schedule an education and culture subcommittee meeting and invite city administration to update the council with the process of creating the position of an inclusion specialist. Councilor Scarpelli. Thank you, Mr. President. I think this is self-explanatory. I think that our parents that came out and spoke with
I know Councilor Kelly and Councilor Lemming at 1st and then we went off to a subcommittee meeting. And, um, um, I think that it's important that at that meeting, we talked about programming for the recreation department and making sure that we supported our special needs community. And I think that with the Tri-City partnership, we've done that. Um,
We have done some amazing things between Somerville, Malden, and especially Medford with Kevin Bailey on that side. But what we're hearing as our residents that are aged out of the high school process, they are left to fend for themselves, in essence, and not really having
a person or a department that they can really turn to, uh, with comfort and looking for guidance when it comes to options for, uh, future living arrangements or job placements, or, or one parent said just, just, um, just the fact of feeling like they belong. Um, and that speaks volumes. So I think we need to move this, um, this agenda item forward to our subcommittee.
And ask the representative for the mayor's office. I know she at the time last year, it was easy just to check a box and say, we'll give it this this department. Well, I won't call out any department, but.
some of these departments are understaffed and overworked drastically. So just to drop this initiative on an under under, um, um, understaffed and overworked department is just checking a box. And to me, that's not acceptable. So, um, I'd like to see some movement. I know that we've had parents that would like to join us at that meeting, Mr. President. And, um,
As soon as we can sit and talk, I'd like to move that subcommittee meeting forward, especially before the budget cycle starts. So I appreciate it. Thank you, Councilor Scarpelli. On the motion of Councilor Scarpelli to refer this paper to the Education and Culture Committee, to invite a representative from the mayor's office and relevant departments, as well as parents who have reached out to us on this matter. Is there a second and is there further discussion?
Second. Second from Councillor Lemming. Further discussion? Seeing no further discussion from members of the Council, is there anyone from the public who'd like to speak on this paper by Councillor Scarpelli? All right, seeing none, Councillor Scarpelli, Vice-President Lazaro and I will work on getting that scheduled. Thank you. Thank you, Vice-President. Yes, Vice-President Lazaro.
I was just going to say you're welcome. It's not worth it. You're very welcome. You're welcome, George. You're welcome, George. On the motion of Councillor Scarbelli, seconded by Councillor Lemming. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councillor Kelly. Councillor Lemming. Yes. Councillor Maloney. Yes. Councillor Scarbelli. Yes. Councillor Singh. Yes. Vice President Lazaro. Yes.
Yes, 70 affirmative, none negative, the motion passes. Communications from the Mayor, 26050 submitted by Mayor Brianna Longo Kern. Special legislation to remove police chief and deputy positions from civil service.
February 19th, 2026, dear President Behrs and members of the City Council, I respectfully request and recommend that your honorable body vote to authorize the Mayor, on behalf of the City, to petition the Massachusetts General Court for special legislation, substantially in the form as set forth below, relating to the exemption of the positions of Police Chief and Deputy Police Chief from the Civil Service Law, General Laws Chapter 31.
Provided, however, that the general court may make clerical or editorial changes of form only to the bill unless the mayor approves amendments to the bill before enactment by the general court, and provided further that the mayor is hereby authorized to approve amendments which shall be within the scope of the general public objectives of this petition. Special act would provide as follows. An act exempting the positions of police chief and deputy police chief in the city of Medford from the civil service law, being enacted by the Senate and House of Representatives and general court assembled and by the authority of the same as follows.
Section 1, the positions of police chief and deputy police chief in the city of Medford shall be exempt from Chapter 31 of the general laws. Section 2, this act shall not impair the civil service status of a person holding a position described in Section 1 on the effective date of this act. Section 3, this act shall take effect upon passage. Thank you for your attention to this matter. Respectfully submitted, Brianna Lungo Kern, Mayor. Councillor Scarpelli.
Uh, thank you, Mr President. And, um, after last week's meeting, I know we talked and we were waiting for a representative from the city to answer any of our questions. I received a phone call from, um, from Harold McGillivray, who's the president of the I believe the, um, leadership union at the police department. This is this was part of the negotiation that all parties agreed on.
So all the unions do support this initiative. So I would ask my fellow colleagues to move forward with this motion and this resolution for the fact that this was the wishes and the understanding of all the men and women in our Method Police Department that use this for negotiations during their last contract completion.
I hope you all join me with approving this. Thank you. Thank you, Councillor Scarpelli. Vice President Lazaro.
I appreciate that context, Councillor Scarpelli. That is, I think, the sticking point for all of us, not to speak for the rest of the council, but the sticking point for many, many of the councillors last time was that we didn't, we couldn't ask any questions of the administration. We just kind of, it was kind of plopped there for us. So we weren't sure what it was.
what the story was and who all was in favor of it and why. But I do believe that removing the chief from civil service and the two deputy chiefs potentially, potential deputy chiefs from civil service opens up the field to a wider group of candidates, allows different, all different
qualified candidates to come and apply for the job and it's best practice and it's just it's just a good thing for the city and the department and all parties seem to be in favor of it. So I'm glad to know that and I would be happy to move forward with this. Thank you. Thank you Councilor Zaro. We do have our chief and.
Here, I don't know if Chief Buckley, you want to? I have a question, which is just generally, how did we arrive here? Why was it important that this happened through collective bargaining? And, you know, generally, what are the implications going forward? I just wanted to understand that from you.
Good evening, Jack Buckley, Chief of Police. So the question is how do we arrive at it? So it came about through the collective bargaining process with the Superior Officers Union and the city and the mayor's office. And I think it's something that the city has been planning to kind of change the future of the police department over the last, I've been in the office now eight years and there's been a lot of work being done to professionalize the police department from where it was. Like every leader should,
work to grow their organization, and this is part of that next step. Since it is a civil service position, and it does impact the future of the members of the Superior Officers Union, it becomes a collective bargaining agreement, right? So they would have to negotiate over those impacts. And so the city did that with the unions, and the unions did agree to go forward. And so that's why it became part of the collective bargaining agreement and settled in there. The benefits of it, I mean,
I think a catalyst, let me go back a little bit. One of the catalysts is that there was a recent change of civil service law in 2025. So the best way I could kind of explain this is in 2018, we had three captains. Civil service law stated that an auto,
to have a test for the next chief of police, you have to have four individuals in the grade below chief of police eligible to take that test. So they didn't have it, and it opened up to lieutenants. So instead of having three candidates eligible and competing for the job, they had an additional nine. So that was 12. It allowed me to compete for the job, and I ended up being a successful candidate, so I think it was the right process. But now, with the change of civil service law, the law only is two.
And at any given time, you know, a captain, you've got to imagine, is a senior officer, right? They've been around for many, many years. And at any given time, if you only have two qualified candidates, you restrict the amount internally in-house, how many you could have. And it excludes, like, my lieutenants. And a lot of lieutenants do a lot of good work and are qualified to sort of compete for that job.
So internally, that was one of the driving points that was restricting a lot of internal offices from competing. But externally, I think professionally, we know that you want to open this job up to the best candidate you could possibly find. This is not getting, this job is not getting easier, it's getting tougher, right? And you want to find somebody with qualified and there's some experience that could come in here and bring, sometimes bring new ideas. It's not always the case, but if you have that option,
It's why you should look at it. And most police departments in cities, right, larger police departments do this and work in that manner. So hopefully that answered the question. Yeah, it's a good helpful answer. And my only other question, this mentions deputy chief. Yes. Is that a?
It would be a new position. We do not have a deputy position. So a deputy chief would fall right under the rank of chief of police. So currently, as chief of police with three captains, this would be chief of police, deputy chief, and three captains, should they fill it. There's no guarantee that the city ultimately will fill it. But as I said, this job is getting tougher. And I'm not getting younger, but as a lot of you know, I got sick this past year.
It's always beneficial to have somebody who's ready to step into that executive role. And you have three captains, and they're all busy doing a lot of other things. And if you can have somebody step in, and so from my learning experience, having a deputy chief who kind of can take my place in a lot of different instances, then it's beneficial for the police department. That's why a lot of departments do that. Yeah. I liked that we were doing kind of a triumvirate
you know, Roman Republic style approach there to fill in for you, but no. I just want to understand because I was like, I don't know that position now and I wasn't sure if that was a quirk of the law or if that was an intent to create a new position or it's just an option to have that position outside of civil service in the future or if it was even maybe a proposal that there be two captains and a deputy chief or something like that. So I just wanted to understand a little bit.
I would push strongly for a deputy chief. And again, it's budget issues and all this sort of stuff, because it helps, obviously, relieve some of the burden for me, because I put a lot on my three captains. And then for me to keep putting things on, I feel, when I left my illness, I felt guilty that I was leaving a lot into people's hands. And I just think it's beneficial for this police department to have that extra resource at that executive level, as I said.
It's highly beneficial, and that's why most police departments run with the deputy chief. Okay. All right. Well, thank you. That was my question. Do we have any more questions from any members of the council? We had a motion from Councilor Scarpelli to approve, seconded by Council Vice President Lazaro. Is there any discussion by members of the public on this item? Seeing none, Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Callahan.
Councilor Lemming? Yes. Councilor Maloney? Yes. Councilor Scarpelli? Yes. Councilor Singh? Yes. Vice President Lazaro? Yes. President Pierce? Yes. I have the affirmative, none of the negative. The motion passes. Thank you. I thank you all for your time. I appreciate it. Thank you. Thanks, Captain.
All right, we have here now 26064 offered by Mayor Brantley O'Kern. Request for food truck permits for Charlie Dogs, April through August at Hormel Stadium. I'm not gonna read all of this, but I will recognize Councilor Scarpelli, Subcommittee on Licensing, Permitting and Signs. And I do see someone here from Boston Glory, which this is for their league. So Councilor Scarpelli.
Thank you, Mr. President. Just for a quick synopsis, I know people have been reaching out saying, George, why do we, why does the council do this? And I think that it started back in, perhaps you remember, during the pandemic, we had to protect our brick and mortar businesses and
from outside vendors to come in from outside the city without putting in the proper paperwork and due diligence and commitment to the community.
So we really use that to protect our brick and mortar businesses. And this is the process that we look at and that we've been working with, and I think it's been working fine. We did have a question. The reason why it was brought up, because the petition looked like it was from April to August. So it looked like it was, but it's just a breakdown is for the Boston Glory games, I believe. So I believe it's Sundays or Saturdays throughout,
uh, April through, um, through August. So, um, I see everything in order. All the paperwork is in order. I would move approval, Mr President. It's common practice now, and it provides a great experience for all of our residents that have the opportunity to go watch Glory game over at Hormel. So I move approval.
Thank you, Councillor Scarpelli. And it looks like we have Luke from the Boston Glory here. Luke, I don't know if you want to say anything about your season and how many games, how many weekends you'll be here and what, you know, what Charlie Dogs is. But if you'd like to speak to that, you're more than welcome to. And I can ask you to unmute. Yeah, thanks. So yeah, we'll have six to seven games depending on the playoffs at Hormel this year.
First one is April 25th, I believe. Last possible one is the first weekend of August, but it might end up being end of July based on the playoffs. And yeah, Trolley Dogs is the vendor that comes and serves food to all our fans. It's a great time. I highly suggest y'all come. Awesome. Well, thank you, Luke. On the motion of Councilor Scarpelli to approve, seconded by? Seconded by Councilor Callahan. Do you have a comment? Councilor Callahan.
I have attended the Boston Glory events, and I have eaten trolley dogs, and I have to highly recommend it for everyone. I'm excited personally to approve of this. Great. Thank you, Councilor Callahan. On the motion, Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Callahan? Yes. Councilor Lemming? Yes. Councilor Malay? Yes. Councilor Scarpelli? Yes.
Councilor Singh? Yes. Vice President Lazaro? Yes. President Beers? Yes. I have the affirmative, none the negative. The motion passes. Public participation. To participate outside of Zoom, please email rleco at menford-ma.gov. Are there any people who'd like to speak in public participation? You can raise your hand on Zoom or approach the podium in the chambers.
Seeing none, is there a motion? On the motion to adjourn by Vice President Lazaro, seconded by? Seconded. Seconded by Councilor Sang. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Callahan? Yes. Councilor Lemming? Yes. Councilor Mullain? Yes. Councilor Scarpelli? Yes. Councilor Sang? Yes. Vice President Lazaro? Yes. President Pierce? Yes. Having the affirmative, none of the negative, the motion passes and the meeting is adjourned.