[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, it's 602 and seems like everybody's here.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we'll get started.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have a special meeting of the Medford school committee on August 21 2024 6pm.
[SPEAKER_01]: being held remotely via Zoom.
[SPEAKER_01]: The purpose of the meeting is provided in the agenda section below.
[SPEAKER_01]: This meeting is being recorded.
[SPEAKER_01]: The meeting can be viewed live on the Medford Public Schools YouTube channel, through Medford Community Media, or on your local cable channel, Comcast Channel 9, 8, or 22, and Verizon Channel 43, 45, or 47.
[SPEAKER_01]: The meeting will be recorded.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, since the meeting will be held remotely, participants can log or call in by using the following information.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Zoom link is on the website and the meeting ID is 995-3084-9504.
[SPEAKER_01]: Questions or comments can be submitted during the meeting by emailing medfordsc at medford.k12.ma.us.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those submitting questions or comments must include the following information, your first and last name, your Medford street address, your question or comment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Roll call member Rousseau, please.
[SPEAKER_00]: Certainly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Bradley.
[SPEAKER_02]: Present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Graham.
[SPEAKER_00]: here member and Tapa here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Remember all of high here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Remember Reinfeld here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Remember so present Mayor Lungo here.
[SPEAKER_01]: President seven present zero absent.
[SPEAKER_01]: If we only rise to salute the flag, pledge allegiance to the flag, the United States of America, which stands one nation under God with liberty and justice for all.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we have executive session pursuant to Chapter 30A, Section 21.2, to conduct strategy and preparation with non-union personnel or contract negotiations with non-union personnel, which is our superintendent of schools.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there a motion to go into executive session?
[SPEAKER_01]: Motion to enter executive session.
[SPEAKER_01]: Second.
[SPEAKER_01]: Member Reinfeld, seconded by Member Graham.
[SPEAKER_01]: Roll call, please.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Braley?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Graham?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Intoppa?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Olapade?
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Reinfeld?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Members of the guest, Mayor Lungo-Kirk?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, I'm in the affirmative, zero in the negative.
[SPEAKER_01]: Motion to go into executive session has been approved.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do we want to tell anybody who's watching that we will not be returning at the end of executive session?
[SPEAKER_01]: Correct, we are going into executive session and we'll adjourn in executive session.