We're all in this together. Once we know that we are, we're all stars and we see that. Hi, I'm Gigi Braga here with MHTV 15 and today we're here with Mr. Klein who works in the guidance department here at Medford High. How are you today, Mr. Klein? I'm good, thanks for having me. Excited to be here.
So we've been hearing about this new post-graduation program called Year Up. Do you mind telling us a little bit about it? Sure. So Year Up is a program for students who either have their GED or their high school diploma. And they're looking, it's for students who maybe going to college right after high school is not an option for a couple reasons. So the program is a year-long program. It's completely free for students to do.
And what it is, it's broken up into two different sections. So in the first six months, students are taking classes that they're getting paid to. But these classes aren't your typical algebra history classes. These classes are specifically designed to make them get skill sets they need to be able to be successful in a professional setting. So students are going to learn how to dress professionally, how to write a professional email, how to network, how to arrive on time. And they're going to learn these while they're also learning a specific skill set that's used in the corporate world.
And so that skill set is either they're going to learn information technology, they're going to learn finance, or they're going to learn about customer service and sales. And so in the first six months, they're going to take these classes, and they're going to be getting paid on a weekly basis. And the second six months, they're going to be doing a actual internship at an organization.
So they're going to work at an organization like Google, or Fidelity, or State Street, or the Harvard Business School. And so the idea is that they're getting real world experience. They're building really actual skill set that they can use in the real world. Great. And so with this program, do students just after they do this one year program, is that it? Do they look for a job, or can they apply themselves?
into the college world and reapply themselves into college and get in through there and continue their education? Yeah, it's a great question. So a really huge benefit of this program is that students are actually earning college credits when they're in this program. So when students go into this program, after they complete it, they're going to come out with 30 college credits, which
That's the equivalent of a year in a four-year college. And so what students do after that, they're either going to go directly into a four-year college, or they're going to go directly into the workforce in the field that they were working in. So I think the statistics from Year Up is that 90% of the students who do this program
are either matriculating to a four-year college or they are working in their field within three months of graduating from a year up. So it's really, it's up to the students either way, but if they're looking to go to college after this and they're looking for an affordable way to get college credits, it's a great option. Or if it's students who just want to get a professional skill set and go directly into the workforce, it's a great option for those students as well.
Awesome, and now let's say students are interested here at Medford High or at any other school and they're interested in this program, how do they go about getting more information on this? Do they come and see you? Is there a website that they attend? How do they go about that? Yeah, so they should, they can look on our website medfordhighguidance.com, but definitely go talk to your guidance counselor, and I don't care if you're a freshman, sophomore, junior, or senior.
If you're a senior, definitely come talk to us. What will happen is we'll put you on the list that you're interested. Year Up is going to come talk to interested students in April and then tell them how to apply. And if students are interested, go talk to your guidance counselor and your guidance counselor or I are going to help you step-by-step do the entire process for this.
If you are a freshman, sophomore, or junior and you think this might be a good fit for you, come talk to us as well. Because I think the idea is we want students to have really options after high school that they're really, really excited about. And so if you're a sophomore and you don't know what you want to do, we want to give you this information so that we can set you up in being like, what can you be doing right now to put you on a path to ensure that you can get into a program like UROP?
Sounds like a great fit. So remember, if you're interested in this URO program, come see Mr. Klein or any of your guidance counselors. Or check out the website at medfordhighguidance.com. Yep, you got it. So check it out. See you soon. Hi, I'm Ms. Donlan. The Mustang Report question of the week is, what's my middle name? In case you stopped, in case you needed a hint,
It starts with the letter L. This is called aquaculture, when you raise fish in kind of an enclosed setting like this. And this is a multidisciplinary project where we're working with the robotics and engineering from the boat, also the culinary.
is to raise as many of these fish to edible size as possible, as we can. And by the end of the term, the culinarians have prepared them for us. We're going to eat them. Really? Yep, so these are food grade tilapia. Tilapia? Yep. It's a freshwater fish. It's probably one of the most commonly farmed fish in the world. The ancient Egyptians were farming tilapia.
We expect that it takes tilapia about six to seven months to grow from basically this size to full size. They'll be about maybe 12 to 14 inches long when they reach full size. They're about almost halfway there. They're about probably four to six inches right now.
Mommy, Mommy, where's Daddy? He should be on his way home now. Are you okay, sir? Sir? I'm sorry, I didn't mean to do that. Sir, are you okay? You okay?
Are you okay? Help! Help! Get an ambulance! Quickly! Okay, the doctor should be coming in now. So Rodrigo, I have some bad news for you. You have a brain tumor. So what does that mean? It means that it's spread throughout your body and you can no longer treat it. How long does my dad have to live? Unfortunately, only three months. But if you came in sooner, we could have treated it. So I'll give you guys some space now, okay? I'm sorry.
We should put our seatbelts on, guys. No, we're fine. No, it's fine. You're right. Victoria, why aren't you answering my Snapchat? Oh, I will. Don't answer her Snapchat. You're driving. No, she's fine. She's fine. It's just me. No, that's not safe. It's fine. No! Don't touch my stuff! You're gonna get us all killed! I'm not.
Blue, white, let's fight! Blue, white, let's fight!
Blue, silver, white, we're number one! We're number one! Woo! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We're number one! We