Welcome, everyone, to the City of Memphis Traffic Commission meeting. Today is Tuesday, January 14th, 2025, and the time is 5.03 p.m. The meeting will now come to order. Alva, can you please call the roll call of commission? Commissioner McGiven? Commissioner Hunt? Commissioner Brzezinski? I'm here.
Chief Buckley. Present. All commissioners present, we have a quorum. Also present this evening is Secretary to the Traffic Commission, Ms. Alba Erickson. We have two Midford Police Traffic Sergeants, Sergeant Larry Rogers and Sergeant Jordan Canava in the room here with me. Special Projects Coordinator Jim Silva is present. And I am very happy to introduce you all to Ms. Sarah McDermott, our new Director of Parking.
Sarah, before we get started, you want to say a few words, a little introduction. I know there's a little bit of an audience here, but you can kind of welcome to your first Traffic Commission meeting. The floor is yours, so say a brief word. Hi, I started December 16th. I'm happy to be here and participate in things relevant to our department in any way. If I can help in any way, let me know. Reach out.
Thank you, Sarah. Okay, so the minutes of the December 10, 2024 Traffic Commission meeting have been distributed. It seems to be in order, and the commissioners have reviewed them and have questions. I will entertain questions now. Otherwise, a motion to accept and approve. I have no questions. Sean, Commissioner McGiven? Motion to approve.
Second. On the motion of Commissioner McGibbon to approve the minutes of the December 10, 2024 Traffic Commission meeting, seconded by Commissioner Brzezinski-Alvaroco. Commissioner McGibbon? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski? Yes, ma'am. Commissioner Buckley? Yes. Commissioner Hunt? Yes.
On the vote of 4-0, the voting is approved and the minutes are accepted. New business, we start off January of 2025 with our meeting schedule. Do we have it all? I don't have it in front of me.
Yep, the only change is in November. It's a 3rd Tuesday. The 11th is Bedford state. Okay, so the meeting we will post this publicly. I believe it already has been posted. I believe the commissioners all have it. The meetings will take place monthly throughout 20, 25, January 14th, February 11th, March 11th, April 8th, May 13th, June 10th, September 9th.
October 14th, November 18th, which is an asterisk because the Tuesday prior would be our normal meeting, but that will be Veterans Day, correct? And then December 9th, 2025. So if the commissioners approve of that monthly meeting, I will entertain a motion to accept the meeting schedule.
Can you remind us chief is the reason that the summer months aren't on there has something to do with our rules and regulations or the ordinance that we haven't edited and not because we're choosing not to meet during the summer.
Yeah, correct. We haven't met in the summer months, July and August. I don't think they've ever met the traffic. I do believe once we had a special meeting, but in a regular scheduled meeting, July and August have been excluded from this. And it is per regulation. Right. It's very old fashioned to me to skip the summer months. And so I wanted to make sure there was a reason we were doing it and not because we always have.
Correct. We can look at that as we go, because we are, again, this is longstanding, but we have been reviewing the regulations, just time and effort to get caught up in those. But as it's been posted publicly, do we have a motion to accept this schedule? So moved. Motion or commission are given, seconded by?
All right, I'll second it. I just don't like it. I was on mute. Sorry, I couldn't say it. I second it by Commissioner Hunt. I have a roll call to accept the scheduled meetings for January, for 2025. Commissioner McGiven? Yes. Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski? Yes. Chief Buckley?
Yes, a vote of four to nothing, the schedule has been approved. Okay, 2025-02, handicap parking sign for Marie Alana Chalabi, 105 Yeomans Avenue. Is the petitioner present? Sergeant, can you see and unmute her? She's not gonna be on? No. Okay. She doesn't have a computer.
Could you pull up Dunbar at Yeomans, please? Okay, so for the record and to the commissioners, Ms. Chalabi has been in contact with the Secretary to the Traffic Commission and to with the Sergeant, Sergeant Rogers, and she does not have access to a computer or the ability to call in.
but we have spoken with her and we have reviewed her situation. Alba, while they're pulling this up and sharing the screen for the residents, all the paperwork in order. All the paperwork is in order. Okay, thank you. Chief, I went by twice and I was unable to get a hold of her. I believe she does have a medical condition that she's out a couple of times a week, I don't wanna get into it. She's asking for the space on Dunbar Ave.
Even though her house faces Yeomans, she goes through the back door. You want to tell me where it is? All the way down to the side of the cell. You're not sharing your screen. I'm going to share the screen. Sorry. That white car is her right-hand side, I think. Yeah. All right. Let us know when you can see.
Traffic. Is that good? Did that come over? There's the house. Yes, now we can see it. All right. Can you go to Yeoman's house? That's Yeoman's right there. It's the last house on Dunbar. So right here? No, you just had the house. OK. Oh. Turn. That's the house right there. Oh, you're pointing.
Sometimes it should be a garage then. It does. Right here, there's a garage. Okay. All right. So, she's looking for probably where that white car is. There is a driveway. She cannot use it. I believe she rents and she goes through the back door. So, she's requesting it to be right there on Dunbar Ave. I think that's her car. This white one. Can you go down just a little further and show the driveway?
what there is of a driveway that's not really a driveway. Be right there. So the petitioner is requesting a spot somewhere where those two vehicles are parked right now on your screen. So often one of the things we look for is why aren't they using their driveway. It does not look like a handicapped accessible driveway in any sense of that if she's
Obviously, she's got a handicap placard because she would need that to use this space. Correct. Alicia, I believe she went. She's not allowed to park on the driveway.
Okay. And then it's very, very close to a public district. And so for her to have the awareness that if for some reason somebody else with a handicapped placard chose to use that, although honestly why they wouldn't actually go further into the square and use the handicapped spots that are really in Haynes Square, I don't know.
but she should be aware that this would not be dedicated to her vehicle but would be available to anybody with a handicap placard. Agreed and understood. Do we think that anybody has spoken with her to make sure she knows the rules? Did you speak with her? I've spoken with her, yes. She's been in several times. Okay, so she's been in here several times and she's aware and we will restate those conditions to her.
Right. And did we look at whether there is appropriate space there? Are we actually, are people using this as two spaces and adding the handicapped would make this to be just one for her? And I can see two vehicles. Oh, no, there's more space there, isn't there? Yeah, there's more space there probably even for an additional vehicle. Those seem to be crowded and they're just in that picture. I don't know why they're parked with that. Is there a high hill?
By the tree? In front. I'm going to go up now. I don't think so. I didn't see one. Looking to make sure there's nothing else on that sidewalk. Chief, I didn't observe any other running any gaps. Okay. All right, so it seems still straightforward. Let me, if none of the other commissioners have anything, let me ask, anyone in the public wish to speak on behalf of this petition?
Is your hand? Looks fine to me. Oh, screen. Thank you. Seeing none, back to the commissioners. A motion on this?
I support a motion. I like Alicia's point. I just always like to confirm with the people that they understand it's not for them specifically. That's pretty standard at this point in time and we're doing this for everyone. Okay. I'd make the motion to approve unless there's any other comments. It looks like Alicia's got her hand up maybe. Oh, that was an accident. Sorry.
have a second to approve petition 2025-02?
Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski? Yes. Chief Buckley? Yes. On the vote of four to nothing, the motion is approved 2025-03, Hennie Peck, excuse me, HP sign for Miss Marie Ketley-Barron, 5 Cherry Street. If the petitioner is present, please raise your hand, make yourself known, and unmute yourself. She's gonna get on, Chief. We set it so that people can't unmute themselves. We have to
Yeah, I'll click on them if they're here, but this petitioner. If you just called, she can't. She can't be here as well, but we can speak on behalf of that. Okay, so Ms. Barron has just called the station and indicated that she cannot get on also because of lack of access. Can we pull that up and share the screen with the 5 Cherry Street Police Sergeant? Chief, I went down and spoke with Ms. Barron today. She's elderly. She walked with the cane.
She's requesting a space in front of her house, one for her car, and also for the ride that picks her up several times a week. There was no driveway at this house on either side. She's requesting one spot? One spot. Okay. Further up, right? So what if I'm sharing her door is on the right side? You're not sharing.
coming your way? The other way. No, the one to the left, and that's her door right there. No, go back. This door? Yep, that's her door right there.
So we should be looking for the space right where that car is. Jump up a little. Okay. That driveway is to the house next door, correct? Or the apartment? Yeah, house next door. So no driveway, limited frontage, curb frontage, but there is enough for an HP sign or a parking spot.
Now all the paperwork has been submitted and is in order? Yes, Chief. Paperwork has been submitted and is in order? It seems it makes sense. Just to be clear that she has a vehicle that's going to use it, which we've discussed in the past, that pickup and drop-offs for the ride would be like a drop-off zone, not a handicapped parking spot.
And if she's parked in it, then where's the ride going to park? But that's neither here nor there. I'm fine with it. It's the other side. Any other commissioners' comments? I do want to open it up for public comment, or if anyone has anything. Let me just see. Anyone in the public wish to comment on this petition?
Seeing none, I go back to the commissioners. This same as before, just educating our citizens about what they can be used for and then that they're not exclusive. I would just encourage us to make sure that she understands completely, particularly as Alicia pointed out with the ride, that technically the ride can't use that spot.
Yeah, so you've had a little bit of a conceding with her about yes. And that's correct. Yep. Okay. And then we will, I will make sure that both advisements are made to the petitioner from the traffic department here of the traffic offices. Do I have a motion to approve 2025 03? Motion to approve.
Motion of Commissioner Hunt, seconded by? I'll second. Commissioner Brzezinski, I'll have a roll call, please. Commissioner McGiven? Yes. Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski?
Yes. Chief Buckley? Yes, on the vote of 4-0, the petition is approved. 2025-04 HP sign for Miscondolo 88 Circuit Road. I believe the petitioner is present. Can we...
And while we're doing that, Albert, is the petition in order and paperwork received? Everything is in order. Yes. Paperwork is in order. Thank you. Hello. Hi. Hi, Ms. Cadilby. We've received your petition. Would you like to speak about it and tell us a little bit about your need? Sure.
So I do have a driveway, but my driveway is extremely narrow. It's concrete with walls on each side, and I'm only four foot eight. I have sarcoma cancer, and it makes it difficult for me to walk.
But because of the incline in the driveway, my feet don't hit the ground when I go to get out and it's extremely narrow. So, yeah, there it is. Are you looking for a spot right in front of the house there? Right in front of the house, yeah.
And especially like in the winter when it's icy or snowy in the driveway there. When I put my foot down and it's ice, then I'm sliding. I don't have, you know. Understood, yeah. It's an interesting driveway, to say the least. Well, thank you for the presentation. Just hold on one second. We're going to go to the commissioners. Do you have questions of the petitioner of the situation?
And mostly it's sort of what we've just been saying to make sure she understands that what's installed is a legal handicap parking location, which means anybody with a handicap parking permit can park there. It's not a personal reserve spot. I think it's just useful for people to understand that. Yeah. Okay, I appreciate that. And same thing, it's not also like in a snow emergency.
people automatically assume that you can still park there. I cannot. Correct. It's subject to the other side restriction. I would abide by whatever side of the street. Okay. Do the other commissioners have any questions? Does anyone in the public have any? I would like to comment on this petition.
Seeing none, we will revert back to the commissioners. Further comment or a motion? I have no comment. I'd make a motion, if possible. Motion to approve, Commissioner Brzezinski? Yes. A motion of Commissioner Brzezinski to approve petition 2025-04 for permit parking for handicapped parking blocking for 88 Circuit Road. Do I have a second?
second. Seconded by Commissioner McGibbon. Albert, can you give a roll call, please? Commissioner McGibbon? Yes. Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski? Yes. Chief Buckley? Yes. On the vote of four to nothing, the motion is approved. Ms. Candillo, thank you very much for taking the time to participate here. We will be in contact with you shortly and we will
get that sign placed out there for you. Best of luck. Okay. I'm all set for the meeting. I can sign off? You may, yes. Okay. Thank you very much. I appreciate it. Thank you. 2025-05 Handicap Parking Sign, San Francisco Oliveira 132 Sharon Street, apartment number 1.
We'll get that up on the screen. If the petitioner is available. Chief, I'm by there today. I had no one through the door. It appears to be a multi-family house. There is a driveway to the right, it goes all the way back. But I was unable to speak to the petitioner.
Is the petitioner present here or someone here wishing to speak for the petitioner? Raise your hand. I just joined it. I'm not sure if that was my petition, Megan. As it would be what you're at 18 alternate street. Hello.
Oh, okay. Yeah. Hold on a second. So that's not your petition yet, sir. No, this is Robin. Hi, Robin. Hi, I'm sorry. I don't know. My thing said unmute or something out. This is my 1st time using zoom. So, you're doing a great job.
Well, welcome to the Metro Traffic Commission meeting. So we are looking at your petition right now for the HP sign at 132 Sharon Street. Could you just tell us a little bit about your situation? You do not have to get into your medical situation or any specific details. Just really the details about the property. I am, myself and my husband, we're just moving into that unit. We are moving from 322 Pearl Street, Malden.
And I have a handicapped plaque assigned by the city in front of 322 Pearl for my health condition, for COPD and asthma. So at that unit, it's a three family and it will be musical cards. If I pull all the way into that driveway,
If I get in there first, the next person comes in, I'm going to have to have them move out so I can get out, and vice versa. And the back door, the girl on the third floor, she usually parks her car at the back staircase. So I mean, I know it's a two-car garage, but the landlord uses one. And I don't know who uses the other one. I'm just new there, so I don't know what that
assignment of those garages are for. But I mean, he does say we can park in the driveway, but like I said, it would be to come out, go in the driveway, have someone's parked in front of me or behind me, like I'd have to, we have to play musical cards with three families. So I was just hoping that we could get a sign out the front,
Because it was two parking spaces in front of the house. If I could get the one closest to that staircase would be great. Because under that snowbank, that ground is no good. That really needs to be re-cemented. Okay.
All right, well, thank you for the presentation. Standby, I wanna talk to the commission here a little bit. Commissioner, any questions or comments related to the petition? No, I understand that anyone with a handicapped sign could park there, that's understandable. Excellent. And I thank you for the time. You've been listening, very good. I have. That is one of our advisement. All right, let me see what the commissioners have to say.
I have a question, are you entering through the front door? Robin? Oh, she got muted. Somebody's to unmute her. She just got unmuted. I think that's what she said, right? She wants to park in the front and then go up the stairs. She did indicate that she wanted closest to that front stairs, yes. Yes, so I use the front entrance.
It doesn't look like there's a lot of competition for parking on this street. It looks like even though there's three families and two families, it looks like there's driveways. Almost on the street in this picture. Yeah, at least that's represented by that map picture, yeah. Sam, when I went by, there was plenty of parking and stuff. It looks like it. I think I'm familiar with it. I'm okay with this.
Other commissioners' questions, comments? I'll open it up to the public. If anyone else in the public has any questions or would like to comment on the petition? I see no comment. Entertain a motion. Commissioner McGiven, was there a motion somewhere in there? I'm motioning to approve for sure, unless the folks that want one more discussion. Seeing none, the motion of Commissioner McGiven. Do I have a second?
I'll second. Seconded by Commissioner Brzezinski. Alba, can you give us a roll call, please? Commissioner McGiven? Yes. Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski? Yes. Chief Buckley? Yes. On the order of 4-0, the motion is approved.
Thank you very much for your participation this evening and your explanations. The motion has been approved and we will be in touch with you shortly. And thank you for understanding the advisements that we have presented earlier. Have a good evening. Thank you very much and you also. And happy new year to you all. Happy new year to you.
2025-06 permit parking variance from the Shaheed family, 615 Main Street, number three for Bow Street. Alba, has that issue been resolved? That issue has been resolved. We have received the permits in advance.
So those of the 2025-06 is going to be marked resolved. The traffic department has resolved that situation for those petitions, so it no longer needs to be addressed. 2025-07, permit parking variance for a commercial vehicle to park overnight from Mr. Megan and 18 Holton Street, and I believe he was present. We're just gonna ask him to unmute, and the sergeant can pull up the address on screen.
Megan, can you just unmute yourself? Yes. Welcome to the traffic commission. Thank you for your participation. Can you just give us a brief explanation of your petition and what you are requesting?
Well, I'm a small business owner, and I have a transportation service. My vehicle is mainly, I have a garage in Everett, the service vehicle, but I have one particular vehicle that I use, and it has, under the company's name, commercial plate. However, it's just a white vehicle, sedan, Ford Fusion.
And I haven't had any problem parking, but I realized the other day I get a ticket.
and on Boston Ave. My house is on Halton Street, but I have, there's a driveway on Boston Ave. Usually I park on Boston Ave and Halton Street, wherever, and there's no issue of parking. But I was told that the ordinance is gonna be enforced, and I said that my vehicle has, this is one I use
or private, but it's under the company's name. And I just need to have a permission to have my car parked into my house, my street. And that's the driveway that I have. But I
but I have a couple of cars already in my driveway. And I usually park in right there on Boston Ave. I'm sorry to interrupt. Can I ask a question? So you live your own apartment? Yes, I do. Right.
right behind that building in the back of Boston Ave. But my address is 18 Halton Street. I'm tucked into the middle of a bunch of other houses there.
Or, you know, this is my private car, but under the company's name, company's registration, and I was just wondering if I can be allowed to use. I haven't had any property for 20 years, which I had the service. Just a couple of questions. What is the vehicle make and model that you're requesting? It's a 2014 Ford Fusion sedan. Okay, with commercial plates, obviously.
Oh, thanks. Okay. And that's your driveway there. How many vehicles park in that driveway? That driveway is access driveway for me, but it belongs to 8098 Boston Ave. I have, there is a,
And 90, what's it called, 94 Boston Ave. They have those driveway. This is the access to go in. I have the bink house, I live behind them.
So they have a other, there's another, the gentleman on 98, Mr. Tranzioni has a construction company, has a couple of cars there. And so, and I have a van, and I have a one van parked there. Okay. Commissioners, questions, concerns of the petitioner?
I think this is a problem that we've been needing to solve for a while. Like I have extreme sympathy for somebody who has a sedan with commercial plates that they take home with them.
that we've been saying for a long time this is an issue. We've also talked about the fact that commercial businesses need to have storage for their vehicles and shouldn't be using the public ways for storage. I do think that there is a difference though between that and somebody who works at their home and has commercial plates and is trying to park their car at their home, but they have commercial plates because they run a business from their home. We don't have a way to address that.
and I think this is a longstanding problem that it's been a few years on us since we've had somebody come with this problem. Well, there was somebody last year wasn't there and he actually had a van, like a work van that he was allowed to bring home with tools and ladders. Yeah. I think we ran into a problem even with that one and I don't want to put Sarah on the spot, but I don't know that we have an avenue of giving a residential parking permit
commercial vehicle because we do not have a commercial vehicle there's no way to
So, you're welcome to chime in or not chime in on this situation. Yeah, I understand and I think the video shows that my car was parked there. It's a white sedan. It doesn't have any commercial logins or any lettering or anything. It's completely not being used for commercial except that, you know, for
for the for for Kimberly purposes that it has the registration as a commercial. Now I have a business to provide for eight vehicles that I park on. I have a garage that I lease at the 23 Beecham Street in Everett, so it's not a commercial per se. It's my car that I'm trying to.
to just come at home and go back to it, except having the plate. And it doesn't have logos. It doesn't have any lettering. It doesn't have anything to discern as a commercial except the plate number. And it's a personal use. Understood. Thank you.
So to the Director of Parking, is there an avenue to even do this? I mean, it is a commercial plate and we have his registration here. It is definitely commercial registration type. The only thing I could see us granting is a variance to a resident permit parking, right, that you have available. I mean,
That's something, that's how we would probably enter it if he's getting a variance for Holton Street because it's residential. We could put it in there so that the parking control specialist would not fight it for the permit parking, but to communicate that that is an exception as far as the commercial regulations, there's not a good way for us to communicate that in the field unless I just send them with a list of if this is one of many.
to come of, you know, maybe not many, but an occasional exception for commercial vehicles, there's not a way for us to enter that in the system right now so that there is a way to alert them not to cite it for parking overnight. Of course, everything is possible, but I am weary of making exceptions like this.
And in this case, specifically because from what I've heard, and maybe correct me if I'm wrong, it sounds like this vehicle is generally not used for commercial purposes, but rather personal purposes, which makes me question why it has to have a commercial plate to begin with and isn't registered under the vehicle owner as opposed to commercial vehicle. But that's that. And I will point out to the commissioners,
that we have other table items related to residents looking for commercial parking variances, and we've never found a means of providing this to them that is satisfactory to the city without, I think, maybe opening a tidal wave of requests for commercial parking.
residents, commercial vehicle owners, and wishing to park them on the street. I just point that out that every single one that we've received in the last few years has been tabled, and or I think we did try to deal with one last year, and we had considerable trouble with it. I can't remember the name, which street that was, Walcott maybe? I don't know, memory.
So I just add that for discussion to the commissioners, how they would like to proceed on this one. It doesn't seem like we have the option to grant an exception. It seems like we could table it for some future date that we have a solution. But right now, it seems like the solution is if you want to park your car on the street and you have to have residential plates,
or personal politicians. Before we speak to the petitioner again, is there anyone else? Anyone else in the public wishing to speak to this, raise your hand. Indicate.
I just have another question for the petitioner, Mr. Bangan. I know you own a transport business and you use this as one of your business vehicles, and what you're telling us, you're using it to go back and forth to your residence, but is there a reason you can't park into your driveway with that vehicle? I don't... Am I muted? Can you hear me?
We can hear you, yes. Yeah, yeah, yeah. I don't have a driveway, actually. The driveway belongs to... It's an access driveway, but it belongs to the two other buildings that... My address is on Halston Street, actually. And I have been able to have asked Mr. Tranzioni to give me one spot from him.
And, but I've been trying, this is, I'm trying, as the director says that, the residence permit, that's fine. I'm on Halton Street. I'm willing to take the residence permit, but I don't have a spot to park on my car. And this is, it's not a business. It might be the plate.
Yeah, but you have commercial plates on that vehicle. That's that's right. But it's not as it comes, you know, you just indicate to us again where you reside, because we had 18 Holton, but then I thought you indicated that residence was on Boston Ave. No, no, no, the driveway to enter into the access driveway.
is on. I have a drive, you know, I have a path to get in. The building is stacked between 14, behind 14 Halton Street and 94 and 98 Boston Ave behind it. Is that another building back there? That's the only building. 94, 98. No, no, it's the,
16 Holton Street and 18 Holton Street is in the behind building. It's a kind of a rear building. If you look at the overhead map, you can see in the middle of the block a building situated in the middle of the block. Which is kind of an isolated building. That's where I am.
And I'm, you know, the reason that is that I cannot put on my name in terms of the cars already under company name, which I kind of many benefits that comes with it. And I, you know, it's a more of a company vehicle, not a private vehicle. I could have done that.
But I tried to do that, and it's a company vehicle that I was given, and I'm trying to, it's not a business vehicle per se. And I've been long residents here, this is the first time that I have an issue, and I'm hoping that I will be given that exception.
Commissioners, any further comments, questions?
I guess my question is, is there any way to do it? What I heard from Sarah is there isn't a technical way for us. Like if we voted tonight and said, yes, he should be able to park that sedan on a municipal street, it makes sense. There isn't a way for us to technically implement that with the parking department, at least not a way that scales, because we can't have them driving around with paper lists of who's allowed to actually park places. Exactly.
That's where we'd be, is we would have to start a list or a text chain or an email chain of do not cite this, just this one. The other ones get, and then I'd have to explain to my staff, because they'd be curious, why this one in particular is not being cited. And in the interest of fairness and consistency, I wouldn't really have a good answer for them.
I think we have to wait until there's some infrastructure set up to do it. Right. I'm wondering if we're working on this because I would really like us to have a way for us to allow commercial vehicles in appropriate situations to park on our streets. I don't need big vans and stuff like that, but this has been this way for a very long time and it just seemed a very nimby thing in the beginning.
I mean, we can, I'm open to discussing that and figuring out a way with our software providers to add that in if that's something that the commission thinks is worthwhile and would be beneficial to people who have to, who can have the option to drive the commercial vehicle home, don't have a driveway, et cetera. It could be case by case. And then if there were some criteria to
Train with, you know, like, if if somebody, let's just say this fella got cited and our staff, he got to talk to them. I would like for them to be able to refer them to this commission with the proper. Documentation or anything they might need.
to get an exception, if that is something we want to look at. I'm open to it. But at this time, we're not set up to do that. We can make a workaround, but it's not going to be built in as things are right now. And I know other communities do allow it.
I mean, that's something we base a lot of our policy on is, is it allowed elsewhere? What are the exceptions elsewhere? So again, it's not something that has come up in my month in this position, but happy to take a peek, take a look around, especially if you have some tables that could use revisiting. I just worry about, from the policing perspective, we get vast amounts of commercial motor vehicle
I am always overly worried that we just do not have enough parking spots for all the vehicles that are registered here. And that's a bigger issue. Because if you open up, you know, I'm not looking at this as Mr. Megan's request. I'm looking at this as a request of the entire city. He has proved it's not getting an influx of all of these. And so it's not personal on his side. It's just that what can city, you know, maintain for a while, how many parking and parking spots
The other thing would be if we do, Sarah, then we'd have to confirm that they can. Also, I understand that the vehicle is garaged in Medford. Not that it's just a commercial plate. We would need to be able to make sure that they have the technology. To know that right and that would fall under the commercial vehicle that could come from outside of the state of the city. Yep.
So I'm not sure that they can or they can't, I'm not sure. Yeah, it's a lot of work that would have to go into allowing any ordinance like this. And that's why, as I pointed out, we've tabled so many of them in the past. Certainly not going to be resolved this evening in my mind, but that's up to the commissioners, if any other commission has a comment or question. I think we've got to table it with the others and maybe give
give some more time to this and see if we can get a new permit procedure or a new category or whatever we need. I don't think we should try to rig this to work. I think we're just asking for trouble if you do that for one person. So I'm OK with tabling until we have an opportunity to actually grant these types of permits. Commissioner Brzezinski.
I'm going to allow for your comments, but with the request to table, I do believe we have to take a vote on that. But go ahead with your comments. Yes. What is the, I'm trying to think, because we've been dealing with this, like you mentioned, for a while. What is the reasoning? Is it statutory that we don't allow for it? Or is it just because we don't have a procedure in place? For some reason I'm thinking,
A long time ago, we talked about the fact that there was actually like, it wasn't in the code or the code prohibited commercial vehicle parking ordinance. Yeah, there's an ordinance on commercial vehicles parked. Okay, so isn't that our starting point? I mean, isn't that the city hall? Oh, yeah, there's multiple static place, but 100%. Yes, it's the ordinance. It'd be great if we had a city hall representative on the call with us who could comment on that.
I mean, that would be the council. Jim is here if he's willing to do it, but the reality is I would not advocate for changing the ordinance without having a process ready to implement. Because the day you pass that ordinance, you will have people lined up asking for the permit. Yeah, I agree. I always support the idea of being prepared, but coming up with a program,
is great, but everybody should understand, citizens importantly, that this is a city hall issue. I mean, I'm happy to help formulate a program and present it to city hall with what we suggest they do, but if it's ordinance preventative, then everybody should understand that that's what needs to be fixed in the end. Thank you, Commissioner Pizzitti.
Jim Silva, did you have a comment? I mean, I just see you unmuted yourself, but if you're good with what was said, then you're good with what was said. So we do have a motion by commission to be given to table. I do believe we have to take a vote on that. Nobody seconded me.
Okay, I heard a suggestion, not a motion, but if it's a motion, I'll second. I think we have to have something spearheaded elsewhere to resolve this, and then we can do business with what's tabled. Okay, so if I read this, we have a motion from Commissioner McGiven to table, seconded by Commissioner Hunt. I'll have a roll call, please.
Commissioner McGiven? Yes. Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski? Yes. Chief Buckley? Yes. On the vote of four to nothing, the motion passes. 2025-06 has been tabled. To the petitioner. Go ahead, Commissioner Hunt. I was going to say, do we have a plan, though? Because I don't want to just sit there on the table list forever. Well, it sounds like a special project.
There's only one person on this call with that title. Agreed. And that did not go unnoticed by myself making the comment. That's going to take us. And so I say this to the commissioners and to the public and to the petitioner. Obviously, you can tell by our discussion, this is a longstanding issue for the city that we have to do some considerable work on. And if anything, while you haven't,
Been successful tonight and been able to grant and been given a variance. You have spurred the conversation and we are going to kind of push forward a review of the commercial parking. So, I cannot grant you a variance tonight because of the table item, but we are going to move forward and look at this and.
Is still on the agenda on the table business and at some point in time that we're prepared to deal with the commercial parking situation. We will notify you of your options that so thank you for participating. And I appreciate your understanding and listening. Thank you. So, thank you. Thank you 2025 dash 08.
uh village place base 64 Salem street to discuss parking problems this is an interesting is the petitioner um i'm here this is me tiffany huffman hi how are you very good welcome uh to the traffic commission um so it's a very vague um petition but could you just discuss with us your situation and the reason for your petition
Yes, absolutely. My business is 64 Salem Street right across like diagonally across from City Hall next to the hockey store. So we are like next to that parking lot that now is business permit only. It used to be like paid parking where my customers can park.
My business is an indoor playground for kids from 0 to 6, with a focus on 0 to 3. So babies are coming to our play space every single day. So as you can imagine, that parking lot being no longer available to the public has been very detrimental to my business. And then so the parking on our side of the street, so if you're driving on Salem Street, it's on the right-hand side. It's only 30 minutes, like the metered spots.
So I understand that guests can obviously cross the street, they can use the crosswalks, but again with the children that they're bringing, people make poor decisions and they don't always use the crosswalks.
If we can do some things to make the parking on our side of the street, not short-term parking, but like two hours, that would be helpful. I don't know if there's any other, like, you know, there's really no other solution. And the other thing is that, again, people are whatever, you know, I always see someone driving the wrong way, the one way, at least once a day, if we could just have some more one-way signs for them.
So the second part is easy. We will take a look at that. We have been dealing with that for about... It gives me a heart attack because I know those people have kids in their car. Yeah. Understood. And we'll deal with that one for you separately. Two quick questions which may or may not be relevant to the conversation with the commissioners tonight. What are the hours of your operation for the business? And how many customers do you seem to have in your business at a time? What's your sort of...
We're 9.30 to 5 for the most part. On the weekends we operate a little bit later for birthday parties. So like around 9 to 6.30 is roughly the times we have customers in. We have about 30 kids, maximum 30 kids at once. So probably 30 cars is maximum. Even if there's 30 kids, they might, more than one kid can come in a car. So more realistically, the max,
we have is probably around like 15 cars in our space. So our space itself has four spots. Myself and my employees, or at least I have, my employees don't really drive to work, but I have business parking, so I never use our spots in there. So we only have four spots available. So that, you know, helps take care of that. The spot in front of the hockey store, I think there's one or two spots, I can't remember. Those are all 30 minute parking. And then the other one in front of the business lot, I believe is also
30-minute parking. So if even those three could be, that's just three more cars that could be on our side of the road versus the other side. Excellent. Thank you, Elise, for presenting so far. Commissioners, any questions of the petitioner or just in general? I had a question. She said that the parking lot next door was business parking?
Did we change that? We did. Yeah. What I heard from the Chamber of Commerce is that Verizon owns it and they don't want public parking there anymore. So there's not a lot that we can do there. So obviously, one of the reasons why we chose that location is that parking can be so easy. But I mean, it is what it is. At least that's what I'm hearing, that it's a dead end on that route.
Jim Silva, comments on that? I mean, we understand that it has been changed to business parking, but... It has just changed to business parking only, and exactly for that reason, because it's owned by Verizon. It's not owned by the city of Medford. And we cannot derive income from parking, municipal parking, for public, whereas a program parking was allowed, and it was changed to business for that reason. Thank you. And understood.
I just wanted to say that I hope I didn't come off as dismissive about this issue because she did email me. I think my first or second week here and I wasn't really sure how to handle it. I wasn't yet familiar with, you know, even why that law was businessful, things like that. So that might be why she ended up here. It might be something that I could handle.
solo in the future, so I hope that Tiffany, you didn't feel like I was trying to just shut you up. Oh, no, not at all. My question is whether you've spoken to the adjacent business or businesses, I don't know if somebody is next to you in that commercial building, regarding the parking. I know that Hockey Town has parking behind their building,
And I'm not sure if they are in agreement about those spaces. I'm just hesitant to take away spaces or change spaces if other adjacent businesses use them for pickup. I mean, I can talk to them, but I will say that their customers just don't like parking in their lot because they don't like that they have to drive around. I know this because their customers are always trying to park in our lot.
and a lot of them just don't know. A lot of their customers don't know, but they have 10 parking spots back there. There's plenty of parking for their customers. Yeah, and I agree your reasonings are noble, not wanting people to cross the street with small children, but I'd hate to take away those spaces, put your customers there, and then have hockey town parents crossing the street with their children, thus creating the same problem because they didn't want to park behind. But they can park behind, so it's a little bit different.
Right, I don't have another option for my customers like that. Yeah, if I did, like, I wouldn't be here. And so the meters beyond the 1, I can't speak for the 1 solo meter out there by the business lot, but all of the meters in on that side of the street into the square.
are all two hours. So if anybody has a real aversion in the meantime, with crossing the street with their children, that side of the street beyond that business lot and the bus area there is two hour parking at the meters.
So further north, right? The issue is that those spots are mostly taken, whereas directly across the street from me, because there's not as much foot traffic, those are the ones that are open. And I don't know if my customers are more concerned or I'm more concerned for them, because honestly, they come with nannies. I love nannies. They're great, but they're nannies.
So I don't think they make the best decisions. Honestly, I've stopped a child from running into a street that wasn't mine. Right. My only concern is impacting the other businesses and catering only to one business in that general area.
So the only other business is the hockey store. I'm happy to go work with them to see if they care. I've needed to talk to them anyways because I'm the one educating their customers that they should be parking not in my lot.
Yeah, that is unfortunate. I'm sorry that's happened. No, it's not your fault. I just go to tell them. But I was also wondering if the area in front of your business that houses that one single space meter, it could be turned into two single space meter spaces if there's enough room there. I think there was recently work done on the curb. Is that correct, Jim?
It's correct, but I think it would be very dangerous from a visibility standpoint for at least when I leave the business law, or actually, maybe it doesn't affect it. No, you're right. There could be one more meter spot. I can't guarantee there. There might be enough room. I don't know the exact measurements, the requirements there.
just without, just off the top of my head, but that's something we can consider perhaps as well. Thank you. Commissioner Hunt, comments? Couple of, I would actually, if we have any record of how long these have been 30 minutes and therefore why they're 30 minutes, because I realized the street that Hockey Town is on is a two-way street. It's very easy for customers to turn up that street if they don't bloat right past it. If their customers know they have parking back there,
and why these are 30 minute spots. And I wonder if it actually goes back to the mean chicken and rice guys in there, which was a fast takeout business. And now that the business that, so chicken and rice is gone, that is the location of this village play space now, that maybe actually these spots should go to longer meters.
Because that looks like a two-way street. And I'm wondering, this is the other thing, is it R? So I will bicycle down that street that you're looking at right now to come to City Hall. And it's not really clear to lots of people that that is, in fact, a two-way street. Every once in a while, somebody will come up it. And I'm wondering if it would be in the city's best interest to make it more clear that that's a two-way street?
I don't know how you do that. You painted double yellow. Yeah, at the intersection. I get concerned that people coming down it to Medford Square don't realize that somebody could come up at them. Yeah.
You mean to access the Hockey Town parking lot, that's what you're talking about, right? Right. They could access the Hockey Town parking lot. There is no other really great reason to go up that street that are to the church. One assumes that if you are a regular member of the church that you would know, find out over time. Yeah. I would imagine that pure hockey tells their folks to park in the back, I would think anyway.
Uh, but at least I have the same question as you. Why are those two spots or two, three spots 30 minutes? That's the burning question in my mind. Well, we could do some research, but I probably willing to bet you that it either relates to, uh, the sporting goods store. I mean, pure hockey or Tony luchas as it was in the past, the animal or the chicken and rice have, it's, it has to be one or the other, but we can go through and look at the, uh,
The history of the traffic commission when they presented those just kind of, it's not at our fingertips right now. And there's some other things I think, environmentally, or at least urban design. We can look at the crosswalk, the double lines in Oakland, making people understand looking at the 30 minutes. I just, I mean, unless another commission has a.
Proposal for allowing this, maybe we can just kind of get together and do some research into what we can provide to the petitioner here that the traffic commission can do to alleviate some of the problems, which is timed parking and roadway markings and parking signs, et cetera. I know Verizon is interested in selling their lot. Maybe the city should buy it. It seems like a great spot for a public parking lot, but anyway.
Pure hockey does not on their website say anything about parking. They have a whole bunch of photos, but none of those photos show the parking lot or an overhead showing that you could get there. So there's no indication on their website that there is a parking.
Tiffany, the other question I asked, is there another business in there with you? Could you park other cars in your lot facing the other direction and create some more spots that way? So there are no other business, like, we only have four spots in our spot, like, it was kind of, it was taking vehicles in this way.
So we do fit one we can fit one to two more in there and we do do that sometimes. So are there are there tenants upstairs because above you is apartments and there were supposed to be spots for the apartments up there. Yes. So they do have they park overnight. So there are promised parking at night. Also the tenants don't have cars up there.
It just worked out for me that they don't have cars. It was permitted that there was one spot per unit for the apartment? Exactly. Technically, we're sharing. There's only one right now. I am lucky that right now, only one tenant has a car.
though and most of them leave during the day like basically since we're they're usually gone by the time we're in business and they're not back like we you know we're just nine to five really so they're usually out before and like after so the tenants haven't been a major issue it could change obviously if the tenants start getting cars but i think um
So that hasn't been an issue. Also, this building used to have the green space were parking spots, too, that were taken away for the tenants. I mean, obviously, it's not my problem. I mean, it is, but that was another thing that has happened. But, I mean, overall, it's fine. I just worry about, like, my customers aren't really too bothered. I just worry about, because when are people going to make poor decisions, right? It's going to be when it's raining, when visibility is bad, right? They're going to jet across the street and the cars can't see.
I just don't want a tragedy to happen. And I just know that people don't make the best decisions. And I think the smallest thing we could do is if we could change back the 30 minutes, at least that just helps me like that's two more spots, right? Agreed.
I would be in favor of changing the meters to longer, but I do think that it's only fair for us to just find out why for somebody to have a conversation with pure hockey. Honestly, part of me says pure hockey is a lot. They have to use it. That's just how it's going to need to be. But they should be spoken to. They should know. They shouldn't find out from the meters in front of them just changing.
And if we can add another meter, that would be great. I think we ask whoever would be appropriate perhaps Todd to review that. Yeah, could lay one out if it's doable.
we could do some research on why it's 30 minutes and get that information, obtain that information. We can speak with traffic engineering. Director Blake isn't available this evening, but I'm sure we could come up with some ideas, including the markings of Oakland Street and make sure people understand that they can get up there and out easily enough and that Peel Hockey could use that parking lot more for themselves. The bigger question is that's what we could do. How do we want to handle the petition this evening?
What does it actually say? It's just to discuss parking problems. That's why I said it's a unique item on the agenda. We did abide by the parameters of the petition, but I don't see a motion that needs to be taken on something that's a discussion. I want us to follow through on this. I think that we could resolve this off our
Our agenda know if we know that somebody else is gonna it doesn't need to come back on our agenda to change the length of time of those meters. yep. Just just to throw it in there i'm happy to take this back over after this meeting i'm happy i'm very glad to have your all feedback and we'll you know figure out why we'll kind of dive in and figure out why they're 30 minutes.
I'm also curious about that single space one by the business lot, because I could have swore that one was two hours. But if that one's not two hours, same thing. We'll see why it's 30. Then also look into adding another meter there. Maybe worry about the 30-minute issue first. Having to take this off of the commission's hands now that I'm a little bit more established in this office and I have a better idea of what to do and I've gotten some feedback from this commission.
Um, so, uh, if you want to, if you want to resolve this issue, it will not be forgotten after today. And I will maintain contact with the business owner.
Director McDermott, thank you for those comments, and I will offer you my traffic sergeants to assist with Director Blake and the traffic engineering, as Commissioner McGiven has already indicated would be part of that. Excellent. So to the petitioner, Ms. Hubschman, are you okay with this? I mean, it's the petitions for discussion. We've discussed it. We understand that there has to be some kind of changes here, but we have to take a deeper look at that.
So net net, I will follow up with Sarah, right? Perfect. Yes. And Sarah will have access to all of our teams. Okay. Perfect. Sounds good. Thank you for listening. I just, again, just don't want those poor little kids.
No, I understand it. I think we also have some concerns that we're all looking at independently here. So I think hopefully we arrive at a really quick and easy solution to the situation there. Thanks for your participation in bringing this forward. Thanks for having your business here.
All right, thank you, guys. Yep, thanks very much. And as the Commissioner, we will mark 2025-08 as resolved, because it has been discussed and we have some sort of resolution. 2025-09, City Hall parking lot, new parking restrictions. Mr. Jim Silva, Special Projects Coordinator, the floor is yours. Yes, this impacts the 71 spaces on the
south side of City Hall facing City Hall Mall. Currently, the sign has two-hour municipal business. We would like to remove that and have it only for municipal employees. There are 76 spaces in total, but this only impacts 71 of them. One of them is a veteran spot which we'll maintain and four are HP spaces which are open to anyone.
Currently what is occurring is folks are parking there and potentially going on a commuter bus, or they're going to Atrius Health, et cetera, or they're going to the dentist office. We have very little ways of enforcing this. So where the charging station is to the left and from the charging station towards City Hall, that area there.
So those 2 lanes currently the sign again says municipal employees by permit with additional 2 hours for city business. We just like to remove the city business. There are 19 spaces out in front on the north part of City Hall available for folks to manage city business.
Ultimately, our goal is to encourage our employees to seek alternate transportation modes, be it blue bikes, bikes themselves, or public transportation. So we're exploring some options, but this is a good opportunity before there are some major developments potentially taking place in the area.
to kind of straighten out a situation, so be it, and head that way in the future. If you zoom in on the parking lot itself and look at the sign at the charging station, go to street level. Anything to the right, it will tell you there are some signs that need to be adjusted.
So you'll notice this is parking permit for municipal employees, and then a two-hour for municipal business. That will be removed, the secondary statement that exists there. I think there are three signs along there that need to be changed. And I know where the veterans parking spot, what are the other spots that will not be impacted, Jim? Or is it just the veterans? So if you head back towards the other way,
So it's the east side of City Hall, which is where you're going, yep. So you'll see that there are four HP spots there. Got it, makes sense. And then if you go over to, it's not listed in this particular version because this is from 2018, but the silver, the gold Honda, that's where the veteran space is located.
Yeah, correct. Excellent. So everything else will be municipal employee parking and we're going to open up out front to visitor parking. Correct. And it is already signed out front accordingly. There are two HP spots there as well as a veteran and the remaining 16 are for people doing municipal business.
Majority of folks that do come to City Hall are generally there to pay a bill or drop into the city clerks, etc. So their business is generally less than 30 minutes from observation. Some of the other aspects are that there are some other additional parking spaces if people are coming in, specifically a vendor, etc. There are some places for them to pay to park.
But this is an opportunity again with the development potential in the location. We're just trying to tighten it up a bit. And again, put a little enforcement teeth.
If people are abusing the system by not paying a commuter pass but actually parking there all day and jumping on the bus or heading over to atrius for an appointment or going to the dentist office at zero city hall mall without having to pay in the parking lot, pay for parking. So this gives us a little bit more of an opportunity to kind of tighten it up a bit. Commissioners, comments, questions?
Honestly, my staff would be thrilled about this. It's very frustrating for them to see people getting on the bus.
and to be walking across the street to the health center, and then they can't find parking. And then they have to go park in the commuter lot across the way when this is supposed to be employee parking. And it feels that people are cheating the system. We have commuter parking. You just have to buy the commuter permit, and then you can hop on the bus and go all day.
And we have short term paid parking. It's literally on the other side of that green grass strip. People can if they don't want to park in the free parking for the health care center, they can literally park right there and pay the meter. It's not fair that they park in the city hall lot.
when this other parking is right around, our staff cannot park in this particular lot because it's not covered by their special permits and we have to do special arrangements. We have to jump through hoops for people to be able to park over there in the commuter lot. So I just think it's the right thing to do and it's the only way to enforce employee parking and make sure that we have parking for employees.
I have mild concern about special events at City Hall. And that if we're doing, we should have in mind, there occasionally will be a luncheon with 60, 100 people during business hours. Doesn't make it easy for us. But people shouldn't, but we should have some answer for that.
I think we're looking at waiving for special events, voting, for instance, that type of thing that would require. We have in the past just recently directed people to a voting location out in front of the building during the early voting period, but there is an opportunity to review what the event size will be, et cetera. At least we're prepared, but it would be something that is not a common day-to-day process.
Let me just see if there's anyone in the public who has questions and comments on this petition. Seeing none, quick question. Actually, first a comment. Maybe we should consider additional signage in that lot and outlining clearly where Republican Park and Pater Park is and where
employee parking is, sometimes these little signs just don't go enough. The second question I have is, what about the charging stations? We have EV charging stations. Are those going to be municipal employee parking spots? Have we said that this would be during business hall hours only? Business hours only.
Because we do find that there are hotel people, people who use the hotel who use those charging stations overnight. And I like that.
There's someone in those spots all day long. They could be municipal vehicles. It's possible, I just thought. Some of them have been in municipal vehicles. I, on occasion, have spoken to people using those charging stations. Sometimes they've been people who work at the health center across the street. I've also talked to somebody who charges her car there every few weeks when she's visiting a relative who lives about two blocks from City Hall.
I don't see the need to restrict them to employees only during business hours. That is possible through a technical setup, but I don't know that we really want to go there.
What do other people think? So I do know that employees use them. I do know that they're not always available when employees use them, but it's good to provide, I mean, part of our goal is providing this service of charging stations. We do not have the ability
right now to add a charging station to the other lot here because of the electrical services location. We literally can't put another charging station right next to that one because of the electrical service to the lot at this time. Not to mention that these parcels are out to RFP for redevelopment, so I wouldn't put any charging stations in there when we don't know the long-term future of these lots.
I asked a quick question, Alicia, as far as, for instance, Yale Street Law, how do you handle the charging on those on municipal law currently? Do you limit the time or are they open? And I'll use that as an example. So on Yale Street Law, there are two charging stations.
We passed and we passed something in this committee and I don't remember what it is that we passed. So we need to reference that particular item to see if we. How do you handle that? How we handled it at that point? Because the charging is a lot longer than the 3 hour limitation with a 2 hour limitation depending. I think that we did say.
that you were allowed to park there as long as you were actively charging. I feel like we gave some buffer because we didn't feel that people should have to come out in the middle of the night and move their car. But we may want to visit what we had there to make it more rational, like during business hours,
three hours or while charging their business hours, because all of this is also used by the Chevalier at night, which is fine when City Hall is closed. I think that is how the regulations want to occur, extremely office hours or business hours, and so obviously a late night on Wednesday, early on Friday.
So if the commissioners are willing, they could allow the motion and just grant permission to deal with the EV charging stations as we have with the Eel Street lot in the past. We don't have to come back here with a petition. I'm happy to
I would like to hear what the other commissioners have to say. I've got a lot to say. I'm sorry. I don't have. You made a lot of good points. I mean, I'm okay with this change. I agree with Tim. Okay. Charging. That's good. And Chief's idea of dealing with the charging separately, I think makes sense too, because we're not really changing that condition. We're just saying, if you want to do City Hall business, go to the front.
I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know. I don't know
It would be great if somebody who's not me could dig up what it was that we passed previously. I'd like to make sure we share that with Director McDermott, that we should review that and think about whether it's, now that we have experienced, the other person actually, Jim, you raised your hand if you're gonna share it. Can you also share it with Brenda Pike in my office? I don't think we had her on staff when we originally passed this.
She's our climate planner, and so I would love to have, now that we've experienced with the station, how it's actually being used, Brenda is able to pull any data if we want to know how often is it used during business hours, overnight, is it being, you know, when are charging sessions starting, what time of day, she can get all of that data for us, because my goal is to balance, like,
Don't make it impossible for people to use it. Let's get people using it, but let's not tie up spots that should be used. I will tell you city staff are definitely using it. There are a few staff that have electric vehicles that when all the other spots are full, they'll decide to charge because they can get a spot there. I think I'd love to review that and we can review that as a different item.
Okay, do I have a motion on dealing with this petition? Motion to approve. Second. Commissioner Hunt, seconded by Commissioner Brzezinski to approve 2025-09. I'll have a roll call vote, please. Commissioner McGibbon? Yes. Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski?
Yes. Chief Buckley? Yes, I vote 4-0. The motion is approved. 2025-10 Sprague House Honeywell Avenue resident parking only sign removal from the public street. Jim Silva, the floor is yours.
Honeywell Avenue residents brought this to our attention in the mayor's office. There are signs along the Sprague House that say that limit parking on a public street to Sprague House residents only. But it requires them, the eight residents first come first serve, to participate in the resident parking program. So the Sprague House folks can park anywhere on Honeywell, according to the sign.
but the folks on Honeywell, even though they're resident parking, can't park in those spots. We had an opportunity, Alicia reached out to her department and actually we went through the materials in 1984 when the proposal for the development happened. In 1986, the resident parking limitations were included.
in the variance list that we currently use. There is nothing in there that says specifically they own it. This is public property. Interestingly enough, those signs have been up since Honeywell Ave became a resident parking entity.
My water on this and just the parking, the traffic commission did approve this special permit in January of 86 stickers only no visitor passes. How many did you say? Just just for me for my was it 8 1st come 1st serve? Yes. And if there's an, it isn't by household, it is by who comes 1st.
et cetera, and that's how it's sort of doled out. And I think this development is key. The size, for instance, is large. There's parking provided on site. This was, I believe, something that when Honeywell Lab went on board with resident parking, it was a way of helping the development sort of thrive at that point.
But this is a key example of the future and how we work with larger developments in residential areas, even though they are residential development, whether or not they can effectively participate in a resident parking program and how it looks like in the future. But that's for another time. These signs need to come down potentially and resident parking put up so that everybody can park there. Folks on Honeywell can park there.
The eight people in Sprague can park anywhere at Honeywell as they come. There still will be eight variances granted to residents of that Sprague house. No additional passes and the street is their parking, whatever's available as opposed to limited restrictions along with the rest of the names. That is correct. Commissioners.
agree entirely that shouldn't be uh dedicated for the are you saying sprog sprog buildings how do you say that sprague right yeah
You were unable to find anything in the detail of the development. And again, it was 40 years ago, so I'm not quite sure how things were handled then. But as the chief alluded to, in 1986, they came up and asked for the variance, and they were granted. And subsequently, people have participated over that time period, and so they haven't lost an interest.
The neighbors would like to be able to park there if they need to. And I think that is the variable here. Yeah, it's a public parking lane. Jim, Alvin, I had a conversation earlier tonight and to the best of her recollection.
Again, this is 30 something, 30 to 40 years ago. But Alva, there's a business around the front of this on Riverside Ave. And she believes that that business occupied more of that parking lot than it does today. And that was probably one of the reasons they made an exception to allow some additional parking out limiting. So if that helps by way of history. Now the business is still there, but I don't think it is doing the same.
the volume as it was back then, they were serving food, et cetera. And that's sort of back at that date. So may not be accurate, but it's the best of our recollection. And said, Alba, she doesn't forget a thing, but if that helps. So commissioners comments or questions. Have we had any conversation with the management company or anything there? Like, do they know we're even talking about this?
It really won't impact them, per se, because there's still eight folks. That number isn't going to change. They currently can park anywhere. So who does it impact? It only impacts the other folks who can't. Right. Are all the residents going to be allowed to get parking permits on Honeywell Ave, or we're just saying there won't be dedicated spots, people can still get permits? So the variance will maintain. The signs will come down. And the variance said that these folks, these eight
folks in the Sprague House can participate on resident parking on Honeywell. So none of that has changed. The only thing that will change with the signs coming down and resident parking only there, anyone else who lives on Honeywell Ave is able to do that due to our street by street. So it doesn't really impact them. Right. Other than there's less likely that one of those spots will be available.
Jim, do we know, I'm sorry, do we know how many permits are requested each year? Are they requesting the eight? Are they getting them every year? I don't think, I think they did the renewal this year, so yes. Okay.
And they are active. As you know, we've sort of reverted back to the 4 or 5 years. If you don't participate all the time in your variance, we sort of rescind that and have you come back to traffic commission. So it looks like they have participated over the years. I think 1 thing we should do is clarify that it is for 8.
eight residents to receive variances and only because the original traffic commission petition says
What they did was grant that area that's approximately eight spaces. So they're saying by traffic commission, the rule is you have this amount of sidewalk space to park cars. We're now going to take it away. So we want to be specific about how many variances we're granting as opposed to an approximate area where they can park. I just stole that suggestion.
Does anyone in the public wish to comment or ask a question on this petition? Seeing none, back to the commissioners. Thoughts, comments, and or motions? I think it's fine. I will reiterate because it's a point I continue to make when these things happen, I wish we do a better job of notifying the affected people.
But even with that said, I'd vote for this. I do think that some of them are going to be like, what happened to our signs? What's going on? And somebody should be prepared with an answer and a response. And how this impacts them. I'm understood. Depending on how this goes, we're probably just going to have to do some outreach right away with them. There's signs that are not going to be long before they come down if it passes.
I think it's inappropriate that we're using spots on a public way signed for a particular apartment building. If there had been something in the earlier agreements with the construction of it and there was some situation, then at least we would understand that and we could decide whether to amend it. But as Jim said, I went back to the site plan reviews and stuff and there was stuff about that.
It's as a fun fact, the little store that's in the side of that building, it was a standalone store there at that location that was a well-loved corner store type business, and people were very concerned about it leaving. Part of the agreement to build the apartment building was that they would put a space for the store there. They built the building and the store moved in, and then the store was on the side of the parking lot and they tore down the store.
to make room for the parking lot. That's why there is a little store set into that building there. But there was nothing about street parking in any of that documentation. Yeah. That's what it matches. To Director McDermott, for the eight residents who have parking passes now, do you collect contact information, an email address, phone number? I mean, if we specifically wanted to reach out to those eight individuals, do we have that available? Are that option available in the
Well, we can't hear you, Sarah, sorry. She's unmuted. She has to go home soon. Sarah, you're unmuted, but we can't hear you. You're unmuted. Before, your sound was making weird noises. It was very screechy. And now it's making no noise. We could follow up with that later on. It was just a question as to whether that might help us with the outreach part to this. When that first was passed,
The Condo Association gave out the permits to the first eight, and that continued for a couple of years, and then it reverted to the parking authority, not us, the Hyatt one. But they originally gave out, and if you got it one year, you couldn't be one of the eight to get it the next year.
I'm not sure how that is going. We may have a history in our records.
Thank you, Director McDermott. We see your chat. A motion on this petition.
I'll make the motion, again, I'll just reiterate, doing some outreach to the people affected by this in a proactive manner. Understood. On the motion of Commissioner Baszynski to approve 2025-10, and that comes with the declaration that we should do outreach on those impacted, which will happen. Do I have a second? Second. Seconded by Commissioner McGibbon. Alva, could you give us a roll call, please?
Commissioner McGiven? Yes. Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski? Yes. Chief Buckley? Yes. On the vote of four to nothing, 2025-10 has been approved.
That is it for new business. We do have two items that have been tabled for this evening, and I think it's still early enough if the commission would like to deal with them. They would be 2024-55, that's the Washington Street parking lot that was originally petitioned by Commissioner McGibbon, and then 2024-70, that's the Dexter Street Sunday Adventist Church.
which was tabled and then we did a little bit of research on that. So if the commissioners have the time and ability and willingness, I'd accept a motion to take 2024-55, 2024-70 out of tabled items for discussion. So moved. On the motion of commission we're given, second? Second.
seconded by Commissioner Hunt. I have a quick roll call for this motion. Commissioner McGibbon? Yes. Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski? Yes. Chief Buckley? Yes. The motion for nothing. The motion is approved. 2024-55 Washington Street parking lot. Originally petitioned by Commissioner McGibbon,
it's required that we bring it up. Commissioner McGibbon, I'll start with you. Do you have any updates on the original petition and where we stand today? No, not really. I know that there's a development or a request on the table for it. So maybe that's what tonight's about. But no, I don't think there's been any progress unless Alicia has any. I don't know anything. Yeah.
All right, do you want to? Yeah, so I'm just pulling up the Sergeant Rogers and myself went over to the church and no, this is Washington Street, Washington, Washington. So I've gone by several times. Just residents.
a parking in there. No one registered or dump cars or anything else. It's residents within the area. We were able to talk to the vehicle that was doing mechanical stuff, Sam, so we got him, you know, kind of put that in his driveway. So other than that, we just, nothing that we, out of the ordinary, nothing like, or Mel. Thanks. It's good to know.
I mean, I think that's what it was. If you look back on the development documents, the parcel was given to the city, and then it says in the site plan approval documents that it should be used by the residents in the neighborhood or something like that. Anyway, but it's a public lot, so again, strange thing, but we were gonna, I was gonna work with someone in planning, I think it was Amanda, just to see what made sense for that lot, if we're gonna do anything with it.
Sorry, I missed that you had switched from the Seventh Day Adventist Church, which I thought you were talking about, to the Washington Street lot. The other thing that's occurred is that a resident, not a resident, somebody who has redeveloped, so the house next door is for sale, and one of the potential buyers has inquired with the city if they could buy that lot, and then do a larger housing project there, like build more units.
then would be allowed on the one lot. It wouldn't be allowed under the current zoning what they want to do, so they would need other kinds of relief as well. But it was an intriguing idea that rather than making it a parking lot, it become housing.
That can be dealt with as it comes up, I guess. Commissioner McGibbon, the original petition, I'm just trying to wrack my brains, was just to make sure that this is used by residents. And I think my traffic division is showing at least that that's what's happening over there. Is there further concerns? Do we need to keep something? I mean, again, it's on for discussion. Is there anything further you would like or should we deal with this petition for discussion as resolved or would you like to keep it tabled?
We don't, I don't think it needs to stay on here. I think we found out the information we wanted from my initial inquiry. And now, basically, if something needs to happen by this commission and actually needs to be taken on the lot, we'll deal with it later. We just don't know if or what we're going to do with it or what the fate of the lot is. So.
Okay so as 2024-55 is and has been placed for discussion and we have discussed it and we've come to some of these resolutions from the police side that is in fact being used. Unless a commissioner objects we will mark 2024-55 as resolved as discussed. No objection. I'll move to 2024-70 which is the Seventh-day Adventist Church, 62 Dexter Street. We've had in church parking.
Sgt. Kalawach, you were going to speak on this too. So other than the signs we went up there, we were able to kind of see that they have three parking spots as the, I don't know if it was the pastor had explained to us, but the solution that myself, Jim Silva, Todd and Sgt. Larry Rogers came up with is, you know, we can add two more spots across
7th day Advent Church, which would include 5 parking spots for them. And then I know he was asking for 10, but we feel that with it being so close to Main Street that 5 adding 2 more would be suffice for the numbers that they are dealing with. And the distance from Main Street to this Dexter Street location is a very short walk if need be.
The only thing that we kind of came up with is the signage is different. That's in front of there is is Wednesday, Friday, Saturday and Sunday. But we looked at the website and the 7th day church only has Wednesday, Sunday, Saturday, but the signs we have posted up there just needs to be changed.
So I guess we can kind of look into that. Tim, I can send you an email with with what they have on their website and just kind of the 2 signs that are out there just have an added day on there for times. But. If I recall the petitioner actually said that the.
Yeah, so I think we just have the Friday is the only day that we need that. I don't know why Friday was on there, but they must they must have had Friday for something. They have Friday on the signs Friday 730 to 9 PM. We spoke to them and they don't have any. Reason for that. So I think that was the only difference.
We allow the 2 added spots going in front of the cross right right diagonal across I have the number here alone. So, the question is, where would the 2 added spots be? And so I just pull them up now. Can you pull them up? Yeah, I'll pull them on screen share and show you guys. Sorry. And while he's pulling it up to the commissioners have any questions concerns if you remember this 1 was, you know.
We had, there was already dedicated spots there that we're looking for additional, but it was very difficult for us to find. But I think we've come up with a working solution that involved a petitioner and the traffic engineer, et cetera. So if you have questions while he's pulling this up, we could just show you where the two additional spots are. So would we add similar signs? The sign is right here. It would just be,
I don't even know if it's either change it or black out the Friday. I'm not sure what what's easier for you, Tim. But I mean, even a blacked out Friday, the sign is good. Otherwise, the times are so that marks the three spots. Where would the two additional go side to additional would come over here.
And we've notified these residents, we asked them if they wanted to come on the petition tonight. Should be in front of 61 and we also notified other neighbors that were here. And there were no objections. They had objections.
While they were there, their objections were that the amount of vehicles that are parked there during church hours floods the streets. But there weren't objections to us adding more parking, directed parking for them, but we notified them of the Zoom. We told them that they can show up here for this.
It was more the residents that we had were in this blue house because this is, I believe, like multifamily correct townhouse usage and they don't have much parking. So. They're saying when the church is in session that the issues where the parking not so much.
that they had any issues, so that's adding more parking for them over here. All right, so let me just, well, since you mentioned it anyway, we can do this. Is there anyone here in the public wishing to speak on this petition, just to make sure, because I can't see every, there's not many left, but I want to make sure that, yeah. Okay, seeing none. Commissioners, questions or comments on what the sergeants have presented to you? Is Dexter a permanent parking street? No.
It's an open street. It's only from Bow to Broadway that it's resident parking. Edwards, though, that runs parallel or across, is resident parking. So those folks on Dexter are limited, as well as the folks who are attending service. Because generally they're legacy streets, and that means they're 24-7.
versus having one day of a reprieve, Sundays and holidays. So I know the seven-day advent, their service day is actually Saturday and not Sunday, so it's a little bit different. So the resident parking process generally goes out the window with Sunday and holiday at that point.
and the street is open. Do we have other churches who have public parking lane dedications? We try to mirror them. St. Clements on St. Clements Road has it. If you go to St. Clements Road, you can see the signage, and it just says during service. It doesn't say specifically Sunday if I'm familiar with it, like specific service hours like they do. Thanks.
Question would be related to 2024-70 would be to approve the petition based on the recommendations of the traffic sergeants to add two additional parking spots across the street. The petitioner and the church have already been advised that the brother's member's congregation would have to park out on Main Street and on appropriate parking spots
Uh, they've been advised when they were here that they should look into transportation or transporting their, uh, congregation to the church in other means. And the neighbors have been, uh, spoken to regarding this or to deny the petition outright, but place it into your hands.
Did you say you had advised them of what we found? We advised them. They were advised of the meeting here tonight as well. Did we tell the church what we had decided to do? I left the voicemail with him. I haven't been able to get a hold of him. Okay.
I have no problem going down there. I should be able to get into this week, so I will notify him. I don't know if there's any benefit to notifying them what we've decided to do before we vote on it, or just go ahead and approve it. He wanted 10, we're allowing five. We think that was a similar number that we've awarded with other churches in the area of Medford.
I mean, I would vote to approve it. I would just be curious as to whether we should advise petitioners of these situations before we go ahead and vote on them. It's always a good point, but I would just remind us that the petitioner was present and was told we would review in 30 days.
We have the original date, he was told we would be taking this up again. And that is what we are doing. And we did make attempts to get him present here this evening. And we didn't know that that meeting. Okay. Yeah. Barring any further questions or comments from my colleagues, I'd submit a motion to pass it.
Okay. On the motion of Commissioner Brzezinski to approve 2024-70 with two additional parking spots as recommended by the Medford Police Traffic Sergeants. Preferably in the number 61. Preferably by 61 with a change to the signage to reflect the actual church hours of Wednesday, Saturday, Sunday on all sides. Do I have a second?
Second. Seconded by Commissioner Hunt. Alba, can I get a roll call, please? Commissioner McGiven? Yes. Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski? Yes. Chief Buckley? Yes. On a vote of four to nothing, the petition is approved as recommended. That's two more tabled items taken off.
I wouldn't say we're burning down the table. We added one. Took two off, added one. Took two off, but we added one. Still positive. Yeah, absolutely. OK, so that concludes all new business and table business that we are prepared to deal with. Chief, can I make a point? Yes, please. Sorry. Yeah, don't worry.
2024-37 was a 6-month review of the G-Zone, which should have been this month's meeting. Do we need to make just an acknowledgment? Presuming no one is ready to talk about that, can we push that a month?
I'm going to ask Jim Silva, would you be prepared to deal, is that that next month? Or would you like to discuss tonight? It's probably should have given you a little bit more advanced notice, but. Yeah, I know. You can start the conversation. I think that would be fine. Questions, review?
specifically, we have had a great deal of community, a positive response. People are participating in it. We've worked out some of the variance issues. We still have to do that for our main streets. Specifically, I think we
We've looked at some of them on Stanley and Main as well as Bow and Harvard Street. So we still have some work that we need to do to accomplish, but at least now those folks are able to get variances where we've had two complaints in community.
We have done an informal review going up and down streets during certain times of the day to see if they have been inundated with cars. I think from a traffic group here can probably attest to this. We haven't seen a great deal of influx or one location that folks might be moving from one part of the G zone to be closer to the public transportation, for instance, even in the colder weather.
I think from a resource from enforcement, it's a much easier process where you're not looking to see what street you're on to check a car for what street. I think our LPR is working a little bit better this way. And again, we are a bit resource challenged. So I think the response has been good. Specifically, I know from interaction in my community, my neighborhood,
So I think it's important that people are happy that on the smallest streets, they can find parking when they need to.
I want to entertain questions from the commissioners related to the G zone, but I do recognize that we're probably going to have to take this up at next meeting for approval, because this is a pilot program. I assume, Jim, that we want to move on from the pilot program and make this G zone a permanent parking system within the city of Medford.
Well, I'll let the commissioners comment, but I would like to put this on the agenda for next month for more discussion. Early on. For next month? Well, it's table of business. Well, it's table for tonight, but I don't know if we're prepared to address making it permanent. I think we probably should have given Jim Silver a little bit more heads up if he was prepared. I mean, those are great comments, but commissioners, do we have any questions or concerns?
I guess just from a procedural standpoint, do we need to just amend the reference to the January 2025 meeting? Does Jim want to submit a petition to approve it for approval next month or in March? Or can this be some sort of transition to actually a discussion to make it or take it out of a pilot program status?
specifically what do you need to identify what information would you be comfortable, what data would I be able to provide you that you might request? I think what you provided tonight was enough. I mean, I think that if I can remember correctly, what we were looking for is just to try to appease people that thought this would be a disaster. It sounds like it's not a disaster.
So, you know, I don't necessarily know that it mean, maybe it kind of transitions on its own from being a pilot program to being like a full fledged program. But no, I think what you've provided tonight is suffices for me. I don't need to see data or anything along those lines. It's very fair to suggest that we could just.
I don't know if we want to allow people who are in that
do we push the petition to take it out of a pilot program status to the next meeting? But I would not necessarily be looking for a full-fledged presentation by Jim unless my colleagues decide otherwise. Again, I think if I remember correctly, I just wanted to know that this thing wasn't falling apart. The traffic division hasn't filled it.
Any calls about the G zone. So to Steve's to Steve's point, we did say in our public meeting that it was a pilot. We're going to revisit in 6 months. So, I think we owe the public an agenda item. The next meeting, just so we can say that we did that. And then anybody who wants to speak. Maybe there's issues that new issues that maybe we could solve now.
I don't know what those would be, but we can get, you know, a similar report that we just heard from Jim. And then if there's anybody else that attends from the neighborhood or would like to say something, then I would like to hear that. Thanks so much, Commissioner Hunt. As any major objections, I would be looking for a motion to defer the six-month G-Zone review until February 2025, the 2025th meeting, with appropriate notifications. So moved.
Okay, on the motion of commission to be given. Can I ask a question real fast? I mean, how do we alert people to know that this is like next month we are voting to take this out of being a pilot program? Are people notified of that like they would a new petition? I think anybody who's interested knows because they were here and then we said six months and then they should be right around now looking at our agenda.
Um, to come here, that's fine. That's fine enough for me. I just didn't know if we needed to actually have, like, a, a separate petition that says, like, conversion of pilot program to final. And that triggers some sort of additional notice, but if we're comfortable that it's been on there, you had a right for 6 months. I'm all about caveat. So, you know, we can just leave it as is and vote on it next month.
So I have a motion of Commissioner McGiven to take 2024-37 and defer the six-month review until February 2025. Do I have a second? I'd second that. Seconded by Commissioner Brzezinski. Alva, roll call, please. Commissioner McGiven? Yes, siree. Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski?
Yes. Chief Buckley? Yes, on a vote of four to nothing, the motion is approved. We will take up 2024-37 next month. And then, Chief, one last item, and then I promise, because I want to go home, I'm still in Boston. 2023-47, looks like we were supposed to review that February of 2024. And there's no left turn in. Yep.
Again, that's actually a good one. Let's take this, well, I'll wait for the motion, this 2023-47 to take up next month because I do want to gather the data on that. I don't believe we've had a single issue up there on this from the police perspective. We probably may want to have also put that out publicly as an agenda item to allow people who live in that neighborhood to come forward. We actually just took down a speed radar sign there on Emerson Street that we've had up there.
Prior to the no left turn and now where it is, and we've dropped. 57% of vehicle traffic on Emerson street, so. Awesome, I would assume the ways and GPS has have corrected themselves.
I, I feel it 1 of the safest decisions we made. We haven't had a collision in that intersection. I know that was some of the concerns that they had in the beginning with this, but we haven't had 1 collision there since since this has been an active other than the 1st and cracking into the numbers, but that doesn't count.
So Commissioner Brzezinski, if you would like to make a motion to bring that to the forefront with an agenda item for the next meeting and allow any of the neighbors impacted, we can do that also. A motion to bring 2023-47 to be discussed and voted on at the February 2025 meeting. Okay, on the motion of Commissioner Brzezinski, do I have a second? Second. And by Commissioner McGiven, I'll have a roll call vote, please. Commissioner McGiven? Yes.
Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski? Yes. Chief Gossage? Yes. On the vote of four to nothing, the motion is approved 2023-47. Bring forward to the traffic commission. And I promised one last one, 2021-59. Looks like we were supposed to review that in six months in September of 22. Well, it's pulling up.
the West Metro Community Center. That was the request he made for he just wanted to have some help to park in front of the center and I think you know we agreed to provide for one sign and then revisit it. I don't know if we've heard from him since. Yeah so you know that's actually very interesting and timely. We have reviewed it ourselves and we felt initially as this was going along that one side was
comfortable, but the West Memphis Community Center has requested that second sign again. So we will, if we follow suit and bring this up again for next month, I think we should reach out to the community center and just have a conversation with them about their needs for that second handicap sign.
Because they had asked for two originally, we agreed to one with a review to see if they still needed the two. We felt it was sufficient, at least going up through those six months, but we recently received a request from them to add that second sign. So something we could, if we want to follow suit and have the motion to make sure that we take up 2021-59 in the February meeting, we can notify, or at least in the meantime, have the conversations with West Memphis Community Center and get their input into whether or not they feel it's still needed.
The only point of order, I would just, I'd much rather either bring it up for vote next month or can we correct the fact, correct the date on which we're gonna review it? To give you and your team some more time to take a look at it. I think we're comfortable with the next month. I would handle this one. It's not gonna be heavy lifted. So if we follow suit and do the same thing to take up 2021-59,
which has already called for a review in six months on the February 2025 meeting, it would be sufficient for us to be able to provide all the information we need to this commission. Motion to bring 2021-59 for a vote at the February 2025 meeting. The motion of commission of Brzezinski to bring 2021-59 forward at the February 2025 meeting. Do I have a second? Second.
seconded by Commissioner McGiven. Commissioner McGiven? Yes. Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski? Yes. Steve Buckley? Yes. All three of those will be placed on the agenda for formal review with notifications from the other parties. I feel like we're actually starting to clean up some of this business. It feels good.
it's a positive emotion. Okay, anything else from the commissioners?
Jim, I appreciate your presence as usual. Sergeant Talbot, thank you. Sarah, welcome aboard, and thank you for coming. It is, I mean, we make reference all the time to having additional parties who are impacted by our decisions present at these meetings, and your presence is gonna go a long way. You already cleared up some of the stuff that we can and can't do with Barking the Bombing, so kudos to you for taking the time to do this, and thank you very, very much from the Traffic Commission, and welcome aboard.
With that, I'll take a motion to adjourn and happy 2025 to all of you. Motion? So moved. Second. All those in favor? Aye. Aye. Motion is approved. I think there's so few of us, we don't have to take another roll call. I think Alderman's roll called out. I have a roll called out. All right. Thank you very much. I appreciate it. Thanks for your time. See you next time. Thanks, everybody.