[SPEAKER_02]: Good evening, everybody.
[SPEAKER_02]: Good afternoon, ladies and gentlemen, and thank you for being here for a lottery.
[SPEAKER_02]: We're just doing some final preparations.
[SPEAKER_02]: and setting up the Zoom, Dr. Edouard-Vincent will be with you shortly for the lottery.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you very much for joining us today, and we'll be with you shortly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good afternoon, Mustang family.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am so excited to be here.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have right now 77, probably more than 77, because I see some of you are with your parents right now on the call.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm really excited.
[SPEAKER_01]: We are getting ready to do our middle school lottery.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am Dr. Edouard-Vincent, your very proud superintendent.
[SPEAKER_01]: And with me today, I have our data manager, Ms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Kim Miles.
[SPEAKER_01]: who is going to be working magic in the background on the table right behind me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And next to me is Dr. Bernadette Riccadeli, who is our director of professional learning and student assessment.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Dr. Riccadeli is here as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as we go through today's process to actually select the schools and do the actual lottery, if there are questions,
[SPEAKER_01]: We will be putting it in the chat box.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you have questions or you need clarification or support, either Dr. Ricciardelli or Ms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Kim Miles, you will be able to email them with questions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we will make sure that we get that into the chat box.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I want to thank you all for your patience.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have a couple of different technology.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're using the Zoom room and we're using our individual computers.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we're muted at different points.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I want to end the suffering and hopefully have lots of rejoicing that's going to take place.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're going to start this lottery process.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're going to do it in ABC order, alphabetical order with our schools.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as soon again, as the schools are picked,
[SPEAKER_01]: we will be working very diligently to get those numbers online.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that you will be so give us about an hour, but we may be able to get it online, you know, maybe within 30 to 40 minutes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that depends on how quickly we are able to get everything done.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am also just gonna pass the baton to Dr. Ricciardelli and give her a minute just to address you as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then we will start
[SPEAKER_01]: The lottery process.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you again for your patience and good afternoon to all of you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hello families.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's so great to see you.
[SPEAKER_04]: I see a couple of familiar faces.
[SPEAKER_04]: for those of you that have your screen on.
[SPEAKER_04]: So as Superintendent Edouard-Vincent just said, within an hour, maybe a little over an hour, you will know for sure.
[SPEAKER_04]: So when we run the stat track program, which is a random number generator, Kim Miles, who you were introduced moments ago, is gonna be running that.
[SPEAKER_04]: So she's in the room, but you're not gonna see the numbers as they're pulled up.
[SPEAKER_04]: She's gonna pull them up,
[SPEAKER_04]: they're gonna be printed out, and then they are going to be put onto our website.
[SPEAKER_04]: All right, so at that point, you'll see which school you're assigned to, whether it be the McGlynn or the Andrews.
[SPEAKER_04]: We are gonna pull them in alphabetical order, so the Brooks will be first, followed by the McGlynn, then the Mississippi, and then the Roberts.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then once you do find out which school you're assigned to, you will be invited to one of the open
[SPEAKER_04]: one of the two open houses.
[SPEAKER_04]: So the Andrews open house will be on May 4th and the McGlynn open house will be on May 2nd.
[SPEAKER_04]: You'll also be getting an official letter with the school assignment that is slated to go out on April 24th.
[SPEAKER_04]: We're hopeful that we're going to be able to get it out to you before the end of this week.
[SPEAKER_04]: So we scheduled it for April 24th, but we think we can get it out to you earlier.
[SPEAKER_04]: All right, so I think without any further delay in this process, I know that you wanna find out as soon as possible.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think at this point, we are gonna turn it over to Kim and she is gonna start the random number generator for the Brooks Elementary School.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it's just gonna take maybe a minute or two, maybe three for each school.
[SPEAKER_04]: So sit tight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Also in true lottery fashion,
[SPEAKER_01]: I've had the pleasure of always playing our Jeopardy music because we're kind of waiting.
[SPEAKER_01]: So please enjoy the music from Jeopardy.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, Miss Miles.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, so Lottery 1 at the Brooks.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, you know,
[SPEAKER_03]: okay the first draw
[SPEAKER_01]: I apologize.
[SPEAKER_01]: I apologize for the echo.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first draw just took place for the Brooks, and the second draw will be taking place as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: I apologize for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Second lottery just pulled lottery to Brooks.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's complete.
[SPEAKER_01]: Brooke School is complete.
[SPEAKER_01]: So for each school, for each school, there will be two draws.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first draw and the second draw is for some of our students that are that have some of our students with disabilities that there is a draw to evenly balance the students between every single school.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for every single school, there will be two draws.
[SPEAKER_01]: And right now that we've completed the Brooks, we're going to move on to the Glen, but both draws just took place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: McGlynn McGlynn first draw is complete.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's printing right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we are going to wait for McGlynn second draw to come out next.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Second draw for the McGlynn just took place.
[SPEAKER_03]: Third draw is going to be
[SPEAKER_01]: Missittuck Elementary School.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's getting ready to print.
[SPEAKER_01]: First draw for the Missittuck is printing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And second draw for the Missittuck will begin shortly.
[SPEAKER_03]: second poll is complete.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is printing right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mr. Tuck.
[SPEAKER_01]: Second poll is
[SPEAKER_01]: Robert's school first draw is being pulled.
Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: First draw for the Roberts took place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Second draw for the Roberts is taking place right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: said you want to let people know.
[SPEAKER_03]: I promise we will get things up there within 30 minutes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Um, people are waiting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good news.
[SPEAKER_01]: We know that families are waiting.
[SPEAKER_01]: I hope.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I see a thumbs up if families can hear me?
[SPEAKER_01]: Excellent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Um, good news.
[SPEAKER_01]: Miss Miles said she she will be able to get the
[SPEAKER_01]: all the numbers up onto the website within 30 minutes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So let's hope for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I actually see that we have some of our principals on the call as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, Jessica Sa, I love you too.
[SPEAKER_01]: I love all of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just wanna see, now we have 86 families on the call.
[SPEAKER_01]: So all of our draws took place.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm gonna look at our reactions.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are from the Brooks School, let us see how many clapping hands pop up on the screens.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just would love to see that.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're from the Brooks School, all right, I see clapping hands.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see clapping hands.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see Ida and Jessica and Lily and Grace.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see Rosa.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know some of us don't have our cameras on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Poma and Sophia.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fabulous.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm trying to swing to jump through.
[SPEAKER_01]: I wanted to just give you a shout out for being on the call.
[SPEAKER_01]: This will be available to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are from the McGlynn school, can I see a thumbs up?
[SPEAKER_01]: Um, under reactions, McGlynn school.
[SPEAKER_01]: All right.
[SPEAKER_01]: I saw, um, Oh, Lally.
[SPEAKER_01]: I got clapping down there too.
[SPEAKER_01]: Great.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jessica, Victoria.
[SPEAKER_01]: Um,
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's see who else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wonderful for the McGlynn.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are from the Missittuck, can I see some hearts?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I see any hearts go up?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're representing the Missittuck Elementary School, Kim D, Tom Ye, I see you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm flipping through, so I'm not, I just wanna recognize you.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are from the Roberts School, can I see the hooray little horn, like the party horn?
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's look.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see you, Lynn.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I see AK.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see, I just saw George.
[SPEAKER_01]: All right, let's have everybody who's on the call, whatever school you represent,
[SPEAKER_01]: And what I asked was, clapping for the Brooks, thumbs up for the McGlynn, heart for the Missituk, and the little party horn for the Roberts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I see everyone respond all at once?
[SPEAKER_01]: Fabulous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Erlandy, I see you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see you, Ben, and Ida, and Michelle, and Miss Deimos, and David, and Lynn.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wonderful.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see all Mary and Victoria and Jenna and Courtney and Wally.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see Kirk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, Kirk Davis.
[SPEAKER_01]: I miss Hayes.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, warrior.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wonderful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I just wanted to give any of the principles a quick opportunity if they if they just want to say hello and Kim I saw you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you for your wonderful reactions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we don't announce the numbers because the numbers are personal to every single student and family.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we pull all the numbers, the numbers will be posted, and no one's name is affiliated with the number.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have your personalized number, so that will happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Demos, I'm not sure if you wanted to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just here for the excitement.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Equally excited.
[SPEAKER_01]: And of course, principals will be receiving the list as well to be able to confirm once it's done.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I was looking to see if I saw a different administrator, but miss demos, I think you are on the call today.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you for representing all of our elementary principals.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, ah, Principal O'Brien, there you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't see you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you like to speak, Principal O'Brien?
[SPEAKER_00]: Certainly, Dr. Edwards.
[SPEAKER_00]: Congratulations to all our fifth grade kiddos who are about to find out where they will be attending middle school next year.
[SPEAKER_00]: Very happy for you all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Super, super happy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Principal O'Brien, there was a wonderful question asking, where is it gonna appear?
[SPEAKER_01]: So our website team, we're gonna be working with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're gonna try to have it prominent, like a button or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when you go to the main page, there will be something that is gonna say middle school lottery, and then you'll be able to go into that
[SPEAKER_01]: and we will have that information available front and center.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you will not go on a wild goose chase.
[SPEAKER_01]: Go to Medford Public Schools, our main website, and you'll be able to do it that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm just trying to look at...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I want to say thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll see the number.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some of the questions I'm looking at.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Each student was given a number and Dr. Riccadeli, I'm going to ask if you are able to just put your email in the chat box for both you and for Ms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Miles.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again,
[SPEAKER_01]: if for whatever reason you need to speak with an administrator, both Ms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Miles and Dr. Riccadeli, they are going to be available to help support you with this process.
[SPEAKER_01]: But thank you for jumping on the lottery.
[SPEAKER_01]: I could see Lynn is so excited.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know this is like, it's exciting.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't wait till all of you get your wonderful assignments.
[SPEAKER_01]: And thank you to so many of you for jumping on the call today.
[SPEAKER_01]: And your numbers will be up within 30 minutes, within 30 minutes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's 328 by four o'clock.
[SPEAKER_01]: We will have the numbers up and available for everyone to find their assignments.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you, parents.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you, family, caregivers.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you, principals.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you, team.
[SPEAKER_01]: Have a great rest of the day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Enjoy the beautiful weather outside.