All right, we're gonna start the meeting of the October meeting, 2022 Traffic Commission. I will be filling in for Chief Buckley, who cannot make it. I'd like to introduce Sergeant Jonah Canava, recently promoted, is assigned to the Traffic Division. Sergeant McGilvery is now Lieutenant McGilvery in Night Patrol.
So Jordan will be helping me, assisting me in the traffic. I'd like to call the meeting to order. Albert, could you do roll call, please? Commissioner McGibbon? Here. Commissioner Hunt? She didn't tell me she's coming, so for what that's worth.
Thank you, Commissioner Pesetoro. She has called in and she will be absent. Commissioner Brzezinski. I don't hear anything. We don't have a quorum. Hold on, they must be here. So I'm gonna let them in now. One more, there are two more joining now. That might be them. Oh, Steve is in, okay, Steve Brzezinski.
Okay. Okay. Commissioner Brzezinski. One second. It might take them a second. That should be, that should be better. How's that? Should be good now. Commissioner Brzezinski. We see his name. Yeah. He's not present. Thank you. Sergeant Rogers present.
I believe Alicia's Alicia just came on as well. I am here present. Do you want to make me a co-host and I'll help with the waiting room and stuff? Sorry. I'm late. You should be able to call us now, Alicia.
Yep, got it. Okay, I'd like to- One present, one absent. Okay. I'd like to approve the meetings of the September meeting. Could I have a motion, please? Motion. Second. Second. Tim and Steve. I have a roll call. Commissioner McGibbon? Yes. Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski? Yes.
Badger Rogers. Present? Yes, yes. All in the affirmative, one absent. Okay, thank you. So we're gonna go on and do new business. 2022-54, permit parking variance, military exemption from Matthew Seath, 12 Golden Ave. Is the petitioner here? This has been approved. It has been approved.
Yes, and this is more or less bookkeeping. Okay. So a motion to approve. Could I have a motion to approve? Sorry, I don't have any understanding what this is. Could you, I can't vote for something. I have no idea what a military exemption is. I'm not questioning it, I just don't know what it is. He is assigned to this area for two to three years.
In the military, he's an active member of the military, he's assigned to this area, and we give variances with military exemptions. Does that mean he gets a parking permit without having to register his car at the Medford address because he's military and moves frequently? Is that what that means? Yes, it does.
And I assume, Alva, you were saying you have all the paperwork, something proving that he is military. Somebody can't just say it. You have something. Yes, Commissioner. It's quite a stack of papers. Great. And I assume that's a permit parking street. Yes. Yes, it is.
Yeah, there it is on my on my map. Which is I'm ready to move approval unless other commissioners just had other questions. I've never been asked to approve this kind of permit before. So let's say this is administrative approval. Why do we need to vote for it? If this is already approved?
I think it's just a process, Tim, to approve a variance. Where it's military. Military exemption. Yes. Yeah. I mean, yeah, I'll second it to keep things moving. I'm curious about it just a little bit more. But anyway, to keep these moving, I will approve it. Do I have a motion? Yes, Alicia, and second Tim. All right. I have a roll call. Commissioner McGibbon? Yes.
Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski? Yes. Sergeant Rogers? Yes. Four, one absent. It's approved. Okay, motion passes. 2022-55, handicap sign for Giovanni Ciampa, 18, Dexter Street. Is the petitioner here? And I don't believe they have access to Zoom.
The paperwork is in order. Paperwork is in order. Commissioners, any comments? Have we done our standard to go out there and take a look at the property and ensure? I did, Steve, I did it on Sunday. Okay. Do we know what the issue is that they just can't get, there's no driveway, there's no access?
Easy for her to park right out front, the stairs are right there, the driveway I believe is on the left hand side. And I just, I called it up an image of it and it looks like the driveway is right next to the house and that the car door, driver's door opens to right next to the door. They have a handicap parking plate and a car that they're planning to park there? Correct.
Can we pull it up on Google? I'm aware that this area is a very tight neighborhood, tight for parking. I'm looking at... Is 18 the white house?
with a light colored house? Right there at the corner. Yeah, it's right there. This one, right? No, I think it's the one right there. Those are odd numbers on that side. Yeah, turn around. See that white house? Not that way, the other way.
at the corner. That one? No, it's the one in between that one and the one that is the green color. It's the next one over. Which way? To the left. This way? Left. Left, yep. Wow. Right there on the right. That's the one, that light blue.
Is that driveway their driveway or is that the number 16 driveway? I think it's number 16. Yeah, it is number 16. Their driveway is to the right. So they don't have a driveway. No, there's no driveway to the right. That light blue house says 16 if you zoom in. No. It says 18. That should say 18 right there. Yeah. That's 18. Okay.
So I guess that SUV, that's not their vehicle. I didn't think it was their vehicle. I thought it belonged to the brown house when I went out. And this is just sort of why it's good to hear from, because I would have assumed that that would be the perfect place to park. They don't have access to Zoom at all.
Okay, I'm just gonna take a quick look at the assessor's maps while we get it open. Also, her father was extremely handicapped and she does drive him. So if it is that, the father cannot get out of the passenger. She is handicapped and he is handicapped.
And she is his lone caretaker. I'm just reading my notes now. The father was extremely handicapped. And for him to get out of the passenger and for her if they parked the other way, for her to get out would be a burden.
And so is the issue that they're already parking on the street, they just want something more guaranteed? Correct, Tim. Steve. Steve. Was that Steve or Tim? Not offended. I like Tim. Tim, were you looking up anything in particular? I mean, I'd support a motion for this. I was just trying to confirm if that driveway was the neighbor's driveway. Tim, I thought when I went out there was the neighbor's driveway.
Okay. Cause I did speak to the sun. And do they have a, okay. So how do they get back to the back of their property? Then I'm wondering, it must be a, is there a path on the other side? The path on the other side. Okay. Yeah. It looks like there's a little pathway of some sort. Commission is anything else?
All right. I'm OK with it if we don't believe that that driveway is theirs. Yeah, give me one second, I'll pull it up, I'm having some trouble finding the property. Even if it is, again, the way you say that's their truck, the father cannot get out of the passenger side. Mm hmm.
A lot bigger than I thought. Wow. There it is, 16. Thanks for showing those up. So what it looks like is that
It does actually look like the driveway is on their parcel, is on the parcel for number 18. I mean, it sounds like, Larry, that there's multiple reasons that they're looking for this, multiple people that are in need of it for this handicap parking spot. Are there any other handicap parking spots on this street
on this block, if not. Not in that block. There are on Texas Street, but not in this area, no. Not in this area? I mean, I wouldn't be opposed to having a handicapped parking spot on the street in general on the block, especially if we have people in need of it. But it does look like that driveway is at least on their property, whether or not there's any easement rights shared or anything. I'm not seeing any handicapped spots. Steve has made
The motion, do you want to accept that? Yeah, I'll second that motion. Second. Alva, roll call. Commissioner McGibbon? Yep. Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski? He made the motion. Commissioner Rodgers? Yes. So in the affirmative, one absent, the motion passes.
Thank you. 2022-56 Harvard Street. No parking anytime within an hour from approximately 192 to 196 Harvard Street, South on Main. Sorry, from Sergeant Rogers. So if we can pull this up. So just to commissioners,
There is resident parking on Harvard Street. So I wish Todd was here tonight, he's not. He measured it and there is enough ample space for those cars to park and for traffic to get by on both sides. 192 to 196, there is not enough traffic to get by flowing and therefore we like the no parking sign
in that area to prevent people from parking on the sidewalk.
Am I correct in, sorry, I've discussed this issue with a number of people. I believe that we've discussed this even here at traffic commission that it is extremely common for people to park on those sidewalks and that that becomes a pedestrian because one could imagine that do you really need the signage because it's not wide enough, but people are actually parking on the sidewalks
And there really is not room to be on. It's illegal, Alicia. Right. You can't be back on the sidewalk. So this would help that situation. Correct. Any other commissioners.
Larry, are we codifying something here that is physically kind of impossible safe and safe anyway? Yes, exactly what we're doing. All right, I'm in favor of that. I mean, I'm not even sure I need to look it up, but 192 to 196, are these close in proximity? It's further down. It's almost at the corner of Main Street. No, no, no. Oh, it's right there? This is 192. Oh, okay, all right.
It's almost opposite the driveway coming out from between the townhouses and the condos. Do I remember correctly that people were actually parking on the sidewalk up at the crosswalk and we discussed the need to put signs up that said no parking on sidewalk? I don't recall that, Alicia.
But I don't know why we would, for a sidewalk, there's no parking on a sidewalk either way, so it'd be no parking. Yeah, we shouldn't put any signs that say no parking on the sidewalk. It's already illegal. Yeah. It's already signed, just sign clutter. My next question is, are we talking about eastbound only, or are we talking about eastbound and westbound? Eastbound only. Okay. All right, a motion for approval. I need to open it up.
Do we have anyone in the audience? I wanna make one other comment. When I go on Google, so I just wanted to make sure I understood the, when I'm looking at them, if I look at, so it's, what is the street range that we're talking about? Like when I look at Google Maps right now in front of 186, that image that they're using, there is a vehicle sitting on the sidewalk. So that would be in the area where it would not be allowed.
Correct, that that's all of that is where it's not. Can you just show us again, it's so it's from Main Street, all the way up to where 192 to 196, I'll follow it through. Okay. Yeah, I just want to make sure I understand what it is we're approving. So we're at Main Street, correct. Yep. I'm going to just go down to it.
So it's these vehicles on the left, which we can all walk there. Correct. All right. We have any other, um, no parking here at all, like, uh, near the intersection or anything like that. There is on the other side, not on this side on Westbound side, we have, you know,
No parking here to corner and nothing on eastbound side. Okay. There's no, and then what, what I understood Todd did mention this to me. I asked him about it today. Was that above the other direct, the rest of the street, he said is wide enough for somebody to legally park on the street.
Yep, correct. And so from there up, if people parked on the sidewalk, they would get ticketed from the police, but legally park on the street. Correct. As long as they're residents, right. It's resident resident. Okay. That answers my opening up commissioners moment.
Nothing here. Okay, I see there's a member of the public with their hand up. Sergeant, were you going to call on them? Are you waiting? I thought we're waiting on Tim. Oh, no.
Tony said you needed a second. Yeah. But, um, if we're going to wait for public input before we vote, I mean, I can, I'm ready to motion, but if procedure, yeah. Procedure is public input. You know, definitely speak. So we should let her speak. I think she, she can speak. Yep. You have to talk. May I speak?
Go ahead, yeah. Can you hear me? Yeah, sorry. It's okay. It's Anne Fretz of 215 Harvard Street. Unfortunately, I initiated this whole process by responding to the blocked sidewalks on the opposite side from where our condominium complex is located. It is a safer side of the street for us to walk because the trucks actually don't jump the curb behind the cars. And unfortunately,
In the effort to unblock the sidewalks, the parking on the sidewalk has been brought forth to you. I appreciate that very much. However,
What I'm most concerned about, and I'm sure all the other residents and owners of the 50 condos here, is where will the 20 or more vehicles that are going to be displaced, where are they going to park? The most logical place for them to park is in the Yale Street public lot, which as Todd has said many times, is underutilized, and particularly overnight. However,
We, condo owners, even with traffic gates up, are besieged by trespassers coming from Harvard Street over to the Yale Street lot when there isn't parking available, even worse during snow emergencies. This presents a liability for us and also an influx of people on private property using it as if they live there.
It's not just an insensitive, I'm going to run to my car quickly. They're under our windows. This is a city, we recognize that, but we are a private property and I would like to see this issue tabled until determination is made where these displaced vehicles would park, how the trespassers would be handled, because there is no way for the MPD to support
not having trespassers on our property. They will not patrol. They cannot stop them. We've been advised do not approach, do not confront, do not take pictures. So we're sitting ducks for people to just stream through back and forth to the property. Again, they're a liability. Even if they're trespassing and they get hurt, they can sue us. We don't want to see 20, 40 people
you know, two people per car cutting through the property as they're doing. We can hear them late at night. We hear them during the day. And I'm wondering what options and what thought has been put into place for how to deal with this, it basically exacerbating an ongoing issue that has existed for 12 years. And I've tried to manage it by myself with my husband, who's Larry Fretz, the president of the Condo Association and other,
people who live here and own the property. We have two owners who cannot sell their property because they live along one of the driveways, units one and two. I don't think they'd be too pleased to hear that they still can't open their windows or raise their blinds because there'll be more people cutting through to get back and forth to their cars. The trash, and I'm pretty sure that Dave Perlis, who lives in 18 Yale Street, abutting our property, won't appreciate it either, having more traffic cutting through.
And it's just a major concern for the value of our property.
for the existence of the peace and quiet of the people who live on the property known as Lincoln Kennedy condominiums. This should have been designed and anticipated years ago prior to the construction. We've looked at both Charlie Hart, I'm sorry, Lieutenant Hartnett and I looked at perhaps putting a pathway through requesting the fire department narrow the driveway distance from 24 feet to perhaps
19 feet that would allow the another alleyway to actually be put in place and fenced in by the city and maintained by the city for said trespassers to get through the property without interfering with our lives and increasing our liability.
I don't think that would happen. Another option might be to issue parking permits for the people who would be displaced and ticket them if they do trespass on the property. That would have to be monitored by our cameras, should we have any that would capture them. But until now, we haven't been able to ascertain who the people are, because we don't have the support to or
inclination to confront them, follow them to their homes. We don't have their names and address. No one wants to pursue filing a no trespass order. According to the police, it would be left out of the courts, wasting the court's time. But it is an issue. We are a private property. We don't want people cutting through the property in addition to the capacity that we already have that use our property on a daily basis. And I'm wondering what your thoughts are.
Thank you, Anne. Do we have anyone else like to speak? Larry Fretz, can I speak? Am I unmuted? Welcome. Go ahead, Larry. Okay. I don't think I could have done a better job than Anne just did explaining the situation the way it is. As the president, I'm concerned about the safety of everybody who lives here and having people walking through our property
is especially in the middle of the night is concerning. As you're rotating, that's one of the entrances across our property. And if you go the other way towards Main Street, you'll see there's another entrance to our property that crosses over to Yale Street. And Anne is referring to the small parcel right there where possibly a fence could be built and a walkway going through our property.
One of the things that's a bit distressing for me is I've heard through the grapevine that if we stop people because they're trespassing through our property, sort of like if somebody was trespassing in your backyard to get to the other side of the street, if we stop them and if we confront them and say they're trespassing and they continue to move, I either have to physically stop them or call the police.
I'm being told that the police will not enforce a trespassing in this particular situation. And I'm having a very difficult time understanding that since their job is to enforce laws. The law is you can't trespass on somebody else's property, needless to say. So this whole thing is a little bit disconcerting for me and for the association. And we're trying to get, trying to find some kind of
middle ground where we can make it work for the city as well as make it work for the association. So Larry, as far as the trespass law, they have to be served with a no trespass order. And then if they trespass, then we can take action. But if they are not served with the trespass order, well, we cannot take action.
Thank you. May I speak again? If they're in the middle of the property and I call the police, you're saying the police would not come down? Let's assume maybe they're not just trespassers. Maybe they're somebody who wants to rob the place. You're saying the police will not come down because they haven't been served? Larry, that's not what I'm saying. What I'm saying is you cannot take action
on a trespass until they have been served with a trespass notice. May I speak again?
Go ahead, Den. The question is, if we don't know who these people are, and they're regularly trespassing through our property, and we ask the support of the MPD to identify who they are, get their address, so that we can serve them with a no trespass order, how do we go about that? Because right now we're not going to get that support. And it's private property, all right? So to stop someone on a trespass,
All right, you need to find out who they are, where they live and serve them with a trespass order. We've been told do not follow them, do not confront them, do not photograph them or videotape them. We've asked for support to visit certain homes across the street on Harvard Street to ascertain the names and addresses of said trespassers. And that happened maybe once or twice in the past 12 years.
We don't have the support we need to eliminate or even reduce this problem by one or two people. How do we go about getting names and addresses in order to serve a trespass notice?
We can't very well go up to their door without support behind us and ask, hey, could you stop trespassing on our property? We did ask at one point that the chief and the mayor send out a notice to the residents of Harvard Street asking them to respect our right to privacy. That fell through because of legal issues. And that was done two years ago. And it was a dead issue because no one wanted to pursue it for us.
So here we are, a property of a hundred residents who are going to be controlled by anybody who wants to use our property as their alleyway. And it's just not appropriate. And you're adding, by adding a no parking on Harvard street, the issue that exists is going to be exacerbated by people moving over to, from the Harvard street side where they used to park to the Yale street side.
And the logical route is right to our property through any one of the three axis driveways, whether it's between the buildings, describe what you're looking at right now, or through the driveway of the Lincoln building that leads right over to Radcliffe street. Thank you.
Well, I'm looking for answers. How do we deal with it if you can't do anything, if the police, you can't do anything without having a no trespass order and we don't know who these people are? How do we deal with it? And we're looking before this gets put into place, we're looking for answers and solutions
that protect our property values and our right to privacy. We have every right. I mean, you wouldn't put an, as I said to Harry today, you wouldn't put an alleyway through Dave Perella's property or the DeAntonio's property or allow people to cut through their yards, yet it's okay for our property. I don't understand the difference. If Anthony DeAntonio called,
and said, there's a guy in my driveway that keeps cutting through my property, please deal with them. How would that be handled? We don't know who these people are. We don't have their names and addresses. The landlords are, except for a few, absentee landlords.
and they really don't care about Lincoln Kennedy property. We have some of them showing up and having picnics on our lawn. We have to deal with those one-on-one, but we can't get their names. We can't do anything because we are not supported in obtaining the information necessary to file the appropriate paperwork to get a no trespass order. Have anyone else in the audience, please? Do we have any hands up?
So I will raise it. I do see these, I realize that the Fretz CDs is the same issue, but right now Yale Street is permit parking only. So any of the properties on Harvard Street that wanna park over there have to come and get permits. Nobody's automatically getting them. And the Yale lot is open, but it is paid during the day.
So it's free at night. We're not giving anybody automatic spots. And I'm looking at these, we see five or six cars on the street. This is the other half of Harvard Street. It will be easier for these people to park further up Harvard Street than walk around through to the Yale lot. Also, Alicia, could you just explain that by me again? I didn't follow you there. So only half of Harvard Street is going to be no parking.
So they can just go further up the street and park it. When we look on the street view, we're seeing about six vehicles. And Yale Street, the street itself is permit parking only. So they can't just go park over there. They can park, I assume they can park in the Yale Street lot overnight without coming to us for additional permission. I actually, I don't know that rule off the top of my head.
I'm sure you know it better than I do, but they would have to move or pay the meter first thing in the morning. Sadly, may I speak again? The lot is not patrolled. It's not patrolled overnight except by the NPD and they're not there to ticket. And I do believe that permits are required to park overnight. And if you look at Harvard street during the evening and overnight,
It is jammed from Main Street, back to the bridge. There are no parking spaces for these people to just move down the street and easily find parking the logical flow.
And in speaking with the people who live in 162 Harvard Street, who parks on the sidewalk and is a delightful young gentleman, he said, I'm just going to drive around and park on Yale Street in the lot overnight. I've never been ticketed. I only got ticketed once for street sweeping.
when parking on Harvard Street. So he knows he can do that. And he's blatantly told us, I'm going to cut through your parking, your yard, whether it's the safe place that's well lit between the two buildings or through the driveway next to the Kennedy building exit onto Yale Street. And there is a paucity and others in the neighborhood will tell you, there's a paucity of parking places in the neighborhood. And again,
The entire street is backed up with cars on Harvard Street. Yale Street, yes, is permit parking. The public parking lot used to be permit parking as well, but it is not patrolled. Well, that's an issue with the parking department and the police about whether they're checking for permits overnight. Yeah. Can I check for you?
There's a lot of nuance here in terms of what's legal, what's not legal. I guess I come back to my issue. What do I do when somebody cuts through my property? They're illegally there. I confront them and let them know they're illegally on my property and I don't want them cutting through my property. What is the traffic commission gonna do
to help alleviate that situation and prevent it from happening in the first place. Hey, Larry. Yeah. I'm sorry, not Mr. Fritz. Sergeant Larry. Yes, Tim. May I speak?
Yeah, go ahead. I'd just like to address a couple of things here. So the traffic commission purview, and I'll kind of go backwards with what Mr. Fritz was just saying. So we don't really have purview over your private property and how you deal with trespassers. So Sergeant Larry has given you some advice on that, but there really is a whole section of mass general law that applies just to trespassing. I see two issues here. One is you guys are concerned about trespassing on the condominium property. So I can acknowledge that as a real issue.
But what is on the table tonight and what we are dealing with has to do with the geometry of the road and whether or not people can park safely in a parking lot.
It seems to be that for this stretch of the existing Harvard Street, that it would be unsafe to allow parking on this particular stretch. Now with that said, that's an entirely separate issue that may be related to people then being displaced to travel to your property. I haven't seen evidence of that. However, you are presenting some verbally tonight.
If there's an issue in the public way having to do with the geometry of the road and safety of parking, this commission should act on it. It's our obligation and under our purview.
The concern that you have with trespassing through your property is not. So they are two separate issues, although they are intertwined and I acknowledge that they may impact each other. So the idea of tabling it puts this particular commission at a certain risk because we are leaving a unsafe geometric condition out in the road for another month longer, which that is not palatable to me. I do not know about my fellow commissioners.
That can happen and we can vote to fix this issue while acknowledging your issue and providing advisement thereof. But I don't think we really have much choice in the matter when it comes to making action related to your concerns on this particular issue. Thank you.
Thank you, Tim. Thanks, Tim. That is what we understood it to be, but we wanted to make the entire commission and Larry Rogers and the entire police force aware of what will more than likely happen on our property and asking for support there. It's a real issue and we're concerned. Absolutely. No doubt about that. I hear that. And I think that offline,
If you want to contact me, I have some suggestions as far as no trespassing goes and things that you may be able to do within the purview of the law to better secure your site to prevent trespassing. So that could be something that we could discuss offline.
Great. Thank you. Appreciate that. And by the way, thank you for all the signs. We noticed the sign, no parking to the curb on Yale street, which prevents some of our neighbor's cars from being tapped and easy, easier to get out of the public parking lot and the crosswalk sign as well. Thank you. I just want to thank the commission as well for listening to the issue. I really appreciate it. Thanks. Thank you.
Commissioners, any other comments? Do I have a motion? I think Tim summed it up quite well. Motion to approve. Second? I'll second. Alva, roll call. Commissioner McGibbon? Yes. Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski?
Yes. Sergeant Rogers? Yes. Following the affirmative, one absent, the motion passes. Commissioners, that concludes new business. I'd like to go to 2022-53 of table business, a handicapped sign, Catherine Lima, 79 Dexter Street. It was tabled. Alva, is the paperwork in order?
Yes, at the last meeting, the registration was her old home. She was in the process of re-registering to the MedBit address. And the very next day I received all the paperwork completed from the registry through her. Everything is in order. She is present if she wants to speak. Commissioners, any comment? I'd love to hear from the petitioner if she's here. That's always helpful.
Hi, yes, I am here. So for the parking issue is, you know, the house next to us has a lot of roommate situations going on, the amount of parking on the street is very difficult. The driveway is used by my landlord who lives on the first floor.
And with the two trees there, it can be very difficult to get out. So I was asking for the sign to be where the slow children sign is presently. I've had both my hips replaced and need both my knees replaced. So wintertime especially can be challenging for me.
Right, so that I just, I think I want to repeat what you just said you just said that the there's a driveway there but the landlord who lives up upstairs or downstairs use it uses that so you have to use street parking. That's correct. Okay.
I don't have any other questions. And you have a handicap plate or tag. And just to make sure that you're aware that when we do do these, it is a generic handicap parking sign. If there are other people in the area with handicap tags, they have every right to park in that spot as well. Understood, yes.
still want any unpleasant surprises, you request it, and then it's always got somebody else in it, and that's legal if they have the appropriate tags. I understand. Anybody else? Motion to approve. Second. Second.
have a local commissioner given. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. For the affirmative one absent the motion passes. Okay, I just have one more. The resident parking.
We've been to two of the two resident parking for the GLX stations. Two of them are on the table, which one is the original one 2022 49.
That's the only one that's come in front of us that we haven't, the earlier version we passed. Oh, all right, okay. So that's the one that's, yes, I'm sorry. You are correct. This is the one that is remaining, yes. 2020 to 49. All right, commissioners, Todd is not here. He is, you know, the petitioner as well as the chairman. I would like to keep this table till the November meeting.
I would like to know if there's anybody in the audience that you may wanna hear. Do we have anybody? If there's any audience who wanted to speak on this, we had said that we would tabling this to this month, but several of the people we need to participate aren't here. We're happy to hear people. If there's somebody here who wants to speak on it, you can, as two gentlemen just have, if anybody else, you could raise your hand.
on the screen or put in the chat that you wanna speak. Okay, Bob Payne, you can speak. Oh, thank you. I live on Westbreed and the other person who raised their hand is across from me on the street. We have anticipated that Westbreed would be included in the permanent parking program and though we're way beyond half a mile from the farthest GLX station. And so we have gathered petitions and submitted those to
to Alva for consideration of a petition to defer having our suite included in the permanent parking program once it gets enacted. They want to opt out. I do have the petition. OK. That'll be no issue. Once it is approved or not approved, you can then opt out. OK. The paperwork has been submitted in anticipation of you
acting on that. We didn't know if it was going to be this month, and I guess it's not going to be until next month, but you have that in place when the time comes. Right. Yes. Thank you. That's all I need to say. Okay, thank you. Can you just confirm for us and for them that they've submitted everything they need to submit? It's all in order? Yes, Alicia. Yes, it's a quite well-prepared petition.
Great. I would just hate to have them show up and then find out later that there was something wrong with it. Everything is perfect. Okay. I think the Strassfeld family, I think we have nothing to say that Mr. Payne hasn't already said and can't say better. So thank you. Thank you. Is there anybody else? Uh, P Hanson is also got their hands up so you can speak on this as well.
Good evening. My husband and I are residents on Toro Avenue. And we spoke with the last meeting in favor of the permit parking. And in the interim, we spoke to several neighbors and they're also in favor of permit parking on our street. Okay, thank you. All right, thank you very much. Have a good night. You too as well. Lindsay G.
Hi, can you guys hear me? Yes. Hi, this is Lindsay from Goldilocks. Sorry, I don't have my camera on. I don't think I just found out about this. Yeah, I definitely, I just heard about this. I think I agree with the two folks that just spoke from West Street. And also, do we know when the November meeting is yet? Second Tuesday, I think it's November 11th. It'll be November 11th, so Friday. It's November 8th.
Thank you so much. I definitely want to attend that. Okay, thanks.
One of the things that had been raised in the previous meeting where we discussed this was the option for putting in business areas to our permit parking or resident parking. And that had come up specifically with regards to your business at the end of, sorry, you guys are on West Street, right, the end?
Yeah, our technical address is winter but we are on both. It did come up with regards to your business to include that two hour parking, even though we all know your business doesn't need it for two hours, that you have
employees that park down there if um it sounds like the the request from the west street residents to exempt west street from the program would cover that if that's uh what you guys also want if you guys would want something
different with the business? I mean, we wouldn't change the $15,000. Okay. I'm sorry, I didn't hear that. What was that last sentence?
Alva, I think we could half hear you. Oh, I'm sorry. I believe that we already have 15 minutes parking posted alongside Goldilocks on West Street. Yes. And that would stay if the exemption was approved. Okay, perfect. Okay.
Hi, this is the Frollis-Drossel family again. Lindsay, I just wanted to point out, I'm not sure if you were on for this part, but the West Street would be exempted on the basis of a petition that was circulated, but Winter Street would not be covered by that petition. So if that's an issue for you, I know you have patrons.
that that that may or if you have staff or patrons that need that access, that would not be covered. And obviously, as the commission can tell, West Street loves its Goldilocks. And we are we want to make sure that they're accommodated. So, Lindsay, just want to flag that for you. OK, we appreciate that. OK, thank you. I'll definitely I got to do some thinking. Thank you. OK, Joe Mizraka, if you'd like to speak. Hello, Joe.
Joe, are you there? Oh, his thing says connecting to audio now. Now there it is. Joe, just unmute it and then you can speak. Yeah, I'm going to, I just asked him, can we forcibly unmute him?
I asked him to unmute it, but that should work. Joe, if you could unmute, Joe Mizraka, if you can unmute your speaker then that... Joe? Yeah. So I've asked him to unmute it now three times. Joe Mizraka, if you want to unmute that, then you can speak, but we can't hear you.
All right. Do we have anybody else? That's the only person we have left. Did he leave the meeting? I believe he did. All right. Thank you commissioners. Um, obviously this is going to be a long process that we're going to be dealing with and that is all I have tonight. Do we have a motion to adjourn? Motion to adjourn.
Second. Second. Alva Rocco. Who made the motion? Tim. They sound alike on the thing. Commissioner McGibbon. Yes. Commissioner Hunt. Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski. Yes. Sergeant Rogers. Yes. Four to one. The meeting is adjourned at 5.54 PM.
Thank you and we'll see you in November.