11.05 on Tuesday. Good evening. Welcome to Community Media Medford. So, I'm just back from the City Council. I left there at 9.40 or so. Had to do a little shopping. It's now 11.05 p.m. Boy, our numbers on the blog have shot through the roof tonight. There's so much information out there that we are bringing together at MedfordInfoCentral.com. I'll give the address again later.
MedfordInfoCentral.com. But on the front page of the Boston Globe today, Medford, Massachusetts City Councilor George Scarpelli, the man who wants to be mayor. We heard on Good Authority two, three weeks ago that Scarpelli is running for mayor. I heard this morning from a very good source that Scarpelli is floating it out there, floating it out there on the day he's again on the front page of the Boston Globe. Now remember,
2015 on the Friday before election Tuesday, Scarpelli was front page news and it's not good. It's not good. So here's an individual with absolutely no thought of public service, no thought of anything but himself, willing to throw your child under the bus. This is what George Scarpelli is all about. You don't need a verdict on guilty or innocent here. You see, all those chaperones, when it happened, it happened on their watch.
So whatever they want to say, whatever defense they want to come up with, here's the bottom line. A rape happened on George Scarpelli's watch. Now, if he was any kind of human being, if he had any empathy for the students, for their parents, for their brothers and sisters, for their fellow classmates, this individual would have resigned if he had any integrity.
Now he's floating it out there that he's going to be running for mayor. They have no shame, no shame whatsoever. George Scarpelli failed to reach that high bar, that very high standard that comes with public service. Just because you had a cagoots like Paul Camuso, you want to hold yourself to that bar, Mr. Scarpelli? It's a joke. It's a twisted joke.
on the citizens of Medford. They charge so much for water. They charge so much local taxes. And then there's all sorts of things, excise tax, go on and on and on. So these people are just gorging themselves on the citizens of Medford and they do not provide public service. Where's the public access station? Why are you watching this on YouTube?
I have a little bit of experience in public access. I'll go a step further. A woman saw me tonight at Medford City Hall. She agrees I'm the most qualified person to run access television in Medford. But you see, the qualifications wanted by City Hall are if you will censor, if you will harass people, and if you vote for Stephanie Michini Burke. If you vote for anyone that is in McGlynn's corner, that
That is what your qualification has to be. Not talent, not veteran status, not years of experience. Experience is the best teacher. New technology comes out every day. We're always learning how to learn about the computer, how to speak properly into the computer with, I like my flowers behind me, but that's all, you know, it's all orchestrated. It's what I want you to see.
That's what the image is when you do television. I like it whether or not you do watch or don't watch. Listen to the content. Don't listen to the content. Mr. Scarpelli is on the front page of the Boston Globe. His name is on D5, but the story is front page news and none of it's good. Now,
If Mr. Scarpelli had moral integrity, he would have resigned June 6, 2017. Because you don't need a verdict on this. These chaperones did not take care of the children they were entrusted with. What were they doing? That's what I'd like to know. And I hope that comes out at trial. What were they doing? You mean to tell me they weren't watching freshmen?
You weren't reading them the riot act, putting the fear of God into them, saying, my political career is on the line. I'm going to be selfish right here, so I don't have to be selfish later. My political career is on the line. You people are here to engage in sports and recreation, and that's it. Any hazing won't be tolerated. You'll be prosecuted to the full extent of the law, but
It was a party. There were multiple hazing incidents according to the witnesses now, multiple. Now we're going to get all the paperwork on this. We're going to study it. Mr. Scarpelli has to resign just by virtue of him being negligent. Okay. He didn't do the right thing. None of them did.
But City Hall is a disaster. It is. This new mayor is like she's got City Hall's all falling apart and they're going about it all the wrong way. It's the doors, the doors of City Hall, valuable doors. They want to just get rid of them, just like they got rid of public access and didn't replace it. Look, without this personality, you would have still had
The same old, same old crony crew. The $600,000 that I saved the city of Medford. Kiss that goodbye. Now it's being spent on the Volk Tech School, which we'll address that down the road, maybe in a court of law. But here's tonight's observation. George Scarpelli should be ashamed of himself. I'll look him in the eye. I called him and he failed to return my phone call.
They pick and choose which citizens they want to talk to, and if it's a tough question, if it's the MSNBC of Medford, they don't want to know. They're not going to return your phone call. I called George Scott Pelley. He had his opportunity to speak. Shame on him. He didn't speak. He didn't speak to you. Because with no Medford Mercury in town, and Allison's new site is basically propaganda sheet for City Hall.
The transcript, even with a new editor, with Nell Coakley gone, the transcript is still as empty as ever. All you've got is my blog, medfordinfocentral.com. You can write me, informationcentral2 at gmail.com, informationcentral2, all one word, at gmail.com. You can read the blog, medfordinfocentral.com, medford, I-N-F-O,
Central.com. You can go to the Facebook page Real Medford Mass Politics. We're getting the word out. This is communitymediamedford.com. We're getting the word out. Mr. Scarpelli, resign. You should be ashamed of yourself. Ann Marie Cugno, pull out now. Pull out now. Rick Caraviello, he's a disgrace. He lost in criminal court January 31, 2017. How does that individual even show up at the city council? They have no shame.
They have absolutely no shame. They have no idea what public service is all about. These are not public servants. These people, these individuals are selfish. And that's why the city of Medford needs a lot of work. Needs a lot of... And it starts here. I'm a citizen. Just bringing information to you. We got lots of new information. Lots of new information. Community Media Medford. George Scarpelli, resign.