Welcome to the Affordable Housing Trust meeting, Wednesday, March 5th, 2025, six o'clock. We're gonna call the meeting to order. And it's a roll call. Ms. Taylor Lessingham? Here. Robert, Roberta, sorry, Roberta Cameron? Here. Carrie Weaver? There's somebody, what's the list? Penelope Taylor? Here.
Lisa Sun. She's joining us. Hi, Lisa. Can you hear us? Hi. Yes, I can hear you guys. Can you hear me? Yes. We are calling the meeting to order and taking roll call and we're at you. Lisa Sun. Here. Maya, Brianna, Lungo, and Lisa Davidson. That's me.
Okay, so we are going to start item number two, working group updates the trust action plan. The action plan working group will provide an update on the upcoming community meeting, which is scheduled for a week from today, March 12th. Roberta or Penny, do you want to?
That was just yeah, so we met last week and went over the presentation, which will largely be kind of the data presentation and then. Um, some conversation introduction to the, well, we're going to put together a great presentation suffice to say, so it introduces the trust covers some of the data we've been looking at increases what.
It's already out there and then have some provoking questions to get the conversation going. We heard that we had some good survey responses so far. So hopefully we'll hear how many we've had to date. 48 48 responses. Great. So keep sending those out. We also worked on kind of.
warm up that kind of gives us an info about who is participating in the room and online and then also kind of a mini survey for in-person day of just to get a quick sense of like who's in there with us and responding in live time and whose kind of commentary is going to be in that like focus group of sorts of that meeting. And yeah, we're really looking forward to it. So I don't know if you want to add anything. Yeah, I think
But I think that covers it, but it's going to be hybrid. So we'll be there in person and hopefully people will join us. Do we have more people registered? So 10 people have signed up to be present in person, but we don't have a number for virtual participants. It's just to know how many people are going to gather in the DPW building. So yeah.
So we have a plan for facilitating a hybrid discussion. Okay. Yeah, and my colleague Teresa is going to be present in person and myself and Teresa will facilitate the participation responses. We'll probably take turns, that's what we decided. So one in-person response followed by another one from a virtual participant.
Depending on how many yes, if necessary, we're going to do to break out groups hybrid breakout group and in person. Okay. And then bring it back in. Bring the information back. And then again, that's next Wednesday.
6 o'clock at DPW. So DPW is on James Street, which is down Main Street a little bit. 21st James Street. Yes. And then you have a nice meeting room there. So if you've never been there before, you'll go in the main door and
Hopefully that'll be unlocked for us. And then there'll be a hallway to the, like after you go in a few feet, then there's a hallway to the left and you turn left there and it's at the end of that hallway. That's great. And I just wanted to know, it's DLX exam this weekend, so make sure you set those clocks so you can make it to the meeting at the right time. And can you tell us a little about the interpretation services that will be there? Yes, so our community liaisons will be present
We'll have interpretation services in Spanish, Haitian, Creole, Brazilian, Portuguese, and Arabic. That's wonderful. Thank you.
And I hope that the liaisons will feel empowered to also participate in the conversation, especially because they may have insight about the needs of the people who they work with, even if none of those people come to the meeting.
Yes, that is true. I attended one of their evening meetings where they get to know what different departments in the city hall is doing. So I spoke about the affordable housing trust and the community meeting and they had great questions about affordable housing. So I'll probably send them an email saying that they could also participate. Yeah.
And I think we wanted to also talk about the timeline beyond the meetings. After this community meeting, then we're going to turn the action plan toward, so we'll draft a summary of everything that we learned from the stakeholders in the community meeting and
the data analysis that we did, and then bring that back to this group and start over the next few months going through what is going to be the substance of the action plan. So this group will look together at the mission statement, goals, priority actions, guidelines, and procedures.
that will guide what the group does going forward. So that's what we'll be using all of this input to help us develop those things. Does anybody have any questions?
In the community meeting, I'm assuming that you three would kind of be kind of head and field the majority of questions and comments through it. I just wanted to understand if there's any specific role that other members of the trust should prepare for before that meeting. That's a great question.
I'm sorry, I thought just one more time. I was going to say, I assume that the three of you were going to kind of lead the discussion and field the majority of the questions from the community. Was there any specific role that you wanted the other members of the trust to prepare for before coming to that meeting? Or just kind of show up, throw in a center to here and there and just let things kind of
unfold? Yeah, I think so. And, you know, it may be that we don't, we didn't think of questions that might come to you to ask as you hear the discussion. So I think, you know, there will be room for a back and forth conversation. And I think that rather members of the trust can feel free to contribute questions that would be helpful for you to hear about. I think
make sure you invite people and encourage them to take the survey before next Wednesday will be really important and then also yeah I think we should introduce all the trust members at the beginning and I know that in just chatting with neighbors about
interest in topics, I was like, oh, there's a trusted member that's really into that. This is you actually. So I was like, oh, you go to the community meeting, she might be there and you can talk to her about it. So just in terms of like making connections in the community too. But yeah, I think like inviting folks to participate, meeting and the survey and yeah.
being part of it, because... Yeah, it's exciting. Yeah. I'm really excited. We've done a lot. Roberta has done amazing work on the presentation of data collections. Thank you. Thank you.
just signed the contract this morning for the first $250,000. Yes. Yes, we did. Thank you. I know that probably is an extra agenda item. Yeah. It's exciting. It's exciting. Last month, I'm so excited. We've got things happening. Any other questions about the upcoming community meeting next week? Just in case I haven't said it, next week, March 12th,
6 o'clock at the DPW 21 Jane Street and Zoom, right? And Zoom, yes, it is a hybrid meeting. Great, thank you. 21 Jane Street, okay. And Rupula, do you mind sending the presentation? We'd like to have a clue also for the survey that Penny prepared so that participants who are virtually present can also sign up.
Yeah, right down the street. Cheap swearing and ceremony so I'm, I may not run late but that's probably.
All right, so we are going to item number three is funding application guidelines and framework. Kayla has created a draft, a developer application for the board's review and to provide comments. Thank you, Kayla. This looks great. So I did start and then I started like a summary and guidelines and then I realized I didn't know what I was doing. So I wanted to just keep it to the, you know, the information that I think we might launch
I'm a developer and try not to get into what our priorities are, what any specific programs are going to look like. So it's pretty general as much as I could. This is supposed to just kind of be like a one-page cover sheet. You get some basic information about the location and the big numbers. How much are they asking you to trust? How much is the total project cost?
Number of housing units and number of housing units that are below 80% AMI. Then I just gave them a really big page to just give a narrative summary. I think they'll probably answer a lot of the following questions in this, but just wanted to give them the space to give them the whole spiel. Then the next section, again, just trying to keep it broad and not
Eliminate possibilities, but also try to give us a sense of what everything is the type of projects. Purpose of funding requested again, try to keep it broad since we don't know exactly what we're talking about here. Sources of funds again, just try to. Think of all the possibilities that any of these might end up with.
So obviously the affordable housing trust fund, that would be what they're requesting from us. You know, another local match, construction loans, permanent loans, any other things that they can think of. Targeted population, you know, if they have any specific populations that they're looking to assist and house, any other services.
Type of full housing, so this is almost supposed to be like a two-sided column, but we didn't get that in this iteration. So either home ownership on the left or rental on the right, again, just a check the box situation. Unit composition, so I split it up by the different bedrooms.
and SRO, which is single room occupancy, and then try to break it out by the different AMI levels that we would be looking at. I did throw in 120 percent if we end up seeing any workforce or upper tier, up that tier of housing, they just want to know that it's there and it is restricted. That is something to note and then the number of market rate.
Also wanted to talk about accessible units by unit type. So maybe have them append something in the same kind of format using that. And then I think, do you think this is yours? Add the affordability restriction type and the affordability period proposed for all of these affordable units.
So that's really the bulk of the form. And then I just go into a huge list of everything else they have to provide us. I think most housing developers would be pretty familiar with this list. A lot of it's based on one stop and then a lot of it's gonna be just kind of narrative about that organization. Community outreach was one section that I tried to maybe
focus on a little bit, you know, talk about what our priorities are, when we do have priorities, talk about how the project meets Metro's housing needs as referenced in the housing production plan, and I linked it, talked about any tenant relocation plans, also the description of specific tenant outreach and meetings.
And same for community support. So I wanted to both talk about letters of support from community groups, letters of support from the neighborhood. And also just want to hear about any communication or meetings that they have, you know, really positive or negative, right? You want to hear that they're at least out there talking to people. And then how they incorporate that feedback from them. You know, if they have made changes to respond to them, I think that would be important for us to know.
And then the rest, again, kind of site control. If there's an existing building, just information about that building. And then try to just create a laundry list of anything, any kind of information that we think we might need or they would be gathering. I think depending on where level, you know, how far along they are, some of these they wouldn't have. But I think that that's just kind of a sense of how ready they are and where they are in the process as well.
That section's a lot. If anyone has any questions or additions in that area. Thank you for doing that. It's amazing. Thank you. Does anybody have any questions? A couple of things. First of all,
This application alone exemplifies why it's so important that we have the Affordable Housing Trust and not just relying on the CPC because we just haven't had the expertise to be able to ask the questions that we needed to ask of developers to help them design projects that would be successful along the way. So this is just already value-added that we have been sorely missing.
A couple of really minor points, questions I had was on the table, the first table of the sources of funds, be helpful to have a total row at the bottom. And on the table for unit composition, I wonder if it could be helpful to have an other column in case, you know, like there are other percentage points that they could hit in between.
Okay, 40% and 60% mean. Yeah, another fillable column. Yeah.
Which brings me to I had a couple questions as well on the cover sheet where we're asking for the number of units at 80% of AMI. If we're using CPA funds, we can go all the way up to 100% AMI. And if we ever get non-CPA money,
please correct me if I'm wrong. I have to go back and look at our declaration of trust, but usually non-CPA money, trust money can go up to 110% of AMI. I don't know if we did that. I think we stopped at 80. But I'll have to check again. Yeah. But at least CPA is able to go up to 100% of AMI. Okay. And I don't know if that works. And then
The only question I had with the unit composition is if we're doing equal to or less than 120% AMI, does that
Is that an assumption that we would fund something at 120% AMI? So I think that's a good clarification. I did not mean that to say that we would fund something in that level, but just wanted to get a sense of the total mix and not just loop it into market rate.
There are some funding sources that are linked, so I think 100 to 120%. Yes. We do have workforce units in Medford, and I monitor their rent increase approval, and they're at 120%. Yeah. Okay. Maybe then it would be helpful to have a sentence of explanation under the title unit composition to say this includes both affordable housing trust-supported units and units that are not supported by the authority funds interest. Yeah.
Okay. Well, actually, now that I look at it, it has the market rate on it, too, so I'm like, yeah, request some market rates. I'm sorry, but thank you. And then I had one more, tiny questions, really, for the city staff.
When we're talking about does this project meet the proposed housing needs of Medford, when looking at applications for developments, do they have to work with the consolidated plan? Do they have to meet within
The consolidated plan. Um, is it the comprehensive? Yes. Yes. Yes, they do have to. Yeah. So maybe that maybe that's what an additional question to ask is, is it this is in line with our company. They have to align with the company, but they don't have to like.
Yeah, they don't have to. There's been proposals that don't align with the comp plan, and then it would just go to normal process, to CD board or zoning board. Yes, zoning board, yes. Is that what you were referring to? I know. It does a development plan, 100%. Oh, no, no, no, no, no. That's just a guide. Yeah, just a guide. Okay, thank you.
So we can edit it just for B to say housing production plan and comprehensive plan rather than making it a separate question. Yeah. Okay. And maybe I'll reword it because I think meets kind of conveys this idea of like you have to conform to some of that. I think meets might be the word that I need to change.
Align, align, align. Yeah, yeah. And then like, when we're looking at applications, because we're excited about getting applications, you can go like, based on scores, like if somebody's aligned with a score or something that way. Yeah.
Lisa's son has her hand raised. Oh, I'm sorry. Hi, son, Lisa. Hi. I had just two minor questions as well. So back to the unit composition matrix. Is there a reason we're using those AMIs or like those are called out in columns? I feel like I typically see
60% AMI and not, I don't remember seeing 50 very commonly. So just wondering the reason behind the ones you chose and if it makes sense, yeah. Yeah, I think the 50 and the 60 is sometimes a tough one to pick. I thought of 50 and now I'm trying to remember why.
I'm not sure why I thought it was 50 versus 60. Was it the 20 percent? I think for a low-income tax credit, it has to be 20 percent at 50 percent or 40 percent at 60 percent. I think a lot of times people year towards the 50. I think also I use 50 sometimes because I believe that that's usually the AMI that local housing agencies use for mobile Section 8 vouchers.
generally what sometimes I use, but I think those are the only reasons why I did 50 versus 60. I am perfectly open to just saying 60 and below, which I think would encompass that same AMI level, no matter what. So we do 30, 60, and 80, if that makes more sense. Then maybe replace the 120 with a question mark, like make that one be the fillable.
The other, okay. Yeah, that makes sense. Should it go up by maybe 20% for each AMI? That's a good question too. So it'd be 60, 80, 100. I believe though the 30 is one that is usually designated. So I think that's why I think the 30 might be the right level on below. And I don't think there's a lot of 40% of AMI. No.
All right, so. I would say about 30, 60, 80, 100 and then maybe leave the 120 blank and say other and let them fill in what they want just so we don't get too big of a table here in the middle. Yeah. Lisa, did you? Yeah, no, I don't know one way or another. I just I just know that on a lot of
applications, I see 60. So just wanted to ask. And then the other question I had was for the targeted population, do we want to include veterans as a category? Yeah, so I think we could probably work on some of the language in this as well. I'm very happy to take
All comments on language and what other populations we should talk about. So right now just have family, which I think in general is just like untargeted. Senior slash elderly, homelessness, homeless at risk of homelessness, special needs, housing with support services, and other. So we said we talked about veterans, maybe special needs slash disabled. Okay.
Most applications I see usually says senior elder slash disabled. I kind of like the idea of keeping them separate as population groups though.
You know, for public housing, they're grouped together, but in other, like in private housing, they're often not grouped together.
And I also think like, it's just like, young disabilities is a group that I know is really hard to place in housing and find housing for. So I mean, like other distinctions within each of these that I think like, are, yeah, could be focuses. So I would propose keeping them separate. And then, just as I'm talking, I'll say I wonder if we want to align our percentages to what the like,
zoning incentive percentages are or if that is too complicated and starting that idea into the percentage conversation. I can't remember what that one is. Oh, that depends on the different zoning districts. Oh, it's a different district. Forget it. Forget that. I'll just work on keeping those two separate. Zoning, you know, tonight on 7th Street, things like that. Yeah.
What about maybe veterans? Yeah, I think we're going to include veterans as a separate organization. Does anybody object to taking out special needs and just put disabled? That's what I think. Yeah, no, that's great. Thank you. That's a good question.
Are studio apartments ever funded with these or not? Does that need to be a row studio unit?
You know, I think that a lot of the state funding kind of prefers at least a bedroom. I don't know if there's a lot of studio that aren't SROs, but we could at least leave the option open. And I think maybe also with our specific housing needs, it might be an area that we want to at least explore. Because they could be market.
Sure, they could be a studio. Okay, so why don't I do studio before one bed in between us our own? I'm seeing a lot of so single room occupancies for SROs. I'm not seeing a lot of SROs applications.
Yeah, I mostly just, I go to Caritas each year, so I think about Caritas. And they're perfect for some of the targeted populations that we care about. I think Malden had one recently. Did they? Yeah. Metro North Housing, they worked with that development, yeah.
This looks great, thank you. Does anybody have any questions, any other questions, comments? Before we move on to the next agenda, I just wanted to talk about this potential developer who has requested funding from the trust. In terms of the timeline, they are expecting soft commitments from the trust by this summer.
just to give you a heads up, if we can have the application and loan documents ready by the summer, that would be great. Like early summer? Probably late summer. Late, late summer, I think, because the one-stop application is in October. So they need to have a local soft commitment ready before they apply for one-stop.
October is the pre-application window for the one-stop application. Chair, what are the next steps with this document? I guess, do we need to approve it? Does it need to be run by anybody else? Just thinking of the timeline.
It's a pretty awesome document that obviously, you know, it's a little feedback. So I think it's in a great place personally. So whatever, what do we need to do to move that forward? So like that box is checked. Move approval as amended. Yeah. Yeah. And move that we approve this document as amended. Thank you. Okay. And then we will vote on the motion to approve the application as amended. Kayla? Yes.
Roberta? Yes. Carrie? Yes. Penelope? Yes. Lisa? Yes. Mayor? Yes. And Lisa? Yes. Motion approved. Motion approved. What's the likelihood, excuse me, what's the likelihood
of the city being able to have draft loan documents and everything. Just looking at the time frame, we're in March. Yes. This would be a commitment to the developer.
They wouldn't have to close on the... That's true. That's true. So it's just a funding commitment today, and then I think we can negotiate or see when you'd actually need the funds. They would actually need the funds. Yes, but I think we should have some guidelines ready so that they know what are our loan terms, and probably the board should discuss what the rate of interest would be for the loan terms, so if we want to have the loan. And through the chair, can you just refresh my memory what the developer's looking to do?
I didn't specifically talk who the developer is. I just said there is a potential developer who's interested to develop 100% affordable housing. It's a non-profit developer. 100% affordable housing. So we don't have any units or anything like that?
I would say, yes. I don't think we've asked anything yet. Yeah, because we just had an initial call and they wanted to know if... Can you tell us how much they're looking for? In terms of the funding, anything that the city can offer. Yeah. Yes, yeah.
So we could potentially for the next meeting, which would be in April by March, actually start putting it on the agenda to discuss a long term. Yes. Okay. Would we discuss how much we would.
loan per unit like how does that work yeah that's great questions and i think those are those are the things that we're someone heard we got money and they're like yeah we're talking about another development and it's probably a different one than that that's just started talking about yeah this money this week too so there might be multiple so i'm just like if we
I'm going to take 250 because it sounds great. Yeah, exactly. So there's a couple of things that are in it. We don't know what we're going to do for our unit funding. We haven't had that discussion yet because we're so in, like, starting at it, right? We don't know what they're asking for. I think
These are great questions that we can start talking about and that's in April, maybe May meeting. But I think I heard that the CPC would welcome us back
if we needed more money. I'm not gonna put anybody on the hook, but I feel like that is what I heard when we were A, presenting, when we were here presenting for the ask, what I heard a lot from the members, and this is going back several months, like 250,000 is not a lot of money.
I don't know if they still have money available, but that is a potential that we could go back. I think we have to go back with the need to show that we have applications coming in.
I'm just throwing it out there, putting that spaghetti to the wall. So that's enough there. I think I've seen per unit right now, cost per unit, is it anywhere from $650,000 to $750,000.
a unit for subsidies. So that's a lot of money, right? So what I'm hearing is a couple of things. We're doing an awesome job telling people that we're here and we want to help with the development. So yay.
So I'm thinking about given what we need to know, it would be really helpful for us to spell out a timeline. And so perhaps the things that I described that this group needs to agree on, we might be able to do over the three months of April, May, June, and then maybe aim for another public meeting in July. And then we could
Um, present our final report to City Council in August. I don't know if City Council is meeting in August, if they'd be willing to hear us then, or we might have to wait until September, but at that point, we will have already needed to finalize our plan, so that would be a courtesy presentation. Um, then that means that August, like,
We could give them the application so they could start working on it, but as of August, like we can officially say these are guidelines and then be able to make to approve something in August or September. That would.
you mean that when they send in the application, we actually should talk about like how soon we want materials to review before a trust meeting, like a developer coming in, they should be getting the, within a timeframe to the staff, staff's reviewing it, asks the various questions and then get it to the trustees, so the trustees have time to review it.
a conversation so we'll have to look at that the time frame as well. That's assuming that they come in with a complete application and we have no questions and then we could vote. Would they be looking for us to vote on that night? That means I've seen trusts that will vote
on the application that night, and then I had also seen them defer it to the following, but if they need a conditional commitment letter for their one-stop application in October, they're going to need it in September. Yeah.
have a fair ground so that all developers can come in here. I just
So we're going to meet in October. Our September meeting will be the third. But we could have a special meeting in between if we have to make a decision for them. Yeah. Since we're talking about our schedule, I'm just, this is on our agenda, but I'll just show it here if it's easier. Yeah, something out of order.
So we're actually not scheduled to meet in July. If you want to change this. Yes, please don't. Yes, we can save. All right. What such need to happen. What in addition to this document would be need to prepare to post.
For folks to respond, I mean, I think that's part of the decisions that hopefully we can make next meeting or in addition to kind of. Numbers and just parameters in general, but also, I guess, like.
Do we have a window or rolling admissions and kind of what the admissions materials and timeline need to look like? I feel like that's a whole other realm of things we need to decide. And I think great questions. And I think some of those questions would be answered in our action plan that we're working on, right?
right now, I've seen trusts that they have been around a little bit longer, they're a little bit more flushed, and they start talking about how much of their funding are they going to put towards development versus other rental assistance programs or whatnot, right now we're just doing development. I don't know if we're going to put that in our action plan,
thinking about it. Right now we're just on the path for development. I think this would be answered in an action plan unless I'm wrong. I think
So I'm just going back to the things that we need to talk about for the action plan. Mission statement, goals, priority actions. Those are all things that I feel very comfortable with developing and usually they come first, but they could, we could kind of do it in reverse order so that we answer some of these critical questions. The next thing that we need is
Guidelines and procedures and that's what we're talking about now is program guidelines and procedures. So, those in particular, given the expertise that all of you have with. You know, positive developers, it could be helpful if someone else were to take the lead on drafting some guidelines and procedures.
And so that we would have this for discussion over those three months, April, May, June, and in whatever order we discuss them, we could be able to answer some of these questions that we're raising right now.
Yeah, I think I think that makes sense. And I'm happy to take another crack guidelines and procedures. Um, the only other thought I had is that some of the other types of assistance are kind of maybe more flexible, you know, rental assistance or ownership, like there's a lot of other questions, rental, you know,
It's boring, but you know, like there's a process laid out that's mostly driven by the state. So I could probably also like just, you know, specify that this is kind of like a rental development procedure, and this is our timeline. And then we could still leave some flexibility for other endeavors and have more flexibility in those areas. We wanted to try to not put everyone in the same box, I guess is what I'm saying.
Yeah, and also to Lisa's suggestion that we might want to consider a portion for development versus stabilization programs. The CPC has been funding stabilization programs through direct applications to the CPA program over the last four years or so.
So it could be possible to coordinate with the CPC to take on that role and maybe see what the funding level and appropriate funding level is. And so that those funds would go to the trust in addition to say the 250 that we got this year for the trust to be the gateway to that money.
So we could focus just drafting guidelines and procedures just right now on development applications. And then if we decide that we're able to grow and do stabilization, housing stabilization pieces, then we can focus on that.
I think I think that might be a way to do it. Because I also I think, like I said, I did start trying to draft something and I found myself getting bogged down. But what are our overall priorities and what are our percentages and how am I going to score any application? You know, the bigger picture. So I think if we're if I'm able to narrow like a procedure of guidelines for a certain subset, what we hope to see
yeah, I think that'll be easier than to try and answer the action plan questions. That's what I ended up trying to do. I can't answer these action plan questions. We haven't done the action plan yet. Okay, now I can take practice.
And then at the end of the calendar, you leave it as is, but if we, you've seen that the developer needs it by, say, by September 20th, and we just need a 48-hour notice to have a special meeting, then we can even do it by Zoom for just that one vote. So we can schedule a 6 to 6.30 meeting on a Wednesday, just as long as we post by Monday at 6.00. We can just do that by Zoom. I think my only two cents about it is that I'm sure that the developers
doing the pre-meeting with ELHLC, which is usually over the summer, and then they usually like to hear that they have, and maybe he could just say we have discussions or we're in the process or something, but. Hopefully we've been given a vote on it on the 3rd, it's pretty, but if we ever need any more time, we need to do a vote on the 1st, we can always add a special meeting. Okay.
and I could give them a timeline as to when. Yeah, as long as we plan to. We can do the special meeting in July or August, where we're all just, even if you're on vacation, you can hop on for 20 minutes and just take a look. And we could maybe, just thinking, if they're going to present, they would have to maybe try to present in the June meeting.
All right.
public meeting, open meeting law, I feel like we're getting off on the topic of what might have been on the agenda. Are we going to, is that okay that we've kind of gone off the agenda topics? We're still talking about funding application. It's just that we have... Yeah, we have an agenda for this, but it's fine. Yeah. Perfect. All right.
I think you answered my question and it was also 2 questions at once. So, in terms of, like. If you want them at the June meeting, then at some point, we have to post.
The application. Yes. And when we post the application, what's that look like timing wise? And does anything else need to get posted with it that we need to make and decide on before then? I guess it's just like, that seems like it needs to happen sooner than later. But we're just putting it out there. When do we need to decide that? And is there anything else we need to decide around it? I mean, it depends on what they're doing in June.
if they're coming in to introduce themselves and introduce their development and not asking for money, just saying, this is who we are, this is where our plan is, we wanna lay the landscape, and then the application comes in. I mean, I've seen developers do that, introduce themselves, come in, and they're just sort of,
setting the table for a potential application. Let me rephrase, I guess. How does the developer get a copy of that application? Is it posted on our website or is it something they ask us and we send it to them? That is my technical question. It will be posted on the website, yes. But that is whenever the board decides that it should be.
Yeah, I think the fruit is amended. I think there might we might want to have some guidelines and procedures from us just laid out before we post this application. Yeah, you know, maybe like a super minimal. This is like your steps and then and then we could post it with us. And do we have to do an RFP? I mean, it's so.
Well, people don't know that we have money. It depends on how we decide to do it. Are we going to take applications on a rolling basis and do a first-come, first-served? Yeah. Or are we going to do an RFP? It sounds like there might be another developer out there who might be a change, so we need to know what we have in front of us.
We could issue a notice. Those are valid questions. We could issue a notice of funding availability, NOFA, and then as part of NOFA, we can have the application guidelines and the application form. So then everybody knows that we have the funding. So we need to do all of that by June so we can do the NOFA and have the application.
I have a couple of suggestions. I think this is all definitely part of what was on the agenda to discuss. So back to our process for the action plan. Maybe we can say April we can discuss the mission statement goals and priority actions. And that way you will feel like you have the information that you need in May
To have the guidelines and procedures for us to discuss and then June.
We can have the whole draft together to look at as a group. And then that draft could be posted for public view. And then in later June or early July, and I think we should put a date on the calendar now, have the public meeting to review the draft. So let's commit to actually having the draft ready to release in June.
So we could have, we could make the applications, put out a NOFA, make the application available and say preliminary applications process based on the action plan, which is in progress. And like have some qualifications saying that final terms and guidelines will be determined or are to be determined.
And so we can create in that a timeline saying that the CPC can make a decision as early as August. So we can make a decision in like as early as the earliest August. And then working backward from there, when do they need to submit the materials in order for us to make a decision in August?
Well, it goes back to whether or not they're going to have a July meeting. Well, they could submit the materials to us, and those could be distributed by our staff person without us having a meeting. Let me break it. Hold on. Don't cut. Everything's not going to be ready until June.
The NOFA, the prelim application, the final thing will go out in June. The NOFA can go out anytime.
But it'll say it's preliminary based on the plan that will be completed in June. So that lets them start preparing, but with an understanding that there's still some question marks that are going to be filled in. And they will know the date of when the draft will be released. And then,
Would the board, sorry, just because I said, would the board require to vote for the NOFA to be publicly available? Or was the vote that we just had is good enough for us to issue a NOFA? Notice of funding availability?
So we can push out the, we can. All right, so let me again, I'm sorry I'm slow on the uptake. I've been going all day like everybody else. All right, so if we do the NOFA.
And we're in March right now, let's just say the NOFA goes out because it's a prelim saying that this is it, we've got money, we're gonna start looking at it. What I'm hearing, I think I'm hearing, is we can do that anytime we want. Put that out, like we could do it sometime in March. So the NOFA goes out in March.
I don't know if it goes out in March. And then our action plan is completed by the end of June. The draft is completed end of June. Draft, sorry.
So I cannot come up with a schedule that allows us to have no summer meetings. Yeah, we can't skip them. Next year we can skip them, but this year we kind of have to. That's what I was getting confused with, because I don't think that we could have somebody come in and do a presentation
And I would prefer to do a presentation in person. That's just my preference. We could do a hybrid if necessary. Okay, so then they can present in June and then we can vote if it doesn't happen in June and happen at a special meeting.
Okay, thank you. I'm sorry to take so much time. I just had to walk through it. Just a suggestion. I think the board should have a look at the NOFA document before it's issued. So it would be hard for it to go out in March because the next board meeting is April. That's when you probably have to
approve it. So we can be posted. So we have to have the agenda in April already and we're not done with this meeting. So I just want to review like the local timeline is going to be. Goals and NOFA we're going to discuss in April. Guidelines and procedures we discuss in May.
We look at the draft plan and maybe we have a second, oh, somebody can come and give us a presentation in June. So a draft plan, we discuss, say, yep, this looks good, and we have a presentation from a developer in June. And then that draft plan gets posted on the city's website. And in July, we're going to have another community meeting.
And then in August, we're going to have a meeting where we approve any final changes and make the plan final. So final plan is released in August, and in August, we're going to make a decision. So they're going to be submitting their materials based on our draft plan, but hopefully it'll be close enough to what's going to be final.
And that's why it's called preliminary. Next year, we'll be able to have more definitive guidelines. Yeah, I think so. If we were to put actual dates to those things, that might work out for these. Does she have for May again? May is going to be discussing guidelines and procedures.
and NOFA. April is the mission goals priority actions and the NOFA.
So Kayla, just to clarify, I'm assuming NOFA will be part of the Midland Network. I can send you some examples if you, yeah. Thank you. Thank you. Did you sign up from one of these sites? Have you done the guidelines before? But there's so much good stuff online. Yeah. Yeah.
I have program guidelines from stabilization programs that I've helped to set up, and program guidelines for affordable housing trusts to guide development projects, but maybe not really applicable to Welfare.
I'll look to see what we have, what Somerville has for guidelines and reviewing applications, and I'll send them through.
Okay. Okay, so item number four.
funding and development on affordable housing. The city council has invited the board of trustees to the committee of the whole meeting to discuss the request to transfer and convey the reformed parcels to fund affordable housing. In advance of the meeting, the board would like to discuss the understanding and context of the conveyance of the parcels and review the other options that could provide funding for the next study.
This is back in 2018 and 2019, there was an interested party on one of the McCormick Ave lots. So since that time and after I became mayor, worked with Alicia Hunt and Danielle Evans helped as well figure out what parcels we have in the city that
either could build affordable housing on or potentially sell to then be able to put money into the affordable housing projects. And this parcel, I thought, since there is an interested buyer in at least one of the lots, we wanted to make it a buildable lot. So we're taking both lots and have it before the council to set up terms to sell both lots.
and the values in the 700,000 range for the two, and we're gonna set minimums as my hope. I'm spending a good amount of money into the Affordable Housing Trust, and that's, I know some of you have lots, maybe a potential for an affordable housing builder, but this is a way to get money in our account and linkage access to try to create an affordable housing section in our linkage intake.
Yeah. So we haven't scheduled it yet because the board would want to discuss it before we go.
Can I understand? So they want to meet ahead of time with us and then have us at the committee of the whole. Is that the understanding? No. No. We want to meet, discuss, and then propose a time when the board is prepared to go before the committee of the whole. Yeah. Okay.
It's not clear, but they said the board of trustees here. I think, because initially this is like a special meeting to talk about this right and then like the way the schedule works out it's on our regular schedule, but hard.
To me, an unanswered question was like, if there's a strategy and in meeting with them, because of concerns that were raised about, I think, like. Is it the wording of the transfer or something that came up in the meeting that. We wanted to make sure we were all on the same page going into a meeting just to either ask what needs clarifying or like.
And then he handed the request is for other options. So, yeah, we could send them a statement and see if that would suffice. So we get some of the vote that you agree with this proposal and you'd like them to set.
I'm not, we don't usually sell property, although the prior mayors have done it in the past. So you all may be more educated on what we would put in a vote to approve or ask them to do this so that we can add some money to the Affordable Housing Trust to do the linkage nexus study, and then some. I mean, the study's 80,000. If we could put a half million in from this sale into our trust, I mean, it's a whole lot of,
No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no,
totaling up to $720,000 each. Daniel and I met with the chief assessor this morning to understand how these city-owned parcels are assessed. Just to give you some background about it, there's a cost curve factor. You may already be familiar with that. The rate of the value of the land diminishes as the land area increases.
And they also consider some sort of condition factors like accessibility and whether it's developable or not, and any other environmental factors that could impact the value of the land. And there's also a certain threshold, a threshold of 8,000 square feet beyond which the rate of the value of the land is lower than
The area of land up to 8,000. So, if that makes sense, so there's a certain rate for land area up to 8,000 and beyond 8,000, it's a lower rate. Yeah. In addition to the cost curve. So, um.
We digged a little deeper and then we were wondering why McCormick Avenue parcels are valued at this because these individual lot themselves are not developable. But in the SSS office data, it's considered as developable. That is probably a mistake because the land area of each of this parcel is 3,600 square feet and it's an undersized lot.
And then we just did some trial and error to see if these two lots were merged, then it would be developable like Mayor mentioned. Then approximately this land would be valued at $435,000 and not $720,000.
And I think the suggestion is to have this land appraised to see the actual value of the land before we convey the parcels because
how the land has been assessed so far is different because they are individual parcels and not merged. And once you merge, probably the land value is going to change. And we don't know what that is. And the chief assessor is of the opinion that they don't do the appraisal of the land because then it's a conflict of interest. So it's usually a third party that would come in and assess the land.
So I'm not sure if that is something that we'd want to do and see what this land is valued at.
So we have two parcels of land. Yes. Each parcel of land is $300, $250, $300. And then if we merge them, did I hear you say that they could possibly go down to $400,000? $435,000 as per the SSS office. Right. Yeah.
That's because of the cost curve factor, so they become larger lots, and then the value per square footage is... But also, I think the $700,000 number is probably incorrect because of the incorrect coding. Because it's considered as developable. Right. So right now, they're not really worth $700,000, but right now, they're carrying them at $700,000 in the assessor's logs. Because I think the abutting lots are valued at...
35,000 or something like that. Yeah. And we have a potential buyer for the 700. We have a buyer for one of the lots, so I'm assuming that person owns an adjacent lot. We were trying to be fair and get
do a full bid process and not just sell to one person. So PBS recommended we sell them both, which I'm fine with. I want it to be a fair process. I just feel like we have somebody interested, we need money in our political housing trust to build on other lots and give money to other developers. So I've been following the process to do it fairly and transparently.
I mean, maybe if I just make sure I understand it right. So it seems like someone's interested in one. But if someone were to get one, the other one's too small to do anything with. So to move forward at all and get a profit, it's that lower number is what sort of seems like.
The expectation, right? To move forward, it's better for the city to sell both the parcels. Then we would just be left with one undeveloped lot. Do we think the interested party would bite at a combined two lots? We don't know. We don't know, but no matter what, one of those two lots is adjacent to the land that they own, so I think it's a possibility.
Yes. Just a question. I remember reading in the housing production plan a recommendation to have zoning that would maybe allow affordable development on these undersized lots.
Yes, this is the conversation that we have been having, but I'm not sure as part of the zoning overhaul if they have really included that as part of the zoning ordinance yet. And I think it's an ongoing process, but hopefully we'll have that.
There are a few other options also just so that the board is aware if that's something that you'd like to explore. There's undevelopable parcel on 0 Tresor Ave. Tresor Ave is a paper waste street, so it's considered undevelopable parcel and the abutting property owner is interested to
by this adjacent property and it's currently valued at $31,200. And then there's also the Zero Riverside Ave and this is a landlocked property.
A developer is interested to build housing. If we were to convey this to that developer, they would just merge this whole land and build around 30 affordable housing units. I think initially they had
agreed to provide 25% of the housing development as affordable, and then they would come in as a friendly 40B because now the zoning doesn't allow for development of that scale. But if we were to convey the parcel at market rate, then maybe, I don't know if we can still enforce the affordability restrictions when we convey, but maybe we could still say that you are required to build housing.
in that property, so that's another option. And then we have the Bailey Street lots. I think there are two city-owned parcels that are valued at $33,000 each, but again, if we merge those like similar to McCormick parcels, then probably the value would change, and we didn't check with the SSS office how much that would be valued at.
Would you be able to develop a list and a description of all of these units that we can include in the in the action plan? Sure. Yeah. Okay.
What was the initial question? So the city council wants one of us or all of us to come. I think a representative would be fine. So what are they looking for? Are they looking for us to say, no, we don't want the money. We don't want the $700,000 from McCormick. We want to take $30,000. If you're interested, I think we'd send a motion.
potentially draft a resolution, a motion that were somewhat in approval and maybe invite them to our next meeting to discuss it with us. I mean, they can be on Zoom, you know, any of them that want to come can be on Zoom. Yeah. Great. And this, we're specifically talking about the McCormick or I think like
Why not all kind of question emerges in my mind? Like, can we address all of these? And then I guess, I'm afraid I've omitted our guiding principles. It's the time. So since I initially asked the question to PDS, it's been six years. So I, my office, has moved from a clinic.
and I'm looking on ways to fund it. And it's an initial, let's do the first one. Is there going to be an uproar of the neighborhood or an uproar of the city? How do you sell property? I just don't know the landscape yet. So I wanted to do one at a time. But that's what PBS was doing. They were looking at everything and it just never, you know, with so much going on, we just never moved forward. So I've done this.
So it's gone through the legal steps with Coleman and Page. They've done all the work with the assessing and taken off. So it's been, well, six to nine months to get to the point where we need to go to the city council. So I think the next are probably gonna come in line, even if I have to do that on my own. I guess it's too busy and we need to decide which one comes next. Okay, great. Thank you.
I think it would be really helpful for us to have some more concrete understanding of the scenarios. So one scenario is that someone buys one of these parcels and the other parcel is then just not marketable unless we have zoning that allows for it to be
for housing to be developed there. And if we're going to have housing that allows for affordable housing to be developed there, have we then given up the opportunity for an affordable housing site by selling something for less than it should be valued? So, and how, you know, how much is it going to be worth
to sell them both together or just the one parcel given what the appraisal will come in at. So it sounds like it's not going to be $700,000. Maybe both of them together might be $400,000, one alone. What is it actually going to be worth?
The proposal is not to sell one. That's not a possibility. The way it's before the council now. We figured out it was probably the fairest, cleanest way to do it. If it was sold, do we get to say that it has to have affordable housing on it or can they build anything they want on the wall?
Um, anything they want, but the money would go. I propose it, the money would go to the affordable housing trust and then you be so we can build affordable housing with the money, you may not get it in this in on this site, but we may be able to get it with a developer.
Yeah, it's got three developing. Yeah, yeah. And does the zoning that's under discussion right now affect the potential value of this parcel? It's going to be the proposed zoning is NR1 and it's still going to be single unit dwelling with an ADU. Yeah. This site is not
the most ideal buildable location without serious or mean tolls. It's just a lot of ledge. Okay. Thank you. Yeah, no problem. So it's on the agenda. Do we need a... We discussed it. What is the possible... Do you have the letter or the...
document that we discussed last time? Yes. I'll have to disconnect this. I'm trying to find a layer.
There's two ways to do it. Put it out to bid.
Create the term, put it out to bid, and then before you've sold, we could go to the council for approval. Or I chose the more transparent route, get them to approve even going out to bid. Yeah. Before they would then need to approve the sale.
So that's, this is the first step. We are at the fully beginning step, yes. Okay. Which I didn't have to, we didn't have to take, but we chose to just, because I wanted to know, as a neighborhood, on and on a public agenda, open public communication, in case there was any issues by any chance someone could always pull back. Yeah.
I'm sorry, let me know once you.
The second page.
As I remember it, there was kind of a honing in on the may be used versus will be used and the exact intention of the use, but I might be misremembering that attention. So I guess. Yes, strategically, what is like, an understanding that like.
This is what we understand is going to be used for and we support this use and this proposal, I guess. I mean, what do we think? I would do a motion to approve the disposition of this parcel land if the money proceeds are going to go into the Affordable Housing Trust, which will then be by vote of the board.
to be used for things like the linkage review. I had a motion. Yeah, second. And then also we can write to the council that, you know, we've discussed it, we've reviewed it. We're happy to invite them to an upcoming meeting if they want to discuss it more with us.
Is that before the committee of the whole meeting that we invite them? I think they invited them. Yeah, I can talk to the president too and just say, what's the premise of having us there? You know, we voted to approve it. Do we need a meeting or did you want to come talk to us about terms of sale? I can talk to him on the phone and get him and the vice president on the side and see what they're looking for as far as meeting.
Also, a question on why we would need to motion to approve the sale. Motion to support it. I think we want it on this proposal. Yeah, sorry, that makes sense. Motion to support the sale. Sorry. To support the approval by the City Council of the sale, transfer, and authorize the sale of McCormick Ave.
for the purposes of funding the housing trust fund that may develop housing and fund an access study. We all want an access study, as does the council. The council alone is leading the charge on that.
I can jump into it. Great. Share the site. I haven't seen it in a while. Yeah, that's what I was going to say. Oh, okay. Yeah. I think that, I'm hoping it will, in a second, it's obviously happening. Did you guys get the motion? It was, okay. So we got a motion, we got, Penny is a second, a second motion, was that correct, Penny? Correct. Okay. We'll do a roll call. Kayla? Aye.
Roberta? Aye. Carrie? Oh, Carrie Leno. Penelope? Aye. Lisa? Yes. Madam Mayor? Yes. And Lisa? Yes. I don't know if you will be emailing this to the Council?
I can email it to the council, but since I sent an email to President Baer saying that the board would discuss first before we schedule a committee of the whole meeting, so I'm not sure if... Lizzie, let me in and then I'll just say, hey, can we talk on the phone for five minutes? We just want to get a better idea of what you want from the board.
Yeah I know whichever way you want because I know the chair and vice-chair were cc'd on that email as well yeah so whichever yeah no when I requested yeah yeah I requested president best to give us give the board some time to discuss about this before we schedule a meeting at the committee of the whole so
And if they want somebody at the board, at the committee of the whole, I'm happy to attend as part of, you know, as Justin said. Yeah, if they don't want the whole board to come, and then we'd have to schedule it as a joint meeting, or do you just want a representative or two? We took a vote, we took this motion, so I'll talk to them. So see me when you send them, like, this is what the
board of housing trust voted for, CC and the mayor, you and her can just discuss, you know, whether it's a joint meeting or a representation at your committee level, you know. Okay. Just to say this, I know this is going to be, seems like more meetings for us in general, nevermind, so yeah. Appreciate that.
Okay, so the next item on the agenda was trust meeting schedule, but we took that out of order. So, yes, we need an approval. Yeah, just a question from the chairs. Are you thinking about and then the July 2nd, just so we can all be able to have our calendars.
One second. That's a problem with the summer then you could wait when I can do the second I just can't do the ninth. I can do this. So, unless you do one meeting in the summer and it's the 16th or 23rd type.
But what I would suggest is maybe it doesn't have to be on the 2nd, but sometime in July, we have a public meeting and that will be the July meeting. Okay, so if we could pick a date for a public meeting in July. 16, I heard the 16th that works. Okay. Yeah, that works for me. And I think that the action plan group will start planning that meeting pretty soon and maybe conjunction with our awesome staff.
And there's an amendment to the meeting in April. Last time when I presented it, I said April 9th will be the next meeting, but it's on April 2nd. But you've got an updated invite for April 2nd. Motion for approval as amended of the meeting schedule.
Anybody second it? Second. Roll call. Kayla? Yes. Roberta? Yes. Mary's von Penny? Yes. Lisa? Yes. Madam Mayor? Yes. Lisa? Yes. That's six. Elaine is two percent. Six, one absent. All approved. Yeah.
I think we have set everything up. Motion to adjourn.
Thank you so much, and it's been a great pleasure working with all of you, and especially the city and the Affordable Housing Trust. I've learned so much along the way, and thank you for your guidance and patience as you worked with me for the past couple of months.
That's such a strong foundation and so much of it is through your efforts. Thank you so much. Thank you. Thank you. You're welcome. Very much missed. Yes. I will miss all of you. But it's exciting going with them. Virginia? Yes. Yes. I wasn't going to say, I didn't know if you were still in a public meeting. I stopped myself. Thank you so much.
All right, motion to adjourn. You go. Seconded. Seconded. All right, Kayla. Aye. Roberta. Yes. Carrie's gone. Penelope. Yes. Lisa. Thumbs up, Lisa. Motioning to adjourn. Madam Mayor. Yes. Yes. Yes.
Sorry, if you called my name, the audio cut off. I wasn't sure if you said my name already, but yes, I did. Thank you. So we are adjourned. Thank you very much. See you guys all in April.