22-508, 22-538, and 22-577. Committee, the whole Wednesday, November 9th, 2022 at 6 p.m. is called to order. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Vice President Behrs. Councilor Kerrio. Present. Councilor Collins. Present. Councilor Knight. I do not see Councilor Knight. Councilor Scarpelli. Present. Councilor Scarpelli. Councilor Sang. Present. President Morrell.
President, six present, one absent, the meeting is called to order. There will be a meeting of the Medford City Council Committee of the Whole on Wednesday, November 9th, 2022 at 6 p.m. in the Medford City Council Chamber on the second floor of Medford City Hall and via Zoom. The purpose of this meeting is to discuss papers 22-508 and 22-538, special permit and class two auto licenses, request by Lyft slash FlexDrive, and paper 22-557, a secondhand articles license request by ProRepair.
The city council has invited attorney Jeffrey Blake from KP law, Cameron Javito from her repair and representatives from list slash flex drive to attend this meeting. For further information, aids and accommodations, contact the city clerk at 781-393-2425, sincerely yours, Nicole Morrell, council president. So as this meeting notice notes, both of these papers were sent to Committee of the Whole, just to allow us more time for questions,
both with the representatives from these companies, as well as the counsel we've been provided from KP Law, Attorney Jeff Blake. I think we will take, as it's a shorter paper, we just have one person, we'll take the pro repair paper first, 22-557, with Cameron Javador from Pro Repair. And I'm happy if councilors wanna open up for questions or if we wanna hear from Cameron once again to remind us of the permit.
For the, as a CCK. Yeah, sure. Yeah, we can take questions, but yeah.
Thank you, Madam President. We talked about this last week, and I think some of the people may be confused on what the gentleman's doing. And I would, because you say you're a junk dealer, junk collectors, and I think people are having a fear that
The gentleman's going to open a store and it's going to turn into a tool shop like on Riverside Avenue. And I don't want to see that in the square. I feel the same. I would have no problem supporting this as long as the gentleman would sign an affidavit and say his business was repairing phones and repairing and selling phones only. And I would have no, if he agreed to that, I would have no problem supporting that and making the motion.
Would you have any interest in that? Yeah, my business is about only like phone repairs and phone sales. Actually, I didn't know that secondhand article license also contains different items like TV, selling TV, bikes and others. I didn't know that. But yeah, yesterday from the City Hall, small business development, Victor Schrader just came to my office and visited me. And he also aware of what I'm doing and what my business is about. So definitely it's going to be on the phone repairs and phone sales.
and you'd be fixing computers like this. If you want to state that in writing, I have no problem supporting it, and that would take away everyone's fear.
of a pawn shop, some jewelry and tools and all that. So I say, I'd make that motion if the gentleman agrees to submitting something legally to the council that his businesses phone repairs, phone sales, you know, in tablet repairs, et cetera type repairs. Thank you, Councilor Kerrio. Councilor Scarpelli.
I thank you, Madam President. I know I tabled this paper because of that issue, so I know that the petitioner is, it's an understanding now, and I concur with Councilor Carviello. I think this is a simple fix.
that the petitioner would put that in writing just to make sure that it eases the minds of the constituents that had the fear of what else could be moved into that. As long as we're, again, as long as we're legally, as long as we can legally do that and ask for that, I would move to support that. So, thank you. Thank you, Councilor Scarpelli. Any other questions from the committee?
Council, since we do have Attorney Blake on the line, do you have insight on if that's something, the process, just a process as far as just getting in writing the exclusive use of this space, how we should go about that? Thank you, Madam President. Jeffrey Blake here from KP Law for you guys. In my opinion, the authority to issue a permit, it also comes with the authority to condition that permit. And I think that you could get an affidavit or something in writing from the gentleman
But I also think that you could condition the permit. The permit is valid only for the use as in whatever language you'd like to put in there. That way, rather than having an affidavit from the owner, it's a condition of the permit. A violation of that condition of the permit could result in suspension revocation or suspension of revocation. Thank you, Attorney Blake.
So Madam President, if I can, I would make the motion that we would put those stipulations in writing that it would be used for a
cell phone repair, selling cell phones, I believe it's used cell phones, and computer products, I think. Would that suffice for the petitioner, if that was what we put in for the stipulations? Yes. I'll second that motion. Then I would make that as the motion, thank you.
cell phones, cell phones, cell phones, tablets and computers. Smart devices, no TVs, no, no. And they're like second use only for some cell phones, cell phones, tablets, tablets, computers, laptops, and sales of cell phones. Great. I'll second that motion, Madam President. Any further discussion from the council?
I would just use the word phones instead of cell phones. Just given that the terminology is changing. Fair enough. Is that acceptable to Councilor Scarpelli? Councilor Scarpelli, is this phones fine? That'd be fine. Thank you. Could you read that back to me when you have it? Absolutely.
Councilor Scarpelli moved to put the stipulations in writing that the shop would be used for repair of phones, tablets and computers and sales of phones. And there's a second from Councilor Kerrio. And I would further motion, assuming that that motion is approved to report the paper out of the license application out of committee with the aforementioned conditions.
Vice president bears move to report the license out of committee with the aforementioned conditions. Second by Councilor Caravello. So we'll take the first motion from Councilor Scarpelli, seconded by Councilor Caravello. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Vice president bears. Yes. Councilor Caravello. Yes. Councilor Collins. Yes. Councilor Knight is absent.
Councilor Scarpelli? Yes. Councilor Sang? Yes. President Morrell? Yes. Six in the affirmative, one absent, zero in the negative. The motion passes. And we'll take the motion for our crisis affairs, seconded by Councilor Garbell. Please call the roll when you're ready. This is to report the paper out of committee with those conditions.
Vice President bears. Yes. Yes. Yes.
Councilor Singh? Yes. President Morrell? Yes. Six in the affirmative, one in, I'm sorry, one absent, zero in the negative. The motion passes. Vice Mayor Harris. Thank you, Madam President. And just, Cameron, thanks for coming to this one. We have to report it back out and vote on it one more time at our regular meeting. I think we can have that on the agenda for next week's meeting. I would also say probably you don't have to be here for it, although I'll let my other councilors speak for it. I think we just- Yeah, you don't have to come. Yeah, if you want to be here, you're welcome, but you don't have to be here. All right. Okay, great. Thank you so much. Thank you. Thank you. Thanks a lot. Thanks.
So moving on to papers 22-508 and 22-538. These are the papers regarding the special permit and class two auto license request by Lyft FlexDrive. I know we have representatives on the call from that company and happy to take questions from councilors first, or if we want to hear Councilor Carvejo. Thank you, Madam President. Again,
I don't have any problem approving this one either. I mean, I don't, I bet you most people don't even know Lyft even as an officer. They've flown under the radar, I think, for the last four years. No one even knows their rover. They're on top of a men's warehouse on the Fells Way. And my only concern is, you know, so you're having, what, 80 cars? How many cars are gonna be parked on the station landing?
So we're running a business as normal for them. Or is there at any given time? We have these spaces for 50, but that is designed as overflow, things go wrong. Sorry, can I just have your name and address for the record? Yeah, sorry. My name is Glenn Solomon, I work for FlexDrive, and I'm from Georgia, sorry to say. Glenn? Glenn, yes. Two N's. Solomon? Yes. Thank you. So my only question is, so when someone goes to pick up a car,
What do they do with their car? So a majority of the Lyft drivers, they either get dropped off, and one of the great bonuses of this spot is it's right next to a train station, so the public transit allows them to get there, but no Lyft drivers are able to leave their vehicles on that site. Where would they leave their car if they had a Lyft? They need to either bring someone with them that will take the car away, and or they'll need to take public transit or a Lyft to the site.
they wouldn't be able to leave their car on one of the 50 spots? Correct, only Lyft employees will use those spots. Thank you, Councilor Kerrio. Councilor Scarpelli. Okay, thank you very much. I had some questions, both legally and we asked for the traffic report. Is Mr. Blake there this evening?
He is out sick today. Okay. So the biggest the biggest concerns one where the, the making sure that if they're parked in the city that the excise tax go to the city of Medford, as, as was stated. The, the other questions I had was that, you know that.
the impact in traffic, especially in that area. I know there was talks probably about the, I'm glad to hear it's only 50 cars. I thought it was a lot more. I thought it was some, the talk was about 150 cars. So that makes me a little bit more at ease, but at the same time,
I would have loved to talk to Mr. Blake about the study that was signed off from traffic, saying that there would be no issues. And I think that if we have the representative here, I would move to approve it if we put a 90-day review for the fact that I'd like to see what it looks like at the site, at the Falls Way Plaza.
you know, if there was any within the 90 days of operations that it would be, there would be an impact of overflow of cars at that location, so. Thank you, Councilor Scarpalli. Councilor Caravaglia. Thank you, Madam President. Again, I don't see a need for a traffic report, because these people, they're gonna take the car and go. They're not gonna be, if they happen to be driving around the city, then pick up and say that's,
They were gonna be here whether they got a car from you or they got a car somewhere else. So, I mean, so I think the traffic impact is negligible at best, because how many cars are gonna be here at the minute? So there should never be more than six to eight cars. So six to eight cars, so six to eight cars is really negligible for the traffic in that area. Madam President. Councilor Scarpelli.
Like I said, I understand that. If we can just put a 90 day review on that, just to make sure that there isn't a, and it's not really that area, it's the area at the Wellington Circle.
one of the most dangerous intersections in the nation. So, and then the overflow of parking in the area for, especially in the morning. So like I said, I understand that I would, I did some research. I can understand that and I would move forward to approve it. As long as we put a 90 day review on that, just to make sure that we have no concerns or issues or overflow or parking over at that location.
Thank you, Councillor Scarpelli. Councillor Seng. If this does go forward, I know other Councillors have questions. I might have questions as well. I would, out of an abundance of caution, like to see a traffic review, just because, as I think Councillor Scarpelli said, well, the Wellington Circle area is known for its traffic problems, that somewhere I were,
It's a neighborhood where I grew up so I know how hectic it can be around there and just out of, out of an abundance of caution if this does go forward I would like to see a traffic review. Any other discussion from counselors. Thank you, Madam President. Thanks for being here Glenn. Quite a trip.
I guess, first off, just for some context, how big is FlexDrive as a company? From an employee standpoint, vehicle standpoint? Employee, vehicles, yeah, yeah, yeah. Or how many states do you operate in, that kind of thing? Yeah, so FlexDrive is spread around the country. We have another number of locations across the country where we operate our rental vehicles. Yeah. As far as absolute size of staff, I don't know those off the top of my head. I really focus on moving the cars from A to B, the operational side. Gotcha.
Do you only work with Lyft or do you work with other companies? I personally only provide the vehicles for Lyft. Okay. But does FlexDrive as a company provide vehicles for other companies? Not that I'm aware of. Okay. You know, and my concerns with this, you know, I definitely have community concerns with this. I can understand the traffic impact. I can understand the, you know, some of the locations near a wetland. I've heard some environmental things come up.
My real concern about this is about is kind of the economics and of the workers, the folks who are working for Lyft and renting the cars.
What happens, you know, someone rents a car, but the Lyft, you know, they don't make enough money on Lyft for the day to pay for the car. What happens in that situation? I, unfortunately, am not the correct person to ask that. I'm on strictly the flex drive side, not the Lyft side of the business. Yeah. So my interactions don't go as far as that. We do have Christy Origins from Lyft on the call. Christy, could you speak to that? Lily's also there. As well as Lily. If anyone from Lyft could speak to that question from Bars and Bears.
Can you repeat the question? Sure, sure. The question was, you know, if someone, you know, a driver rents a car for the day to drive lift, but doesn't bring in enough fares to cover the cost of the car, what happens? Similar to what they do with Uber and Lyft, those who rent cars from, like Uber does, they have a deal with Hertz. Their car payment comes out first.
before you start making any money. So if you don't make enough money, then you. And you owe the company. Okay. Christy, can you, is that correct? Yeah, unfortunately, I don't know that I can answer that question either in terms of what happens if they can't pay. Okay. And then, you know, I'm also heard, you know, I think to councilor, it was a councilor Parabello's question about the, or maybe it's councilor Scarpelli, the onsite parking.
for like a personal vehicle. So you get there in a personal vehicle, rent this because your personal vehicle, maybe it's too old to be a Lyft, right, something like that. You know, we're hearing you'd have to have someone with you to drive the car away or you have to take public transit or a Lyft. You know, that's a pretty significant cost to the person involved. It may not be directed at you, it may be directed at Lyft. You know,
Do you provide compensation to the driver for the cost of public transit or do you provide a free lift to allow them to get to the site to access the vehicle? Again, I don't know how that lift side of that works. So unfortunately, I can't answer that either. Christy, are you able to answer that?
Yeah, so the, we are not, we don't compensate for the driver coming to the site. It's just like a normal, you know, rental agreement where if they, you know, this is a service that we provide and if it's something that they want to utilize, you know, they come to, they make the appointment and they come to the site. Got it. And then I guess my question there would be to Attorney Blake, would it possible, be possible to put a condition on the permit requiring that
either parking be provided for a personal vehicle or compensation be provided to the person for their transit time to the site? I think the former would be a sufficient nexus for this land use permit. I don't think the latter would be requiring compensation. This is a land use permit and there has to be a nexus.
obviously having sufficient parking for what could be overflow would have a sufficient and is clearly outlined in your ordinance, the ladder requiring compensation. I think that probably goes beyond what you could do with a land use permit. Got it. Yeah. And I figured you were going to say that, but I just wanted to make sure.
I, you know, again, I've voiced my concerns here that, you know, basically we're talking about moving from a business model around providing rides to folks where, you know, you had compensation and capital costs borne by the corporation, now to have compensation and capital costs borne by the worker.
and the worker actually has fewer labor protections under the new model than they did under the old model. And, you know, I understand, you know, that's certainly good for profits. It's certainly been good for transit network companies, you know, in the short-term gain of their shareholders, but I seriously question whether it's good for our society and our economy and for people themselves. So at the very least,
you know, I'd like to see if we could do the condition that parking be provided for the personal vehicle. That's, it seems like that might be the one thing we can give to the person coming to this site to take a little bit of cost or something off of their plate. So I'll believe that as it is, that's something I'd like to see. I'm not sure. I know there's other councilors. I don't know if we're moving this out tonight or waiting for traffic study or what, but,
If we, when we do move forward, I'd really like to see that condition put on. And to be quite frank, I'm gonna try to think of any other conditions I can, that would serve the same purpose. Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Supervisor. Is parking be provided for workers vehicles? Yes. Councilor Scarpelli and then Councilor Collins. And Councilor Kerbelo. I'm good, Madam President. Okay, thank you, Councilor Scarpelli. Councilor Collins, then Councilor Kerbelo.
Thank you for some real and thank you to the representatives who are here tonight. Much appreciated. Thank you attorney Blake. I'm, I'm also interested in getting additional context around this permit. You know it's a, it's well heard the point about this site be very close to the orange line we also know that ridership levels.
are not at all what they were a few years ago so I am concerned about. At the same time I'm concerned about drivers I was going to call them employees but they're really more like customers who are coming to the site to use the cars.
You know, and making sure that there's a reasonable accommodation for them since they're, you know, paying paying to use the service to pick up to pick up riders. At the same time, if we can only condition the permit for providing parking to drivers, and not compensation for those who are traveling to the site by other means. That strikes me as a bit of an inequitable compensation.
mechanism, because we're only conditioning for those who are arriving in personal vehicles and not those who, you know, for example, maybe they don't have access to a personal vehicle, maybe they can't afford one. So I am interested in entertaining that, but it strikes me as kind of only getting at a fraction of the worker population that we're that we're trying to
include here. So kind of on both sides of that issue of how are folks getting to this site to use the cars, personal vehicles, public transit, you know, to the extent that some will be driving, pick up the lift vehicles I am interested in seeing that traffic study. Thank you. Thank you, Councilor Collins. Councilor Carvillo. Thank you, Madam President. I would Councilor Baez on this one here, as far as the employees there.
People who work for Lyft and other similar type companies have to work an awful lot of hours to make a decent living wage. And now they're gonna be renting a car from you. Do you know what the daily rate is that they're gonna pay? Do you know what the daily rate they're gonna be paying or weekly or monthly rate? And listen, I'm in that same business and I see them there, these people, they work tremendous amount of hours. And I think they work way too many hours to make a,
barely a living wage. I understand your model, but I don't like practices of lifting over myself. You're not doing anything illegal, but there should be better compensation and better benefits for these people who really are out there.
an awful lot of hours to, I say, to make a lot of, I say, especially with gas being the way it is now, it's gonna, you know, they're gonna be spending more money to rent these vehicles. So that's, you know, like I say, you know, I understand your company, I just don't like how they treat the employees. Thank you, Councilor Carvalho. Any further questions or discussion from the Council? And if I could just essentially just summarize, and this is gonna be a question for Attorney Blake,
I think multiple counselors, if not all the counselors have expressed, we are elected to serve in the public interest. And I think a lot of us feel that these types of companies, because of the amount of hours, because of the low pay, because you can get increasingly lower pay depending on how you operate. We have concerns about this operating in our community, but it's my understanding, Attorney Blake, that we are very limited in the reasons for denial. And as you've said, conditions, correct? Because it is land use, it's not about,
business organization. That is correct. Are they going to be bringing the cars back to that when they've done, are they going to be bringing the cars back to that location also correct rentals pickups and returns will happen at that location, and will they be like I said,
will they be checking into an office or anything, or just drop them off? Yep, so we have the office there, and what we do is we set up appointments on an hourly basis throughout the day, throughout the week, however we need. So they're gonna have to walk across- Drivers make an appointment. They'll have to walk across street to, is there gonna be an office on the station landing side? Yeah, so at the location where the physical location is that we'll be operating out of, the drivers will drop the vehicle at that location, so no crossing of the street, and then Lyft employees will bring those vehicles to that side separate lot.
employees are the ones on site. Christie Lawrence, I saw you had your hand up. I did, yeah. One of the things that I just wanted to bring up too is we have done traffic studies in the past for other markets and just one thing to bring up is our peak times tend to be between noon and 3 o'clock and usually it tends, I mean even more so it's been around 145 to 245.
So I just wanted to call that out because our drivers want to be out on the market, you know, want to be out driving during peak times. And so from a traffic perspective, really the in and out happens in the middle of the day. Just something that I wanted to call out from a traffic perspective. I appreciate that. Have you have you been to the space where this would be operating from? I have. Yes, I have been. Yeah, I have.
It's a uniquely challenging intersection regardless the time of day. So it's a mess over there. Any further comments, questions from the council? I'm still thinking. I don't want to end, but I don't know what I'm going to say. We know this will, if this paper is voted, we will have, Councilor Collins. Thank you very much.
President Morrell, I'm curious. I was just reviewing before this meeting the draft comprehensive plan to the extent that that touches on some of the guideposts that we have for, well, guideposts for the community as they pertain to jobs in Medford. This plan, which is still in draft form, it mentions vibrant jobs, it mentions professional jobs, high-paying jobs, jobs that serve Medford residents and keep Medford residents employed within the community.
Um, you know, and obviously very well aware this is a land use ordinance, and it's only that, um, at the same time, I was curious at the point that we were waiting on a traffic study, um, in order to consider this matter further, I was curious if we might be able to request from Lyft, um, as context for a subsequent meeting, um, information for markets similar to Medford on, um, average daily driver compensation, uh, hourly compensation, um,
from how far away are most drivers coming in? How many hours are they spending on the road and around Medford? I know I've heard from constituent concerns about when the hourly rate for a driver gets low, of course that could incentivize drivers to drive more. We wanna make sure that we are not creating an incentive structure in Medford wherein drivers are
having really long days on our roads and just other, you know, worker metrics and road safety metrics such as that. So I'd be curious to entertain if Representative Goodlift could provide that type of information for a future meeting. Thank you. Thank you, Councilor Collins. So I just wanna make sure you're asking to see if a similar metropolitan area could provide information related to daily rates, compensation, where folks are traveling from.
That would be if Lyft could provide for, you know, for an example or two of metropolitan areas similar to Medford, average hourly wage, average daily wage, how many hours per day drivers are spending on the roads, how far away they are traveling to Medford to pick up those cars. Thank you, Councilor Collins. Christy, is that something that, is that data that's available that might be able to be provided either now or in the future?
I mean, it's not information that we would be sharing. And part of it too is, you know, this is for us asking for permission for the rentals use. And just to clarify, I just wanted to make sure you know we all understood that the drivers that come onto the site can use the vehicle for personal reasons for other platforms.
they're not using the vehicle solely or can, but they don't, they're not required to use the platform or this service only on our platform. Thank you for that. Councilor Carvilla. For those who know, these people are classified as independent contractors. They don't get an hourly wage. Misclassified. Well, they're classified as independent contractors. So they're not getting any health insurance or any benefits from the company.
For those who don't know, City of Medford derives, I think, 20 cents for every ride share service that starts in Medford. And you'd be surprised how many that do start in Medford. I think last year we had a couple hundred thousand. And those cards that they're taking aren't necessarily gonna be in Medford. If they happen to get calls in Medford, then they do, but they're made to go anywhere they want.
Some of them will be doing food deliveries, am I correct? Like, you know, Grubhub. And they can use anything they want. So these people, they're independent contractors and they have to really scramble to make their money. You'll notice that a lot more of these, a lot of Uber drivers and Lyft drivers have now switched over to the food platform because they realize that they can stay in their own community and make more money and get tips,
They're not getting when they do the right share service from other people. So again, I know there's not much, I know we don't get to stipulate what you pay your employees or don't pay them. That's not within our purview, but I do think, I don't support your model for what you do with employees. Thank you, Councilor Kerrio. To that point, Christy, if we're using
relevant question. If folks can use these vehicles for whatever they decide, does that TNC charge still apply the same way for each ride? So it's like if they're, so that surcharge that we have in the state of Massachusetts for these rides. So if they're checking the car out for whatever, does that, does that surcharge still enact? Right. But if they're taking the car that originates in Medford to run errands, is that correct, Chrissy?
It's based off of when they're using the app. When they're on the platform, it's not connected to the vehicle itself. Okay, so it would just be if they're in it, if they're, okay. It's when the app is on, great. Thank you for that. Vice President Behrs. Thank you, Madam President. First question is along a similar line. Chrissy, do we expect non-Lyft or app workers to use the service?
So the driver has to be on the platform to make the appointment to use the service, but they can use it for other services or other times for other things that they need. So the advantage to this program is that there are individuals out there that don't have a vehicle. And this is an opportunity for them to be able to rent a vehicle and make an income through the platform.
So I don't know if that answers your question. Yeah, I mean, so you have to have the Lyft app to get the car. That's correct. So even though you could use it for other purposes, you're starting on the Lyft app at the very least. That's correct. Do you provide any sort of additional
coaching, financial training, you know, estimated, you know, some sort of guide as to what a worker can expect to make, you know, or why the, essentially, did they get any additional financial literacy information to know whether or not they're actually gonna, you know, make a positive income
or not using this service compared to when they're using their own personal car. Unfortunately, I don't, I mean, I, to be honest, I don't know that I can answer that question, but it's definitely something that we can find out and provide that information. That would be helpful. Yeah. And then this question may again be for Attorney Blake, but,
could we condition some sort of regular report be provided to the city based on the activities at the site? And what would the limits be? And I know that's an open question. So I guess it's first, could we condition some sort of regular reporting and what are the limits of the information we could request in that report? Thank you, Councillor. In my opinion, you could request reports.
but those reports would have to have an access to the criteria outlined in the bylaw. And I think probably the big one in the earlier counselor had indicated that he wanted to have them come back in 90 days. I think what you could do is you could ask for traffic information and that kind of information. And you could ask for monthly or quarterly reports. Okay.
you guys still thinking? Well, yeah, I mean, I think knowing that as a tool in our toolbox, I think we, you know, thinking about what we may want to include in a report like that would be a valuable exercise to do. I have a couple right off the top of my head, but I would like more time to think about it. Great. And a reminder, this will come before us at the regular council meeting too, if we decide to vote it out. Councilor Collins.
Thank you, President Morrell. I appreciate that. I think that the idea of the recording mechanism that Vice President Baird suggested is a good idea. I think that's something that might be able to allay some of my concerns. Given that we kind of have asks out for some of these other metrics, like the sort of de facto hourly compensation, daily compensation that I asked about, and the traffic report
I would make a motion to keep this paper in committee for now, while we're waiting for this additional information. I think when we get that additional context, that will be information that I think would be helpful for us to discuss in this setting in some more detail, just because there's kind of a lot of data points that will be included in that cache of data with the traffic report and whatnot.
I second that motion. Oh, I was gonna second that I think it's reasonable, reasonable, as we're waiting for them. These are questions about worker metrics and the traffic work that we take that we need again to evaluate. Yes, I just but I just want to understand that lift has said they will not be providing us with those worker metrics. Oh, I just heard Chrissy say that.
that could provide metrics on whether they provide financial literacy training to the workers. Mr. Blake is sick as well, so he can maybe come back and provide additional information when it comes to traffic. Yeah, absolutely. I wasn't speaking out against the motion. I just wanted to make sure we're clear on what we can expect before the next meeting. I did have a question. Do we know if there's an environmental impact report out there?
because I know some residents have reached out to Councilor Behrs and I about the environmental impact of this. I don't know if our city has a report or anything. We're not given one? I don't believe we were. I'm not seeing anything. Could we request one if there isn't?
Attorney Blake, is that something we could request of the petitioner or? If there are environmental concerns, you can certainly request information regarding those concerns and or a some type of report that says there are no environmental concerns from the petitioner. Yes. Thank you.
If there are environmental concerns, we can request that or request some type of report that would say that there are no environmental concerns of the petitioner. Well, I would move to request the report. So we have a few motions before us. We have the first from Councilor Scarpelli.
Madam President, I would see what the other votes would go for us, if you wanna keep this in committee. That would, okay, thank you. I'll be the second Councilor Singh's motion. Okay, so first we have the motion from Vice Mayor Behrs, sorry, Councilor Collins to keep this in committee as we await the traffic report and the answers to Vice Mayor Behrs questions from petitioner. Would Councilor Collins
That's problems. Yes. So environmental work. Yep. So the motion I have Councilor Collins has amended by Councilor saying, which is to say Councilor saying withdrew his original motion and added an amendment.
So on the motion of Councilor Collins to keep the paper and committee to allow us to get the traffic report responses to the questions or advice and affairs, as well as a report or statement of environmental impact or potential environmental impact.
Councilor Collins moved to keep the paper in committee for now until the council receives additional information, a traffic report and an environmental report or statement of environmental impact. And that is with a second from Vice President Ferris. I would just take the words for now out. Yeah, I'll take that out. Yep. Hang on. Transcribed rather than wrote a motion.
I have a second from Vice President bears on that. On the motion of Council con second by Vice President bears Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Vice President bears. Yes. Council carabino. Council Collins. Yes. Council night is absent Councilors compelling. Yes. That's the same. Yes, President Morrell. Yes, 16 affirmative one absent zero negative emotion passes.
Any further discussion, questions from the council? Councilor Scarpelli has his motion out there, but he wanted to wait for the council. Oh, Councilor Scarpelli, do you want, would you like to keep your motion or withdraw it? I would withdraw right now, thank you. Thank you, Councilor Scarpelli. Motion. Second. On the motion of Councilor Carvalho to adjourn, seconded by Councilor Sang. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
It's embarrassing. Councilor Kerrio? Yes. Councilor Collins? Yes. Councilor Knight is absent. Councilor Scarpelli? Councilor Scarpelli? To adjourn. I think he's gone. He just... I think he was... I was... I accidentally... I muted him because there was... Councilor Hussain? Yes. President Morrell? Yes. Five in the affirmative, two absent. Motion passes. Meeting is adjourned.