[SPEAKER_03]: Council will come to order.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sir, would you please step outside of the rail?
[SPEAKER_03]: Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_04]: Councilor Caraviello?
[SPEAKER_05]: Present.
[SPEAKER_04]: Councilor Falco?
[SPEAKER_07]: Present.
[SPEAKER_04]: Councilor Knight?
[SPEAKER_01]: Present.
[SPEAKER_04]: Vice-President Lungo-Koehn?
[SPEAKER_06]: Present.
[SPEAKER_04]: Councilor Marks?
[SPEAKER_00]: Present.
[SPEAKER_04]: Councilor Scarpelli?
[SPEAKER_08]: Present.
[SPEAKER_04]: President Dello Russo?
[SPEAKER_03]: Present.
[SPEAKER_03]: With seven members present and none absent, please rise and join us in saluting the flag.
[SPEAKER_03]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mr. Messenger, would you please secure the area inside the precincts here, please?
[SPEAKER_03]: Chair recognizes Councilor Knight for suspension of the rules to take the applicants for board members on the motion of Councilor Knight for suspension of the rules.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_03]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_03]: Motion passes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Communications from the Mayor, 16-384.
[SPEAKER_03]: To the Honorable President and members of the Medford City Council, dear President and Councilors, I respectfully request and recommend that your Honorable body confirm the appointment of Mr. Dean Bruno of 41 Saunders Street Method as a member of the License Commission.
[SPEAKER_03]: This position became vacant with the resignation of Mr. Maurice Del Vendo.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mr. Bruno's resume is attached and he plans to be present tonight at your meeting, Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mr. President, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's with great pleasure that I'm here this evening to endorse Dean Bruno and his candidacy.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've known the Brunos for a number of years.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're a long time Medford family, grew up in West Medford and Dean now resides up in the Heights.
[SPEAKER_01]: He has over a 20 year career in law enforcement and prior to that he had worked in government for about five years, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I have absolutely no problem with this appointment and I would move for approval.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion approved by Councilor Knight, seconded by Councilor Falco.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion for approval, all those in favor?
[SPEAKER_03]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_03]: Motion carries.
[SPEAKER_03]: 16- Congratulations.
[SPEAKER_03]: We're very glad to have you serving your community.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the 16-385, to the Honorable President and members of the Medford City Council, to Mr. President and councilors, I respectfully request and recommend that your Honorable body confirm the appointment of Mr. Nabin Sapkota of 53 Earl Street, Earl Ave, Medford,
[SPEAKER_03]: as Commissioner of Trust Funds, this position became vacant with the passing of Juan Ramirez.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is Mr. Stepcorder here, please?
[SPEAKER_03]: You are welcome.
[SPEAKER_03]: Chair recognizes Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mr. President, although I don't know the gentleman personally, I have reviewed his resume and it's rather impressive, and I'd ask that the committee move for approval.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion for approval, Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_03]: Second?
[SPEAKER_03]: Second, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_03]: By Councilor Caraviello on that motion.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_03]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_03]: Motion carries.
[SPEAKER_03]: Congratulations and welcome.
[SPEAKER_03]: We're glad to have you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion of Councilor Knight to take from unfinished business number 15-734, loan order addition to the DPW facility project fund of $300,000.
[SPEAKER_03]: This motion began its journey with us on November 10th in 2015 after being tabled and referred to committee a number of times.
[SPEAKER_03]: It finally passed its first reading this past March, second reading on March 31st, and now is eligible for a third and final reading on today, April 12th.
[SPEAKER_03]: So the chair recognizes Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mr. President, yes, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_01]: As noted, this matter has been before the council a couple of occasions prior.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's relative to some surveying problems that were had with the Winthrop Street drainage project.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's my understanding that
[SPEAKER_01]: There is litigation subrogation that's in place relatively.
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I looking at the right one?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I'm not looking at the right one.
[SPEAKER_01]: 15-734.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is the DPW facility.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the DPW facility.
[SPEAKER_03]: We just had to tie the up.
[SPEAKER_03]: There was an underestimate on some.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was underestimated.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was underestimated on the mitigation for the pollution underground, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we've passed a couple of readings on this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I would move for approval on the third reading.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to get paid one way or the other, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_03]: So a motion for approval by Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_03]: Seconded by Councilor Falco.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_00]: Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the issue that I've had concern with for a number of months now regarding the original estimate that the city hired an outside consultant to come in and give us an estimate on the contaminants at the DPW yard.
[SPEAKER_00]: The estimate was off by, I believe it was 500,000.
[SPEAKER_00]: The estimate was off by 500,000, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I know we had many discussions with Louise.
[SPEAKER_03]: We have before us Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Louise Miller, the Director of Budget and Finance, who can answer any of our questions.
[SPEAKER_03]: She's answered many of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: She's answered them all.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am in opposition of this paper.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I want to explain why, for the viewing audience, Mr. President, that I feel... If it's too comcastic tonight, it will be viewable.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's great.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I want to explain my position, why I'm opposed to this, for the fact that...
[SPEAKER_00]: The city went out and hired a consultant to come in and provide the city with facts and figures on what it would cost to remove the contaminants at the DPW yard.
[SPEAKER_00]: And to be off by $500,000 on a project that was originally estimated at, what was the amount?
[SPEAKER_02]: It was just about $500,000.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was about $500,000.
[SPEAKER_00]: So they were off by $500,000.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the project ended up costing us
[SPEAKER_00]: A million dollars, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I'm not sure, would we pay this outside consultant?
[SPEAKER_02]: It was around $150,000.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't have the exact figure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we paid $150,000 to an outside consultant to ask or to let us know what it was going to cost to remove the contaminants.
[SPEAKER_00]: They said $500,000.
[SPEAKER_00]: We started the project, it was closer to $1 million.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we lost $500,000 on that and we paid $150,000 for a consultant that gave us bogus information.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's actually $650,000 in net, which I have a real problem with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I realize that the remedial treatment of what was under there may have differed based on what they found and so forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have a tough time thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's almost like being a meteorologist.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could be right 50% of the time, and you're doing a good job.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I don't understand why we'd pay a consultant to come in over $100,000 and be off by 100%.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just doesn't sound right to me, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_00]: And for those particular reasons, I cannot support this particular funding
[SPEAKER_00]: for the cleanup, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor Marks, for your frankness.
[SPEAKER_03]: So we have a motion for a pull by Councilor Knight, as seconded by Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_03]: So on that motion, Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_04]: Councilor Caraviello?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Councilor Falco?
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Councilor Knight?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Vice President Lungo-Koehn?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes
[SPEAKER_04]: Councilor Marks?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: Councilor Scarpelli?
[SPEAKER_08]: Yes
[SPEAKER_04]: President Dello Russo?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, with a six in the affirmative, one in the negative, the motion passes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Congratulations.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_03]: Loan order passes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you, Councilors.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Miller.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion of Councilor Knight to take up item number 16-309.
[SPEAKER_03]: Again, an item eligible for third reading, amended ordinance on outdoor dining.
[SPEAKER_03]: After much consideration, we took this up at tonight.
[SPEAKER_03]: It is eligible for its third and final reading tonight, April 12th.
[SPEAKER_03]: So on the motion for approval by Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, Mr. President, it's my understanding that this is just a simple clarification of the existing outdoor dining license ordinance that's in place.
[SPEAKER_01]: There was some misinterpretation of the legislative intent that's been addressed through the language in this newly crafted zoning ordinance, and I move for approval.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion for approval, Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just wanted to thank the subcommittee that was sent to Councilor Knight and under his leadership on that subcommittee.
[SPEAKER_00]: They vetted this even further, the paper that we received from the administration.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I wanted to thank that subcommittee for their due diligence on this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Councilor.