[SPEAKER_12]: We wish you a merry Christmas.
[SPEAKER_14]: We wish you a merry Christmas.
[SPEAKER_04]: We wish you a merry Christmas and a happy new year.
[SPEAKER_14]: Good timings we bring to you and your kin.
[SPEAKER_03]: Good timings for Christmas and a happy Mustang report.
[SPEAKER_16]: It's a stacking like brain game type challenge where they have to move weights in an order and then reassemble the platform at a different spot in the gym.
Let's see how it can do.
[SPEAKER_16]: Alright, so this is called the Rice Relay.
[SPEAKER_16]: Each team has a little plastic spoon, and they need to sprint down, get as much rice on the spoon as they can, bring it, put it into their cup.
[SPEAKER_16]: They're not allowed to touch the cup, like Lovicka just cheated.
[SPEAKER_16]: They can only use one hand, and then when we're all done, we'll see the winning team gets to pick what the three losing teams are gonna do.
[SPEAKER_16]: Hey, you're dropping rice everywhere, Mikey.
[SPEAKER_16]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_16]: Bruh, I saw you.
[SPEAKER_16]: I fell you apart here.
[SPEAKER_16]: Look, look, look.
[SPEAKER_16]: Kids will take every advantage they can.
[SPEAKER_16]: Look, bro.
[SPEAKER_16]: This Jerry's got a handful of rice somewhere.
[SPEAKER_16]: Where'd he go?
[SPEAKER_16]: No, it's not this one either.
[SPEAKER_16]: Cheater.
[SPEAKER_16]: Look at all of them.
[SPEAKER_16]: Really?
[SPEAKER_16]: Excellent.
[SPEAKER_16]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_16]: I have this bonus rice in my hand.
[SPEAKER_16]: Once I finish the question, the first group that yells out the correct answer goes in your cup.
[SPEAKER_16]: What is my favorite color?
[SPEAKER_10]: Clear!
[SPEAKER_16]: That's my favorite color.
[SPEAKER_16]: First place.
[SPEAKER_13]: Hello?
[SPEAKER_13]: No.
[SPEAKER_13]: You don't say.
[SPEAKER_13]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_13]: Bye.
[SPEAKER_13]: Who was that?
[SPEAKER_16]: You didn't say.
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't say.
[SPEAKER_07]: you don't say i don't know how do you think this is the case in the bus airport and i'm here at today's medford versus arlington catholic track meet where the first of the event will be in about ten minutes where will be we'll be seeing for medford will just go and julia gail back into the boys you're just as if the air and then candy who should be the favorites for medford this is the new canister for the bus airport and i'm back to you what's
[SPEAKER_07]: What's up guys, this is Dick Henniston with the Mustang Report and I'm here with Amber Harris, the captain of the track team.
[SPEAKER_07]: Amber, how's this season going so far?
[SPEAKER_14]: You know, it's been pretty good.
[SPEAKER_14]: We have a lot of upcoming freshmen that are pretty fast.
[SPEAKER_14]: You know, they're doing great for their meets.
[SPEAKER_14]: You know, we ran against Malden and Everett and we held up pretty well.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'm here at the track meet for Medford vs. Arlington Catholic.
[SPEAKER_07]: Tia, you just won your race.
[SPEAKER_07]: How do you feel?
[SPEAKER_10]: I feel pretty great.
[SPEAKER_10]: I love track so it's a great feeling every time.
[SPEAKER_07]: And how do you go out there and prepare every day for the season?
[SPEAKER_10]: Every day I really try to stretch out my muscles so I don't get injured, so that's a really big key for me.
[SPEAKER_07]: And Ben, first you went from football record-breaking 33 touchdowns and now you're in track.
[SPEAKER_07]: How do you feel?
[SPEAKER_08]: I feel good about it.
[SPEAKER_08]: After the football season I was very tired, but just had to keep grinding.
[SPEAKER_07]: And Sean, small in stature but large in speed.
[SPEAKER_07]: How do you feel after your race?
[SPEAKER_12]: tired and amazing.
[SPEAKER_07]: Come on Max!
[SPEAKER_07]: Wait.
Is that Max?
[SPEAKER_04]: Come on Maxi!
Let's go Maxi!
Let's go Monica!
[SPEAKER_08]: Let's go Kelsey, catch it.
[SPEAKER_08]: Come on Amber.
[SPEAKER_07]: First question is for Mr. Milne.
[SPEAKER_07]: What do you do over the holiday break?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do I do over the holiday break?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I celebrate a very Italian Christmas on Christmas Eve, you know, the seven fishes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then Christmas, and then I pack up and I coach a ski team in Quebec City for the week.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by the way, the cold that we had the other day is our warm day up there.
[SPEAKER_07]: And Igor, same question is for you.
[SPEAKER_07]: What do you do over the holiday break?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I'm usually just with my family a lot.
[SPEAKER_02]: I also watch a lot of soccer games on Boxing Day.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's usually just a lot to be with.
[SPEAKER_02]: I just like to be a lot with my family.
[SPEAKER_07]: And Kaitlyn, same question is for you.
[SPEAKER_07]: What do you do over the holiday break?
[SPEAKER_00]: I usually hang out with my family because we don't really see each other during the year, just around the holidays.
[SPEAKER_00]: And my friends.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a nice, relaxing week.
[SPEAKER_07]: Lucy DeMarco, first question is for you.
[SPEAKER_07]: What do you do over the holiday break?
[SPEAKER_11]: Over the holiday break I spend time with my family and my friends and for Christmas I go over my grandmother's house.
[SPEAKER_07]: And Ms.
[SPEAKER_07]: Donlan, same question is for you.
[SPEAKER_07]: What do you do over the holiday break?
[SPEAKER_09]: Well, I'm having 28 people for dinner, Christmas dinner and 53 for dessert.
[SPEAKER_09]: So that's, we'll start the break a little, little craziness on the Donlan family side.
[SPEAKER_09]: And then it'll be a lot of relaxation.
[SPEAKER_09]: I hope to get to the movies.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm going to Celtics Tuesday night, dinner with friends and, uh, sleep in late every day.
[SPEAKER_05]: Joe, what do you do over the holidays?
[SPEAKER_05]: I like to spend time with my family, just relax, eat some good food, stay warm.
[SPEAKER_05]: Speaking of food, what is your favorite holiday meal?
[SPEAKER_05]: It has to be crab legs when we eat at Christmas Eve.
[SPEAKER_07]: Do you do the entire seven fishes?
[SPEAKER_05]: I'll be used to not anymore.
[SPEAKER_15]: Happy holiday Mustangs!
[SPEAKER_15]: I'm here with Mr. Skorker.
[SPEAKER_15]: So Mr. Skorker, what is your favorite holiday meal?
[SPEAKER_13]: My favorite holiday meal would have to be pernil, which is pork shoulder.
[SPEAKER_15]: That sounds really good.
[SPEAKER_15]: And how about your favorite holiday movie?
[SPEAKER_13]: The Family Stone would have to be my number one favorite.
[SPEAKER_15]: And your favorite holiday song?
[SPEAKER_13]: Well, that has to be Jingle Bells because it was written in Medford.
[SPEAKER_06]: Mr. Ambrose, first question is for you.
[SPEAKER_06]: What do you do over the holidays?
[SPEAKER_06]: Over the holidays, I like to get together with my family.
[SPEAKER_06]: We're going to visit my sister this year for Christmas Eve, and we're going to visit my wife's parents for Christmas Day.
[SPEAKER_06]: That sounds great.
[SPEAKER_06]: And Thomas, same question to you.
[SPEAKER_06]: What do you do over the holiday break?
[SPEAKER_02]: Go on a vacation with my family, ski trip usually.
[SPEAKER_06]: uh... what is your favorite holiday movie to sit back and relax and watch uh... i'm a guy is a tough choice uh... i'd say it's probably a tie between elf and home alone abby what do you do over the holiday break
[SPEAKER_12]: Well, I get to see a lot of my family, which is really cool.
[SPEAKER_12]: And it's about it, hang out with my friends.
[SPEAKER_12]: I have basketball practice every day, so that'll keep me busy.
[SPEAKER_12]: That's about it.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yes, my grandmother makes, it's not really a meal, but my grandmother makes really good sugar cookies, and she spends hours decorating them, and they have little beading on them, and they're really intricately designed.
[SPEAKER_12]: They're so cute, I love them.
[SPEAKER_07]: And last question, what is your favorite holiday movie to sit back and watch?
[SPEAKER_12]: Oh jeez.
[SPEAKER_12]: Oh, The Grinch.
[SPEAKER_12]: Not the creepy Jim Carrey one, but the cartoon is like my favorite movie ever.
[SPEAKER_04]: Merry Christmas!
[SPEAKER_04]: Happy Holidays!
The Empty Sweater Contest winner is Raquel Quiroz.
[SPEAKER_11]: Falls with boughs of holly.
[SPEAKER_11]: Fa la la la la la la la la.
[SPEAKER_05]: Tis the season to be jolly.
[SPEAKER_08]: Fa la la la la la la la la.
[SPEAKER_08]: Don we now our gay apparel.
[SPEAKER_08]: Troll the ancient Yuletide carol.
[SPEAKER_15]: Fa la la la la la la la.
[SPEAKER_15]: La la la la la la la la.
[SPEAKER_15]: Fa la la la la la la la la.
[SPEAKER_15]: moon's outside.