I like cars, you know.
Hello, I'm Mr. Cassidy and I am one of the automotive technology instructors here at Bethel Vocational Technical High School.
Some of the skills a student will learn in the shop.
Freshman year we start out with general maintenance stuff.
The engine theory, they get to see what a four-stroke engine is all about.
From there, when you go to like sophomore year, you go into suspension and braking.
Junior year and senior year we get more into like deep diagnostics, electrical.
You get all different areas in our trade throughout the four years you were here.
I really didn't have any interest in cars, but then I saw this shop and I was like, that's kind of cool.
I think I've always been interested in cars and it was just a way to do that during my school time, especially when I didn't have access to a car at my house.
Well, I've always had a big passion for cars and also do what I enjoy the most, so what better place than to be here.