[SPEAKER_00]: And I have two kids in the public schools and Mr. Tucker McGlynn.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm a very enthusiastic public school supporter, former public school teacher, and current sub at Medford Public Schools.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I want to
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank everyone who made time in their day to come here today.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we are here gathered to kind of show some love and spread awareness about the exciting ballot initiatives that some of us have been waiting many years to be able to vote for Prop 2.5 override.
[SPEAKER_00]: to fund our city.
[SPEAKER_00]: We know many of us residents know that we desperately need funds and so we have this opportunity to fund our schools, to fund the DBW to do some much-needed work and to build a fire headquarters which for those of you who have been paying attention that's been many years coming
[SPEAKER_00]: So this is an incredible, incredible opportunity.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm so excited that we have the chance to go to the ballot and vote on this.
[SPEAKER_00]: So thanks to all of you who have come today to either show your support or learn more.
[SPEAKER_00]: or to get involved.
[SPEAKER_00]: This campaign runs on volunteers and so if anyone wants to get involved please make sure you checked off the box at the sign-in and we will email you with opportunities.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can find there's lots of different ways to help.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you to all the people who
[SPEAKER_00]: are involved, there's already so many people involved.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the part no one likes, of course, is that campaigns need money.
[SPEAKER_00]: So if anyone is able to, there are QR codes around with the ActBlue code that you can donate to our campaign.
[SPEAKER_00]: The more we raise, the more we can spread the message and get the word out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So thank you to those who have donated and to those who will donate.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am really happy that people showed up today.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to say just one more thing is just basically why I am personally so excited for this opportunity.
[SPEAKER_00]: And basically being a former public school teacher working in an underfunded school district that was not Medford, but very similar, and now working back in the schools and having kids in the schools,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just the reality of what it means to be underfunded.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's hard.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means that you get data, see where all your kids are at, and then cannot offer support to all the ones who need it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to make decisions based on what can be done, not what kids need.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means that we don't have
[SPEAKER_00]: money to pay teachers, sometimes a competitive wage, and then we lose teachers because we also have to pink slip them at the end of the year and can't retain them.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means that we don't have subs because we can't pay a competitive wage and kids don't get to go to specials or kids don't get their services that they need.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means that we are making these horrible, sad decisions every day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even though we don't know exactly where the funds will go, we desperately need the funds.
[SPEAKER_00]: So what I say is vote yes and then pay attention and advocate for where you think the funds should go.
[SPEAKER_00]: no matter what we need funding to invest in our students our children our teachers and you know give them the best education they deserve so that's all and i'm going to introduce