the CMR process, and take a look at the draft RFQ that was sent out to the team last week. So just to kind of give a quick overview of the short agenda we have, the CMR process will do a quick overview of the two phases that we'll need to go through. We'll look at, yep. Do we have to open a meeting and everything?
Sorry, before you continue, I need to read the post of the meeting and we need to do a roll call. So, let's let me do that. And then we can continue. Okay.
Please be advised there'll be a subcommittee meeting of the Medford Comprehensive High School Building Committee via remote participation only. The meeting can be viewed live on Medford Public Schools YouTube channel and through Medford Community Media on your local cable channel, which is Comcast 98 or 22 and Verizon 43, 45 or 47. The meeting will be recorded. Participants can call or log in by using the following information. The meeting ID is 988-3308-0541.
Um, we have rules around public comment, um, and, um, in the event that there are folks in this meeting who wish to provide public comment, um, the public comment is limited to three minutes per individual and be limited to matters on the agenda. Speakers may only speak once on each topic. The chair may limit to two minutes based on the number of individuals wishing to speak. And we'll announce that at the beginning of the public comment period at every meeting.
The public is encouraged to reach out in the following ways. There are two email addresses. One is for questions that require an official response from the project team, which is mhsproject at medford.k12.ma.us. And then comments and perspectives you'd like to share with all members of the MCHSBC. That email is mchsbc at medford.k12.us. I'll call the roll. Libby Brown.
here brian hilliard i'm here ken lord here matt rice here jenny graham here um dr galusi is absent she's she'll be along shortly and who um from the left field team is our official designee for this uh i am okay matt yeah
Okay, so we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 present, 1 absent, and we'll call the meeting to order. I'm going to turn it over to you, Matt. Great. Thank you, Jenny. Okay. Yeah, so, like I was saying, this is really a kickoff meeting for this team just to go over the overall construction manager at risk process.
We'll talk a bit about the timeline, and then we'll look at the critical sections of the RFQ that we do intend to post at the end of the month, which I'll go through in the timeline as well. So after the meeting today, I'll distribute to the full committee to give them a chance to review. We do have this on the agenda for the June 18th meeting, so we'll receive any comments from the committee on the 18th.
we'll get it updated and ready to post at the end of the month. So just to highlight kind of quickly the two phases that we go through. The first phase is called the prequalification process. This is, you know, to confirm that any of the firms that want to bid on the project or submit proposals are actually qualified to do so.
It's based off of experience, past performance, personnel, financial capacity, and their overall project approach. So only the firms that are determined to be qualified through this first phase will be invited to submit proposals in the second phase. So this is kind of our opportunity
you know, to do a deep dive into the firms that are interested and make sure that they are qualified to do something of this size and complexity. After the qualifications have been completed, the qualified firms will receive the RFP or request for proposals. This is another document that will highlight
uh, more specifically, you know, what the proposals need to include, um, and, um, how they should be pricing it, uh, both for pre-construction services and throughout the entire project. Uh, just seeing, you know, exactly what they are looking at from a, from a budgetary standpoint. Uh, the initial contract negotiations will be for pre-construction only.
uh, the full, uh, GMP or guaranteed maximum price contract will not be executed until the bid phase of the project, which will be sometime in, in 2028. Um, so the initial, uh, kind of negotiation that we'll have to do with the selected, uh, construction managers for pre-construction, it's usually a pretty, uh, usually a pretty simple and straightforward negotiation for pre-construction. Um, the firms will outline
You know, everything that they plan to do in Pre construction, and it's pretty typical to see all of the construction managers, um, you know, give a discount, uh, sort of say, they know that the Pre construction budgets are typically. Um, you know, fairly small with limited scope. Um, so they, they try to meet those, you know, that budget. Um, knowing that the real work comes through the construction phase of the project.
Any questions on kind of the two different phases? All right. Just looking at our schedule, the prequalification timeline is on the left. These are just the high-level kind of milestones. So, on the 25th is when we're intending to issue advertising. This is when the submissions are actually made to the Central Register.
We'll work with Medford's procurement office for the combines and newspaper ad postings. The intent is to have those issued on the 25th so that they appear in all of the publications on July 1st. That is when the firms will reach out to left field requesting the RFQ. We'll distribute to anybody that requests it.
They have just over a week to review the initial RFQ and then issue any questions that they may have. We'll respond to those within a week. Those are usually just clarifications if there are any, but given that the RFQ is usually a bit more straightforward than the actual RFP for the proposals, they're usually pretty minor.
and we anticipate the statements of qualifications to be due on July 24th, so about six weeks from now is when we'll see the first submissions from the interested firms. From the 25th through August 11th, the pre-qualification subcommittee will review the SOQs,
and with the anticipation on the 14th to notify the firms that have been pre-qualified. After the pre-qualification, we'll go into the CMR process. Can I just ask a question about that first block? Yep. In that 725 to 811 time frame, when we say we're going to do the SOQ review, what does that entail?
So the SOQ packages will come with a lot of kind of standard information like their DCAM certificate. So a lot of the information, sorry, I'm getting a call and I can't mute it. A lot of the documents in the SOQs are documents that left field will confirm that they have provided like their DCAM
Certificate there's nothing really to review there for the subcommittee per se. The, the big review from the subcommittee will revolve around the actual evaluation criteria and I'll pull up the RFQ shortly and just kind of walk through that section and kind of. Uh, you know, we can, we can see how those criteria are currently spelled out and just talk about kind of the.
review process and how we'll do that. I will create an RFQ matrix, review matrix that the subcommittee can use. Usually it's a, you know, not advantageous, advantageous, most advantageous. This phase does not come with an actual number scoring. The numbered scoring is in the RFP or in the actual proposals.
uh, there that is spelt out in, um, in mass general law is a base out of a hundred points. Um, so that is something that we'll, um, we'll pull together, uh, to make sure that they are, uh, to make sure that the committee knows exactly what sections need to be most closely reviewed. Uh, because like I said, a lot of it is really going to be on left field side just to confirm like, yes, they have submitted this, um,
And typically, sorry, Matt, at that stage, as part of that review matrix that first pass that left field provides, there are some notes on things and our observations of, you know, part, you know, making sure that they've checked the boxes, but also making some notes on some of the more nuanced or important parts of the qualifications packages.
Excuse me, Matt, have you reviewed this timeline with City Procurement already? I have not, no. ASAP, because they may question some of these dates. Okay, yeah, I will reach out to them. That was also what I intended to do before the end of the week, once we had this meeting, was reach out to them and make sure
You know, they have a couple of weeks to make sure that they've got the advertisements lined up. The last time I they weren't a half day on Friday. That's all. Okay. All right. Yep. I'll, I'll make sure I get something out to them. Uh, this afternoon, can you tell us, like, what does what role does our city procurement play in this process? So that that is, uh.
One of the questions I do have for them in terms of, um, you know, do they require all submissions to come through them? Uh, is it okay for them to come through left field, especially the electronic submissions? Um, so they don't need to play a role unless, uh, unless they. I guess want to, or per Medford. Procurement laws want, uh, need to control that process.
uh, we've seen it done kind of both ways. So, um, you know, typically we would say, try to keep it through left field. Um, just so it's a, it's a bit cleaner since we'll be the ones distributing documents and, um, you know, performing kind of the bulk of the review on, um, kind of the mandatory documents that I had mentioned earlier. Um,
So that was one of the questions I did have, was what kind of involvement does Medford Procurement need to have? And if none, then I think that that's okay. But I'll just want to make sure that they don't have any requirement that submissions need to go through them. You have to talk to the Chief Procurement Officer.
Through the other projects I've worked on, they have run the bids through their net direct system and done all that, but. I'd refer to them, so. Okay, and do you have a. Do you have a preference on whether we. Like, suggest that left field run point on this or that city procurement does. You asking me? Yeah, like, do we have a preference that Matt should communicate.
I don't have a personal preference. It's really going to be per college chief procurement officer, whether she'd allow it or not. Okay. Yeah. And so Matt, if you'll copy me on those correspondences, that would be great. Yeah. And so in this 725 to 811, I know there's like, we're reviewing a lot of paperwork. Are we meeting what, what is like, what is this team doing besides like waiting for you all to vet the paperwork? So I do have another.
I can skip ahead to that slide. I do have another, our next meeting scheduled for 7-13 at the moment. And again, we can go through these dates and make sure they work for all of the pre-qualification members. At that meeting, I'll have the full matrix. I'll certainly distribute it before then, but this will be before we receive the actual SOQs.
we can talk about, you know, the actual review process a bit more in a bit more detail so that when we do receive the SOQs, everybody can kind of go back, review on their own, fill out their matrix, fill out the matrix. And then when we meet again on August 3rd, that will be to actually review the statements of qualification and finalize which firms we see as pre-qualified.
So, we have 2 other meetings around the RFQs around the RFQ process to review the same qualifications in this time period. So that that was my intent right now. Okay.
Uh, the 1st date works for me fine. Um, the 2nd date, I cannot be in person. And so if we want to have that meeting in person, if we could perhaps do it on July 31st. That would be better for me. I don't know if everyone else is able to. If we're making an assumption that the future meetings will be in person. Um, I don't know how those dates work for everyone else.
I would have a conflict on 8-3. Say that again, Ken? I'd have a conflict on 8-3. Okay. Brian? Well, I was just looking. Yeah, 8-3 may be tough for me too, but I would have to do a little more consultation to figure it out for sure if things can move around.
Well, sounds like a 3 is difficult for a few people. So, it sounds like we will be moving that 1 anyways. 731 does that work for folks. Yes, I think those are all fine for me. Friday.
Are we under the assumption that we should all be in-person for this particular type of thing? Yes. Yeah, I think the 731 one will be important to have in-person. Okay. I think the one on the 13th could be remote. Again, we'll have questions on the RFQ and we'll have the matrix to review, but we won't have SOQs and be reviewing anything.
uh, at that point, just preparing for, for the review. So the 3rd, I think the 713 meeting could be, could be remote if that is easier. Uh, but the 731, uh, with the more detailed discussion on the SOQs in person, I think is best. I'll just say that we can make it work. Okay.
9, 7, you said is is we have a conflict. Oh, it's a Labor Day. Okay. Sorry, Matt, we, we sort of dove into that bullet. If you want to go back to your, like, chart. So that we can talk about yeah.
We jumped from the left into that other slide. So do you want to talk about the proposal timeline? Yeah. Yeah, the proposals, yeah, once we notify the pre-qualified firms on August 14, when we notify them, we will also send them the request for proposal. There's no advertising or anything needed for that. It's just a continuation of the process. Once people are qualified, they get the RFP.
During that process, we will have a mandatory site walk at Medford so that everybody that's interested can see the site, walk through the school, really kind of get a sense of the logistics and the challenges that they're going to face. So I think that's a super critical one. We typically do make that mandatory just
We want people that are serious and really interested in going after this project. After that walkthrough, everyone can submit questions for the RFP, whether it's related to the actual document or questions they may come up with during the walkthrough. We'll have about a week to respond to those questions. And then the actual proposals will be due on September 4th.
From there, that should be from the 4th to the 21st, is when the selection committee will review the proposals. We will hold the pricing proposals during this first part of the review, just so that we can look at the proposals and look at it, you know, from a qualifications and experience standpoint first. It's typical to look at the
non-pricing proposals, see how the firms stack up against each other, and then after the interviews, we'll take a look at the pricing proposals as well, and those are kind of the three separate categories that we'll have to rank them on, you know, their proposal, their interview, and then their pricing proposal. So that will be the kind of general
have reviewed the proposals to set up the interviews. Right now, we're anticipating for the end of September with a follow-on meeting of this committee. We can either, depending on the timing of those interviews, I have in the past held executive session following the interviews so that the selection committee can review and discuss the final ranking while everything is still kind of fresh in our minds.
So between the 28th and the 29th, I think it will be critical for us to kind of finalize that ranking. I have proposed a meeting with the building committee at some point in October, early October. We still need to finalize what date that will be. But at that meeting, we would review the ranking of the construction manager firms and ask the building committee
you know, to proceed with negotiations with the top-rank firm. Again, those negotiations are usually fairly quick and pretty easy to get through for the pre-construction services. And once we have that negotiation, we will issue a notice to proceed while the paperwork is kind of circulating for signatures so that they can, you know, get their heads into the project.
Uh, through the month of October, that's that's when we'll be seeing the final, uh, you know, space, uh, recommendations from the building committee on the 14th. So it'll be good to have them involved to to see that process. Uh, and then they'll, um, you know. Be able to weigh in heavily with on logistics and phasing, which is going to be a very critical part of this project.
So that's what we're looking at pretty much from now until we issue a notice to proceed in early October. But for the sake of this meeting, we'll focus really just on the qualification pieces since we won't be issuing the RFP until August. So we have some time to finalize that document and review that.
I had sent out an email last week when I issued the draft of the RFQ with just some of the pages to take a look at. The general information section is really just confirming if this committee wants any hard copies. A lot of these submissions have gone fully electronic,
If we want to request our copies, we certainly can do so. Before we dive into the CMR, can we look at the detailed schedule that's on the next page? I think I just want to make sure that the subsequent dates for meetings work for everybody here before we proceed. Actually, I'd like to jump in two things.
So I found out I'm going to be on a plane on the 13th, on July 13th. I thought it was in the evening, but it's actually in the morning. So that throws a wrench in for me on the 13th, the first meeting. Second, Matt, left field, Matt, I don't think I got, and I'm actually quite positive, I got your email with any of the information on this.
And also because the calendar invite didn't come through. So I think somehow I got dropped on the original. And they should be going to your Medford School Building Committee email. Ah, OK. That's exactly why, which I never check. Usually everything comes through my work email. But I can.
Um, bring that back and forth. I haven't had to use that recently. So I'm just not in the habit of checking. Okay, yeah, that's usually where I send all documents just to keep everything, you know, within. Kind of city Medford. Yep.
All right. And Brian, just like you are on copy, I can see that. So if you look in your Medford inbox, I think you'll see all of the docs. But the reason we want you to be operating in there is because from an open meeting law perspective, if you get into a habit of using your personal email records requests, like sort of have the right to reach into your personal email.
As well, so if you stick with, like, your city of Medford, your public schools, email address for all your stuff, like, it is a safer bet for you personally. In an event of, like, somebody having questions, like, open meeting questions. Perfect. Thank you. Yeah, no problem.
So 7.13, Brian, would 7.14 be better or? So I'll be, I mean, I can make it work. I can make anything work simply because, you know, this is, I know this is important. Let me jump up. I'm going to be flying into Western Canada. So I'll be, you know, I can do anything from anywhere. It's just I won't be in person if that's
And I think for this 1st meeting, it sounds like that's okay. That's right. Yep. So, is there a, because it sounds like you'll be on West coast time. Is there is there a time of day that maybe we can coalesce around for this so that. We're not blowing up Brian's whole day. Yeah, I mean, I'll get up at 4 am right again. I can, I can kind of work, you know, obviously this is a bigger group than just me, but if we are.
Uh, doing, you know, what was this an 11 a.m. meeting if it were in that zone, I can make that work. Obviously, um, if it's evening, that's fine. Matt, are you expecting to, to do these sort of working hour, uh, meetings in, in general? Uh, I'm, I'm pretty flexible. You know, I typically do kind of defer to what works for, for all of the,
You know, the district members, um, just because your. Schedules are, um. You have normal day job, so, um, you know, I want to be sensitive to that. And so if evenings work better, I'm totally flexible for that. Um, but.
Yeah, I'm, I'm fine. Again, if, if we sort of have a, you know, cross the board, if this is like an 11 AM type of meeting, typically I'll just make it work. That's fine. And Libby, what about you in terms of like preference for things during the day or later in the day? Either is fine for a virtual meeting, you know, either one is totally fine in person.
Evenings are easier because I'm not, you know, I'll be back in Medford, but, you know, on a certain day, I can be there in person to just as long as there's a heads up. So, if we were to look at 714 at 11 am, does that work for everyone here? We'll have to check with Dr Lucy, but.
That that would steer us clear of that and then it sounds like on 731 731. Although if we're going to meet in the evening, we may not want to do that on. Friday in the evening, so I don't know.
If if you all have any, like, thoughts about. The time of that meeting, and if we prefer the evening, Libby, are you thinking like, 5 or 4, 6, that's the 31st. Yes, I work from home on Fridays. So, um, I could do more easily. Um, during the day, if it's better for everybody, I'll be 3. Yeah, yeah, I think.
I think I can make that work as well. Great. And so then, Matt, when we get into the proposals. On 824, we would be meeting the same kind of same thing to talk about the.
the review matrix, questions, et cetera. That is the first day, no, that is not the first day of students returning, of teachers returning, Ken, right? It's the following week? Correct. That's the induction week, but that doesn't start until like Tuesday. Okay, so Monday would be okay from a school perspective. Okay. Against Suzanne, but yeah. Yeah, I think I'm pretty flexible on the 24th.
Um, I don't know Brian and Libby if that works for you. That 1 sounds like it could be zoom if we wanted it to be. That's Monday, August 24th, right? Yeah, I think that's fine for me. I think I leave on Tuesday, the 25th. so that would be 24th is ideal. Perfect. And I see I'm good there as well. The 24th. Okay, do we want to shoot for 11? am we'll check we have to check all these with Suzanne, but.
Yeah, sure. Okay. And then, uh, on 9, 7, we are looking at actual proposals. So that would be the, what we need to find there is a date and time for an in person meeting. Is that right? Yep. Correct. And that's Labor Day, right? Yeah. 9, 7 does not work. So.
I'm pretty flexible that whole week, maybe with the exception of Friday. Um, does anybody else have any I know we're back to school at that point can. Yeah, Wednesdays are Wednesday 10 thirties bags. I have the weekly. McLean Andrews meeting. Okay, and then we have a 1 PM meeting. Typically that day, but other stuff can move.
And this would probably be like a 4 or 5 PM meeting. Is that what we're thinking? Yeah, if this is an in-person one, then yeah, I think evenings sounded like they were better.
Brian and Libby, do you have any preferences? We're so far out that my schedule is wide open at this point. I mean, I can be around Tuesdays, Fridays during the day more easily if it works better to not do evenings. But I mean, I'm pretty wide open that week. For me, I would say, Jenny, I'm kind of like you. I like things clustered in the middle of the week. We tend to travel a lot. And sometimes we leave early on Fridays. Yeah. OK.
So that's, you know, again, like that sort of Tuesday to Thursday is ideal. But it doesn't mean, again, I don't have anything specific planned, so we can adjust if necessary. My only blackout that week is I just can't do Wednesday morning. But anything else? We did like a four o'clock start. It sounds like Tuesday, Wednesday, or Thursday are available. Yeah.
Okay, we can just check with Suzanne and pick 1 of those dates. And then 922. This will be the. Um, yeah, this will finalize the ranking of the of the non. Tracing proposals.
So would a four o'clock start work for folks on 922? Yep. We have a building committee meeting that week, but right now it's on Monday, which is Yom Kippur. So that might move to Tuesday. Yeah, I've been messing around with all of those dates, so we're not interfering with various calendars. So if we'd lock this in, I will feed it back to the other calendar. Sure. That should be fine for me too.
Yep, that works for me. 922 or. I mean, 920. 922 yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Yeah, right now I have a 29th for.
CM interviews. How long are the interviews, Matt, usually? Usually we'll get, I would say roughly like 45 minutes. You know, you do like a 20 minute presentation, you know, and a 30 minute Q&A is usually pretty typical. And then, you know, we'll have 15 minutes kind of between each of the interviews if we schedule them on the hour and kind of stick to that.
Um, but, uh, we've seen, you know, we've, we've seen other, you know, people do longer interviews, shorter interviews. Like, it is really kind of up to, um, to what we want. So, you know, if we want to do a longer, you know, allow them to do a longer presentation, uh, we can bump, you know, bump it up to a full hour. Um, but pretty, pretty flexible. Sorry, I was gonna get my calendar updated here.
You're asking what the length of the interviews? Yeah. Like if when we're interviewing CM firms, what should, what are, where are you thinking like we should be in terms of timing expectations? This just feels like a really big decision. So, but I don't know what that means because I've never done this before. Yeah. I've never made the decision myself. I mean, but I assumed there would be guidance, but I mean, I would expect they, they give a presentation for,
I don't know, half an hour, 40 minutes, and then there's some amount of time for Q&A. Yeah, we did an hour at least total. Yeah, it was at least a 30-minute presentation for them, and that was tight. Yeah, I mean, I've actually never, I don't think I've ever sat in on a CM interview, but the ones that we do usually are 40 minutes.
Sorry, you can break them up over a couple of days as well. If you want the longer presentations, because I think.
The good thing, I think, about the interviews specifically, one, you're learning about the team and how they might fit into our team, our wider team, including the Medford folks. And then the other thing is you learn a lot about the project itself through the lens of a number of different builders. So we're also taking in a lot of information on how different CMs would approach your project.
So I think for this project in particular, a longer interview would make a lot of sense. And so breaking it up maybe over a couple of days, of course, we won't know exactly how many firms we're getting, but so we can kind of fine tune that. But if we, I think, you know, a lot, two days for this and on the second day, we stay and deliberate and, you know, do the final ranking after the second day of interviews, I think makes a lot of sense here.
I think that makes sense. If we somehow get down to three firms, you know, maybe we can squeeze them into a day if people's schedules allow, but, you know, it's going to be hard. I mean, leave some space in between for. We'll know more once we get to the qualification process, who will qualify, but then some may not submit. Right. Yeah. Right. It is entirely possible that, you know, if a CM firm, you know, doesn't think that they can actually support the project, they may not submit a proposal.
Um, so, yes, that that is a possibility. Um. If we, if firms do submit a proposal, we have to interview them. That is a part of master law. So. So we will, we're not shortlisting. The shortlisting is really through, like, the Pre qualification process. So we've already said they're qualified. So correct. Yeah, they get to decide if they want to be interviewed basically. Correct. Yep. Got it.
And what should we expect, like, how. How many proposals do you think is. Likely, I would say this, this project is large, so we might wind up getting.
a handful of maybe five or six, I would say, and maybe a couple of joint ventures thrown in. It really comes down to who can handle the size of the project bonding-wise, but the joint ventures will open it up to following partnerships. Yeah, I think, yeah, there's probably... I don't think a more than five company, that would be big enough. Yeah. Yeah.
I see, yeah, two, three firms maybe submitting proposals by themselves. And yeah, I could see a couple of joint ventures as well. But yeah, I think Jen's right, probably between five and six is what we'll see. And depending on the composition of those teams, we can determine if we find them qualified or not. Why don't we at least
Just count on an hour per and once the prequels are sorted through, if we need to add an extra day or stretch it out, does that make sense? Yeah. Or if we want to stretch them to 90 minutes or something, there's two in a day. You can easily do that. Yeah. I think we'll have a better idea once the prequels are. Yep. Maybe we block the 29th and 30th from like four on. Yeah.
Okay, yeah, easily. Okay, great. There's a lot of calendar Tetris going on to set the schedule too. So that's why I just want to make sure we have the right timing for for this to be thorough. And then we would do the ranking at the end of day 2. Yeah.
And I think we could be surprised either way. It may boil down to just a few firms. And we might be surprised, depending on the market, that it's way more than we expected. We were surprised the architects a bit also. We'll see. Yeah, true. I actually thought it would be more. I did too. Yeah. OK.
And yeah, we, I'll get back to you about that date. Yep. Yeah, that, that will have to get coordinated with, with the other building committee meetings. Um, but yeah, some, some time in that 1st week, I think the 5th is the Wednesday. Um, I know we've been holding some building committee meetings on Wednesdays when Mondays don't work. So that's why I threw that in there. Um, the 5th is a Monday. Yep.
Yeah, and it conflicts with our so it's going to move. So I will, I'll take that action item to figure that part out. Now that we have the rest. Okay. Hold on just 1 2nd, Matt, before you move on and that will use them calendar invites to everybody for these times so that we can. Yep, I'll have them locked in.
All righty. I am going to take a quick screen share because I don't think this will disappear when I move the screen.
Can I ask a question? The MSBA doesn't, other than dictating the process, they're not weighing in on how we select RCM at all? Nope. It's entirely different body. Yep. As long as, you know, we, you know, when we submit schematic design and have, you know, the OIG approval,
That's, you know, they just want to make sure that we've gone through all the necessary steps to actually procure a CM at risk. Oh. Okay. I think all of these are gonna. Matt, it's okay. I'm sorry.
Yeah. So. We have 9 minutes left. And I think we have to go through any sort of feedback and comments that we have on the. RQ draft is that right? Yes.
Yeah, and I did receive, um, I'll actually pull up the. The actual RFQ, so we can look at the actual. Sections and then from a, like, you asked a question earlier and I see it was like, 1 of the questions on page 2 and that 1st section, um, the question the question you asked was, like, do we want paper copies or do we want. Virtual, like, just electronic, um, and.
I would prefer to have a hard copy. I think it's a little bit easier for people to be able to, like, be in meetings and moving around, but I don't know how the rest of the group feels. I'm fine either way. Yeah, either one's fine. If we're getting hard copies, it is nice to have them physically.
Same here, yeah, either way, but. I feel bad because we hate printing them, but we don't print them anymore, but. It is nice. It was nice for the. It was extremely helpful. Yeah. Yeah. Okay, so we'll make sure there's enough hard copies for everyone on the committee.
Other than that, I think the other parts of. This page 2 was really they're really questions for procurement. Is that right? Matt? Yes, yep, which I'll follow up with them on. Yeah, it's just confirming. Uh, yeah, how how they want to handle it. I know when we did the designer, everything went through. Left field, um, so I'll, uh, I'll double check. And make sure that that's still the intent, uh, and okay, moving forward for this.
Is 5 the right number of hard copies? I put 5 for the district members. I won't need one. Matt Rice, do you want one? He was texting me that he's having a hard time getting his mic to work, I think. Oh. I'll confirm with him, but I'll get at least 5 or 6.
Uh, yeah, 5, 5, at least for the, for the Medford members. And if Matt wants 1, I'll bump it up, but I, I do not want 1. I don't need more paperwork and the trunk of my car. When you talk to procurement, I think ideally those copies, the hard copies could be delivered to the high school so that they're a little easier for us to distribute and field.
get if they have to go to city hall, that's fine. Um, but I think expressing a preference to procurement would be, um, would be helpful if they're okay with that. Okay. If you want to put my name, cause if you put Matt Galino, God knows the point. And Matt Rice has confirmed that he is good with the digital version only. Okay. Okay.
Procurements okay with that. Yeah. Yep. Great same thing. I'll just kind of confirm if they want to have any sort of project contract number. It's kind of up to the procurement team. If they want a specific number, but. And then these numbers will all of these facts and figures will be updated with 2.2. is that right?
Yep, yeah, that that is what I was working on this morning. So, they should start, uh, they should be reflecting. Um, the, the C2 2 options. Um, the description that I already had in here. Uh, you know, the project history is just a quick summary of of the high school, which is really from, you know, what you guys had provided in your.
Some comments about the project description. Go ahead, Libby. No, you go first. Maybe it's the same thing.
Um, I think the 1st thing is, and I've mentioned this to you all before, but the city of Medford is pursuing a project labor agreement. So that has to be reflected and noticed in this. CMR application, right? In some way, it's they have not finished. There's a study or something that has to happen. There are things that have not been completed, but there has to be like, I.
I believe what I've been told is that there has to be some reference of that possibility in this before it goes out. Hopefully, you-all can take that on and figure out exactly what that reference needs to look like. You're talking about the standard, the prevailing wage ordinance one? No, it's called a project labor agreement and it's specific to the project.
Um, so that was 1 comment. Um, the 2nd comment, um, was that the project history, uh, was clearly copied out of the, but the language doesn't belong here anymore. Like, we're not submitting an any longer. Right? So that part needs to be updated to not be talking about. We're submitting an like, we did that. We are moving on.
So that has to be reframed on the top of page 4. The other thing that I think is important in this section, and it's actually like, it comes up. A lot in the community, like, this building was built for.
You know, however, many thousands of students, right? And so why is it? Why is it so big? Well, 1 of the things that has happened over the course of time is that it did start as the building just for, like, 9 to 12 over time, though, we have added.
Things right to the building, like the registration center central expanded central office kids corner. Like, none of those things were there in 1970 when the building opened, but they are part of.
like the evolution of the building. So I think that should be reflected here somehow that like, yes, we started as like, it started as a building and it has, as the, as the student population has changed, all kinds of things have happened and decisions have been made to like, sort of bring us to where we are today. And I don't think that's particularly well reflected in the project history at the moment. Um, and I think it would need to be okay.
Um, my other comments, um, in this section are about, um. The, the phrasing and the language about lead be 5 silver. Like, I, I know that's the minimum from an perspective, but that. That is not the stated goal of this project. So I just want that. Language to precisely line up with, like, where we are going, like, we, the school committee issued like.
A goal there, and we have not taken any formal votes to change it. Although I know that's in progress. So I'd like that language to. Be modified in some way to acknowledge. Like, our continued consistent intent.
which may change, but as of right now, like there, there is, there is something on the table that is not exactly what this says. So, um, that needs to be updated. Um, I think in the, like the work includes section, um, we also need to make reference to the possible secondary egress, whether that will happen or not is still very much, um, up for,
Discussion and may not happen, but I think it is substantial and kind of belongs in here. And then in number 3, there's reference to modular classrooms, and we did just pick an option that is free of modular classrooms. So that needs to be. Updated those are my comments on that. Section Libby, did you have others? You got mine.
Oh, yeah, I did. Yeah. And I did take out the, um, modular, uh, modular reference this morning. So that, that is gone. Is that duration right? Uh, I'll double check as well. Uh, I am still actively going through and updating these, but I will, I will double check and make sure that the durations, uh, align with, with the schedule that's outlined up above.
I'll just circle back to the lead question. Jenny, do you think it should say platinum still or just, I mean, it says, you know, minimum silver, but our goal is gold. I know we've talked about reducing the goal to gold from platinum, but that's what sort of hasn't been officially decided. Do you think it should say platinum at the moment? Just say, you know, that's the goal and we can always change it.
It's good. I think it's fine to say, like. The school committee, like, the project began with an intention to do this, given that the. You know, whatever there's a new version out the project is exploring a modified goal of this, but has not been decided and the minimum is. Whatever it is, like, I think it's fine to just say.
The truth where we are, but make sure it's it's very clear. We're not just going for the bare minimum. Yeah. I think I can add in add in the majors, add in the language from the school committee discussion about leave the. For platinum and, um. Just make a reference.
Matt Rice is texting that currently the target that needs to be ratified by SBC is LEAD V5 gold, which seems to be the equivalent of LEAD V4. And that just hasn't happened yet, so we should make that clear so that if that does not happen, there are no surprises. Absolutely. OK.
I can get rid of. Okay. And I know we're over time, so. I need a little more time to read through the next 2 sections. For me personally, so Matt, I will send you any other comments I have, but I don't know if anyone had anyone else had comments about the next section, which is our, which is like the scope of services right on page. Yeah.
I had sent you, Matt, some notes about that. Yep, I did. Yep, I did. I did see your comments, so I'll go through those today and incorporate those as well. There were comments about adding in about project safety, about site security, about our communication. Yep. Yep, the about our communication is a good one for sure. So yeah, I'll definitely go through and make sure those comments are addressed.
And then page 14 C, you would had a 10 month after substantial completion commitment. I wasn't sure if that was enough given substantial completion will be likely. I don't know what substantial completion when we're moving the building or when the whole site work is done. Because I know we'll continue to work on the site for almost another year probably. I don't know if that was substantial completion when that was done or when the building is moved into.
It's usually the building portion of it, but also we, you know, you can also make it clearer and reference both. Yeah, so you just got to tweak that so that, you know, it's not just, there's still a lot more work after that. And then 10 months after the whole project is done. Yep.
And if everybody that sends Matt any comments can copy me just in case with Matt's impending nuptials so that I can make sure that the next couple of weeks, if anything changes or comes up, I'm copied. And then just, I've got a meeting in another 10 minutes and I'm the host of the meeting. On the evaluation criteria, aren't we required to have all of our criteria listed in this?
You know, we're going to say highly advantageous, advantageous, not advantageous, you know. Yep. All the standards because. Yeah, this is the evaluation criteria section. Yeah, that's the minimum, but you've got the minimum criteria there. Which I think at least 1 project within the last 10 years of this total construction cost is a problem. Because there haven't been that many.
Correct. Yeah. And I think that's something that, um, that when I issue this to the, to the building committee and receive comments from them as well as is one thing that we'll have to address is maybe not dollar value, but, you know, size, uh, a square footage. Uh, yep. So I can clarify, clarify that. And, and I think it's something that, that, um,
you know, we may want to talk about, too, in terms of, you know, there aren't a lot of other high school projects in Massachusetts that are this size. So do we want to entertain, you know, higher education facilities that maybe are large and have similarities to, you know, to Medford High School? There is a way that we can, you know, we can kind of adjust what we consider as a similar project, as long as we are doing that equally across all
all of the applications. So that's just something we'll have to consider between now and when we get proposals is how kind of stringent and strict. Sorry, Matt, that's not right. You have to have the minimum criteria correct in this document, because you cannot waive a minimum criteria. Correct. Yeah, no, that's kind of what I'm saying. Before this is issued, we will make sure that we have
You know, clarity on exactly what, um, you know, similar type construction project means. Yeah, I mean, I, I would think more about the value of criteria in the next section. We don't have any listed. I think we're supposed to have that up front.
Yeah, I'll take, I'm going to be going through this again today with updating comments and I'll certainly make sure that any numerical rankings are clear. And Libby, did you have any other comments based on what you reviewed?
I was just going to go back to speaking of the project types. I mean, I think it would be fine to consider other non-public K-12 projects if it was a very large, complicated public university project or huge health care. But there's a lot of complications that it shows somebody can handle the work. A small project wouldn't be the same. But I think I don't want to limit us yet. It would need to be public.
I think I agree public public work, I think, and yeah, there's so few project typologies that are. Entail this many types of construction in this many. Spaces, I'd be shocked if there was anybody that has. You know, meets the criteria that hasn't done a big public school. Yes, my other comment on that was is.
Is having done 3 of these enough, like, that doesn't seem like they're going to be able to. Well, that's the minimum criteria that would get them to us to be able to review as a proposal, let them submit a proposal. Yeah, I think that's okay. Okay. And to Ken's point, that just allows us to look at them and consider them.
Okay, because 3 projects, the sizes is that's a lot. You can have 1 of the evaluative criteria say, okay. 3 is, you know. Not advantageous 3 to 5 is advantageous 5 to 10 is highly advantageous that way. Yep. Because it's a CMR project. With a total construction costs in a similar amount, right? So it's not just.
They did a CMRS project, but they've done three of a similar size. Yep. Yeah, and I'll mess around with the- How does similar size work in our context? How do we define similar? Yeah, I think it's really going to be from a size and complexity standpoint, just knowing that not many or really anyone is going to have
You know, especially a high school project of of this dollar value, uh, just with how pricing has increased over the years. So, um. I think is there like, uh, a square footage minimum. That we should be articulating like, this feels like super squishy.
And cutting it to cost is hard because if it was done three years ago, it could be significantly less expensive, but still as complicated and as large. Half the price. Yeah. Exactly. I think, Jenny, I think it sort of wants to be squishy because I think what Matt Galino is getting at is that this is sort of, this is a kind of a unicorn project. And we really need to consider, I think, cast a fairly large net, wide net.
Because I just think that it's going to be tough to find somebody that's spot on with this, with a ton of experience building this exact project. Yeah, my fear with adding in like specificity like that is, you know, people be like, you know, 550 or 600,000 square foot building, like we haven't done one of those. You know, or we haven't done three of those. You know, we're not even gonna bother, you know, but they may maybe had a 500
you know, 1000 square foot building, you know, so the similar is really kind of what we need, what this committee will have to kind of agree upon and having it a bit squishy does give us that flexibility to, to kind of make that determination. Um, if we start to put very, very specific criteria, my, my fear is that, you know, we'll just kind of push out interested firms.
and not give us the ability to evaluate them apples to apples when we receive them. What's your recommendation? I think we all agree, we don't want to push people out, but what's the recommendation? I think the recommendation is going to be more based off of size, square footage. What's the number?
So Matt Rice is texting me because he still can't get through his mic. He's saying he'll send over the Lexington CMR FQ because that is, they had similar discussions with that group around size and complexity for the similar project scope. Great. Okay. Yeah. And I, and I have been talking with Kevin Sullivan, who is working on Brockton. So I will take a look at their,
RFQ as well and see if they had, you know, anything. Um, since they are a very large project as well. So, I think we are, like, kind of running out of time here and. I, um, I guess 2 things 1 is it's our expectation that we're going to get an authorization from the building committee. On next Wednesday. To proceed, and this is not ready. So.
how do we go from here to ready and give the building committee adequate time to review this? My, my intent is still to update this and get it out to the full committee tomorrow. Um, and we never gave them the heads up that we talked about that this was coming. Did we? Uh,
I mean, I've been referencing it and giving updates to it in our weekly recap and kind of giving the overall schedule and what the game plan is. We talked about sending an email saying, as a heads up, you should expect this thing on this day so that you can review it, so that you can be prepared to provide an approval. And that didn't go out.
I don't know. It went out in the weekly recap, Jenny. That's exactly what we talked about last week, that I would highlight those things in the weekly recap. And that's what I did. It was in the email or in the attachment? Yes, the attachment. OK. I don't think we should assume people have read that. But I think more importantly, if we are going to send them something, we have to figure out
the messaging because this is not ready. Do we want to send it out to this group tomorrow, Matt, and then circle back? Do we need another meeting? I'm available next week. If we need another meeting of this group to be able to, for this group to make that recommendation next Thursday. If we post a meeting today, we can have a meeting
On Monday, we need to meet or can we do this by email? I don't know. Yeah, I mean, maybe that's a great question can so perhaps the better path forward is for everybody to provide their comments.
And this group to take a vote to authorize somebody to like, green light this. To the building committee, and that can be me, or it can be can. Can be the 2 of us, that's not a quorum, so that would be fine. Yeah, why don't Jenny and I do it? Yeah, that's so can somebody make that motion for me? So moved. Okay, so motion to.
Um, provide feedback via email and authorization to Ken and Jenny to give the final say, go to the, um, to send this to the building committee, um, by Ken and seconded by Libby. I'm going to call the roll. Um, Jenny Graham. Yes. Ken Lord. Yes. Libby Brown. Yes. Brian Hilliard. Yes. Matt Galino. Yes.
Matt Rice. He has texted I. And Dr. Galuski is absent. So 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 in the affirmative, 1 absent, the motion passes. OK. Is there a motion to adjourn? So moved. By Ken. Is there a second? Second. By Libby. I'll call the roll. Ken. Yes. Matt. Yes. Libby. Yes.
Brian yes, Jenny. Yes, sorry in the affirmative 1 absence the meeting is.