Test 1-2, test 1-2.
Number 10, 2024 Governance Committee. I'm calling this committee meeting to order.
We're meeting on paper 24468, resolution to discuss updates to the city charter, be it resolved by the Metro City Council that the Governance Committee discuss updates to the city charter, including creating a timeline for action and reviewing proposals of the Charter Study Committee once finalized.
Representatives of the Edward J Collins junior center for public management at Boston are invited to provide an overview of the charter review process and the next steps for the city council. Mr. Clerk may call the role. President bears. President. Vice President Collins counselor Lazaro.
present, seven present or five present, two joining us, or one joining us, and the meeting is called to order. Great. Before we start, do any councillors have comments or questions about this paper, about Charter Review? I see President Behrs on Zoom, and I recognize President Behrs.
Thank you, Chair Seng. Just wanted to thank the Collins Center representatives for being there in person. Apologies that I can't join you there tonight. I'm really excited to hear from the Collins Center what the next steps are for the council to take action on the proposals and the framework of the Charter Study Committee. I know that we haven't received that yet, so we won't be discussing their proposals and specifics, but more of what the timeline will look like in the new year for us to consider that.
And, you know, I have a few questions after we hear from them, but in general, I'm excited to work with my colleagues on this committee to consider, you know, any amendments to the proposals from the study committee. And then my personal preference, I think, would be to hopefully report something out by the end of the spring to put on the ballot in November that would go. And then if the voters were to approve it, it would go into effect
after the 2027 or for the 2027 election. So still a ways away from this going into effect, but really excited and hopeful and looking forward to working with my colleagues over the next few months on finalizing a proposal and getting that before the voters. Thank you. Thank you, President Bares.
Fellow Councillors, have any preliminary questions, comments, remarks? Councillor Zara.
I just want to echo what President Behrs was saying, and I'm really excited about getting started and looking forward to taking what the committee discussed and what the Collins Center has to report and moving forward.
and getting going. This is really exciting work. This is something that we've been talking about for a long time and what many of us talked about during our campaigns as well. So this is very exciting. So I'm excited to get going. Thank you, Councilor Collins, Councilor Zara. The mic system is new, so we're all still learning the ins and outs of turning stuff on and off. Do any other councilors have any comments before we invite the call-in center up?
doesn't seem like it. Um, I just wanted to thank you all, uh, for, for being here at this meeting, um, for being willing to, to have this conversation with us and giving us a better idea of where the city council fits in, uh, into the, uh, charter review process.