We're going to call the meeting to order. The next item on the agenda is the approval of the minutes of the meeting.
to provide updates on the minute meetings, if there's been any changes to the minute meetings. Have there been any changes? No, there haven't been any changes to the meeting minutes. Okay, so if there's no edits to the minutes, I would like to request a motion to approve the meeting minutes from September 4th, 2024. Second.
One for me. I'll approve. I'll accept. We have to do a roll call if we have anyone. Is there anyone of our members who is online? No. Oh, OK. Then we're good. Yes. Do I need to do a roll call? Can I just say? You don't have to. Yeah. If we're all here in the room, then we can just raise our hand. We'll all accept.
Bye.
Thank you. I'll get better at this as we go along. It's all good. It's my fault. We'll get better. We're all friends here, right? All right, so next on the agenda is the Working Groups and Updates Declaration of Trust. Kayla will provide us with a draft and comments. Thank you for doing this, Kayla.
Um, so I finished the draft, and I had a couple questions as we went through, but if you want to just go through each, or, you know, just scroll through and then, and just questions on them, feel free to go as we go along. And I think, you know, I am not an expert in this, but I'll try to answer any questions that we had going through. It's great reading the other trusts, kind of try to like know some, and then really just use the ordinance as a
I just try to kind of limit it to that. And that is why some of the questions is going to be about whether we feel comfortable expanding anything from the ordinance. We want to just keep it exactly what the ordinance says. So just the explanation, title, and address, purpose of the trust, again, just lifted it directly from the ordinance. If you want to expand it into a more substantive paragraph, we can.
place to start. The composition and identity of the board of trustees just talked about how many terms of office, how to deal with resignations or vacancies. So I said that anyone can resign by written notice signed by the trustee who's resigning and sent to the chair. If a vacancy shall occur, it should be filled in the same manner as the
making a trustee for the unexpired terms, basically like substitute a trustee in. Removal, there was a removal section in the ordinance and it just said this, which was any member can be removed by the mayor for cause after the opportunity of a hearing, which I wasn't sure if that was specific enough, a hearing in front of who, a hearing in front of what body, that was my own question there. So that might be something for the solicitor to,
If anyone else had any ideas about what would happen in removal? I don't know if the CPA have any removal causes in there. That's actually a really good question because we actually had a situation where we wanted to remove a member and we didn't know how to go about it. It was kind of clumsy. They finally just left of their own accord.
And so we tried to write some procedures that would help us to handle that situation if it ever arose again. And we never had the legal assistance to review that to make sure that what we drafted was legal.
And so, yeah, I feel like that's something that we'll have to handle if it ever comes to that. And I'm not sure if there's a best practice that we can draw from. Yeah. No, I have no idea. Yeah, I'd have to look, try to think about the City of Somerville's Affordable Housing Trust for the full declaration. I'll look to see if there is one.
but maybe putting examples of reasons. Well, I was thinking less about so much reasons and more about the process. I think that the kind of the due process is kind of what I'm thinking about here. Like for city employees, there's a process that's very clear about what happens and who hears it. So I think that's what I was wondering here is who would hear it. It just says the mayor kind of initiates it, and then there's a hearing by a party to be
So I think that's the weird part about it. Yeah. We didn't want to just follow the city employee process then. I'm sorry, what would you? No, I was thinking sort of along the same lines. It's like if somebody is being terminated for cause, they get notification of some sort of reasons. That's why I'm saying is there maybe like examples of violation of the social,
We just signed it. The social media. Thank you. The violation of the social media policy, a violation of the ethics or something like that, like those various reasons. And then figure out. I'm just trying to think, and then, yes, I agree that there needs to be something like some sort of like, who are we? Is it the city council that we that has the. Yes, I'm not too sure as well, but I could check with our
the council. And this might be a question to bring up again when the mayor is in the room because ultimately she might be the arbiter for how to deal with this situation. It's really complicated. When we dealt with it before, it was because that person's behavior was problematic and committee members felt threatened.
by being in the room with him. So we had like, we probably went about it all wrong at the time, but it was clear that something had to happen and the mayor was working with us to try to figure out what that was. Another trust had, if you miss like three or four meetings in a row, then there's kind of like an automatic bounce just for non-attendance.
Somerville had a conflict of interest clause, which I think was interesting, but then they didn't have what happens if you need to remove someone's clause. So it's kind of assumed that no one would need to be removed if, if only, but for the conflict of interest clause. So yeah, I think that's a good idea. I want to bring it up when the mayor joins us. The next article,
is very long, but kind of just lays out all the possible powers that the trustees will have as a collective whole. Again, a lot of this came from the ordinance. I don't think I really added that much to it. I did add one section. There was one provider that I think was probably added by the city council. It was
that the trust may not convey any real property having an area more than 7,500 square feet without the approval of the city council is how they wrote it. And then I wondered if we wanted to say if it's a unanimous city council or if it was a majority city council. So right now I've drafted as majority of the city council, but that is probably a question that we should refer back to council or city council itself.
It might be, I don't know about unanimous, but another option, it might be a super majority. It might be like a financial decision. But that would be helpful to know how many city councilors have to approve something. In number five, I just added consultants. Previously, it was just accountants, appraisers, lawyers, and I thought being a little broader there might be useful.
Another question, 13, the language used this word attribute, which I just couldn't figure out. So I questioned whether that meant arbitrage or if attribute is a different word for arbitration.
The master plan said state, no states. That's the attribute. And then at the end, I just added a couple of different ideas that I saw from other municipalities. One was to accept or create loans and grants, and that was in the Somerville article.
And then Lexington, I thought was interesting. They did say like they were going to be the body that made recommendations about how housing policy to their legislative body. Also help develop policy goals and then be the lottery agent for political housing in there. Yes, copy as well, which does come with some compensation. So that is also might be another place where we can get some income for the trust.
One caution about using Somerville as a model is that their trust was created before the state legislation, so it's not always consistent with what we're allowed to do today because ours was created under the state legislation and Somerville's was not.
In most situations, they were grandfathered in, but every once in a while, something comes along where the state says, no, you actually have to do what everybody else is doing. Actually, some of them ended up adopting the state. Oh, OK. They have a homeroom petition to try to go back to. Because they had more freedom before. Exactly. But again, some of these questions, question marks that you've left, maybe
are things that we really need to go over with the mayor and perhaps with legal counsel. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, probably. And we're talking about item 16. It wasn't really item 16, it was whether we were going to add any further items. I think this was really more just a point that things were different in other towns and if people feel comfortable with
going just by the plain statute ordinance as it was written. And I just disregard this section. If we're allowed to add more than what was in the ordinance, I feel like the more flexibility we give ourselves, the happier we'll be down the road. Most likely, yeah.
Are there other places in the section that they can do policy advocacy? Because I think I've been taking that question around myself and I think giving us the option to do it while we decide our action planning goals needs flexibility that I'm interested in, but I think it's something to consider as a group.
I don't think the list at this time really includes that. I would say that powers of the Board of Trustees, I mean, I think this is kind of supposed to be limited to legal actions, financial actions, things like that.
It would be relevant if we had to commission a study or get a consultant in order to reduce the advocacy. So I think, yeah, I would say right now it's probably a no to just plain advocacy. It was kind of like in Lexington, like they outsourced some of their housing policy to the Affordable Housing Trust Fund.
And I've seen communities where they use the Affordable Housing Trust kind of as a substitute for missing town staff to guide development projects and help them navigate the approval process.
So, or to recruit developers to build affordable housing projects and then so I don't know if we're precluded from doing things that are not in the powers. Maybe another question for the council. Does that include things as issuing?
No, I think so. If an RFP has been issued in relation to something like creating a new house or, you know, selling land to do X, Y, and Z, I think that would be fine. I think it's just, it would just be like, we believe in some sort of housing policy would be good overall, and we're going to advocate it to the city council or the public. I think that's kind of, that's probably not in here right now.
As trustees, you know, so majority of trustees may exercise all the powers. No trustee is going to be required to give any sort of like bond or guarantee. And then we don't need like a special action in order to have another party say like, okay, the Board of Trustees gave us this approval and we don't need any further court action. It's Article 5.
Article six is always one that everyone here should understand. So we are not liable for negligence or defaults of any trust or any employee. So if an appraiser makes a mistake or something like that, we're not liable for that. We're not liable for acts made in good faith and we're not liable on acts that were on vice counsel.
The other way you can do it is to basically say what you are liable for. Right now, this is all in the negative. You're not liable for x, y, z. You can also say that you are going to only be liable for things, and it's usually gross negligence or willful misconduct. So I've written it in the negative right now. It could be in the positive if people feel either way. I've seen it both ways, this kind of clause.
hate to be the ones that sound negative, but I like it being there. I'm not a negative person, but it really spells out what we are not liable for. I think that's sometimes just the way you're phrasing it. Like, we're not liable for this, but you are liable for that. It just sounds different. It's the same, but it does sound different to us.
Meetings of trustees, we said at least quarterly, and then special meetings can be called by the chair of the trust or any two trustees. So if there was a reason for a special meeting, that's how it would be done. Obviously, we have to abide by open meeting law. I said that we would annually elect officers, chair, vice chair, and treasurer, and that we can establish committees of need.
And then we can adopt rules and regulations, you know, on top of these, if we want to, about more specific things. These are kind of just, I'd say, more public-facing, you know, registered deed kind of level of things. Article 8 was about funds of the trust. Basically, you know, just funds go into the trust. They remain trust property.
I think this is also the ordinance. It said that the treasurer shall be the custodian of the trust funds, and I at first assumed it was going to be the Medford treasurer. It is the city's treasurer. Okay, so I might just specify that there. And then the only report we're going to have an annual audit
Um, and then that copy should be provided to the mayor and there was no other reports required to the city council going forward. But I didn't know if it should be, or if we're just going to kind of leave that as flexible.
So this is something that could be just business between the CPC and the trust, but I feel like it's a good practice in general to have an annual report that spells out what all of the revenues are and what everything we've spent funds are during the year. And maybe like the template that I have for the
The boards that I'm working with is a section on revenue and spending and a section that's reiterating goals. So just like, where are we in terms of the action plan? And also, what has happened over the past year? What are some major highlights that contextualize
what the trust is doing. Yeah. I do think that would actually be more helpful than just a very dry audit. Yeah. Again, I don't think that has to be specifically put in the declaration, but we could if we want to, or we could just do that and maybe put it in our rules and regulations. I like the idea of rules and regulations. Yes. In addition to it.
And I agree, an annual report, you have to show off what you did. Show off what you did. I do have a question about the audit and will the city of Medford's auditor be the ones performing the audit of the trust fund or will the trustees have to get their own auditor to do an audit?
I should probably check that with the city treasurer if they do an annual audit. I think they should do an annual audit. Yes, yes. But I'll just confirm. Okay, thank you. I know in some of all the city, whoever is doing the city's audit, they do a separate audit of the... How does it say CPA?
It has never really been on my radar how it happens. So I imagine it just goes with the general city audit. Yeah. Those trust you don't even have to think about it. CPA money is pre-council approval and housing trust money is post-council approval. So that might make a difference in
Did you just elaborate on housing trust when you forced council approval? So we don't have to, if we decide to spend money, we make the final decision and the money is spent. But CPA, if they decide they want to spend money, it has to go through the city council for approval. You make a recommendation. We make a recommendation and it goes to city council for approval.
And it's Tracy here. I can just add that our audit does follow with the regular city audit. We don't hire a special side consultant or anything like that. Thanks. Thank you. Yeah, the next ones are pretty basic. We're exempt from taxes. We're a board of the city of Medford.
The trust will be in existence until terminated. If it is terminated, we're going to, the trust would continue until all the affairs are wrapped up in some way. This document will be recorded as Article 12. Oh yeah, Article 13 amendments. So kind of a similar, somewhat similar question that we talked about before.
So we could either have this be a unanimous provision, so all the trustees would have to agree to amend this trust, or definitely seen a supermajority. So with seven trustees, that would be five voting for an amendment. I don't recall if that was in the ordinance either way, but I think either unanimously or a supermajority is the usual way for an amendment to this kind of document.
That is pretty much it. I think a couple of questions for the Mayor and a couple for the Council. Thank you. Any other questions?
I would just comment on the very last thing that you gave about amendments that just try to give ourselves the most flexibility for seeing that something could go wrong in the future, or we might, if we need to exercise the right to make amendments, we probably want a super majority and just have a little wiggle room in case,
I think we should put it though in the rule and
I mean, I think, um, this is, this is documents kind of laying out our powers. You know, this is kind of like everything that we want to do as a board. Um, and if we ever, I think even like, even spending time on it as a board does feel like, you know, we should get, um, that approved, you know, as, as board. So.
Yeah, I think if we want to have advocacy as part of the powers of the board, I do think we should have it in here as opposed to just the rules and regulations. So, Penny, can you walk me through your vision of advocacy? Is it like going down to the statehouse and advocating for more funds for whatever it is? Is it advocating for a developer to come in
or fund it? Great question. Well, I guess I was thinking of it in terms of policy advocacy. So as you'd like, some things in the action plan might relate to like certain policies on either the local or state level that would work in tandem to either. I mean, I just spitballing here, but like, for instance, the tenant opportunity for purchase, that's like sort of
Policies and being able to tie that to the funding or other things that we're also opening up so they can work like altogether. So I just didn't want to not be able to do things that kind of making the point that, like, certain work we're doing would be really supported by certain policies on a different level. So I could read what was in Lexington just to give you a little guideline of what I saw.
So they had number 17, to make recommendations on proposals or town meeting warrant articles which affect housing. 18, to develop policy goals and statements to serve as guidelines for the trust subject to approval by the select board and consistent with the town's housing goals and plans as may be adopted and amended by the select board from time to time. So we've kind of already done that. Yeah, I think it was really, it was kind of that first one in Lexington, at least.
So maybe with that knowledge in mind, I might say, like, it sounds like recommendations, right? So we're going to be setting our goals, and there might be certain policies or actions that are, would help us realize those that we, as a body that is studying and compiling and making, working towards those goals, would want to recommend. So just to not cobble us to not have that ability, if we found that as something that we wanted to do.
I was wondering if it's more like, well, you know, as a city employee, you can't, you can't go down and lobby for something at a state house. So that's what I was thinking when I'm thinking of what did you envision as advocacy? Yeah. And the body of a lot of knowledge that also will be in play.
Yeah, gaining knowledge from lots of others as well. So being able to then convey that, I think, is what I was thinking. Use our capacity to support housing policy. Yeah, and I think in Medford specifically, right? Yeah, I think that would make sense. Yeah. OK, thanks. Thank you. Yeah. Any other questions or comments?
Okay, so then we are going to go to the declaration of, nope, we just did that, sorry, the action plan. And Roberta and Penny and myself have been working on the action plan, and I've asked either Penny and or Roberta to give an update. I'll walk through the methodology that we've laid out.
So we begin with data collection, and we've looked at what are a range of data that might be helpful for to guide us help us to think about the city's affordable housing needs. And then we gather input from.
the Planning, Development and Sustainability is what PDS stands for. That's the department that NDT is a member of, Planning, Development and Sustainability. So we gather input from their department about like what is the status of the housing production plan and the master plan implementation seeing as
Those two documents are a couple of years old now. What is the progress that we've made? And what are some things that we see on the horizon that might be development opportunities or policy changes that we can anticipate in the next year or so?
So they'll provide us with that information. This is all just part of the background for our planning purposes. And then we gather input from stakeholders. So we'll hold a small series of focus group meetings with regional affordable housing developers and service providers. So the three of us will attend those meetings and then report back to you all what we've learned from them.
And so down at the bottom, we can see the timeline. Those three things are the data collection input from PDS and stakeholder input are all to take place over the next three months so that we have that much completed by the end of the year. And we'll be gearing up for
then in the new year, focusing more on thinking about the content of the action plan, thinking about what our action plan is actually going to look like. So we'll begin with a community meeting, presenting the market assessment and what we learned from PDS and stakeholders, and then ask for community input about what are the needs, priorities, and observations about
the what they're experiencing in the housing market. And so we'll be preparing for that outreach meeting in December and then in January hold the outreach meeting. And then we'll begin a series of discussions amongst ourselves. So we'll dedicate a series of meetings beginning in February.
February, March, maybe into April, to go over several topics together. Our mission statement, goals, priority actions and guidelines, and procedures. Like, what are the procedures that people will go through to obtain support from us? We'll lay all of that out and discuss the drafts together over those two or three months.
And then we'll hold a second community meeting which we're targeting for April 2025. The second community meeting will be to review the draft of the plan that we've laid out and then we can make
any final changes based on what we learned from the community meeting, and then request a meeting with city council, the committee of the whole, to present the action plan, which at that point should hopefully be final, if this timeline works out for us. Thank you, Roberta.
And I've also provided an outline if we go to the next page of just kind of a general picture of.
what the action plan looks like. We'll have a background, which is really just saying, what is the Affordable Housing Trust and how did we get here? And then the mission statement goals, describing what kind of funding we anticipate over the next five years, and then what are the priority actions that we're going to undertake. And then the appendix is going to have all of the stuff that we learned,
the contextual information data that we collected in the fall. You're welcome. Anybody have any questions on the observations? I had one and that was only about the
stakeholder meetings, stakeholder input, if you were going to solicit names from the whole board, if you were going to come up with a list and then talk to the board? That's a really good question. We did just off the cuff generate a list, which Aditi is projecting on the screen right now. It's a long list of people to invite. So I wonder,
whether it makes sense for us to just read through this list together and see if any of you can think of anything that we left out. Maybe you want to increase the zoom in a little bit. Yes. Okay. And then, yeah, we can add to the list if there's anything that you can think of that we didn't. So
Medford Community Housing, they've actually recently built a very small affordable housing development in Medford. Housing Corporation of Arlington, kind of a similar very small organization.
Preservation of Affordable Housing, POA. They're currently building a large affordable housing development right up the street in Somerville. The Neighborhood Developers is another regional affordable housing developer. Caribbean Integration Community Development. I spoke with them one time. Thank you for remembering them. Yeah, they are interested. They're a small CDC that's interested in
expanding regionally and provide, you know, seeing if they can partner with communities to provide some services. Metro North Housing Corporation is a regional housing developer that's working kind of to the east and north of us. Malden. Malden, yeah. The Medford Housing Authority
And then some service providers, housing stability, youth, childcare, employment services, serving unhoused population, community teamwork. I don't recall, like the name is familiar and I don't remember where community teamwork is working. I know Newton. Okay. Really? I have, I think there's one in Lowell. Okay. Yeah.
Housing families currently, housing families and ABCD currently operate housing stability programs funded by the Community Preservation Act. Justice Start is a non-profit organization in Cambridge that does services and housing development. Metro Housing Boston, they provide some services. Caritas Communities, currently they have
They're an affordable housing organization that specializes in single room occupancy, and they currently have a site in Medford. They might be interested in developing another site in Medford. CAS, Community Action Agency of Somerville,
Respond, which is an organization that addresses victims of domestic violence in Somerville. Heading Home is another service provider in Somerville. Somerville Homeless Coalition. Wayside Youth and Family Support Network, which interestingly has a
essentially a homeless shelter that's just up the street from us and very close to another homeless shelter, which I forgot to put on the list of another organization that we might want to reach out to, which is Volunteers of America. I was thinking that as I was looking at the listing. I just want to correct. It offers a tiny
at it, they don't, it's not in a homeless shelter. They actually have permanent supportive housing and it's transitional housing. So transitional is a timeframe up to two years they're able to stay. Thank you for that. And they also have an office right here in Medford Square too. So another reason why they might be interested in working with us. Bread of Life, an organization in Malden,
And Housing Medford is just a local advocacy group. And Medford Council on Aging and Mystic Valley Elder Services. So. Yeah, yeah. Greater Boston Legal Services, because Medford is in their coverage area for including legal groups with a housing event there. Yeah. Is it the Greater Boston Legal Services? Correct. Thank you.
and DeNovo Legal Services. I don't know if their service area covers Medford. I can double check and let you know. I believe that Housing Families has provided pro bono legal services to our residents. I just didn't want to repeat the names that they provided services to. Oh, thanks, Alyssa. Alyssa's great. The company I work for has been involved in Caritas before.
don't get an answer from them, feel free to let me know. I could ping them as well. I would just maybe advocate for the addition of one or two more on the development side. I think you have a great list. They're all incredibly knowledgeable, but I think when we're talking about housing supply, I think, you know,
Having a for-profit developer in the mix might be just an option. And even just a lot of 40B developers are really market rate developers, but they do produce a lot of housing. So if you want, I can think about it and submit one or two names that I think might be a good fit as well, just to add to the numerous list. There's an organization. What is it called? Beacon Properties? Is that who it is? Beacon Properties is really good. Yeah, I agree.
when development is coming into Somerville fairly soon, taking over the DNA. Oh, then, yeah, let's include them, too. All of those, I think, are top options. Thank you. And there are a few of those that I'm not. There's a bunch, but it's hard to remember them all. There's another non-profit one that I see a lot, though, Community Builders. Ah, yes, yes, yes. And then arts.
And then Habitat. They're also not for profit, but they do a lot of work. And there is E3. They just did a development in Somerville. I forgot the woman's name.
It will come to me late tonight. Not Lisa. Elisa? Elisa, yes. Is it Davis Square Architects? Yes. Yeah. They do a lot of work. They do a lot of work. Yes. Yeah. So it might be, yeah, we may not reach all of them, but we can at least send out an invitation and see how many we're able to plug in. Sure.
Thank you for that. Thank you. I think we just went over the stakeholders. I actually have some follow-up question on the stakeholder groups and preparing an email and reaching out.
Who's that lucky person that's going to do all that? Am I looking at it? I can do that as long as we have a template. Yeah. I was also going to ask about funding. Are we doing any physical flyers? Is that something the city would cover cost-wise or would the trust need it so we fund this? If we are planning to translate them, then
you'd have to pick it up some funding sources because you don't have that ability at this point.
especially for community outreach, but for stakeholder engagement, I'm not sure if you do want to have them translated. Oh, right. Yeah. Yeah. I was I was thinking more of the community. Yeah, we should have to ask. Yeah. I mean, so does the city of Medford have a department that helps with translation services? No. Yeah. OK. All right. There are community liaisons under the health department.
And we can work with them to try to reach the communities that they're liaising to. So that, you know, it's not quite on the level of having translation services, but we can do some targeted outreach. I just want to make sure that when we're doing the community meetings and getting the feedback from the community that we're able to communicate
What we might want to do is incorporate into our timeline meetings with each of the community liaisons.
to ask them to do outreach with their communities. And maybe they can see if they can even just make a small focus group and just bring together a handful of people who are in their outreach communities who'd be willing to talk with us. So we could try to have brief
small meetings with them, in addition to our community meeting, to ask for their input on the needs. I've been speaking with the DT about what support the city can offer in terms of outreach for the community meetings, so I'm happy to continue those conversations. I think translation is a great question on accessibility questions, spatial questions, all the gamut, but I'm happy to work with you to help figure those out.
I think maybe our next meeting we'll have some updates. Yeah, we'll run out of ideas. Everyone has some great ideas. Just to remember the update, I think Ameya is online. Welcome, Ameya. Hi, good evening. Sorry I'm late.
Did we want to just revisit some? Yeah, a couple of them. So we had a couple pending questions from the Declaration of Trust. Let me just point it out now. So I think the first one might be article three, number five. Oops, not four, sorry, four, four, circled the wrong one, number four.
Sorry, article three, number four, excuse me. So this was taken from the ordinance, and it just says that any member of the board may be removed by the mayor for cause after the opportunity of a hearing. And I didn't know if we needed some more details there about what the hearing might entail, or if there was already a process or procedure in place
that I could reference, I think some amount of detail here might be useful. Mia, can you hear us?
Yeah, you're asking me this question. The only way I can remove somebody from a border commission is through cause. And that would just be, I believe it would just be a letter. And honestly, I don't think I've had to do that. So I don't have specific information for you. Okay.
And then I guess, Madam Mayor, the question was, in addition to, for the reasons was, is there an outline of what the hearing, who participates in the hearing? If somebody was removed for cause, it says that they do have, they will have an opportunity for a hearing.
So would that be the city council, trustees? No, it's not the way it's written. Not the way it's written because it says that the mayor shall remove with a hearing. So you would think it would be some sort of committee, I don't know. Okay. Maybe we'll kick this over to
I'll leave the comments at that. Great. And then I think the only other question that we had was from article four, number three. So this was a limitation that I think was specific to our city council. They asked that any sale of real property having an area of more than 7,500 square feet
has to be subject to the approval of the city council. And then they didn't specify if that was gonna be a majority, a super majority or some sort of unanimous votes. And I didn't know if you had any idea of what they might want there or what they meant there. I don't think you have to put any specifics in because they already need to approve any sale of property as it is. And that would follow the general legal process.
So I think if there's land that is given to us or that we control, I don't, unless it's over the 7,500 square feet as our board, we might be able to dispose of it ourselves without their approval. So they've limited themselves to what approval rights they have. But normally if it's a piece of real property that goes through city council, is it a unanimous vote by city council?
I do not believe it's unanimous. Okay. So when I want to keep a majority for now. Yeah, I can give you get specifics for you for the next meeting we're working with an attorney right now to potentially sell to smaller parcels up on McCormick.
that could potentially, it's a lot of ledge, but there is abutters that are interested, and I think it would be a great way to put funding into the Affordable Housing Trust. So I do have an attorney working on that now, so I could get more specifics on exactly what the council needs to vote on, and if it's by majority or not. But it's definitely not unanimous. Okay, great. Thank you.
All right, so that brings us back to the CPA application and NDTs will provide us with an update of the application that was submitted. Thank you for that. So we submitted the CPA application on September 9th and we have a presentation on October 22nd. So I just wanted to go over the outline of what the presentation may look like.
So this is an outline. I was thinking we can just introduce affordable housing trust and then it was established and how many meetings we've had so far. And then probably with the help of data, identify the need for affordable housing and then update them that are working groups.
That's the action plan, what's the status and the declaration of trust. I'm not sure declaration of trust is necessary, but definitely action plan may be helpful just to update them with the status.
And then, sorry, these are the five potential projects that we mentioned in the application. So probably have a slide for each of these projects. And then the scope and budget, which you're all seeing, will probably be added to the presentation. And then the letters of support that will proceed from three different parties.
In addition to that, our application also included some city-owned lots that could be potentially used for affordable housing developments. This is the Fulton Street plots. There's been some study done on this, and there are developers who are interested in building 100% affordable home ownership in this lot.
And another one is Ciro Riverside. So this is a city-owned lot, and it's sort of landlocked because there's the expressway. And the Everding property is interested in acquiring this and building development that includes 25% affordable housing. So something that we could probably explore.
And then we have two city-owned lots on 0 Gailey Street, and then there's a land in between, which was on sale earlier last month, if I'm not wrong. I'm not sure if it's still on sale or if the owner is interested to sell this property, but this would be something that the trust would look into. And then these are just city-owned lots
are sort of ambiguous and would allow for a larger development. But this has not been in the conversation. It's just something that Teresa suggested. And so we have included that here as well. Thank you.
And if I'm not mistaken, you were looking for trustees to accompany you at the October 22nd meeting, correct? That would be great. If not all, just one or two. I know that Roberta is going to be there, but she's going to recuse herself. Don't say you'll have to vote for her. The 22nd. I probably can.
I think technically, but it's been the practice of the CPC to not vote for vote for your own board. But I think you technically are allowed to, because as long as they're both for the city, you're still representing the city. What time is the meeting on the 22nd?
Theresa, could you help me with that? I don't remember the timing. 6.30. 6.30. Thank you. Correct. And I believe that you are one of the first applicants that evening, just to have that be a factor. Thank you, Theresa. And I, too, have blocked it off. Yes. I don't think I can make it, but I'll let you know if I make it.
Thank you. I might be able to come directly from tennis, so I will be sweating. At the DPW office, I can send you the details. It's actually a nice meeting room at the DPW office. It's bigger than this. It has a table and a bigger audience area.
And we even learned how the light switch works. It did take us, it took me, you know, 90 minutes to figure it out. We made it. Got some sophisticated lights over there. All right, thank you. And I lost mine. All right, so we are on item five, finances.
going to discuss the potential funding sources and questions raised by Shelly from MPMHP. And she, that's the email that you sent on the various? And I've just included the questions, not the entire email. You want me to read them all through or do we want? Yeah.
Um, so the first question is initiating a fee such as linkage is citywide effort. Is it appropriate for the trust to initiate this effort? I think that's going to be dependent on the the input that we get from PDS because I know that you've been working on this. So is that is there like this is where we want to advocate. Is there a role for us in helping to advocate for the
linkage fee or is it something that's already sufficiently baked? I think we are moving towards, as Mayor mentioned that the Mayor is also working on it and so we are also looking towards potential funding sources and then eventually we will draft the RFP and probably the trust can provide inputs on that. Okay. Yes.
Are people like the nexus study? Yeah, this is an example of where the trust would want to be involved in advocacy to guide the effort to create a linkage fee and to get it passed. I'm not involved in this because I trust that something is initiating the study, but it could be wrong. Yeah, might be. I don't know.
The second question is if linkage were to be instated and not good, would all of the funds be directed to the trust? Probably not, because currently we have linkage fees that go to a number of other sources. And so we're not going to win any friends by redirecting all of that to the Affordable Housing Trust. I think it's only going to be the Affordable Housing Linkage. Yes.
All right, so I just want to wrap my head around one thing that we're talking about. So the city of Medford already has linkage fees. So now we're talking about initiating another linkage fee citywide to benefit the affordable housing trust funds. Okay, so then question number two would be,
Yes, it would come all the way to the trust, right? Yes. But I mean, to be more Medford specific, so we already currently have a linkage fees, but it's a very old ordinance that really
doesn't work all that well to our benefit anymore and for complicated reasons we haven't been able to update it because we need to have a nexus plan and we are working on putting out an rp for the nexus plan and retaining a consultant but that's been much more complicated than anticipated so we're really looking at adding affordable housing to the linkage to the existing linkage program
But also it needs to be overhauled anyway. So, again, I need to wrap my head around it because it's spinning at the moment. It's.
instead of two separate linkage fees, it would be one, we look, I'm hearing two different things. I'm hearing we're looking to do a separate linkage fee for the Affordable Housing Trust Fund, and if that's the case, it would go all to the Affordable Housing Trust Fund. But then I'm also hearing that we already have a linkage fee on the books in Medford that the study, the NEXUS study is looking, hopefully,
is to be able to expand the usage and or the ability, the funds, where the funds are coming from, expand that, and then the usage. I could provide some context just to take a few steps back. So we have an act that allows Medford to adopt a linkage fee. And currently we have
if I'm not wrong, four different buckets. There's police and fire, water and sewer, parks and recreation, and then there's traffic. So these are the different buckets under which we are collecting our linkage fee. The Act allows us to adopt affordable housing linkage, but we do not have that in the ordinance yet.
issue with the ordinance is that it says that we have to review the linkage fee every three years and we have not done that since 30 years, since the time it was adopted. An issue with that timeline that every three years we need to review this linkage is that in other communities they review it
Every 5 years, and then we review the linkage fee, we have to do a next study, which would sort of ensure that we do not face any legal challenges with the fee that we impose.
So every three years would be, would include, yeah, it's very costly to do that. And based on interaction with our potential consultants, a Nexus study that would review the existing linkage as well as include affordable housing linkage would cost $200,000. So spending that much every three years is a challenge. So we are trying to amend the act
To review the linkage being every 7 to 10 years. So currently we are in state to the act. Yeah. And the 2nd option is.
we may not update the existing linkage, but do a nexus study to add affordable housing linkage. And that would cost us $60,000 to $80,000. This study will also include reviewing our current inclusionary zoning ordinance and see if we can include cash in lieu instead of just providing equitable units.
a fractional payment. We don't have that in our ordinance. So these are the two routes that we could consider. So there's $200,000 and then there's the $80,000 fee. Okay. Which one is the city leading towards? We are figuring that out. I think the first step is to amend the Act. And also, as Mayor mentioned, we are also looking at
figuring out how to add funding to the trust by identifying certain city-owned lots as well. So, hopefully that will provide some funding to Lewiston. And just out of curiosity, amending the current linkage act. Yes. I think I heard you say State House. So, is that a home rule petition? That was in the discussion at the City Council meeting. Okay. Yeah. Okay.
That takes a while. We've had something in summer for quite some time. If that takes a while, one solution is just to do a next study to add affordable housing linkage. I think people still do that. But if you do that, would you then be on the three-year update route?
Yes, yeah, that's a good question. Just less than a three year cycle and some other parts of the ordinance, like the structure. So just kind of sticking in the structure is there that it could work that that money could then come possibly just do the next day for housing to get it. Okay. Yes, the actor loves.
Just to be clear, the act allows us to add affordable housing linkage, and then probably the ordinance should outline that and directly go to the trust. Okay. Yeah. All right. So I think we've answered the first three questions.
Question 4. Is there another way to fund the trust through a more traditional channel? Example related city department? Yeah, these are Shelly's questions. So it's meant to help us. So I think you mentioned.
an option earlier that could potentially help to fund the trust, which is selling city-owned land that's not a candidate for affordable housing, but the proceeds could go to the trust? I'm not very clear on that. I don't know if Madam Mayor would like to add to that. Madam Mayor, do you have any thoughts on that?
Could you just repeat the question, please? Whether a possible source of funding is if there is land that the city is disposing of that's not appropriate for affordable housing, could the proceeds of selling that land go to the Affordable Housing Trust? Yes. Yes, that's what I'm doing with McCormick.
Perfect. Yes. Thank you. I think there's a balance of, like Aditi mentioned, we're looking at a bunch of different city-owned parcels. Some we would like to maybe build affordable housing on, and then others, my hope is we do a mix of also including the sale of some of these lots so that we can add funding to the Affordable Housing Trust. Great. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
The question is, was it a mail tax or some other thing that you had mentioned? Yeah, madame. It is the city of Medford have a mail tax. I should know. Yes, all the time and I never look at it. Yes, yes, we have hotels tax and mails tax and that that funding goes into the general fund. It does, but I yeah.
So I was sharing with Penny that a number of conferences that I've gone to for the unhoused in different parts of the country, they actually use a portion of the mail tax to
subsidize or fund housing programs. I was wondering if we didn't have one, could we put one and then we could bring it right into the affordable housing? Short-term rentals? We have them, excuse me. Short-term rentals. Is there a fee for short-term rental registration and could that go to... Oh, like Airbnb? Yes. Yeah. Do we have any restrictions around short-term rentals?
Yeah, there are some restrictions on that. Yes. But we do have restrictions. Yeah. So are we, do we already or are we allowed to charge a fee or a tax on short-term rentals? And could that go to the affordable housing trust? I need to look at the arguments before I see something. But me, Madam Mayor, may have some inputs on that.
No, I was going to say the same thing. We can check out the ordinance and we can also see if the building commissioner has any insight or experience in anything, you know, in fees that we could potentially collect. And then I would assume we have to adjust the ordinance if need be.
I wonder if it would require a rental registry to be able to also monitor that. I'm not sure. Yeah. Well, maybe, I mean, a short-term rental registry, sometimes cities, municipalities have a vendor that does the monitoring for them for short-term rentals.
So there is an administrative fee associated with that. So it would only make sense to implement that if what we collect in the end exceeds the administrative fee rather than having our short-term rental guests just paying a third-party vendor and the city doesn't get anything out of it.
I mean, if there's an ordinance in place, the city must have some sort of idea of what properties are operating as short-term rental. Hopefully. Okay. It's a whole new world. All right. Thank you. Great idea. Do we want information about that and more information about that ordinance or about this kind of direction? Short-term rental? Yeah.
Yes. I'll be right back. I'm sorry. I believe Councilor Callahan brought this up to have a rental registry. So we've been discussing that. And at our office, our intern is also researching on a rental registry at this point. So it's a work in progress. Great. And I did contact
a third party that hosts a rental registry application in other communities like Worcester, and they're planning to have one in Chelsea or Everett. And that would cost the city $25,000 annually to maintain the platform. Yeah. I guess I'm curious to know what information is gathered, if anything, about the short-term rentals. But you don't need a ton more info, because it sounds like we're going
look at that ordinance and figure out. For the short-term renter rental monitoring, they actually monitor
All of the platforms that people use to rent out apartments or places to stay. And so the third party vendor is making sure that everybody who is advertising is registered.
and that they're paying the fees that are required for registration and that they meet the requirements that they don't exceed whatever their allowance is. So they do all of that monitoring, which is very different from rental registry.
Question 5. The statute does not explicitly allow for fundraising expenses. It does allow for purchasing or retaining real estate or personal property, including investments that yield a high rate of income. Essentially, spend money to make money. Perhaps that idea or others in the statute would allow for use in resources to explore funding options for the trust.
You had mentioned another thing earlier of the possibility, or maybe it was you who mentioned it, the possibility of providing services for a fee that would generate revenue for the trust, but we'd have to be able to actually provide those services like the.
income certification and monitoring resale, the lotteries. So if we're already doing that, you know, we could just take on more for a fee, but we'd have to actually have the capacity to do that. So that's also something that one of our nonprofit partners could do to generate revenue and might give them an incentive to do more work here in Medford.
Currently, I'm monitoring the rental approvals for affordable housing, and that's part of the regulatory agreement, so I don't think we could charge a fee to do that. But are you doing the lottery? Yeah, we're not doing the lottery. You're not doing the lottery. Yes. Yes. But I wonder if the trust is considered as a municipal employee, would that allow them to actually conduct the lottery, because that has to be
organization that's impartial. I mean, the city of summerville does lotteries for affordable housing for the inclusionary, for the inclusionary properties.
or if we had 40 B properties. Yeah, those will go from a private law, a lottery agent. Yeah. So we could be the lottery agent or maybe one of our nonprofits could be, or I don't know, maybe, maybe not. I don't know. It's a lot of work. It's a lot of work. Especially the city of San Juan just went from
the little, the bingo wheel, no, I'm not kidding you, to actually digitize it, which makes it still easier, but it's still a lot of work.
Yeah, we just have our housing stuff. We always have to keep in mind our limitations, which are very significant. But it's the compensation. Maybe subcontract out to the third party or through us. I think that's the that's the idea. If we designate ourselves and we have a deal with someone else, we can at least have
part of it, but it is also a lot of work. Yeah, it's about how many the lotteries are happening in a year. Yeah, putting on an RIP. Yeah. I have a question. Do we have any agreements with Tufts University to get any sort of financial benefit from them? A pilot?
pilot agreement payment in lieu of taxes. We do. We already have an agreement. They pay $450,000 plus $250,000 for the Cummings property. Gotcha. And then where does that money go into general fund that goes into the general fund? Yes. Could it be negotiated that some
amount be added or changed, like redirected to go to the Affordable Housing Trust?
They just went up to 450 maybe two or three years ago, and the 250 payment is new that was attached to when the Cummings property got their certificate of occupancy. So those are fairly new, but if we do any additional negotiation, or I could extend it and ask to Tufts, I'm not sure they'll bite, but I could try. Isn't there new development for student dorms?
Coming up, something we can negotiate for a 1 Boston, right? Yeah, yeah, they have a very large proposal coming before the city. So, yeah, that would be a pretty good time. Yeah, especially.
If there's any if there's any like room for negotiation in that proposal, you know, they're offering something for for the affordable housing trust might might be helpful to come to an agreement.
Oh, that's a good question. Can I ask, do, are these uses or kind of actions that we're talking about currently covered in our declaration of trust or would we have to like add language to it? The actions that we're talking about? Are we talking about actions or are we talking about funding sources? Funding sources, yeah.
Which could not not yeah, the lottery was probably one that might be decided. I think something linkage and stuff and that's that's. This last one, yeah, no, I think I think most of that is just. Or passively accepting funds, and it may seem concluding us or not that actively added, but OK, yeah.
I imagine it's going to be an ongoing conversation about what are opportunities to generate more revenue for the trust. Those opportunities might not be available to us today, but might come in the future.
I think that it's a conversation that should be had similar to what you're saying, Roberta, just constantly because there are new ways of getting and having the thought process, keeping our eyes and ears open for research. Yeah.
I apologize for stepping out of the room. We got a phone call. We just got a 0.5, 0.6 and 0.7 or something for us to keep in mind. Thank you.
Just to add to that under finances, we do have to set up a bank account. I spoke with the city's treasurer. They already have a bank account under which they bring trust at the line item. So for us to have a line item, we need to have funds. So once the funds are in there, then I can inform the city's treasurer to deposit it. Thank you.
And then we are on item number six, invitations to discuss housing resources. So wondering if the trust may consider inviting individuals and groups that manage federal state funds to support housing, CDBG and home funds, nonprofit organizations that provide housing related services, ABCD and housing families.
advocacy groups made for housing and mission driven developers and so on. So do we want to invite anybody in, tell us about, tell us about themselves, we can share how new we are and how excited we are to be able to work with them as we get them.
Do we want to talk about a little bit about that? I spoke with our CDBG manager and they'd be interested to provide some updates on what they're doing and they'd be happy to attend the meeting in November. That's our next meeting, yes.
And I can also provide some updates on NSC's plans and what the funding sources are and what's available. I should remember what this means. NSC can use... North Suburban Consortium. Eight communities that have formed a consortium. That's our home consortium. That's our home consortium. And Malden...
manages the consortium. Yes. And I'm the NSC representative from Medford. Yeah. And then what was CWG? CDBG. CDBG. Sorry for the acronyms. Community Development Block Grant. Yeah. So CDBG is a funding that we received from the federal government. And it's celebrating 50 years actually in October. Yes.
So, yeah, that would be very helpful to just get the kind of the general picture of what our resources are. And yes, we can have at least CDBG and HOMA in our next meeting and then moving forward if the trust would like to invite more groups and entities that support affordable housing or housing services. Yeah.
We will have the stakeholder meetings, which it was our, it was our thinking when we had this, the sub committee.
that the whole committee might be too many people to be in the room at once with a group of stakeholders. So we were thinking that the three of us would gather that information and then give all of you detailed notes from the conversations that we have with them. So that would cover a lot of the types of stakeholders that you mentioned. But if there's anyone that is like,
stands out as somebody who would, it would be helpful to have like some background context for the whole group should identify who those would be. Yeah, I think that sounds good. I think from our last meeting, one of the other ideas that came from the consultant was
getting just like the basic real estate developer, you know, playbook. Yeah. Like how they determine how they determine which property. So, you know, I could, I could put some thought on maybe submit a list because I think, I think some of the people we've already mentioned are pretty good at that as well. But, um,
I think also looking at some of the sizes of the lots that we're talking about, we're talking about probably smaller scale than some of the people that we're inviting. I think we should have a mix, but I also think it might be better to talk to, I mean, some of these people are basically going to be, you know, small homeowner, you know, developer. And I don't think some of the groups that we're talking about really, that's not almost big enough scale for them, honestly. So.
If we wanted to maybe talk about getting someone who could come in and just give a presentation on what they do and what they look at and how they build the stack of capital, that might be a little bit different than the big stakeholder. This is what we're interested in meeting. This is a little bit outside the box, but I don't know if we have anybody in Medford who's doing this kind of thing. But a community that I used to work in
further out in the suburbs, they had local developers who would come and take an old house and rehab it and convert it to, say, four to six apartments, four to eight apartments. And so they'd add on to the back of it. The front would be historic preservation. And then it was infill development.
So, and it would be, it was, they did that using 40 B. so it's just a model of development that might help with infill. I feel like that.
Thinking Main Street, there was, I remember driving by this one house that was on the back. It was a beautiful white house. It looked like a single family, but it was demoed and it is now multi-unit. So maybe that for-profit person, I imagine it was for-profit.
kind of on the lines of what you're talking about. Yeah, I mean, because that was what they're affordable housing trusted was to invite and basically like look at who was building in the community already right and invite them to use the 40 B process to do infill development and historic preservation and build affordable units. It's a great combination.
on some of my sustainability measures in there. I guess I'll make that my question number one, or idea number one of three. One is having someone come. I would love to learn more about building sustainability measures and what they can actually do. I'm just going to learn more about that. So somewhere down the agenda, I don't know who to recommend, but I feel like I could certainly learn more about that.
I want, and this is just in the terms of knowledge coming and sharing with us. So I'm also curious where the city's at with accessory dwelling units, which were just approved by right on the state level. So that is something in the mix that I'm sure there are people with some knowledge on or some thinking happening around, but that's kind of base it in coming this way. So that is another topic I'd put out there. And then I'm just curious, kind of the level
detail, so I think some of this will come out in the stakeholder conversations, the action plan, but for the agencies that currently get CPA funding to provide services to Medford residents, like what the numbers look like, what the demand, what the need, and of course, I'm sure that funding doesn't cover all the needed stuff, but kind of getting a sense of those numbers and kind of their thoughts. Again, the stakeholder will get that, but if that then turns into a bigger conversation that we want to learn more from them about as a group, we'll put that on the walks too.
That would actually be great. Maybe that would be a stakeholder to target bringing to either a CPC or a trust meeting to talk about, like maybe when we have the presentation for the CPC by ABCD or Housing Families. I don't remember if they're both.
At least Housing Families is coming in for more funding. I don't remember if ABCD is. That we could ask them to provide more background on how long it's taken them to use up the funding that their previous round of funding and who received it. What was the uptake like?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah,
It's not, I like the idea of coming into the Trust as well. Yeah, very true. You can always invite them if they say no. I think they'll go wherever they're going to get money as a result of going. Then we'll really know how much they want to come, because we don't have money. Be a good introduction.
All right, thank you guys. Does anybody have anything else to offer on the invitation for discussion? People coming in, Madam President? I'm sorry, I upgraded you. All right, so if that's everything we've got, I'd like to, is there a motion to adjourn the meeting?
So moved. Second. Thank you everyone. Thank you. Thank you everyone. Thank you. Thank you.