Special meeting, Medford City Council, June 12th, 2024.
Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Councilor Callahan.
Present.
Vice President Collins.
Councilor Lozaro.
Present.
Councilor Lemike.
Councilor Scarpelli, the City Committee, absent.
Councilor Sang.
Five present, two absent.
The meeting is called to order.
Please rise.
Oh, I'm present.
Five present, two absent.
Meeting is called to order.
Please rise to salute the flag.
24-408 offered by Mayor Brianna Longo-Kern.
Regarding workers' compensation settlement, dear President Behrs and members of the city council, I respectfully request and recommend your honorable body enter executive session pursuant to general law chapter 30A section 21A3 to discuss strategy with respect to litigation concerning a workers' compensation settlement with Michael Nestor.
I also recommend that the council's agenda state in the executive session notice that the votes may be taken.
Attorney Brian Mazur will be present on June 12th, 2024 to provide the council with guidance on this matter.
Thank you for your kind attention to this request.
Sincerely, Brianne Algo-Kern, Mayor.
This is our only item for the night.
Is there a motion to Vice President Collins?
Motion to enter Executive Session.
Can we amend that to be pursuant to General Law Chapter 30A, Section 21A.3 and note that votes may be taken and note that we may adjourn in Executive Session.
So moved.
On the motion of Vice President Collins, seconded by Councilor Gallihan, Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Councilor Calderon?
Yes.
Vice President Collins?
Councilor Lozaro?
Yes.
Councilor Lemming?
Councilor Scarpelli is absent.
Councilor Sang is absent.
President Paris?
Yes.
Five in the affirmative, none in the negative, two absent.
Motion passes.
We're entering executive session.
I'm gonna create a breakout room.
Attorney Mazer, I will invite you.
Thank you.