Welcome back for our next installment of Coffee Chats with the Kingsleys.
And I am again joined by Annie.
So what's the next part of your platform?
Wow.
Thank you for asking.
So the next part of my platform is the belief that families and schools need authentic and real engagement.
Okay.
So what that means is we know that schools have a lot of expertise and we know that families have a lot of expertise.
So what are schools experts on?
and what our families experts are.
So when you put those things together, we are going to be able to better meet the needs of our students.
But right now that happens too infrequently, or we rely on just individual teachers that have that belief instead of really investing in a system that supports that at all levels of Medford Public Schools.
What do you mean by the system?
Well, so a system might be
that we say this is like the one type of software we're going to use.
The system might be we make it really easy for teachers to reach out to parents because we like set up recommendations of when they do it.
A system might be the district creates opportunities to bring families in and talk to them.
So it's not always up to one teacher.
And right now we have some systems in place that actually make it harder for families and teachers to communicate, like not sharing testing information until, you know, report cards come out.
There's ways that we can make it easier for teachers and students, or teachers and families to work together.
So that, like, the teachers can, like, do their stuff, their, like, test stuff earlier?
Yeah, so like the math test that you take,
Right?
It would be great if once those tests are done, families have access to that information and they're able to help teachers say like, sometimes we know you're really, really good in one area, but you're still struggling with a different area.
So if parents know that and teachers know that as it's happening, we can work together to help build those skills as opposed to kind of keeping information and what I would call a silo, like keeping information separate.
So you don't get those authentic partnerships.
Cause parents like knowing what their child scores.
It's true.
And like what their child is doing great.
And when their child isn't doing so great, sometimes they might need to talk to their kid, right?
And then they have to wait until the end of the year.
Yeah.
And that's no good.
So what do you think?
Would that be a good idea?
Okay.