All right, how you doing, everybody?
So we'll give kind of a light agenda tonight.
So last month, we had a walk of the South Street to look at potential locations for street signage.
We identified three spots.
So two of those spots would be signs like
This picture?
Yeah, I can share the screen.
Okay, perfect.
Thank you.
Yeah, of course.
I try to be prepared.
No, it's excellent.
You're very well prepared.
All right.
So everybody should be seeing a horrible rendering of South Street, of the signage here.
I'm saying James Nodding.
Thank you.
So this would be one of the potential signages that we could do, and it would be a descriptive signage where it would be a sign that describes what the South Street District is, and it's like a grassy area right off of the river there.
That would be an excellent spot for it.
There's been talk of at some point being a larger project and making a walking path there or whatever.
That signage could potentially be incorporated into a sitting area to look out at the river as you're walking or whatever.
That would be nice.
That one might hold off.
I personally would love to do that one first, but that's going to be
A large budget item and a little bit of more logistics.
Yeah, it's it's operation because we don't have control of the waterfront.
It's got a zillion hurdles to it.
Yeah.
It's awesome though.
I just love looking at that.
But anyways, but to actually get something done,
we located two spots uh to put signage on either end of um of south street like you know where the houses start and end or end and start depending upon well i guess it's a one way so it is starting to end yeah um and uh one there one's using uh a pre-existing like sign oh so it'll be a new sign post but it's an existing location of a sign so it doesn't like
uh clutter up the street with more like signposts and signs just kind of just changing what the signage would be um and then the other one down the other way we're gonna we're just gonna go on the street with that or what was the end thought yeah we we're probably just going to be able to go on the street with alan this is at the corner of curtis and south street which is effectively the the first house um that is in the district is right at the corner of that um
Ideally, looking at the space there, it would be great if we could go on to the grass area.
However, that is not our property.
So I think that there would be a bit of, either we cannot do it there or approaching that homeowner and saying, hey, would you be willing for us to put a very decorative, very prissy signpost on your property?
Just be barely on your property.
Because that particular, actually I think,
Everybody should still be seeing a Google map at this point, or are we still seeing the street signs?
Still seeing the street signs.
It's the first one.
Yeah, I thought I wasn't sure if I shared just the application.
So it's this location here.
So this house with the green shutters and the tree in the front, that is in the district.
So right here on the corner of that sidewalk would be an ideal location just because that is
the anchor, the first house coming down the street.
I don't think we'd have enough room on the sidewalk here.
You can see the sidewalk's also not in great shape.
But something to explore with DPW, maybe we could do a bit of an enhancement of the sidewalk.
So to fix the issues here while also having a place for signage is a small possibility.
So the plan, the plan, and Teresa's done a real tremendous job on this.
So what the plan is, is that we're going to, she's approached the carpentry teacher at Medford High Folk and
He seems to be receptive of making the sign and then the deep we would purchase that like we like the historic district commission would purchase the sign post.
Yeah, well, they post the material has to get purchased by.
through this budget, then they would do the work to it, however they're going to make the sign.
And then we would purchase a signed post, and then the DPW would install that, which is great.
Yeah.
And when I approached the vocational school, I feel like City Hall, we have a great resource there, but I wanted to not just say, hey, can you make something for me and call it a day?
I think this would be a really great collaboration
with the high school, you know, I asked him, like, it's a loose bag.
So I said, Mr. Spagnola, do you have anybody in your class you think would be really interested in history and maybe, you know, be more involved in, like, the content creation of this, just to see if there's some collaboration there.
He seemed really excited about that idea.
So, you know, not just, hey, kids, make this, you know, it's, you know, be involved with it, understand what we're making, understand the content, the importance of it.
and also make it.
So yeah, some really exciting opportunities there.
Yeah.
And I feel very comfortable that they'd be able to make these signs for us, the more laid signs, very easily.
This one will be a little bit more involved, the interpretive sign.
That's the officially inferred informative sign, it's called an interpretive sign.
Yeah, and initial thoughts, Pasita, James?
Yeah.
In terms of the interpretive sign, do we know, it was mentioned that maybe there'd be a bigger project along that part of the river.
Is there any timeline for that?
Do we know if that's going to happen in the next five years?
I think if we start the conversations now, I mean, it'll end up, we can't just put a sign here.
We'd have to put in some sidewalk, which
As we were walking, we saw that the ground had been worn down for people walking on this grass area.
So it's indicative that there should be a sidewalk here, too.
So it's a little bit more involved in the project.
I would say if I could call Mr. DCR right now and say, can I please do this, it would probably be a two-year project, two to three years.
just to improve that area.
For us, just to make a sign and put it in somewhere else on South Street that we have jurisdiction of, that would be faster, so we don't have to go through approvals and whatnot.
But this just seems like a great opportunity in this spot.
When you see that spot, it's a great spot.
Yeah.
It really is nice.
I'm curious, and again, I agree with you.
I think that'd be great.
I'm curious if
waiting until a larger improvement project is done might be more prudent, just in terms of the cost of it.
Because we could put a sign there, and then they could come along a year from now and say, oh, yeah, we're going to tear this all up and put something.
Yeah.
Do we lose the sign, or does it have to get pulled up and that kind of thing?
So I don't know if that matters.
If it's something where, you know what, we could do this, and probably we won't say anything for another 10 years, great.
Yeah.
You know, and like you said, people already use it probably to walk their dogs and jog and all that kind of stuff.
And honestly, if I was walking along the river there, I would likely use that side of the river also, because again, just.
It'd be a lot easier on my on my legs and back walking on ground and pavement for three miles or something.
So this is just a natural, you know, people naturally want to walk closest to the prettiest thing, which is the river.
So
Yeah.
Okay, so it sounds like we're on the right path here.
So I'll piggybacking on James's comment.
Sorry, sorry, Theresa.
Can we look for putting a temp sign on temporary signage, which can be moved?
Like, can we put a temporary sign on the residence side?
like the property, residence property that you just showed, can we request them for a temporary sign for now?
And then when this project is done, we can actually move it to a permanent location.
I think that's certainly an option.
I just think if we were to put in this interpretive sign, as you're seeing now, where it's something that people have to walk up to, the city is just in an obligation to make it accessible to get to that site.
Oh, yeah.
But I think a temporary sign, though, might
Skirt that a little bit because, you know, nobody's saying it's going to be here forever.
It's just, you know, temporary thing.
I think that's a great idea to explore that.
That's a great idea.
Yeah.
Write it down and that's something I think we could also churn out faster than, you know, this design framed thing, you know, make.
Well, how about I bring that to Mr. Spagnola at the high school?
Absolutely.
And we can go from there.
What were you envisioning?
If I may ask Basita, what were you kind of picturing?
Like an A-frame sign, like a sandwich board sign, or just something that is still stuck in the ground, just not...
as a labyrinth?
Yeah, I think something that's still stuck in the ground, but we don't want to potentially damage the ground if we're using the residence property.
Anything that goes into the ground definitely needs a little bit of foundation, concrete, and everything on it.
So minimal damage, but still the sign can be there for maybe two years if we're expecting the DCR to put a walkway for two years.
And it can be replaced.
And it doesn't need to be elaborate, huge sign.
It can just say that, you know, you're welcome to historic district, just maybe a two by two, small one.
Yeah.
I think we're in a position where we could move quicker on the blade signs that just say South Street Historic District, like what's on the screen.
I could probably even just order them online and have them in a week and then go to DPW, you know.
So... I'm speaking aloud a bit there.
Why don't I bring that idea to Mr. Spagnuolo and, you know, he's a graphic designer.
He might have some more thoughts.
I'm not a designer.
I have thoughts and I can, I think, cobble things together, but, you know,
And again, I think it would be fun to see what the class comes up with.
Yeah, that's true.
Yeah.
Not trying to voice the responsibility onto the kids, but trying to get them involved in it.
I'll tell you, if they really do that, that would be excellent.
Yeah.
And they'll be excited, too, to have their design something in the city.
They'll walk through it and then be like, oh, wow, this is something I did.
Right.
community fridge that's here in Medford Square, the vocational school built the shed that's around it.
And, you know, they're so proud of it.
That's awesome.
You know, have a little impact on the community.
All right.
Awesome.
And in terms of the locations, it sounds like where we like make sense where they are.
Is everyone okay with the locations?
Okay, great.
Fantastic.
I don't know if we need to necessarily vote on it.
um we don't need to then yeah because i mean this is still subject to dpw they may come back to me and say like oh no you can't do that teresa you know um yeah and on the on the sign post what are we gonna it is that something that can just be purchased are we just gonna go right onto that sign post um i think it would look a little i like keeping the um
yes my personal opinion you know that you're the committee here um let's just use something a little bit nicer okay yeah yeah other districts it doesn't happen yeah i don't want to go over anything over something that looks like power strut yeah so uh yeah cool all right so i will proceed thank you very much for your thank you your thoughts on that one
I know next on the agenda is to review a drafted informative mailer.
I did not get a chance to finalize the mailer, but this is something that the board has talked about in the past just to help bring more awareness to either new homeowners or existing homeowners in our districts just to make them aware.
What I can
show and I'd love to get folks's feedback maybe and that would give me a little bit of a point me in a direction.
If I may share a couple of examples of what other communities do.
I'm going to share my screen again.
Sorry, it keeps like, I keep bouncing around.
All right, so folks should be seeing, I know it kind of looks funky, but it is a trifold.
So if you can envision it folded, where it says preserve one of the most important assets in your neighborhood, that would be the front page.
And then this orange section here is the back side.
This is from Milwaukee, but I think this is really a great example of what can be done.
At least the content, it still applies.
to here in New England.
So it just kind of has some overview of what type of work needs to come before the board for review, certificate of appropriateness.
I think this is actually a really big one to the financial assistance.
We have a lot of folks in Medford who are
I don't want to say house rich, cash poor, but a lot of low and moderate income homeowners happen to also be homeowners of historic buildings.
So in my other role in City Hall, I get a lot of inquiries from folks saying, hi, I live on a fixed income, but I need a new roof, or I need a new window, and I live in a historic home.
Are there any grant programs out there for me?
And the answer is yes.
super robust, but you know, there's historical tax credits that are out there.
There are a couple of grant programs that will help, you know, fund smaller projects.
So I think it's, I'd love to really see people taking advantage of that.
Yeah.
And maybe they just don't know, you know, people don't know.
Right.
So I, you know, this is again, centric to Wisconsin, but, um, but we can tweak it obviously for Medford, uh, for Massachusetts.
Um,
So I think it's, I love this example just because it's eye-catching, it's informative, you know, it's something that they won't just throw away, you know, if it's a postcard or an envelope stuffed with a letter, they might just, you know, but this is something they might tuck away.
Any initial thoughts?
I would make sure that it has the city seal on it, because otherwise this would end up in the barrel of my house.
I would not even spend two seconds looking at it.
Interesting, so you think because it just might blend in with other marketing materials?
Yeah, it looks like a marketing material to me, like they're trying to buy my house or something.
It does a little bit give the marketing fields, but we are trying to give them helpful information.
I've also noticed that a few like goodies, something like that.
I recently got a realtor's card as a refrigerator magnet, and it had all his information on it.
It's something you put on.
You might use it.
So can we add something like that that can be in front of them when they are cooking or just looking somewhere?
It can catch their eye now and then.
Yeah.
I think we have so few homes that this could be something.
I keep calling it a mailer.
It could be something that I'd be willing to go and hand deliver.
It would take an afternoon.
But maybe we could print up like a magnet that goes on the fridge.
So I could hand out the mailer with like a little goodie thing, you know, clip to it to see that it worked.
Yeah.
So it's just like, you know, this is, it just says that your home is a historic, your home is a historic home.
So, and then you just have a QR code that says, you know, when you scan the QR code, you just,
get all this information that's on the mailer.
Yeah.
And it's always on their fridge.
So whenever you think of something, you just scan the QR code on your fridge and then you're, even if you lose the mailer, you just still have this information handy on your phone.
I love that idea.
Um, you know, and have it be like a fun thing, not just, yeah.
Um, I like that idea.
And, and Magna is cheap money.
You know, I could probably get a hundred of them for,
less than 100 bucks, you know.
Not that I'm spending your budget or anything.
It's there for a reason.
No, that's a great idea.
Yeah.
What do you think, James?
I was going to say, the other thing I would do, just as you've kind of flipped through the different pages, and I don't know when they produced this.
I think it looks terrific.
I would almost say that the contact information, whether it's the hotline, a website, whatever it is,
I'd put that a little more front and center.
Yeah.
Because as I'm reading through it, like on this one all the way at the bottom on the left hand side, it seems like it has phone numbers.
And then I think we're on the second or third page before you actually see a website.
And all of this could also be on the website with additional links and things like that to other local and state resources and stuff like that.
Yeah.
I'd like to see on a two with some, if we could tuck it in somewhere that, you know, we'd love their participation on the board.
We're always looking for new members or come join us every where we meet them.
Yeah.
Yep.
All right.
I do have another option.
It's a, it's a little bit more.
just a letter that would get stuffed into an envelope.
And I think this one comes from... That one's easy on the eyes.
It's nice reading something like that.
Yeah.
Let me just do a quick share of the other one, just so you can see.
This is an example coming from our friends in Norwell.
Beautiful.
They mailed it, yeah.
They mailed this out.
Every February so folks will see the same letter coming through them, you know, year over year, but.
It's a little bit just more high level informative.
If we go this route, we definitely have to have the magnet.
Yeah, because this isn't one you hold on to.
If you held on to this, you forgot where you put it after.
Yeah, I think it's good content, but it isn't eye-catching.
I think a lot of this content could probably be something that could be put on the website.
Yes, absolutely.
And with the tri-fold,
That's the pizzazz.
That's the thing that gets somebody excited.
They're interested.
They stop because there's graphics, there's color, there's something.
And then when they go to the website, not that it turns into blah, but when you go to the website, then you can kind of drill down and find this different kind of information.
And it almost looks like it'd be a little more of a about us or who we are, what we do.
right and if someone if someone's gotten to that point that they've gone to the website to look at it they're probably interested enough to where they are going to read it anyway exactly okay so um i'm hearing that maybe we should stick with the trifold um i'm gonna go ahead and stop sharing this but um stick with the trifold but make it a little bit more
You know, I'm definitely meant for it if I, but okay.
So moving some contact information, make that front and center, adding in a call to come join us, whether as, as a member or just to join our meetings.
Okay.
That's, that was super helpful.
Cause I was trying to start it from scratch and you know, now I have a little bit of a direction, so I'm confident that our next meeting I'll have, I'll have one to review as well as a magnet.
I love that idea.
OK.
Well, thank you, everybody, for that input.
I super appreciate that.
The next topic?
Yeah.
So Hillside Avenue, we're fielding a lot of phone calls, I guess.
Yes.
So these next two projects are just more awareness.
So first, 20 Hillside Avenue.
It's a home that is in the Hillside Avenue historic district right here in Medford Square.
It recently went on the market and it sold like in two seconds to, we're presuming a cash buyer.
So this is a home that definitely needs some restoration.
The listing was very clear on that.
You can see from the photos, it had beautiful bones, but it definitely needs some work, I would say, as well as on the exterior.
So this is more of a heads up.
Maybe if you want to go drive by the house, buy it.
Because I imagine that soon we will see something.
Because somebody bought it with the intention of putting work into it.
But yeah, it's a gorgeous house.
I wish I had... I think it ended up selling for $810,000, which is a steal in Medford at this point.
So yeah.
and the buyer is aware that it's a historic district house?
Yes, I will.
I don't recall who the listing agent was, but I actually want to commend them for putting that front and center in the listing.
You know, I think it was mentioned on three separate times, like, this is a historic district, which is why I was getting quite a few calls when it hit the market asking, OK, my buyers are interested in this.
What does it mean?
Like, what type, what would be the next steps?
for if we were to buy this property and we want to do some work to it.
And does the website have the guidelines listed on the MedFed Historic District Commission website?
It does.
I will say the website needs a bit of a sprucing up, but our guidelines and how to, you know, for anybody who had those questions of like, how do I, what do I do?
owning a home in a historic district, they could eventually find that information online.
It is out there.
Just trying to make it a little bit easier for folks to find.
I'm just trying to save you time from people like how did you on the phone?
But I mean, even if you put attention, you know, yeah, it's still going to call you.
Yeah.
And that's that's OK.
It's my job.
It was just comical at one point.
I think I talked to like eight people on the same day, just saying the same thing over and over again.
Which is good, I'm glad they were calling.
That means they were doing their due diligence rather than somebody just buying the property and then figuring it out afterwards.
So again, no real action on this one.
Just, you know, if you're so inclined, I might encourage you to take a walk by the house or drive by it just to acquaint yourself with it.
Because I'm sure something's coming soon.
So that was 20 hillsides.
And then we got 41 Mystic F.
So yeah, 41 Mystic Ave, this board has been asked by the historical commission to, again, acquaint yourself with the property and then perhaps explore whether we would be interested in pursuing a historic district designation for this property.
This property is 41 Mystic Ave.
It sits on Mystic Ave, which is, as y'all know,
and very industrial area.
It is being targeted as an area for rezoning and, you know, redevelopment.
So right now it's a historic home that kind of sticks out in the middle of nowhere.
Is this that one that's next to the guitar shop that looks like it's going to... It actually has like... I'll pull it up here real quick and do an aerial view because it has what looks like a car lot all around it.
Okay.
I'm going to do another screen share.
Sorry, folks.
Hopefully you're not getting motion sickness from it all.
All right.
So this is 41 Mystic.
You should be seeing a property here.
What's significant about this property, it is one of the last 12 buildings in Medford that are pre-18th century.
This house was built in 1750.
I know it doesn't really look significant.
It's certainly been hacked apart and added on and a dormer put in and all that stuff.
So it doesn't obviously look like a 1750 house, but nevertheless.
So what triggered the historic board to
Yeah, is he applied for a permit?
Yeah, something the property owner has applied for a demolition permit to raise it to the ground.
Okay.
Um, just for everybody else's quick, just quick education.
Uh, the historical commission, they review, um, all permit, um, all properties slated for even partial demo.
If it's over 75 years old, the property.
So that's, that's their job is to evaluate.
Should we try to preserve this house?
or just allow it to go ahead and be demolished.
Could you move us to the other side?
Is that Columbia Road, I guess?
I think that's what the rest of the house looks like.
Yeah.
And if I do an aerial, which I can do,
Sorry.
You can see that it is completely surrounded by cars.
It's a car lot.
Yeah.
So there's nothing really interesting else about the property.
It's just the home itself.
Another thing to note, this property has already been moved twice.
I was just thinking that.
I was going to ask that.
What if they moved it?
Yeah.
Um, I recall it's it, the whole family, um, is significant to Medford because Isaac Hall was a captain in the, um, uh, and he was actually the, the first house that on Paul Revere's midnight ride that he stopped in and said, the British are coming.
It was actually at captain Isaac Hall's house, um, which is right on, on main street.
I'm sorry.
High street.
This house was owned by a member of the Hall family.
I'm not sure if it was a uncle or brother, but Benjamin Hall owned the home.
So there's a little bit of a historical tie there.
I don't think anybody would say that this is a beautiful building.
And gosh, look at that.
Isn't it so lovely historic, but it does have significance for its, you know, the pedigree of the house has significance.
Was it always,
That size?
I mean, that seems like a pretty big house.
Yeah, I think it's a four.
I'm pretty sure it was.
I think I have the 40.
Actually, hold on.
I might have.
In the meeting packet.
Yeah, I actually just stopped sharing because I'm sharing this.
I'm so sorry.
1752.
Here we go.
I'm scrolling through to see.
I think there was, again, I'm so sorry about that.
There we go.
Okay.
So it was originally at the foot of Governor's Ave where enters High Street.
So it looks like there was an addition in the back perhaps, but overall, I think the footprint really doesn't seem to have changed too much.
No, no, maybe.
But regardless, so
The property owner has not requested this.
This is coming from the historical commission to see if we would support this property being put into a local historic district.
I mean, we could, we could reach out to the property owner and see if they're interested in that.
I don't think they're going to be seeing that they'll demolish it.
Yes.
A thought I had was, heck, this house has already moved twice.
Could it be picked up and moved again, and then maybe donated?
Again, it's not a beautiful piece of architecture.
And it doesn't need to be.
It doesn't need to be.
But your thoughts?
I think the thing that gets me is
just the age of the house.
It's survived this long.
I mean, it was built before America was America.
Yes.
And it just seems to me that even
even though if you were going to bring it back to that photograph, you know, looking at that picture, I mean, it would need a lot of restoration work.
It would, I mean, you know, maybe if fingers crossed, if you tore off all the vinyl siding and stuff like that, maybe all that coining is still there.
Maybe the old siding is still there.
Maybe, maybe, maybe, I don't know.
But it's kind of one of those things where, what would you do with it?
you know where where where could it go where could it be reused is there is there any place in Medford or for that matter in one of the abutting communities that they would want a visitor center they have a park where it could go in and said it could be used for something there I mean is there anything anything like that you know because otherwise I
I don't really know what you do with it.
And if you put it in a historic district and prevent people from tearing it down, or really doing a whole lot to it, would it then start to suffer?
Because what is somebody gonna do with it where it's located now?
Other than maybe make it into the office of a business or something, you know, maybe I'm making this, you know, electrician buys it and that becomes their office for their business or something, I don't know.
When was it, so the Dormer addition, and that I'd assume was done when it was moved, when was it moved from, to the location that it is now?
I want to say it was, the first time it was moved, I think it was late 1800s.
It says that it was 1835 to 1894.
Is that the one?
Yes.
Thank you.
And then it was moved again in like the 19th?
Yeah.
I can certainly pull that information together.
It is, you know, this form B, which again was in the meeting packet.
I would encourage folks to read through it thoroughly.
It is pretty comprehensive about the history of the home.
Again, big takeaways here.
I don't know for certain, but I doubt there would be support from the property owner.
to keep it in its place.
And the argument's going to be that it's, so yeah, the part of it is, you know, 1700s or whatever, but then it got moved at a much later time and then altered at that time.
You're going to get the, you know, the George Washington's X argument, which is, you know,
I have George Washington's axe, the handle's been replaced five times, and the head's been replaced three times.
Right.
You know?
Yeah.
Oh, when's this?
Okay, so this one's showing the dormer.
What year is that?
1800s, circa late 1800s, late 1890s.
So this is it, where it's currently at, yeah, corner of Columbia and Mystic.
The work that was, I mean,
The work done to the front of it looks nice.
Is there an incentive?
Is there something that can be done to incentivize moving it?
There's not a lot of places to put it.
That would be a much bigger conversation than I think this board.
My understanding is that the intention is to demolish and then put something that's, you know, multiple stories high, really dense housing.
I believe that's my understanding.
Yeah.
You know, whether or not the project is by right by the zoning that's there, you know, there might be, I don't want to say an opportunity for negotiation, but, you know, as part of the review of that, maybe there's a little,
Hey, would you be willing to do this?
I don't think the city could compel them to, certainly.
But at least there's an opportunity to maybe have a conversation there.
I don't know who would pay for that.
I don't know where it would go.
There's a lot of questions there.
If we were to move the house again.
Yeah.
I will say that the city, I reiterate, the city is looking to revitalize the Mystic Ave corridor.
So, you know, single family, two families aren't really the direction.
And it's kind of vision, you know, I mean, the whole area changed around this house, you know, like in the back.
Yeah.
Um, so.
But it is a 1750s house that is still standing and still gets mail delivered to it.
So it's something to strongly consider.
And honestly, other than that two-story piece that they kind of stuck on the front of it, the dormer has been there since
1800s.
So I would almost I would almost consider that I would consider that to be kind of historic because okay, how many how many historic houses are around that also have additions that his family's got bigger as you know, whatever happened, they reuse things like that.
So actually quite a bit of that house is intact.
I mean, it's all the form of it is still there.
Yeah, you know, so it's not like it's been
It's not like it's been butchered to pieces and it's like, you know, like we said, yeah, we've changed the handle five times and the head three times.
You know, it's like, no, it's still pretty close, you know.
So I don't know.
I guess if it could be moved and if there was a use for it, whether it was to be used for residential or for some other purpose,
If there was a way to do it, I'd try that.
But if not, I mean, it really doesn't belong where it is anymore.
Yeah, I want to see it saved, but I don't.
Maybe not in that location.
Yeah, not in that location.
I'd like to do whatever it takes to move that.
Whatever would help move it that we could do.
Cause the thing is, is it's going to be a lot of money to renovate that too.
And it's just a losing situation for whoever's going to be doing that.
Yeah.
But maybe somebody would be really excited about the projects.
Some, I have no idea.
Um, it's, it's having a, I mean the money it's having a bank that's, you know, cause they're the ones that, you know, okay, let's, what's the appraised value.
Okay.
We're not lending you the money, you know?
Yeah.
I've been there.
I've been down that road a bunch of times.
Okay, well, when I'm hearing, just because the historical commission has asked for our thoughts on this, they haven't asked for official support or an opinion or anything, I'll take back to them that it sounds like we would love to see the building preserved.
I'm sorry, you mind?
Could we reach out to the homeowner?
Because you never know.
Because the thing, look, I mean, there are programs, there's some type of incentive.
You know, we can do whatever we can do to help him out to get those programs.
And you never know.
Yeah.
And at this point, the only information I have about the property owner's position on this
is that they applied for a demolition permit.
So who knows?
Yeah, I'd be comfortable reaching out to them just to have an initial conversation.
And they may tell me to pound sand, and that's fine.
But at least we'll have an opportunity to talk about doing something alternative with this rather than just taking it down to the ground.
Then you can get into the conversation of moving it.
Yeah, yeah.
So everybody would be okay with me.
I do want to do have the follow-up with the historical commission just as like an informal, just like here's where we're feeling right now.
So if everybody's okay with it, I'll say we believe in preserving the building.
We want to explore with the homeowner whether they'd be open to moving the property again.
Yeah.
That would be okay?
All right.
I don't want you putting words in anybody else's mouth.
No, very well put.
Was the initial idea,
and I think it was said when we started talking about this, to somehow incorporate it into a local district.
Is there a local district anywhere?
No.
Yeah, I also think that would be, I mean, I know if I was the owner of that house and all of a sudden, oh, hey, yeah, we put it on a historic district because we want to stop you.
It's like, nah, I don't think that would go over too well.
Yeah.
We don't want to be
those people who would do that to somebody, quite honestly.
I think that would be more ill will than anything else.
That's a good point.
That's why approaching it like this incentive, saying, hey, this incentives with the grants or whatever, did you explore these options?
This board is more than willing to help you with that.
I bet he might be receptive to that or maybe not, who knows.
I don't know.
But we should talk to them and see.
But OK.
Thank you very much.
I will reach out to my friend on the Historical Commission just to have an informal.
And then I'll reach out to the property owner and just have a casual conversation with them, see what can come of that.
Awesome.
Great.
All right.
Well, thank you very much on that.
And I think the only thing we have left is
I have the meeting minutes in the folder, which, where's my, reorienting myself here.
So meeting minutes, I did not have them ready to go for the walking tour we did, because I'm not sure how to wrap my head around those minutes quite yet.
It wasn't a formal sit-down meeting, but we do have to have some sort of minutes captured for that.
I also have a copy of the minutes here for you, Joe, but do we want to... I guess you would be looking, Joe, for a motion to accept the minutes.
Looks great, so did anyone read through that and make a motion to accept it?
Motion to accept the minutes.
All right.
Can someone second that?
I wasn't present, but then I can second it.
It's pretty clear.
Great.
Okay.
So let's take a vote.
James?
Yes.
I. Has he done?
And I vote yes, too.
So it's good.
It's accepted.
Thank you very much.
Again, you're just voting to accept the minutes.
Vouch for what's in them, you know, that's all the stuff on the agenda.
Does anyone else have anything they want to bring up?
But do or.
No, I'm good.
All right.
So our next meeting would be on November 13th.
Sounds good.
Okay, if there's any conflicts, let me know, but I'll send out.
Was that helpful?
I feel like I may have been obnoxious with the amount of reminders for this meeting, but was that helpful for everybody?
It was helpful.
Yes, yes.
I'm not going to lie to you.
I thought it was, I was so turned around this week.
I thought it was Tuesday.
And then when I saw it tonight, I was just about ready to head out the door from my office.
And I'm like, dope.
So I sat back.
So thank you.
Thank you.
I appreciate that.
All right.
That's great.
So if everything's all set, can we make a motion to close the meeting?
Motion to close the meeting?
Can you second that?
All right.
Let's have a vote on that.
James?
Yes.
And I vote yes as well.
So the meeting's over.
All right.
See you guys next month.
Thanks, everybody.
Thank you.
Bye.