This is the Stupid Siblings Show.
A podcast about moments with siblings.
Siblings, the uncontrollable annoyance of your life.
Whether they're older, younger, twin, or triplet, they will be annoying.
And we're here to talk about that.
Penny, age nine.
Conrad, age 10.
Izzy, age 10.
Juniper, age 10.
Annika, nine and a half.
So, what is your sibling's name?
Annika.
Maggie.
Izzy.
Willa and Ava.
Penny.
Um, Clark.
What is the gender of your sibling?
Annika?
Girl.
Penny?
Clark!
The gender of your sibling?
Okay, boy, boy, come on.
Okay.
How old is your sibling?
A tiny bit over seven.
Ozzy?
Two for Willa and six for Ava.
Okay, and Penny?
Almost seven, but he's still six.
If you could describe your sibling in one word, what would you use as the word?
And it can't be anything like crazy.
Annoying.
Obviously.
Stupid.
Annoying.
Obviously.
Everyone knows that.
Stupid.
Scoopid.
Obviously, that's the name of our podcast.
Now, Penny... Awful.
Congratulations.
Just plain awful.
Okay, on a scale of 1 to 10 of annoyance, what would you rate them?
I would rate them... 11.
Pass.
Okay.
I would rate them 15.
I would rate it a 5,000.
okay now is the craziest what is the craziest thing they have ever done to you well this isn't the craziest thing they've done to me but i know it's the craziest thing they've done
We, one time, were in an art museum, and then they, my sister, had to start touching things.
So she ran around, like, touching, like, the Mona Lisa and stuff.
Well, not the Mona Lisa, but very famous paintings, and, like, by Leonardo da Vinci, Vince Van Gogh, and, like, needed to run and wrestle in the hallway.
Izzy?
Penny.
Well, one time my brother, well, I was in the basement doing my piano practice and my brother thought, I asked him for a snack, so I called him like, Clark, get me a snack that I like.
And he brought me cereal.
The milk on the piano and everywhere.
What the heck?
Izzy?
During my piano practice, just like Penny, my sister came in, interrupted it, and said a blaggledy bloop right in front of my piano teacher.
What the heck?
And for the crazy... And I really don't have a sibling.
How do you consider yourself an angel or a devil and how does your sibling consider themselves an angel or a devil?
Izzy?
I consider myself a devil.
Also, I know I didn't say myself.
Devil.
Do you consider yourself an angel or a devil?
Izzy?
I consider myself a devil.
Anika?
Devil.
Ava?
Conrad?
Just to be separate from all you weirdos, I'm gonna say angel.
I am obviously the angel of my family.
Penny might not be speaking the truth.
I am!
I so am!
And I consider myself a, and I know this might sound crazy, but I consider myself a devil.
Now, for the next question.
Aren't we all devils?
Shut up!
How would you describe yourself in one word?
Izzy.
From my sister's perspective, very, very annoying.
Annika.
Okay, we'll get back to you, Annika.
Conrad, speak to the mic.
Mike is actually spelled M-I-C.
I know.
The most amazing thing on the earth!
That's more than two, that's more than one word.
That's seven words.
Fine.
Awesome!
Ava, I forgot who... I would say weird.
What would you say, describe yourself in one word?
No!
Come on.
We need to stop that.
No, we don't stop.
Weird!
And I think I would describe myself in one word as... I think I would describe myself as psychotic.
Now, how would you describe your sibling, Izzy?
Very stupid and annoying.
Izzy, how would you describe your sibling?
Very, very stupid and annoying.
Ava?
Dumb and annoying.
Well, probably I would describe my sibling as the worst thing possible.
And Clark.
I'm just gonna leave.
And now me, Clark, my opinion is my sibling might be the weirdest thing ever.
Okay, I take mine back.
Mine actually is also the weirdest thing ever.
Okay, now say the craziest thing your sibling has ever done.
Annika!
How would you describe your sibling in love on a scale of 1 to 10?
And it can't just be like a negative 50.
Izzy, how would you describe your sibling on a scale of 1 to 10 in love?
Who ripped our sticker?
Who?
Are you?
Oh, I did.
And by the way, it's not ripped.
Izzy, how would you describe your sibling in love on a scale of 1 to 10?
Izzy?
Zero.
Conrad?
Five.
Anika?
You don't have a sibling.
I don't care.
I answered for you.
Ha.
Anika?
Eleven because... actually no.
Ten because she loves... Because she loves me too much that she copies me every second of the day.
Quit it!
isn't it called like there's a word for that tobycat no it's like an actual like an actual good one that big kids use i'm older you know and ava
Clark is a seven.
I'm three and I hate my sister because well my sister smells like farts.
I'm six and
I think my sister is an alien.
Don't tell her that.
do you ever wish you could just slap your sibling in the face with a diapy then look no further the slappy diapy it's a diaper that you can just slap your sibling with with fake poop and pee inside so you're walking through the house your siblings trying to hit you normal day but then you whip around and slap it and it's in the face of your sibling is the slappy diapy
now if that's not all for you and if you don't just want to slap your sibling in the face and you want to put that diaper on them but that diapers sealed full of fake stuff well guess what our newest model the real diapy
It is something that you can fill with an assortment of gross items that comes with every purchase.
If you just send us their shoe size, shirt size, most likely underwear size, any size, then we can get you a perfectly fitting diaper to put in their face, head, butt, anywhere else.
And the best part is,
It will never break.
And you might be wondering, well, what does this do?
It's the same thing as the other one, except we can change out stuff inside of it and our siblings can wear it.
But the difference is, your sibling will be so stunned you put a diaper on them, full of fake, slimy goo and everything like that, that they won't move.
And they'll just be quiet for the rest of...
Three seconds.
Available at dybey.com.
Yes, find our products at dybey.com.
just go to dypee.com please.