No, that's a school committee meeting. So if you're not listening to this, um, so I just, right. Um, so I would like to know what's going to happen with my big thing is animal waste. I already have holes in my barrel. The rats have already chewed through. And so what do we do? Like cat waste, dog waste, baby diapers, because
When we had people come around here to handle the rats, they said the big thing is like dog waste. Make sure you pick up your dog waste, you throw it out. Well, we do that, but now in the rats, it's just gonna attract them more to the barrels that they chew through. I can't put, use a disposal. We don't throw food outside, but we have a bigger family and we're always full at the end of the week.
So i'm not sure How this is going to work And for these questions, are you going to like put them online to kind of eat what we're asking?
Yes, we're going to be updating the frequently asked questions section that's on the website. And the website is on that slide there. Yep. So there's a lot of feedback, just so everybody realizes it's worth repeating. There's a lot of feedback, a lot of people want to speak. So we're trying to, you know, take the most common frequent question answers. And if we don't have answers, as was mentioned before, or if there's a gap somewhere, then we're going to try to
fill that and make updates as needed. So that's really what the goal is here. All right. So thank you, Jessica. You're welcome. All right. I'm going to mute you and lower your hand. And then we're going to move to Daniel. I can't see the whole name, actually, unless I go.
One second, Daniel Rosenwig. Hi, I'm Daniel Rosenswig. I live on Wilson Street. I'm native to the greater Boston area, but pretty new to Medford specifically. I'm already composting. That's a great program. Thank you. Trash cost is for collection versus how much for disposal.
Along the same lines of Robert, who spoke recently, I'm not concerned about paying for a bit of extra volume, but I am concerned about having it sit there for two weeks. And I'm particularly concerned that excess might sit outside proper containers, and therefore more exposed to animals. You have said that extra containers are available, but they only make sense if you'll overfill every week, and not if you overfill on an erratic basis.
I do think that composting will help to reduce the volume, but I'm concerned it won't reduce it enough. Another speaker mentioned that pay as you throw has reduced waste by 32% elsewhere, but in order to make things work based on our existing consumption, it would have to be reduced by 50%. And that's a lot. I also think that our waste limits should be dependent on the number of residents.
for a two-person household might not make sense for a six-person family. And if we could have different limits, depending on your household size, that's a big difference for all of us. And the tighter our limits are, the more that becomes an issue. You know, right now, if we have some spare room, maybe it's not such a big deal, the same limit. But when it becomes really tight, I think that'll matter a lot more. All right. Thank you very much, Daniel.
T Silvestro is next. T Silvestro, I'll ask you to unmute. Please, your name and address. Thank you. Hello? Hello, welcome.
Hi, my name is Tony Silvestro. I live at 5 Royal Street in Medford. My biggest concern is I live in South Medford and the rat population. I've already lost one dog to leptoporosis in 2021, the pandemic with all the rats. But I also have two dogs and I have a lot of waste. And I am also a senior citizen. So my biggest concern is the senior citizens are going to be able to reel that cart out every other week.
It's going to be heavy. It's all kinds of crap. Pardon my language, but I just, I don't understand it. And if you're going to save money, are you going to give it back to us in our tax bill and lower our taxes? Um, those are my big concerns. And, but the biggest one is the rats. And I have had to hire an exterminator. I have rat boxes all around my house.
The house across the street from me is an apartment building. They have their barrels are so overfilled. It's not funny and half of it when it blows flows down my driveway. So that those are my big concerns. And that's about all I have to say. And I'm going to tell everybody please make sure your dogs process because it's not a fun thing to see your dog die from. Thank you very much. Thank you, Tony. Next up is TK.
TK, when I unmute you, please, your name and address, and you'll have two minutes. Good evening, Tom Kubelos at Toro Avenue in Medford. Toro Avenue in Medford, how are you all? My comment is essentially around the pain. In other Massachusetts communities, residents have the option to choose to holler.
That would mean multiple haulers could be down your street on a given day. All it takes is one home to request a haul. And now we have two trash trucks going down the road. Has that been thought about? And also, is that built into the metrics regarding the use of trucks on roads and the damage to its targets? Thank you. Thank you, TK.
All right, next up is Erin Dalbeck. I'm going to ask you to unmute, name and address for the record, please. Thank you. Hi there. Can you hear me? I can, Erin. Welcome. Thank you. I don't have a lot to say. I just wanted to say I'm in favor of this new trash program. I've seen, personally, composting has decreased my family's need for weekly trash pickup.
I have a dog and we have a container that does lock and it stays outside. And I've never seen any rats around my compost or in my trash area or in my dog's poop bag area.
Um, I just really love the idea of how this is the mission behind it. I like that. It's going to save our city money. Um, and, um, I feel like it's just the future of our country, what we should all be doing, um, to adapt. Um, and I think that's it. So thank you for all your work. Thank you. All right. Next is Stephanie Bima, Serez.
When I unmute you, please your name and address for the record, and you'll have two minutes. Thank you. Hi, Stephanie. Hi. I'm Stephanie Behme. I live on Broadway. So Broadway is owned by Medford, but I'm actually not sure how much of this applies to my service because the road is owned by Somerville. But anyway, I think it's a great presentation. I understand it's been long in the works.
I'm not an expert in this area, but of sustainability information. And from what I understand, pay as you go and the composting availability and everything, this is directionally, as maybe was also reflected by the awards and the rankings, this is directionally where things are going. Also based on my travels in other countries, the places where their waste management is like you experience it the best, they have pay as you go systems, like Japan, for example.
So anyway, I think it's great and I want to support it. And my suggestion is that perhaps you could in the future touch more on the plans that the city with the rollout. Could any part of it be progressive or gradual? And as it rolls out and people adjust to it, what are the end points of feedback and possibilities for adjustment? For example, if people need loaner bins or, you know,
increases in their volumes. So perhaps addressing some of those concerns. Thanks. Thank you, Stephanie. Good suggestions. All right. We're going to move on to Patty Kaya. Patty Kaya, when I unmute you, could you please list your name and address? And you'll have two minutes. Thank you. Welcome, Patty.
by patty k a monument street and i only have one question though i do have a couple of comments the question is how do we stop this how do we stop this train before it leaves the station um i disagree with the reducing the cadence of garbage pickup for all the same reasons that many people have have said on this call social media have said on the fourteen hundred
signatory petition against this reduction in such an essential public service for all environmental concerns that we're trying to address. My problem is that this should be the absolute last resort. Taking away weekly trash pickup should be the last thing you do, not the first thing you do. And there are people on this call that have come up with solutions that would reduce the waste product that we're talking about
before we would cut people's essential service for all of the health and safety concerns out. So we didn't vote on this. We didn't have any input. And my last comment is about the way that outreach has been handled by the city.
It's almost like you think you can educate us into submission, as if we're all too ignorant to understand the environmental context of the problem, the greater problem. We think it's the wrong solution to the problem, so you can keep trying to educate us. We're not too dumb to understand. We think it's the wrong solution. We don't ignore the fact that there's a problem.
And we're asking you to rise above and try something else first. Try other things first. That's the problem. The survey was incredibly leading questions. This educational event tonight isn't about listening. It's about telling us that we're too dumb to understand why you're doing it. I would like some more respect from the city. Thank you very much.
Thank you, Patty. I know I respect every single one of you. So there's that. All right. Thank you. We're going to move on to Jen. Jen, I'm going to ask you to unmute. And of course, as a reminder to everybody, I'm trying to do this out of the utmost respect for all of you. So Jen, if you could list your name and address, and you'll have two minutes. Thank you very much.
Hi, Jen Segotsky, Placedead Road. I'm just going to piggyback on what Patty was saying. I feel like the city has been pushing toward having a half of the pickup that we have right now, but they're not addressing the fact that there are not currently that many options for reducing the amount of trash that we have. There are certain things like soft plastics and Styrofoam in particular that are very hard to recycle or get rid of other than in the trash.
I think before we implement something like this, the city needs to have a harder push toward finding ways to recycle soft plastics, to recycling styrofoam, so that we can have the room in our bins, that it could be a lesser pickup. But right now, we live in a society where there's a lot of soft packaging, there's a lot of styrofoam. You know, if I get a piece of furniture delivered, it fills up my entire bin for the week. There's nothing I can do about that. There's no place.
My other concern is how do we avoid illegal dumping? As we saw with the mattresses, when the city started implementing having to pay to have mattresses picked up, I've had to call the city more than once for mattresses that have been dumped in random places, like my kids' school, for example. How is that not going to happen with trash going forward when people don't have room in their bins?
And the third thing is, I'm not sure why the city is not pushing for other solutions. Like, for example, we have this great online community called Everything is Free Medford, where people can post things and have other people pick them up, which keeps thousands and thousands of pounds of things out of the trash. Why the city is not pushing that more as an option for posting things to keep things out of the waste stream is just beyond me. Thank you, Jen. That was good feedback.
We're going to move on to Charlotte Cahill. Charlotte Cahill, I'll ask you to please report your name and address, and you'll have two minutes.
Great, thanks. Hi, Charlotte Cahill. I appreciate you creating this forum tonight and giving us an opportunity to provide some feedback. I want to start by just sort of echoing some of the public health and sanitation concerns that other people have shared.
regarding the shift to weekly or bi-weekly pickup. I'm not going to repeat everything that others have said on this, but would just add that I think one thing that's getting lodging around this is that the city's goal for composting is to have 19,000 households composting. If that goal is achieved, that's three quarters of households in the city, meaning that one in four households will still have food waste,
their trash and federal guidelines recommend weekly pickup of all food waste precisely for the kinds of public health reasons that folks here have been raising. So just want to really kind of like emphasize that point and I think the other thing that folks haven't, some people have talked some about like
cuts to an essential service. And what I want to call out really directly is that this is like creating an equity issue when you're cutting an essential public service. What this cut is doing is reframing a public health and sanitation service that should be civil government and turning that into a conversation about the consumption choices that individual people are making.
That's happening without any real meaningful effort that I can see to provide alternatives. So this isn't just about education. It's not about telling us that we're going to have access to the same recycling and compost programs that we have now. But what else can be done here? Thank you, Charlotte. And just to correct some information that you're putting out there, the compost service will go universal. So that's everybody who has eligible trash service now gets coal. So thank you.
All right, we're going to move to Catherine. Tim, can we just make that a little bit clearer? Sure. Because I've seen that out on the web before. When we say our goal is 19,000 households composting, 19,000 households is 100% of the households on the city's waste trash system. The total number of households in the city that is a higher number, those people are on commercial composting programs that are not run by the city. So our goal is composting.
100% of the eligible households composting. Correct. Thank you, Alicia. Now we'll move to Catherine. Catherine, I'll ask you to unmute. If you could report your name and address, you'll have two minutes. Thank you. Hello. Welcome.
Hi, thank you. I think I missed it the first time. Catherine Bradshaw Street, Medford. Lived here all my life. So the couple of people ahead of me did touch upon what was on
of the list of things that I did want to mention. I do want to ask though, I didn't see how we're going to, the city's going to make out with paying less money to go to the burning in Saugus versus
The difference that we make in garbage to God and that was one thing I felt unless I missed it during the presentation.
I did want to bring up the illegal dumping, though. So I travel down commercial to Riverside a lot. And before those apartments that are going to go up where CKS is, there's a lot of illegal dumping. It's dark over there. There's disfurniture. So I think we're going to see a lot more of that. Maybe not only there, but as other people had said,
You know, the mattresses being dumped when you get furniture. People leave it out on the street. I just want to mention, I have called four times from May to September. People leaving furniture out, you know, you're supposed to pay for it, they don't want to pay for it.
And then the city is saying to me, where is it? Why is it there? Oh, well, if you live there, like if someone dumps in front of your house, it's your responsibility. Well, I didn't put it there. I mean, I think that may be happening. And then maybe not to mention, possibly the fistfights that will be happening when people are using other people's trash barrels. I think those are things I just wanted to put out there. And thank you very much for listening. Thank you, Catherine. Appreciate it.
Okay, Nicholas Girlio. Nicholas, I'll ask you to unmute. If you could report your name and address, you'll have two minutes. Thank you. Real quick, may not have got you. Hopefully I did. If not, I'll do it again. You may have hit the one next to him. Oh, yes, I hit Fred. I'm going to unmute you again. Oh, you already did it himself. Thank you, Fred. And I'm going to try Nicholas one more time.
Welcome, Niklas.
Only about 20% of people could actually commit to a yes response. Now you compare this to the survey that was recently released, which doesn't ask do people want this service change, right? And it's full of loaded questions and really, really unscientific in a lot of ways. So my question for the city is very simply, will the city make a decision here that reflects what the majority wants?
Based on that poll, based on what people are saying here tonight, it seems that overwhelmingly, and based on what people have said leading to this, it seems overwhelmingly that people don't want this. So will the city listen? Will the city propose an alternative? And I fully understand and respect the financial implication, but will the city propose an alternative here that reflects what the majority wants? Thank you. Sure, Nick, you got a little bit of time left. I just wanted to ask a clarifying question. Was there a specific element of the program that you were speaking about?
the service change obviously to bi-weekly trash collection. Okay, you shouldn't say it. I had a feeling that's what you're talking about. I just wanted to make sure it was clear. Thank you. All right, we're going to move on to Fred Roach from Mute. If you could say your name and address, you'll have two minutes to speak. Thank you very much. Yes, hi. 77 Whittier Road in Medford.
I just want to go out there and say that I'm totally opposed to this. Big surprise. Second, I spoke to two landlords today at a social event. They don't live in the city. Neither landlord knew anything about a trash change. So I don't know what kind of notifications gone out, if any.
And, you know, this decision has already been made, and this has been in the residents' throats. And I've lived in the city for 65 years, and in 65 years, this is going to be the worst decision I've had from the city of Medford. And second of all, I have scrap plans to build an ADU because of this. So I don't know if your millions of dollars in savings is going to calculate what you're going to lose.
But that's my thoughts on it. I won't waste my time. I'll be wasting my time. Thank you, Fred. Just same question I had for Nicholas. I believe you were specifying the part of the program where it goes to every other week as opposed to like universal compost or other aspects of the program.
Absolutely. I just wanted to clarify. I have some time remaining, so let me comment. There's been no soliciting of the citizens with regard to how they feel. And if whatever's been done, it's been disregarded. And that's really a decision is going to come back and haunt the city. It really is. Thank you very much. Have a good night. Thank you, Fred.
I'm going to move to Sarah Berndt. Sorry if I'm mispronouncing that. Sarah Berndt. I'm going to ask you to unmute. You have your name and address. You'll have two minutes. Thank you. Hello? Hello. Can you hear me? Oh, there we go.
Welcome. Sarah, nice to see you all. Thank you all for being here. Um, I live on Sharon street. Um, and what others say are saying, you know, waste costs are up because plastic waste is a problem globally. Now, you know, we're, I don't think we are going to only compost our way out of this one. I think it's going to take, um, a more holistic approach. You know, our family already composts everything that we can. We try to reduce waste as much as possible.
We visit the local plastic-free refillery on Boston Ave, Trove Green Preservations. If you haven't heard of it, it's a great way to cut down on some of that packaging for your household goods. But like others have said, I'm also worried about trash sitting. We're pretty rat-free here in West Medford so far, knock on wood, but we really, really don't want any from Somerville over here across the river.
you know, dog waste, diapers, like people have said, the food waste, meat, all of those are going to be really, really smelly. I think, you know, the program in
And its intent is really great, but adoption is going to happen when we make things easier for people, not harder. I think we should be thinking of this more holistically, like can we increase soft plastic cycling to keep that part out of the trash? Can we provide free compost bags for families to drive them towards the composting program? So if we could just have options instead of feeling like we're punishing residents for having trash,
Maybe we try to think about this as a explore other areas for reducing trash overall. Thank you. Thank you, Sarah. Appreciate your comments. Okay. Shayna, over here to get the name here. Shayna Simenstein, if you could please address, you'll have two minutes. Welcome Shayna.
Hi, I am on Hume Ave in Hillside and I just wanted to thank everybody in the city for trying to address the really challenging problem of waste management because
Um, the cost of waste disposal is increasing, and, like, we are running out of places to put trash, and I think this is a, and so, like, I'm in full support of trying to find creative solutions to deal with this. Um, and, um, I guess I had just a couple of questions, I think, to reiterate a few other folks who have
like are in support of this, but also have some questions. And one is, what is the city going to do about all of the residential buildings that don't qualify for this because they have more than four or six units? I don't remember. Especially when the 2030 ban on food waste takes effect from the state.
And then my other question is, yeah, like, what is the city doing to kind of like holistically address this issue in addition to, like, trying to cut down on the waste stream through trash pickup, but...
Like through reducing plastic at the grocery store or takeout containers etc just to like help residents achieve the goal of having like half as much trash as they currently do. Because I think like what I'm hearing is a lot of the concern about this is like fear of not being able to fit everything in your bin. So I feel like
Having the city work on tangential issues that could help reduce waste would be really helpful, especially in the next 18 month lead up to this rollout. Thank you, Shana. Appreciate the comments. And it looks like we have Alessandra back. Alessandra's iPhone is next. So go ahead and unmute you. If you can let us know your name and address, you'll have 2 minutes.
Alessandra Cameron. Alessandra's iPhone, you hear? She told our troubleshooting staff that she was having trouble clicking the unmute button. Alessandra, if you want to message your comment to our troubleshooting staff, get it out for you, or you could email it to waste at medford-ma.gov that you see on the screen there. I'm really sorry that
you're having technical trouble. Yeah, sorry about that. Let's try it one more time for good measure. That doesn't work. Move to Jim Bennett. So Jim Bennett, get ready. All right, Jim Bennett, I'm going to go ahead and ask you to unmute. If you could guess, you'll have two minutes. Thank you.
Oh, there we go. Thank you. Yeah, I have a lot of the conservative this every two week pickup, but some of my I think the intent is good about reducing trash, doing more recycling, but I find our program is not. We do the standard recycling for the state. I understand that, but there are a lot of the programs and styrofoam is not very recyclable, but there are places will accept it in there.
Not in their curbside, but they have, um, but that fact, the recycling compost we have on there every, at least every two weeks, uh, getting rid of cardboard because yeah, you cycle bin, but try fitting everything in there with cardboard. It doesn't work.
And when you go to the compactor, you'll find a lot of people have stuff that shouldn't be in there, hard plastics, baskets, styrofoam. And recently I saw someone say that they don't flatten their, their cardboard. So that, that's an issue.
And I think that's great that it's there. I mean, years ago, I remember bringing bottles down and breaking them down at the city yard, probably in the 80s. But what I kind of, my other question too is, in the contract, my understanding is the contract was signed two years ago, but that's not correct. Correct me?
And in the consideration of the contract, do we look at different vendors? Do we look at dual stream? I mean, right now we dump all this paper in there with all the other stuff. It's not, it's a contaminated, more contaminated than a dual stream. And then there's a multi stream, which is, did we look into dual stream? Cause I know that's available in this area. I looked up a chart on the DEP.
nasty ep and i don't know if that was because you get a better product where you divide in your bottles your cans and your plastic um so i don't know if that was considered or not that would be bonus it seemed to be it would be better recycling uh cleaner non-contaminated thank you thank you um
So, we did go through a lengthy RFP process just to make sure folks understand that. So, lots of things were considered. So, the RFP process was comprehensive and lengthy. So, any of that information? It was comprehensive, but did it consider other streams, or? Yeah, comprehensive, that's what that means. So, all options were considered, yeah. All right, because single stream, I was never for single stream. I remember when we did paper, and we did our bottles and our cans and separate bins, and I was very happy with that.
Thank you, Jim. All right, we're going to move on to Ted Blake. So, Ted, I'm going to ask you to unmute if you could let us know your name and address. You'll have two minutes to speak. Thank you.
Hi, Ted Blake, Toro Ave. I'm going to skip some of the things that other people have said, concerns, dumping was one of the ones, concerns about single stream plastics, like, you know, making sure this is addressed, not just on the citizens, but you know, the residents, but on the grocery stores and things like that. The two other things that I just wanted to chime in that haven't been mentioned.
Number one, kind of going along with dumping is just the idea of like, I anticipate, I don't know, people just like filling up the bins at the parks and things like that. And so I'm just wondering if that's taken into account, just like if that there's going to be increased volume there. And the second one was if there's any potential solution for having a transfer station that's open to residents. I know other towns have transfer stations you can bring things to or instead of the pay-as-you-go bags. Thanks.
Thank you. And just to make sure folks know, a transfer station requires land and a whole different set of permitting, so we don't have one. Anyway, thank you. We're gonna move on to Christian's iPhone. iPhone, when I unmute you, if you could list your name and address, and you'll have two minutes, thank you. Christian. Did I say Christian? I meant Christine, sorry.
Thank you. I was got a little confused by that. I don't know why. I think, you know, I'm just starting to cross. Well, one, you know, a couple of the things I wanted to go over was, uh, using this single stream recycling. I'm thinking like how much money we could probably get just on paper and cardboard alone. I mean, a lot of cities and towns use that, but by using a single, we're wasting just the paper, you know, the chance of getting paper.
I'm sorry? I think that was a rogue microphone. So I just wanted to know, like, we're using single stream, we could be getting money back on paper and cardboard and all that. I wanted to know, the city is paying for the concurrent composting. I know that we received a grant, but what will the future cost be?
I just wanted to get that question out. And then, Mr. McGiven, I know that you've questioned a couple of people saying, you know, what was it that they were talking about? What was it in regards to? And I think the actual advertisement for this particular Zoom said, if you wanted, we wanted to hear about our upcoming changes to our waste collection system. So I would assume that it would always be regarding the once every two week pickup.
That's why I asked. I wanted to be sure because we also have universal comprosses part of this program. Yeah, but that's not that people have. It's the major concern is that you're asking people to pick up once every other week and that would be, you know, that that's the part that would impact most people. And that's exactly why I'm asking folks to clarify to make sure that that goes on record. If that's the concern. Yep. That's exactly why I'm asking. Thank you, ma'am. All right. On to Ralph Klein. So Ralph Klein, if, uh,
You could give us your name and address, and you'll have two minutes when I ask you to unmute. Can you hear me? Hi, Ralph. Yeah, welcome. Welcome. Yeah, my concern is with this every other week. I think it's absolutely ridiculous for a reason. For a bin that's
uh, composting bin. That's one 10th the size of the regular barrel. You think people are going to reduce their trash by half per week? That's a little unrealistic. I remember the composting we did back in the sixties. We had a bin thing bucket in your backyard. I gave pictures to the city council of the bin. You take it out. The swill wagon would go down the street and would stink the street up. Now you have all this money. You think every week it's supposed to be.
from my understanding, but trashes every other week? Why is this one-tenth size bin and cuts the trash in half? That's totally unrealistic. The second problem is rats. Wherever you have construction, you have rats. Route 93, when they redid the rotary, the rats went over to the church.
and all that neighborhood. On Salem Street, when they did the sink building, they're now doing the building on the corner of Park Street. They're talking about doing another one down the street. That's gonna bring rats into the neighborhood. People say, oh no, it doesn't. We don't have a rat problem. Yeah, we do. I've seen more rats around here than I have in years. I mean, it's crazy. And they're saying, oh, well, we can strip. Well, why not make a third collection bin?
for trash, for the plastic recyclables, for the styrofoam. That way there, or give us a drop-off spot for it. You have a dumpster for cardboard. Why can't you put another dumpster full of trash? And overflow styrofoam or the plastics to be recycled. It eliminates part of your problem. I mean, sit in this instinct. Yeah, it's wonderful. It's small. Everybody has a garbage disposal. For the amount you're gonna put in it, it's ridiculous to say, oh, every other week. Thank you.
Thank you, Ralph. Appreciate the comments. Okay, we're going to move on to Gianna Salvalletti. Gianna, when I ask you to unmute, if you could give us your name and address, you'll have two minutes.
Hello, I'm Chiana Salveletti, Tamar Drive. I turned to plus plus most of the concerns others have raised tonight. I'm very concerned about the impact this will have on public health and the rodent situation in the city. I have a dog and last summer has been by mistake. And so we had to wait for the next week for it to be picked up. And in the summer heat, I ended up getting maggots in my bin. And I'm super concerned that this would become the norm with this plan.
And after today's presentation, it sounds like a good area for improvement for our current trash strategy is resolving the contaminated recycling. At this point, if folks aren't recycling correctly, I don't have much hope that they'll be able to handle bi-weekly trash responsibly.
But I think that would be a good place to say we should create milestones that we must achieve before implementing something this drastic. And lastly, I feel like it wasn't previously communicated properly that the Massachusetts Food Waste Ban was just a proposal, and that's how it was presented today. And by drastically changing our trash schedule this early on, I feel like we're being overly proactive for something that's just in the proposal phase.
I think there are much easier milestones we could achieve as a city to positively impact the environment without posing such a significant risk this early on to our city. Thank you. Thank you, Jenna. Comments are appreciated. All right, the next person is just named iPhone. So, if you're just named iPhone, I'm going to ask you to unmute. Please let us know your name and address and you will have 2 minutes.
Good evening. Thank you so much. I'm calling from my mom. She lives on my mystery. I also live in Medford as well I'm calling because so it's Monument Street Yes, and I live in Medford as well There's an equity issue regarding seniors who live in their homes who have incontinence issues and
And my mom has lived in this city over 60-something years. She's over 100 years old. She does not get out. She doesn't make food waste and we use a garbage disposal, but her trash bin is filled every single week.
Um, and, and she says the, we have two trash barrels that she says with her tenant, um, and they fill it every week. Um, we're getting boxes almost, you know, every week for the stuff that she has to use. We flatten the boxes. Her recycle container is filled every other week. I want to know, because I think this is a done deal. Will there be a discount for seniors? Because, um, you know, you talk about the pay to throw some seniors cannot afford.
I don't think, I hope you can still hear me, I lost my part, but some seniors cannot afford, and I think we just all just use the pay to throw, just you don't know the extra cost that can be for a senior to take that on every single month to pay for
the bags or a bigger bin, and I saw some cost about $12 a month. Maybe I read it wrong, I don't know. So that's why I said there's an equity issue. Will there be a senior discount, some sort of, and we need to take that into consideration. Not every senior lives in an apartment building, and also Method does not do a good job in notifying residents about issues. We should not have had to hear this on the news, especially since it was proposed and done since,
Thank you very much. All right, there's a written comment from Alessandra. I want to read that was the person that on so she submitted a written comment. I'm going to go ahead and read that. And I also want to clarify that for compost, we don't pay for the tonnage. So we're not the tonnage. That's important for folks to know. So it sounds like there was a misunderstanding out there. So, um.
I'll go ahead and read this out. This is from Alessandra. I want to know how they're going to deal with the Tufts population around here, with four and five adults per apartment throwing out trash. I live on Yale Street in South Merritt, surrounded by two family houses rented to students. Landlords are absent, and there's no communication to them about this upcoming change in trash pickup. The landlord of their neighborhood, or even their own properties, in many cases.
Additionally, the communication around this was not optimal. We are hearing about this and the decision has been made. Why weren't residents allowed to vote on this? Thank you, Alessandro. Okay, we're going to move to Natarajan, Pravitha Natarajan. I'm going to ask you to unmute if you could let us know your name in a few minutes. Thank you.
Hi, this is Pravita. I live on Osborne Road. I wanted to voice my support for this plan, but I also understand the concerns from a lot of residents. I understand change is hard, but we can do hard things for the greater good.
I wanted to talk about a couple of things. I think the cost perspective, we spoke about that, and it is going to save the city a lot of cost. But also one thing I wanted to highlight is that, unfortunately, trash is not something that is out of sight, out of mind. We spoke about Asaga's incinerator, which means they are enclosed to the incinerator.
landfill stations and everything that's getting burned is affecting their air and water quality and there is a health impact for communities that live next to the incinerators. So by reducing our trash we are indirectly helping them as well.
Another thing I wanted to suggest was that potentially the city can also, so the rat problem has been raised and it is a real issue. Composting well can prevent rats from getting into your compost, but also would the city also help residents replace kind of damaged or compromised trash cans, so that could keep rats away from their trash cans, potentially with dog poop and whatnot.
And then finally, I wanted to say that a small group of Medford residents, we have started an initiative called Zero Waste Medford to work with the residents and help them learn about ways to reduce. Look forward to the opportunity to work with the city as well. Thank you. Thank you for those offers, Praveeta. And we appreciate it. We're going to move on to Niver, she, her. Niver, I'm going to ask you to unmute. If you could give us your name and address, you'll have two minutes.
Hi, I'm new there. I live at I live on Hicks have and I wanted to a lot of what people said, I really appreciate the thought that has gone into this and you soliciting opinions now. And I think it's a really good idea for.
us to be thinking about reducing our waste stream. I have been trying to do that all my life basically. But I am concerned particularly about the aspect of these changes for single family condo townhome owners like myself who are not going to have access to trash and recycling services anymore. So basically
will still be paying the same taxes to subsidize everyone else's trash and recycling services and then we'll also have to pay for our own trash and recycling. And if we want to compost on top of that will then also have to pay for that and I'm just concerned that that's accessible to me and I wanted to boost some of what other people have said about
providing other options. I would love to have more options of things to recycle, places to recycle them. I think the reuse communities people have pointed out are a really good idea. I think there are a lot of other solutions that could make this easier for people, but it does feel like someone else said like
this was rolled out to me. I'm a pretty new resident I just moved here this year and it feels like almost as soon as I moved here I got told like oh you're not going to get trash and recycling or compost anymore and pay for it yourself and but keep paying the same taxes and that just didn't feel right. Thank you. Yes. Thank you. We're going to move on to
Vinny or Vinay. Vinny or Vinay, I'm going to ask you to unmute. If you could give us your name and address, you will have two minutes. Hello, hello. Hello, welcome. Hi, thank you for the opportunity. I'm Vinay. I'm from Osborne Road in Medford. I am for this initiative. I think the biweekly crash is the right thing to do.
I cook a lot. And so I after the composting free composting, my compost bin gets filled up more often than my trash. And I think the city is doing the right thing by getting ahead of this problem. Because this is something we'll eventually need to address. I just wanted to share my opinion. Is it Vinny or Vinay?
Oh, anyway, he's already muted, so you may never know. Thank you very much. We're gonna move on to G. G, I'm gonna ask you to unmute. If you could tell us your name and address, and you'll have two minutes.
Hi, Ben Lindvig-Lingler, live on Sunset Avenue. I joined a little bit late, so I'm not sure if this has been asked, but I was really curious, has the proposal been a big cost savings? I was curious if the City or what the City has been doing to explore actual increased municipal revenues to ensure that we main level of service as opposed to cutting services and passing on costs to residents as was just described, whether that's
In expanded containers to meet the 2 week requirement or like with the single family condo owners who have to put the bill themselves. It seems like for a city that. I believe we're in the bottom 10% of.
Uh, taxes as it relates to other municipalities in the state. We should be considering increase. That's not a unrealistic thing to be planning for. So I'd really like to understand how we are increasing municipal revenue. So we don't end up having to cut, but others as well.
Also, as it relates to pests, it's not just rats. Where we live near Tufts University, it's rats, it's squirrels. They get into the existing trash bins. We've had to replace the lid on our trash containers twice in the last year due to squirrels and rats. So I think that that's only going to be increasing as well. So I want to make sure that that's understood as a problem, not just being rats, but other pests.
Thank you. Thank you very much, G. We will move to iPhone. That's how the name is listed. I'm not sure if it's the same one from before. If it is, maybe you have a new comment. OK, I'm going to ask you to unmute. Please give us your name and address, and you have two minutes. Hi, Chris from Winchester Street. Welcome.
I would just like to start off by saying this until a couple of weeks ago when it was on the news, radio, WBZ, television. I think this even made Jimmy Kimmel late night. It's even being reported worldwide.
I think that it's kind of a crazy idea to go to every two weeks. I don't know where the survey came from. Was it mailed to the house or what? Never heard of it. The whole thing that I heard about this was media just a few weeks ago. So I don't know how long you've been working on this, but
You gotta look at how long has the public known about what you guys are doing. I do not feel that trash pickup every two weeks is a good thing. People have been talking about all the reasons why it's negative. Rats, there's rats everywhere in South Medford.
I don't know how you guys don't know that. There's the raccoons, as the other gentleman just mentioned. There's stuff, you know, mattresses just dumped to pay a hundred bucks to get rid of them. I just think that the whole way this is being put out to the people is just not right. You can really take a hard look at yourselves for just throwing this out at the public.
And, you know, the other thing that's been brought up is the absentee landlords. A ton of them in South Medford, all over Medford, I'm sure. A ton of them in South Medford with Tufts. They couldn't care a crap less about trash. Trash is everywhere over here. I think you really got to take a hard look at maybe putting this on the ballot for the residents to, rather than having this forced on them. Thank you.
Thank you. Appreciate it. I have a raccoon that lives near my house too. So I know the room. Thank you for your feedback. And also my department picks up and pays for those, uh, those dumped mattresses. So I, and I feel them as well. Uh, so that's, that's pretty deep there. All right. So I'm going to move on to Sarah. Calico asking on mute. And if you could give us your name and address, you'll have two minutes to speak. Thank you.
Yes, my name is Sarah. I'm on. I am not in favor at this time for the every other week. Trash I do already do the composting and we do do the line here. I'm. In South Medford, and we have over the past couple of years notice quite the uptick and.
different rodents. So I want to know before something like this goes into effect, what is the city going to do? I have logged requests, I have neighbors have logged requests, nothing is being done. I have a whole series of port-a-potty outside of my house. And I was told that was going to be gone two weeks and I'm still staring at it. They assure me that that's not going to increase, but I can sure tell you on my ring cameras, I can see them every day running in and out.
And there's just been no accountability by the city and it's really, really frustrating. Neighbors were very clean. There are some neighbors that rent down the street so I'm sure that some of this could be coming from there as well but it's only going to get worse. I also have animals pick the waste removal but also.
To the woman who has the elderly mother, I really feel for her and that is a lot of supplies and that's a lot of waste and it's terrible when it's in your home. You're trying to do your best to take care of them and what are we going to do for these family members? This really needs to be considered and the communication needs to be better. The survey was
disgraceful. It was so unprofessionally written for a bunch of people who are on a board that are very well educated. So I suggest someone go look into revising that document going forward. Additionally, I don't know how much of a 20 seconds left is not everyone goes online, not a phone that text messages. So then we need to get to the residents that don't text, don't do QR codes. Like it may be 2026 that many people can't even afford a phone. We need better communication to all of our residents.
Bye guys.
Thank you, Sarah, just to just to address a couple of well, 1 thing that you said, the board of health has been doing a lot of work. I know on rodents. So, I know you don't think that we're doing anything, but I'm not both, but there's lots of resources. They're doing lots of citywide initiatives. We do help with them with some, even the mapping of the incidences in the DPW and also closed containers that hold our food waste is part of reducing rodents as well. I know a lot of people believe.
that rodents will increase when you separate and contain the food waste, but that's not what they're finding out there. No, I'm more concerned about... Sorry, I should have muted you, I'm just trying to address the things that you said. The ordinance, the Board of Health and the City Council just passed a rodent control ordinance too, that's a bolstering of a previous ordinance that they had, so there's a lot of action happening there. The engineering division about that port-a-potty, if you haven't already,
That sounds like it might be a construction project from the engineering division. Thank you very much. I'm going to move on to Dylan Compton. Dylan, if you could give your name and address and let us know. Sorry, yeah, your name and address, and you'll have two minutes. Thank you, Dylan.
Yeah, hi Tim, thanks for taking comments tonight. Dylan Compton, I live on Sunset Avenue. Echo, you know, a lot of the other comments and concerns tonight. I compost, I recycle, I actually don't run out of space in my trash can, but to me I think there's a huge amount of dogs in the neighborhood, there's
human waste there's things that become quite odorous and so my concern is almost exclusively with the frequency of pickup and not the the waste reduction goals and so um you know one of my sort of you know you phrase this is looking for questions you've been getting a lot of comments i appreciate you you hanging with us um i think one of my questions is what would it take for us to look at
smaller cart sizes on a weekly basis as opposed to a bi-weekly system and like what would the relative cost savings there be if just the tonnage reduction versus the the pickup frequency reduction because that to me feels like potentially a very workable alternative
that would address a lot of the commute concerns around the waste. I think there's still volume concerns, but that's where pay-as-you-throw really is structured well to solve for that, potentially, where the frequency, it really isn't, right? There's not an option for me to go out and say, hey, I want somebody to pick up my dog's, you know, poop every week. I mean, there's a couple private services for picking up in your yard stuff that we put in our trash right now, right?
And so, yeah, I think that's my core question. Broadly, I understand where this is coming from and appreciate the city trying to solve for it, but would really like to see us think creatively about how to keep the frequency higher and achieve those tonnage in other ways. Thank you. Thank you, Dylan. Appreciate the feedback. All right, we'll move to Charlotte Cahill. Charlotte, if you could give us your name, you'll have two minutes.
Great, thank you. Charlotte Cahill, Central Ave. I am sneaking in a second comment. I didn't be able to get away with it, but I'll make it really short. One is to just say, and I appreciate the fact check on my previous comment where I had the proportion
of households represented by the city's composting goal wrong. Remind my sort of larger concern about like, there's going to be food waste in the trash. And like, 100% compliance is not real, I think. I think your comments still made sense.
The other point I wanted to make was just to say, and really echoing some of what just before me, is I would love to have more information in whatever FAQ or whatever else you put together on what alternatives to biweekly pickup the city has considered and why you decided against them. So I appreciate here the waste reduction goal.
I think that a lot of the comments we're hearing are not pushing back on that. They're pushing back on this particular biweekly approach. And so it would just be really helpful to understand kind of why you thought this was the approach. And I think about, you know, lots of other communities in Massachusetts have pay-as-you-throw. Very few of them are right here in the Boston area. I know Malden and Brookline are in it.
And I know Malden at least has chosen to maintain weekly trash pickup at a lower volume, so I'm just curious about kind of what the options are and why you think this is the right one for Medford. Thank you.
Just Charlie, just let you know, your comment did make sense. I just needed to correct that fact, just so folks had the correct information. People bringing it up, keep it every week, but reduce the volume. That is an option that was looked at closely, many options. And just so folks know, the cost of collection is a lot higher than the cost of disposal.
That information is out there. Some was presented tonight and then there'll be more detailed information on the FAQ. I'm sure once we're done with tonight. It's a lot. It's a lot of people seem to be interested in that, which is great. I love the brainstorming. I love the ideas. So thank you. We're going to move to big Haas. Hopefully that's your real name, big Haas. And we're going to, if you could let us know your name and address and you'll have two minutes to speak.
because it looks like maybe you clicked it and then clicked it again. So I'm going to ask to unmute again and just this time. All right, well, I'm going to put your hand down. If you would like to try again, please put your hand back up. Okay, I'm going to move to G Turk. G Turk, I'm going to unmute you and please let us know your name and address and you'll have two minutes.
Yes, hi, my name is Gilbert and I'm a Turk and I live on Woods Road in Metzl. And, you know, I, you know, I watched the presentation by, you know, environmental issues and, you know, mainly, you know, we want to reduce our waste and we want to reduce everything is done in a proper way. But
again, you know, as many other citizens and, you know, express the same concern about rodents. I mean, last year, we had raccoon in our trash bins, summertime when it's really hot, it's terrible. And yeah, I mean, you know, I understand, you know, that, you know, I mean, we're not, you know, I don't think
We were consulted before this program was implemented, and to convince people that having trucks that were run once every other week would put less strain on streets and roads and would cut down pollution, I mean, it's a joke.
You know, again, we're paying also more property taxes and getting less services. That's right. Yeah, go. And I understand cities have big trouble closing their budgets, the cost of living everything. But I believe there's way better ideas to implement stuff. And certainly, the every other week, you know, program is not the right one. And I believe, you know, Metro
only city which are going to this direction. I'm not sure what the result is going to be, but I mean, will you allow to, I mean, to change course if things will not go the right way? I mean, we're open to anything new, but I don't know. Thank you, G-Turk. We appreciate the comments. And this is, I'm going to say something, but it's nothing to do with what you just said, just in general.
just been notified maybe they're aware of it didn't seem like it to me and they were masked if and there's only a few more speakers left but no personal attacks no veiled personal attacks we're all people we're trying to do our job here okay so thank you um we're gonna move to i believe he has a new comment to make so i'm gonna i'm gonna uh ask him to unmute and if you could just say your name and address again thank you vinnie
Thanks, Tim. My name is pronounced Vinay. But I also wanted to add to my previous comment that I only put my trash out once or twice a month now. And I have three big dogs and all of their dog poop goes in the trash bin.
And we don't have a rat problem here in West Medford. And I think it's because my trash can is in good condition. And someone else also mentioned before that when used in a secure container, that really restricts the amount of rats or food that critters in general have access to. I tried to get to the compost bin, but it was secure enough that it couldn't open it, figure out how to open it. And I wanted to share that as well. Okay, thank you. Appreciate your comments and your feedback.
Okay, Ralph Klein, I believe Ralph spoke, but he may have a new comment. So I'm going to ask him if he could give us his name and address again, and I'll have two minutes. Hi, can you hear me? I can. Well, thank you. All these comments about, you know, the plastic bins, the old containers they used to pick up with metal, they got into them. My trash bins have very little food in them.
But there are animals that have chewed through the plastic. So these plastic bins should not be used. They're chewing through the regular trash barrels. What makes you think they're not going to chew through these plastics after a while when they find out there's food in there? The other thing is all these heavy trash trucks going down the street. They're saying, yeah, how heavy are they going to be every other week? You're not reducing it. You're just pushing it into another week. All the other things come from,
stores really that are open. Our stores are closed and left and right. Everything comes from Amazon wherever. That's where everything, that's where all this trash is generated from. We need to stop local shopping. Stop and shop where they have the food delivered. They put it in boxes to get rid of their boxes when they deliver it to home.
I mean, all we have is all these other trucks going down the streets and everybody thinks the electric vehicles are great. They're destroying our streets. They're destroying them in California, that roads in the summer here, the electric vehicles. And if they're going to electric trucks, they're even heavier. They're going to destroy our roads even more. So why not reduce it by half what you're doing? Thank you. Appreciate the comments, Ralph.
have been studying weights of vehicles for a while, and the weight of the vehicles matters, but the number of trips also matters, and the movements, the wheel friction on the road. So there's lots of impacts to roads, not the environment per se. Anyway, I will move on to Gary. Gary, when
Can you hear me? Oh, yeah, maybe. Who's this? Gary? This is Gary. Yep. Oh, I didn't even know you. Someone else must have. So thank you. Hi, Gary. I'm here tonight to speak against the proposal to reduce the trash pickup schedule to every other week on the surface, although cutting back may sound like a simple way to save money.
In practice, it creates far more problems than it solves. Problems that affect public health, neighborhood cleanliness, and overall quality of life. First, less frequent trash pickups means more waste sitting longer in homes and on our curbs.
That leads to overflowing bins, very unpleasant odors, and increased pests. We already have rats, raccoons, insects, and bugs near Salem Street and in Felsway, and these are not minor inconveniences. They're real health concerns, especially for families with children sleeping in multifamily homes.
Second, reducing pickup does not reduce waste. It just shifts the burdens onto the residents. Families will be forced to store more trash for longer periods, which is not realistic for most households. Many properties also lack extra storage, and the community relies on regular disposal
and will struggle to stay clean. Third, this change risks making our community look neglected. Overflowing bins and illegal dumping become much more common when people don't have adequate disposal options. That hurts property values and undermines the pride we take in our community.
At my home, we already recycle, and we're already signed up for composting, even always full. There's never a week when our bin is not full. We have two young children who are in diapers, and it's all quite awful. Our bin already smells awful as is, and I can't imagine what it would be like with every other week pickup. Thank you. Thank you, Gary. Appreciate your comments. I'm going to move to
It's all one word, Judith Weinstock. Judith, I'm going to ask you to unmute. If you could give us your name and address for the record, and you'll have two minutes to speak.
Hi, my name is Judith Weinstock. I live at 144 Burgett. I'm actually a little surprised, not at the comments about going to every other week. I actually think the city seriously needs to revisit that if it's not too late. In other words, if a contract's already been signed.
then this is all somewhat moot. But I would like to comment on the composting program, which I think is pretty phenomenal. And I just want to focus on it first. There's some kudos deserved by the city and by the company that you've contracted with. I only started doing it about three months ago. It was remarkable how easy I found it, but I think that the city could actually work
much harder on encouraging many, many, many more houses to do it because it is a relatively simple program. But I also think that the city, just as you did with rain barrel options for people years ago, people do have to go out, they have to buy a bin for their internal collection, they have to buy those bags, they have to buy the bags for the bin that you provide for free. And I think it would be great if the city could provide some additional resources, potentially bulk buying and discounting.
for in-home bins that people have to use for that program. I would love to see the city at this point, with all this feedback, decouple these programs and begin to focus 100% on increasing the number of households who are doing composting
now and for the future and work longer and harder on solving some of the really important issues at PNight. I think they're legitimate. They don't affect me. I'm a single-person household. I don't fill my bin. Please don't come by and drop your stuff here. But I really think you're hearing some really serious concerns that need serious fixes before you implement the program. Thank you very much for that. Thank you, Judith.
We'll say comments and feedback are not moot. We're trying to identify gaps, respond to feedback. There's flexibility within the signed contracts. There are contractual dates and milestones that we have to meet certain things and make certain decisions.
And because of the pay-as-you-throw relationship, it's actually been coupled as opposed to decoupled because they feed off of each other and it's part of one whole program. So hopefully that helps clarify things for folks. Definitely not moot at all. This information is incredibly valuable to us, to apps, and take those flexibilities and continue to design the program over the next year and a half, really. So that's what we're looking at.
That's everybody who has their hands up and I'll just give, it's 8, 10, if there are other folks who would like to speak, now's your chance. If not, I'm gonna, I suppose, I don't know if we have, I don't recall if we had any closing planned, but I don't know if Steve, you wanted to say anything or anybody else wanted to say anything or if we should just log off.
Kim, we have one other comment from the person, Big Hoss, who had trouble, do you want me to just read that one? Sure, yeah. My name is Amy and I live on Princeton Street. I do not have a resident. He should have muted her so that he could speak over her. There seems to be a huge disregard for the residents you are serving. I am a mother and can't tell you how many trash weekly. It's insane to announce this during a cost of living crisis.
for the population of your residence, which is families, elders, and students.
Thank you. Just to clarify, I was not being disrespectful in any sense of the word. The mechanics of this particular meeting and the way it was formatted doesn't give me particularly a lot of flexibility. That's how we agreed to have a Q&A open dialogue. It's really to receive feedback, and my role is to correct things that maybe are facts that are wrong. So hopefully that explains it. I certainly didn't mean anybody any disrespect whatsoever. So I hope you can appreciate that.
With that said, if there's nobody else to speak tonight, we can wrap it up. And we have other
Scheduled events January 28th is at City Hall. That's at 6 p.m. January 28th at 6 p.m. Medford City Hall, City Council Chambers. There were a lot of comments or a few comments at the beginning about how this was only on Zoom. It's not. There's educational workshops that are going to be taking place as well. There's lots. So we appreciate everybody's feedback tonight. Thank you.
Steve, do you wanna call it, say goodnight? Yeah, I didn't get to see no other questions. As Tim said, we're gonna have an in-person meeting on the 28th of January at 6 p.m. at City Hall. A recording of this meeting will also be available on our website, on the city's YouTube, and on MCM. And please head over if you have any other questions, or if you have any other questions after this meeting ends, and you wanna answer it, please email us at waste at medford-ma.gov.
And for more information, head over to our website medfordma.org slash waste dash dash system. Thank you. Have a good night, everybody. Thanks a lot. Really. Bye bye. Thank you.