This is the moment an hour long standoff comes to a peaceful conclusion.
Police seize an opportunity to rush in when a man with three knives is momentarily distracted.
He was depressed.
The drama unfolding at Columbus Elementary School in Medford.
Moments earlier, Sky 5 captures the man sitting up against a wall right in front of the school.
350 young students are inside.
He stood up, he sat down, he made no no gestures like he was going to run towards the door.
Patient police negotiators talked to the man.
The school goes into lockdown.
We obviously lock in doors, put kids in places, put people in key strategic locations to watch doors and corridors and any other possible area where someone might get in.
And everyone follow that exactly.
Many parents rush to the school as soon as they're notified.
I never drove so fast from Woburn to here.
You know, with all the stuff going on, you never know.
But the Columbus School did a great job after the takedown.
The suspect is put into an ambulance and taken to the hospital.
A short time later, parents and kids are reunited after the anxious hour long lockdown.
I'm just going to take him home and you know he's only four so I don't know kind of what's going to cross his mind.
The police chief here in Medford says it's too soon to tell whether that suspect will face any criminal charges.
Reporting live in Medford, Todd Kaskiewicz, WCVB News Center 5.