Hi, and welcome to the Mustang Report.
This Mustang Report will be featuring a preview of the Eric Farazani Faculty Flag Football Game, an interview with Heidi Riccio, the director of the Vocational High School, an interview with the National Honor Society members, clips and interviews of Medford's own veterans, the amazing shootout victory of the boys soccer team in the state tournament,
So could you tell me a little bit about the open house this upcoming Tuesday?
Sure.
What differs from the vocational school's open house to the high school's open house is that the high school open house focuses on the academic side of our programs, but the vocational open house focuses on the career and technical education programs.
So do your students facilitate this open house?
Do they show the other upcoming 7th and 8th graders around?
Absolutely.
So we'll have tours going on, we'll have different activities in each of the programs happening that will be completely run by our students.
So, I just said it, but this open house, is it for just 7th and 8th graders?
It's an open house where we obviously invite the community in, so any community member can come.
It's from 6 to 8 p.m.
on November 12th, next Thursday.
We'd love to have the community in because we will also be dedicating our new health assisting lab and thanking all of the donors that helped us move that along.
Can you tell me about what National Honor Society is and what you guys do for National Honor Society?
So National Honor Society is a cohort of students and we're dedicated to giving back to community and currently we're focusing on high school so far so it's been nice.
So I know you guys recently did a Tenoch food truck fundraiser, so can you tell me a little bit about that?
Yes, so we asked Tenoch to come over for during one of the half days and basically we had a pre-order session where people just came during lunch and order what they wanted for
from Chinooch and then $10 was the cost and then $2 comes to us and $8 goes to Chinooch and we raised over $200 so it was a that's going to contribute to our phone book initiative which is going to help us get laptops for our tutoring service that we offer to the school.
So can you tell me about the after school I know the National Honor Society does tutoring so can you tell me a little bit about that so the students know?
So our program is called How to Survive High School 101, and it's not just tutoring.
It's also networking service.
So we have a whole database and whole list of community service opportunities, jobs, internships.
that are offered to the school, and we're, our hope is that over the years it's gonna grow and grow and grow, and then other kids can use it year after year.
And then our last one would be just advice, like anything that they have questions about, whether it's school out of school, anything like that.
We're currently in lecture hall three, but we'll be moving down to the library.
Same services, we'll be supportive no matter what, so it's exciting.
I'll be there in December on Monday, so thanks for telling time.
Have a great rest of the year.
Mr. Kane, how did you get involved in getting the veterans to come to the high school?
Well, this is my 12th year as a social studies teacher, and every year that I've been here, I've had veterans come in on Veterans Day as part of this program.
So last year, I had the opportunity to help coordinate the program, so this is the second year doing that.
It's a wonderful program to help connect social studies with the local community.
Awesome.
And what do these veterans serve as coming to the high school and educating students on what they do?
It's an amazing resource that we have them volunteering their time to come in to celebrate Veterans Day.
It's something that we see on the calendar, but it's something that needs to be made real to students, the service of people, local people in the community for their country.
Do you think the veterans coming here encourage students to go into the military?
I think it depends on the student and so to some it may and to some it might discourage them.
That's not really the idea of this program though.
This program is to look at Veterans Day and what it means to us as a country and also what it means to us as a community.
Awesome.
And what branches of the military do we have here today?
I believe we have all branches represented today.
Awesome.
And some are veterans from beforehand and they're out and some are currently enlisted?
Absolutely, yeah.
We have some, yeah, absolutely.
Awesome.
And what is your opinion on the veterans of this country?
Oh, I think the service that they offer the country is something that you really can't put a measure on.
And it's something that we should all be thankful for.
This is Lydia Ryan reporting from the Mustang Report.
And we are here with two former Medford High students for Veterans Day.
I understand you guys were former Medford High students.
What was your time here at Medford High School like?
My time was 1972, I graduated from Meffitt High.
I was actually a Vogue student.
I was the second class actually to graduate out of this new school.
And I graduated in 98 from Meffitt High.
I did a little time in the Vogue too.
Awesome.
Did you go straight into the military right after high school?
Yes, I did.
I went to Norwich after high school.
And then I went into the Marines.
Awesome.
What branch of the service did you go into?
I was in the United States Marine Corps.
I'm in the same service.
In the Marines.
How long did you spend in the Marine Corps?
I spent five years, 1972 to 1977.
I spent 17 years, 99 to right now.
I learned a lot.
It was a very rewarding experience.
I got to go places that everybody doesn't get to go.
I learned a lot.
I got to see some beautiful, beautiful places in this world that I never thought I would get to go.
I got a lot of experience and a lot of good schooling.
out of six years in the Marine Corps, which helped me further in my life.
I got out of the Marine Corps and I was a police officer in L.A., and that helped me.
My military experience helped me when I was a police officer, so it was pretty cool.
Hi, this is Lydia Ryan with the Mustang Report, and we're here on Veterans Day.
Hi, what's your name?
My name is Sasarn Zee with the Marines.
And what is your status?
My current status right now is active duty.
I'm actually the recruiter out of Boston in Medford Square.
Oh, awesome.
Did you grow up locally around here?
I did not.
I'm actually from New York originally.
Go Yankees.
No.
Go Sox.
What made you go into the military?
I enlisted for quite a few different reasons.
Most importantly, I wanted to serve my country.
And I felt the best way to do that was to enlist in the Marine Corps.
I lost family in the World Trade Center, so that was definitely something that inspired me to actually take that step into enlisting.
How many years were you in the military?
I have been in for over 11 years now.
Are you still currently in the military?
Yes, I'm currently active duty.
I work out of Medford Square in downtown Boston.
We didn't have iPhones back then, we had a camera with film, so you had to get the camera and take pictures, so I took a picture.
We're up north, so up north, there's a lot of mountains, terrain, you'll see the terrain.
Typical village, you come across, you walk through a jungle, come across a village, a hut, a couple of huts, so you have to go through, make sure there's no bad guys on any arms or anything like that.
Typical village.
That's me, I used to carry,
Forty-five, and I carried an M-16.
Carried probably about 200 rounds of ammunition on me.
Bayonet, grenades, things like that.
Intelligence.
So I was an intelligence officer for about four years.
Went down to a tech school down in Texas, out in the middle of nowhere.
I don't know if you've ever heard of Goodfellow Air Force Base or Goodfellow, Texas.
It's literally in the middle of Texas, about three hours away from civilization.
Absolutely nothing to do.
So I was out there for about a year.
stationed out at Beale Air Force Base in Sacramento, California.
So you had to be prepared for that.
Luckily the colonel
because I believe in the principles of fighting for your own country.
This is Nick Keniston from the Mustang Report, and I am here up at the Field of Dreams where yesterday Medford Mustangs varsity soccer team defeated Acton-Boxborough 3-2 in the PK shootout.
Jordan Howard,
Normally a defender, showed his versatility yesterday in the PK shootout, scored the final goal for Medford.
Sammy Reed, in his first ever game for the Medford Mustangs, filling in for an injured Mateo Cunha, normally the starter, Sammy Reed filled in, made some spectacular saves throughout the game.
And the Mustangs now will move on to the quarterfinals against Malden at McDonald's Stadium on Monday at 6 p.m.
Every Mustang should be there showing their pride for this Mustang soccer team.
Speeding off to left.
Drink it.
Yes, middle, middle.