Welcome to Medford High School.
My name is Marta Cabral, and I am honored to be your child's principal.
As an educator and parent, I understand the importance of creating and fostering an environment where students feel safe, supported, and academically challenged.
Alongside my colleagues, we will create a school community where all students feel welcomed and an inclusive environment where one's individuality is embraced and celebrated.
Medford High School is a comprehensive high school that includes the Medford Vocational Technical High School.
At Medford High School, we encourage and support students in becoming creative and critical thinkers who embrace global citizenship.
We foster a belief in lifelong learning where students collaborate and engage with each other to develop and realize one's potential.
At MHS, we believe in the power of building partnerships with caregivers and community members.
Through a strong partnership, we will work together to create a positive school experience for all.
Please know that you are always welcome at Medford High School.
On a personal note, I'm a parent to a second and third grader.
I speak English, Spanish, and American Sign Language fluently and was raised in a multicultural family that has shaped my identity, beliefs, and values.
I'm a first-generation college graduate and believe that all students can attain their post-secondary goals when supported by educators who believe in their true potential.
I have had the opportunity to work in a variety of school settings, both in Massachusetts and Madrid, Spain.
My experience in private, charter, and public schools has fostered my growth as an educator and school leader.
I'm excited to meet our students and work alongside the inspiring Medford High School educators that educate and support your child every day.
Thank you for welcoming me into your community.
I'm a proud new Mustang.