Hey listeners, this is Danielle. And Shelley. Shelley is a radical Dravidian and racial equity activist. And Danielle is a community mobilizer and changemaker. And this is the Medford Bites podcast. Every two weeks, we chew on the issues facing Medford and deliver bites of information about the city by lifting the expertise of our guests. Join us in discussion about what you hope for the future of Medford. And as always, tell us where you like to eat.
Hey everybody, it's Danielle here coming at you today with a special bonus episode sponsored by the Chevalier Theatre. It's been a while since I kind of took some time to introduce myself and maybe we have a few new listeners. So I just wanted to share that my name is Danielle. I use she and her pronouns.
I'm one of the hosts of this podcast and in my real life, I'm a social worker and I'm a parent of two kids in Medford. So yeah, I really wanted to also ask myself or answer the question that I ask everyone, which is my favorite place to eat in Medford and what I like to eat there. I do realize being on this side that it's an almost impossible question to answer because we have so many great
Food options in Medford, but I will say the most recent food that we got from Medford in Medford was for real gusto I just think like any pasta dish there is delicious and we loved it that Trentina salad Which is like which is like lettuce. I think it's like pears walnuts honey delicious And when we were at Oktoberfest this past weekend We got to see a lot of our favorite
uh eating spots in person there and I finally got to try the pizza from Goldilocks which was delicious um and have you know my favorite thing to get there is usually the rosemary salt bagel with cream cheese which I also had at Oktoberfest which was great um and at Oktoberfest we also got to see some of our
friends at Event Them and other local businesses. My kids really enjoyed the Rock, Paper, Scissor tournament from the Beyond Sports podcast. They also really enjoyed the community hoops section where they brought a basketball hoop, which, you know, my kids love to play basketball, so that was amazing. And Medford Rec also has some great games and activities set up. At our table, we asked folks to share what they love about Medford.
We got to talk to a lot of people and had some long conversations and met some new people that were new to Medford, which is always great. So it was just a really nice way to connect with the city and to meet our neighbors. So yeah, thank you so much to the Chamber of Commerce who put that on and who invited us to be a part of Media Row. It was a great, we had a great time.
So another booth that we saw there was the Chevalier Theatre, who is generously sponsoring today's podcast episode. At Oktoberfest, they were trying to get the word out about an upcoming show called
the Gazillion Bubble Show. And so I'll just share, if you look at their website, I'll share the description. So, prepare to be amazed and transported back to an enchanting world of bubbles with the Gazillion Bubble Show. This mind-blowing spectacle combines the joy of bubbles, the wonders of lasers and lights, and the musical science fun for the whole family.
Get ready to rediscover the sheer wonder and delight of bubbles as you embark on a one-of-a-kind interactive journey through this hour-long show. The extraordinary stage design and production features awe-inspiring bubble artistry, high-energy music, and captivating lights and lasers that will leave you spellbound.
After enchanting over 50 million audiences worldwide, this one-of-a-kind show is finally making its debut in Medford on December 8th. Perfect for all ages, the gazillion bubble show guarantees an unforgettable experience that will whisk you away to a fantastical world of endless fun.
The incredible bubble artists behind this phenomenal show are none other than siblings, Denny and Melody Yang, who have captivated audiences since their early years. Coming from a family of performers, their parents worked tirelessly to infuse their passion for performance with a perfect blend of art, science, and entertainment that makes this show so special.
Today, Denny and Melody journey across the globe captivating audiences of all ages with their mesmerizing bubble artistry. They have transformed the simple act of bubble making into an unforgettable spectacle of pure joy and entertainment. As one of the longest running off-Broadway shows in New York City for nearly two decades, their performance is a testament to its enduring charm and appeal.
Don't let this opportunity slip away. Come and experience the magic of the Gazillion Bubble Show, a dazzling celebration of bubbles, science, and family fun. My family will be there and we hope to see some of you there as well.
this episode today. As I said when we were at Oktoberfest we asked folks to share what they love about Medford and you know I know this is a time both you know in Medford and across our country where the world might feel a little tense and dark so we wanted to share just some positive messages that can hopefully help our city feel a little bit more united so I hope you enjoy.
What I love about Medford is that I'm so close to having a playroom with Abby. I'm so excited to have a playroom. And my name is Jack and I'm five years old. What do you love most about Medford? My school. And what school is that? The Brooks. Thank you.
senior built it and it's so convenient for transportation and places and stores. I just wish they had more restaurants. I enjoy going to the senior center. There's so much action and everyone is so loving and caring there. What I love about Medford, one is the location.
Two, that it's a tree city. And three, I love that there are all these young families moving into the neighborhood and having little children. My favorite thing about Medford is how the community can come together and do outdoor and indoor events, all ages, and have a blast.
Do we like the parks? Yeah. And the playgrounds? Yeah. You say the playgrounds? Playgrounds. Okay. Do this really fancy microphone. I like everything. Can you yell? I like everything of my friends. Awesome. Good job, cutie. I know what I like. I know what I like. I like all the things they have for the kids.
I love the people in Medford and I love the community. I think they have awesome soccer. I like their soccer leagues.
It's always nice and the people there are nice. What I love most about Medford is that there's trampoline parks in Medford and that I like to pull that car park. We have really good soccer teams.
We love all of our friends who live in Medford. I like that I'm Polish. McLinn Elementary School. The resources and the team behind the Medford Family Network.
What do you like most about Medford? One thing I like about Medford is the people. Medford soccer. Basketball.
My favorite thing about Medford is that it's very safe and family friendly. My favorite thing about Medford is the public library. My favorite thing about Medford is that everyone's really nice. My favorite thing about Medford is that everyone is so nice and everyone's really friendly. My favorite thing about Medford is that it has really good food. What I love about Medford is all the community events.
I like paddle boarding on the Mystic. Recently I had ice cream at CV Scoops and I can't get it out of my mind. I keep wanting to go back there and get more. I love Medford's balance of blue collar and I'll call it Gen Z young people and how they are in a tight fight against moving the city forward
I love that Medford is so small and it's an amazing community so you can go everywhere and have fun. I love how Medford is a really beautiful city and it has a really wide community for all people. I love that the community respects anybody for the way they are.
My favorite thing about Medford is my friends. My favorite thing about Medford is the people. My favorite thing about Medford is it's a nice combination of city and suburban and outdoors.
My favorite thing about Medford is the community. My favorite thing about Medford is the soccer teams. My favorite thing about Medford is their place to live. I just love the diversity and the people in Medford.
Honestly, I just love the community. Everyone in the city is really nice and yeah. I love Medford because I get to play hockey and it's really fun and I get to play other sports.
What I like about Medford is that we have pretty cool trees and grass and stuff. We also kind of live here, so that's pretty cool. And then, what else did I say? Oh, we have Colleen's. That's a pretty cool ice cream place. And we're free country, because we're America. Pretty cool.
What I love about Medford is I go to school here, I go to the library, which is great. The trees and grass are pretty cool and it's just a great city all together. What I love about Medford is we have trees, grass, and it's just a cool old city.
What I love about Medford is that it's a community that definitely cares and there's a lot of people that love their Medford and I like all of the people really really try hard even if it's all different stuff and everyone might not like the same things there's just so much pride in this city so that's what I love.
So two things I love about Medford. I think Medford has really underrated food from our Italian food, our Chinese food, everything in the square. I think it's really underrated and I've been trying to get all my friends to come in. I think one like bigger picture thing I love about Medford is
I think we really walk the walk when it comes to what we say. I think we're a community of such inclusive values and we really want to make things more affordable. I think there's such a community effort behind that. When I work in other cities, I don't necessarily see that all the time and it's always nice to come home to Medford and see how much people really do walk the walk here. Go Mustangs!
Thanks so much for listening to today's episode. The Medford Bites podcast is produced and moderated by Danielle Balacca and Shelly Keshaman. Music is made by Hendrik Idonis. We'd love to hear what you think about the podcast. You can reach out to us by email at medfordpod at gmail.com, or you can rate and review the podcast on Apple Podcasts. Thanks so much for listening.
Guys, what's the name of the podcast? Never Bites!