[SPEAKER_10]: Hi, everyone.
[SPEAKER_10]: Welcome to February 2023 Commission on persons with disabilities meeting.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's nice to see all of you.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm Frances.
[SPEAKER_10]: And over to you, Tom.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thanks for the welcome and do we want to do a quick introduction?
[SPEAKER_11]: Excuse me.
[SPEAKER_06]: Marsha, we can see you.
[SPEAKER_11]: Marsha, we can hear you.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm sorry, that was bad.
[SPEAKER_11]: It's okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: I don't know what happened or why it happened.
[SPEAKER_11]: But we can see you too.
[SPEAKER_11]: This meeting thing, I have to go back into it somehow.
[SPEAKER_06]: You went to a different window?
[SPEAKER_06]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_11]: I don't see you.
[SPEAKER_06]: Well, we'll do introductions while you're looking.
[SPEAKER_02]: Here, here, here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: All set?
[SPEAKER_02]: Except I can't get there.
[SPEAKER_11]: Now I'm set.
[SPEAKER_06]: All right.
[SPEAKER_06]: Awesome.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I'm Tom Hamill.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm the chair of the commission.
[SPEAKER_06]: Been serving since my third year.
[SPEAKER_06]: Marcia, you want to go next?
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm Marcia Kirsten, if we want to say years.
[SPEAKER_11]: I didn't say your age.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm 81 years old I'm very proud of it.
[SPEAKER_11]: This is my two and a half years commission.
[SPEAKER_02]: Go ahead.
[SPEAKER_04]: So fella fan.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just a few months on the board.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's all I can say.
[SPEAKER_07]: Joe, would you like to go?
[SPEAKER_00]: Hi, I'm Joe Casey.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm new also, two months on the board.
[SPEAKER_00]: I love the city.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's unique in its own way.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hi, I'm Sue Bibbins or Susan Bibbins.
[SPEAKER_03]: I've been a commissioner on the commission.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't remember how many years, but a long time.
[SPEAKER_03]: I am the past chair until last year.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I am a past vice chair too.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I live in South Medford and my pronouns are she and her.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: So the moving on to approving the January minutes, so I just sent them out about a half hour before the meeting via email.
[SPEAKER_06]: They are in a Google Doc.
[SPEAKER_06]: I don't know if anybody did everybody see the minutes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Marsha says no.
[SPEAKER_06]: Susie says no.
[SPEAKER_10]: Go on, Susie.
[SPEAKER_10]: Did they want to maybe take some time to look them?
[SPEAKER_10]: Did you not receive them, or you just didn't get a chance?
[SPEAKER_05]: I'd go hunting now, but I'm afraid I'll lose you guys.
OK.
[SPEAKER_05]: I can't answer this.
[SPEAKER_05]: Let me turn the other one on.
[SPEAKER_05]: Go ahead.
[SPEAKER_05]: Keep going.
[SPEAKER_10]: Let me make this.
[SPEAKER_10]: Why don't I make this easier, Tom?
[SPEAKER_10]: Why don't I make you co-host and you can share?
[SPEAKER_10]: Is that OK?
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, sure.
[SPEAKER_10]: I already saw them.
[SPEAKER_10]: So, yeah, so if you screen share, then both Susie and Joe will be able to like, see.
[SPEAKER_02]: Actually, I have a question.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was not there.
[SPEAKER_11]: What do I do?
[SPEAKER_10]: Oh, you were not there so you actually technically cannot approve the meeting minutes because you were not there and you did not watch the video?
[SPEAKER_10]: I thought I was going to and then I didn't feel well.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay, no worries.
[SPEAKER_10]: I made an effort.
[SPEAKER_10]: No worries.
[SPEAKER_10]: So are you okay with us approving the next meeting then?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, I think we, because we wouldn't have a quorum, so we'd have to do that unless.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_06]: You weren't here anyway, so it's okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: If a vet or Gabby shows up and we have time, we could do it at the end of the meeting.
[SPEAKER_02]: All right.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think if that is going to sign up, come in late.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: All right, Frances, I'll turn it over to you for the next item, the discussion, the variance request for the MBTA for Wellington station.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes, so I believe that I shared the information with all of you.
[SPEAKER_10]: A while ago, I think now it's probably about two and a half weeks ago that I was just going to be briefly discussing the decision to approve the various variants request.
[SPEAKER_10]: So the MBTA is redesigning several stations.
[SPEAKER_10]: The one that is under my purview is the Wellington station in Medford.
[SPEAKER_10]: And really what they're trying to do is they're trying to improve the ADA accessibility of all their stations to bring them up to the next level, the next level.
[SPEAKER_10]: In actuality, there is a situation with the Wellington station because even if they were to break down the water lines, the pipes and things of that nature that run through,
[SPEAKER_10]: It's still, that bathroom still would not be fully ADA accessible.
[SPEAKER_10]: So it would just be incurring a costly expense for no real value or no real benefit.
[SPEAKER_10]: So, I looked at that I looked at the measurements as did building commissioner and as did facilities director as well.
[SPEAKER_10]: So we're all under the yeah, it's okay for us to go ahead and.
[SPEAKER_10]: issue the variance in this case, because there is no benefit to be derived from not issuing the variance and saying you have to go through this work.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I just wanted to share that with you.
[SPEAKER_10]: I don't know if you've been informed before when people make requests for variances that specifically have to do with ADA related issues, but that sort of
[SPEAKER_10]: how I like to bring the information back just as a way of keeping you informed.
[SPEAKER_04]: I learned a lot from it.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, it's really interesting, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: And it's like, ideally in a perfect world, I really want that magic wand, that Harry Potter wand, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: And I wanna say, it has to be done this way.
[SPEAKER_10]: But when I really broke it down and it was helpful to have both the building commissioner and the facilities person there, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: trying to figure all this out in my layman's hat.
[SPEAKER_10]: You know, I have people where if I get stuck, they can explain things to me.
[SPEAKER_10]: I really, I started to understand and I started to see like, you know what, that's not, that's not worth it.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'd rather you take that money and go make a brand new bathroom that's fully accessible from the scratch, you know, from scratch, so.
[SPEAKER_10]: There's that.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I just, you know, wanted to share that with you I told them that I would.
[SPEAKER_10]: I told them that I would not render a decision until after this meeting, because I think it should be, I think that that's how things should work.
[SPEAKER_10]: Things of that nature should come in, should think about it, prep, you know, share the information, prep the commissioners on what might, you know, where I'm leaning towards so that we can use the meeting for discussion, if needed, and then issue the, what you call it, the variants or the response.
[SPEAKER_11]: Can you clarify for me, which, what, what exactly they're changing from.
[SPEAKER_11]: Oh Marcia you'd have to look at the document.
[SPEAKER_11]: I did.
[SPEAKER_11]: I can't tell which wall it's from, or if it's the height of the toilet.
[SPEAKER_10]: No, it's not the toilets.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's the it's the walls themselves.
[SPEAKER_10]: So they're able to do the toilets and they're able to do the if I remember correctly, they're able to do the banister.
[SPEAKER_10]: But it's a spatial issue between the wall and the toilet.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_10]: But but overall, a spatial issue that would require them to go behind the walls and reconfigure pipes and things of that nature.
[SPEAKER_11]: I understand that but what, what do they want those extra inches.
[SPEAKER_11]: What will the impact of those inches be inside the bathroom.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm sorry, what are you asking.
[SPEAKER_11]: When, when they change.
[SPEAKER_11]: They can't just change the wall they're going to change some dimensions inside the best between the wall and the toilet.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's my question, you, you would have to look at that.
[SPEAKER_10]: I can't doesn't show me.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think it says specifically what they plan on working on there in our section where they address Wellington.
[SPEAKER_10]: I don't know, I don't recall them working on anything between the walls.
[SPEAKER_10]: I know that they planned on moving things around and changing things like the flush system, and something else.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_11]: I, I'm, I'm confused that it's things behind the walls that makes that they don't need a variance that today.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think there's not enough room in between the wall and the toilet already.
[SPEAKER_03]: And they were asking for variants because they can't make enough room between one wall and the toilet.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so it's between the toilet and the wall.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's, that's what I seem to remember.
[SPEAKER_10]: And then they were upgrading something else that's already in place.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think that we're using a going for a different kind of a flush system.
[SPEAKER_11]: They were upgrading a number of things.
[SPEAKER_11]: I got that.
[SPEAKER_11]: I just didn't understand because they have the dimensions marked, but they didn't specify enough for me.
[SPEAKER_11]: That's why it's nice to have the building commissioner and the facilities director.
[SPEAKER_11]: Because I'm wondering about, it seems to me it impacts wheelchair access.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes, it does.
[SPEAKER_11]: And okay, Sue, so you understand.
[SPEAKER_11]: So how much do you think it impacts?
[SPEAKER_11]: That's our issue, right?
[SPEAKER_11]: The way I see it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It depends on how big the wheelchair is.
[SPEAKER_11]: Do you understand, Sue, what the sort of,
[SPEAKER_11]: flexibility of the ADA might be?
[SPEAKER_11]: Because I don't care about the dimensions of a wheelchair either, not really.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, the ADA has certain caveats.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if this caveat falls under, it's a major expense for a little
[SPEAKER_03]: All they need is, I think, three quarters of an inch.
[SPEAKER_11]: Right.
[SPEAKER_11]: The biggest one is three inches.
[SPEAKER_11]: That seems the one that would be most significant.
[SPEAKER_11]: Whichever one it was on there.
[SPEAKER_11]: One site was- I can't remember.
[SPEAKER_11]: Well, I do because I thought about it.
[SPEAKER_11]: I tried to figure it out.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's pretty big.
[SPEAKER_11]: That's what I thought.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if they would incur major expenses for those three inches.
[SPEAKER_03]: The three inches, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then they may not have to do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: They can apply for a variance.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's what they're doing.
[SPEAKER_10]: Additionally, what what they want to do is still not going to make it fully accessible.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I think that that's what you have to keep in mind it's not just about the cost it's one thing to incur the cost.
[SPEAKER_10]: If it's going to get you to where you need to be, but it's still not going to get them to where they need to be fully.
[SPEAKER_02]: After all that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: I understand that point.
[SPEAKER_11]: My hesitancy, I thought that what I was thinking was correct.
[SPEAKER_11]: My hesitancy is approving things that make the ADA less effective.
[SPEAKER_02]: if it does.
[SPEAKER_11]: What word did you say?
[SPEAKER_11]: If it's going to decrease the impact of the ADA, then I have concerns.
[SPEAKER_11]: If it's not, especially with the one that's three inches, and I did make the assumption that was the wall, so if that's correct, then it might limit some people.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I'm not an expert in wheelchairs.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is, I'm sorry go ahead see, are they going to build a new bathroom.
[SPEAKER_10]: I don't know the answer to that Sue because there are four bathrooms that they're working on.
[SPEAKER_10]: So the way I read the document is that they're trying to upgrade things in stages.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I kind of really just went to Medford.
[SPEAKER_10]: I don't want to read about Harvard.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't care about other.
[SPEAKER_03]: I only care about Medford and Wellington.
[SPEAKER_10]: Are they going to, to, there's nothing in there about rebuilding bathrooms basically the upgrading bathrooms, and this is this is the best that they're able to do with the upgrade, so they can't make any other bathroom in Wellington.
[SPEAKER_10]: ADA I think it's a space issue I think it's again it's sort of like this building right it's sort of like how things were built in order for some in order for a bathroom in my current location to be fully accessible you're talking about major construction you're talking about knocking down walls and I think that for them the things that they have to go through include water pipes you can't just change the direction of
[SPEAKER_11]: As much as a three inch one or the smaller one.
[SPEAKER_11]: That's what we're going to focus on.
[SPEAKER_11]: I don't recall that.
[SPEAKER_10]: I just want to make sure that you know that I am going to go ahead and issue the variance though.
[SPEAKER_10]: And this is the reason why I, you know, after looking at this, I think it's extremely important that things get upgraded.
[SPEAKER_10]: So the fact that you were attempting to make upgrades
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes, to me, that makes sense.
[SPEAKER_10]: But the other issue is that no matter how I, you know, we can sit here and we can debate this.
[SPEAKER_10]: The reality is, I've been asked can we have this variance, because even if we did this.
[SPEAKER_10]: we still wouldn't have a fully accessible space.
[SPEAKER_10]: And that's the real issue it's sort of like the issue that I have at this location.
[SPEAKER_10]: The square footage is not there.
[SPEAKER_10]: You cannot.
[SPEAKER_10]: So, I understand your point.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm not with you point.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, so I wanted, I do want to issue that but I am also grateful that people are.
[SPEAKER_10]: I mean, I don't know if you've if you've had these variances come through before but it gives me hope that people are actually thinking and reaching out.
[SPEAKER_10]: and asking these questions and the fact that they were willing to wait a month for me to get back to them because I said not doing it until after I have the full conversation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I just checked with a one and a half inch variance.
[SPEAKER_02]: One and a half, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: As much as I'm disinclined to
[SPEAKER_02]: say yes, because the whole site, nothing in the site is ADA accommodating.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, there's no bathroom in the site that is up to code.
[SPEAKER_10]: There's no bathroom anywhere in the city of Medford that has an up-to-code ADA bathroom.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's the reality.
[SPEAKER_10]: You have different levels of up-to-code, but there is no- Yes, that's a problem.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's a problem.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's a problem, but what do you do if you don't have square footage?
[SPEAKER_10]: Right?
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm not- That's the- That therein lies the rub.
[SPEAKER_10]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Excuse me.
[SPEAKER_03]: They can't make square footage out of thin air.
[SPEAKER_11]: They built that station after the ADA was implemented.
[SPEAKER_11]: And the ADA says, the way I understand it, it says that new buildings must have
[SPEAKER_11]: must meet the accessibility standard.
[SPEAKER_11]: So that, to me, is another flaw, besides the complexities of it.
[SPEAKER_11]: I understand money, but they didn't do the right thing to begin with.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that bothers me more.
[SPEAKER_06]: Are we able to make, like attach comments when we return our response?
[SPEAKER_06]: I see Sue shaking her head, yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think that would be a great idea.
[SPEAKER_06]: So what would we like to say in our response?
[SPEAKER_06]: I mean, I think we
[SPEAKER_06]: I think we go ahead and approve it, but in there, we include.
[SPEAKER_10]: I just, I want to make Tom, I want to make sure that when you say approve it, that you know, that it's not something that the commission is voting on just, just, just for the record.
[SPEAKER_10]: I don't want folks to think like, oh, this is a voting thing.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you for clarifying that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you comment on it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Francis, do you know if we can comment on it?
[SPEAKER_10]: Basically, do you remember the other letter that I shared with you about the Tufts Park
[SPEAKER_10]: And what I did was I made a recommendation that if they were to use accessible signs that they utilize the modern universal one that show.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I was just thinking about writing a letter just, you know, just like that.
[SPEAKER_10]: It says, yes, you know, blah, blah, blah, you know, approve this variant and highly recommend that moving forward.
[SPEAKER_10]: whatever else, you know, whatever we'd like to add in as apartments.
[SPEAKER_06]: So a comment like we, you know, if, if there are future major renovations happening, we would request that a fully accessible ADA compliant bathroom be built.
[SPEAKER_10]: I can't write that quickly.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: I got future major renovations happening.
[SPEAKER_06]: PB, David Ensign — Her.
[SPEAKER_06]: He.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, and I assume like Marcia says that that's, I mean, it would be required because, I mean, I don't know, I'm not an expert at all in ADA, but it seems like that should be.
[SPEAKER_10]: So the ADA has continued to expand and has continued to change.
[SPEAKER_10]: That was the big focus of the CAM two-day training.
[SPEAKER_10]: So a lot of what was in place
[SPEAKER_10]: has actually no longer in place, like things keep changing.
[SPEAKER_10]: Um, and the, again, I'm trying to do this from memory, the architectural board folks now have to refer to the architectural board, and if I remember correctly, I want to say 1998 is standing out in my head, as that's the go to that folks have 2010 is no longer.
[SPEAKER_10]: Or maybe 2010, I don't, I don't know, it was two days, it was intense, it was a lot.
[SPEAKER_10]: I have a question.
[SPEAKER_10]: It was not for people like me who require the pencil and the paper and the diagrams drawn, I can't, you can't just say it and expect me to see it, you know.
[SPEAKER_10]: But there is another one, but however, the instructor did continue to speak solidly about the changes that are taking place.
[SPEAKER_10]: So if you are able to attend any of them, I suggest that you do.
[SPEAKER_06]: And Marsha, this will be the last comment and then we should move on to the next agenda.
[SPEAKER_11]: I was just wondering if there's any written material from that seminar.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's not just written it's also diagrams, it's 1000 pages.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's a link.
[SPEAKER_10]: Well that's, that's yeah it's a Google link I don't know if it's still accessible but I can get it to you if you want.
[SPEAKER_10]: But I feel though that it's done that way because they need people to go, it's two days, and it's six hours each day, and it's done online.
[SPEAKER_11]: I know and I.
[SPEAKER_11]: I would be interested.
[SPEAKER_11]: I feel like I need some.
[SPEAKER_11]: Some updating, but not that intense.
[SPEAKER_10]: Marsha said not that intense.
[SPEAKER_10]: Marsha, there's another one I'm going to look, because there is a softer and gentler one.
[SPEAKER_10]: And the reason I call it softer and gentler is that you don't feel so overwhelmed.
[SPEAKER_10]: I seriously felt like I was encountering the LSAT exams or med school exams.
[SPEAKER_10]: quite intense, you know?
[SPEAKER_10]: But I think that there's a one day one Marsha that we can attend.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'll go on the MOD website and email you.
[SPEAKER_10]: And that one's just a few hours, which I think it's more digestible.
[SPEAKER_10]: This was like real school.
[SPEAKER_10]: But if anybody's interested, I emailed the date.
[SPEAKER_10]: Tom, when's the next one?
[SPEAKER_10]: Is it March or something?
[SPEAKER_10]: Because I remember, or April.
[SPEAKER_06]: I can't remember.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: If anybody's interested, you know, in two days of ADA intense, let me know and I'll resend the information.
[SPEAKER_10]: But I think the next session's in March and it's all done online too.
[SPEAKER_10]: So.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you, Tom.
[SPEAKER_10]: I've got the comment future major renovations happening at Wellington station request that they are fully ADA compliant.
[SPEAKER_06]: So our next item is also Francis for give us an update on the
[SPEAKER_06]: commission's webpage as part of the City of Medford's update to their website?
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, so the city's webpage, the city's website went live.
[SPEAKER_10]: Many things on, well, I can't speak for others, but on my three webpages, which are yours, another commission, and the DEI one, seemed to drop off and did not look
[SPEAKER_10]: like what I had sat and gone through on.
[SPEAKER_10]: Now, I know that I was told that there could be delays in things loading up, but this was not the case.
[SPEAKER_10]: So what I wanna ask you is, instead of the back and forth emails of add this to the webpage, add this to the webpage, I'm just gonna do them in stages so that that way I can go back
[SPEAKER_10]: and see, okay, has that been done?
[SPEAKER_10]: Has that noted up?
[SPEAKER_10]: Because a lot of the great information that we gave, I don't know what happened to it.
[SPEAKER_10]: You know, Marsha, all of a sudden your name's not on as a commissioner and that area was not touched because Joe and Susie had been added on and Yvette, they'd all been added on already.
[SPEAKER_11]: So, gone before they took me off.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_11]: I was on one of the lists.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's what I'm saying is that that section, the commissioner's section was not touched during the transition because we had already added Susie, Joe and Yvette.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I don't know what happened, but I can say nobody physically took you off, but things did not load the way they're supposed to load.
[SPEAKER_10]: So that was going to be my proposal to you, because it is difficult to keep track of all the back and forth.
[SPEAKER_10]: And I don't work on this like all day.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I kind of like to get the information in groups, work on it, come back, report back to you, get the next set of information, go back, work on it, come back, report back to you.
[SPEAKER_10]: Otherwise, I feel like we're just going to spin endlessly.
[SPEAKER_10]: Is there a particular section.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_06]: Is there a particular section you want to work.
[SPEAKER_10]: The first thing I need to do is to make sure that Marcia is added back on.
[SPEAKER_10]: The second thing that I need to do is all of our information regarding SCM transportation was removed.
[SPEAKER_10]: I don't know where that information went, but that needs to go back because that transportation is not just for seniors but also for persons with disabilities, it provides a lower rate.
[SPEAKER_10]: And the only reason I noticed that is because I wanted to add information about the TAP program.
[SPEAKER_10]: that I had heard of because Yvette and I both attended the Boston North regional coordinating meeting that has to do with, you know, transportation and stuff.
[SPEAKER_10]: So those are the three things that I want to work on.
[SPEAKER_10]: And then, finally, I want to upload that list, the member organizations list that Shanine Pellegrin had so kindly shared with me.
[SPEAKER_10]: I've gone through and I've clicked on the links.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's for all the different recreational and outdoor sports.
[SPEAKER_10]: inclusive, accessible, fun, and I want to get that list up there as recreational options as well.
[SPEAKER_10]: So that's where I want to start.
[SPEAKER_10]: I said three, actually four.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's where I want to start.
[SPEAKER_06]: So do you need anything from us right now?
[SPEAKER_06]: Or it sounds like no.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: That sounds good.
[SPEAKER_06]: So you'll keep us updated next month if you need something from us.
[SPEAKER_06]: I will.
[SPEAKER_06]: OK.
[SPEAKER_06]: So the next item was actually talking about that Boston North Regional Coordinating Council meeting.
[SPEAKER_06]: I know Yvette was going to give an update, but she's not here yet.
[SPEAKER_06]: I don't know, Francis, you want to also talk about that?
[SPEAKER_10]: I could talk about it, but I react for so long, and I was prepared to support Yvette, but not prepared to present on it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Well, we can move to, we can have Susie report on what she's been working on, and then if Yvette's on, then she can update us.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, so Yvette and I coordinated
[SPEAKER_04]: and what we're looking at the logo.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, we're looking at two things, I believe.
[SPEAKER_04]: One is the logo, which I know, Frances, July, 2023, I know that's the target date.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then also library with the computer with high school students.
[SPEAKER_04]: And for some reason I, well, I know the reason.
[SPEAKER_04]: I know a lot about different units
[SPEAKER_04]: in Medford and right around Medford, where disabled are part of those units.
[SPEAKER_04]: You have Triangle, you have Mass Rehab, you have, oh, I have four or five other ones, but Senior Center in Medford, then there's a lot of different pockets
[SPEAKER_04]: in the Medford and around the Medford area where disabled have their niche.
[SPEAKER_04]: But we're trying to, Yvette and I are trying to look at all those different pockets and then hit them to try to get them involved in the logo because it's sort of a dual thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: You get them involved with the logo, but you also pull all those units together.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't know, did I explain that okay?
[SPEAKER_04]: So you have triangle, you have this and that, and some of those disabled only go to this site, only go to this place, only go to this place.
[SPEAKER_04]: Social security even, and that was one I didn't know.
[SPEAKER_04]: Could you actually contact social security and say,
[SPEAKER_04]: we're looking for, you know, that's a government thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: Could we contact disabled social security and bring those people together kind of through the logo of getting to know there's other places they can go.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the one that I know about lightly, but Yvette knows is the West Medford, what does she call it?
[SPEAKER_04]: She had an acronym for it.
[SPEAKER_04]: West Medford Senior Center or West Medford Community Center.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I feel like that's more senior.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then I think Tom and I had back and forth about the seniors were absolutely okay to go to the library tech stuff, which I'll talk about in a minute, but maybe there'd only be a certain section that were disabled that would then be involved with a logo.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think I'm saying this okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm pretty tired actually.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that's- Can I ask a question?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: So just to, I guess, a clarification.
[SPEAKER_06]: So you wanted to approach these different groups to gauge their interest in one, helping the commission create a logo and two, learning about different kind of training opportunities likely at the library for those groups of people.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right, and three would be for all of us to understand that different disabled people go to different places.
[SPEAKER_04]: They might go to Triangle, they might go to the senior center, they might go to whatever for resources or social support, whatever they need.
[SPEAKER_04]: But have we brought, do they know about all the opportunities?
[SPEAKER_04]: have they sought out what specifically they need that might not be at their unit, it might be at a different unit, and they didn't even know about it.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's what I really am taking away from some of the research that I did, or have learned through my experiences, or Yvette introduced me to.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't know how else to say it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Go ahead.
[SPEAKER_07]: You're on mute.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay, go ahead.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm on mute.
[SPEAKER_10]: So my question for you is, once you identify these places, or, you know, the different locations, how do you plan to outreach?
[SPEAKER_10]: Do you plan to send them a letter that says, hey, the City of Medford's Commission on Persons with Disabilities is?
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a good question.
[SPEAKER_04]: So what Yvette said she would do is do like a
[SPEAKER_04]: Excel spreadsheet, putting all different data on it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And we would develop a specific letter that would be online, that would be hard copy.
[SPEAKER_04]: And we talked about all the different places you could leave a hard copy.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like the library is a beautiful place to leave hard copy for stuff because people walk in, they see something, oh, and they take it home and they read it.
[SPEAKER_04]: The senior center,
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm Riverside they're beautiful place for hard copy.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then other place, and then also online, so they can read about it, and we're going to have a meeting, say at the library at three o'clock on Wednesday whatever day.
[SPEAKER_04]: Come and bring your ideas for a logo.
[SPEAKER_04]: send it online and incorporate all those ideas.
[SPEAKER_10]: Can I just ask, did you have a chance to connect with the school?
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, this is a thing, there was a disconnect and I think, Tom, you were involved with it, where somebody named Sam from the library mentioned that he has somebody coming in
[SPEAKER_04]: a senior maybe, not senior citizen, a senior in high school coming in to do tech work.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I said, Sam, Sam told me when he was gonna be there.
[SPEAKER_04]: And Tom, I think you said you had COVID and maybe blah, blah, blah.
[SPEAKER_04]: You couldn't come in right away.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I don't think Sam got back to me after that.
[SPEAKER_04]: So maybe he's away, it's okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: OK, Sam is not a he, first of all.
[SPEAKER_10]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_10]: Sam is not a he.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I want to make that correction.
[SPEAKER_10]: Sam is what?
[SPEAKER_10]: Not a he.
[SPEAKER_10]: You've been referring to Sam as a he.
[SPEAKER_10]: Sam's not a he.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I just want to correct you.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's OK.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm sorry if I did that.
[SPEAKER_04]: I didn't notice that thing underneath.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm sorry about that.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm getting a bit nervous because June is around the corner and July the commission is on break.
[SPEAKER_10]: I definitely appreciate the idea of seeking beyond the typical, but I feel that for right now, it would be a good start to go where you know.
[SPEAKER_10]: So like connecting with the school, the school has IEP classes.
[SPEAKER_10]: You know, if we, you know, if we need to come up with a letter.
[SPEAKER_10]: We can always do a letter on the DEI letterhead that says, hey everyone the Commission of persons with disabilities is looking for your input in designing the next logo.
[SPEAKER_10]: If interested, please reach out to blank rain, tell you about the high school.
[SPEAKER_10]: So there are different, be it the high school, the middle school, there are different classes.
[SPEAKER_10]: So pinpointing and reaching out to them.
[SPEAKER_10]: Triangle is great.
[SPEAKER_10]: Triangle are our partners.
[SPEAKER_10]: They're right around the corner, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: You can send the same letter to them as well.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: So I talk to Yvette a lot about the high school, because I think it's a prime opportunity for high school kids to get to know each other.
[SPEAKER_04]: the disabled and the non-disabled, and to use like the graphic department there.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I mean, that's what a lot of my notes are written down about.
[SPEAKER_10]: So the graphic department, I want to say, I don't know why the name Lou is coming to my mind, but I could be wrong.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think we'd have to go online to see who the teacher is for that department.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'll do that this week.
[SPEAKER_10]: You know, but
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, you're what you're saying, let me, you're saying, we shouldn't spread out too much.
[SPEAKER_04]: We should focus and get the logo done.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then if six months later, we get some input, we change it.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay, so you're not gonna make about changing it because once the logos done the logos done when it goes to print, you know, I think that you have to be, you have to be realistic about your timing, and about when you want to execute.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay, so I would say who
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a graphics department.
[SPEAKER_10]: You mentioned mass rehab well mass rehab is an organization, an organization is not going to release a list of names to you.
[SPEAKER_10]: Oh, I know that contact.
[SPEAKER_10]: However, you could go directly to the triangle.
[SPEAKER_10]: Right, that's right in our backyard.
[SPEAKER_10]: We could also talk to our rec department and say, Hey, I know that you have, you know, some inclusive or all accessible classes, you know, would you mind distributing these letters so that that way.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay, you've got some groups to work with.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay, take it from there.
[SPEAKER_04]: So I'm going to target, which I wanted to do from the beginning target.
[SPEAKER_04]: The high school in the middle school probably the rec department and triangle.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sounds good.
[SPEAKER_02]: Joe, did you want to add something.
[SPEAKER_07]: You're on mute.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I was just looking.
[SPEAKER_01]: just to get some ideas on some disability logos.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just happened to Google.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could probably get a lot of ideas.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's great having a high school involved.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't believe there's 1,000 great ideas right here I just Googled on my computer.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're really nice and colorful.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just thought that would be a great good start or help somebody out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: All right.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, um, it sounds like for the logo, uh, idea, we have some, uh, direction and moving forward.
[SPEAKER_06]: Um, so that's great.
[SPEAKER_06]: And, uh, I think, um, I, I know that Sam, uh, did email us back about getting together.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I can follow up on that email and try to find a new time for, Susie, would you prefer that I go to the meeting or do you just... It's totally up to you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Can I clarify, I think Sam is mostly about tech support at the library.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes, I think, and it sounds like Sam was aware of a high school student
[SPEAKER_06]: That is already connected with the library that Sam wasn't sure whether or not this is the same person that we were thinking of or, and I don't think we're thinking of anybody in particular.
[SPEAKER_06]: No.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, okay, so I think it's, yeah, I think it's setting up the meeting and, and there so I may or may not be able to make it but I hopefully you and that can make it.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: Let's see.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, for instance, or do you want to do you want to summarize the best you can or?
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I just wanted to find out how you are feeling.
[SPEAKER_10]: Where's Marcia?
[SPEAKER_02]: We lost her.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I think, yeah, we must have lost Marcia.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm just quickly scanning my emails, pardon me.
[SPEAKER_10]: She didn't email me.
[SPEAKER_10]: I just wanted to find out how you are feeling with regards to the proposal made by Melanie McLaughlin on a disabilities resource fair.
[SPEAKER_10]: Are we feeling like we can do this or are we feeling like, eh, not yet?
[SPEAKER_12]: What is our date line.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, that was gonna be my question as well.
[SPEAKER_12]: Is that still planned for April.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, it was, I believe it was April 29.
[SPEAKER_10]: Well, as the Commission on Persons with Disabilities, we would sort of be responsible for coordinating.
[SPEAKER_10]: Of course she would provide the support, but remember this means reaching out to different organizations and inviting them, you know, an element of education and an element of play.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything basically.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: Go ahead.
[SPEAKER_06]: Did we pinpoint somebody.
[SPEAKER_06]: Is there somebody from the commission that's kind of driving this or we did not pick someone.
[SPEAKER_10]: We didn't pick anybody, and Frances is getting a little tired of being the go, go, go, one woman show.
[SPEAKER_10]: Can we get this done?
[SPEAKER_10]: Without a doubt, I think that we can.
[SPEAKER_10]: But I also know that we are competing for space, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: So depending on where we choose to have this, we have to be more intentional than anyone else.
[SPEAKER_10]: you know, so our place has to be accessible.
[SPEAKER_10]: And to minimize the, you know, the rain dates and things of that nature, we're better having this indoors.
[SPEAKER_10]: So that brings me to like the school, like the Andrews that has a lot of parking.
[SPEAKER_10]: Well, I'm hearing now that that may not be the case, because we've got a couple of parks and things that are under construction.
[SPEAKER_10]: So
[SPEAKER_10]: you know, the Andrews could be more full or more utilized than it typically is.
[SPEAKER_10]: So we do need to make a decision because it also involves showing the movie Krimp Kramp, which is an hour and 45 minutes long.
[SPEAKER_10]: So even if we were to do a half day event, we still need to plan accordingly.
[SPEAKER_12]: You know, if we have access to, like, I'm thinking when I was a kid, I went to a lot of like Medford sponsored events that were in the Cuffs auditorium.
[SPEAKER_12]: I know obviously we don't have much of a budget to work with.
[SPEAKER_12]: So like renting a space in Medford maybe isn't an option, but I'm just trying to think of where.
[SPEAKER_12]: Logistically, like I'm thinking if I want to reach out to organizations that I'm familiar with, I don't want to invite them to an event.
[SPEAKER_12]: TAB, Tila Duhaime.:
[SPEAKER_12]: : Without full confidence that there will be plenty of parking for them to get there and things like that i'm.
[SPEAKER_12]: : I think this is a great idea and i'm happy to do it, I just do think we need to find a location.
[SPEAKER_10]: Right.
[SPEAKER_10]: I certainly agree with you, Gary.
[SPEAKER_10]: You know, I mean, I've never been to the Chevalier Theatre, so I thought like, OK, well, maybe in the theatre part, right, you can have the, you know, we can show the movie and then everyone can transition to like the education and resource part.
[SPEAKER_10]: Well, I was told it's not necessarily like that.
[SPEAKER_10]: There's no parking, you know, you say theater, I'm thinking the big movie theaters, it's got to be parking somewhere.
[SPEAKER_10]: So those things are those things are definitely important and they're very meaningful.
[SPEAKER_10]: And especially if people are, if we have vendors, right, that are coming with adaptable goods that they want to show.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's good.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the tricky part for me.
[SPEAKER_12]: Are the middle schools technically fully accessible, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: I believe that Andrews is, I would double check again, but I believe that Andrews is, now I'm doing this visually right, I'm doing it from when I went on the tour, lots of accessible parking and lots of regular parking, concrete in front, concrete in the back,
[SPEAKER_10]: And even though there are grassy areas, you don't have to go to grass, to concrete.
[SPEAKER_10]: You go from concrete, and then if you choose to go to grass, you go to grass, which is important.
[SPEAKER_10]: So there's front and back access, bathrooms are fine, lots of space on the inside.
[SPEAKER_10]: I just don't know where the movie would be shown.
[SPEAKER_10]: I mean, of course, I haven't asked.
[SPEAKER_03]: The cafe, the cafe.
[SPEAKER_12]: I was also just thinking, as you were saying that I'm starting to visualize the schools I went to.
[SPEAKER_12]: I went to the Brooks Elementary School, and I think they have a little bit more parking than the Andrews, but the Andrews, I think we could also.
[SPEAKER_12]: Sorry, go ahead.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I said go.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I said, oh.
[SPEAKER_12]: I think there's a lot and then there's a lot of like side streets there.
[SPEAKER_12]: And that school was built when I was really little.
[SPEAKER_12]: So I'm, off the top of my head, I'm pretty sure that that's a fully ADH compliant school.
[SPEAKER_12]: And the same thing with it's all curbs.
[SPEAKER_12]: There's no like weird grassy areas.
[SPEAKER_12]: And they also have a big cafeteria area where they have a screen.
[SPEAKER_12]: I'm just thinking as far as like parking that they might have more spots than the, yeah, than the Andrews, but I'm not,
[SPEAKER_12]: if anybody else is familiar with the area.
[SPEAKER_10]: The cafeteria with a screen that keeps everything together, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: People aren't, you don't have to go watch the movie in one place and then you got to get in your car or your mode of transport to get to the other place.
[SPEAKER_10]: And then the cafeteria, I'm picturing, is it like a big one where the different resource tables could be?
[SPEAKER_12]: I think so.
[SPEAKER_12]: I haven't been inside since I was 10.
[SPEAKER_12]: So maybe the size of it, it's like way bigger in my head, but I'm pretty sure it's comparable to the Andrews.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: So do you, do you want to check in with the Brooks and see if that opportunity is available on the 29th?
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, I would be happy to.
[SPEAKER_12]: And I'll also just double check to make sure.
[SPEAKER_12]: like that they have a screen and, you know, make sure that the elevator is working and all that stuff.
[SPEAKER_10]: They would be okay for us to host something like that.
[SPEAKER_10]: They might want to be involved, you know?
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'll wait to hear from you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll reach out to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I have a question.
[SPEAKER_04]: Is the point of it to give out resources to disabled
[SPEAKER_04]: or is it to make the community more aware of disabled and what their world is?
[SPEAKER_04]: Like if they go on the playground, if it's not accessible, or if they, like I'm thinking about, I just walked along the Mystic River this afternoon, and behind the, I guess it's Andrew's school,
[SPEAKER_04]: They made this really cool thing with rocks.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like a maze that kids can jump on and go around in a maze.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, there's no way that somebody with a wheelchair can even think about that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Are we trying to make them aware of what disabled have to deal with?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or are we doing resources or a combination of both?
[SPEAKER_10]: It's a combination of both, Susie, because when you think about it, too, people with disabilities do need to hear about the different kinds of options that are out there, the different kinds of holidays, the different kinds of sports.
[SPEAKER_10]: Remember how excited I got about the Grit Cheer, which, you know, one day we're buying that Grit Cheer.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm saying it right now.
[SPEAKER_10]: One day.
[SPEAKER_10]: The city of Medford is going to have at least five of those Grit Cheers.
[SPEAKER_10]: But, you know,
[SPEAKER_10]: things that you ordinarily wouldn't come into contact with, but also providing education to the community.
[SPEAKER_10]: I would like to see some of these, more of the adventure, extreme adventure companies be present.
[SPEAKER_10]: Right?
[SPEAKER_10]: Because sometimes people think that just because, you know, someone has a disability, oh, they can't do this, they can't do that, they may not like this, they may not like that.
[SPEAKER_10]: When in actuality, there are people that can do a lot more than I can do.
[SPEAKER_10]: There are people that have more, what's the word?
[SPEAKER_10]: What's the word?
[SPEAKER_10]: More bravery.
[SPEAKER_10]: You know, so I think it's just, yeah, it's a little bit of both.
[SPEAKER_10]: You know, and some takeaways, right, in how some things are truly inclusive, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: Some things are not just used by somebody who has a disability.
[SPEAKER_10]: There are things that are built into our natural everyday life that we utilize for the sake of convenience and helping people recognize that as well.
[SPEAKER_06]: Another component of this, right, is I guess contacting the vendors that we want to be at the resource fair.
[SPEAKER_06]: Is somebody interested in doing that?
[SPEAKER_06]: Or multiple people doing that?
[SPEAKER_10]: I think that's, that's gonna have to wait until we find a location.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Fair.
[SPEAKER_06]: Right.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I, I guess I worry a little bit about we're two months out, and
[SPEAKER_06]: If, you know, I mean, we can plan offline, but I don't know how much time.
[SPEAKER_10]: You've also got the school transition fair that's coming up in March.
[SPEAKER_10]: I just don't know what day in March specifically.
[SPEAKER_07]: It's the 15th.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: So you've got that, so that could be, you know, that's that's only a couple of weeks away.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm not sure what you're suggesting, that going to the transition fair and asking?
[SPEAKER_10]: Many of the people that are at the transition fair would more than likely also be interested in this.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I believe that Melanie had made mention of that when she was here.
[SPEAKER_10]: You could get a list of people who would be interested in calling, but it's going to be based on finding the location.
[SPEAKER_06]: Anything else we need to do?
[SPEAKER_06]: besides finding a location and I guess obviously making sure it's available on the day we want.
[SPEAKER_10]: Making sure the movie is available as well, because that's part of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, there's a I never pronounce the name right.
[SPEAKER_04]: There's a place in Malden.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is like they do all these things in escape room and all this stuff.
[SPEAKER_04]: Bonga something.
[SPEAKER_04]: Somebody will know.
[SPEAKER_04]: What?
[SPEAKER_04]: If you maybe get that company in to show how they can do things, they do all this like climbing and all this kind of stuff, how they could, I'm just throwing this out there.
[SPEAKER_04]: They could modify so that people with disabilities, kids could try that kind of stuff.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know what I'm talking about?
[SPEAKER_04]: Gabrielle, do you know where I'm talking about in Malden there?
[SPEAKER_04]: I do, yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: I think that once we have a location.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_12]: Set down, so I will commit to contacting the Brooks tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_12]: I'll also contact the Anders just to get an idea.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: Promise, I will try to move as quickly as possible on this.
[SPEAKER_12]: So hopefully tomorrow, end of the business day, I'll have some sort of update on that and then we can
[SPEAKER_12]: I don't know, go from there with a quick email of who it's going to contact too.
[SPEAKER_12]: I can make like a Google Doc.
[SPEAKER_12]: But yeah, I think any activity sort of organization would be great to invite.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yvette, welcome.
[SPEAKER_06]: I don't know if this falls in your purview or not, but are you able to help with the purview
[SPEAKER_06]: finding out how to get Crip Camp, and the availability of that movie and playing it at the event.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's Melanie.
[SPEAKER_10]: Remember, Melanie said she would take that on.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, she's going to do that.
[SPEAKER_10]: Oh, OK.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, she was the one that mentioned it.
[SPEAKER_10]: And so she had access to the deck.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_10]: Well, I will.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'll follow up with Melanie and I'll ask her.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yvette, we were just discussing whether we had the ability to handle the disability resource fair.
[SPEAKER_10]: But I think it's coming back to you for feedback on the BNRCC meeting, the meeting that we attended together.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm so sorry.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm at no worries.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay, so we were taping and we had a malfunction, so it's kind of a little delayed.
[SPEAKER_09]: As far as the MBTA meeting, okay, so I will type up those notes.
[SPEAKER_09]: I apologize for not typing those notes.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay, but it was a very fruitful meeting and definitely something that we can be involved with, especially some of the training they have for requesting
[SPEAKER_09]: a ride on the MBTA, they have training that they can actually come out to a site and conduct these types of trainings.
[SPEAKER_09]: So I definitely connected us with this.
[SPEAKER_09]: Of course, thank you, Frances, but I'll get you all more details, but we will be involved.
[SPEAKER_10]: If that, and am I mistaken?
[SPEAKER_10]: I wanted to say that I think they recorded it and they sent us the link, or am I dreaming?
[SPEAKER_10]: Because I- I will double check.
[SPEAKER_09]: Please double check.
[SPEAKER_09]: And that would be even better.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: Because I seem to be dreaming things up like, I can't find it in my email.
[SPEAKER_10]: And I'm like, I know I saw it before.
[SPEAKER_10]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: And let me correct my name.
[SPEAKER_09]: on here.
[SPEAKER_09]: And also, I know sometimes individuals send me email, but the AOL.com is the incorrect one.
[SPEAKER_09]: It's gmail.com.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_10]: All right.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you, Yvette.
[SPEAKER_10]: Back to you, Tom.
[SPEAKER_06]: All right.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I think we're on to new business.
[SPEAKER_06]: There's nothing under there.
[SPEAKER_06]: I don't know if there's anything that anybody wanted to share.
[SPEAKER_06]: I will go ahead.
[SPEAKER_09]: So if I could go back to the follow-up, I don't know if Sue and I did have a chance to talk on the phone.
[SPEAKER_09]: And so I'm going to get Sue an Excel spreadsheet just to kind of keep track of the individuals that we're reaching out to.
[SPEAKER_09]: We're looking at, of course, the library.
[SPEAKER_09]: This is all about the logo, the branding.
[SPEAKER_09]: We are still moving forward on that just to find a space.
[SPEAKER_09]: Also, I meet over at the West Medford Community Center Friday, and that could also be a space for us to hold opportunities for people to get together so that we can build community awareness around the logo and help people learn who we are.
[SPEAKER_09]: And what we can offer.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: We had, we had, um, we talked a little bit about, um, the logo and I think, um, well, Susie's not here, but, um, maybe you guys could connect to talk more about it, but basically the plan is to, um, focus in on, uh, students.
[SPEAKER_06]: Um, and we could also send letters to the organizations that you guys have been talking about.
[SPEAKER_06]: But the goal is to try to get a logo drawn up soon, hopefully with the assistance of some students, so that we have it ready for July.
[SPEAKER_07]: That makes sense.
[SPEAKER_09]: Well, I think Susie and Sue and I will talk about it because I know we, I don't know if there's an exact reason on why we are just sticking with students versus individuals with disabilities.
[SPEAKER_09]: So that's just a little thing that Sue and I can talk about.
[SPEAKER_09]: The whole group can talk about it.
[SPEAKER_07]: No, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think that's, yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think when it was presented, it was presented as reaching out to mass rehab, reaching out to social security.
[SPEAKER_10]: Well, mass rehab and social security offices are not going to give you addresses, and they're not going to put things.
[SPEAKER_10]: They're not going to put our information in their envelopes.
[SPEAKER_10]: So where are the concrete locations that we know that we can tap into
[SPEAKER_10]: where we know that there could be people with disabilities.
[SPEAKER_10]: So we talked about the schools, middle school, high school, the different classes.
[SPEAKER_10]: We also talked about Triangle, which is right there, Malden, Medford, Everett.
[SPEAKER_10]: That whole area looks the same to me.
[SPEAKER_10]: Those are concrete go-to places, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: Something else just occurred, you know, sometimes some of the Medford Housing Authority locations as well.
[SPEAKER_10]: And then we talked about using the REC department, getting in contact with Kevin or Danny, because they run specific classes that are inclusive in nature.
[SPEAKER_10]: And they could, you know, we could actually physically give them something and say, hey, we need you to get these to the parents that show up.
[SPEAKER_10]: So that's why.
[SPEAKER_10]: But remember, this money is going to go away.
[SPEAKER_10]: And our cycle is very, very different.
[SPEAKER_10]: So when ARPA ends, ARPA ends.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's gone.
[SPEAKER_10]: So we can't spend a whole year
[SPEAKER_10]: trying to come up with a logo because we go persons with disabilities commission goes on holiday.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think, I think last year you were, I think it's July and August you're off.
[SPEAKER_10]: And then you come back again in September, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: So we got March, April, May, June.
[SPEAKER_09]: Oh, correct.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm not.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm not concerned about that deadline on getting a final logo by July.
[SPEAKER_09]: It was just, I guess, a clarification on input.
[SPEAKER_09]: This is something more about individuals with disabilities.
[SPEAKER_09]: And I do have a clarification question.
[SPEAKER_09]: Like, when we talk about disabilities, does that also include the elders?
[SPEAKER_09]: Does that include elders or how does... Think about it this way.
[SPEAKER_10]: Disabilities are...
[SPEAKER_10]: visible and invisible.
[SPEAKER_10]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_10]: So if an elder chooses to identify or chooses to be a part, who am I to say, oh, you don't have a disability.
[SPEAKER_10]: Perfect.
[SPEAKER_09]: Perfect.
[SPEAKER_09]: Because that was the reason why of just confirming that is to
[SPEAKER_09]: you know, confirm why we can include the elderly, the Medford centers, because we're not going to discriminate against them.
[SPEAKER_09]: It's like, if you want to participate, then thank you.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: You know, I think it would be interesting to see what somebody in their
[SPEAKER_10]: Somebody in their late 80s, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: It would be such an interesting comparison to see what they present as an image for a disability with somebody in their 40s and somebody in their 20s.
[SPEAKER_10]: And there's a reason I say that, it's about how disability is being viewed during those timelines.
[SPEAKER_09]: Exactly, exactly, perfect.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_09]: And Sue, I'll get back, we'll get back together.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: Now, are we on to new business?
[SPEAKER_09]: We're on to new business if we think we can finish it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: Oh, I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_09]: Go ahead.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: So a young lady lives over at the apartments across from Wegmans.
[SPEAKER_09]: And so she's a mother, her two children, her, well, her sons have MS, they were in wheelchairs.
[SPEAKER_09]: And one was 27, the other one's like early 30s.
[SPEAKER_09]: Well, her 27 year old son just passed away.
[SPEAKER_09]: She just had a stroke maybe two, three months ago.
[SPEAKER_09]: And just in the last month, her son passed away.
[SPEAKER_09]: I wanted to know, does this commission, do we do outreach for individuals within our communities that have had something like this happen?
[SPEAKER_10]: That's not, that's not the role of the commission but I do.
[SPEAKER_10]: Why do I feel like this story sounds familiar and I might have to follow up with you offline because something like this came through the Board of Health a couple of weeks ago.
[SPEAKER_10]: Does that complex across from Wegmans have a name.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes, that one.
[SPEAKER_10]: I do believe that this is the same situation.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think the health department in Medford could help.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I want to be clear, though, that when it comes to outreach, you have to be very careful because you always want to create what is going to be sustainable, what's going to be able to go on.
[SPEAKER_10]: So when the health department was made aware because the person was there conducting business, they did offer some support for what was needed.
[SPEAKER_10]: However, the city, as with most local and state agencies and not check writing agencies, can't just write you a check for be it a funeral, be it whatever.
[SPEAKER_10]: So sometimes we become hampered in that way.
[SPEAKER_10]: but we are rich in knowing where the resources are, knowing who to send people to.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I don't, you know, I did not get to meet this person.
[SPEAKER_10]: As a matter of fact, the person that came in was this person's mom, not the actual mother of the children.
[SPEAKER_10]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: who came to conduct business and was just speaking.
[SPEAKER_10]: But this is a perfect opportunity where we already know that this level of, I don't even know what to call it, devastation, shock, sadness.
[SPEAKER_10]: I mean, it's gonna have some level of impact and, you know, maybe we
[SPEAKER_10]: you know, we form a relationship and we say, hey, you know, not sure if you're interested, but I'm just going to use the senior center.
[SPEAKER_10]: The senior center is having a special lunch on such and such day, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: just so that the person can decide if they want to go or not.
[SPEAKER_10]: Or did you know that West Medford Community Center has first Fridays?
[SPEAKER_10]: Because what are we trying to do?
[SPEAKER_10]: We're trying to help that person reconnect with community just in case that there is any loneliness or aloneness that's being felt by that person through these losses.
[SPEAKER_10]: You know, those are the things that we can do.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's such, yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: But it's not the job of the commission then.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, I can imagine that's not our job, because we don't know everybody out there that does.
[SPEAKER_09]: So it was just, for me, they were an inspiration for me to be part of this commission, to be that, to help share this information, right?
[SPEAKER_09]: And so to know that this woman has lost a son who's 28, and he's got MS, and the brother has MS,
[SPEAKER_09]: And you know that that was a daily fight, right?
[SPEAKER_09]: I don't know if maybe on our agenda, we look for how do we have opportunities for people to get together?
[SPEAKER_09]: Maybe every three months or something, there is some kind of gathering, even if it's on Zoom, but just so that people just don't feel lost because this mother is in a room, in her apartment with her sole surviving son, right?
[SPEAKER_09]: And she just had a heart attack.
[SPEAKER_09]: So, I mean, a stroke.
[SPEAKER_09]: So I know that she's not the only person in Medford that is going through this.
[SPEAKER_09]: And so anyway, I thank you for allowing me to share that, but I would just maybe later on down the line, we can think about how do we create a space where we can come together and at least share and be around other people.
[SPEAKER_04]: What about the new space on, I wanna say it's Riverside, where they made a little plaza?
[SPEAKER_04]: You know the plaza they made where there's a chess game going on?
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, a plaza where people know once a month, once every two months, this is the day or the morning, come share your grief.
[SPEAKER_04]: with other people.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know what I'm saying?
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm just saying it lightly, but I think about a space.
[SPEAKER_10]: Those things are all wonderful, but they have to be led by an individual.
[SPEAKER_10]: They can't be led.
[SPEAKER_10]: Like if you want to lead that, it's just like the meetups, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: But it's not something that the city could lead this because the city couldn't commit to that.
[SPEAKER_10]: Do you see what I'm saying?
[SPEAKER_10]: And that's why I said, like, as the way I share information with all of you as to what's coming, you know, maybe with this woman, we can, if we have her, you know, email address, we can somehow, you know, make sure that she's on the email list to get, you know, the flyers that come out so that she knows that things are out there.
[SPEAKER_10]: But, you know, as far as, you know, creating spaces,
[SPEAKER_10]: Many people are doing that on their own, you know, people are forming knitting groups, people are forming, you know, Mums Take Their Lives Back groups and things of that nature.
[SPEAKER_10]: So if as individuals you want to do that, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_10]: But it wouldn't be something necessarily under the purview of the commission, not by the way the commission was designed.
[SPEAKER_10]: Now, if the commission, again, so this is future, future idea.
[SPEAKER_10]: If the commission decided that it wanted to commit to once a year, a celebration of our immunities, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: You now, and it's like this big powwow, prom, limos, big hotel, blah, you know, that's different, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: You're doing something and you're doing something specifically for the disability community, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: It is focused, it links to you, the group as a commission.
[SPEAKER_10]: But what you're talking about, Yvette, is just in general, you know, it's just that humanitarian piece.
[SPEAKER_10]: Like, there's just, I'm still shaking my head because you reminded me of the story, you know, and it's not just this one.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's so many others.
[SPEAKER_10]: And it's the unfortunate reality of this world.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think that that's why it's important for us to be more intentional in our work, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: Like if we're gonna do the resource fair to do it well, because we know that it's gonna mean more than just a resource fair to some people.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a lifeline.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right, right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_06]: Um, I had kind of, well, I know we only have a few minutes left.
[SPEAKER_06]: Um, I'll forward you the email, but I did go to a training with the mass office, uh, disability.
[SPEAKER_06]: Uh, it's called, uh, quarterly tea.
[SPEAKER_06]: Um, and I get to, they get together quarterly and the, um, topic, uh, this time was navigating support options to resolve disability related issues.
[SPEAKER_06]: So they went.
[SPEAKER_06]: went through how to, if you're presented with an issue, how do you figure out where to go to get support?
[SPEAKER_06]: So I'll forward you the slides and there's a transcript, I think it was a video and all that.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I'll do that after the meeting.
[SPEAKER_10]: Sorry, Tom, I forgot to add that in.
[SPEAKER_10]: If you're interested, I would encourage you to sign up for the MOD newsletter so that the staff can come to your
[SPEAKER_10]: your inboxes directly.
[SPEAKER_10]: Sometimes I feel bad.
[SPEAKER_10]: Sometimes I feel like I'm doing inbox assault because I'll send things at strange times of the night because that's when I'm getting to actually read them, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: And I need to get them out to you ASAP.
[SPEAKER_10]: But there's just a lot of this fabulous free information that's empowering.
[SPEAKER_10]: You know, a lot of times I take it and I store it somewhere like a squirrel storing, you know, their nuts for the winter.
[SPEAKER_10]: And then all of a sudden someone says something and I go and I open it up and I take it out and I'm like, here you go.
[SPEAKER_10]: I learned this two months ago, you know, but I do encourage you to sign up for the MOD newsletter because they have a lot of really great.
[SPEAKER_04]: Can you say the initials again?
[SPEAKER_10]: Oh, gee, so that's mass office of disability.
[SPEAKER_10]: Oh, of course.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, Francis, do you want to wrap up with the to see there's two respondents.
[SPEAKER_10]: Sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_10]: So the Human Rights Commission is hosting a Black History Month event on Saturday.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's going to take place at the Royal House and Slave Quarters.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's titled, Remembering Belinda Sutton, Resistance, Activism, and Reparations.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's from 1 to 3.30 p.m.
[SPEAKER_10]: And it will feature a guest speaker, a reading of the petition, singing by S Factor, who are an a cappella group from Tufts.
[SPEAKER_10]: And there'll be some pastries from Grek Cafe.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yvette, you don't want to see the list of yum-yums.
[SPEAKER_10]: She was showing them to me and I was just like, yeah, we'll take that.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes, we'll take that.
[SPEAKER_10]: Oh, yes, we'll take that.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_10]: Marsha, Marsha, you're chuckling.
[SPEAKER_10]: But, you know, it's just it'll be nice.
[SPEAKER_10]: And there's a tour available afterwards.
[SPEAKER_10]: Medford Community Media is going to be recording it and then it will be edited for rebroadcast.
[SPEAKER_10]: So there's that.
[SPEAKER_10]: And then on Sunday, join the Office of Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion and the Interfaith Community.
[SPEAKER_10]: We are hosting an interfaith blessing at Shiloh Baptist Church.
[SPEAKER_10]: Again, another Black History Month events, the second to final one for the, you live in the same building.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: Oh, how dangerous.
[SPEAKER_10]: So that event is on Sunday, February 26.
[SPEAKER_10]: It is a potluck finger foods.
[SPEAKER_10]: Everybody is welcome to that event.
[SPEAKER_10]: It is at three o'clock starts at three slated from three to five.
[SPEAKER_10]: I have a feeling we're going to be there past five by choice, not by necessity.
[SPEAKER_10]: And I don't know if you've gone to an interfaith program before.
[SPEAKER_10]: This is not so much worship.
[SPEAKER_10]: This is more of a coming together of the different embodiments, the Jewish culture, the Pentecostal culture, the Baptist culture.
[SPEAKER_10]: There's going to be some singing.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yours truly is going to be reading a poem.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: And that's at 1 Halton Street.
[SPEAKER_10]: And there'll be, yeah, food.
[SPEAKER_10]: And there'll be, you know, a healing ritual.
[SPEAKER_10]: And I believe we're going to be doing, oh my gosh, don't let Rabbi Jessica know I pronounced it like this, but it's the alhit.
[SPEAKER_10]: Alhit, it's a incantation that's in line with the Jewish tradition and stuff.
[SPEAKER_10]: This is when we want to set intentions.
[SPEAKER_10]: So that's going to be really, really nice as well.
[SPEAKER_10]: might shed that flyer already.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: We're right at seven o'clock.
[SPEAKER_06]: OK.
[SPEAKER_06]: I know we did not approve the January minutes, so read them.
[SPEAKER_06]: Well, why don't we wait till next meeting?
[SPEAKER_06]: We'll do it the next meeting.
[SPEAKER_06]: So if you can read them between now and then.
[SPEAKER_06]: And Gabby, I'll send you the minutes from the beginning of the meeting.
[SPEAKER_06]: and then we'll put together this month's minutes so we can review them together and we can vote on them next time.
[SPEAKER_12]: Perfect.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_12]: I already shared tonight's minutes with everybody on a Google Doc.
[SPEAKER_12]: I've just been working as we go along.
[SPEAKER_12]: So I promise there won't be any more delays in sending them out.
[SPEAKER_06]: You're awesome.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you, Gabby.
[SPEAKER_12]: Likewise.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_09]: Watch the video of our meetings.
[SPEAKER_09]: Are they somewhere?
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, Medford Community Media puts them up.
[SPEAKER_10]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_10]: If you go to MC, if you go to MCM, because what happens like this is recording to the cloud.
[SPEAKER_10]: So once the meeting ends, it takes about, usually it's like five minutes, seven minutes, max spits out a password and a link.
[SPEAKER_10]: And I usually send it off to them or like today had this not here.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I would send it off to Heather, just, you know,
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: We have a motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_09]: Motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_10]: How about a second?
[SPEAKER_10]: All right, everyone.
[SPEAKER_10]: Wow, it looks like we're having thirds and fourths.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay, Yvette, hold on one second.
[SPEAKER_10]: All right, I'm stopping the recording, everyone.
[SPEAKER_10]: Are you sure you want to stop the recording?
[SPEAKER_02]: Recording stopped.