[SPEAKER_03]: Go at the same time.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like shoot to the mirror.
[SPEAKER_03]: Start at like 50 miles an hour across the room.
time will change everything
[SPEAKER_02]: I intended this to happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a space shuttle.
[SPEAKER_00]: All right, Chris.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wow.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're getting so ambitious
[SPEAKER_03]: I remember at the beginning of the year, you were like, if you get an A, you're out.
[SPEAKER_02]: That was four minutes.
[SPEAKER_02]: You did that in four minutes.
[SPEAKER_03]: That was two servos, too.
[SPEAKER_02]: Two servos, four minutes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Good job.
[SPEAKER_00]: That looks like a win.
[SPEAKER_00]: Double elimination round.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go, go, go.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wow, nice job.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop, stop, stop, stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is a great job.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good, good.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know.
I don't know how high you were about to reach.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no,
[SPEAKER_00]: We are doing so much better than last year.
[SPEAKER_01]: 100% better than last year.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, we're doing 132% better.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, 132... more.
[SPEAKER_01]: 132... more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, no, like, we're doing infinity... infinity high.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever, we did it!
[SPEAKER_02]: Next up, outstanding robot synchronization.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, this team had one very efficient robot.
[SPEAKER_03]: And another one that went up like absolutely everything it possibly could, came back, and then usually, at the last minute, it would drive it into the loading zone, and the other robot would finally wake up and push the transport square on top of all the cool stuff.
[SPEAKER_03]: Very cool, very patient robot, and well-synchronized.
That is Team 547 Medfield.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't see me come, oh who can blame them?
[SPEAKER_00]: They never seem to catch my eye, but I never wonder why I won't fall asleep, I won't fall asleep I am, don't let them know we're coming I am, tick tock higher, take some time to