Well welcome everyone to our March 2023 Commission on persons with disabilities meeting I have no idea where February went but if you find it let me know. And I have no idea where March is going, either.
I guess resistance is futile, but I hope you're all doing well. And I'm going to push the record button and hand over to chair Tom for the agenda. Recording in progress. All right, happy March.
I here, let me, and I was looking for the January minutes. I'm going to pull up the, the agenda, which I think the first one is to do the minutes. I'm on the wrong email. Hold on a second.
All right, so I guess we will do an introduction. We'll do a quick introduction. I don't know if we have any... My name is there. I've looked at everything. I can't get on. Oh, we can hear you. Now she's muted. All right, well, why don't we start introductions? I'll go. I'm Tom Hamel. I'm the chair.
on the commission for a little over two years. And yeah, pass along. Marsha, you want to go? So I'll go ahead and jump in with introductions. I'm Linda Braden. I am a resident of Medford, and I've been on the commission for a couple of years. I'm the vice chair. I help out mainly with digital accessibility aspects for the
the commission and I'll pop it back over to Marsha. My audio there. Can you hear me? Okay. I can't hear. I am using not my own computer, which may die in the middle of this. They say, no, it overheats. It needs a core. And so
I'm sorry, I'll try again. I'll get it nice back. That's what the person I borrowed it from does. That's enough. Computer complaint. Yeah, sit here please. Susan, do you want to introduce yourself?
Hi, I'm Susan. I am a chair. Oh, I'm a past chair. And I've been on the commission for at least eight years. And I live in South Medford and I,
Yes, I am. Yeah, that's me. And my pronouns are she, her, hers. Thanks, Susan. Gabby, you want to go? Sure. Hi, everyone. My name is Gabby. I've been on the commission since 2019. My pronouns are she, her, hers. And right now I'm serving as secretary.
Thank you. Hello, my name is Yvette Wilkes. I just joined the commission this year. And my pronouns are she, her, hers. Thank you. Susie, you ready? I don't think she can hear us. Heather.
Hi, Heather McKinnon. I've been on the commission for, I guess, about a year and a half. My pronouns are she, her, hers. Thank you. Frances? Hi, Frances Wojciech, Director of Diversity, Equity and Inclusion for the City of Medford and also City Liaison for the commission.
All right, and Melanie. Hi, everyone. I'm Melanie Perkins McLaughlin. I am Medford resident. I live in West Medford. I have three children. My youngest has intellectual developmental disability, and I am a school committee member. Thank you. Susie, can you hear us?
She's still working on it. So our first item on the agenda is to approve our February meeting minutes we're also going to approve our January meeting minutes, we did not have a quorum last month so we were unable to go through this every month. So we're going to go ahead and approve.
Why don't we do January 1st, or we'll do January 1st does anybody want to make a motion to approve them. We did, I believe we can review them last time which is never done before. What you're doing right now. I saw Joe and that raise their hands in regards to the January meeting minutes. Oh, thank you. I missed that.
Joe, would you make the motion to approve the minutes? And Yvette, you're going to second it? All in favor? I see everyone's hands raised. Excellent. All opposed? Any abstentions? All right, great. Gabby, you got that? Thank you. Got it. Thank you.
All right, February meeting minutes. Anybody have any revisions to the February meeting minutes. I'm going to click the board. I can't keep doing this stuff every month. Francis, do you know how I can mute Susie? I did already. Got it. All right.
Sorry, anybody, you can unmute yourself if you have a revision or you want to make a motion to pass the February minutes. I would make a motion to pass the meeting minutes, please. For a second. Thank you, Heather and Susan. All in favor? Oh, I should be voting, by the way. Great. Any nays? Abstentions?
Thank you. All right, so our next item on the agenda is we want to talk, we actually want to spend a lot of our meeting talking about the Disability Resource Fair. So we have some updates there. Gabby, do you mind starting us off with the information you have?
Sure. So we reached out to both the Brooks and the Andrews. They did confirm availability for both buildings. I know we've done a little bit of back and forth. Unfortunately, the person who is in charge of kind of putting everything together has been out of the office. So I've been kind of playing email tag with them a little bit. But to the best of my knowledge, both the Andrews and the Brooks are still available.
I believe at this point that the Brooks may not have a screen in the cafeteria area, which may make it difficult if our main goal is to stream Crip Camp. When I did speak with, I think his name is Bobby Maloney. He's like a
one of the directors of, um, I don't know, planning for the city, but the schools, um, and he explains that the Andrews may be better, um, because you can use both of the gym and the cafeteria space, which are all on the first floor. Um, he also emphasized that the bathrooms are a little bit more easily accessible. I guess they have the main bathrooms on that first floor in between the cafeteria and the gym.
that obviously have accessible stalls. And then he mentioned that there's another accessible bathroom somewhere else in the building that could be used as well. So he kind of advocated for the Andrews. I know that there was an email somewhere along the lines where there was some concerns with parking. I didn't get the chance to confirm with him if we could utilize the parking also at the McGlynn, but I would imagine- No, it's gonna go back to the same thing. Lee, please.
Um, so at this point I don't have an immediate response from him, um, from Bobby. He's still out of the office, but I've been kind of just making sure that they're still available and that's, that's the best I can do at this point until he's back in the office. He's supposed to be back on Monday. So I, um, I finally got some confirmation about what's really happening.
you know, parking at either the Andrews or the McGlynn is going to be impacted by the fact that all the fields are being used at a variety of different times. And the, basically what I was told was the later the event, the better. Well, I don't know how much later we can go if the soccer field is being used until five o'clock in the evening.
So, you know, if we're having a disability resource fair and we have a parking situation, that's not ideal. Melanie, I see you've raised your hand.
Yeah. I mean, I was going to say that perhaps the screening could be, um, a little bit later because it leaves a nice, you know, atmosphere for a movie anyway, when it's, you know, evening versus sort of midday or morning. But, um, I guess I'm a little bit confused too. I didn't know if this, I didn't realize this was a, uh, as much a disability resource fair as I thought it was a disability pride event. Um, and so maybe I'm misunderstanding.
resource fair pride event, either way, the parking is still going to be an issue. You know, if it's got something to do with people with disabilities, we need to make sure that it's as accessible as possible. And, you know, it's something that I have to speak about in house, because, you know, if we're gonna, if, if everything is going to shift to the primary spaces that people utilize to host events, because we're working on
parks and upgrades and other areas, we have to sort of give space to the disability community.
I guess I'm not sure. So from what I'm hearing Gabby say is the Andrews and the Brooks are the choices now because the high school was not an option because of the school events that are there on Saturdays. Is that accurate? I did not inquire about the high school only because at our last meeting, we had just discussed the Brooks meeting, but I'm happy to check on
Medford High? I thought the reason we weren't doing Medford High in the first place was that there was an issue with parking because that was actually what I understood was going to be the first choice. Um, and then I think, I thought the issue there was parking. So Francis didn't, am I mistaken? All the fields are being used by different teams, be it soccer, be it baseball. They're being used for an expanded period of time.
So the fields that surround like the Andrews, the fields that go all the way back, as a result, that impact- Because we can hear you, can you? As a result, that impacts the ability to have parking. No, I understand. I understand. And there's parking in the back for the fields for Medford High School and all on the side where the Medford Family Network is.
And then there's the front whole parking lot. So it just seems to me that there's more opportunity at the high school for parking than there would be elsewhere. I understand that the fields are being used, but if the fields are being used over at the McGlynn, then it's the McGlynn and the Andrews lot as well. And I'm assuming you guys are locked in on a Saturday. Is that why? Cause I don't know. Could Sunday be an option? Like what are the other options that we're thinking about?
And I guess I also just didn't, I also thought the ADA committee was working on this at the schools too. So I feel like we, you know, could have had a direct connection with the schools to be able to keep updated on this too. So I want to make sure that I reach out to the ADA committee that we've been working with too. So they're looped in, but I feel like the, you know, I know that when this was first brought up, both,
Mr. DeLava and Mr. Tucci were, you know, very responsive and, you know, offering their building and their unit. So I'm just not sure if there's been cross communication with the school organizations as well, or if I can facilitate that or what's going on.
Is Mr. DeLava still in his current role or has he switched roles already? Because there's a role transition that's taking place. Yeah, I believe he'll be here to the end of the year. Gabby, would you mind reaching out to Mr. DeLava to ask about the high school? Yeah, I would be happy to. Would we still be planning for the 29th?
It would be the 29th. I don't have the ability to change my schedule and I've already put a hold on the day. And just as far as logistics, as Melanie kind of mentioned before, would we be wanting to do it still as a vendor event to be inviting people or would we just want it to kind of be more of a community event with the high school and people within Medford and then streaming the movie?
I think that it would be lovely to stream the movie. I think that there is, you know, you get better collaboration.
having vendors on hand who are available that can, you know, that can share some of what they do. Part of the reason why I leaned towards the resource fair, but also having, you know, people from the community coming in to see what, you know, what vendors are available. I mean, my gosh, if somebody was an OT vendor and did like specialized meal equipment,
that, believe it or not, crosses over, not just for persons with disabilities, but sometimes, you know, folks that might, you know, have had like a medical situation, like a stroke and things of that nature. So I envision having variety of those types of vendors are available and showing the movie at the start of the event, which is the movie, if I'm not mistaken, is one hour and 47 minutes, I think.
I'm not sure about the version though, Gabby. I watched the movie, so it's about one hour and 47 minutes, but I'm not sure about the version that you pulled. I think that that's extremely important. This also is a great space to honor the mother of disability rights, Judy. So I really feel like, you know,
the movie is the mainframe and everything else is just sort of the backdrop and introducing people to being in the same space at the same time. May I, Tom? Go ahead. Thank you. Um, yeah, no, I would agree. I think the movie is a really important part and I think honoring Judy Heumann is a really great idea and helping people understand who she is and why she
was so, um, is so important to the movement is really important. Um, and I think having, um, vendors there is also really an important idea in terms of, you know, people gathering to understand, you know, who, who exists, who they are, you know, what opportunities are there, whatever. Um, and I, I really was interested when this idea was first brought up with the ADA committee,
the initiative was, you know, the, um, the, um, LGBTQ pride event went so well and has gone so well over the past couple of years that we really wanted to, you know, um, expand that to, uh, disability pride and really looking at this as, you know, a disability pride movement as well, and not as much a resource fair, um, as, you know, people getting together, gathering together to celebrate.
um, differences and disability and also to understand resources and what's there. And I think, you know, to understand the history of disability rights and civil rights and, you know, the school district, we were able to, um, a couple of years ago, get the school district to implement a disability awareness program that they do training with the staff and do professional development. And we offer, um, a disability awareness presentation, um, around, you know, civil rights, um, of persons with disabilities. And so,
I imagine that we could have something like that even on a monitor, some of the images of disability rights and disability pride around with the vendors. So I would like to see this as a celebration with information.
I think that's a great idea. I think that was kind of the vision that we started with. And the more we brainstormed, we kind of, there's a lot of great ideas. And I think finding a way to incorporate them through more of a disability pride event, but still have resources available is a great idea. I think my last question for locking in, hopefully the high school, do we have an idea of how much time we would want?
And is there a specific space in Medford High that we want to request, or should I just kind of let Mr. DeLeva guide where he thinks events work? Like, I'm not super familiar with the high school, so I just want to make sure that I'm requesting what we're looking for. I believe Mr. DeLeva offered the Karen Theater. I mean, I'll have to double check on our emails, but I believe he offered the theater for the screening, which obviously makes sense.
And then generally what happens when there are theater based events there, then there's the, you know, the foyer out front for, you know, vendor activities or other activities. Now, the Japanese school has been active there on Saturday. So I'm not sure what the status is with that, but we can check with Mr. DeLeva. And again, if it's a later in the afternoon event, cause the Japanese school is in the morning, it might not be, you know, as significant and thinking about, I think it's also really important that folks understand that Crip Camp is not,
It's PG-13, right? It has to be for people older than 13 with parental guidance even in that sense, because it's a wonderful film and it definitely deals with some adult topics. So I think we need to make sure that families are aware of that. But I believe Mr. DeLeva offered the Karen Theater in the beginning as Mr. Tucci did with the McGlynn Theater.
I just want to make sure that everyone knows that I have 10 to 2 blocked off on the city calendar for this event. And then 3 to 6 is for the Arab American Heritage event. So if there is a switch, that is going to create a conflict. Because initially, when we talked about this, this was supposed to be
I think we went from a six-hour event, because we're looking at a full day when the ADA group was speaking, and narrowed it down to a much shorter event. OK. So I'll, sorry, go ahead, Tom. Can you repeat that? I missed the times. It sounds like, for instance, we're working within the time restriction. Can you just repeat those times? 10 to 2. 10 to 2, OK.
Go ahead, Gabby. So no, I was just going to say, I'll reach out to Mr. DeLava and propose 10 to 2, and I'll kind of explain that's the that's the window we're working with. And hopefully there's not any conflicts. I'll try to get information on
or dates and times, locations, um, and I'll update by email, but, um, fingers crossed at this point and we'll hopefully go ahead. I would also make a suggestion that maybe the resource, I mean the, you know, the, the vendor tables happen first, people get to mingle a bit with the vendor tables. Maybe there's like a, a concession table where, you know, some money can be raised for, you know, either the,
you know, autism support group through MFN or CPAC or both, whatever. And then people could, you know, view the movie. And so I would suggest like a, maybe like a 10 to 12 sort of social networking and a 12 to 2 screening if I might. And I think that that will give people
because I think if people watch the film, they might just leave. But this way, if people are coming in, can come and go, meet people, the vendor tables can get to know each other. People can sort of talk a bit and then start to gather for the movie from 12 to two. So that's how I would think it, the way that I've seen them work before, that it could work. And just putting a bug in people's ear for like the future. I mean, I think, obviously this is the first one, I hope, of what will be an annual event.
And so really thinking about, you know, what works, would it be better to do something like, you know, in the future, like in the evening, there's lots of events at the high school in the evening too, that are really fun. So just thinking about like, when you go to events, what do you like? What do you see? You know, what do you think is, you know, helpful? And I'm doing the same, just sort of keeping an eye out. And speaking of which this next week, the 29th, is the transition fair.
And that's from, I believe, seven to nine. And I think it's at, well, it's definitely at the high school, I don't know. It's in the gymnasium, yeah, at the high school, seven to nine. And that's a really great opportunity to see some of the vendors that you might be interested in, or we might be interested in for this event, because there's lots of vendors there as well. And the transition program is for those folks who are 18 to 22, or actually 14 to 22 considering
you know, uh, their adult life and transitioning out of, um, school. And so it's an event where, um, students and parents and community members and anybody who wants to can come and, you know, meet folks that provide transition services and opportunities and recreation and stuff. So I think that I'll definitely be there gathering, um, cards from folks and talking to them about the 29th. So, um, just might be a good opportunity for others if they have the chance to come by and check it out.
Thank you for mentioning that Melanie I just wanted to also bring up the, I know you've mentioned before the accessibility issues at the high school is there a way to reduce or, you know, I'm not sure what the word is I'm looking for but making it easier for, especially with folks with wheelchairs I think that's the kind of the biggest accessibility issues at the high school.
Yeah, they're gonna have to use the right-hand ramp at this point. There is an accessible ramp by the media station, so they'll use those. We'll have to block off those parking spaces at the top for anyone that needs disability access. There's two spots there already that need to be repainted, I think, but there should be other spots, too, that we can certainly mark for the event at the top, sort of right near the ramp. And there's a ramp there, and then they'll just have to make sure that the door on the right-hand side is open
And then once they go into the door on the right-hand side, they can get to the auditorium. They just take a left to get to the auditorium. So the main door is the bumpy part. And I think we'd have to have people there directing for folks that need disability access and clearly marked signage, which is another topic for another day, perhaps.
Does Gabby need to ask for that? I don't know what, I'm not sure what it's like on a Saturday in terms of who's there and do we have to ask that that door be open? I'm happy to work with Gabby on that. If you guys want me to, I'm happy to work with her on, you know, making sure that not only that the door's open, but that there's very clear, you know, instruction and signage and, you know, whether there's, they have somebody outside with a vest on too, that's sort of directing people.
to help support people provided that the date's still available and Mr. DeLava still thinks that, you know, I mean, is still available that, you know, we can still do that. And then secondly, I would just say, if that's not the case and it's back down to the Andrews and the Brooks, you know, I think that the Brooks is certainly an option. It's just that it's smaller. We can get a screen and a,
and a projector. I don't I don't think that's a problem. We could do that. It's just a small, it's a small venue. And again, you know, maybe in the future, you know, next year, we'll be thinking about bigger venues and being able to do something outside or something otherwise. But I just think the Brooks is small. But I think checking in with I know, Francis, you said the fields are all being used on Saturday. And I know
Bobby Maloney, as you were saying, Gabby has a better idea sort of of what the schedules are on Saturday as well. So even circling back with Bobby about that Saturday, because it could be that there's an away game, who knows, you know, maybe because he knew he said he recommended the McGlynn. So I would double check with him about why and what he thinks about parking and accessibility. And if you don't feel comfortable doing that, I'm totally comfortable doing that. So we can also figure that out if you'd like.
And then I'll also ask maybe if the minutes from tonight could be shared. I guess we have to wait till they're approved. I guess I could just include notes from tonight to the ADA committee to let them know sort of how the planning process is happening here too.
Um, I can send you my like unofficial draft notes if that's helpful. Um, on that note about the ADA, it's the ADA committee. Is that the official name? Okay. Um, I was thinking that while we're kind of trying to get ahead and plan more events and kind of be more involved in the community, I do think it would be a good idea for us to collaborate, um, with the ADA committee, just because I know there are some areas that our group is very familiar with and I bet there's,
some areas that people in that committee are also very, very well versed in. And I was thinking that perhaps for our future meetings to maybe put on the agenda to invite them and have them included just for kind of planning.
I could make a motion to do that if anybody would like to second it. So I guess I would like to make a motion to invite members of the ADA committee to our next meeting to kind of continue planning, looking into the end of the spring and into the fall as well. I'd second that motion. Before we make the motion, I just want to make sure that we keep on track only because we're going to make the motion. So maybe bring it in under new
business right when we get to that section so that it's noted under there and it's not lost because because we have a lot of like open items from all the different meetings because we get excited and energized and it's like, wait a second, we need to go close this off, you know, so let's sort of like finish this discussion about, you know, the upcoming event.
who's doing what, what piece people are taking and not taking, set some timelines, and then go into the technology update from Tom and Sue. And then we have Marcia who emailed about wanting to share something, and then the motion for inviting members of the ADA group.
So I think you have a motion on the floor with a second. So either you guys have to vote, and according to Robert's rules, I think either you guys have to vote for that, you know, about the motion, or you can ask to, the person who made the motion can ask to postpone the motion, I believe, till, you know, or put the motion on the table, and then you can pick it up off the table. But you, now that you have, if you've had a motion and a second, it's on the table and you can't take it off without,
you know, a person that made the motion or somebody else asking for the motion to be tabled. And then the group can decide whether to table the motion. And then somebody has to vote to take it off the table. And then the group can decide whether to take it off the table. So this is all Robert's rules, basic, you know, Robert's rules of order, parliamentary procedure, not to be a nudge, but having learned far too much of it from school committee, I just know that, you know, that's the way that it has to be followed, especially if there are folks watching,
who know the rules. So Gabby, do you want to table this for a new business?
Sure, I am happy to do that. I do need to be kind of in the car by like 6.35. So if we're not on new business at that point, I may bring it up again, just to make sure that it is on. I'll still be on until seven, but I'll kind of be, my camera and my audio will be off as much as possible. So we can continue, but I will bring it back up
Pretty soon. So Melody, you're saying we have to vote to table it? Gabby has to make a motion to, not has to, if Gabby chooses, she has to make a motion to table her motion. And then she needs a second, if people have a second, and then you take a vote on whether you're all willing to table the motion. And then when, and whether Gabby or anybody else wants to take the motion off the table, they'll make a motion to take it off the table. They'll need a second, and then you'll have to vote on that. So Gabby would need to make a motion to put it on the table.
Okay, so I am making a motion to put it on the table. Does anybody second my motion? I'll second it. Thank you. All in favor, you say either aye or raise your hands. Anybody opposed? Heather, I didn't catch your vote. Anybody abstaining?
You're voting yes. Okay. All right. Motion carries will table it to new business. So, I don't know if we're ready to move on from the disability. You know resource fair day. Because there is still some things that we need to plan concurrently such as okay who's doing what right now.
removing a lot of the physical logistics. So I was thinking we should talk about vendors and who can invite vendors. Is that what you're referring to, Frances? Yeah, so sort of like a division of labor. We've done the location. We've done the time. Now we're on the vendors. We know about the movie. And vendors invite creation.
All right, so does anybody want, well, so we can come up, we can brainstorm some ideas about vendors. Does anybody have, anybody want to coordinate contacting vendors?
I'm happy to do that. I don't know tons of vendors, but I was thinking of creating a Google Doc where people could kind of list who they're planning on contacting, who they've already contacted, just so it can be updated as we go along. Can you share some of the ideas you had for vendors?
My wheelhouse is mostly the blind community. So the Carroll Center and Perkins were my first two. My guess is if I ask the Carroll Center, they will just ask me to be their information person, and that's fine with me. I feel wonderful, though, Gabby, because that is a sector of the disability community that doesn't get as much
coverage you know I didn't mean to cut you off but I don't know if folks understand that it was the result of a legally blind person that you actually got braille on the ATM machines because before you would have to take let's say somebody like me right to go and help you and what if I was a bit of a shady character right so I you know
I love the idea of having the Carroll Center and Perkins, and I don't know, maybe if one of those, maybe Perkins, you know, if they're willing to join us, you know, to bring some of the glasses that really help to stimulate some of the visual impairments that people go through. Here I go again, getting off track.
All right, somebody keep me calm. I would also say the Federation for Children with Special Needs will table, I'm sure. And then, you know, I'm going to a resource fair this Saturday at Boston Public Schools. And there'll be lots of vendors there. And I will be going, you know, obviously, I work at the Federation, and we have lots of resource fairs with lots of vendors. So, you know, I definitely would like to see some
recreation vendors like Waypoint, who's doing some work with our schools, Waypoint Adventures, I think could be on there. I think I would love to see Walnut Street Center there. So folks know that we have Walnut Street Center here, especially if people wanted to volunteer or get to know some of the residents over at Walnut Street Center. I think it's a really great opportunity to think about how we're fostering community and community-based stuff. I think, you know,
maybe having a table that's for Medford Public Schools that is, you know, tabled by, you know, some of the students with disabilities, I think would be a great idea. And, you know, I'm happy, Gabby, to work on the spreadsheet as well, and I think other people obviously can, with a shared Google spreadsheet, I think is a great idea. You know, and I can commit to, I can commit to contacting, say, 10 potential vendors
If, if folks want to take, you know, numbers and think about, you know, adding them to the list or however you guys want to do it but I can certainly offer 10 that I can reach out to. So if Gabby and Melanie.
coordinate putting together a spreadsheet? Would there be some assistance from other commissioners to make contact from that spreadsheet? So Marsha, thank you, Marsha. No, no, no, no. I have my own. Oh, you're raising your hand for something else. Okay. Yes. I have a little bit of contact in elder services. And to answer the floating question, many elder people are disabled, a higher percentage than any other age group.
So I don't know exactly what's available, but I'm willing to talk to the people I know. Okay. Thank you, Marsha. Yvette, I see your hands up, but is that to ask a question or is that to join in the contacting of the vendors? Okay. That is to join. I don't understand what you all mean when you say a vendor. I don't know if that's a vendor that's selling a product. I'm asking, are you,
Are they charging or like Melanie said, tabling, you know, are these organizations that we're bringing? So is that what this whole area is going to consist of? Yes, these are organizations that are going to come and share their resources or their products as part of this event. Oh, okay then. So nobody's selling anything.
No. Okay. Okay. Thank you. It depends, you know, it depends like, you know, clothing, like, let's think about that. You know, we have some small businesses that do unique clothing for people that have sensitivity issues. Right. Um, so if we're talking, if we're talking about like adaptive clothing, dignity, that's dignified. Yes. I think that that would be,
a great vendor to have on hand but we're not this, this is not a, it's not a fair, a business fair, per se, the specific focus is on expanding the world of the disability community to those who don't live in that community right so bringing people who aren't familiar closer
And also showcasing and sharing the pride that there is in all of our unique abilities and the different resources that are out there as well. Thank you. Okay, so I'm getting a little bit. I only have x number of time.
Yes, we can hear you, Susie. Okay, I'm really sorry, and my husband's name is up on the screen. That's okay, Susan. I'm way out of state. I'm not in the state right now. Susan, that's all right, that's all right. Okay, so I just wanna finish my sentence. So I'm giving up precious family time, because this board is really important to me, but I couldn't get on my computer for some reason. Luckily, I have a very tech,
daughter who lives where I am right now, came running down and said, put it on her father's computer. And that's why his name is up there. So anyway, I apologize. I was excited to share with Tom about the library because I'm very excited what I learned about the library from Sam. I am just thrilled about what they're doing. So I want to get back to, I know the agenda is about the disability fair. I will contact for sure.
the med for rec department, because what they're doing with adaptive programming for children is really great. And then also at the library, they'll resources that they have for not only adaptive children, for seniors, for disabled and really reaching out. I think Tom got a gist of that right the other day, Tom. But it's-
They have sensory rooms, they have technology, accessibility to seniors and disabled. I'm looking at Marcia. Marcia, a lot of resources from disabled and games and just really embracing seniors and disabled. So I'd really like to get them at this fair, you know, even if it's one representative,
And from each of those two, I would love to see that because the library and the rec department really can shape a city. And the fact that they're embracing it is really heartening to me. Anyway, that's all I'm going to say as Tom Fowler Finn, even though I'm not Tom Fowler Finn. Thank you, Suzy. Francis, do you want to finish your thought?
So what I wanted to find out from the commissioners, because if it's a yes, I have to get some orders in ASAP, is do you at this time, as you don't have a logo, want to do what the Human Rights Commissioners did, have something such as the City of Medford's logo or seal and then the wording Commission on Persons with Disabilities.
so that you have something to give out and you have the ability to use it on a table where people can come, they can sign in so that you can capture email addresses for your future events, that type of stuff. And then they can take some swag along with them. So that's one question that I wanted to throw out.
Um, and then the second question was for you, Joe, I do recall that you had mentioned that you had a friend who fixes wheelchairs. Is that correct? Or did I get that wrong? Um, there's a, uh, one of the prisons up in Shirley, they have the inmates, uh, rebuilding wheelchairs and, um,
I believe the program is still there. I can look into it. I also have another person that has wheelchairs. So are you asking for wheelchairs or just for that day? No, I'm not asking for wheelchairs. It's going to be again.
I'm not asking for wheelchairs. The reason I brought that up is because wheelchairs are one of the most expensive things to fix. And if you're one like myself, they don't fix it right away. So it's really nice to have that sort of option that's available.
I don't know if it's gotten any better, but when I was more involved in the field, I mean, sometimes it could take up to, you know, a good five years for somebody to get a wheelchair that they had actually outgrown or that was really no longer well suited for them. So that's why I brought that up. You don't see a lot of places that fix wheelchairs, and that would have been like a nice vendor to invite.
There's an organization called re equip that does that now for the state. And it's, um, was started by parents actually of children with disabilities. And, um, we were able to get access to a wheelchair very quickly for grace. My daughter, when she had, um, significant, um, hip surgery, um, and they deliver them right to your door, um, and they'll fix this and people can donate the ones that they have and they repair them for use for others. So,
It's now under the state government, but it's re-equipped. But you know, there's lots of places like that. So the Mass Office on Disability, some of the other state agencies that we can reach out to for tabling. I mean, it's not that long a notice now, so it's hard to know who will and who won't, but I think it's just a great first attempt. And I was just gonna ask you guys, I know you're talking about your CO,
having commissioned for persons with disability from Medford. And I'm wondering if there's a budget for you at all for potentially a tablecloth. So having a table for the commission, I think would be really great.
Melody, what I'm doing right now is not the finalized logo. The committee is actually still working on getting their logo, which would go on their tablecloth. So this is just a temporary fix because we're not going to have the window that is needed because they're actually working with members of the community to help design this.
So this is just a temporary fix to do a short order of whether it's pens or magnets or something, just so that the, um, the commission can have, you know, some swag there, but it's the city seal, um, that would be used, um, because I wouldn't want to use a logo on behalf of the commission, um, when the commission is a working with the community on actually designing, um, a logo. So this is just a,
And then that, once that logo has been designed and the commission is in agreement, then of course that will be on like their tablecloth and things of that nature. The other thing is tables and chairs. So that was just asking if people generally pay for the tables. In my experience, they don't, but you just have to let, you know, the organizer know, you know, if you want a table and then, you know, a chair or two chairs,
So I guess that's another question for Mr. DeLeva or whomever to see what the availability is for tables and chairs. Once I know the dates, then I would be able to fill out the event form, get it to the DPW. I mean, not the date, the number of vendors, get it to the DPW. That form, you get to request the appropriate number of tables, the appropriate number of chairs that you might need. So there's already a set process for that.
Francis, did you get the answer to your question about what you wanted from the commission for, I guess, for a swag for our materials? No, I didn't. I was simply also just asking if that's okay with you. Okay. It's okay with me. Do you want us to take a vote?
Not necessarily a vote, but it would be nice to get some ideas from people for because this is this is just really about the commission. And this is just a short term temporary fix. And I don't want to you know, I don't want to over order, you know. So what would you be interested in in, you know, short term swag for right now? For this, you know, for this event?
and to know that that swag would really just be the city seal with the words commission on persons with disabilities. That's fine with me. So Francis, are you asking for suggestions on what you should get? Suggestions would be welcome as well. It shouldn't be, it shouldn't be the city liaison's decision, right? So I'm giving you ideas and I'm waiting for feedback.
Oh, okay then. So, okay, if I throw out something, I would say something that is useful, right? And maybe a towel with the little pin in it, the circle in it, because you can always use a towel. You know, those little hand towels? And with our name on it, the seal, and contact information, a website or something.
So this is short term, right? So I think this is not the one that has your real logo yet. So, you know, more ideas. Do you want magnets? Do you want pens? Do you want water? You know, because I have to now go on and find some items. So that's, yeah. I think a pen and a little pad of paper would be nice so that people can write down
any information that they get during the resource fair. On the paper, I don't know if this makes, I was actually thinking, Gabby, when you mentioned the Perkins School for the Blind, I know on their business cards, it's in Braille.
And I was thinking it might be cool if we had some sort of contact, something like that contact, since we're the commission for disability, you know, persons with disabilities, if there was something that we had in Braille or something tactile like that. I mean, I don't, I don't think like a pen and a pad of paper, I think that would be a little ironic. Um, although maybe I'm speaking out of place, but I, you know, if there's like a contact card, um, that would also have Braille on it, that could be kind of cool.
Yeah, I have the capability to do that at work. Um, I don't know what day I will be back during the week. I can look at my schedule. Um, if not also the national Braille press in Boston, uh, takes customized orders. Um, and they're usually pretty quick with the turnaround. Um, so I can definitely look into that. That sounds cool. I mean, because that just really makes it so inclusive. People will,
it will open up another world to individuals, you know, having something and knowing what it actually says and feeling it. That's cool. Any other thoughts for Frances on SWAG? Frances, is that enough to work with?
I do. All right. I see flyer on the list, too. Do we do we need someone to design the flyer? Well. Hmm. If no, I can have the consign design the flyer so that we can get it out as soon as possible, it will just be just a very basic flyer.
But I can have them something that we can use for social media and for the calendar. Do we know how we're going to publicize this? I don't know if we need to brainstorm some ideas of where to post it.
The city would obviously do it on the social media, the calendar, our own individualized contact list. But I think that as commissioners, if you have outlets and networks, it should be shared that way as well. Excuse the question. Will you all be printing up flyers?
Or is this all we typically just do online, we do very few, very few runs of hard copies, unless they're going to like a specific place. All right, so that I like that idea, for instance, when when it's done. If you need feedback on it, I'm happy to provide feedback. But then we can send it to all the commissioners and we can
post it in the social media spots that we visit. So I feel like when the mayor calls with the announcements, she does it about every two weeks. I get a phone call. Definitely would be great to have that included in the phone call on April. I'm sorry. That's all part of the outreach. The road calls, the video.
I think it's the videos are now done weekly so that will all be included, or be mentioned. If you look I believe it's already on the city calendar, even though we don't have a fly. That's all part of the communications package. Awesome, Marcia.
I was wondering if there might be a small amount of money to advertise in things like a pack where you have to pay to get prominent announcements. You can get one for nothing, but it doesn't show up in any other pocket. It's inexpensive, like $25. It's not huge, or it used to be not huge. Francis, do you have a budget for advertising?
We don't really have a budget for advertising. Where would you be suggesting that we advertise? Well, that's one place that comes to mind. I would have to think about that some more. I'm not sure there are many other places where you pay, except that would be really big. And I don't think they could discover that.
I'm sorry, Marsha, I'm having difficulty hearing you. You're not coming through clearly. Is everybody able to hear Marsha clearly? No. I can't do anything else. OK, now I can hear you a little bit better. I moved it toward me. I won't think. Oh, OK. Now you're clearer. I was suggesting the patch, which you can advertise in.
more prominently. You used to be able to get a free ad, but it's amongst many other events. It's an event source. I don't know about advertising in the patch, but why don't I talk to comms and see, because I know comms usually works with the patch. So if they can, you know, if it's not something that, you know, where we can put a fly, but how about something along the lines of a press release,
does make spaces such as the Patch. I don't think the Patch is doing so many things like that anymore, specifically in Medford. I'm sorry, I'm not hearing again. I think the Patch has moved away from only having Medford news and having more regional news, just so you know. Frances, is there a budget for the Disability Commission at all?
No, there isn't a budget for the Disability Commission. There hasn't been one for the Disability Commission. Do any of the other commissions have a budget? Sorry. I acquired the two commissions that I have do not have a budget. Do you know if any of the other commissions have a budget? Some commissions have budgets, some don't. The ones that I have don't have budgets. And if we wanted to find out which commissions had budgets, how would we do that?
I think that you can see it online, you can see where the stipends are assigned to people. Okay. So I just, I just want to be clear and I just want to remind everyone. So when ARPA was issued, I requested some funds from ARPA funding for the committee, but for specific things.
So that's the money that we have. If you remember, I had expressed that I was going to request this because we felt like we were going to do a logo, we were going to have some identity. So that's what we have, Melanie. But you know that once that's done, that's not replaceable. When ARPA ends on the 31st of December next year, it's gone. And when the funds that were requested are expended,
That's it. Well, or the commission can make a vote and someone can make a motion to request more funds and people could vote on whether they want to do that. So there's always that option. But again, I think it's getting ahead of, you know, the cart getting ahead of the horse, if you will, in terms of, you know, the event for the, um, this particular fair, but I think it begs the question. I think, you know, the commission might want to think about whether you, whether the budget is needed and for what, and,
how to go about getting one if you want one. I think that's important for you all to consider. I know we only have about 20 minutes left and we have a couple other agenda items. I think that is important to have a budget. I'm glad we have some funds for April 29th. I know that our next meeting is not till, I think three days before the event. So we have our,
you know, a number of things planned between now and then. Is there anything else that is on someone's mind about the resource pride day that we need to discuss before we move on? I do have a quick question. I know that now I'm hearing this bit about the budgets and being mindful of the finances. Is something as, you know, for when we talk about SWAG, Francis,
maybe something with just a QR code leading everybody back to, you know, our website. And then that could be something that's very simple. We're not spending a lot of money and maybe it's done. You know, I don't know if it can be done in braille and just a QR code and a piece of paper in a sense. And it's very simple, but that's all I wanted to say about that. Thank you. I love that QR code. And then it'll access a lot of people.
go directly to our site. And then, you know, it's not you don't have to worry about what you should buy Francis, you know, a pen, you know, the towel or whatever. And they could be still used. All right, so we should move on to the next agenda item unless you're up.
We just lost Francis. I was going to ask if Francis had something else, but we'll move on to the next agenda item. Susie, do you want to give a short summary of your meeting with Sam at the library? Yes. I just have to shift and get my notes. I'll just quickly let you guys know that Susie and I went and met with Sam.
who you may know, Sam, the librarian at, I'm not sure what Sam's role is there. But I was there for like three minutes, and then Susie ended up meeting with Sam. And we've learned about a number of resources that the library has available. So yeah, I don't know if you can. I was absolutely bowled over. So they have homebound delivery.
and they have technology support. They have students coming in from Tufts to do technology support. They have youth services where they have quiet spaces for kids who have sensory issues. They have a sensory story hour. They have teaching computer lab for all ages. They have
Oh my goodness, they have, Homebound, they have, they want volunteers. I didn't have any idea about this. Chapters Coffee Cart, which is upstairs on the second floor, where they do a lot of the technology and story hours and maybe the art spaces, that is personed by people with disabilities.
And not only do they employ disabled, they also, that money also supports the endeavors of people with disabilities. And they have things where they have books and games and audios and movies.
that they circulate for people. I was astounded and they keep like very current. I stopped teaching officially special education about four and a half years ago. And I kept, I was trying to listen to Sam, Tom, but I kept looking at all the games, hands-on family game boxes they had.
of things that would teach kids cooperative play, sensory stuff, and so on. And I don't know about the whole library, but Sam is definitely embracing the whole disability community. And I said, well, what we're trying to do, and I know Yvette and I talked about this a lot, is we have all these fractures in Medford.
You have the senior center, you have the library, you have the med, uh, med rec, you have all these different places are doing triangle that are doing things. Oh, here's Yvette was the, um, West Medford, uh, senior center doing different things for seniors and for, uh, disabled, but we've got to get it all together. And I think Yvette and I really talked about that and Sam at the library,
totally agreed with me that we've got to pull it all together. And I'm hoping in this next year between our board and between different things that will happen. That's my vision of it all. I think it's Yvette's. Yes, Yvette? It's ours. It's a team. Yes. Anyway, the library made me really feel excited by it.
And I'll just thank you for that summary. I'll just add there are some specific dates. On April 8th, from 9 to 12 at the library, they have a high school student who will be there answering questions in their tech lab. And then on the same day,
I think they have 68 tough students who are going to- I had that written down. You got it. Great. All right. That's till two o'clock to also field tech questions. So it would probably be good to add to that. It's before our pair, but my impression was from Sam that this may be a recurring thing that's happening there. Melody- It's wonderful. Yeah. Melody, did you want to add something?
Yeah, I want to add, I think that that is a fantastic idea and something that I've been dreaming about for Medford for a long time. So I love hearing you say this, Suzanne, and I love hearing that, you know, on board as well. I think it's super important to grab, to get these disparate groups together. And I think one of the themes of the disability pride, you know, could and maybe should be one of the logos or something, slogans could be that, you know, as we hear, as Judy has said, Judy Heumann, as others, you know, say all the time,
is that disability is natural. We are ultimately all disabled at some point, whether it's by old age, whether it is by pregnancy, accident, birth, you know, any number of things, we all experience disability at some point. And so I think, you know, helping people understand that we're a community and that we're an inclusive community and that ultimately
everyone will be part of our community, whether they realize it or not. And so I think that's really great to really create all these groups coming together and helping them understand that we're all part of it together. Marsha, I see you shaking your head and I'd love to see it. This feels good to you, Marsha? Wonderful. Good. I really love that idea. Good.
I wanted to add one more thought that I loved in our last brochure, which if it's still proof answers, I'm not sure. But it was a statement that came out saying Medford supports individuals of all ability. And that was right under whatever design thing we had.
It was prominent in the flyer that we made. And I still like it. So I don't know. That's something that other people like and want to keep. But I do. That's it. Thank you. I think that summarizes it well. I think the key is getting this information out to people.
Um, uh, Gabby, I don't know if you're able to, to talk, but I know that, um, when it makes you Linda, you might be aware, right? We put together this database of emails, um, that we've collected over the past year or so. Um, is there a way that we can send out this information to the folks on that, on that list? Yes. Can you hear me? Yeah, we can hear you, Gabby. Go ahead. Sorry. No, go ahead.
Oh, I think you're talking about the MailChimp account. And I think that's still active. So I'd have to just double check. I don't see why it wouldn't be active. So we could send an email out to that effect if someone wants to write up what we want or just compile information. I'm happy to start a Google Doc if people want to throw ideas in there or if someone already has an idea.
then what we want to say, then, you know, feel free to go nuts and create a Google Doc, and then I can put it into the MailChimp and send it out. Yeah, I've just been thinking with the, obviously we want to get the information out about the resource fair to that list, but also these other events that are going, other events at the library that are going on, it'd probably be good to write them all up.
I can, Sam summarized the meeting with Susie in an email, so we can easily, you know, kind of copy and paste that information. So I don't know, Linda, you said you're up for starting the Google Doc? If you could do that, I can just paste the stuff on there. Tom, go for it. I'm away right now, so go for it. That'd be great. Did somebody raise their hand?
No? All right. All right, so we should move on to the next item. We have about 10 minutes left. Marcia, did you want to share what your piece about Judy? Well, it's actually not quite about Judy. I was thought, since I think I'm the only person who lived through the 60s in this. It was?
I'm the only person who was in college starting in 1959, when the Civil Rights Movement was very active. And I thought maybe just sharing a little bit of some of the strategies that were used then might, and I'm sure that Judy must have adapted, might pertain to some of the things we might need today.
And I'm sure you all know that Martin Luther King was the leader of the Civil Rights Movement, and he was a very vocally adept and kind of uniting force. And I thought that was one instrumental thing. And of course, there were a lot of marches, many marches, a lot of the time.
But as I've been thinking about it, and I'm sure that Judy did so much more than that, there is much more required to accomplish a goal like that. And one of the things that happened, first of all, was this was all, or the main part of it was peaceful. There were fringe groups that were not peaceful, but mostly it was, and there were,
There was a lot of information put out, like our fair. There was a lot of politics being played at that time. So the people, leaders of the movement, met with people high up in our federal government.
And I believe that a lot of participants went to Washington to meet with their representatives and senators. So there was also a lot of political pressure. So all these things were happening at the same time.
I am sure that Judy knew some of these strategies because she was a child of the time. And that's really what I wanted to say. I think it's a lesson for us, her life and some of the civil rights issues that persisted. And I think that's exactly what you see in Crip Camp.
You know, that's exactly what you see in Crip Camp. Thank you for sharing that, Marsha, because it's so true and it's so motivating. And when you really see the, you know, disability rights and civil rights, I think it puts everything in a whole different perspective. So thank you so much for sharing that. You're welcome. I like the time. And I wish I had it in me to be in a march. I keep thinking of marching in a wheelchair, but then I need someone to push me. So it goes on and on.
I'll push you any day, Marsha. Which March do you prefer? We have to figure that one out. Thank you, Marsha. If anybody else wanted to share anything, I know our next item is correspondence and announcements. I have a couple of items, but before we move to that, I don't know if anybody else wanted to share something about Judy. All right.
About Judy Heumann? Yeah. Go ahead, Melanie. I sent out a video to the commission that, I can't remember his name, Dan Habib's son. Samuel. Yes, the interview that he did with Judy. Judy, yeah. Oh, I did an interview with Judy and I kept meaning to get it to her and I felt terribly that I never did get it to her. I did an interview with Judy and my mentor, Tom Hare.
at Harvard who was an inclusion expert. And they were old friends. They used to work together at OSEP, you know, back in the day when they were both younger working to reauthorize IDEA. So they tell all kinds of stories about that and just, you know, great friends and great woman and, you know, a lot of fun to be around and, you know, beautiful smile and you didn't want to be on her bad side because you would know. And, you know, she was supposed to be
our keynote at the Federation for Children with Special Needs conference last week. And we got a call, she was gonna be on on Friday as part of like a fireside chat kind of thing. And we got a call on Thursday that she wasn't able to come and I think she died Friday morning. So it was just devastating to so many. And Judy helped so many people in the disability community, young people in particular, who just looked up to her so much as well.
When you see Crip Camp, if you haven't already seen it, you know, Judy is young and beautiful and a fighter and amazing in that film. But, you know, even at, you know, 75 or whatever it was when she passed, she was as beautiful and vibrant and all of those things up until the day she left us. So I hope people really enjoy her spirit. Thank you.
Anybody have any correspondence or announcements that they want to share? So I don't have anything. Oh, go ahead, Gabby. Sorry. No, I was just going to say, I don't know, would this be an OK time to perhaps lay on the table my earlier motion with that? Yes. Go for it. You want to make a motion to pick up from the table, Gabby?
pick up from the table, okay. Still learning the terminology, but okay. So is it a motion to, do you make a motion for that or do I just? Yeah, you have to make a motion and then you have a second if they approve, and then you have a vote. So make a motion to, you know, take that off the table, take from the table the motion that you had, and then you wanna state what the motion was and then if somebody seconds it. Okay, I would like to,
Sorry, I have to move my car. Sorry, I would like to, what was the word you used? Sorry, not lay, put place on the table. Like you're picking it up from the table. Take from the table, my earlier motion to invite the ADA committee to our next meeting to facilitate more community planning. So first you have to make the motion to take it from the table. So you want to split the motion, sorry.
So Gabby, are you making a motion to take your initial motion from the table? Yes, I am making a motion to take it from the table. I second your motion, Gabby. All in favor? Thank you, Linda. Anyone opposed? Anyone abstaining? All right, motion carries. Now your next motion, Gabby.
I would like to make a motion to invite the ADA committee to our next meeting. The Medford Public Schools ADA committee? Yes. Anyone want to second that? Yes, I will second. All in favor? Anyone opposed? Great, motion carries.
Thank you, Gabby. That's great. So now will someone from one of the commissioners send an email or maybe, you know, Francis certainly knows the committee, she's on it. So maybe through work with Francis to send an email invitation to the committee. Yes, I can do that. Thank you. You're a great leader tonight. Yeah, we thank you for bringing that up. I almost forgot that part.
Um, so I'll just add in we have what one, two minutes. I just a quick update from representative Sean Garber Lee, I chatted with him about the West Medford commuter rail station, which has been a kind of an ongoing issue that was trying to get funding to make it accessible. We put on the kind of was up took a pause last year, because of the
New governor was going to be coming on board. And so Democrats were holding off on making funding decisions. And so trying to re-engage, he has sent letters to the new governor and lieutenant governor and would like us to do the same. So I am also talking to the mayor and the city council about sending their letters.
Again, so I will, I know Frances isn't on, but I'll engage with her about that. Actually, I guess we should probably make a motion to re-send or re-formulate our letters in support of finding funding to make the commuter rail station accessible. Marcia. I make that motion with the caveat that we get ready tomorrow. Can I ask a question?
If you don't mind, just also if, or a statement, I guess, I don't know, but I would also really encourage people individually to contact Representative Garbally or send him an email and let him know that you support this. And also, you know, Senator Jalen or Representative Barber or Donato, whoever is your representative,
to let them know that you support the West Medford MBTA, you know, becoming accessible. And I don't know, Tom, if you guys offer language for letters for people to reach out to their legislators, but folks can also ask, you know, friends and family to do the same and reach out to their legislators. The more emails or phone calls they get, the more it is relevant to them because they really do equate it with votes.
you know, most people don't even send a letter or a few people do, but they're always the same people. And so when they see, you know, more than one coming in, and you know, it's, it's great that Tom is talking to Representative Garbley, I think that's hugely important. And like we say in the Special Ed Parent Advisory Council, when I was working on it, you know, you know, one parent is a pain in the neck, you know, three parents is a email, six parents is a phone call, and 10 parents are a policy change.
Right. And so really thinking about the group effect and being able to reach out both collectively and individually, because in addition to being commissioners, you are also individual residents and constituents. So you're able to do that too. Thanks. Yeah, I agree. And I can, I shared it before with the commission. So I will do that again. And I will also reach out to,
Brie brothers, I believe, who originally brought this up on a Facebook group so I can read Facebook chat so I can re-engage with that. So Marsha had made a motion. Anybody want to second the motion to contact the council and the mayors to send letters? Sure. All right. All in favor? I'm going to leave. I'm going to go.
anyone hold on anyone opposed great motion passes all right we are over time and so we're going to adjourn the meeting thank you everyone motion to adjourn anybody motion to adjourn that's motion to adjourn in a second all in favor good night good night