Hello, we are very pleased to have this opportunity to introduce you to your new pay-by-plate parking kiosk.
The new pay-by-plate kiosk is solar powered, accepts many forms of payment, and is very easy to use.
Now I'd like to demonstrate just how easy it is to make a parking payment.
With this type of parking system, it's important to remember your license number.
For me, it's easy to use my smartphone and take a picture of my license plate, then I always have it on hand.
To begin your parking transaction, hit the start button on the keypad to wake up the display screen.
Next, you are prompted to enter your license plate number.
Once you're finished entering your plate number, push the green key on the keypad to confirm.
Now you are asked to insert your payment.
The kiosks take credit and debit cards as well as coins.
The appointed slots are labeled to help specify where to pay.
To pay with coins, just insert the coins, one at a time, into the coin slot.
The display screen will show you the dollar amount you have inserted and the time your parking will expire.
Press the red button if you need to start over and your coins will be returned to you in the coin bowl area.
For credit cards, just insert the card face up with the card logo facing to the left.
Then remove the card.
Select the amount of time you wish to purchase by pressing the blue buttons shown on the keypad.
Press the red cancel button if you need to start over.
When you have selected the amount of time you wish to purchase, press the green button and your receipt will print out.
Take your receipt for your own records.
There is no need to display it in your vehicle.
Your license plate information is communicated to parking enforcement officers wirelessly.
Extremely easy to operate, your new pay-by-plate parking kiosk will make everyone's parking experience so much more convenient.
Thank you for taking the time to watch this brief instructional video and happy parking.