All right, it's 6.01.
Technically, we have quorum, so we can go ahead and get started.
I think Hasita was going to join.
I don't know about Kristen.
But we can go ahead and get started.
I'm going to record.
And actually, before I hit record, folks that are at home, is there any sort of background noise?
We have the windows open right now.
Are you guys hearing any sort of traffic noise that's loud?
Fantastic.
Good.
I just wanted to make sure.
Am I supposed to have any?
No, if you want, there's a copy of it in Agenda here if you want to just follow along.
Yeah.
But yeah, if you want to doodle, there you go.
All right.
Now I'm going to record.
Recording in progress.
Okay.
This is the Medford Historic District Commission meeting by hybrid means on August 14th, 2025 at 6 PM.
We are in room 201 at City Hall, as well as meeting via video conference to Zoom.
So thank you, everybody, for making it tonight.
Joe, do you want to?
Sure.
How are you doing?
How are you doing, everybody?
So we're going to do three things out of the agenda here.
We're going to do the meeting minutes hopefully next month.
So we're going to discuss.
a meeting time that we can all get together and walk the South Street District area and figure out where we're going to put the signage.
Then we're going to have a discussion of holding a joint meeting with the Historical Commission, which is the other commission in Medford, to discuss an overall plan for the city about historical preservation of the properties of Medford.
And then
A couple weeks ago in the email we got the Senate bill.
The housing production bill.
Yeah, housing production bill number 993.
So this hasn't been voted on yet.
So we have an opportunity to weigh in on it and voice our opinions of what.
What's that again?
What bill is it?
993.
For what?
It's regarding
Uh, housing and receiving, uh, historical districts authority in regards to changing the zoning.
Yeah, some jurisdictional changes that that bill were to pass.
So.
All right, so let's start with the, uh, with the South Street site visit and signage plan update.
Yes.
Um, so, uh, South Street is our latest and greatest district is currently lacking signage.
So, um, also, it'd be really great for this commission where we're a newer commission.
Um, I know some of us have Joe has been here.
Um, and as well as Charlotte throughout the duration, but it would be good to get out there and walk the site.
It's a, it's a pretty walkable street.
Everybody knows South Street.
So those who are able to join us, I think it would be good for us to walk the site and to discuss permanent signage locations.
So get our hands on the district, if you will, put our eyes on it and familiarize ourselves with it as well as to identify those signage locations.
We can pick some dates.
I can round robin it after this meeting, or we can discuss it now.
But it would be good to put something on the calendar, since it would be a public event.
We would have to advertise it.
So it's not something we can just all text each other and say, hey, what are you doing Saturday night?
We would have to properly advertise it.
So a lot of people are welcome.
Is that it?
Yeah, the public would be welcome as well.
I'm not sure how much participation we'd have from the public.
I'm sure we'll have some neighbors comment.
It would be nice if they did.
Yeah, it would be nice if they did.
But, you know, the intention of this would be for us to all familiarize ourselves with the district itself and, you know, to pound the pavement at it.
But it would be public.
People would be welcome.
Bring your friends.
So I'm open to any weeknight.
It would be difficult for me on a weekend.
And I would, so we would have to be next month.
So we're still going to, you know, sunset would still be, you know, before seven, you know?
So, I mean, what, what night would work out for everybody like prior to, you know, like, let's say six o'clock so that that way, you know, when seven, when it starts getting dark, we'd already be done at that point.
What, what time around, what day on six o'clock would be good for you guys like next, um, next month?
I'd have to check my calendar, but probably
Any time.
Is there like a day of the week that might work best?
No, I'm both retired, so I'm doing nothing, unfortunately.
So I live on South Street.
Oh, yeah, perfect.
That's right.
So it's not a long walk.
You don't have to walk far to get there.
No, I don't.
I'm thinking maybe Tuesday will work.
Tuesday's the best for you, Charlotte?
OK.
What about you, James?
Tuesday's work.
I'm pretty much open to any night, though.
Yeah, I'd say I agree with Tuesday as well.
I have meetings in Cambridge, and I tend to work from home in the morning.
And I could always just extend that into the afternoon and be in Medford.
I would not be available to do that until the week of the 15th in September.
OK.
Because I'll be out of town.
early in September, but after that, but don't let that stop you.
But that's when I would be around after the 15th and after.
Okay.
So why don't we say like the 16th and we could send, if it'd be okay, could we send everyone an email and then everyone can check and then get back within the next couple of days to confirm and then we'll just consider that a hot date and then post it for the community to know?
You can meet at my house if that's okay.
Yeah, great.
I don't mind.
That's awesome.
Sure.
I haven't thought we can meet on, you know.
Yeah, that's a great idea.
Like a central meeting spot.
That's great.
Yeah.
okay so let's tentatively plan for tuesday september 6th at 16th i'm sorry 16th at 6 p.m 6 30. all right let's do six okay that works for me that works september 16th which is a tuesday right tuesday september 16th at 6 p.m and like like you said i'll circulate that and if it doesn't work for the majority we can get from there but i
I think it should be fine.
Yeah.
We're 15th or 16th.
16th of Tuesday, September 16th.
Yeah.
Great.
So, yeah, I'll, I'll round robin that with everybody and email, make sure we're good.
And then I was just wrapped with this time again, 6 and 6 PM.
Oh, it should only take us maybe.
I think an hour maximum here, you know, we're all chatting Kathy's.
I'm joking.
We can have some nice discussions, but plan it for an hour or so.
Perfect.
Awesome.
Yay.
And then I can.
I was starting in September.
Is that the question?
Is that the proposal?
Or August?
September.
Yeah.
Tuesday the 16th.
And that gives us enough time to get to post it so that we meet our criteria.
Perfect.
Yeah.
Technically, we only need 48 hours.
Oh, yeah.
That's good.
So what are the signs going to say?
That's something we can certainly kind of flesh out on site.
I can bring some I'll bring photos of our existing signage and our other districts that are in need of updating their old and delaminating and just kind of falling apart.
So I'll bring some examples of what we currently have.
Maybe I can put together a handout of, you know, what other cities do for their historic district signage.
You know, Joe and I were kind of sidebarring earlier, but I love the idea of making it, not having it be just like a blank sale sign.
It should be historic in its appearance as well.
So I'll bring some examples and we can kind of all vote or something like that and then flush it out later.
I think the location is important for us to get with, because that way, that'll dictate how many signs we're going to order.
And that way, I can get appropriate pricing.
The other districts just have one sign per district on the main thoroughfare that attracts the district, from what I could see.
Norm Simmons has three.
Do they?
OK.
They've got one right past the Winter Street Circle.
One is turned down.
I don't remember the name of that street, but there's there.
I think there's at least two.
I think there are three from our Simmons, but he'll say it's just one.
Yeah, that's a tough one to find.
Oh, it is.
It's like in somebody's yard.
Yeah.
So, you know, maybe we look at the other districts to increase the number of science there as well.
You had said, I believe, that they were interested in shipbuilder's house.
Am I wrong in remembering that?
I'm not sure.
Because my house was built by a shipbuilder.
And I have a house in the back to the late 1700s that is still habitable.
I have people renting it.
that is where the shipbuilding crew lived.
Oh, nice.
You go in, the ceilings are really, really low.
Yeah.
And they all have beams.
And it's officially rentable.
I have the city come and look at it.
Yeah.
So even though, you know, a six-foot-two guy would have to go.
Would have a hard time.
But it's interesting.
Yeah.
That is very cool.
Maybe down the road, we can look at more
I forgot the name of the signage where, you know, you can put up a placard saying, like, oh, here lived Captain Isaac Paul, and he was the first one that followed your, you know, rain on his midnight ride.
But maybe, like, that's something we can look at for more of our interesting homes in these districts.
Maybe we can look at signage, additional signage specifically to that property down the road.
I love the little story that you just shared there.
What is that little house across from Brigham's on Governor's Ave?
They have a whole folder on the history of my house.
Yeah.
It's interesting.
The historical society there.
That's something we can certainly look at as we get down the road.
I think there's also, it's not on the agenda, but the city is also looking at wayfinding signage.
Wayfinding is like those directional signs if you're in the middle of the city saying like, oh, a five-minute walk this way to go to City Hall or a 10-minute walk that way to get to the Condon show.
So the city is right now looking at introducing a permanent wayfinding signage.
So maybe we can dovetail some of this.
That would help with the budget on that too, wouldn't it?
It would.
Very good.
We get creative here.
Fantastic.
I love it.
I can't guarantee it, but it's an opportunity.
Perfect.
Awesome, okay.
Oh, so windy.
I think a storm is about to come through, so.
I'm dying for those heavens to open up and rain.
My tomatoes hate me right now.
Okay, great.
Do we have to vote on anything of that or no?
No, because it's not,
You know, any sort of decision written a decision, we're just going to do it.
All right.
Perfect.
So we can move on to the 2nd item here.
So the discussion of holding a joint public meeting with the historical commission.
So.
You've already spoken with them and they're, they're amendable to this and yeah, just as a little background.
My day job is CPA grant manager for the city.
CPA also focuses on historic preservation citywide.
So this is an idea that really kind of came from me.
I'm creating more work for myself.
Oh, sure.
Sorry, we heard something come from your microphone.
Anyway, so other cities have put together what they call a citywide historic preservation plan.
Um, there's always these various commissions and other cities and towns that are doing good historic efforts, but sometimes they work in silos and it's not cohesive about how we can best set up the city to protect our historical assets and our properties in the city.
Um, the preservation plan would help.
kind of bring all these various efforts and missions together to really put it into an actionable plan on how we can best preserve these buildings.
You may have been aware that the city was looking at doing some residential rezoning updates.
So this really kind of bubbled out of that conversation because frankly, some of the zoning, as it was proposed, you know, certainly there are,
opportunities for revisions, but as it was proposed, would really incentivize these historic homes being taken down to put up a more denser, newer housing building.
Which is not great, right?
We're all here to help protect these buildings because once they're gone, you can't get them back on.
Yeah.
So long story short, that's just a backstory to explain why we would be looking at a preservation plan here for Medford.
We're doing good stuff here on the district, but
You know, it's 112 properties at this point that we're protecting.
Meanwhile, there's thousands of other vulnerable historic homes right now that have no protections under the district or any other, you know, national registry or whatnot.
So all that to say, the historical commission is very much on board with helping with this.
So they were thinking we should have a joint meeting just to talk about it.
As the two boards for city hall that are tasked with historic stuff, you know, um, so the, the.
And cut me off if you have any questions as I'm going here, but the idea of this joint meeting, which is to be able to talk about it, um, officially as a, Hey, this is what we're doing right now.
We're, we're discussing the idea of holding that joint meeting.
Um, it's something that we all have to agree on.
But that's the question.
Yes, sure.
A way historical district commission or just a historical commission.
We are the historic district commission.
Okay.
Then there is a separate entity called the historical commission.
They're the ones that look at demo delays and.
Determining the property is significant, so they're kind of.
I don't wanna call them the lead organization for historical, but they tend to- Well, it's different.
Their property's not in the district.
Ours are in an established district.
They're determining historical significance of a home 75 years old, older.
Correct.
How far does the South Street district extend?
Is it to any houses off of that?
No, it is a little bit, I hate using the term gerrymander, because it's very prevalent in the news today.
I'm showing her a copy of the historic district for South Street here.
But it's not every property on South Street.
And you can see how it went up.
It's nothing behind South Street either.
It's nothing behind South Street.
Yeah, because one of my neighbors who lives behind me sent me an email about what they want to do on Manning Street.
They wanted to tear down a house.
And do you know anything about that?
I've heard it because I work in the planning department.
So we've been talking about that one.
I thought a little bit.
I thought it had to go in front of the commission if it's 1910 or younger.
Yeah, 75 years or older at this point.
So that year just rolls with it because it's 75 years.
Yeah.
But that is the historical commission.
So they would review it.
Yeah, I think it's on hold, but- I think so too.
I don't know.
Yeah.
Because anytime a property that's 75 years or older wants to do some sort of exterior work to it, changing a roof line, extending a dormer, adding an addition, the historical commission makes a determination if that property is significant to Medford or significant to the area.
If they do deem it significant,
then they can institute what they call an 18-month demo delay.
That's what's happening.
Right.
If they want to demolish it and build something else.
And some of these developers sitting on something for 18 months, they can do that.
They can float that cash.
So I think that's where that particular property is at right now.
But so back to the joint meeting, is this something that this group would be amenable to?
The preservation plan itself wouldn't be on the backs of everybody here, or even on my back, or the historical commissions.
We would bring in a consultant.
Other cities and towns have done that.
They've essentially farmed the management of this project out to a consultant, so it actually gets done, which is nice.
But so no fears of like Charlotte, you got to write 15 pages of preservation, you know, mission statement.
That's not going to happen.
But you know, our input would be needed.
So.
So can we get, so are people amenable to having a joint meeting with the, with the historical historical commission?
Okay.
So let's, if someone could initiate a vote on that.
Is there a motion to approve?
Can I make that motion?
Am I allowed to?
From the chair, no, unfortunately.
So again, it's a motion on the table to engage in a joint public meeting with the purpose of hosting a public discussion about a preservation plan.
So the motion to approve?
Can I approve?
Yeah.
We've got a first motion from Anne Marie.
Do we have a second?
Second.
Want to do a roll call?
Okay, so let's do a roll call vote on that.
James?
Yes.
Aye.
Okay.
Charlotte?
Yes.
Annemarie?
Yeah.
Okay.
And I vote yes too, so it should be all set.
Excellent.
Thank you very much.
I think the dates on this one will be, I'll have to work with the historical commission, but I think what we'd do is just invite them to our next meeting in September.
I believe this is September 11th meeting.
Um, so I don't think we have to do anything additional.
I have so connect with them, but that's the plan is to invite them to our next meeting.
Okay.
So it's great.
We'll give you an email.
I would know when, when that's going to be, if that's accepted.
Perfect.
That's great.
So then, uh, last item here is the review of S nine, nine, three, the, uh, the housing, uh, production bill.
Um,
It was sent out, so it looks like the thing that most affects us is section six, which if you printed it off is one, two, it's on the third page.
Would it be helpful for me to bring up the language on the screen?
Yeah, that would be awesome.
Yeah, I can do that.
Thank you for your patience, folks.
I'm basically using a 70-inch monitor as my second screen, so sometimes it gets a little funky.
Right, so everybody should be seeing our from mass.gov's website here.
This is actually, so the, I don't know, do you want me to explain this?
Okay.
You do it so well.
So S993, it is a proposed housing production bill, which essentially, there's a lot of housing production bills being considered right now at the Capitol.
This one in particular isn't any more aggressive or anything
it wouldn't produce more housing.
The language in this one isn't very different from other housing bills that are proposed.
However, this one does specifically have language in here that would effectively strip the historic district commission for being able to stop a demolition if it results in the project, the construction project results in one or more net new housing units.
So what that means is, for instance, if somebody has a beautiful carriage house in their backyard and they want to knock it down and then build a bigger ADU, an accessory dwelling unit or housing unit, if this bill were to pass, we wouldn't be able to stop, prevent that carriage house from coming down.
So, you know, it's, it's, does it affect a lot of properties here in Medford?
No.
but it would, you know, we only have, I don't know off the top of my head, but like a dozen carriage houses in particular left here in Medford.
And that was, you know, that's something that's, that we love seeing, you know, that's, that's a historical architectural feature that is very unique to, to what we still have left here in Medford.
So I don't think this is, it's not going to totally strip all of our jurisdiction.
You know, it's just in that niche, um,
project as we're looking at them, this would tear off the backside of a house or again, take down a carriage house in order to build new housing.
So.
I think the concern would be that it, I think somewhere in that language, it says like substantially like slowing it down.
So like we wouldn't be, I don't think anyone wanted to stop the addition, the making of an AU, but like,
it should be done, you know, through the process of, you know, accepting a project, right, you know, and keeping it historically.
So, I guess, is, is this some like, so, you know, we have two different historic commissions, you know, so, you know, I think that my opinion would be that we would write a letter ourselves and then have the other historic
you know, the other historic district could do an independent letter themselves.
So two different letters would go out.
So I think, you know, are people amenable to us drafting a letter and sending it to the legislators that would be voting on this?
You know, voicing our concern is that, would people be amenable to that?
Yes.
Okay.
Yeah, I haven't.
Okay, yeah, we would have you guys review it before it gets sent off.
So, you know, you wouldn't be co signing on something blindly.
You would be able to review it.
Okay, but we need to vote on this and we can just start drafting a letter and then.
Yeah, yeah, there wasn't really an action.
This is more just a review, but we'll draft the letter.
I think whenever our next meeting, we bring that letter to the next meeting, then we can perfect.
So some of the things that I thought to include in the letter would be one that so the we'll have to get the exact date, but the historic districts was started in in 1960.
And I think that it should be said that.
The majority like that's a 1960 obviously is, you know, quite quite a few years ago in the houses.
probably the majority of the houses have changed ownership in that time period.
And people bought these homes, you know, knowing that they're in a community that's protected.
And there's got to be a better way to say this, you know, like, yeah, you know, we'll have to work on the wording, but like, people bought into this, you know, knowing it would be knowing it'd be a preserved right.
And then it's all getting swiped with like, really,
you know, quick, like, you know, so that would be one thing that the line would... Well, if they have known that, I have a super question.
How would they have known they're buying something, you know?
Well, that would have to be disclosed, so when you're buying... Buy the real tech?
Yeah, that would be something to be disclosed.
Oh, okay.
All right.
If I were to sell it, well, it would be the seller's obligation to disclose that to the real estate broker, who would then disclose that to the purchaser.
So they would know.
In the second, the...
One other thing that we should include in that letter is that we recently added a district.
That's a good percentage of the homes.
And that was well supported by the people in the South Street District.
So then once again, that's just getting swiped away quickly in a couple sentences.
I think that those two things should be somehow wordsmithed into this letter.
So I thought it might be nice if we went around and anyone else had some ideas of what to add to the letter.
And then if anyone wants to take on writing the letter, that's fine.
I have no problem passing that off to someone.
And if not, I'll write the letter.
And you, Teresa, will make sense of that.
of my thoughts and put it in, you know, put it into something that someone will read and not put in the circular file.
And I will also share, uh, boards and commissions often will write letters of support or letters of concern for various bills.
So this isn't a weird thing.
You know, this is something that is pretty standard, um, as we come across, you know,
I don't want to say problematic bills, but bills that could end up being problematic, because I think the intention of this bill is all great.
Housing is needed.
We need to do something about increasing our housing stock, certainly.
But does it need to be at the expense of our historical assets?
We might want to state in this letter, too, that we just met a month or two ago, and we're already working on... There's already an ADU going into
the Marm Simmons community into a carriage.
I was like, perfectly right.
What an awesome use of that space, you know, like, without changing the facade of the building.
Yeah, there's no reason.
There's no reason to like, there's no reason to demolish and make a smooth makeup.
Makeup.
There's no reason to change the way it's currently set up.
Right.
Yeah.
The other thing is, is that taking these
taking these assets that we have, not just individual houses, but also the fabric of part of the city that's been preserved, that has lasted as long as it has, and then to knock down a carriage house, it's like, what did you actually gain by that?
I mean, you maybe gained one unit, maybe two units.
It's not, it's, I mean, no, it is an urban renewal where you're blowing out whole sections of the city or something, but it's like, is it really worth
damaging that fabric and damaging those buildings for so little.
I'd almost say it's like, well, OK, if you took this house down but got 30 units out of it, OK, maybe, but you'd still have to argue with me.
But not if it means, OK, you're just going to go around and just start blowing out what makes these areas what they are and worth protecting.
I don't like the wording of that thing at all.
That's kind of stupid.
And the concern that I had as well on this is it's not clear.
So where is, so what the 1900 date of this, so when you read through it.
constructed after January 1, 1990.
So is that the structure on the property or is that the overall?
Because these houses, they may have been constructed one-time additions.
Are we just going to take someone's word, all of that?
garage was built after this period.
1901.
All of a sudden, everything's built in 1901.
Because the records don't go back for all these different things.
And that's going to really cause an issue with that.
And it really should be protected because it's in a district.
We have a better, I think ours is a better standing than even the other commission because ours is already protected as a district.
Is that something we could add into the letter to like, it's going to be difficult to age that structure in the district.
And burdensome.
Yeah, and very costly.
Because, to your point, the structure could have gone up in 1860, but the carriage house
When was that?
When were they going to say, oh, we're going to rip the back off?
You know, and it's, you know, these have, you know, you've got a beautiful old house and they put an addition to the back that was like part of the kitchen or something, you know, like all of a sudden that's going to get ripped off.
And then, yeah, that was built in the, you know, I mean, some of them might be obvious when it was built, but I mean, that's going to be really burdensome to figure out when that was done.
And, and, you know, uh,
As we're having this conversation, a lot of the time with the Historic Gold Commission will do as they're reviewing, as I mentioned earlier, the demo delays, is they hire a consultant to do like a form B, it's called.
It's basically a historical report of that property, like how it came to be, like the architectural design.
It's pretty comprehensive.
There's probably one for your house, Ann Marie, out there.
That costs money and that takes time too.
So like, is it now that as every one of these projects comes forth, we have to go and order a Form B so that we can?
ascertain when the structure was built.
And then what was the point of having the money?
And then what was the point of having the district?
The people have already they've already bought into the homes over all these years since the 1960s that they purchased these homes.
And these people that have signed on to this and all excited about it and very happy at the at the voting that happened last year.
You know, like it's.
Yeah.
Like I said, the intention of the bill is great.
I just some some word choices in there.
have some pretty big consequences here.
And again, we're not talking about it affecting a lot of properties here in Medford, but, you know- It potentially could, because the wording is not well written in this, because it's the structure.
So is it the, so at the very least, they're going to have to talk about when the structure, you know, is it a structure added to a structure?
Which part of it, like if 90% of the home was built in, you know,
pre-1900, what's the percentage?
This isn't well thought out or well written.
I think that a good letter like this actually would have the districts then separated out and protected from this.
Because it's going to be way too confusing and hard to do.
Right.
Any additional thoughts that we'd want to have captured in the letter?
Or do we think we encompassed everything?
Does anybody have objections to sending a letter?
No, I think it needs to be done.
I'm sorry, go ahead, James.
I was going to say, I think what we've talked about is a good number of things to at least get the draft started.
Perfect.
And then as we read through it, we can say, OK, let's tweak this or let's add something.
Because I'm sure once we have something in front of us,
to look at, that can be massaged and added to.
Right.
Perfect.
Does anyone want to take this on?
Do you mind if Teresa and I work on it?
Is that OK?
What's everyone's thought on that?
Does anybody have a burning desire to write this letter?
I think you probably have a good handle on what this is about, and I'd like to see it come from you.
And if we have any questions, we certainly can get back to you.
You're there for us.
Yeah.
Okay.
That works.
So it's good.
I'll take that.
I'll take a first stab at it.
Okay.
I'll kick it over to you.
Great.
Do we need to vote on this?
We're just starting with something.
So yeah, I'll just vote at the time of the letter.
So this is just a discussion.
Yeah.
All right.
Great.
Well, I think that's, um,
Yeah, the minutes were the only other thing, and I apologize.
I will get those for next time.
All right.
Well, that's it for this meeting.
If we want to get a motion to end it, then someone second it, we can wrap it up.
Anybody want a motion to adjourn?
Motion to adjourn.
Do we have a second?
All right.
Let's take a vote.
Adjourned.
Emery?
James?
Yes.
Charlotte?
Yeah.
Yes.
And I vote yes too.
So we're wrapping it up.
We'll see you guys next month.
Awesome.
Thank you all so much.
Thank you.
Take care.
Bye.
Thank you so much.