[SPEAKER_07]: I'm Yutori Arashi, and welcome to the Mustang Report Talent Show.
[SPEAKER_07]: First off, we have Jocelyn McCarthy, who's a juggler.
[SPEAKER_07]: Next, we have Amber Harbison, a world-renowned gymnast.
[SPEAKER_07]: And now we have Katrina Arashi, a comedian.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you, thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why did the sesame seed not leave the gambling casino?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it was on a roll.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why did the chicken cross the road?
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: I forget.
[SPEAKER_07]: Tune in to the 17th Mustang Report to see if the Medford High School Talent Show will be better than ours.
[SPEAKER_07]: It will be.
Remember the girls hockey team since 7th grade.
With a huge presence on the blue line.
So let's stand as we introduce you.
Big heart, big smile.
Number 15, Ashley Wallace.
At center, number 20, Amy Schreier.
At right wing, number 18, Christina Scholl.
Up against number 15, Ashley Wallace.
At left wing, number 10, Brianna Scholl.
Up against number 3, Julia Schreier.
[SPEAKER_05]: My unique talent is twisting balloon animals.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Mustang Report question of the week is, what is my special talent?
[SPEAKER_02]: When the glory comes, it will be ours.
[SPEAKER_02]: It will be ours.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, one day when the war is won, we will be sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: We will be sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, glory.
[SPEAKER_02]: Glory.
Glory.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, glory.
[SPEAKER_06]: Hands to the heavens, no man, no weapon.
[SPEAKER_06]: Formed against, yes, glorious destiny.
[SPEAKER_06]: Everyday women and men become legends.
[SPEAKER_06]: Sins that go against our skin become blessings.
[SPEAKER_06]: The movement is a rhythm to us.
[SPEAKER_06]: Freedom is like religion to us.
[SPEAKER_06]: Justice is juxtapositioning us.
[SPEAKER_06]: Justice for all just ain't specific enough.
[SPEAKER_06]: One son died, his spirit is revisiting us.
[SPEAKER_06]: True and living, living in us.
[SPEAKER_06]: Resistance is us.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's why Rosa sat on the bus.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's why we walked through Ferguson with our hands up.
[SPEAKER_06]: When it go down, we woman and man up.
[SPEAKER_06]: They say stay down, and we stand up.
[SPEAKER_06]: Shots, we on the ground.
[SPEAKER_06]: The camera panned up.
[SPEAKER_06]: King pointed to the mountaintop, and we ran up.
[SPEAKER_06]: One day.
[SPEAKER_02]: One day when the glory comes, it will be ours, it will be ours.
[SPEAKER_02]: One day when the war is won, we will be sure, we will be sure.
[SPEAKER_06]: Selma is now for every man, woman, and child.
[SPEAKER_06]: Even Jesus got his crown in front of a crowd.
[SPEAKER_06]: They marched with the torch, we gon' run with it now.
[SPEAKER_06]: Never looked back, we done gone hundreds of miles.
[SPEAKER_06]: From dark roles, heroes, to become a hero.
[SPEAKER_06]: Facing a league of justice, his power was the people.
[SPEAKER_06]: Enemy is lethal, a king became regal.
[SPEAKER_06]: Saw the face of Jim Crow under a bald eagle.
[SPEAKER_06]: The biggest weapon,
[SPEAKER_06]: is to stay peaceful.
[SPEAKER_06]: We sing.
[SPEAKER_06]: Our music is the cuts that we bleed through.
[SPEAKER_06]: Somewhere in the dream we had an epiphany.
[SPEAKER_06]: Now we right the wrongs in history.
[SPEAKER_06]: No one can win a war individually.
[SPEAKER_06]: It take the wisdom of the elders and young people's energy.
[SPEAKER_06]: Welcome to the story we call victory.
[SPEAKER_06]: The coming of the Lord.
[SPEAKER_06]: My eyes have seen the glory.
[SPEAKER_02]: One day, when the glory comes,
[SPEAKER_02]: It will be ours, it will be ours One day, when the war is won We will be sure, we will be sure
[SPEAKER_04]: Together, together, everyone.
[SPEAKER_04]: Together, together, come on, let's have some fun.
[SPEAKER_04]: Together, we're there for each other every time.
[SPEAKER_03]: Together, together, come on, let's do this right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Here and now, it's time for celebration.
[SPEAKER_03]: I finally figured out.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That all our dreams have no limitations.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what it's all about.
[SPEAKER_05]: We're special in our own way We make each other strong Each other strong We're not the same We're different in a good way Together's where we belong We're all in this together Once we know
[SPEAKER_04]: That we are, we're all stars And we see that we're all in this together And it shows when we stand hand in hand Make our dreams come true