Hi, I'm Jocelyn McCarthy with the Mustang Report, here with the left shark, who just moved back to Medford.
How do you think the Super Bowl went this year?
I thought it was pretty good.
It was, um, Beyonce killed it, of course, but I think it was missing some sharks.
How's your new home at the MHS pool?
Um, it's nice and warm.
It's really nice, but, you know, I don't like, I don't know, the swim, the swim team, they're all really skinny, so it doesn't really help me, so I'm hoping that, like, um, some more people come swimming so I can have some more food.
Remember MHS, fish are friends, not food.
Welcome to the Mustang Report.
Hi, I'm Joss McCarthy with the Mustang Report.
I'm here with Frank D'Alessio talking about his role at Meffitt High School.
Thank you.
I'm the district technology specialist for Meffitt High School, and my role here is to take care of all of the PCs that are in the district.
There's currently about 1,100 of them in the district, so there's a help desk, and when a call comes in the help desk, I take it, I look at what the problem is, and I go to the teachers or to the school, and then I repair that.
And then we put it back into its normal operation.
Thank you.
Can you tell me one of your hobbies you like to do?
Yeah, one of the hobbies is I'm a professional bowler.
So I average between 200 and 190 and 200.
And I bowl a couple of nights a week, Sundays and Thursdays.
I've been doing that for probably 57 years.
And right now I instruct people on how to bowl, how to hold the ball, because there is a science to holding the ball.
You know, you don't want any space between the ball and your fingers or thumb.
Have you been with the same team for your whole life?
No, there's different teams.
The team I'm on now on Sunday is, well, let's see, is Infinite Power.
So that's one team.
It's a group of guys.
There's four men on a team.
It could be females too.
It's a mixed league.
Hey Mustangs, the answer to the question of the week, my middle name is Lee.
Good luck.
I hope somebody got it.
The question of the week on the Mustang Report is... What game show has Ms.
Perfoni been on?
I'm Victoria, the meteorologist here with a Mustang report to let you know it's snowing and it's cold.
Don't go outside, this well is for the penguins.
But if you do go outside, beware of snowballs.
Hey, I'm already here at the bar.
How long are you guys going to be here?
Ten minutes?
Okay, sounds good.
I'll start ordering drinks then.
See you soon.
Hey, how's it going?
Hey, good, how are you?
Good.
Are you here alone?
Uh, yeah, I'm here waiting for my friends.
Your friends?
Yeah.
So, what's your name?
Gigi.
And yours?
Antonio.
Oh, nice.
So, uh, I was thinking, uh, do you want to get a drink?
Sure, yeah, that's fine.
So, what's your poison?
Uh, can I get a gin martini straight up, please?
Me too, me too.
Me too.
Good morning, straight up.
Here you go, sir.
Thank you.
Thanks.
I think your friend's over there.
My friend's?
Yeah, just check over there, see?
Oh, I don't think I see them.
Oh, I'm mistaken, I'm mistaken.
Oh, okay.
Yep.
So, bathroom, bathroom, bathroom?
You know what?
I think I need to go to the bathroom, alright?
Okay.
Just to notify you to put something in your drink, I'm just going to switch it out for you, alright?
Oh, okay.
Thank you very much.
I'm gonna call the cops and by the time he gets back, he'll be arrested.
Okay, sounds good.
Thank you very much.
You're welcome.
Sorry about that.
So, how's the drink?
Um, I haven't really tried it yet, you know.
Really?
I'm just waiting for my friends to show up.
Oh, okay, okay.
It's alright.
What's the problem here?
The problem is, this guy put a suspicious tablet into his drink.
And he's going to arrest him because he put drugs in here?
Sir, can you stand up?
You are under the arrest for drug possession.
Wait, what?
What are you talking about?
You have the right to remain silent.
Anything you say or do will be brought against you in the court of law.
Hello, residents of Medford.
Welcome to the City of Medford's Mayor's Office.
We're here today with the Medford Malden Elks, exalted ruler Mary Fitzgerald, who would like to present a check on behalf of the Elks.
to the Crystal Campbell Medford Strong Spirit Award Scholarship.
The Elks has been kind enough to donate $2,000 toward a scholarship that will be awarded this spring.
And we want to thank Mary on behalf of all of the students here today for being a member of our community and doing such wonderful things.
So Mary, please step up.
Thank you, Stephanie.
Thank you, Mary.
Well, it's my honor to present this check to the Crystal Campbell Scholarship in the amount of $2,000 from the Medford-Malden College of Economics, number 915.
Wonderful.
Thank you so very much.
And I believe we have this right here for you on behalf of Crystal Campbell Scholarship that we have here in Medford.
And this is Medford Strong in the front and Crystal.
And we're joined today by Mr. Campbell, Crystal's dad, superintendent of schools, Roy Belson.
many of the members of the girls softball team at Medford High School, Allison Goldsberry, who is a, I believe she formed, co-former of this scholarship foundation.
So thank you very much for all the work that you do on behalf of the citizens of Medford.
Thank you.
She's awesome, and we love her.
She's the best.
Thank you.
Not just us.
See you later.
Student of the month, this is a special moment.
Awesome job.
Nice beard, by the way.
You're looking pretty cool.
Is this your first time winning student of the month?
Yeah.
This is a pretty special moment.
How are you feeling?
Pretty good.
Pretty good?
Well, you should feel awesome because this is an honor.
We're real proud of you.
Teachers and faculty think the best of you.
Congratulations.
Keep it up.
Thank you.
We're recording it.
This is going live.
It's a live feed.
Congratulations.
How you doing?
Carpentry too?
You're the first carpentry.
Very impressive.
What are you going to do this weekend?
What are you going to do about this celebration?
You going to go up to eat or something?
I'm not sure.
I didn't really expect that.
Congratulations.
You have a great day, all right?
you