[SPEAKER_00]: All right, let's take a look at the other C option that we advanced.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some people are calling this the Starship Academy option, or fondly known as C3.4.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so when I look at this one, what I see, and you tell me if I'm right, we're sort of hugging around the existing gym and pool.
[SPEAKER_00]: So those spaces will be renovated, just like we just talked about with the other C option.
[SPEAKER_00]: But how we use that space in that area of the site is changing somewhat dramatically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So can you talk a little bit about that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it does change the dynamic a little bit between where the addition is and how it interacts with portions of the site, not in a wholly distinct way from the prior option, but ways that I think will provide a benefit.
[SPEAKER_01]: to the overall experience of the site and really from when we think about the variety of programs that are on site, making sure that there's an area of the building that really feels like it belongs to different groups.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so really by these different arced elevations of the building that fall around it, the one that's going to be facing the field in this scenario would definitely be the main high school entrance and it will have that welcoming feel just by the building form that surrounds it.
[SPEAKER_01]: but as you move up and around the building that might be an opportunity to have the CTE spaces that have a public facing component and have a section of the building that really feels like it's dedicated for them and then likewise around the next side of it could be the early education center sort of face of the building and down at the ground level so it really tries to optimize the challenge of or optimize the response to the challenge of
[SPEAKER_01]: How do we address all of the different needs for the different groups that are going to be coming to the building and make sure that it's easy for people to understand when they visit the building.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where should I be going in if I'm coming here to drop off my child for preschool or if I'm a high school student that's coming just for the beginning of the day.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I guess the other thing that I'll say when I look at this, lots of similarities to the other one.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in both of them, it looks like we could avoid modulars particularly for some of those CTE spaces that we talked about, or like needing to bring them offsite or any of those things that you were talking about earlier, because that back portion of the building where those programs are located today would not be in the footprint of everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: correct that that is correct i think it it does offer that option certainly building a new portion of the building and there there may be more square footage more area of the building that is not overlapping with the existing footprint in this particular option one thing i do want to point out as we're trying to find ways to reduce though the number of modular classrooms which is a great goal and something that we're really going to be thinking about in a very fine level of detail is that it
[SPEAKER_01]: will potentially result in an increased duration of the project as well, because it means there's another phase that we're going to have to add in terms of breaking up the construction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think at the end of the day, that's going to be a preferable compromise to spending all the effort and sort of the disruption involved with moving back and forth to modular classroom buildings.
[SPEAKER_01]: But we just don't want anyone to think that it's well, we can just get rid of the modular classrooms without any other sort of impact, because there is always an impact in terms of the decision making process.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and I think like when I think about somebody who's done something like that, I think of Arlington, which is fairly new, and they went through, they had a many, many, many phased implementation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so when I went for a tour, when I was in the building, I did not feel like I was disrupted by the fact that I was in only part of the new building and then sort of dipping over into the old building.
[SPEAKER_00]: So there is some opportunity there that like phasing is not necessarily a bad thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just another thing to weigh when we are talking about these choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that fair?
[SPEAKER_01]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, more time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, cool.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's our C options.