Members of City Council, City Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Del Rosso. Present. Councilor Falco. Present. Councilor Knight. Present. Councilor Longo Kern. Present. Vice President Marks. Present. Councilor Scott Perkins. Present. President Gabriel. Present. Senator present, not absent, please rise to salute the flag. I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America.
and to the Republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all. Motions, orders, and resolutions, paper 17-027, offered by President Caviello. Be it resolved that the Memphis City Council commend and congratulate Chris Curtin,
for his life-saving actions performed on a Meffitt resident that he be presented with a council accommodation. Be it further resolved that we recognize Sean Magnin of Armstrong Ambulance and Sam Tabalesi of Hallmark Health for making the life-saving classes available. Council President Caviello. Thank you, Mr. President. Mr. President, every year I'm taught a service along with Councilor Falco at the corners.
This is a service put on by Sam Terabelsi from Hallmark Health and Strong Ambulance. And what we're taught every year for the past ten plus years is we're taught CPR, choking, and how to operate a defibrillator. And fortunately, I've never had the opportunity to ever have to use these services, but someone in the audience had to perform CPR on a train going to work one day.
Chris Curtin. Chris, do you wanna stand up? Chris, if you come up to the mic. Those of you who know Chris, Chris is a quiet guy, very reserved. Chris, if you wanna tell the story of what happened on the train, and you know a little bit better than me. Sure, well, I took the training from Sean the last couple of years, actually, and stayed at home,
the Haymarket T Station on Halloween Day, about 2 o'clock in the afternoon. And John sat down next to me and lost consciousness, but was struggling for breath. So one person went down to the end of the platform to hit the panic button, and I called 911. And then John stopped struggling. He stopped breathing. So I put him down onto the platform of the train and did exactly what Shawn Mangan taught us to do.
All of the points that the pointers that he and teachings that he gave us just kicked right in. And I was able to do, I don't know how long I was doing chest compressions on John, but the EMTs and the paramedics showed up. I don't know how many minutes it was, if it was 10 or more, but it felt like a lifetime. And I'll tell you, I never,
felt a more greater feeling of relief than the moment I saw all the professionals show up in the work that they did. Incredibly impressive. I walked away from that experience really dumbfounded that day and incredibly impressed with the type of work that they do every day without, with very little recognition. So I'm incredibly pleased that
the city council and you, Mr. President, Mr. Carvey, uh, counsel Caraviello, uh, recognizing Armstrong ambulance and Hallmark health. Um, Sean Mangan and Sam Tara Belsey in particular, uh, for the, for the generous, uh, uh, volunteer work that they do, uh, to teach us this, you'd never think you're going to need to use this. And I, I wish, uh, I, I don't, I hope I never have to use it again, but, um, I'm so happy it worked out. And Pauline, uh, John's wife reached out to me.
five weeks after the incident and she wrote a really nice letter. She got the police report, the T police report and got my contact information and wrote a really nice card and a beautiful letter and we got together for lunch and then the rest kind of took off from there. A colleague of mine in the juvenile court wrote a letter to the Kiwanis and that's how the council, Mr Rick, you became aware of this. And so I really appreciate the,
all the kind words, all the flattering compliments that I've received from family, friends, and colleagues. But I really want to point out that the most important and the people that really deserve the credit and should get all the congratulations are the people like Sean and all of the first responders, police, fire, EMTs, paramedics. When you see them at work, up close and personal, it's just beyond impressive.
I'm really glad that they're here tonight to be honored by the council. Thank you. If you could introduce the family. Chris, if you could introduce the family.
who tells me he's recovering nicely, thanks to the paramedics at EMTs and the people at, the professionals at Mass General Hospital. And John tells me he's doing well. John, if you'd like to say something. Thank you very much for him and for the EMTs. And Sean, Sean Manganer, John, if you could stand up and be recognized, and Sam.
Those are the guys that make it happen, and they teach us every year, because CPR changes every year. And again, I've never had a chance, I've never had an opportunity to use it, and I hope I never do, but again, Chris, he learned it, and it came right up, and Chris, I want to thank you. And Sam, and Sean, again, Sean is a great ambassador for Armstrong Ambulance, and Sam is a great ambassador for Hallmark Health, and they're great community partners.
Well, as you can tell, they're in credit. They do not seek out the spotlight, but they really deserve a lot of credit and recognition. They do. Chris, I'd like to give you a citation. Thank you.
Thank you. The Memphis City Council takes pleasure in awarding this council accommodation to Chris Curtin in recognition for his life-saving actions performed on a Memphis resident. The Memphis City Council extends a sincere congratulations on your heroic action. Thank you.
Chair will be in recess for one minute.
Just if I also could, I just want to recognize one of Medford's own that was just recognized here tonight, Sean Magnin. He received back a few years back a distinct honor by the American Ambulance Association regarding the Boston Marathon. Sean was the first responder
and was recognized nationally. And really, he's done yeoman's work in this effort, and we appreciate, Sean, all your work. Thank you, Mr. Vice President. Before we get back, I want to introduce our new reporter for the transcript, Ethan Hartley.
It can be taken over, so I hope to see some good writing from you in the future. Positive good writing. Positive, that's right. 16, 17, 030, offered by Councilor Lungo-Kern. Be it resolved that the administration reach out to Park Medford with regards to improperly ticketing those who have paid accordingly. Be it further resolved that a representative from Park Medford
10 day metric city council meeting of the whole to discuss the issues or problems that are still occurring. Council member Kern. Thank you. Um, president Caraviello. I know that I think yourself has been requesting that park method come to a committee of the whole meeting or a city council meeting. So we could sit down and discuss what has been going on in the last several months with park Medford.
Especially since now we had, it was sold, bought and sold, and we're dealing with a new contract. And as of recent, the complaints have really been coming in. I'm not sure if my colleagues have realized or witnessed the same thing.
One complaint leads to another, and people are now going public with their complaints, which leads to a whole host of issues that bring light to our eyes and make us realize what is going on. It seems like there was a lot of kinks that needed to be worked out and a lot of changes that should have been made with the old administration. But now, the last nine months, it seems like things are going downhill. And I don't know if that's because of the purchase and sale.
or what's really going on in that office. I hear it's really a disgrace to work with. When you go in, nobody has the correct information. I had a complaint this week with regards to somebody who was just going down to get her parking permit pass. She brought the proper documentation with her to get that pass. They sent her out the door without the pass telling her she needed A, B, and C.
Finally, she went back with somebody that knew exactly what she needed. She had brought the correct documentation the first time, and it was corrected the second time she went in. But she should have been saved that second trip if people at Park Medford knew exactly the rules and regulations and what needs to be collected in order to get that parking permit pass. I've also had several complaints with regards to people that are, one of the big ones that was upsetting was a woman
taking her child out of the car, went and paid for parking to head into the Medford Public Library, and paid for parking, and then five minutes later, got a ticket. Once you got that complaint, you realize that this is happening to several people. They're paying for parking accordingly, and five, 10 minutes later, they're getting a ticket incorrectly. Now, for that to happen maybe once or twice, it's one thing, but I've got about six complaints with regards to that in the last couple weeks.
So something needs to be corrected. Something needs to be done. Another issue is with regards to when you do get a ticket and you pay that ticket, that should obviously be recorded in some sort of system that Park Medford has. But people have been complaining that they've gone to the registry to try to renew their license. And for some reason, it hasn't been recorded. And those tickets have been improperly sent to the registry. And people have been turned away from the registry.
not being able to renew their license because it's showing that they had a ticket, although they have their receipts and they've paid for those tickets. So those are three, three or four different issues that I've got complaints of in the last four to six weeks. And I think I've, I have emailed the chief of police. I know he's helped me with a couple things, but I've also requested, and hopefully I'll hear back from him soon. I've asked that he specifically talk to Park Medford. I know he was almost the ambassador
of what has been going on, and he's done a tremendous amount of work to try to get the—within the last two years to try to get it up and running. But there's just so many improper things that are going on, and people seem to—I don't know if they're not trained correctly or they're—some people even online are saying that they feel like these tickets are given out of spite at some point. They're joking with the people, saying, yeah, of course I'm going to give—you know, it's
what I hear is going on is not right and we need to get a grasp on it. The chief of police hopefully will reach out to Park Medford, but I think it's really important that also this city council sits down and ask the appropriate questions, make sure we let them know how unhappy we are and what our residents are going through. I've got complaints from people outside of the city as well, which you know, can't be unnoticed. And I hope the administration, you know, is, is getting these complaints to, or, you know, reading up online when,
things are posted because the administration needs to get a grasp on this. Little tweaks were made, I believe, in January, but that's just not enough. What has been going on is people are not happy, and again, it's going downhill. And I think we need to get a grasp on it, and this council needs to take the lead. So I ask that, Council President, we try to get Park Medford down to a Committee of the Whole meeting so we can sit and roundtable it and discuss what's been going on and the complaints we've been hearing.
and why they're not being corrected. We've been asking since January for a meeting of last year. So maybe now that you're in control, we can get that done. Yes, I would say that we should have Dan Nash down here within the next two weeks. I think a committee of the whole meeting, just so we have the full hour. And I think he needs to come and talk to the people too, publicly, because people are not happy. It's really a shame that after two, three years we can't get it
we can't get under control and whether that's because it was bought and sold or what's, I don't know what's going on, but at least people in the office should be educated and people who are out there giving tickets should be taking the time to make sure they're certain this A, B, and C haven't paid for parking so that they can't, you know, cause then people have to number one, either pay the ticket, fight the ticket, get upset, go to Diane McLeod to appeal it, go to Park Medford. They have to take time out of their busy schedule.
that they could be doing other things to try to fight these tickets, and it's not right. Thank you. On the motion, second? Roll call. Roll call is seconded by Councillor Falco. Roll call has been requested. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councillor Dela Russo. Yes. Councillor Falco. Yes. Councillor Knight. Yes. Councillor McKernan. Yes.
Vice President Marx. Yes. Councilor Scafelli. Yes. Vice President Cabrillo. Yes. Seven in the affirmative. Then the motion passes. Motion by Councilor Dela Ruzzo to take paper 17-029 out of order. All in favor? Aye. Aye. 17029, petition for a signed denial reversal by Edward Batten, Batten Brothers, Inc.
For Maple Park condominiums, 65 Valley Street, Medford. OCD application 01-17 exceeds allowable size 94-306-5C. Councilor Marks of the signed committee. Thank you, Mr. President. We do have a gentleman here from, I believe, the sign company. Yes. So if you can address the council. My name's Ed Badden.
work with Batten Brother Signs. And right now we're just requesting approval for the size of our signage. Right now it's at four by six feet, which is, I'm about five foot 10, a couple inches wider than my wingspan. And we feel a sign of this size is necessary for the property where it's located. Maple Park Condominiums,
occupies the entire building at this, excuse me, at this address. And the business also occupies a whole street block, which comes into close to 34,000 square feet. And we feel as though one 24 square foot sign should be acceptable for the amount of space that they are occupying. Okay. Councilor Knight. Mr. President, this is purely a request to seek variance just based upon the size of the sign.
Presently, the current sign ordinance would read that the square footage of the sign cannot exceed 12 feet. So that sign would be six by two. The sign here is six by four. And I think that this is a measure that I wholeheartedly support. I think it will not have much of an impact on the quality of life in the neighborhood by passing traffic, so on and so forth.
renderings. The sign is about a six or so feet off of the sidewalk, Mr. President. So it has a ample setback. Um, really all it is is just so that the letters on the sign can be larger so people can have an easier time reading it, which I think will make it safer actually. Thank you. Move approval. Councilor Del Rosso. Mr. President, I concur with my colleague. I think this sign would make a wonderful addition, uh, aesthetically to the neighborhood.
We'll identify the domicile there, uh, in an area that, uh, suffers from a brisk rate of traffic with also abrupt stopping at the stoplights at Fulton street. And, uh, this will help people in search of the condo complex. I second. Thank you. Do we have a motion by Councilor Marks, the science chairman? Yes, Mr. President. Um, this is, um, a newly constructed, uh, entrance, uh, into the building itself.
And it was beautiful craftsmanship done constructing this new entrance. And I see no problem with this particular sign. I think aesthetically it fits in to the property and the neighborhood. And I would motion for approval, Mr. President. On the motion by Councilor Marks, seconded by Councilor DelaRusso. All those in favor? All said, thank you very much. Thank you. Motion passes.
We have one more, one thing I want to say, Mr. Councilor Knight. Be it resolved, offered by Councilor Scott Pelley, be it resolved that the council and the, Councilor Scott, I can't read your writing. Be it offered by Councilor Scott Pelley that we get an update on the focus group on recreation. Councilor Scott Pelley.
I can't thank you, Mr. President. I've been the chairperson for the focus group on recreation for the last three months. And the group has been working diligently making sure that we are covering all of our bases and making sure that we're getting all the information that the administration would need to bring a full time recreation department in the city of Medford. The reason why I bring this up, we'll have a full report soon.
Uh, this week we'll be sending out a, uh, the administration will be sending out a survey that we're asking all of our constituents to spend about two or three minutes and it will be very helpful to see what, what, um, not just a few people, not just the 20 people that are on the focus group or myself, but what, uh, most of our constituents are looking for and, um, and give us a better idea in which direction we'll go when this council have to make, have to make a decision. Um,
and the city administration has to make a decision to allow this wonderful opportunity. So look out for that. I know that, uh, it'll be on the city website. Uh, there'll be a press release soon and there'll be, um, there'll be doing a verse nine one one. I believe that, um, for all the students in, um, in the school systems that will have that online too. So, uh, thank you very much. Thank you. It's Councilor Scott, probably for all your hard work. Councilor DelaRusso. President, I just want to,
Lord, Councilor Scarpelli and the group who've done great work in advancing a central clearinghouse of sorts for all the recreational entities within the community. It's a great thing that fosters cohesion in our community and provides great opportunity for the young ones and also for parents to get involved and stay connected to the generation coming up. It's a wonderful thing and I think
uh, the counselor in the group for their good work. Mr. President. Thank you. Counselor Mox. Thank you, Mr. President. I too want to thank a counselor, Scott Pelly. Uh, you couldn't have appointed a better person that has the insight and knowledge already, uh, regarding, uh, recreation, how departments established, what the needs are, uh, staffing wise for a city this size. And I look forward to, uh, the, or eventual recommendations and implementation, Mr. President.
of a long needed recreational department in this city. Thank you. Counselor Monks, counselor Falco. Thank you, Mr. President. I also want to thank councilor Scott Pelley for his hard work on this issue. Um, I, uh, I know him and his, uh, committee has been working on this for a while and, uh, they've had a lot of meetings and, um, I'm hearing a lot of great things. So I look forward to, uh, the results of the survey and the, uh, the formal report from the committee.
Uh, this, uh, recreation department, in my opinion, and I think you'd agree is long overdue and a city of this size, I think could benefit greatly from a recreation department. So thank you for your hard work on this. Thank you. The council member motion to receive council. Okay. Uh, thank you. Um, president Carviello. I also want to thank the committee and council Scarpelli. If you could just reiterate, when will the survey be coming out and how will we get a, how will we be able to access it? Just,
I missed that. Okay. So we will, we will have it, uh, there'll be, um, uh, survey monkey, uh, attachment on the city's website. Um, we'll have hard copies at a few locations like the library and some other visible sites. And, um, we'll be doing reverse nine one one. So everyone, uh, from, uh, preschool to seniors have an opportunity to, uh, add their opinions and what they feel.
or if they feel that a recreation department would do without to our community for our community. And, um, uh, we'll also be reaching out to all the schools via the, via the, uh, the student sites for their parents and students work together and to get the most information that we can get to make, uh,
prudent decision moving forward. So pretty excited about it. Thank you. And when should we look at this and what, how long, how long a timeframe will they be serving? Like 30 days? Well, actually it should be going out by the end of this week and we'll, we've given two weeks as a timeline to, um, so it's a coordinated effort with, um, you know, with, um, reverse nine one one.
uh, city's website and their, their, uh, the news, uh, uh, news release and, uh, and that's, we're looking for for this week. So thank you. Thank you. Motion by counselor Knight to receive a place in file. All those in favor. Aye. Opposed? Motion passes. Motion by counselor Knight to revert back to regular business. Oh, brief announcement. I'm sorry.
Uh, Mr. President, recently I did have a conversation with our highway superintendent and he asked that, uh, I announced that they will be accepting applications for pothole filling. Um, uh, always through Seekick click fix or through seven, eight, one, three, nine, three, two, four, four, five. Mr. President, uh, the highway superintendent did ask that I announce this at the meeting because they have been out patching. Thank you. Motion by Councilor Knight to revert back to regular business.
17-028 offered by Councilor Knight and President Caraviello, being resolved that the Memphis City Council extend its deep and sincere condolences to the family of former Memphis High Boys Varsity hockey coach, Charlie Driscoll, on his recent passing. Councilor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much. Someone, being someone who doesn't know how to ice skate, but who certainly enjoyed watching hockey games growing up, I remember sitting in the stands at La Conte rink and
listening to Mr. Driscoll, Coach Driscoll, coach at the top of his lungs from across the rink. But he did a great job. He really put Medford hockey on the map. And as a child growing up, the greater Boston league was very competitive in the sport of hockey. And it was always Arlington and Medford battling for the top spot. And then everybody else fell in behind us. And a lot of that had to do with great players and a lot of it had to do with great coaching. And Mr. Driscoll had a great deal of success here in the city of Medford.
I remember my freshman year in high school watching Sean Bates and Eddie Buckley skate at the Boston Garden in the Super 8 Tournament versus Catholic Memorial with Coach Driscoll on the bench, and it brings back great memories. I'm very sad to see him go. He was someone that meant to a lot of young men in this community, and he will be sorely and sadly missed, Mr. President. I offer my deep condolences to his family, and I ask that the council join me. Thank you. Counsel Scott Pellett.
If I can, as a former colleague and fellow coach in the Method System, we often sat in meetings together with Coach Driscoll, and we'd be fighting for different awards for our Mustangs, and there wasn't a person that fought harder for their kid, his kids, than Coach Driscoll. He had a charisma about him and an aura about him that you could really appreciate today's world of coaching.
He was special, and he'll definitely greatly be missed. He's laid the groundwork for a lot of great coaches today that he has mentored, and he'll be missed. The President Thank you. Councilor Marks. Councilor Marks Thank you, Mr. President. I, too, got to know Mr. Driscoll when I served as a member of the school committee. And I can tell you, he was not only respected in this community, but he was well respected across the entire state.
Mr. President. And as Counselor Scott Pelley mentioned, he always put the kids first, no matter what it was. And he'd go to bat and fight for the kids. And I was at meetings where he would stand up, Mr. President, against school administration and against anyone else that he felt was doing something that was against his students and his hockey players. And I respected him for that, and he will be sorely missed, Mr. President. The President Thank you, Counselor Marks.
I've known Charlie Driscoll for many years, you know, through the Meffitt hockey community. And Charlie is responsible for many kids going to college and the pros, um, Olympic hockey teams. And again, Charlie is a good man. And they say he, Councillor Knight was right. He put, he put Meffitt hockey on the map and again, he will be missed. If we could have a moment of silence, please.
17-031 offered by Councilor Caraviello, be it resolved that the Memphis City Council send its condolences to the family of Ernest Casasa on his recent passing. Mr. Casasa was a Navy veteran who served our country in World War II. Mr. Casasa is a neighbor of mine, and again, his presence in my neighborhood will be missed. And again, if we could have a moment of silence for him also.
Motion by Councilor Scott Pelli to take papers in the hands of the clerk. I can move it. Offered by Councilor Mox, be it resolved that the owner of Wet Cuts, Kathy Bianco, be recognized for being in business for the past 22 years in the city of Medford. Councilor Mox. Thank you, Mr. President. If anyone's aware of Kathy Bianco and Wet Cuts,
She was located on Boston Ave for a number of years and has been in business in this city for over 22 years, Mr. President, and has been an outstanding businessperson in this community and has serviced thousands of Meffitt residents, Mr. President, with a hair coloring, a perm, or a wiffle. She ran the Gambit in that particular shop over there. And she is still going to be cutting hair, but will no longer be at that location, Mr. President.
And I want to wish her well on her future endeavors. She will be, she was a staple in the Boston Ave area, and she will be sorely missed, Mr. President. Where she will be to? She will be on the road, I guess, so she doesn't have a fixed location. But, you know, she had a number of distinguished people in this community, former President Robert Mayorko.
got his haircut there. So, you know, very quickly. He was a great customer. Very little work. But he got his haircut there. And like I said, Mr. President, it was like the neighborhood coffee shop. Everyone would go in there, get your haircut, make small talk. And I just want to thank Kathy Bianco for her many years of business in this community, Mr. President.
Thank you. Receive a council citation for years of service. Yes. Thank you. We will, uh, if you'd like to, uh, better up here in the next couple of weeks, we can get, we can get her a citation. I don't know if she's much for the public eye, but, uh, we'll see. You can invite her up. Okay. On the motion by, uh, customer night, all in favor of the post motion passes offered by counselor night and counselor carrier of yellow being resolved at the Memphis city council.
Send his condolences to the family of Grace Richmond, longtime Medford resident and election inspector for the city of Medford.
Councilor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much. Ms. Richmond will be sorely missed in our community. She was a member of our faith-based community here in West Medford with relationships with St. Rayfield's Church. And she was also an election official here in the city of Medford who gave a great deal of her time dedicated to the public to make sure that our elections moved smoothly and made sure that Clerk Finn had an easier time on election day because of the hard work that she did. So with that being said, Mr. President,
I'd like to extend my deep condolences to her family and ask that the council join me in doing so. Thank you. Councilor Dela Rosa. Thank you, council. Thank you. If we could stand for a moment of silence, please.
Councilor Dela Ruzzo. May I take this opportunity to kindly recommend with the change of leadership in our body that yourself and Councilor Marks be
take the helm as being the two spokespersons for this body with regards to a legal matter pending in the courts. Thank you, we will make that change and I will notify the attorney and Councilor Marks. I'd like to keep Councilor Longo on the position where she is an attorney.
and neither one of us are attorneys, and I think we can use Councilor Lango's legal expertise. I found that the attorney that we're paying to engage brings great legal expertise to this. Thank you. On the motion, Councilor Del Rosso. Councilor Lango-Grant. I just wanted to know what the resolution was, because I, too, I mean, it's been quite a while I've been dealing with it. Currently, yourself and Councilor Del Rosso
are the go-to person for the suit in regards to Love Street. Yeah, I mean, I'd be happy to stay on and communicate with. Right, so we would just change it to myself and Councilor Moxley to say if you wouldn't mind. I'd love to stay on, please. If you wouldn't mind staying on. So if, you know, again, neither one of us are attorneys and yes, we have the solicitor, but sometimes. We don't, we don't have the solicitor. That's right, we don't. We only have the. We have the attorney that came to converse with. Thank you. Yes, on the motion by Councilor Del Rosso. As amended. As amended.
by Councilor Kerrio. All those in favor? Aye. Opposed? Motion passes. Records of the meeting of January 10th, 2017 were passed to Councilor DelaRusso. Councilor DelaRusso, how have you filed those records? Mr. President, I've filed them to be in order, but I feel that I must point out that in brief time I've returned to this floor
It's been duly noted. Motion to adjourn.