So,
you
[SPEAKER_05]: Mayor Langer-Cohen, Superintendent Edward Vinson, members of the Medford School Committee, distinguished educators, parents and caregivers, family, friends, and most importantly, our graduating class of 2024.
[SPEAKER_05]: Good evening and welcome to the Medford High School and Medford Vocational Technical High School Commencement Ceremony.
[SPEAKER_05]: I am Marta Cabral, Principal of Medford High School.
[SPEAKER_05]: At this time, I would like to ask you to please stand for the Pledge of Allegiance recited by one of the voices of Medford High School, Riley Mulvihill.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then please remain standing for the National Anthem performed by Coral Chobbs and Taya Cruz.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America and to the Republic for which it stands, one nation under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh say can you see by the dawn's early light what so proudly we hailed at the twilight's last gleaming?
[SPEAKER_03]: Whose broad stripes and bright stars
[SPEAKER_03]: through the perilous fight, o'er the ramparts we watched were so gallantly streaming?
[SPEAKER_03]: And the rocket's red glare, the bombs bursting in air,
[SPEAKER_03]: gave proof through the night that our flag was still there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, say does that star-spangled banner yet
[SPEAKER_05]: At this time it is my honor to introduce members of the Medford High School and Medford Vocational Technical High School community who are present here today.
[SPEAKER_05]: I ask that you please stand to be recognized.
[SPEAKER_05]: Superintendent of Medford Public Schools, Dr. Edward Benson.
[SPEAKER_05]: Assistant Superintendent of Enrichment and Innovation, Dr. Peter Cushing.
[SPEAKER_05]: Assistant Superintendent of Academics and Instruction, Dr. Suzanne Galusi.
[SPEAKER_05]: Members of the Medford School Committee, Ms.
[SPEAKER_05]: Nicole Branley, Mr. John Entapa, Mr. Aaron Olipade, Ms.
[SPEAKER_05]: Erica Reinfeld.
[SPEAKER_05]: Secretary of the Medford School Committee, Mr. Paul Rousseau.
[SPEAKER_05]: Vice Chairperson of the Medford School Committee, Ms.
[SPEAKER_05]: Jenny Graham.
[SPEAKER_05]: And Mayor and Chairperson, Mayor Breanna Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_05]: From Medford High School, Senior Class President, Darren Truong.
[SPEAKER_05]: Senior Vice President, Brady Leet.
[SPEAKER_05]: Senior Class Secretary, Mohammad Jamaluddin.
[SPEAKER_05]: Senior Class Treasurer, Jacob Steckerl.
[SPEAKER_05]: Class of 2024 Faculty Class Advisors, Mr. Dello Russo and Chef Pearlstein.
[SPEAKER_05]: Class of 2024 Assistant Principals, Ms.
[SPEAKER_05]: Allison McDonald, Mr. Patrick Hamilton, Mr. David Blauch, Ms.
[SPEAKER_05]: Sheila Freitas Haley.
[SPEAKER_05]: Principal Director of Medford Vocational Technical High School, Mr. Chad Fallon.
[SPEAKER_05]: Class of 2024, today is your day.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's a day to celebrate not just the end of one chapter, but the beginning of so many more.
[SPEAKER_05]: As you absorb this milestone, I want to take a minute to say congratulations.
[SPEAKER_05]: Congratulations on your perseverance, your dedication, and your incredible achievement.
[SPEAKER_05]: You may have heard this quote by someone who grew up not too far from here, Ralph Waldo Emerson, who said, it's not the destination, it's the journey.
[SPEAKER_05]: Although today you've arrived at a much sought after destination, graduation day, your high school years were themselves a journey, not a destination.
[SPEAKER_05]: A time of growth, of discovery, of developing and creating the person you have beautifully become.
[SPEAKER_05]: And through it all, you've shown resilience, adaptability, and potential.
[SPEAKER_05]: Whether in academics, athletics, the arts, or simply in the way you've supported one another, you've demonstrated the kind of leadership that will serve you well in the years to come.
[SPEAKER_05]: As I look out at you, I see pride.
[SPEAKER_05]: Pride in yourselves, in your peers, in the community you've built together.
[SPEAKER_05]: That pride is more than just a feeling.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's a testament to the hard work and heart you've invested in your education.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's a reminder that every late night study session, every challenging test, every moment of doubt was worth it.
[SPEAKER_05]: To the parents and caregivers, friends and families here today, I know that seeing your loved ones graduate is a mix of emotions.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yet, as you look at these graduates, remember the people they've become is a direct reflection of the unwavering support and love that you've provided.
[SPEAKER_05]: Be proud of yourselves as well for the role you've played in their journey.
[SPEAKER_05]: Class of 2024, please take a moment, stand, turn around, and please show some love to the family and friends here today.
[SPEAKER_05]: Graduates, you can be seated.
[SPEAKER_05]: As you move forward, the world awaits.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's a world full of possibility, of opportunity, of challenges that will push you to grow in the ways that you never thought possible.
[SPEAKER_05]: Embrace those challenges, chase your passions, even when the path isn't easy.
[SPEAKER_05]: Lead with kindness, with empathy, and with the knowledge that you have the power to make a difference.
[SPEAKER_05]: As the class of 2024, I charge you to create a future that is a testament to the incredible potential that lies within each and every one of you.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, as you close this chapter and step into the next, remember that you will always carry the lessons of high school with you, the friendships created, the wisdom gained, and the belief in your own strength.
[SPEAKER_05]: Congratulations, class of 2024, on this milestone in your magnificent journey.
[SPEAKER_05]: Your story is just beginning.
[SPEAKER_05]: Go out there and make it worth telling.
[SPEAKER_05]: Congratulations, Mustangs.
[SPEAKER_05]: It is now my pleasure to invite Mr. Chad Fallon, Principal Director of Medford Vocational Technical High School, to address the class of 2024.
[SPEAKER_09]: Good evening, Madam Mayor, school committee members, faculty, staff, and invited guests, and most importantly, you, our graduates, class of 2024.
[SPEAKER_09]: As your proud principal of Career and Technical Education at Medford High School, otherwise known as the VOC, it is my honor and privilege to join you tonight as you prepare to close one significant chapter of your life and embark on your future, where you'll experience all the amazing things that are ahead of you.
[SPEAKER_09]: You are,
[SPEAKER_09]: the future electricians, chefs, scientists, programmers, nurses, carpenters, auto specialists, welders, teachers, designers, and entrepreneurs that will pave the way for future students that will take your place at Medford High School.
[SPEAKER_09]: For CTE students, along with completing all academic coursework and meeting all requirements for graduation, 106 of the graduating class tonight have also completed over 900 hours of technical instruction and practical hands-on learning in one of our 15 programs.
[SPEAKER_09]: Many of you have also been working all year through our cooperative education program, where many of you will retain a job as soon as tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_09]: Together, we've shared moments of happiness as well as challenging situations that we've overcome together.
[SPEAKER_09]: I would like to personally thank you for allowing us to be part of your life these past four years.
[SPEAKER_09]: I have no doubt that you'll do great things and use the experience gained from our school and lessons learned from our caring faculty that will support you when you face challenges or obstacles along the way.
[SPEAKER_09]: Life can be tough, but I have faith that you'll do great things.
[SPEAKER_09]: And remember, as Principal Cabral mentioned, it's about the journey and not the destination, something I remind myself every day.
[SPEAKER_09]: So my closing message to you all tonight is enjoy the moments, surround yourself with people who love you and support you, and don't be afraid to reinvent yourself as many times as it takes to be your best self.
[SPEAKER_09]: Congratulations to the class of 2024.
[SPEAKER_09]: At this time, I am delighted to call to the podium the class of 2024's choice to give the faculty address, Mr. Nicholas Kane.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you to the class of 2024 for selecting me as your faculty speaker.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm so privileged to be a part of this day and of this community.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to say thank you to the families, friends, teachers, class advisors, and to our new administration teams turning this school in bright new directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thanks also to the counselors, to the nurses, and the folks in food services and our security teams.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thanks to the custodians and the night cleaning crews who keep that old building afloat.
[SPEAKER_01]: And thanks to the unsung heroes, administrative assistants like Michael McLaughlin who are the heart of our school community.
[SPEAKER_01]: Graduates, today is a celebration for you, but know that the joy of it is shared by so many of us in the community who are lucky enough to play a small role in your journey to this moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what a ride you guys had here, from those classes in Zoom freshman year to this beautiful evening we get to share together here.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want you to know that we saw you along the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: We saw you struggle.
[SPEAKER_01]: We saw your victories.
[SPEAKER_01]: We saw you make friends, and we saw you lose some friends.
[SPEAKER_01]: We saw you grow beyond yourself as you grew into yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I want you to know that we're so very proud of you for what you've accomplished, for the people you've become, and for the people that you're becoming.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I'm not sure why you picked me to be your faculty speaker, but you did, and I'm grateful.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so I'm gonna share a little secret with you about being a teacher.
[SPEAKER_01]: This seems like a good venue to share secrets.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most of the folks who know this don't say this part out loud, so don't spread it around, but it's true.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being a teacher is the best.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, we might run out of water, we have to buy our own supplies from time to time, we have to protest to try to get salaries that match inflation, but that's all just background noise.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a teacher, I get to think creatively every day and to interact with amazing young minds like yours, year after year.
[SPEAKER_01]: I get to reflect on our place in history.
[SPEAKER_01]: And every day I can walk into school knowing that your potential, your perspective, and your kindness will surprise me and broaden my understanding of the world and what's possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't think of another job where that's true.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not to say it's easy.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's so hard.
[SPEAKER_01]: but it helps me figure out on a day-to-day and a moment-to-moment basis what's most important when it comes to helping others and living a meaningful life.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the longer we do it, the more rewarding it becomes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Teachers get to see so many young, beautiful minds grow into themselves, and sometimes they come back to visit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes they come back as school committee members, as city counselors, or as teachers.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know if you know this, but your class advisor, Mr. Dello Russo, was a student in my World History I class way back when I was a young teacher.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's one of the great joys of my career to see him grow from being a student to a colleague and a friend.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's always willing to take on new challenges and new responsibilities if it means supporting students.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's an inspiration, and his generosity is a superpower.
[SPEAKER_01]: But here's a funny thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he came back to teach, he told me that he still remembered the three class rules we had back when he was in ninth grade in my class.
[SPEAKER_01]: These were our three rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rule number one was show up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rule number two was there is no rule number two.
[SPEAKER_01]: And rule number three was don't be a jerk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I must have been a smarter teacher back then, because those are some solid rules to live by, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Show up, it's so basic, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's so necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Show up to school and work for sure, but also show up for each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Show up for our friends, for our families.
[SPEAKER_01]: Show up to the party.
[SPEAKER_01]: Show up to the weddings that are coming, to the funerals.
[SPEAKER_01]: Show up for yourself, and for the promises you make to yourself, because you're worth it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rule number two, there is no rule number two.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just goofy, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's a reminder that we're free.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're free to think in new ways.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're free to innovate and to act.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're full of all kinds of unperceived potential.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's no rule number two that's going to hold us back.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rule number three, don't be a jerk.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just golden, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's so easy to recognize when other people are breaking it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's easy to admit it when other people call us out on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't be a jerk.
[SPEAKER_01]: That means all the little things we know make a difference, like being happy to see each other, like not imposing on others if we can afford to.
[SPEAKER_01]: But don't be a jerk also means occasions like this, when you're given a microphone and an audience, that there's some things that need to be said.
[SPEAKER_01]: We owe it to people we care for.
[SPEAKER_01]: So in that spirit, I want us all to just take a moment and recognize as a community, trans rights are human rights.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's recognize together that love is love.
[SPEAKER_01]: Happy Pride, all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's recognize together that we all are or descended from displaced peoples, refugees, immigrants, people brought here against their will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's recognize that we're all gathered here today on land and near the waters that their creator put in the care and the protection of the Wampanoag, the Pawtucket, the Massachusetts, and other tribal nations over time.
[SPEAKER_01]: That our city was built here without permission and is a colonial project.
[SPEAKER_01]: Knowing all this, together, let's work for peace, for love, for refuge, and for each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: I also know rule number three, don't be a jerk, means keep your speech short.
[SPEAKER_01]: So in just a few moments, you'll all be heading off in different directions, carrying your experience here along with you to those lives that await you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want you to know, I'm so happy to have been a small part of your journey.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're a miracle class of 2024.
[SPEAKER_01]: So congratulations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now go get to work, promote peace, promote love, and shine your light on the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: I love you guys.
[SPEAKER_01]: Next up, we have your class president.
[SPEAKER_11]: This is my villain arc right here, guys.
[SPEAKER_11]: What a special day it is to see so many important people here to join in the celebration of the graduating class of 2024.
[SPEAKER_11]: Good evening, my fellow Americans.
[SPEAKER_11]: It is with great humility that I speak here today at the inauguration of the President of the United States of America.
[SPEAKER_11]: Oh, sorry, wrong speech.
[SPEAKER_11]: Joking aside, it has truly been a privilege and an honor to represent the class of 2024 and the first-rate students here at Medford High School.
[SPEAKER_11]: Let's give a round of applause to all of our graduates here sitting today.
[SPEAKER_11]: First and foremost, I would like to thank the people who have allowed me the opportunity to stand here before you today.
[SPEAKER_11]: My mother and father, who have played an undeniable role in shaping my personality, as well as the wonderful teachers and faculty members that I've had the opportunity of learning under throughout my time within Mefford Public Schools.
[SPEAKER_11]: I would also like to express my gratitude to the many vocational shops who have helped make this year's many events possible.
[SPEAKER_11]: From Mr. Spagnola and Mr. Spagnola in the graphic design shop,
[SPEAKER_11]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_11]: Miller in Programming and Web Development, Mr. Jackson in Metal Fab, and Chef P and Chef C in Culinary, just to name a few.
[SPEAKER_11]: They make really good cookies in the bistro, by the way.
[SPEAKER_11]: I would also like to thank my fellow class officers, Brady, Muhammad, and Jacob.
[SPEAKER_11]: Is Jacob here today?
[SPEAKER_11]: I heard he forgot about today's meeting.
[SPEAKER_11]: Oh, there he is.
[SPEAKER_11]: Is he over there?
[SPEAKER_11]: Lastly, I would like to thank our tireless class advisors, Mr. Dello Russo and Chef P, for all their time and effort in collaborating with the student government to help make this year's events possible.
[SPEAKER_11]: When I first entered senior year, I wasn't sure how much work and responsibility lay ahead of me, nor how many groups and organizations I would join that would help further shape me into who I am today.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm glad I decided to become involved in just a few school clubs and organizations here.
[SPEAKER_11]: And it's been a delight for all the class advisors and students that I've had the pleasure of meeting with.
[SPEAKER_11]: When I first moved to Medford in second grade, I had difficulties fitting in.
[SPEAKER_11]: But during that time, I met some of my closest friends who are here today, some of whom have been by my side since second grade.
[SPEAKER_11]: giving of themselves to help me feel like I belonged.
[SPEAKER_11]: In middle school, I struggled as well with academics, feeling overwhelmed and alone.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yet during that same time, there were friends, teachers, and fellow students who despite the tasks they faced, they made time for me.
[SPEAKER_11]: Through my time in Medford Public Schools, I've only been able to focus on myself, putting myself first, improving myself, whether academically or socially, because someone else had put themselves second.
[SPEAKER_11]: a teacher, a student, or a community member decided, despite everything that they had on their plate, would put me first, would go that extra mile, take that extra row, attend that extra meeting, or write that extra line of code so that I could be more successful.
[SPEAKER_11]: And at the beginning of high school, I wasn't anything like the person you see here staying today, giving speeches, speaking regularly with the high school administration,
[SPEAKER_11]: or advocating for more equitable school budgets at five hour long school committee meetings.
[SPEAKER_11]: I think I may have a couple gray hairs from that one, but.
[SPEAKER_11]: I was only able to become this person in part from all those who believed in me, invested time in me, and were willing to take a risk on someone others may have deemed a potential red flag.
[SPEAKER_11]: Don't worry, I'm just a yellow flag now, so it's all good.
[SPEAKER_11]: Our class, our generation, are facing monumental challenges, which we have the unique burden to solve to avoid dire consequences.
[SPEAKER_11]: We were born into a generation forced to solve a multitude of mountainous issues that previous generations created.
[SPEAKER_11]: We will be forced to work harder than any other generation to achieve our American dream, only to likely end up in our parents' basement until we're 35.
[SPEAKER_11]: We will have to face these massive debts placed on us so that the next generation, our children and our grandchildren, can enjoy the fruits of our labor and may or may not appreciate the efforts that we put in.
[SPEAKER_11]: Womp womp.
[SPEAKER_11]: So with all this bad news, seemingly impossible to overcome, why should you even get involved?
[SPEAKER_11]: Why should we bring ourselves to face the challenges of our generation, some, well, most, of which we did not even create?
[SPEAKER_11]: I could put on my politician shoes and talk on about the whys, but instead I'll tell you what led me to realize the importance of getting involved, instead of just sitting and watching others talk about the problems.
[SPEAKER_11]: And so, as Mr. Brophy would say, here's my tie into current events.
[SPEAKER_11]: Within the next 50 years, if we are lucky, we will all have more gray hairs.
[SPEAKER_11]: because we will have faced and fought some of the toughest challenges our civilization has seen, both domestically and abroad.
[SPEAKER_11]: We must fight climate change.
[SPEAKER_11]: We must address gun violence, end the opioid epidemic, end food insecurity for the world's populations, implement criminal justice reform, preserve our democracy, and most importantly, fix the Potholes and Mefford.
[SPEAKER_11]: So like Sisyphus, say that five times fast, rolling the boulder to the top of the hill only to have it roll right back down, these challenges might seem impossible at first.
[SPEAKER_11]: But like those who took their time and a chance on me, the potential red flag, from what I've seen our class face, I'm confident that we can address these challenges head on.
[SPEAKER_11]: Because among other things,
[SPEAKER_11]: We are intelligent, we are resilient, hardworking, considerate, creative, and as many of our parents and guardians will tell you, and teachers, we don't take no for an answer.
[SPEAKER_11]: So I urge you, in whatever careers or future endeavors you choose,
[SPEAKER_11]: to take a chance on someone and put time and effort into things that really matter to you.
[SPEAKER_11]: Don't only show up just for the money or for the prestige.
[SPEAKER_11]: Put your time, energy, and resources into what you love, your passion.
[SPEAKER_11]: Tackle real challenges.
[SPEAKER_11]: Give back to your community.
[SPEAKER_11]: Stand up to injustices and those who have no one to stand up for themselves so that we may all have a better future and society.
[SPEAKER_11]: Signing off for your last time as class president, I'll see you all at our class reunion.
[SPEAKER_11]: And now for our Honorable Mayor, Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_06]: Great job, Darren.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: Good evening, superintendent, faculty, parents, and of course, our graduates.
[SPEAKER_06]: I will not be long, as I know you can't wait to celebrate with your friends and family after you throw your caps high in the air at the end of this ceremony.
[SPEAKER_06]: First, let me congratulate the class of 2024 on this momentous milestone.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm so proud to be here to celebrate you and all the hard work you've put into the last four years.
[SPEAKER_06]: Graduating from high school is a huge accomplishment, and you all should be very proud of yourselves.
[SPEAKER_06]: I know there were obstacles, challenges, as well as learning transitions that you've had to overcome during these last four years.
[SPEAKER_06]: You entered high school during a pandemic, for goodness sake.
[SPEAKER_06]: and had to navigate a shift in the way the world was operating, in addition to getting acclimated to a new school.
[SPEAKER_06]: Your resiliency and strength are inspiring, and those are gained skills that you will all apply as you move forward beyond Medford High School and into the next chapter of your life.
[SPEAKER_06]: Be ready for anything, continue to be curious, and remember that positive thinking is the first step towards future success.
[SPEAKER_06]: There is nothing you can't do, and I know this because I've watched you all as you graciously have risen to meet your challenges.
[SPEAKER_06]: I have all the faith in the world that you will continue to do amazing things and leave your positive mark on the world.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I know your teachers, families, and friends are excited to see what you do next, as am I.
[SPEAKER_06]: If I give you any advice, it's to never be afraid to try.
[SPEAKER_06]: Try it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Try something.
[SPEAKER_06]: Try anything that scares you.
[SPEAKER_06]: The best things out there are the things that are the hardest to try.
[SPEAKER_06]: Be kind, compassionate, and accepting to everyone in everything you do.
[SPEAKER_06]: Or as Mr. Kane said, don't be a jerk.
[SPEAKER_06]: I hope I wasn't a jerk in too long.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'll leave you with congratulations again to the class of 2024.
[SPEAKER_06]: Go Mustangs.
[SPEAKER_05]: It is a great honor for me to introduce at this time the leader of the Medford public school system, the superintendent of schools, Dr. Maurice Edward Vincent.
[SPEAKER_10]: Good evening.
[SPEAKER_10]: We'll try that again.
[SPEAKER_10]: Good evening, everyone.
[SPEAKER_10]: Good evening.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes, for the end, I'll give you guys all a little opportunity to practice cheering on our wonderful Mustangs.
[SPEAKER_10]: But this evening, I am so happy to be here.
[SPEAKER_10]: I stand here as your proud superintendent congratulating this, the class of 2024.
[SPEAKER_10]: I start by saying thank you, as always, to your parents and your support systems, caregivers, relatives, friends, all of those that championed and stood behind you, pushing you forward.
[SPEAKER_10]: I want to personally acknowledge our principals, Ms.
[SPEAKER_10]: Cabral, Mr. Fallon, the wonderful assistant principal team, all the staff at Medford High School.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you for having a positive impact on this class, the class of 2024, and the staff of the Medford Public Schools that served you in the previous grades, both at elementary school level and the middle school level.
[SPEAKER_10]: So we are here today to celebrate you, the class of 2024.
[SPEAKER_10]: I want to open by saying that I received some feedback from some of the staff last week.
[SPEAKER_10]: I had time to talk with them while many of you were dancing and enjoying yourselves last week at the prom.
[SPEAKER_10]: And there was a recurring theme that really struck me.
[SPEAKER_10]: The staff of Medford High School kept saying, this is such a special class.
[SPEAKER_10]: This is a wonderful group of students.
[SPEAKER_10]: We're really going to miss them.
[SPEAKER_10]: I want you to know that you, the class of 2024, truly, truly made an impact.
[SPEAKER_10]: You touched the hearts of your staff, the staff of the school.
[SPEAKER_10]: And it was wonderful just seeing how everyone got along.
[SPEAKER_10]: how you guys supported one another, cheered one another on, whether it was back flips on the dance floor or trying new moves.
[SPEAKER_10]: I want you to know that you made a difference, this class of 2024.
[SPEAKER_10]: So yesterday I had the opportunity to go to the Curtis Tufts graduation, and I wanna share some of my remarks, because those remarks apply to you as well.
[SPEAKER_10]: You are at a crossroads, getting ready to start the next chapter of your life.
[SPEAKER_10]: As you think about the next chapter of your life, think about your future.
[SPEAKER_10]: Dream about your future.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I looked up the word dream.
[SPEAKER_10]: I said, let me look at the definition of it.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's a noun.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's a series of thoughts, images, feelings, or sensations occurring in a person's mind during sleep.
[SPEAKER_10]: a cherished aspiration, ambition, or ideal.
[SPEAKER_10]: As a verb, the verb dream means to indulge in daydreams or even fantasies about something that is greatly desired.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm encouraging all of you to dream big, not to dream small.
[SPEAKER_10]: Have high expectations for yourself.
[SPEAKER_10]: Today, here we are on this platform celebrating you.
[SPEAKER_10]: And today at Medford High School, there is something unusual happening.
[SPEAKER_10]: We have a valedictorian and a salutatorian that happen to be sisters.
[SPEAKER_10]: That doesn't happen often.
[SPEAKER_10]: They're twins, of course.
[SPEAKER_10]: So Oprah and Eleanor, I congratulate you on accomplishing something that doesn't happen often in a lifetime.
[SPEAKER_10]: I want all of you to know, especially as you dream, reach for the stars.
[SPEAKER_10]: Try to shoot for something that's higher than what you can actually attain.
[SPEAKER_10]: I know that I normally like to quote a poem, and I do have a poem by Langston Hughes, which is about dreams.
[SPEAKER_10]: But I also want you to know that I sat and I reflected on the word dream, and I thought about this acrostic poem.
[SPEAKER_10]: The D, dare to be the change.
[SPEAKER_10]: R, reach for the stars or something that is unattainable.
[SPEAKER_10]: E, excel in college, career, life, work, whatever it is that you're going to do.
[SPEAKER_10]: A, acknowledge your roots.
[SPEAKER_10]: Acknowledge where you come from.
[SPEAKER_10]: Do not forget that.
[SPEAKER_10]: And the M, make a positive difference.
[SPEAKER_10]: Make the world a better place.
[SPEAKER_10]: make Mustang Nation and Medford very proud of you.
[SPEAKER_10]: And so I do want to close and encourage each and every one of you to pursue your dreams.
[SPEAKER_10]: continue to work hard, continue to make a difference in the world.
[SPEAKER_10]: Remember that blue and white will forever run through your veins because you are a Mustang.
[SPEAKER_10]: Bring that Mustang spirit with you.
[SPEAKER_10]: You are a leader.
[SPEAKER_10]: You are kind.
[SPEAKER_10]: You are in front and not behind.
[SPEAKER_10]: You are on top and not the bottom.
[SPEAKER_10]: Here is a poem by Langston Hughes.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's called Dreams.
[SPEAKER_10]: Hold fast to dreams, for if dreams die, life is a broken winged bird that cannot fly.
[SPEAKER_10]: Hold fast to dreams, for when dreams go, life is a barren field frozen with snow.
[SPEAKER_10]: I want to ask Ms.
[SPEAKER_10]: Freitas Haley to come on up and join me.
[SPEAKER_10]: I want to say a special, special congratulations to this, the class of 2024.
[SPEAKER_10]: And in true Mustang fashion, when I say Medford, left side, you say Mustang, right side.
[SPEAKER_10]: One, two, three.
[SPEAKER_10]: Medford.
[SPEAKER_10]: Let's ask the audience, can we split you in half by the MHS side?
[SPEAKER_10]: One half will say Medford, and one half will say Mustangs.
[SPEAKER_10]: One, two, three, Medford.
[SPEAKER_10]: Medford.
[SPEAKER_10]: So when I say Mustang, you say pride.
[SPEAKER_10]: Mustang.
[SPEAKER_10]: Congratulations to the class of 2024.
[SPEAKER_09]: At this time, it's my pleasure to invite the top ranked career technical education student,
[SPEAKER_09]: To the podium, please, Mr. Matthew Harris.
[SPEAKER_08]: I don't know if I can compete with that level of enthusiasm, but I'll try my best.
[SPEAKER_08]: So before I begin, I'd like to say that I am incredibly honored and terrified to be up here today.
[SPEAKER_08]: There have been some really incredible speeches, especially you, Darren.
[SPEAKER_08]: That was awesome.
[SPEAKER_08]: The bar has been set very high, so high that I don't think my original plan of reading green eggs and ham to all of you is going to be enough.
[SPEAKER_08]: So instead, I'll try my backup plan, just telling a story.
[SPEAKER_08]: How does that sound?
[SPEAKER_08]: So during COVID,
[SPEAKER_08]: I discovered that I had a knack for coding.
[SPEAKER_08]: I was a little software nerd boy, so naturally, when it came time to choose a vocational shop, I chose programming and web development.
[SPEAKER_08]: And then my sophomore year rolled around, and suddenly, building robots seemed pretty cool.
[SPEAKER_08]: And it sure didn't help that robotics and engineering had an amazing new shop, and that half of my friends were in it.
[SPEAKER_08]: So every day, I would see the stuff that my friends would be making in robotics, and I'd think, oh, man, maybe I should have chosen robotics.
[SPEAKER_08]: Maybe I should jump ship.
[SPEAKER_08]: But then, at the same time, I'd think, oh, well, I do really like software, and I don't want to give up that opportunity.
[SPEAKER_08]: So for months and months, I would have this really delightful debate with myself, like every day,
[SPEAKER_08]: And what really frustrated me, as someone who is often very indecisive, was that these two fields, they felt like they were very similar.
[SPEAKER_08]: But at the same time, they were separate.
[SPEAKER_08]: And so that means I had to make a choice.
[SPEAKER_08]: Now, fast forward to today.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm graduating from programming and web development.
[SPEAKER_08]: So I'd like to think it's pretty clear that I didn't jump ship.
[SPEAKER_08]: But did I just tell my interest in robotics to sit this one out, maybe wait until college, or maybe the next life?
[SPEAKER_08]: No.
[SPEAKER_08]: So what did I do?
[SPEAKER_08]: Well, instead, I joined the robotics team.
[SPEAKER_08]: And as I got involved in building underwater robots, I realized that this was actually the perfect path for me.
[SPEAKER_08]: My experience on the robotics team has taught me a really valuable lesson, other than that building stuff underwater sucks.
[SPEAKER_08]: It's taught me that the intersection where two different fields meet is where life gets really interesting.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thanks to the support and flexibility of both Ms.
[SPEAKER_08]: Miller, my programming teacher, and Mr. Christie, wherever you are, our robotics teacher,
[SPEAKER_08]: I was able to bridge the gap between my interest in programming and robotics by spending my shop time writing code for these robots.
[SPEAKER_08]: And in doing so, I discovered how much I loved being right at that intersection.
[SPEAKER_08]: Some of the greatest work, inventions, and discoveries have been the results of people from distinct fields coming together.
[SPEAKER_08]: Think about all the different brains that went into building the phones we all have in our pockets right now, or all the different brains from the wide variety of fields that went into making the cars that we drive every day.
[SPEAKER_08]: And I know that the coolest inventions of the future would definitely be the results of distinct fields coming together in ways that we can't even imagine.
[SPEAKER_08]: And this brings me to something really valuable that I see in the Vogue.
[SPEAKER_08]: flexibility, and a willingness to embrace the intersections between different shops.
[SPEAKER_08]: I've seen really cool examples of this all the time.
[SPEAKER_08]: Think about the biodiesel project, a collaboration between biotech, automotive tech, metal fab, and even business, too.
[SPEAKER_08]: And without the flexibility of the VOC and its spirit of collaboration, my experience on the robotics team just would not have been possible.
[SPEAKER_08]: And so it feels a little weird offering advice to all of you.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm not 100 years old.
[SPEAKER_08]: I haven't figured life or the universe out.
[SPEAKER_08]: And even if I make it to 100, I don't think I'll have it figured out.
[SPEAKER_08]: But if I do, I'll let all of you know, of course.
[SPEAKER_08]: But speaking from my limited experience, what I will say is don't be afraid to embrace the intersection, to be that person that bridges the gap.
[SPEAKER_08]: It might feel weird or uncomfortable at first, but as I've said, life gets really interesting at the intersections.
[SPEAKER_08]: Embrace them.
[SPEAKER_08]: Maybe that means double majoring in college because you're in love with two different fields.
[SPEAKER_08]: Maybe it means becoming a shop teacher down the line because you're really passionate about your trade, but you're also passionate about teaching too.
[SPEAKER_08]: Or maybe it means doing something that I can't even imagine because nobody's even attempted it before.
[SPEAKER_08]: And what I've said doesn't have to just be limited to your career.
[SPEAKER_08]: There are many different intersections you can embrace.
[SPEAKER_08]: Maybe it's your racial, ethnic, gender identity, or maybe it's just where you live.
[SPEAKER_08]: Don't feel like you have to change your interests or who you are to fit neatly in a little box.
[SPEAKER_08]: Embrace being weird.
[SPEAKER_08]: Embrace being difficult.
[SPEAKER_08]: Embrace the intersections.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_05]: Offering the salutatory address as salutatorian of the class of 2024 is Eleanor Nicarra, who will be attending Harvard University in the fall.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thank you, Ms.
[SPEAKER_07]: Cabral, for the introduction and everything you do for the students of the school.
[SPEAKER_07]: Good evening, parents, teachers, esteemed guests, and of course, my fellow graduates.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'm honored to be speaking before you today as a part of the celebration of Medford High School's graduating class of 2024.
[SPEAKER_07]: I would like to begin with a moment of gratitude.
[SPEAKER_07]: On behalf of all the graduates here today, I extend a warm thank you to our superintendent, our principal and our vice principals, our guidance counselors, and all other administrators who work behind the scenes to keep the school running smoothly and to ensure the success of each student.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thank you to the parents and guardians present who support and believe in us even when we do not believe in ourselves.
[SPEAKER_07]: Last but certainly not least, thank you to the faculty members who work tirelessly before and after hours to provide us the education that every child dreams of.
[SPEAKER_07]: Your tenacity and dedication do not go unnoticed.
[SPEAKER_07]: Speaking of faculty, after I was assigned to write and perform this salutatory speech, I visited my physics teacher, Dr. Wadness, for insight.
[SPEAKER_07]: I asked him, what could I possibly say that would hopefully have an impact on the thousands of attendees here?
[SPEAKER_07]: He responded, teach them an important lesson.
[SPEAKER_07]: So I'm taking his advice literally.
[SPEAKER_07]: Brace yourselves for a minute of physics.
[SPEAKER_07]: A quark, spelled Q-U-A-R-K, is a simple elemental particle and the building block of all visible matter in the universe.
[SPEAKER_07]: The radius of a quark is smaller than 43 billion billionths of a centimeter, about a million times smaller than a grain of sand.
[SPEAKER_07]: Now what physicists do with these particles is they accelerate them to 99.999% the speed of light in huge 17-mile-long machines made of superconducting magnets called particle accelerators.
[SPEAKER_07]: You're probably wondering, what does this quark nonsense have to do with me?
[SPEAKER_07]: Truth be told, every one of us here acts as a particle.
[SPEAKER_07]: What I haven't told you about these quarks is that while they bounce around at amazing speeds, some, a very small percentage, happen to collide.
[SPEAKER_07]: United for a brief millisecond, they interact.
[SPEAKER_07]: Imagine two glass marbles smashing against each other.
[SPEAKER_07]: Now multiply that collision by 150, leaving us with 300 marbles, each of them representing one of us.
[SPEAKER_07]: Like these particles, we're all united here by chance.
[SPEAKER_07]: Several graduates have families like mine who immigrated across the globes in hopes of a better future.
[SPEAKER_07]: Many students have gone through the Medford public school system and followed their path here to Medford High School.
[SPEAKER_07]: Others moved from city to city and finally decided to settle in Medford, where they now proudly call home.
[SPEAKER_07]: Regardless of where we come from, we are united by our shared collisions within the walls of our school.
[SPEAKER_07]: We have experienced the highest of highs and the lowest of lows together.
[SPEAKER_07]: We forged connections as we bounced from class to class, bonding over the struggles of finding open bathrooms and having to layer up when walking through the overpass during the winter.
[SPEAKER_07]: We've made friends we'll never forget at the black lab tables in our science classes, and discovered a newfound love for playing ping pong in the senior caf.
[SPEAKER_07]: We have made memories that will last a lifetime at prom, homecoming, and formals, shimmying to Party in the USA and Mr. Brightside like our lives depended on it.
[SPEAKER_07]: But what happens after the collision?
[SPEAKER_07]: What happens after we clean out our lockers and we say goodbye to the teachers who have taught us all that we now know?
[SPEAKER_07]: What happens after we commit to college or start the job search or pack our suitcases for gap year travel?
[SPEAKER_07]: After we wave goodbye to our friends and fellow classmates, some of whom will move across the state, the country, or even the world at the end of the summer?
[SPEAKER_07]: After four years together?
[SPEAKER_07]: Four years, it sounds like a long time, but really, it's 5% of our lives.
[SPEAKER_07]: Comparable to the blink of an eye, to the time that particles interact before rebounding just as fast as they met, never to cross paths again.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yet, there is good news.
[SPEAKER_07]: The good news is that humans are made of quarks, but we do not have to act like them.
[SPEAKER_07]: After we disperse from Medford High, we will not disappear into the nothingness of the universe, and our relationships that we have made here do not only exist in the time vacuum that was high school.
[SPEAKER_07]: So take charge of your future courses.
[SPEAKER_07]: We all have power over our trajectories.
[SPEAKER_07]: Stay connected.
[SPEAKER_07]: Spend holidays together.
[SPEAKER_07]: Grab lunch at the tavern and an ice cream cone at Colleen's.
[SPEAKER_07]: put the many computers you carry in your pockets to use.
[SPEAKER_07]: And remember that each one of us here is only a phone call away.
[SPEAKER_07]: Graduates, make sure that the goodbyes you impart today are not forever, but temporary.
[SPEAKER_07]: Congratulations, graduates, and don't be a stranger.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_05]: At this time, please join me in welcoming the valedictorian of the class of 2024, Ms.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oprah Nakira.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oprah will be attending Harvard University in the fall.
[SPEAKER_07]: Which one are you?
[SPEAKER_07]: These four mere words form one of the most annoying questions to ask an identical twin.
[SPEAKER_07]: Second only to, can twins actually feel each other's pain?
[SPEAKER_07]: While the odds of being an identical twin are one in 200, the odds of guessing their identities correctly is exactly 100 times that.
[SPEAKER_07]: Despite these relatively good odds, people often hesitate to guess, whether it's out of respect, not wanting to be offensive, or simply because they do not wish to make a choice.
[SPEAKER_07]: Ironically enough, we, the Medford High School graduating class of 2024, are all twinning today.
[SPEAKER_07]: That's right, take a second look to your left and to your right, to your peers and to the classmates sitting next to you.
[SPEAKER_07]: To the people you have spent the last four, six, eight, 10, or even 12 years with.
[SPEAKER_07]: To the friends who have been with you through the thick and the thin and supported you through the highs and the lows.
[SPEAKER_07]: To the people who have guided you through countless decisions, like whether or not to break up with your boyfriend, what outfit to wear to the football game, and most importantly, which Quizlet to use for your homework assignment.
[SPEAKER_07]: While the answer to these decisions are up to interpretation, one thing's for sure.
[SPEAKER_07]: Life demands decisions.
[SPEAKER_07]: We make countless choices every single day, and these choices have helped form our unique identities.
[SPEAKER_07]: While we may not realize it, we have been asking ourselves which one since we were little.
[SPEAKER_07]: In the blink of an eye, which toys should I bring to show and tell, and which kids should I marry on the playground has quickly turned into which AP class should I take and which college should I commit to.
[SPEAKER_07]: As we transition into this new chapter of our lives, we are sure to be bombarded with a slew of choices we may be forced to make on our own, or if we are lucky, with a support system we have built around us.
[SPEAKER_07]: Unfortunately, unlike guessing which twin is which, the odds of making the right choice are not fixed at 50-50.
[SPEAKER_07]: Whether we are choosing a college major, a workplace, or a life partner, we will make some of the hardest choices we have ever made.
[SPEAKER_07]: There is, however, one choice that will always be the easiest to make, being the best versions of ourselves.
[SPEAKER_07]: As we make these decisions in the future, let us remember the core values like integrity, generosity, and compassion that characterize our graduating class.
[SPEAKER_07]: Let us remember the commitment to addressing climate change, social justice, and anti-violence campaigns, like walkouts for increased school safety, and speeches that advocate for equitable funding that our generation has spearheaded through social media and activism.
[SPEAKER_07]: Most importantly, let us remember that the sum of our decisions has the power to transform our future, not only for ourselves, but also for our younger siblings and for generations to come.
[SPEAKER_07]: Before I depart, I feel it is necessary to extend thanks to all of the esteemed faculty, family, and distinguished guests who have guided us through these past four years.
[SPEAKER_07]: Without you all, this rite of passage simply wouldn't be possible.
[SPEAKER_07]: I would like to thank my sister, Eleanor, for being my biggest motivator and the best prank partner I could ask for.
[SPEAKER_07]: My friends and family for their unwavering support and being the funniest people I will ever meet, and my family members and parents to whom I owe all of my success.
[SPEAKER_07]: Lastly, I would like to thank Medford High itself for the countless memories.
[SPEAKER_07]: Whether it's Dr. Wanus getting ruthlessly pied in the face,
[SPEAKER_07]: Mr. Brophy unknowingly sitting on his putty, or the iconic video of Mr. Cullen running through the doors of the third floor overpass, Medford High has imparted unto all of us countless memories we will cherish and that will connect us long after we leave its halls.
[SPEAKER_07]: As Taylor Swift once sang, it is the end of a decade, but the start of an age.
[SPEAKER_07]: to the Medford High School's graduating class of 2024, congratulations.
[SPEAKER_07]: Here's to our next chapter.
[SPEAKER_05]: And now, for the moment that we've been waiting for, the presentation of diplomas.
[SPEAKER_05]: Members of the school committee, I'm pleased to certify that the following students have fulfilled all the course requirements of Medford High School and Medford Vocational Technical High School.
[SPEAKER_05]: Graduates' names will be recited by the class of 2024 senior class advisors, Mr. Christopher Dello Russo and Mr. Ethan Pearlstein.
[SPEAKER_11]: Just give me a sign when to go.
[SPEAKER_11]: Good to go?
[SPEAKER_12]: Perfect.
[SPEAKER_12]: Matthew Sungjo Harris.
[SPEAKER_12]: Darren Garhong Truong.
[SPEAKER_12]: Eleanor Christina Nicarra.
[SPEAKER_12]: Oprah Christina, excuse me, Oprah Christine Nicarra.
[SPEAKER_12]: I tried it.
[SPEAKER_12]: Emma Adami.
[SPEAKER_12]: Tanha Alam.
[SPEAKER_12]: Santiago Alvarez.
[SPEAKER_12]: Jason James Anacone.
[SPEAKER_12]: Mariana Machado Aregues.
[SPEAKER_12]: Anthony Alexander Arellano.
[SPEAKER_12]: Katherine Keneally Berry.
[SPEAKER_02]: Magersyn Bazil.
[SPEAKER_12]: Michelle Christine Began.
[SPEAKER_12]: Isaiah Jeremiah Bell.
[SPEAKER_12]: Kenza Belula.
[SPEAKER_12]: Sonia Benapal.
[SPEAKER_12]: Zachary Joseph Bertocchi.
[SPEAKER_12]: Kendi Blaze.
[SPEAKER_12]: Antonio Brathwaite.
[SPEAKER_12]: Eric Adam Brown.
[SPEAKER_12]: Hannah Lorraine Brown.
[SPEAKER_12]: Elijah Justin Welto.
[SPEAKER_12]: Peyton Joseph Brzezinski.
[SPEAKER_12]: Samuel Buxton.
[SPEAKER_12]: Michael Stephen Cadet.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mel Consolves Calzarch Santos.
[SPEAKER_12]: Makayla Malloy DiPiccio Callahan.
[SPEAKER_12]: Aston Martin Colope.
[SPEAKER_12]: Evan Thomas Calvert.
[SPEAKER_12]: Clay Nicole Canavan.
[SPEAKER_12]: Rachel Olivia Carboni.
[SPEAKER_12]: Matthew Jason Carr.
[SPEAKER_12]: Anthony Michael Cardilano.
[SPEAKER_12]: Frank Dennis Amarico Caruccio.
[SPEAKER_12]: Kamili Carrera Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_12]: Luciana Chauchi.
[SPEAKER_12]: Nicholas Joseph Sarandola.
[SPEAKER_12]: J Anthony Caesar.
[SPEAKER_12]: Viva Lynn Chavitana.
[SPEAKER_12]: Johnny Charles.
[SPEAKER_12]: Ava Lee Chasteen.
[SPEAKER_12]: Nathan James Chevalier.
[SPEAKER_12]: Josiah Jermaine Clark.
[SPEAKER_12]: Tristan Antoine Shane Kogel Jean Baptiste.
[SPEAKER_12]: Emma Lena Zisk Cohen.
[SPEAKER_12]: Simon Medeiros Correa.
[SPEAKER_12]: Manuel Brandon Flores.
[SPEAKER_12]: Daniel Duke Cupertino.
[SPEAKER_12]: Sophia Rose D'Amelio.
[SPEAKER_12]: Sandro Davida.
[SPEAKER_12]: Joseph Anthony D'Arazio.
[SPEAKER_12]: Gustavo Medeiros Lopez de Concesao.
[SPEAKER_12]: Emily Matos De Silva.
[SPEAKER_02]: Gabriel Arthur Costa De Silva.
[SPEAKER_12]: Nathalie Daranuwat.
[SPEAKER_12]: Abe Jett Davidson.
[SPEAKER_12]: Lorelei Cheyenne Davis.
[SPEAKER_12]: Mia Olivia Davis.
[SPEAKER_12]: Isabella Leigh DeAngelis Donahue.
[SPEAKER_12]: Brian Olivera Deesa.
[SPEAKER_12]: Stanley Desome.
[SPEAKER_12]: Kamili Pierce D'Souza.
[SPEAKER_12]: Tenzin Dessel.
[SPEAKER_12]: Anthony Michael DeFranzo.
[SPEAKER_12]: Brian Nicholas DiPlacido.
[SPEAKER_12]: Skyla Marie DiRienzo.
[SPEAKER_12]: Andre Ellis Daniel Francis Doherty.
[SPEAKER_12]: Anna Clara Flaherty Dos Santos.
[SPEAKER_12]: Arthur Rodriguez Dos Santos.
[SPEAKER_12]: Fabio Enrique Dos Santos.
[SPEAKER_12]: Graziella Dos Santos.
[SPEAKER_12]: Kyle Raymond Douglas.
[SPEAKER_12]: Serge Edouard Jr.
[SPEAKER_12]: Mira Soleil Paradiso Eforo.
[SPEAKER_12]: Liza Castillo.
[SPEAKER_12]: Joyce Victoria Cancio Espinoza.
[SPEAKER_12]: Stevens Exeter.
[SPEAKER_12]: Jack Stanley Willard Falco.
[SPEAKER_02]: Christopher John Farrell.
[SPEAKER_12]: Jason Robert Fedocchi.
[SPEAKER_12]: Aviana Kristen Fonseca.
[SPEAKER_12]: Ava Raquel Franny.
[SPEAKER_12]: Gage Edward Gagne.
[SPEAKER_12]: Gavin Peter Gagney.
[SPEAKER_12]: Anderson Antonio Garcia Castellanos.
[SPEAKER_12]: Shreya Gochin.
[SPEAKER_12]: Destiny Laura Goggin.
[SPEAKER_12]: Chloe Evangelina Gello.
[SPEAKER_12]: Noah Ewan Dove Gibson.
[SPEAKER_12]: Saheeb Singh Gill.
[SPEAKER_12]: Alexander James Jogas.
[SPEAKER_12]: Maria Eduarda Tetsera Gomes.
[SPEAKER_12]: William Noel Graham.
[SPEAKER_12]: Jiford Garia.
[SPEAKER_12]: Julia Claire Hallam Baker.
[SPEAKER_02]: Alex Hamel.
[SPEAKER_12]: Stella Wynn Heinegg.
[SPEAKER_12]: Diego Esteban Hernandez Castillo.
[SPEAKER_12]: Arianna Ahern Holleen.
[SPEAKER_12]: Nathaniel Keith Hopper.
[SPEAKER_12]: Jared Michael Howe.
[SPEAKER_12]: Bianca Q. Huang.
[SPEAKER_12]: Katrina Huynh.
[SPEAKER_12]: Emily Eileen Ivy.
[SPEAKER_12]: Adrian Conrad Jackson.
[SPEAKER_12]: Muhammad Noor Jamaluddin.
[SPEAKER_12]: Saad Ullah Jan.
[SPEAKER_12]: Nayab Javed.
[SPEAKER_12]: Brian Spencer Jean.
[SPEAKER_12]: Danelle Erica June Alon.
[SPEAKER_12]: Anaya Jeanette Johnson-Oseas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Christy Adriana Jordan.
[SPEAKER_12]: Bobby Isabella Kalau.
[SPEAKER_12]: Islambek Karagulov.
[SPEAKER_12]: Maximillian Chund Kural.
[SPEAKER_12]: Patrick Thomas Keene.
[SPEAKER_12]: William Thomas Kelly.
[SPEAKER_12]: Abby Rose Kelly.
[SPEAKER_12]: Ron Sampaio Kennedy.
[SPEAKER_12]: Emma Claire Kiley.
[SPEAKER_12]: Julia Kathleen Fargo.
[SPEAKER_12]: Gianna Marie Camorni.
[SPEAKER_12]: Sekou George Kouyate.
[SPEAKER_12]: Kaylee Bridgette Laidlaw.
[SPEAKER_12]: Karnessa Lajoie.
[SPEAKER_12]: Christian Charles Langer.
[SPEAKER_12]: Molly Claire Lappin.
[SPEAKER_12]: Danny Lay.
[SPEAKER_12]: Talia Borges-Leal.
[SPEAKER_12]: Brady Joseph Leet.
[SPEAKER_12]: John Francis Leet.
[SPEAKER_12]: Olivia Ariana Leet.
[SPEAKER_12]: Maria Victoria Lima Costa.
[SPEAKER_12]: John Joseph Lombardo.
[SPEAKER_12]: Lorkins Lubernot.
[SPEAKER_12]: Maria Clara Martins Lopes.
[SPEAKER_12]: Helen Crane Lucas Cormack John Lynch
[SPEAKER_04]: Not at all.
[SPEAKER_04]: So you are Coral Korea Sharks.
[SPEAKER_02]: Coral Correa Jobs.
[SPEAKER_02]: Taya Isabelle Farinas Cruz.
[SPEAKER_02]: Riley Jane Mulvihill.
[SPEAKER_02]: Erdenandes Morais Macedo Jr.
[SPEAKER_02]: Julia Rose Marr.
[SPEAKER_02]: Riley Mary Marr.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dakota Fallon Mahoney.
[SPEAKER_02]: Karsten Daniel Mangan.
[SPEAKER_02]: Joseph Pierce Mangoni Neha Durgesh Mankakar Derek James Marino
[SPEAKER_02]: Anthony Michael Martino.
[SPEAKER_02]: Johnny Thomas Mastracola.
[SPEAKER_02]: Grace Margaret Mastromatteo.
[SPEAKER_02]: Miranda Jeanette Mattson.
[SPEAKER_02]: Paul Matulonis.
[SPEAKER_02]: Catherine Anne McDade.
[SPEAKER_02]: Donald James D.J.
[SPEAKER_02]: McDonough Ainsley Marie McInnis Jasper Wyman McIntyre
[SPEAKER_02]: Ethan Avery McKnight.
[SPEAKER_02]: Daniela Andrea Mejia Aguiar.
[SPEAKER_02]: Myra Juliana Mejia Aguiar.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maria Eduardo Mendonca de Oliveira.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dario Alexis Mendoza.
[SPEAKER_02]: Kiara Marie Messersmith.
[SPEAKER_02]: Melvin Mondesir.
[SPEAKER_02]: Gianna Nicole Mongelo.
[SPEAKER_02]: Brian James Moore.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ana Sofia Silva Merida.
[SPEAKER_02]: Madeline Veronica Morris.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mesa Fadi Najjar.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ruth Juliette Nakitende.
[SPEAKER_02]: Samuel Nazir.
[SPEAKER_12]: Nicole Ashley Newby.
[SPEAKER_02]: Amy I. Nguyen.
[SPEAKER_02]: Kim Bin Nguyen.
[SPEAKER_02]: Rosalie Elena Nicholas.
[SPEAKER_02]: John Daniel Nocella.
[SPEAKER_02]: Michael Vincent Norton.
[SPEAKER_12]: Theodore Andrew Norton.
[SPEAKER_02]: Isabella Karen O'Brien.
[SPEAKER_12]: Connor E. O'Leary.
[SPEAKER_02]: Jackson Thomas Olander.
[SPEAKER_02]: Samir Olivera Dos Reis.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dominic Francis Ortiz.
[SPEAKER_02]: Joao Luiz Goncalves Punch Paizanch.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mark Holden Safransky Parr.
[SPEAKER_02]: Shubh Baharat Kumar Patel Sophia Yvonne Perez-Reyes Kaysen Donald-Pierre
[SPEAKER_02]: Gnarly Almica Pier.
[SPEAKER_12]: Reina Pieribia.
[SPEAKER_02]: Lira Elizabeth Polcaro.
[SPEAKER_02]: Austin Dennis Price.
[SPEAKER_02]: Malcolm Tobin Price.
[SPEAKER_12]: Anthony John Pirifori.
[SPEAKER_02]: Lindsey Helena Quinn.
[SPEAKER_02]: Matthew Peter Randazzo.
[SPEAKER_02]: Kenson Raymond.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sierra Bridget Riley.
[SPEAKER_02]: Victoria Kathleen Remick.
[SPEAKER_02]: Morgan Mara Reynolds.
[SPEAKER_02]: Roman Nadenko Rice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Joseph Vincent Riggio.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tenzin Rinchin.
[SPEAKER_02]: Vincent Xavier Roach.
[SPEAKER_02]: Julia Pereira Rosa.
[SPEAKER_02]: Megan Nathania Ross.
[SPEAKER_02]: Christopher Frederick Rothermel.
[SPEAKER_02]: Angus Everett Rotremel.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sephora Emeral Rubin.
[SPEAKER_02]: Terrence Van Russell.
[SPEAKER_02]: Vinay Sagar.
[SPEAKER_02]: Bavia Salhi.
[SPEAKER_02]: Syed Steve Sanin.
[SPEAKER_02]: Benjamin Amaral Santana.
[SPEAKER_12]: Leonid Sarman.
[SPEAKER_02]: Benjamin Alexander Sayers.
[SPEAKER_02]: Cameron Sean Scali.
[SPEAKER_02]: Juliana Joy Scaramuzo.
[SPEAKER_02]: Jolina Sophia Scania.
[SPEAKER_12]: Joey Artemio Simone.
[SPEAKER_02]: Joshua Robert Scully.
[SPEAKER_02]: Alexander Hope Senonho Desiderio Deuce Sesa Rakshitha Shankar Ganesh
[SPEAKER_02]: Rachel Nicholson Shannon.
[SPEAKER_02]: Anya Grace Sheehan.
[SPEAKER_02]: Lily Elizabeth Sheehan.
[SPEAKER_02]: Reese Deborah Sherblom.
[SPEAKER_02]: Xiong He Xing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Riz Shressa.
[SPEAKER_02]: Evelyn Bella Shumway.
[SPEAKER_02]: Marci Reyes Lopes Caraviello Simonini.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ryan Michael Slow.
[SPEAKER_12]: Alastair Pasquale Smith.
[SPEAKER_12]: Emma Louise Smith.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maureen Solter Daza.
[SPEAKER_02]: Francisco Emmanuel Soto-Ortiz.
[SPEAKER_02]: Jacob Frederick Charles Steckrell.
[SPEAKER_02]: Rye Arthur Stefani.
[SPEAKER_02]: Matthew Crowling Sterianos.
[SPEAKER_12]: Juliana Rose Staridi.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ava Angelina Stalker.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dante Mark Suchecki.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sophia Ryan Sunwoo.
[SPEAKER_12]: Elena Gabriela Raffaele Szymanski Tyler George Taddea
[SPEAKER_02]: Sosna Negusi Takelli.
[SPEAKER_02]: Kevin Munoz Tavares.
[SPEAKER_02]: Jason Leonard Techa.
[SPEAKER_02]: Kenneth David Thompson Rodriguez.
[SPEAKER_02]: Avery Alexander Toddfeld.
[SPEAKER_02]: Victoria Silva Tolomeo.
[SPEAKER_02]: Vasilios Danny Tufis.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nathan Conrad Toll.
[SPEAKER_02]: Victoria Vanan Tran.
[SPEAKER_02]: Benjamin Peter Tranga.
[SPEAKER_02]: Kaitlin Sandy Trong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maria Rafaela Saknis.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ivan Armando Vargas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ellis Loper Vasquez.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ahalia Freya Venukrishnan.
[SPEAKER_02]: Louise Eduardo Viana Barbosa.
[SPEAKER_02]: Violet Michaela Veruso.
[SPEAKER_02]: Allison Marie Walsh Riley Kanese Walsh
[SPEAKER_02]: William Thomas Waple.
[SPEAKER_02]: Jacob Paul Wright.
[SPEAKER_09]: Adrian Young Wu.
[SPEAKER_04]: I love that kid.
[SPEAKER_02]: Aiden Tianze Shu Duran.
[SPEAKER_02]: Noah Daniel Urasco.
[SPEAKER_02]: Anna Clara Lopes Zaninetti.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Class of 2024, please stand.
[SPEAKER_05]: At this time, please turn and face your family, friends, and greatest supporters.
[SPEAKER_05]: Please move.
[SPEAKER_05]: Please move your tassel from right to left.
[SPEAKER_05]: Class of 2024, congratulations.
[SPEAKER_05]: You are now graduates and alumni of Medford High School.
[SPEAKER_05]: Congratulations, class of 2024.
[SPEAKER_04]: but you need to take your stands and equipment and wheel it over to the trailer so you can load up first, then you can go, okay?