You won the Powerball!
That's awesome!
It's so weird though.
My numbers are letters.
What?
Hi girls, come on in.
Oh, hi.
We're from the high school and we have a couple questions about the pool.
Yeah, actually my dad was wondering about the open swim.
So yeah, our open swim hours are 7 to 10 a.m.
in the morning and 7.30 to 9 p.m.
at night Monday through Friday.
And then on Saturday, we're doing 8 to 2.30, and we're closed on Sundays.
Do you have any lessons for little kids?
As a matter of fact, our program is starting on January 16th in a couple of weeks, and it's from 8 to 12 on Saturdays, and it's for eight weeks long.
Are you interested?
Yeah, I want to do that.
How do we sign up?
You can go to the community school's office.
It's open Mondays and Tuesdays, 9 to 3, and Mondays and Thursdays, 7 to 10, and then on Saturdays from 8 to 3.
I don't think there's any benefits of swimming though.
Are you kidding me?
There's tons!
There's tons of benefits of swimming.
Come on, I'll show you.
Swimming improves the entire physique of your body and it increases circulation.
And it builds up your endurance.
What if you're really clumsy and have sports injuries?
We use swimming as therapy for all types of sport injuries.
What are some of the other benefits for swimming?
Well, it's a great cardiovascular workout and it helps you control and maintain a healthy weight.
Do you have any information about the program?
Of course.
Follow me back into my office and I'll give you an informational flyer.
Here you guys go.
For each of you.
Thank you so much.
This is awesome.
I'm so excited.
You too.
Hi, I'm Jocelyn McCarthy with the Muston Report.
I'm here with Mr. Ward from the Carpentry class.
Can you tell me a little bit about your project you guys are working on?
Yes, the project that we are working on now is bookcases for classrooms around Boston.
We were actually approached by an organization called Boston Cares about two months ago.
about cutting parts for projects that they have.
And we actually are forming a partnership with them and the vocational school.
And this particular project are bookcases that will be assembled by a community service project on Martin Luther King Day at the Boston Latin School.
And so they had the materials delivered, and we did all of the prepping and all of the cutting of the materials.
And they're actually going to come pick them up tomorrow and bring them to the Boston Latin School.
Do you know how many you made?
We had to make 50.
And we actually started the project yesterday, cutting it out.
And we finished it.
No, we started two days ago.
And we finished it yesterday.
And they're picking them up on Friday.
Mr. Ward, do you have any other projects you'll be working on?
Yes, as a matter of fact, the biggest project we'll be working on for Boston Cares is their toddler bed program that they have where, again, it's a community service project where
companies send their employees and they come and volunteer to sand, assemble, paint beds and they'll do 50 to 75 beds at one time and then those beds are delivered to homeless shelters around Boston and they give them to families for their children to sleep in.
And that was the program that they approached us for to help them with.
And so when they come to pick up the bookcases, they're actually going to deliver us the parts of the bed.
And then we are going to build 50 beds.
We're forming a partnership to build 500 beds in one year.
And we're going to be building 50, and on March 9,
A company from Bill Ricka is going to come to our cabinet shop.
Boston Cares is going to bring all of their materials and they're going to take the beds that we are building and assemble them here in our shop.
And our SkillsUSA program is going to volunteer as part of their community service to help on that day.
as well as some of the carpenters and the construction craft laborers helping people to teach them how to assemble them.
Because these are just volunteers that come.
They may have never done anything like this before.
So we're going to help them assemble and paint them and get them completed because they try to build 50 beds in four hours.
So it's going to be a lot of fun and we're looking forward to it.
That's awesome.
Thank you.
money money