Hello everybody, this is the Medford Historical Commission. Today is Monday, October 7th. It is 703. I'm going to call the meeting to order. Oh, I just realized. Commissioners, if everybody could relabel themselves. Oh, here's Ed. Oh, change of plans.
See? One second, everybody. Thanks. Hi, Ed.
All right, let me get started with our little phrase here to get going with the meeting. So again, Medford Historical Commission, today is Monday, October 7th. Pursuant to Chapter 20 of the Acts of 2021, this meeting of the City of Medford Historical Commission will be conducted via remote means.
Members of the public who wish to access the meeting may do so by using the Zoom link provided for in the agenda. No in-person attendance of members of the public will be permitted. Public participation in any public hearing during this meeting shall be by remote means only. Ed, are you there? I'm just making sure. Ed, can you hear me?
I can, but I'm trying to get myself up. I'm having... No problem. As long as you can hear us and we can hear you. No, don't fret about your camera for the time being. Okay, sure. Okay, thanks. Okay, so up first tonight is 110 Brooke Street. We're going to have a preferably preserved hearing. And at this point, Ryan, I'm going to turn the meeting over to you, and I'm going to recuse myself from this case.
And you guys are good because you have Eleni, Peter and Ed. Okay, I'm going to shut my camera off, mute myself and you can text me when it's ready to come back. Great. Okay, thanks.
Just to recap for the general public, the Historical Commission had a meeting last month where we determined 110 Brooks Street to be historically significant. We placed up on the Medford Historical Commission website under the news section, the MHC Form B and our letter that describes why the building was found to be significant.
This is the second part of the demolition delay process where we determine whether or not the building is preferably preserved. So we ask that the public provide comments to the commission if you wish to speak. There will be a
about a five minute time allocated to persons wishing to speak for or against the project when I open up the public comment period and if you could before speaking just raise your hand and we'll call on you and if you could before you speak just your name and address for the record okay.
But we'll start off this process with the commissioner's comments. And tonight we're determining preferably preserved status, which according to the bylaws, chapter 48, section 77, preferably preserved significant building means any significant building as to which the commission determines as provided in subsections 48-78G, that it is in the public interest to be preserved and rehabilitated rather than demolished.
So we are looking tonight to hear comments on the integrity of the building, everything short of the condition of the building, meaning the actual physical structural condition that is a purview of the building department. We don't hear that portion of the
structure it's in his purview to order buildings down if structural issues are a cause or we're hearing about the historic persons or people or activities at this particular building or what we are most interested in or general comments from the neighbors and the community as to whether or not the building should be found preferably preserved and preserved and rehabilitated rather than demolished and
And this is a case of partial demolition. So this property, as we mentioned in last month, should have been flagged by the building department. But unfortunately, it fell by the radar. And we're reviewing this case following the demolition that took place. But the commissioners in cases like this, as in all cases, we determine
the status based on how the building lies, but also what the building was prior to the demolition that took place. So you guys can see on the MHC inventory form, if you look that up on our website, what the building's condition was. We also have a picture posted on our website.
commissioners does anybody want to start off with a motion and that will kick start discussion and then we will go from there and then after the public comment period we'll finish up with the vote and and take steps accordingly. I'll make a motion to find
Uh, this building, uh, preferably preserved. Sorry, I forgot the address. Uh, 110 Brooks Street perfectly preserved. Okay. In a 2nd, I'll 2nd. Great, thank you. Uh, Peter, do you want to start with a discussion and we'll I'll come to a Lenny and then the rest of us will. Comment to her.
As in the finding of significance, although the house has been denuded of its siding and windows, I feel like there is still extant detail, the front porch in particular, the
attic window has some nice detail. And I feel like the overall mass and, uh, uh, of the building is still intact and could be brought back. I know that previously the original siding had been covered with, uh, vinyl and probably windows replaced anyway. So, um,
Although it looks like it's been stripped, which it has from the outside, I still feel like the building has a majority of its integrity intact. And I don't believe further demolition is happening, or at least from the drawings I saw that proposed, I knew they were going to tear off the rear L.
which I think was a later edition anyway. Yeah, so I feel like this house is a good candidate. Similar homes to this in the neighborhood, we did find preferably preserved. That's where I'm coming down on this for now. Thanks. Great. Lenny? Yeah, I agree with Peter.
I think the details that sort of are worth preserving for this building is the attic window and then the columns on the front, sort of like a pattern with the two columns in the front and the back, I think is something worth keeping. And I do also agree with the removal of that rear addition. I think that adds to the quality of the building and the design and sort of restoring it back to what it used to look like.
Yeah, I mean, I think, I mean, I pretty much agree with Peter and, you know, I'm ready to pass it along to Ed. Great. Thank you. Ed, comments? Again, given the history of the work on the building, given what we've seen of the history in terms of what was removed,
And the intent of basically, this is really a restoration rather than a demolition, I think, yes, it should be preserved, but I think it hopefully will be a short proceeding. Great, thank you. All right, we're gonna
open it up to public comments. I'd like to ask the homeowners if they'd like to make any sort of statement to start with that, and then we'll go with those against the project, those for the project. And if you would just raise your hand, I'll recognize you as we go along. And if I don't see anybody else, then we'll close the public comments and go from there. Homeowners, Adriana?
Hi, so I'm Andreana and I am one of the homeowners along with my husband Chris and our daughter Lucia. We hope that we can work with the historic commission in a forward motion to restore this house to
a beautiful home and true to its historic value. The design as we proposed is pretty much in keeping with the original design we feel. Upon removing those windows when we were
demoing that home, we actually found that the original window sizes were much larger, and I have selected windows accordingly to ensure that we're in keeping with the original scale of the windows and whatnot, but we're also open to keeping similar columns and such.
We're just hoping that we can move forward as quickly as possible to, uh, you know, avoid any other financial, uh, burdens with this project. So we look forward to, um, moving on from here. Great. Thanks. Um, Chris, anything to add while you're can't hear you.
He's with my daughter upstairs. I apologize. I just wanted to make sure that he, if he had something to add, I'd be happy to hear him out, but that's okay. Chris, do you have anything to add?
Yes, the only thing I was actually going to. Sorry, apologies. I was trying to do ear buds and clearly technology is not working with me and I'm sitting here with my 5 year old daughter, which. Honestly, I was so happy for this meeting just to have something easier to do this evening than trying to get a 5 year old to not hop in front of the screen while I'm on it. But I, I do appreciate the fact that. That the historic society has been moving so quickly throughout.
This process everyone has been extremely accommodating to us in the previous meeting. And as my wife had said, we are keeping, we are keeping the overall integrity of the building as it is there. I believe.
Ryan, you said that at the beginning of the meeting, that it didn't look like there was any new demo that was planned. That is 100% accurate. We are not tearing down the building. We've had no intention of tearing down the building. One of the reasons that we actually were looking towards moving into this neighborhood, aside from the fact that we thought it would be a great place to raise our family, was how grand this building looked. And our overall intent is to be able to restore this house to the best of our ability.
And just if we're able to do it, you know, clearly, well, we have the funding to be able to do it. So as quickly as we can go through this process, and we're looking forward to working with you throughout it. Thank you. All right, public comments from anybody else at the meeting, if you just want to raise your hand, I'm happy to acknowledge you, Susan, let's start with you. I just need your name and address for the record.
And you've got to unmute yourself. Hold on. Teresa. Yes, I sent them a message. Hi, Susan. I was going to say, can you make me co-host because I can just.
Are we on? Yes, you are. Great. You need to say who you are. I am Yehudi Weiner at 49 Brook Street. This is Susan Weiner, my beloved wife. And we are not so close to that threat of demolition or of the renovation of the property, but we walk and we are very much part of the neighborhood. The building, in my opinion,
And I'm not an architect, I'm a composer of music, but I've lived with architects. And I must say what my closest friend of the last 10-15 years was Harry Cobb of New York, whom all of you know well, I'm sure, in the architectural realm.
The building has such beautiful stature. It sits so handsomely right there on the street. It's the last of the large buildings on that side of the street. There are other very attractive domiciles, but that building has a kind of monumental presence, which at the same time, while it's monumental, is not pretentious.
And having cleared the property, we see that there's enormous potential for building there, for grooming the house. And of course, we don't know the interior of the house. But I assume with a conscientious, and I would say creative architect, that wonderful things will take place. Great. Anything else?
I appreciate your comments. Thank you. Wendy. Hi, thank you, Reverend Wendy Miller Olopade. I'm the resident of the property right across the street from 110. I live at 105 Brooks, which is owned by the Congregational Church of West Medford. I happen to have the benefit of living in this beautiful neighborhood because of my position as the pastor of that church.
And I just want to affirm my appreciation for the work that's already been done. Sorry for my weird camera position here. I'm on the move. I just want to celebrate, you know, the care and commitment that the commission is putting into this. But I do want to encourage you to move promptly because I am tired of looking.
looking at that poor house all torn apart. It is a beautiful neighborhood and I have no objections at all to moving forward with the plan that our new neighbors have proposed. Great. Thank you. Heather and John? You're going to unmute yourself? Hold on, I'll do it. Yeah.
Okay. I certainly echo Wendy's comments. And I would just add that this has actually been an ordeal that's been going on for several years as we watched the house sort of become more overgrown, look more and more desolate, lots of negative stuff going on. And actually removing all the aluminum siding and so forth,
actually improved the look of the house, but we're getting a little tired of looking at the sheeting, and I would just urge the commission, do everything you can. Hold on, John. You got muted. Everything you can.
I'm just, as I was saying, I would just urge you to do everything you can to get this project moving forward as quickly as possible. And I think I speak for all the neighbors when I say that. And Heather, my wife, would like to say something. You've never known me not to rhyme, right? Just a quick point. What is your address? Just so that I know. 102 Brooks. 102 Brooks. Great. Yes.
I would just like to comment that this is a house that's been in trouble for over 40 years, that this young couple has come into the neighborhood and made every effort to connect with the neighbors, including joining our current rat project, which is not exactly the kind of thing that I'm sure they have time for at this point.
So they have reached out not only in terms of what they need to do, but they have reached out to assist and become part of the neighborhood in terms of other projects that we have going on as neighbors. So again, we've seen the pictures, we've seen the 40 years of history, all of the neighbors that are up here tonight, we have all been in communication with each other, and we support
the Kardashians and the plans that they have. And we'd like to see them in by Christmas, but that's getting to be a little tricky. Thank you. Monique. Name and address for the record. I'll try again, Monique Doherty.
Oh, there you are. Hello. Oh, one sec. We can hear you and you're speaking.
So Adriana and Christopher, Chris, welcome to the neighborhood. I'm so glad to see something being done with that beautiful architecture. I have seen the inside and there are so many gems in that building. And I appreciate all the efforts you're making to make sure that we have an understanding of what your plans are. So thank you. I hope we can get this moving for you.
and get you into the house. So welcome to the neighborhood. Monica, what is your address just so I can... We are across the street, diagonally across the street. Sorry about that. 113 Brook Street. Great. Perfect. Anything else? No, thank you. Thank you. You're welcome. Any other public comments?
Yes, I would like to say something. Sure, Judith, name and address for the record. It's 124 Brook Street. And Judith Watkinson, as you can see.
So I just want to give our support as well for the family. Sorry, Kadachi is it? I'm sorry if I'm not saying it properly. We have been living in the street and the house has been, quite honestly, an eyesore for so long. I just feel very, very
sad that things are being held up when somebody is obviously wanting to do a great job and restore it to something really beautiful. So we just want to express our support for them. And hopefully, we can move forward as quickly as possible on their behalf. Great. Great. Anything else? That's it. Thank you. Great. Thank you. Any other public comments?
All right. Seeing none, I'll close public comments and we'll go to the commissioners for final thoughts. Any further thoughts on the matter? Any further discussion on the building? Otherwise, I'll do a roll call vote. Motion was made by Peter Miller to find the building significant, seconded by Eleni.
All right, hearing no opposition, I'll do a roll call vote. A yes vote for that motion will invoke the up to 18 month demo delay, during which time we would send the plans to the subcommittee who would review them and ask for any architectural changes, and then they would come back for approval for the commission. A no vote would allow them to move forward with the project as it stands, as it exists
Now with the building permit, is that understood by all the commissioners? Okay. Roll call vote, starting with Peter. Yes. And Eleni. Yes. And Ed. Yes, with the hope this will not be an 18-month case. Great. So motion passes three to zero.
So what we will do is we will file our letter and then we will immediately send the project to the subcommittee that's Doug and Peter and.
Are you frozen? So we'll grab one of the commissioners and then we will review the project. If there's any architectural changes, we'll set up a time via Zoom to meet with you guys. And then we have a meeting planned for the second week of November, I believe. So our hope is that we would get you back
But if the architectural plans can be changed quickly enough, we may even be able to do it at the end of this month. I don't think we need it, but there may be an opportunity to just finish up and release the project at the end of the month if all those very minimal architectural changes that I think the commission will ask for can be taken care of. Does that make sense? Yeah.
So we will summarize that in our letter, and I'll send out something. I just have to make sure I work with Jen tomorrow morning to get that filed with the clerk's office. And then from there, I'll confer with the three commissioner subcommittee, and then we'll set up a Zoom meeting with the homeowners. OK? Wonderful. Thank you so much. Thanks. Jennifer Keenan, are you?
On this meeting still, if not, I'll text it. I'm going to wait for Jen to come back. In the meantime, we can start our discussion of the next agenda item, which is the determination of significance for the CPC project for City Hall. So that's Teresa.
Hello. Um, so I sent out earlier, uh, to all the commissioners, the MHC inventory form for city hall. I believe Teresa wants to talk to us about what those projects are that are being planned for the building. Um, I think that those will have an impact on the project. So. Hello, good evening, everybody. I'm the community preservation act manager for the city of Medford.
We have an application before us from the facilities department at City Hall to do some upgrades to the bathroom. They're using the criteria of historic preservation as the building we feel is historically significant. So tonight, as part of the funding, we would require a determination of significance, a favorable
A determinant of significance from the local historical commission to be used in our consideration of the application. So, tonight, I'm here to ask this body to please consider city hall to be a building of significance. And I'm happy to answer any questions. I will stop talking.
So I have a question. So is the plan to, it's probably a combination of ADA, MAS 521 CMR upgrades, which is all handicap accessibility, but also some reconfiguration of the bathrooms to probably optimize them. But the plan is to kind of preserve and maintain all the ornate finishes within as best as possible. As much as possible. There have been some
I wouldn't say poor renovations done, but haphazard perhaps might be the better term from what they originally were to where they are now for us to at least have an handicapped accessible stall. However, it does not meet requirements from the ADA. This is the first phase of what we hope to see as a multiple phase project where we would first make those ADA improvements to the public facilities.
And then in a perhaps a later year, they would that's whenever reconfiguration each back.
those type of upgrades would be made. Ryan, looks like you have a question. I do. Yeah. So it's going to roll into the right next logical question, which is what has the city done for an assessment on the entire building, including a space needs assessment for all the departments and various upgrades, you know, the exterior envelope? I know we went through a series of restorations, but if there's a complete plan somewhere that the city is referencing,
great, but if there's not, perhaps now would be an optimal time. For example, I can see maintaining the historic integrity of some of the bathrooms, maybe perhaps on the most public floors, but then there's an opportunity to certainly renovate other spaces in the building to consolidate those poor, quote unquote, poor renovations into something that's a little bit more spectacular for the inhabitants of City Hall, right? So the buildings are, is well used and we wanna make sure that it's,
up to par so i'm just curious if there's an assessment on those spaces or even just like for example an assessment on all the public spaces you know and all the needs for accessibility etc i know you guys are doing something with the elevator as well so i'm sure there's something but yes um to the best of my knowledge which i'm i'm
I tried to be involved with everything, but I don't know everything. To the best of my knowledge, I don't believe a conditions assessment or a feasibility study or just an assessment in general of City Hall has happened. About 18 months ago, I think it was, is when we hired the first facilities director for the city.
So that could be a project that could be happening that I'm just not aware of. However, as the Facilities Director is the one applying for this funding to upgrade the bathrooms, I'm sure he would have mentioned that. So I don't want to say no, but I believe the answer is no, an assessment has not been done. We have looked at individual properties across the city. A conversation about the Curtis Tufts School comes to mind, trying to look at an assessment for that building.
But yes, unfortunately, to the best of my knowledge, I believe the answer is no. That has not happened yet. That could be something the CTA could consider.
Yeah, I think our, for me, for me, the, my, and I'm sure maybe Peter might chime in and Doug, if he were here, and he eventually will chime in through the CPC. I think 1 of the things that we will ask for as part of this is funding. The work is taking a step.
backwards and at least assessing the entire building. I know there's been various things been done to assess the envelope and assess the roof structure because there's the
I wanna say satellites, it's not satellites. The solar panels are on top of the roof. So, you know, I know various things have been done, but I think a comprehend, you know, just like every other building that we look at, like the cemetery complex or the fire stations, I think this building really deserves a complex view headed by an architectural team that's gonna not just look at the bathrooms, but gonna give the city an assessment of all the projects that need to be done. Good time for all the departments to chime in and figure out what they need for space and,
if there's any reconfiguration, and then give a dollar amount to not just the CPC, but the entire city, knowing what the taxpayers are going to pay, and then prioritize, right? So if the bathrooms are the most important thing that needs to be done right here and now, then great. But at least they have the plan then to back it up and know what also is coming. Yeah, almost like a master plan. Yep. Yes. I would say that's an incredibly fair point.
kind of upset that perhaps I didn't think of that first. So thank you, Ryan. But that's something I can absolutely bring back. And we could even make that a condition of our funding is that prior to or within a certain amount of time frame from this funding, you must conduct an assessment of at least City Hall with the intention of all buildings. It comes down to a matter of funding.
As to why that hasn't happened yet and, as you mentioned, we can outsource this to consultants who can do the work. So it's not. You know, it's super taxing on the little limited staff that we have. Would you make that a condition of this?
Determination of significance? Not a determination of significance. I think the significance is the significance, but it's going to be our recommendation as part of the official role of reviewing CPC projects is going to request that the CPC make that a condition of funding. I just wanted to clarify what I said about master plan. I didn't mean for the entire city. I meant more just for this building.
Yeah, I mean, we can take it on a building by building basis. I think the city's well on its way, right? So I'm sure the schools have something because they're newer buildings and the fire department has something. Police department's a new building. So it's being done in bits and bobs. It's just a matter of somebody. So I think this is a standalone project just all in itself.
You know, it's deserving. So, you know, I can roll into the history of the building, but it definitely is, in my opinion, deserving of funding. Did everybody have a chance to review the form? Does anybody want to kickstart comments? I'll make a motion to fine for significance. Great, Jen. I'll second.
Uh, Lenny got a second. Sorry, Ed. All right, Jen, if you want to start. Sure, um. I think this is a pretty slam dunk case of significance.
Oh, no, I was thinking that we had already determined significance. We just didn't write a letter, but that was something else. I mean, obviously, it's, you know, kind of our shining beacon in the city. It has the beautiful rotunda. It's been recommended for a National Register listing. So to me, it's kind of a no-brainer. I don't really feel like it warrants massive amounts of discussion. Great. Hannah Lenny?
I mean, I think this is an easy one. It is obviously significant historically and architecturally. And yeah, I don't really have much to add. Great. Peter, anything to add? No. And Ed?
classic piece of WPA Medford significance. Yeah, it's like one of the three beacons, this and former DPW building, Chevalier, Post Office, all the projects here in Medford. Yeah, I just want to note for anybody watching at home,
more watching this project. This is a building built by Michael A. Dyer. Michael Dyer is one of the most prolific architect builders in the city of Medford. He, in fact, at one point probably had done most of the municipal projects in the 1930s. I believe he or his father served as a one-time city mayor, so it's very important.
He did take this design elsewhere. Woburn City Hall looks almost identical to this building, but our building was first, so we'd like to think that he designed our building first and took the design elsewhere. And it really, inside and out, maintains a lot of integrity. There's a lot of cool features to this building, from the hallways to the
offices and certainly the auditorium space and even the clock tower is kind of nice. And it sits upon what is later known as Medford Town Common. It was the municipal center for Medford. Unlike an 18th century common, this is more, it started off as a gravel pit and then
became a public park and is now home to our city hall after much fanfare, much debate on what to do with it. And the city of Medford, 16 years before building this building, tore down their town hall without a plan. So I'd like to see not that happen and not have a plan for this building. So yeah, so that's just my thoughts.
All right, with anybody else, with nobody else here and nobody else having comments, I'll take a roll call vote. Motion was for significance, so Jen? Yes. And Eleni? Yes. And Ed? Yes. And Peter? Yes. All right, motion passes for nothing. So we'll get a letter out to you. Fantastic, thank you.
Thank you, Teresa. Well, since we have you, Teresa, and I think you had sent around the email about the quadrennial, I'm butchering that, quadrennial ideas. Quadricennial. Thank you. Oh, I think I put it wrong on the agenda.
This is our next agenda item, not to steal that from Ryan. No, go ahead. I know that you had sent an email back a while back and then Doug reminded me that we needed to talk about this. This is the city's 100th anniversary. Yes. I know some people have been bringing this to us like, well, that's still six years away.
6 years ago was way too long. So time will go quickly. So I just wanted to get this at least started to be talked about so that it's not a mad dash at the end to start pulling something together. I don't know if I had circulated an ideas list of how this could be celebrated through, or it was just the idea of, hey, we should start planning this.
I don't know that I've seen an ideas list, but I'd be curious. Yeah, what the ideas are, are we going to pull a committee together to like a formal committee. Fundraise is going to be money in the city budget. Yeah, and that's another reason why we're talking about it now is budgeting purposes, but I'm.
I believe that we should hold together a committee and whether that is a representative from the Historical Commission, maybe CPC, maybe from the Treasury. I forgot what their fiscal task force or something like that, but having the right players as well as community member volunteers to serve the board as well.
We would love to have the Anderson's on the things like that, but that was my initial thought was put together a committee of established members as well as new volunteers to really start. I don't know if we tag team with the historical commission society, but. Lots of ideas, I don't know what what.
You may have kicked around, but we should form a committee, I think, with five to seven members. Maybe we can bring in Tufts. I'm just spitballing at this point. I wasn't prepared. I think the committee is going to need a budget, which is always a challenge. Yeah, I definitely think a mix of city stakeholders, commission members,
residents, anybody that's potentially interested, Chamber of Commerce. I always think of the commission, I always think of like, we're the B2B and the Chamber of Commerce is the consumer facing, like they're in charge of parades and things like that. But I think for an event like this,
I think kind of a united front would be fun and you know not we don't typically kind of get involved with those things but I think it would be fun to be involved this time with such a big thing and I don't know maybe
Ryan, we can use it as a way to like celebrate our oldest buildings or highlight some of our oldest buildings, a walking tour, or I'm sure we could come up with some like events. Yeah, or just like, you know, depending on what it is, is it a year's worth of events? Is it a certain couple, you know, concentrated timeframe worth of events? Like, are we celebrating it for the whole year? Like, do we know the actual date?
One, I don't know, it was sometimes like the formal charter came years later. After I thought I thought it was sometime in the spring.
It's April, but I don't know when the specific grants came in, because there's the grant to Matthew Craddock, which is 162930, and then there's our founding, which we were not a community formally until like 1680. So, in terms of Massachusetts government, but there was representation
Because we're listed in many, many government things as meat for or mystic. So we can do some research and that will be some of the things that we lead up to is making sure that all the facts are correct. Yeah, I think if every organization does 1 or 2 events.
throughout the year, then, you know, there'd be enough to fill out a year. You know, I think the city should, you know, we could be responsible for two, like I've done at a researcher house programs. We can do walking tours. That's not a problem. Historical society did a couple of programs focused on various aspects of Medford history. Maybe they, maybe the, it might be cool to do the history of the,
The 1930s celebration 100 years ago, and the way that they sell, you know, Lexington was just looking at their centennial and the way that they celebrated the bicentennial and all of that 100 years ago. So that might be fun. You know, because that's recent history. We definitely the city should be responsible for an event a big event, like a big mystic river celebration, but maybe.
rather than do those events separately or even at all, combine them all into one big mega event with people and music and all sorts of stuff. Or do it a couple of times a year. I don't know. There should definitely be a parade and there should definitely be fireworks. Yeah. Yeah. I kind of flushed out like we should have something
Um, every month and dovetail existing things, like, I had waited, like, the state picnic, like, that's something that already happens. Now, maybe we can, like, oomph it up. So, I don't know if it's so much, like, lots and lots of new event planning. It's a couple of new events peppered into pre-existing, you know, community anchor events.
Yeah, I just looked it up too. 2027 is the 175th anniversary of Tufts University. So I would like to think that they will start celebrating themselves a little bit before that or leading up to that. If not, that would be a good kickoff, real rock solid kickoff way to start celebrating Med for 400 is to start with one of the oldest institutions in the area. So
and a good way to partner with Tufts. Tufts has a lot of students, alumni, good way for Medford to maybe raise money and, you know, find ways to bring the kids into the programs, but also get something out of Tufts too as well. Yeah, and are they like bringing alumni, like famous alumni back for their celebration? It could be a way to get some like- Money. Famous people to Medford.
Has, did you guys, did Townsend ever do anything, Ryan, when you were there? Did they ever have one of these anniversaries? I mean, they've had these anniversaries before. I did not. COVID happened in the middle of our big one, so. Well, and all the events right now are, like in Lexington, are leading up to Patriot's Day next year, right? Like they have their big countdown in the Senate. I drive through there every day on my way to my office.
Yes, it's the 250th anniversary has started. I mean, a countdown, like, I don't know if you've seen what Lexington's doing, Teresa. They have like a big countdown board on their town green. I'll try to snap a picture of it when I drive through there. In front of Town Hall, they're counting down to their big celebration. Very cool.
Yeah. I mean, I think like the city, the city of Boston, they're, they're 400 the same as ours, if I'm not mistaken, I think 1630. So they already have like a logo and they're already putting their marketing out there. So, and I know they have Boston money. We do not, but you know, I think it's time for us to really start focusing in on this one. And I think it starts with a committee of, as you said, Jen, you know, bring in,
chamber of historical society, bring in city folks, bring in, you know, just historical consultants who live in the area. It'd be really great to have clear density there, you know, um, and then kind of go from there, establish a wants desires of, of types of events. And then from there we can establish a budget. So it sounds like this is the, uh, the commission supporting this, which is great. Um, I'm a bit of a party planner, event production,
planner by a former profession, so this is something that's exciting to me. Yeah, I think it could be super fun. Yeah, in terms of next steps, I'm happy to reach out and I passed this briefly past the mayor, so I think she'd be open to having a discussion about this. So I'll bring it to her attention and then get her blessing to start pulling
personalities together for the committee? Yeah, that sounds good. Okay. Yeah, I mean, because there's like, we have the Brooks Estate, you know, there's Embelle, there's the Royal House, there's, you know, I mean, everything kind of overlaps with the society a little bit, but I think it's just a matter of how big is the committee and who, you know, like, you know, like, for example, like,
You know there's me like I sit here and I am on mbelt and then Doug's on CPC and he's on mbelt and like I think there's a fee, you know, and then obviously we're members of societies like it, it all kind of overlaps a little bit. Right. Yeah, I'll see what the mayor may have. She may have preference in seeing more chamber folks. I'm not sure. It's just to kind of help share the
The labor, this is going to be a lot of work. Yeah, and I think you need to determine who's driving it, right? Is it the chamber? Is it the society? Is it somebody? City hall. Is it, right. Is it some, Alicia or somebody on her team? Like whatever. Yeah. Okay. Thank you. So my eyes get really big.
But I think starting with the mayor more earnestly in this conversation is the next step. So I will do that and happy to come back and report out to this group or just provide like an administrative memo to keep you updated. Yeah, keep us updated. And you're right. I mean, the time is going to fly by. So the sooner, you know, at least the committee gets formed, I think the better. Right. Excellent. Awesome. Thanks.
Thanks. Do we have any more new business? Okay. All right. Moving on to old business. Properties under demo delay. We did hear from 56 Wareham Street today. I think we still need a little work on those plans, but I think the goal is to try to get them
done soon so that we can vote to lift them. Ryan was gonna send them back a note. Or were you gonna send that to Doug and- I'm gonna send it to Doug and Peter. They didn't really change anything. I asked them to push back the addition a little bit, but they didn't do anything, so. Okay. Were the plans any less diagrammatic kind of?
Uh, yeah, yeah, I think they were before this was um, this was uh, This is not almond street almond street. We haven't even we got to set up a meeting with them. Oh, wait. Yeah, okay I'm getting i'm getting mixed up. I think yeah anyway Yeah, no, I think where ham is pretty concise. I just asked them to
push back the roof line a little bit so that it doesn't look like it's eating the old house, but they didn't. So I'm not thrilled with it. So the rest of it looks fine. I just, that's the only thing I want them to change. Yeah. You know, it should be, you know, a rehabilitation, not necessarily restoration, but also not necessarily development either. So.
All right, so next month, Jen. OK, yeah. OK, and yeah, and we have not heard from all months, so. OK. I don't think we need to order any foreign bees tonight. OK, so we're there if one just. 161 Maine went into open house this weekend and I did walk through.
Unless they're going to raise the roof, it's never going to come back to us. The interior is in very good shape. It was modernized for renewal a few years ago. It was being used as an income property, and it's being sold as either a starter home or an income property at 715 Asking. So if we had ordered a Form B, I don't think it's going to be
Again, absent a raised roof, which given the shape, it's not going to go that far. I doubt it's ever going to come before us, at least on this. What? I was going to say it's covered in asbestos siding, so we have to do some sort of remediation if they decide to do that.
Otherwise it'll just look wonky. I guess they could go over it with vinyl, but that's such a did we already order one for that? I haven't ordered it yet, because I preemptively just sitting on it waiting to make sure that budget doesn't burn that we don't burn through our budget. Yeah, I mean, I mean, I agree with Ed. I mean, it's it's almost in too good of shape to. I don't know that it's a super threat, but yeah, I think maybe keep it on the list and if if you know. If March comes in March and April come and we have a little extra, we can order it.
Yeah, exactly. Okay. And I haven't heard or seen, we haven't gotten any pings this month about kind of new things coming in, so. If people see derelict properties and they want to bring them to our attention, you know, feel free to, you know, if you walk by something and say, hey, this condition isn't looking too favorable, maybe you should take a look at it. You know, we're happy to do that. Yeah, and there haven't been any like,
attention developers. Right. I mean, there was one I don't I'll send it. We'll look at it, Ryan. There was one that came on last week. But everything that I've seen in the past couple weeks,
If it's shouting for a developer, it's because there's an extra lot or something buildable potentially that I don't know that it's necessarily a demo or teardown. It's just adding something to something that's already there. All right. Speaking of budgets, are we? We're okay. Yeah. All right. We're on our pace.
Yeah, I'm going to put out to bid. I have to review after we do the S&P. Eleni and I are going to review what they call the scope of work, which is normally what we do for MHC's grant, but MHC didn't
We didn't apply for an M.H.C. grant last year because we missed the deadline. So we're doing that work and we have a section picked out that's going to be the Sagamore Vale, which is Ashland, Water, Oakland street area. The consultants were pretty convinced that
I think 50 or so properties could be documented for the money that we have in our budget, which is $15,000 for that match. So we'll have to work and we will have to go out to bid. But I just want to review scope of work after the S&P grant goes out. OK. OK, good.
Permit subcommittee, I sent a couple of things to Peter and Eleni this week, so thank you guys for getting back to me on that. I'm actually going to meet with the building department on Wednesday. They have a meeting every week. I've been invited to come go sit with them and just kind of answer any questions, get to know them. They can know me, see I'm a real person. If there's anything that you guys want me to relay,
Let me know. I think I'm just going to kind of go over, you know, kind of talk generally about the things that... Should we start putting our business card back in the office? Oh, yeah. Do you have a stack of them? I do. I have all the boxes of them. I mean, I don't know how many people go in anymore. I mean, all the permits are gone by now. Lots of people. No, they do, but... Lots of people go in. Well, yeah. I mean, all right. Well, I'll come grab some of those from you and bring them with me, but...
Um, just because then the guys will go, the guys will go, Oh, contact the historical commission and they'll go, how do I do that? And you can say, here's the card. Yeah. They, they, they do tend to send folks just right upstairs to Dennis and if he's available. So it might be a nice addition to have them if you have some. Yeah. Do you want me to, uh, you want me to drop off a stack to you guys too, as well? Yeah, that, that would be great. Yeah.
I mean, my goal is to just kind of talk in general about the things that we really look for, about streetscape and changing roof lines, honoring what's there, things in the rear we typically aren't super concerned about.
you know, as long as the house kind of maintains what was there and what is there. And I thought, Ryan, I'd bring that old memo that we wrote that kind of started this whole thing back, you know, what is a four or five years ago now, the examples that we had. And this is from previous commissioners, previous, you know, folks in the department.
where it was just kind of like willy nilly of, of tearing things down and, and just, you know, anyway, I thought going to kind of just sharing a little history, uh, would kind of put us in, in context of how we got here. But, um, anyway, if, if, if anything comes up between now and Wednesday four o'clock that you guys feel is important that I talk to them about, feel free to send it to me. Otherwise,
Going into the lion's den. Good luck. Thanks. Thanks. If anyone wants to come, feel free to come with me. But no, I think it'd be fine. I tease. I mean, they're all good guys. One of the things that I struggle with is
Lands right literally sometimes there's things like sketched on a napkin and like taking a picture and upload it into the system and you know I would like to hear from them in the sense of. Yes, these are acceptable no they aren't. And what do they look for, because I think that that would be.
You know, obviously, I'm not a contractor. I don't know building codes, but, you know, what is the property owner required to do? Because I feel like sometimes we get something to review and it's like.
I mean, Eleni and Peter, you see it more, because I'll send you guys things. And I'm like, there's nothing here. I don't know what you're doing. Even today, there was something I had to kind of send a note back on, because it said, we're putting a cover on and then making storage. And there was no other information about that. And I'm like, can you just clarify what this is and where in the property? Is this inside, outside?
What's happening here in terms of the work? Because it's probably something we don't care about, but. You know, I don't know. Are you tearing down a carriage house like it was so ambiguous? So anyway, so I will let you guys know how that goes. Ryan Cross Street Cemetery. Yeah, Teresa, are you there? Perchance I am.
Have we heard back from Fiona on where she is with the contract with PAL? Yes, she and I connected last week. She said that she hopes to send this out early this week. I gave her today. I'm not going to nudge her tomorrow. And that's the contract, not necessarily the bidding work, or does that also include the bidding work? I believe the bidding work was already pushed out. Oh, OK.
Responses she told me she was thought out mid last week. So I really bad advertiser for 2 weeks and maybe mid next week on the bidding aspect, but the contract. I'll get it out. I'll make sure it gets out. Okay, before I leave for vacation. Okay, so there you have it.
She knew everything that I knew. So yeah, so thanks for letting me know. So I'm yeah, so I'm looking forward to getting PAO under contract so that we can then get moving on that work and then they have to apply for the state level permitting. Then there's going to be some.
uh lag time while they put together their report to the state if the state has any questions there'll be some additional lag time and then we will hopefully be going in the ground so
Will they do that in the winter or will we automatically be delayed to like March? I don't have an answer. I would like to think that as long as they can excavate so just so people know for construction purposes, you can probably dig safely well into January and not hit any sort of frost in the ground. It makes it hairy to pour foundations, but you can definitely go in the ground. The ground is still soft. It's not fully frozen until.
almost late January, early February. So those are really the months. So we don't get in ground by, I would say, Christmas. There'll be a low for the holiday and we won't be getting in the ground until April. I don't know how that impacts the RFP process that's gone out on the parcels, but my understanding is that the RFP is just to seek a development proposal, right?
Is it a single, I didn't look at it yet, I probably should, but is it a singular proposal for each parcel or is it the whole concept? I believe it's a concept plan that they're asking for, but don't hold me to that, that's my understanding. Okay, so we'll be looking at various proposals from various teams on what could or could not go there and the city can certainly pick and choose and then they'll
figure out what they want. Is this for the downtown project? This is the downtown archaeological dig at the former cemetery parcel as it relates to the development proposal that went out. Or the parking lot parcel. Yeah, that is sparking a hot topic on parking in the city of Medford right now. So. That it is.
I was just going to add that that's also my understanding of excavation work. That's that timeline that Ryan presented. I had heard until February, but I think we're about a mile out there. I mean, as long as the excavator can get through. But I think it's a question of whether or not it's an ideal condition for the archaeologists and digging excavation. That was going to be my concern, too. Yeah, if the ground is great enough for us to peel back that top layer,
Yeah, so a concern there as well. But the contract is going to get out, so at least that triggers the timeline that you presented out, Ryan. Okay. That's why we'll get it out this week. Great. Okey-dokey. All right, Thomas Brooks Park, we have a public meeting on the calendar for October 22nd.
So commissioners, if you are available and would love to join us, we're going to be reviewing the project to date with the public. Peter is going to talk about the archaeological cap ideas that we had already discussed.
kind of just give folks a general update and take any questions, feedback, et cetera. Did I miss anything, Ryan, on that? It's going to be on Zoom. Just to make it easier, we could not get the, the library is booked every night this month. So we could not get the room at the library. So Zoom it is. Everything, everywhere. Oh my God, it's bananas. Yeah. It's all good though. There's lots of good things happening here.
So anyway, so that'll be an exciting meeting. And we should probably send out an email, Ryan. Is there a, Theresa, is there a process for a Captain Barry call? Oh yeah, can we get a representative? Or a mayor call for that particular neighborhood, and we can just target the. Yep, yep, I can help facilitate that, but Steve's community is our director of communications.
Um, he, he manages the robo calls and alerts. So. He would be feel free to send it to me and I can send it along to him, but in case I. Disappear hit by a bus, Steve can help with that. All right, I'll, I'll, I'll send that to you when I. Did we file a formal agenda Ryan?
That depends on I guess I could just file it. We probably should only because the last time we had a public meeting about the park. Somebody complained that they couldn't find it on the city calendar. I don't know if the agenda is the trigger point to getting on the calendar. You can have just the public.
event, like if you go to the calendar right now, for instance, there's a great, uh, I'll plug a Hispanic pop-up restaurant that's happening this Friday, um, at the West Medford community center. So if you want your, your public community event, um, you can also send it again to speak community. Okay. Yeah. I think, I mean, we have the zoom meeting, so we should at least have that. So people can download it and have the zoom meeting info. Yeah.
Yeah, OK, OK, all right, we can make that definitely make that happen. OK. And then after that meeting, Ryan, what will our next steps be for finalize that plan and add it as an amendment to the master plan? Right, OK.
perhaps seek estimates for work, and then we are going to start the very long process of working with various city departments to bid all of the public work for Thomas Brooks Park Phase 2. Teresa will absolutely need your help, along with Fiona, because it will be a beast. Looking forward to it.
I'm hoping that the various city departments that would be involved with this traffic and DPW and all those parks will have a lot of the tools that we need, basically standardized stuff that they're using across the city that we can then dump into a standard set of specifications. So not reinventing the wheel. OK.
Great, good updates there. Survey projects, you guys kind of already talked about that a little bit. We're going to put in for a new survey. Yeah, Lenny, did you have a chance to review the, are you going to send me comments? I did, I just remembered that today. I read through it and it seems pretty good for, you know, one pager and I guess when we submit the
If we get asked to submit the larger application, I'd be happy to work with you on that. But I thought it looked good. What does the one pager do?
November 15th, but I'm going to send it ASAP. So it's, I just want to get it off my plate. Yeah, it's a, that one we're looking to do the Hastings Heights neighborhood. There's a huge gap in survey in West Medford between the Marm-Simons Historic District and West Medford Square. Tons of pre-1900 buildings there that were developed, a large amount of them being single families. So
It'd be a great neighborhood to do. They've already previously approved the project. So we're kind of going back and asking them again to just make sure that that's still a priority. I'm hoping it is because this year the priorities are a little bit different as survey work is not their top priority. It's actually planning, but we're a city that was in dire need of.
Inventory, so I'm kind of hoping that they'll prioritize that. Plus, we're executing a plan that's been well implemented over the last decade. So I'm hoping that they'll see past that. Plus, we're a CLG, so we're usually guaranteed to get funding. But if we don't, then we will move forward with a lesser dollar amount and just do other survey.
Great. It's exciting. It'll be nice to have a new project for that since we took this year off. Yep. Yep. Well, yeah, kind of. We were forced to take this year off. Well, we we are catching up, right? So we're making sure that we're getting back on a normal schedule after COVID and all that stuff. Plus, you know, and the budget won't get done. We're just waiting for reimbursement from the state. So. Great.
Okay, does anybody else have anything for tonight before we approve the meeting minutes? No? Okay. Peter sent around the meeting minutes. Motion to approve. Okay, thank you, Ryan. I'll second. Thank you, Eleni. Okay, motion to approve the meeting minutes from September, right? September 2024.
I'll take a roll call vote. Ryan? Yes. Peter? Yes. Eleni? Yes. And Ed? Yep. Okay, great. So the minutes pass 4-0.
Motion to adjourn? I move to adjourn. Thank you, Ed. Second. Thanks, Ryan. Motion to adjourn at 8.15. Ryan? Yes. Peter? Yes. Helene? Yes. Ed? Yes. Thank you, everybody. Our next meeting will be November 18th.
Unless we pull anything together in the meantime, but officially. Yeah, there may be a need to have a special meeting at the end of the month for where hammer Brooks, but we'll see how fast those projects move along. I'm sure Brooks. Yeah, so. Yeah, we do have a meeting on a meeting scheduled for the 28th. That we kind of set up at the end of at the beginning of the year. So we have that date if we need it. So we'll go from there. Have a good night. All right. Good night. Thanks.