So it's 102, we'll call to order the Medford licensing meeting for the November, for our November meeting here. So we've got a fairly full agenda, so we'll try to get everything, keep everything moving along here. So our first,
You know, one of our first items we always have on this agenda is to approve minutes from previous meetings. And we had a number of minutes, which we have not yet approved from previous meetings. Correct, Daria? That's why they're on there. So I'd like to go ahead, Bobby, if that's all right with you, and we should go through those and get that knocked off.
Yeah, that's fine. I had already had a chance to look over the July, August, September, and October minutes. Everything looked in order to me. I didn't see any issues with it. I don't know if you had a chance to look them over, Ben. Yeah, I did. So I have July 19th,
What was the August date? Just to make sure. August 9th. Yep. I did see. Yep. Okay. Okay. It's August 9th. Then we have September 20th, October 18th. That's correct. And that's everything. So. I can make a motion to accept the minutes of those meetings for the four months of July, August, September, and October. Okay. I'll second that motion.
and all in favor. Aye. Aye. Okay, so all of our minutes for those last four meetings are now all in the record and all approved. Very good. Okay. All right, now we'll move into our agenda.
So we have a representative from Medford Brewing Company will present to one day licenses applications for winter extravaganza event on November 29 and 100 year anniversary event on December 14.
Nick, if you'd like to just unmute yourself and give us a rundown on both of those events. Absolutely, yes. So Winter Extravaganza is the annual in front of Medford, in front of the, what do you call your head office? City Hall. City Hall, that's the one. In front of City Hall. We did it last year, as I said.
It's a pretty well-contained event. And then we also then have the 100th Rotary, which Alan might be part of. And what we're doing for them is that's at the Medford Library. They requested that we basically do some beer and wine for their event as well. OK, OK. So one is the outdoor event, and then one is the indoor event. Yes.
Okay, okay, see the applications here. Chairman Delfano, do you have anything? No, Nick, you always do a great job.
You know, you have licensed people there, you know what you're doing. We've dealt with you many times and I feel very comfortable. The only thing we can request, if you don't mind, is just a drawing of the grounds of City Hall for the November 29th event. Just basically where in City Hall, outside of City Hall in the parking area, and just show the area the alcohol's gonna be in.
Other than that, we know you have insurance on file with us. Everything's always good with you folks. Excellent, thank you. Yeah, I'll get Lisa to do that for you. Yeah, that'd be great if you can. I'm not really, it's just a rough sketch. It doesn't have to be anything fancy. Yep, I can get that for you. Great, thank you. Yeah, I agree with that. Okay, why don't we move on to the other ones, see if we have any questions on that one.
and then we can improve them both at the same time if we're good with them both. Okay. I don't have any on the Rotary's 100th year anniversary event. Everything looks in order there and Medford Public Library, they always have their events in the same place. We have our insurance certificate attached, so I'm good with that one. Yeah, yeah. So is this event on the second floor and that sort of,
room across from the kids library? I believe so, yes. OK. The yes, it's I mean, I said it's either way. I know the whole event. It's a private event. It's a closed off event only to members of the Rotary, as far as I know. And and I have a supervisor of Alan, who'll be there as well. So. OK. Nick, you're a busy guy.
Okay, yeah, I mean, I'm aware of the library and the events that happened there. They're all confined to the, you know, the premises, so I don't have any problems with that either. If we're good with it, we could make a motion to approve both of these events.
Sounds good to me. Would you like me to make the motion, Mr. Chair? Yeah, if you don't mind. Sure. I make a motion to grant two one-day licenses, the first on November 29th from 5 p.m. to 7 p.m. for a winter extravaganza at Medford City Hall in the parking lot, and Medford Brewing will be
doing the event. We just like to grant this one on the condition that we have a submission of the drawing. Hopefully in the next couple of days, you can send it out to Daria and also for their other event on December 14th, 2023, 6 to 9 p.m.
Rotary's 100th year anniversary event, which is also going to be handled by Medford Brewing at 111 High Street in Medford in the library. Okay, thank you for that motion. I will second that motion. So all in favor. Aye. Aye.
Okay, Nick, good luck with both events and thanks for getting this together. And then just as soon as you get Daria the diagram, she'll show that to us. If we have any questions, we'll come to you with those. Perfect, thank you. I do have a 30 second question if I may quickly ask. Yes. The former vault site slash Salvatore's building
Uh, they, the landlords actually reached out to me about me possibly taking over the building. Uh, but I was in communication. Someone said there's a lien on it. There's no liquor license could be obtained on that building. Is that, was it something I would check through you guys to see if that's reality or. We don't have any, um, information about, you know, the, the, the, about liens on that building.
in regards to a liquor license not being able to be obtained. We do not, unless I'm missing something. Bobby? You may want to just check in with the ABCC if they have anything on file with the DOR or with, what is it? They're at their meeting.
for the workers' comp insurance. Those would be the only two places that would have an issue. And it wouldn't even be on the license itself because we have plenty of licenses. So anybody can apply for a license. I don't know if the DOR will let you have a new license on a premise address that is
delinquent type of payments. So the ABCC would be a good place to start. And they can point you in whatever direction that the money is owed. And if in fact, you can either transfer a license, or just get a brand new license, it's basically going to be the same thing. Great. Thank you. Very helpful. Yeah, I would do that back end homework on it. I would just say don't listen to any
speculation about, about that because as Bob said there's we have the city has licenses and that's not really how that works so. Thank you. I probably won't. There's only so much bandwidth I can do that building might be too much for me but thanks guys have a good one. Yeah, good luck. All right.
So that's Nick. Okay, we're gonna move on to the next agenda item here. Let me just make sure I have it all here. So, okay, this says representative from the Medford Historical Society will present a one-day license application for a fundraiser and toy collection for a charity event that's being held on December 6th. Hey, hi there.
Sir, I'm forgetting your name, if you could state that. John Anderson. John? Yes. John Anderson, welcome. Can you give us a overview of this event, please? Basically, we're going to have a speaker presenting various items from the collection that are of interest to people. We have lots of fascinating things.
And we're doing a toy drive to collect toys for Medford Family Network as part of the event. Okay. And this is, I'm just trying to pull up the application here. Okay. You have a diagram of this? I included a picture.
of the room? Yeah, it's about, as I say, it's like 29 by 30 approximately. Okay. Okay. Interior room. Okay. Okay. All right. I'm not too hung up on that. Do you see the picture? Commissioner Delfano? Yeah, everything.
Looks in order, Mr. Chairman. Yeah, the room, there's a photo of it, and as Mr. Anderson stated, it's going to be indoors. Only looks like about 30 guests. Yeah, I don't have a problem with any of this. I see the insurance binder here, so I'm good with it. Okay, okay. Thank you. And there's a licensed bartender that's gonna do it? Yes. Who will that be?
Who would that be? Probably Max or one of his people, or we also have a board member who's a licensed bartender. Okay. Okay. Well, then if they're, you know, that sounds, that's always good. That's always reassuring. Yeah, we're, you know, I don't see this as much to worry about as far as a license, like our licensing board is concerned here.
I think I'm all good with this too. So, Chairman Delfano? Yes, I make a motion to grant a one day license for December 6th for a fundraiser and toy collection for Chairman of Medford Historical Society to Mr. John Anderson at 10 Governors Avenue, Medford. All right, and I will second that motion.
All in favor? Aye. Aye. All right, John, well, the license has been granted. And it's good to see you back in here a few times. Some activity and some events happening. Yes. It's nice to see. Thank you very much. Yeah. I hope it's a success. Thank you. Take care.
Yeah. All right. Mr Chairman, I had a good sound to it. You're doing a damn good job. I'm not through yet. Okay. I think it's the new look.
Okay, all right, so the next item of business here. Okay, so a representative from Riverside Yacht Club will present an application for a change of manager at their establishment located at 52 Ship Ave in Medford. So yeah, I'd ask just to unmute yourself. If that's the gentleman.
Actually, I don't know who that is. Is that Michael? Yeah, that's Michael. He needs to unmute himself. Maybe bottom left on your phone, Michael.
If you swipe the screen over, it should come to, it should show where the mute is. Chairman Delfano, just while Michael's signing on, have you had a chance to look at this?
Yes, I have had Mr. Chairman. I've got a lot of issues with this application. I don't know if you'd like to review them while Michael's trying to sign on or do you want to go to the next one and we'll go from there?
Yeah, Mike, I think that what you just said is a good idea. We're just gonna hold this application in front of us and let's just move to the next item while Michael gets the phone sorted out. And I'm sure it's a pain in the butt. Okay, so this is another change of manager. So the next, the item that we're gonna go to right now. So this is a representative from Associanzone Amici, Inc.
will present an application for a change of manager at their establishment at 21 Reardon Road, Medford. Good afternoon, gentlemen. Hey, how are you? How are you? Great, thank you. You did a pretty good job, David. Associate Sonamichi. Oh, yeah, okay. Yeah. You're giving your best. I know, I know, I know. Thanks.
So if you wouldn't mind just giving us your name, please, and just going over what we're looking at here. Yes, my name is Angelo Federico. I'm the president of Association Amici, and we're doing a change of manager. The gentleman that was doing it, Mr. Colella, is no longer able to do it due to his work schedule and so forth. So we nominated Mr. Fabio Riparo.
and has all the documents that was required. Is Mr. Rapara on the call too? Unfortunately, he's not, no. I'm representing him. Okay, okay. He's not, he wasn't able to get on the call? No, he works for
Turner Construction, so right now he's probably on the 30th floor. Right. So, okay. Chairman Delfano, do you have any questions or thoughts on what we're looking at here? Yeah. Mr. Federico appears to be the corporate officer, which is fine.
Mr. Federico, I have to hand it to you. You made out this application for a change of manager perfectly. There's absolutely no issues with this at all. And this is the way all of them should be made out. It's very legible. Everything's filled in where it should be. And I don't have a problem with this at all. Thank you. You're welcome, sir. And just, this is, now this is a club, correct?
It's a cultural organization, yes, 501C3. Okay. Dedicated to, I'm sure I don't know if any of the board members know of us, we've been around them, next year will be 10 years. Okay. Yeah, so it's more filtered through cultural events and so forth, and also for the communities. Okay, okay. And yeah, in the last four years I've been on here, we haven't heard of
anything negative about the license or anything like that. So that's always great. But Bobby, this does fall under club license, right? Yes. Yeah. So I'm looking through it. Does Mr. Raparo, does he have any experience serving alcohol? Yes, he is. He's CIP certified.
which a few of us have. So he does know how to mix a few drinks. As my fellow chairman said, everything's organized. It's what we want. We've had no
no trouble with this group. So I'm inclined to move this along. Chairman Delfano, what are your thoughts? Yeah, I'd make a motion to grant the amendment for a change of manager for Associazione Amici, Inc. Did the Italian say it better?
Oh, a little better, but you'll get there. I still struggled. It was hard for me too. Yeah, to make a change of manager, 21 Redden Road, Medford Mass. Okay, and I'm in agreement and I second that motion. And all in favor, say aye. Aye. Aye.
Um, okay. So it is approved. So the change of manager at the, uh, associate. Yeah. Um, is, uh, is in effect to, um, um, as Angela just gave us the rundown for, for, um,
sorry, for the new manager who is Fabio Raparo. So best of luck, guys. Thank you so much, everyone. Have a great day. OK. Pleasure talking to you all. Take care. Bye now. OK. Michael, any luck?
If you swipe over, does it show the unmute? Think about how to do that on an iPhone. If you swipe over or if you tap the screen, it may come at the bottom as. It'll look like a little red microphone with a line through it. You wanna touch that if you see that. Daria, is there anything we can do as the administrator to just unmute somebody?
I've asked him to unmute a couple times, but I don't know like what it's doing. I'm clicking on the, like on the screen, it says, ask to unmute. I'm trying to do that, but... Because when I log on, it's on mute as a default. Everybody's on mute. Actually, hold on, let me see. Hold on. Now that you say it, hold on. Okay.
Okay, Michael, try signing in again, and I'll see if it will let you, I just changed the setting. Try to log in again. Yeah, let's try that. Okay, so while that's happening, we have,
So is that, so let me just see, because these were some late additions, I think. So Historic Society of Riverside Yacht Club. I think we have three of them for Brian over there, if anything. Yeah, okay. So Brian, and do we have Tufts?
We have one for Tufts too, yeah. That was the last minute. Can we, why don't we just take that one for Tufts right now? Then we can go to Brian's three. That'll work. So, Tamara, or yeah, could you guys just please give us some information on the event?
Absolutely. So this is part of our ongoing effort to do a little bit more for our senior class. And this is their bingo night, the event is going to be from eight to 930. So the bar will only be open from eight to nine.
We will only have one door. If you're looking at that floor plan, the door that's the second door from the left will be the only access point to that room. Just inside the room, we will have a team that will be not only ensuring that they are tough students, but also ensuring that they are of age. So nobody that is underage will be admitted to this event.
We will also have Tufts to PT PD detail there on site. Um, and it's going to be for approximately 400 students, but the main focus of the event is, is to have bingo that night. Okay, okay.
Great, so I'm seeing the diagram here. It's at the Cummings Center. It looks good to me. It's clear you, Tufts has been in front of us many times and without any issues. So I don't have any questions. Hi, Michael, sorry again, you should be able to. Mr. Delfano.
Yes, Mr. Chairman, through the chair, I just have a quick question. The diagram is great, but it doesn't state where the alcohol is going to be served. We will have a bar set up within the room. It'll all be confined to that one space. You're not sure which area or what end, middle, back? It will be toward the back, but I'd be happy to submit an additional floor plan with that labeled.
Yeah, that'd be great if you can, just so you know. No problem. It's not a big deal. You know, I was kind of curious when I saw this, it said senior bingo. I only live behind you. I was all set to get on there on December 1st, because I'm a senior and maybe I could participate, but now I know it means senior students. Got it.
That's what I thought when I saw it too. Yeah, seniors bingo in Tufts. They said, oh, that must be- Yeah, it was kind of unusual, but glad you cleared that up. No, everything else looks fine. Tufts always does a great job. We don't have any issues with you folks. Yeah, if you can do that, that'd be great. And you can even hand sketch when you decide where you're gonna put the bar right on this, scan it and send it back over. That'd be good. Yeah, happy to do it. Okay, great. Thank you.
Okay, now this application is just not right in front of me anymore. I can make a motion if you like. Yeah, that would be that would be great. Okay, I'll make a motion to grant the one day license for toughs catering. Friday, December 1 2023.
from 8 p.m. to 9.30 p.m. for senior class bingo at the Joyce Cummings Center at 177 College Ave in Medford. All right, and we'll just pending, just a quick amendment to this plan just to show where the alcohol would be. Yep, exactly. Okay, great. So that is, I second that motion and all in favor.
Hi. Hi. Okay, so that one day license has been approved for Tufts and hope success and the students love it. Thank you very much. We appreciate it. All right. Good luck. All right. All right, let's go over to Brian. Thank you for your patience. Um,
I know you were in the wave of a few of the last minute ones here. So we're just, but I'm glad you got them in. So do you want to give us a, so you have three one days that we're looking at. So two of them are the collaborations we do with JJ. She was actually going to be here today. I know she was at the last one, but she couldn't make it today. So I said, I'd be here anyways for the one we're doing. So JJ Gonson right now, she is the local artist that we're featuring in the gallery.
She had her opening and she's looking to do another, like an artist talk and another demonstration and bring some other artists in. So another event focused around that current exhibit. And that would be on December 1st. So again, it's basically, it's just another phase of what we're highlighting here. Same floor plan as usual.
And our staff now is fully TIP certified too. So everybody's got it now. But the administrating of the alcohol, Brian, that's... Sorry. So that would be the event staff. That's your staff. Correct. Yeah. Myself. I end up doing... I bartended for 15 years. It's good to do it once in a while again, I guess.
You're probably doing a little bit of everything sometimes, right? I'm doing a lot of it, a little bit of everything these days, but it's what you do. You're an entrepreneur, so. All right, so this is, okay, so this is, so the event, one event is November 19th. Correct. One event is December 1st. Correct.
Those are the JJ ones, yep. They are, are they essentially the same description, the same event? They are the same. Yeah. So, um, what we're trying to do is just create events around that, that gap, the current gallery, um, just get some people in the door. And we noticed that. Although it doesn't probably matter. The Patriots are off this Sunday. So, um, just kind of getting some people to enjoy their Sunday change, I guess.
So we've done really well with that. And it gets people in to see the art and just see what we're doing. But yeah, it's beer and board games on Friday, on Sunday the 19th is what we're applying for. And yeah, it's just like an afternoon, early, early evening thing. It's not- Yeah, for the Sunday one. And then the other one is six to nine. Correct, yep. And that's just a talk and just kind of a description of the art
I think she's going to be bringing in some additional pieces to add to the exhibit for it. So, yeah. Great. One question I just have here. So, Cuisine and Locale, that's the entity? JJ actually owns a catering company as well. So, she's a photographer. She's an event promoter.
Used to own, she still owns once, but once was in Somerville, Mass. But she does catering too. So she carries all her licenses and permits and everything, cuisine and locale. So that's her ID, right, her federal ID number. Okay, okay. Yep. All right, I'm good then on the two JJ events.
Mr. Delfano, any questions on those? Just one. JJ Gonson, Cuisine and Locale, does she have an ABCC catering license? The ABCC catering license. Yeah, she has the full license. If she's got the ABCC license, she can bring in her own alcohol.
Oh yeah, that's right. Okay, I'll double check that. Maybe she doesn't then. Maybe it's just for food. Yeah, I think it was just for food because that happened, I told you the last time too. And you checked with her, I believe, and that wasn't the case. Correct. Yeah, no, there is somebody else we work with that is a catering company we had for like a private event before.
No, no, as far as it's just for catering, that's why we do apply. Yeah. Okay. No, that's fine. Because I was going to say, you wouldn't even really have to bring it before us. She'd just have to give the city 48 hours notice and this commission 48 hours notice before the event. You wouldn't need to apply for a one-day license. But where she doesn't have the ABCC alcohol catering license,
then this is the proper way to do it. And this also, it looks to me that it would be taking it away from your numbers of one day licenses, which is good. You only, you know, you have 30 a year, so it'll kind of ease your, give you a little more slack, which is good. No, all three events look great. Brian, you do a great job all the time.
We don't have any issues with you. We were staying where I like you. I'm good to go. I'll make a motion to accept all three. And I just want to mention just for the record, no thank you, but the last one was the Friday, December 8th, and that one would be under Brian. That would be the one under Brian. It's a book, it was a book release as a local writer.
Okay. So yeah, it's great. I think it's really good for the community as well. You know, so I think she's gonna do great. Is that so is it is it open to public? It's a it's a it's a ticketed event. Okay, okay. Yeah, sounds like a good event. I'll Commissioner Delfano, I'll let you keep going with that motion though. Yeah.
Okay, I'll make a motion to grant three one-day liquor licenses to Event Them Studios at 344 Salem Street, Medford, Mass. Two of them to be run by J.J. Gonson, one on November 19th from 3 to 6 p.m., board game night. The other,
to be run on December 1st, 6 to 9 p.m., hottest discussion and talk. And the third one-day license is granted for Friday, December 8th, from 7 to 9.30, book release and reading to Brian at Event Thumb Studios, 344 Salem Street, Method Mast. Okay.
Thank you, Commissioner Delfano. I'll second that motion. All in favor? Aye. Okay, so it's approved. Brian, good luck with the three events and thanks as always for making it easy for us. Thank you, thank you as well. Have a great afternoon. All right, you too.
So John called me. He said it's not letting him in. So he asked if we could do it over the phone so I could put him on speaker if that works. I'm fine with that. Yeah. Oh, OK. Let me call him. Hold on. So I'm looking at it here now. Who is John, I wonder?
Did I say John? Yeah, is it Michael? Okay, that's fine. Hi, Michael. I was gonna say, I didn't see any Johns on there. All right, Michael, talk. Can you guys hear him? Michael, talk. It's a little faint. Michael, can you hear us? Yes, I can. All right, well,
Thank you for calling in. Hold on. Can you give us, so we're looking at your change of manager. Hold on. Hi, Michael, I don't know why I hung up. Hold on, give me a second. All right. All right, try again, sorry. All right, I can hear you. Okay, hi, Michael. How are you doing? We're doing okay, we're doing good, thank you.
So I'm looking at the application for the change of manager here for Riverside, Riverside Yacht Club. Could you give us just a quick overview of what's happening here?
Well, we had an election and I became the vice promenade. And as the vice promenade, my duty is to take care of the house, which includes the bar and all that. So my name would be put on the liquor license when I'm moving forward. That would be my responsibility. Okay. And this, who does it replace?
And then who is it replacing? But the name of the current manager?
No, I don't have a name. I mean, you put it here. It was Frank Paladino. Paladino. Okay. Is that accurate? Yeah. Okay. Commissioner Delfano, I know you had a couple of thoughts on this application. I do. Can you hear me, Mike? Yes, I can.
Okay. There's a few issues, actually quite a few issues I have with this. Okay. It's...
Well, my issue is the way it was filled out. I cannot read a good portion of it. I know it says Riverside Yacht Club, and there's a couple of things next to it. But like your name, Michael, G-A-R-D-I, and I can't get the rest of it. Vice something or other.
You know, even your email address, I can't read it. And then there's been numerous places you've left information out, entity name, municipality, ABCC license number, you know, and box one, it's all important stuff. You know, your employment information, working something, I don't know what it says.
We're working for me. Yeah. And, you know, what I'm trying to get to, you know, places that needed to be signed, there was a big X on it. You need a signature there, not an X. You know,
It is person voted to authorize you, and I think it's Michael's, the corporate office, whoever that is, that Michael, I don't know, it's Silvestro maybe. What I'd strongly suggest to you is go online where you got this form,
and type the information in and then print it so it's legible. Because I'm not gonna approve anything that I can't read half of it. And that half the blank even on your query request form, you left a lot of blank information, which is ABCC number, license name, city, town, former address, city and town, you didn't sign that either.
I can't approve this, I'm sorry. We can either table it until next month's meeting or if you want to fill it out correctly and have it typed.
are filled out on the internet so it's legible, then we can grant it per our approval if you send it to Daria, we can do that. I mean, that's my opinion, Mr. Chairman, it's whatever, I don't know if you've noticed it on there as well, but.
I don't know how you feel about it, but I know if this goes to the ABCC it's going to probably get bounced back to us. Yeah. Thanks for that, for everything you just said there I mean that that's that's the last thing you said.
I mean, we do have to be able to fully interpret everything that's on here. We just did one change of manager, as you saw, or maybe you were signing in and out, but everything on there was, all of these areas were filled out completely. And then the last thing is that the ABCC, who we are,
we represent would have, you know, may not approve this as it stands and probably wouldn't. And we're not able to just pass this along to them without having, you know, all, you know, numerous fields here filled out. I'm sure this is the first time, Mike, you've filled this, one of these applications out. So I don't wanna be overly critical
Um, but 1 would just be, um. Yeah, if it's typed in, it's it's just much easier, but yeah, like vice now I can see vice Commodore. I understand what that means, but I didn't I actually didn't know what that meant. Or what that said, um. Working for him in town of Burlington, Kevin. Something with the K, you know, we can see that, but if it's all written in, we can really. We can really get that and then.
if you're just taking note of this, I think some of the other critical, you know, yeah, the ABCC number in the licensee name in the top, like of the query request form is not filled in. So, it's not filled in on page one either of the,
amendment change of manager form. I mean, it's municipality. Correct. Yeah, I mean, it's in all the places like on the back of that, you know, in the applicant statement, authorized signatory, it's supposed to be printed and somebody signed it.
I can't even make out the name who signed it. I think it might be the Sylvestra. The second name looks like SIL. It's on the very top of the back of that page under applicant statement. Then there's supposed to be a signature down at the bottom and it's just a big X through it. Then the entity vote, there's no data meeting. That needs to be filled.
voted to authorize the name of the person who was voted to authorize this change of manager. I believe it's Michael Silvestro, but that was left blank as well. So there's quite a few things in the query request form, like Mr. Chairman stated, the ABCC number, license name, city, town, your former address,
and your signature. You know, if you want, if it's okay with everybody here, I've got an edited copy
I highlighted a bunch of everything that was wrong with it. Daria, if you want, I can email this to you and you might be able to email it to Michael. Just everything that's edited. Yeah, that's very helpful. Yeah, so Michael, that's doing you a big favor because that can save you some time here. But I'd say with the club, you have to go in and find those ABCC numbers.
and, you know, get this fully, I mean, does this make sense? We table this for this until this is fully filled out and we can accept it. Yeah. I mean, even the ABCC license number, you did have it on the front page, the OO.
one, three, I don't know what the two middle digits are. It could be a couple of letters, O-6-8-0. C-L-O-6-8-0. Yeah, it is on that one. It's just not on the next page and the next page. Right, and it's, you know, like I say, I can put in what needs to be done, but, you know, since it's okay with my fellow commissioner and Daria, just have somebody
fill it out with you online, and once it's all filled out, print it, sign where you need to sign, and have them just scan it over the barrier, and you'll be good to go. We're not trying to put a stop to this or anything, it's just...
Yeah, it just can't be turned in the way it is, you know, but we'll get it over to you. And if you've got any questions and stuff, you know, you can give Daria a call or she can get in touch with myself or Ben and we can walk you through it. Okay, thanks.
I'm wondering why there's an X on the signature because it's actually on the actual application, which is weird. If you look on the ABCC website, because I know it wasn't there, it wasn't Michael who did it.
I'm looking on the ABCC website right now, and I'm looking at the manager application, and they have the X on manager signature on the actual application. Same with the applicant statement, same thing on the signature, it's crossed. I'm wondering if it does that if you don't start the filling in process online. Yeah. But then it's letting me click on it to fill it out, so that's weird.
It's letting me like click on it. So I don't know. But then you can click on the manager signature. So I don't know. If you were to print it out, because I printed it out for Mike, I believe. Right, Mike? I think I printed it out for you, but I don't remember.
yeah yep um so it came out like that so that's i don't that's not his fault that's just like how it looks on that there's a lot of other missing yeah well because yeah because it's it has the x so it makes sense what page are we what page are we talking about with the x
Um, yeah, I see. Yeah, it's a couple pages. It's literally every, every page Bobby pointed out is there. I don't know why. And when I click on it, just trying to like, it doesn't do anything. It doesn't go away or anything. Applicant statement page Daria.
Which one applicant statement page at the very top where it says I just been, you know, a name or something and see if that gets rid of the x because that's with person that printed name. No, it doesn't. Okay. That's weird.
It is weird. Because it lets you do, it lets you click on the title, like under the signature, but it doesn't let you, it doesn't let me like do anything with the signature. Yeah, because on, on the other one that we approved today, there's no exit. No, yeah. When you say you might have to just start this again, just go back in and just do this whole thing over again and see if that,
I'm looking at a completely blank one. Yeah, I'm looking at there. And we would probably still be able to submit it if there was some, something like some kind of glitch.
Yeah, I mean, if Michael does what we're asking and Texas is still there, he can sign above the box where the- Correct, and we're not gonna be, we're gonna be open to that. Yeah, that's not a problem. I don't know if this, it'll fly with a Cori request form, but I don't see why it wouldn't. Right, if there's nothing he can do, but there is something he can do now
which is, so Mike, another question I have, I know you're a new manager, you're gonna be the new manager, did anybody go to the ABCC training that we had the city held about a month ago for all the liquor license holders? I don't believe so. That I don't know, I'll have to ask the problem on Mike Silvestro. All right, yeah, my hunch was no,
Um, but I just want to say this, you know, online before the meeting, well, like tip certification and all that stuff, you know. Do you have tip certification? Say that again? You know, you're not tip certified, correct? No, so I'm just going to move on into that, you know.
Yeah, I think you would want to get tip certified if we were going to give you the. Have you be the license on record now, the license holder on record also is.
if I'm saying that correctly, license holder and record. But that really does put a burden of responsibility on you for this whole club's liquor license, which could be lost in the event that something is improperly done. Like, I mean, not just serving somebody underage, but serving non-members that have come in without following your proper procedures.
You guys do have to keep a record of people who are coming and going from there. As you know, that's part of the rules. And, you know, any issues have to be reported properly or the club's license is definitely subject to being revoked. So you just want to know exactly what you're signing up for as the license, you know, as the holder of this license.
So I'd recommend the CHIP certification and then properly filling this out and get on next month's agenda. And we can just do this again. Okay. Sound all right? I will come down and collect some paperwork from civilian and all that and move on and move forward. Okay. Yep, I think we can. Okay, Mike. Great. Thank you, Mike. Thank you.
So you can say, Daria, that we just suspended that, pending him, you know, completing the application properly. Hold on, sorry, my, my. They hung up this time, weird. I'll put the phone back on there. Okay, yeah, I said that, I said table did, because it needs to be typed up and then. Yeah.
also needs to be TIP certified and to get on the next month's agenda. Yeah, thanks, Bobby. Now we're not seeing their Cori report now, huh? You notice that? The application, not the actual report. Yeah, you don't see their Cori, we only see like them fill it out, like the application, not the actual Cori. We never did see a Cori report. No. Okay, okay, then I'm just...
Yeah, according to, I think, who was it, Rory that told us, unless you're certified to do Cori reports or read Cori, you can't read, unless you're certified to request a Cori report, you can't read a Cori report. Is that right? I remembered him saying something that like, we're not certified to request them to give us one, but they sort of did that ahead of time, something like that.
Okay, so here, we'll move on to what I have as our final item here. So it's just us here, but the commission will discuss and adopt chapter 138, section 33B, which allows sale of alcoholic beverages by on-premise license on Sunday in certain legal holidays, sales between 10 a.m. to 12 p.m.
Section 33B, in parentheses, Section 33B, the local licensed authority of any city or town which accepts this section may authorize licensees under Section 12 to sell alcoholic beverages between the hours of 10 a.m. and 12 noon on Sundays, the last Monday in May and on Christmas Day or on the following day when said day occurs on a Sunday.
Um, so that's the, uh, that's what we're discussing to adopt. Um, uh, commissioner Delfano is, uh, chairman moderato. Is he fully up to speed on that? We're adopting this. Um, I had mentioned it to him.
um in in passing that you know where he was not going to be here this meeting if he would like us to wait until the following meeting uh our next meeting and all three of us could be here to adopt it yeah
And I kind of unofficially thought he agreed with that. So, you know, we can discuss it a little bit if you like.
but we won't adopt it until the chairman is actually here. And that way the other three of us will do it and do it right. The reason only just briefly, the reason why it came up is I was approached by one of the licensees that wanted to run a special event for that Patriots game that they needed a earlier. They wanted a 9 a.m.
And after looking at 33B, I told them the best that can happen is 10 a.m., but we would have to adopt it for the city. I took it upon myself to go to the city clerk's office to see if it was ever adopted, and they don't have any record of that.
And I took it upon myself even further to give our former chairperson a call to see if he recalled it. And he said that it was adopted. And the only reason why he knows it is there was like a woman's football team that played at Hormel on Sunday mornings that wanted to have alcoholic beverages after the game.
and they granted it for the season.
So, you know, it could be used for a place that does brunches on Sundays. You can just grant it to them year round. Someplace like a club that wants to have a special event just on a certain Sunday, we can grant it that way. A sports team for the season. And that's basically where it came about. But our former chairperson had said that, you know, if the city's got no record of it, they're not going to just take his word that we did do it.
have to adopt it again. So what I was going to suggest is if we all agree that we'd like to adopt it, we'll have Daria send a copy of the motion and a copy of the 13833B that you just read to the clerk's office to file it with the license commission documents in case it ever should come up again. It'll be in the clerk's office where it belongs. That sounds about right.
And as it stands, what time, if not 10 a.m., what time are they allowed to serve? I believe, I don't know why I'm thinking it's 11 a.m. Yeah, me too. Because it was for a one hour earlier. Yeah, I believe it's a one hour earlier. 11 sounds right. I believe it's 11, but I'm not 100% sure.
Well, I mean, that makes sense to me why we would adopt it. And I don't think there's any urgency that we need to do it in this meeting without the chair present, which seems like the right way to handle it. So we've discussed it. Daria, do you think we can put that on next month's agenda? OK. I think we can table it till next month.
discuss it a little further with the chairman as well. Okay, awesome. So we'll move on from that. And then has any other business arisen since we put this agenda together? I know a couple of those one days just came in, but anything else? No, that was it. Okay. So if we don't have any other business, we can all
go about our merry way here. So I can make a motion to end the meeting at 2.03. I second that motion. All in favor? Aye. All right, we're adjourned. Ben, you did a great job. Thank you. You're a natural at it. Yeah.
So I have to do that at work a lot, running meetings. So yeah, maybe it's the beard, though. You might be right. I like that. It looks good. Yeah, well, is that are you guys staying local for for Thanksgiving or traveling or just a small media family at the house? That's about it for me. How about you, Derek? Yeah, just family here. We're hosting it. Yeah, we're going to host here in Medford. So so, you know,
Yeah, the travel on Thanksgiving is rough. You gotta go somewhere. I'm too old for that stuff. Besides driving. Daria, how'd you make out with the license renewal so far? Is it going okay? Yeah, it's fine. You need a hand? No, it's just people coming in at random times. So that's all. All right, if you need any help with anything, I'm around. Okay.
Would you say it looks on track, like people are going to get their stuff in by the end of that month here? It depends. There's about 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.
16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 21 that I have in right now. I still got a couple of weeks. You know, they're going to come in last minute. What do we have, 60 something? Yeah, 60. I think we have like 62, 63.
Do we have to take anything or put anything on the agenda for next month if there are people that don't renew? We just do the regular ABCC stuff. So I'm going to have you guys approve a couple of things. I don't remember now. That's fine. Not right now, but there's a couple of things that I'm going to have to put
for the ABCC so I can send it to them. Okay. This month. Okay. And then congrats Brianna. Yeah, I'll pass it on to her. Yeah. Yes. I didn't know if that would mean we would have a new Daria. I'll never get rid of Daria. Yeah, I just don't know how the government works. That's sort of the changeover.
Yeah, doesn't matter now. All good. I'll send that information over to you. It's marked up and stuff for Michael and, you know, I'm sure he's got somebody that's a little computer savvy that would be able to help them fill this out online.
and just send it back to you. If you're okay with it, Ben, if it comes back good and everything's good, Daria, just send it to us for an okay, or do you want to wait until next month and... Yeah, I mean, I would just say Daria has like her plate full with a lot of applications, so as long as he gets it back, she has enough time, and if it can get to us, yep, we will, you know, kind of feel like we're doing him a favor.
Yeah, no, that's fine. But yeah, I would say that, yeah, I'm okay with it. Yeah, I forgot she had so much on her plate this month.
I'll just, like I say, I'll email it to you, Daria, and you just forward it to him. You don't really have to do anything to do with it, you know? And if you even wanna give him my number, you know, if he's got any questions, he doesn't understand that instead of bothering you when you're trying to do the license renewals, he's more than welcome to give me a call. I'll help him out. Okay. That's great.
Okay. That's really, that's, that's really, that's really helpful. That's helping people out. Cause you know, he's. Yeah, that's, that's what it's all about. You know, exactly. And it's, you know, a private organization, they don't have money to hire lawyers to do all this stuff. They just have to take it like the slightest bit seriously, kind of to, to like the slightest bit, but they have to get all their stuff just so there's never, you know, they take their,
liquor and license serious. That's all we try to get across. That's what I believe we try to get across to them, you know? I mean, whenever I saw it, I says, I can't even read it. It was like the quickest filled out application. Well, hey, that's how they learn, I guess. Yeah. Yeah. That's good. Good catch. Of course. All right, everybody. Okay. Everybody have a nice Thanksgiving. You too. All righty. Take care. Bye.