Hi, I'm Blake.
Hi, I'm Jasmine.
Hi, I'm Marcus.
And we are Graphic Design.
Hi, I'm Mr. Spagnola.
I teach graphic design at Medford Vocational Technical High School.
I'm also the first of two Spagnolas.
Some of the things that we do are made to be fun, they're made to be to industry standards, they're made so that students can get jobs, but all three of them have to do with being interesting.
You don't want people doing something that's just busy work.
So everything we do pertains to getting a job, but also enjoying what you're doing.
The reason that I really got pulled in was because of the environment, the teachers, both of the brothers are very inspiring and I love the way that they do their jobs.
I want kids to want to be here.
I don't want to create an atmosphere where we're constantly pounding you over the head, learn, learn, learn.
You can't learn that way.
in order for learning to happen, in order for the learning experience to happen, it has to be a comfortable environment.
That's the kind of atmosphere that's greatest for learning and for creativity.
My favorite aspect of the shop is my teacher.
He's very caring and funny, but can be strict sometimes.
All of the things that we do have to do with getting a job out in the industry, such as any store, any kind of packaging, all starts on a computer with design, with layout.
And so we teach all of that.
But there's also as basic as sign making.
There's logo creation, branding, and we have a dual path that you could go right out into the industry or you could go to college for graphic design.
I joined the shop because I wanted to pursue my artistic ability and apply it in my academics.
So you can see how there's so much out there for everybody and there's so many roads to different kinds of paths for careers.
Join graphic design!