[SPEAKER_01]: Good evening and welcome to tonight's meeting of the MAPI Community Development Board.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll call the meeting to order.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's begin with some obligatory procedural matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: This hearing of the MAPI Community Development Board is being conducted via remote means.
[SPEAKER_01]: No in-person attendance of members of the public will be permitted, but every effort will be made to ensure that the public can adequately access the proceedings as provided for in Chapter 2 of the Acts of 2023.
[SPEAKER_01]: A reminder that anyone who would like to listen to or view this meeting while in progress may do so by accessing the link
[SPEAKER_01]: that was included on the meeting agenda posted on the city of London website.
[SPEAKER_01]: If despite our best efforts, we are not able to provide real-time access, we will post a recording of this meeting on the city's website as soon as possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: A reminder that given the remote nature of this meeting, tonight all votes from the board will be made by roll call.
[SPEAKER_01]: Please know that project materials for all projects before the board can be viewed on the city's website at recordma.org.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can click on current city board filings.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can also find the link in the chat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Derek, on behalf of the city, if you can please put the link in the chat.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm going to do a roll call attendance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Peter Kautz?
[SPEAKER_01]: Here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just double checking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sabrina Alpino?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not in attendance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Adam Behrens?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yep, here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Annie Strang?
[SPEAKER_01]: Here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ben Lavely.
[SPEAKER_02]: Here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Levali.
[SPEAKER_01]: And myself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I'll give you a few more.
[SPEAKER_02]: No worries.
[SPEAKER_01]: And myself, Jackie McPherson.
[SPEAKER_01]: Derek, would you like to introduce yourself on behalf of the city?
[SPEAKER_00]: Good evening.
[SPEAKER_00]: My name is Derek Seegers.
[SPEAKER_00]: I work at the Office of Planning and Development Sustainability, and I'll be here hosting.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have any questions, please put it in the chat, and I'll do my best to accommodate you any way I can.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you, Derek.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so the first item tonight is a public hearing for 200 Mr. Gabb, special permit to establish a motor vehicle wash.
[SPEAKER_01]: The applicant is requesting a continuous October 30, 2024 meeting because this is a public hearing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need to open the public hearing and read the public hearing notice before it can be continued.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Medford Community Development Board shall conduct the public hearing on October 9th, 2024, after 6.30 p.m.
[SPEAKER_01]: via Zoom relative to an application by New York Capital Investment Group, LLC, for a special permit for a motor vehicle wash with an enclosed structure located in the commercial two zone at 200 Mystic Avenue, Medford Mass, 02155.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now that I've read the public hearing, I am going to ask for a roll call vote to do a motion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, I will ask for the motion first.
[SPEAKER_01]: It continues on October 30th, and then we'll do it by roll call vote.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anyone want to give a motion?
[SPEAKER_02]: I have a motion to continue the 30th.
[SPEAKER_01]: A second?
[SPEAKER_01]: I second that motion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Awesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ben, were you the first?
[SPEAKER_02]: I think so, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then in the second, I thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: All right, we'll call vote.
[SPEAKER_01]: Peter cows.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any strength.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've been lovely.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Adam Aaron's.
[SPEAKER_01]: And myself, Jackie first and I'm an I. Thank you so the 2nd and final.
[SPEAKER_01]: Item for tonight is approval of minutes for 9-4-2024.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before asking for an approval and a motion to accept the minutes, are there any suggested edits?
[SPEAKER_01]: If not, I will ask for a motion to approve the minutes from September 4th, 2024.
[SPEAKER_01]: So moved.
[SPEAKER_01]: Peter?
[SPEAKER_01]: Second.
[SPEAKER_01]: second okay roll call vote Peter Kyle aye Ben Lavallee aye Adam Behrens aye Adam Strang aye and my I'm sorry Annie Strang and myself Jackie McPherson
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so now, unless there's any other items on the agenda for this evening or that I think the board wants to discuss, we can move to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_01]: A motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sorry, Anya, you got the next one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Go ahead, Greg.
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, Annie, are you a second?
[SPEAKER_01]: I second that motion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Awesome, okay, so I will do a roll call.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'd like some stomach peanut cows.
[SPEAKER_02]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ben Lavallee.
[SPEAKER_01]: Annie Strang.
[SPEAKER_01]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_01]: Adam Behrens.
[SPEAKER_02]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_01]: And myself, Jackery Fersen, I'm an aye.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you, everyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Safe travels, Ben.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you all.
[SPEAKER_02]: See you next time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Have a good night.