Good, good. Why don't we have a look at the letter, the draft of the letter. I just took like an hour or so to write it, so I'm totally open to revisions. But let me bring it up here.
Oops. Where the heck is it? Oh, here we go. Okay. Okay. Charlotte, did you and Fred have a chance to look at the letter?
When did the letter come, Chris? I'm not sure when I saw that one. I just sent it out yesterday. Oh, it's yesterday. I saw the minutes. Was it in with those minutes or? I sent it as a separate email. Oh, OK. I guess I've got to keep up on that. OK, now I see it. Let me download it here.
Anyway, let me share my screen so anybody who wants to can have a look at it. Great. Okay, here we go. Share screen. Yes, desktop one. Are we talking about the letter to the homeowner? That's right. Yes, I've read that. Okay. So, as I say, I only worked on this for an hour at the most.
I'm totally open to suggestions, revisions, discarding it, whatever. It's not letting me share my screen. What the heck? Do you have it, Fred? I do. I don't know if I can. Let me see if I can share it here. Yeah, that would be great.
Just made your co-host, so she should be able to. All right. Thank you. I just got to figure out where the little button. Shooter screen. Okay. It's at the bottom in the middle. Yeah. All right. Is that shown? That's it. Okay.
Okay, I have it. All right, so it's very short. Let me just read it. Sure. Neighborhood is graced by over a dozen beautiful pre-Civil War homes, many of them built by wealthy merchants who prospered in Medford shipbuilding industry.
Whether or not you own one of these homes, I hope you'll agree that they should be preserved in a historic district. Redford Historic District Commission and the Massachusetts Historical Commission have both unanimously, both voted unanimously to recommend creation of a South Street Historic District.
The Historic District Commission cordially invites you to attend a public hearing on the South Street District on Thursday, October 12th, 6 p.m. at the Main City Council Chamber at City Hall. Hope to see you there. Yours respectfully, Chris Bader. Okay. Nice and short and sweet, Chris. I like it. Yes. That was the goal. And I wanted to dwell on the theme of the...
of the proposed historic district, that is, it's pre-Civil War, all but a few of the houses are pre-Civil War, and also tie into the shipbuilding industry. I also wanted to make clear that this letter is going out not just to people who own houses in the proposed district, but to anyone who lives within 300 feet of any of these houses. Yeah.
And the historic, the one little twist is the Mass Historical Commission met last night and I attended the meeting. And they also recommended unanimously to create a South Street Historic District. That is they recommended they, what was the exact wording? They recommended that the city of Medford create this district.
Was that unanimous? It was unanimous. Excellent. And by the way, Jennifer Doherty, who is the head of local government programs, she's the new Chris Skelly. This is Honey Badger. Honey Badger, yeah. I gave you your dinner, yeah. Is that our new member?
It's a new member, yes. We're kind of short a member, so I figure Honey Badger could finish it. Well, do you have a way to, I mean, I think it's a good ladder. I wouldn't, hopefully we'll include our little trifold in this, is that? Oh, God, yes. Yes. Absolutely. Maybe just make some reference to please see the attached template. Yes. Yes. No, I can do that. Absolutely. I would say in the third sentence paragraph,
public hearing, and I would just reiterate, we're officially calling it the South Street Historic District, is that? Oh, okay. It's in the second sentence, but I think it should be in the third, just so it's clear that that's what we're talking about. Oh, sure. Okay, yeah. I can add that, absolutely. And then I guess we've got to, you know, you're going to print paper copies of this as well? Yes, I want to print them on nice, you know, heavyweight,
letter paper and I want to print the trifold on something appropriate for a brochure. Not just paper, but the typical trifold, the typical very, I don't know what to call it, very light cardboard maybe that trifolds are usually printed on. Like a glossy cardstock?
Yes, exactly. Yeah, I'm sure, depending on where we get it printed, I mean, Staples has... I was going to go to Staples. Yeah, they'll know what to do if you tell them. Yeah, I think I could just send them the PDFs and, you know, give them my credit card and I can just pick them up probably in a day. Yeah, I've done it a lot. They have an online
yeah well i saw that pdf so it's right and hopefully they'll get it right yes yes the tri-folder printing on both sides it's got to be printed both side which means it has to be oriented the right way and then and then yeah we can fold it whatever but uh so it's got to be a very specific sort of um yeah i will look at what
Order. I'll call the people at Staples and say, you know, do the. Does it have to be. Like, what is the orientation of the two pages, presumably the orientation should be the same. Right. Yeah, but sometimes I mean, just when I'm printing at the office and stuff, I know.
Yeah. Like if you're printing in landscape mode, sometimes the other page gets upside down or, you know. And it is landscape, so it is going to be tricky. Yeah. No, I will definitely attend to that issue. So is anything missing from this besides the word historic in the third paragraph?
I think about mentioning the three houses that are not pre-Civil War, because they're really, you know, I don't want to put a footnote in a short letter. No, I don't think we would do that. But I think the only question would be whether we flesh out what our meeting, the public hearing is for, if you add a little.
The public hearing allows, you know, whatever, feedback, and we could take some language out of the MHC guidelines of what the public hearing's for, just so somebody getting it would know that this is a, it's sort of a legally binding responsibility that we have to do, and that we're going to vote on it or whatever, or at least make comments on it.
So it's an opportunity for the public to- Is that something the recipient of this letter has to know? I can explain it at the meeting. Well, I was saying, I wonder if we would have, I'd have to look at, maybe I could find that, the outline, New York district or whatever, which I know I have in my folder here somewhere.
I could refer to maybe the statutory. The public hearing required by statute. Yeah, so it's part of the. Sorry, I got to. I can't open up my.
Yeah, anyway, I don't think we really need it. You know, we can say the, or we can just say pursuant to Mass General Laws 40C. I think that would probably be enough. Yeah, because we're on the way on this flowchart. Yeah.
MHC within 14 days written notice to property owners. So we're do that and then we have to prepare the warrant article assuming we get through the public hearing. Okay. Yeah, it's up to you if you don't want to do that and that's fine. We can explain it at the meeting, but it is sort of illegal. I would prefer to explain it at the meeting. But if you're more comfortable if you want to put it in the language.
Pursuant to Mass General Laws 40C, blah, blah, blah, we will be holding a public meeting. I'm happy to do that. Okay, yeah. I mean, I wouldn't, I wouldn't, I don't think it's going to hurt it. I think it would make it more. Yeah, make it more official sounding. Like it's an official hearing. Yeah, yeah. Other than that, and then attach the
by full brochure and a reference to it in the letter. Yeah. So I don't know, Chris, if you've got an email or rather a text or a cell phone for Joe that we could text him and ask him to get on the call. I assume- Let me see. I'm assuming Chris Donovan is no longer interested. I don't know what the story is with him.
Yeah, he hasn't been I could text him. I have his phone number, but yes. If you could just ask him to pop in for five minutes. We would appreciate it. Let's see if I have Joe. I don't think I do. Just a minute. Let me check my email here.
So can you text Chris and I will look at look for Joe's number.
What's quorum? Is that what it is? Quorum? Quorum, yes. Q-U-O-R-U-M. All right. I'll just send him a text. Oh, wait. He just replied. Oh, tonight? Yeah. Joe is not going to be able to make it. I'll try to make it to the meeting after I leave the Brooks.
Oh, he's going to something for his kids. Yeah. All right. So that's that's probably not going to happen. Yeah, let's see if we can get Chris Donovan just for. Well, I don't know, I think he got a little. A change of heart after joining our commission, I guess, I don't know. I think so.
Do you have his number? I have Chris's, uh, yeah, I just sent him this text. I have his number here. I don't necessarily want to call him though. No, no, but just text him and say, and ask him if he can spare us five minutes. Yeah, no, I, I did that. So, oh, no response. Not yet. Let's just sit in the waiting room somewhere. Well,
It may be that just having the minutes created, Ryan's not going to be happy that the minutes are not approved. No, he wants that. We got three of us on the call. We need four for a quorum. Yeah, we need four for a quorum. Melanie is out of town.
I honestly don't know why she couldn't, you know, dial in, but, but, um, she doesn't like to do that when she's traveling on business. Yeah. So, um, well, otherwise, I mean, we can try to pull a quick meeting with, uh, meet for a few minutes, uh, I mean, with Joe rather when he's done with everything. Yeah. Um, why don't we try.
Are you guys available tomorrow night for a few minutes? Yeah, I'm available. Charlotte? I think at what time? Around the same, six o'clock? Six o'clock, yeah. Yeah, that should work for me. Okay, I'll just ping Joe and say, hey, can you make it to a five-minute meeting tomorrow evening?
Because I think we all have things to do tonight. I can, well, whatever, depending on what time Joe comes on here. So Chris, I guess the question I had was on these meetings. Let me just see. Yeah, yeah. If you want to bring up the minutes and any corrections or changes of format or whatever.
Pardon me, I'm still in the grip of COVID, sort of COVID light, you might say, because I had my booster only a couple of weeks before I got it. Oh, my, really? Yeah. Well, it doesn't make me feel good about getting the booster, though. It is not surprising. It doesn't keep you from getting it.
it keeps you from getting really sick. Maybe there's some value in preventing it, but I don't think that's its main purpose. I could be wrong. All right. I haven't trouble bringing this thing up and everything, Chris, so all right. Okay. Yeah, let's try to meet tomorrow night at six.
And I will ping and I will let you know, you guys know in advance. We'll just meet for a couple of minutes to say aye or whatever. Yeah. I'll just look at it.
I think any send me send me any corrections, Fred, or, you know, comments on format, or this is the first time I've done this. Well, that's why I'm Chris Donovan. Now he was he voted him to be secretary. I know he did. He did exactly once. As far as I can determine, he did the minutes exactly once. Yeah, that was for the meeting in which he was elected. Yeah. So we're in a bit of a jam there. So yeah.
All right, all right. Teresa, are you helping us with the meeting? Oh, right. Yes, yes, Teresa. Are you available tomorrow evening for a few minutes? I'm not 100% sure of my plans for tomorrow, but I'm sure between Dennis and I, one of us can hang out with you lovely folks for 15, 20 minutes tomorrow. It's not gonna be 15 minutes. It'll be five minutes. Okay.
But is there something you're able to do for us on behalf of the lovely city that you can do meeting minutes? Do meeting minutes? Oh, gosh, no. I'd be happy to help. Here's the back story, Teresa. Just so this doesn't come as a surprise. We've had trouble. Our ostensible secretary, Chris Donovan, is missing in action.
I asked the mayor maybe six, nine months ago if we could get some support from City Hall. Of course, you'd be reimbursed for your time, but a lot of towns and cities have executive secretaries. It just means a person like you or Dennis attends the meeting, actually does the minutes and posts them to the website.
And your department, there's stuff in our budget for this. And presumably, you would actually get a piece of that. I don't know. But I mean, that's up to Alicia. But anyway, just so that's not a surprise to you, that's something that's coming. Certainly. And my role has changed in City Hall, so I'm not a QA. Oh, it has. Yes, I'm then a CPA manager.
Community Preservation Act, so I'm a grant funder. Okay, so you're on top of the whole thing that Ryan has got his tail in and out about. He, he, he, don't say I said that. I have no idea what you're talking about. Yes, Ryan and I talk daily.
It basically we need for some kind of compliance situation, we need minutes for every meeting that we approved any certificates. And that's been going by the wayside.
And what I did in the past few days is just watch the meetings. I figured out what meetings we actually issued certificates, and I watched them over on the video. And then I wrote down the minutes, which I sent out to Fred and Charlotte and company.
And I was hoping to approve them tonight, but that apparently is not going to happen. So let's meet tomorrow for a few minutes. I want to make sure that Joe is available. If not, I will cancel and reschedule for some time where everybody can do it. Great. I'm sure there's some deadline that. Yeah, I'm sure there is.
And when we talked to Ryan, whatever, last meeting of the week before, he was going to request some administrative help from City Hall. So that's Theresa. You're a new face here. I thought that was you had been in Shanghai. Yeah. Or the press gang. That's what they used to call it. There you go. You know what a press gang is, Theresa? I do. I do. And yes, I've definitely felt that some days.
Now, in terms of, yeah, we're just realizing, you know, your commission and the historical commission, you just keep doing bigger and better things, which is exactly what the commissions were put in place to do. So with that, I agree wholeheartedly, having more administrative help would be beneficial.
whether or not we can budget it's another thing, but you know I am an advocate for it. Supposedly there's $1,500 in the budget for administrative support from whatever your department is called now. PDF.
Okay, I'm pretty sure that I did see some sort of a budget line item there. 1,500 doesn't really... I know, that's not a lot, but I think we can probably carve out more because we're not going to spend the whole... We have 5,000 for special projects, so we can probably divert some of that to the admin support budget. Okay.
Well, let me let me connect with Alicia. Alicia Hunt is my boss, even in this new role. I'll try to see what I can do to influence getting that. I just did the math that does equate out to the typical staff stipend for a monthly support budgeted for them.
We just need to find somebody who wants to do so. Yes. All right. OK. OK. I'll see you guys tomorrow night if possible. That is if Joe can make it. Otherwise, we'll meet some other night. OK. Right. We're meeting you. Thank you guys. A message of who we are not meeting. Correct. Absolutely. Absolutely. OK. Can you throw me down on that one, Chris? Yes, I can.