housekeeping items to handle before we start the meeting.
But good evening and welcome to the meeting of the Medford Community Development Board.
I'll call the meeting to order.
We will begin with some obligatory procedural matters.
This hearing of the Medford Community Development Board is being conducted via remote means.
No in-person attendance of members of the public will be permitted, but every effort will be made to ensure that the public can adequately access the proceedings as provided for in Chapter 2 of the Acts of 2023.
A reminder that anyone who would like to listen to or view this meeting while in progress may do so by accessing the link that was included on the meeting agenda posted on the City of Medford's website.
If despite our best efforts, we are not able to provide real time access, we will post a recording of this meeting on the city's website as soon as possible.
A reminder that given the remote nature of this meeting tonight, all votes from the board will be made by roll call.
Please also know that the project materials for all projects before the board can be viewed on the city's website, and that website is methodinmay.org.
And you would go to current city board filings, and you can also find a link in the chat
Someone from the city of Medford will put it there.
I will now do roll call attendance.
Vice Chair Emily Hederman.
Present.
Peter Cowles.
Ari Fishman.
Present.
Pam Marianski.
Sally Akiki.
Present.
And myself, Jackie McPherson.
Danielle, can you introduce any staff on the call?
Yes, myself, Daniel Evans, senior planner in the Office of Planning, Development, and Sustainability.
Also with us is Alicia Hunt, the director of Planning, Development, and Sustainability.
And also we have Gabe Weinstein, who is our graduate student intern this summer.
Thank you, Danielle.
So our first agenda item is 400 Mystic Ave.
It's a special permit and a site plan review.
It's an application from Herb Chambers at 400 Mystic, and it's 400 Mystic LLC for the site plan review to permit the construction of a new three-story structure to replace the existing three-story structure, renovation of the existing five-story structure, along with modifications to the existing parking, vehicular circulation, landscape, and utilities associated with the proposed Herb Chambers-Toyota Boston.
In addition, the proposal requires special permits for the following motor vehicle-related uses.
That's H3, motor vehicle sales or rental of new vehicles only, accessory storage entirely with an enclosed structure, H4, outdoor motor vehicle sales and storage accessory to H3.
Commercial two, zoning district.
This meeting is a, this is an actual continued public hearing from June 5th.
I'm going to ask the Medford City staff to do introductory comments.
before inviting the client to present a proposal.
Yes, so as you recall, this was a public hearing that was opened on June 5th.
The applicant gave a presentation of their initial plans and in response to some staff concerns and concern to the board, they made some revisions to the plans.
Staff was able to review those and
We are recommending approval with some conditions, primarily some engineering conditions and traffic, but we'll go into those later.
But we can turn it over to the applicant team.
Who will be presenting for the applicant?
If you can introduce yourselves and you can begin your proposal or your presentation.
You're on mute, Frank.
And who's actually presenting?
Very, very sorry.
Good evening, Chairperson McPherson.
Frank Marinelli, I'm Land Use Counsel for the Herb Chambers Companies.
It's good to see you all again since the hearing on June 5th.
And as Danielle Evans pointed out, we have made and submitted plan revisions, which our engineering team, Gabe Crocker and Dave Newhall,
will go through with the board.
Also here tonight, just for recap, is John Welch, who's the director of construction for the Herb Chambers companies.
And as I mentioned, the engineering team from Crocker Design, also our landscape architect,
Julie Lucier of Ryan Associates.
The last time, just briefly, we summarized, as Ms.
Evans just recited to the board, the site is about 4.86 acres.
It's in the C2 zone.
And we do need the special permits that the chair referenced in the legal notice, as well as the site plan review.
We presented the last time that the existing five story building will be renovated.
Four stories will be motor vehicle sales and showroom, as we've shown on the architectural plans.
And then we're replacing the current three story
adjunct building with a brand new building, three stories, over 140,000 square feet.
The first floor is about 40 service bays.
And then the second and third floors are approximately 106 parking spaces interior on each floor is pretty robust landscaping as Julie went over the last time and the last time on June 5,
we did have the presentation of the architectural plans and also Gabe and Dave, our engineering team went through the site plan.
So at that time, as Danielle has pointed out, there were suggestions to
make on, and those plan revisions were made, and Dave and Gabe will cover those.
Essentially, it was the handicap accessibility at the crosswalks of Mystic were improved.
We shifted the curb cuts on Fulbright further away from Fulbright and Mystic intersection.
We adjusted that intersection so that it forces a slower vehicle speed when approaching the intersection.
We added a sidewalk along Fulbright Street.
We achieved the 5% interior landscaping requirements.
We're going to be discussing with MassDOT the bus stop, which we'd like to enclosure across the street that we're proposing.
And we have two solar-powered pedestrian signals.
We've added pavers.
It was suggested the last time that we match the design in front of Colonial Volkswagen.
And we did that, we made that.
We have a landscaped area between the sidewalk and Mystic Ave.
We raised the concrete crosswalk across Mystic Ave.
We reduced impervious area and the solar we did achieve.
We're proposing a solar on the new addition.
And we have about 57% solar coverage.
So with that, with the chair's permission, I'd like to turn it over to Dave Newhall and Gabe Crocker of Crockett Design, and they can further describe these plan revisions.
And then we're happy to answer any questions the board or the public may have.
And we appreciate
Danielle Evans making herself available on July 2nd.
We had a work session on June 4th with Todd Blake and Daniel Evans.
And then we had another work session on July 2nd and Danielle was on vacation out of state, but made herself available.
We appreciate that very much and hope that the plans we've submitted meet with the board's approval tonight.
Thank you.
Thank you, Frank, for the record.
David Newhall with Crocker Design Group, Civil Engineers for the project.
So just to take Frank's summary to the next level, give you a little bit more detail of the changes that we did make.
So starting with the handicap accessibility and overall pedestrian circulation on the site and the changes that we had made.
So previously,
We had shown modifications out front to the sidewalk and the curb cut on Mystic Ave.
We've modified those changes.
Main thing being for the sidewalk that was along Mystic Ave here, we added in the landscape buffer to match what is across the street in front of the Volkswagen dealership.
The only spot in which it doesn't have the landscaping buffer is where the existing bus stop is that's going to remain as we had to show the concrete sidewalk going around that.
Additionally, we've added a raised concrete
sidewalk at the entrance.
It's very similar to, or it will be similar to all the existing curb cuts that are along Mystic Ave.
So this will be at grade.
There won't be a ramp down.
It'll stay the same slope going across.
We do have detectable warning strips at each edge of the sidewalk, just so for anybody crossing the sidewalk, they know they're coming up to an intersection where cars will be
accessing and leaving the site.
Additionally, we added in this crosswalk here so now if there's somebody who is coming to the dealership they drop off their vehicle to be serviced and they're going to leave it for the day and use public transportation.
They can now exit the service area and come across using this crosswalk then we have a concrete sidewalk that will then
bring you over to either this bus stop here or you can use the other crosswalk which we've added here at the Fulbright Street and Mystic Ave intersection and then come across Mystic Ave to access this second bus stop that's being proposed.
Additionally, we've added in a crosswalk to the rear of the property so we had a concrete
sidewalk that wrapped around the entirety of the proposed addition on the last rendition.
This one now takes it so if we have any service members who work at the dealership, their main area and locker rooms are back here, they can, they have now two options to walk to the bus stop, they can either come around the building along this crosswalk, which kind of leads them to not having the best ability here as this is more of an operational
area or they can use this crosswalk here, come down our concrete sidewalk and then we have the added Fulbright Street crosswalk.
We then have detectable warning strips and another crosswalk across this Fulbright Street curb cut that will bring you to the two bus stops that we had mentioned.
Additionally, we had the two curb cuts along Fulbright Street.
We originally were opposing to keep those where they were.
Todd Blake had some very good comments about seeing what we could do to push those further away from Mystic Ave and from that intersection.
So we moved them as far as we could up the screen here and further away from this intersection.
We also widened these curb cuts from where they are existing for better access onto the site.
So when we have car carriers access the site, they can come in, enter here, offload on site, and then be able to leave and exit.
Additionally, we aligned this curb cut as best we could with this back drive aisle, which mimics how
the current site operates where the curb cut is more here and the drive aisle is here.
So it is a lot like how it is today.
It's also wider.
We're proposing there was a utility pole here.
We're just proposing to have two new utility poles that span across it to relocate that and be able to still have our power to our site come along here and route how it does today.
Additionally, in terms of making this intersection safer by having this curb cut further away, we're proposing to have this be more of a T. So previously, this intersection, you could come around this corner fairly quickly just because of how it was just a smooth curb.
Now it's more of a 90 degree turn, so you have to slow down.
to come and access this curb cut.
So increasing the safety of pedestrians that might be using this crosswalk or vehicles leaving from this curb cut vehicle travel will be a lot slower than the existing condition is.
Additionally, on the Fulbright Street, we have the added sidewalk.
When we did that, we didn't put it in
leave the edge of pavement where it is.
We pushed it into the edge of pavement so that we could keep our landscape buffer along our parking here and on the back side of the sidewalk.
Additionally, we just continued this street edge down so then we gain some green space along the backhand side of this second curb cut, so reducing impervious within our site to add more green space as well than what we had previously proposed.
Additionally,
for our landscaping.
One of the main things we heard was about this area over here and the sea of parking.
So we've added in two landscape islands here we had a break just
our stormwater design to make sure we have water going where it needs to go as we're treating it and that's properly functioning.
So that's why there's two and there's a two foot break to allow stormwater to travel through one of our catch basins.
Additionally, we added a proposed paver walkway.
So adding in to have better access for anybody looking to view the vehicles or in
In case there is an emergency for fire safety, they have the landscape island plus the walkway.
So it's double of what just the landscape area would be and help breaking up this area as well.
Additionally, we've added in landscape islands along the front parking area that is along the Mystic Ave area.
These changes help allow us to now meet that 5% requirement for interior landscaping.
And we also have the amount of trees being proposed for the site per the landscaping requirement.
Additionally, on our access around the site, the pedestrian crossing here, we added in two signals, they'll be solar powered signals so we don't have to do any trenching within Mystic Ave.
So, if somebody is coming to cross this parking lot, they'll just hit the button, it'll flash saying, hey, people are trying to cross and likewise on this side as well.
Additionally, we also added in pavers and another location on the site.
So we added this paver walkway.
We also added some pavers for parking across from where you have the showroom entrance, and then also from the main dealership entrance here.
So, getting less pavement and adding in more pavers as well.
And then,
As Frank had mentioned, we provided the solar exhibit showing the proposed solar for the addition and for the total site to meet that solar requirement.
Additionally, we did explore that option B that was discussed of when we have to go, we have a number of items that are within Mystic Ave, within the right of way that need to have mass DOT approval.
So we did explore and did provide the exhibit for the option B, which would be a right in, right out for this parking here.
Wait for this to load.
One second.
So this here shows that option B that we were discussing.
to make sure we considered.
So we heard the feedback that one of the applications had to come back because they were forced to have write-in, write-out.
So we went back with our traffic engineers and this would be the option B for write-in, write-out if we're unable to have full access like we're proposing in the site plan set as it is now.
We would keep this raised concrete sidewalk going across
And then we would also add in a landscape island in the middle to enforce that nobody could be coming down Mystic Ave and try to make this left-hand turn or come out of the entrance and try to make this left.
It forces the traffic to be right out and then to be right in.
I think that would cover the changes we've made.
And with that, we'd like to turn it over to questions.
Thank you so much.
I have a clarifying question on your plan B, if there was any feedback from Todd, the actual traffic engineer from the city.
Daniel, do you have that information, if there was feedback on that?
Yeah, we were in the meeting when this was shown to us, and I believe that Director Blake
didn't have any concerns with this scenario plan B in the event that it's needed.
We could put in some language in the conditions that it could be tweaked slightly.
If it's the scenario that's to be taken, and if it has to be moved slightly, that it would not require
a trip back to the board, but I defer to you all.
Well, the language can just cover that.
It would have to be in coordination with director Blake and MassDOT to make sure that it was at the city and MassDOT's standards or something to that?
Yeah, I think some language to that effect that covers in case there's something
that would need to be slightly modified.
But I don't believe that Todd had any misgivings about this alternative access in the event that MassDOT requires it.
I just want to make it as simple as possible, but at the same time, clarify it so that it can actually move forward easily.
Right.
Are there any clarifying questions from the board before I open it up to the public?
Peter Kelce?
I don't have a question, but I think for
regulatory reasons i need to attest that i did uh watch the hearing of the recording of the hearing of june 5th so as to be up to date on this project and be able to vote on it i just want to get that on the record before we move forward and forget about it thank you very much all right i'm going to go ahead and open it up for public comment um those who wish to provide comments can use the raise hand feature or message danielle in the comments
You can send an email to ocdmedford-ma.gov.
Before providing your comments, please state your name and address for the record and remind all meeting participants to please refrain from using the chat function to provide comments as it is not part of the public record.
However, if a participant is having audio or other technical difficulties, this may be entered into the chat to alert myself and staff.
Danielle, can you manage the public comment queue and read any previously sent emails or letters?
It doesn't look like we have any members on.
Madam chair, I don't see any raised hands and I have not received any written comments from the public.
Awesome.
And I think we can officially close the public comment period for this meeting.
And so that brings us back to the draft recommendation and conditions so better understand what we are moving forward with.
Again, if there's any questions or comments from the board at this time, before I move to motion or approve, are you understanding what we are working with now?
And Danielle, for clarifications on the conditions in the offsite, I am not sure what offsite conditions, Director Blake, that have not been addressed to include with the draft conditions.
Yeah, I'll defer to Peter.
If we think that it was everything captured on the plans, because usually we would put things in writing if it doesn't appear on the plans.
But because I was looking at that, well, while the while the applicant was presenting, I was looking at the provided layout plans just to check it against Todd's comments from the
uh last go around and it seems that everything off-site is captured i think we will have to put something uh daniel as you said something in the manner of like if in just authorization discussions with mastod that something comes up that has to be changed that that can be run through todd and through pds without having to come back to the board assuming it's not a major change but other than that uh
Other than that, it looks like everything Todd mentioned in his... Everything Todd mentioned in his comments were, in fact, captured in the plans, both on-site and off-site.
We will have to include some language for the off-site ones just because of the MassDOT approval that's needed in case MassDOT needs any changes.
But it looks like, at least in my view, that, I mean,
The RFB, the pavement markings, sidewalk on Fulbright, the curb radius on the corner at Fulbright, the bus shelter, and the accessibility are all in there.
So that covers the offsite stuff.
And so for the draft recommendations from previously, these have been rectified for the most part as well.
We had eight drafts.
And I want to make sure that we're on the same page with the proponent.
What are the drafts?
What's the remaining conditions?
So, Madam Chair, regarding the engineering comments, Director Hunt was able to connect with City Engineer today about whether one of the conditions or comments was addressed.
I guess this would be a question for the
engineering team here.
It's regarding the waterline service to the proposed hydrant located in the parking lot just south of the building, that the pipe should be reduced directly after the T and valve to limit the amount of stagnant water within the pipe.
And then he also said the second gate is not necessary.
Was that addressed or looked at?
Yes, we did look at that and we've made the change in our plans.
We haven't resubmitted our utility plan yet.
He had some other some minor comments on just the stormwater aspect of it.
So we're just working through just comprehensively addressing his comments.
We haven't received full comments.
We just want to make sure we got all the comments before we resubmitted but we have no issues with that.
The comments regarding the water.
and the hydrant line and the valves and addressing those as he had suggested.
Okay, then I would, through the chair, I would suggest that we, that condition remain.
And, you know, prior or the applicant, you know, shall submit an updated utility plan that addresses the city engineers' comments and concerns per
the email correspondence with myself.
So beginning from condition one, that was highlighted with control plans.
Plan modifications have been resubmitted but have control plans.
So the revised plans that were submitted the other week,
So all the plans should be updated, and I'll correlate.
But I think that we could, it sounds like one of the plans that needs to be submitted that hasn't been submitted yet is an updated utility plan.
So I guess this is a question for the applicant.
Of the plans that were submitted, how many are outstanding that need to be updated so that we are referencing the correct plans?
Sorry.
For our civil plans, we'll have a C5 and C6 are our grading and drainage and utility plans.
So it's those two sheets.
that will have some minor modifications just to address the comments received from Owen and the city engineering staff on our stormwater submission.
Yes, I think the control documents should be ones that we've received already.
And then as modified by
the written conditions which would be incorporating the new utility plans when they come in.
So I think we'll be covered there.
And then I'm just going to go through just to, so we're not, and then we came to number three on your end, requotation.
of the builder permit?
Yep, so that's one of our standard conditions that the entire decision be recorded, the registry of deeds, evidence provided before they're able to pull a building permit.
Then we'll have the traffic and transportation conditions regarding any of the off-site work, basically describing the
Coordination with MassDOT and, you know, final approvals from Director Blake.
Or we try to keep the approvals with the position, so the Director of Transportation or Traffic and Transportation.
And then language regarding the Scenario 2.
City engineers' conditions regarding the water line service.
And I believe that is all of any special conditions that we would need.
Everything else would be required.
Sometimes we do call out that linkage, that this project is subject to linkage.
Kirk house, are you taking down the new conditions or you, um, as we go along, I'm just curious.
As we've been discussing, I've been, uh, writing out based on the, uh, draft conditions that, uh, city staff wrote up and things we're discussing to kind of have a running list of the, of the conditions we will actually need.
Okay.
Thank you.
And have we wordsmithed for that scenario?
We have to decide on language regarding the MassDOT access permit for scenario two?
Madam Chair, I believe we can do some wordsmithing after the fact, as long as the gist of the condition is conveyed and agreed upon by the board.
And then I can work with the applicant's attorney
sharpen up the language and make sure everything is correct and be interpreted by somebody who wasn't at the meeting.
That's going to be one of my questions, probably my only remaining question about the traffic and transportation conditions.
At this point,
If we can do wordsmithing after the fact, as long as the general point gets across, what is the condition surrounding the, what's it called, the, yeah, the alternative, the scenario two?
Is there a separate condition for that right now, other than saying that should modifications be required due to mass-out approval that that,
that further city approval of those changes would be delegated to the Director of Traffic and Transportation?
Because would that not cover the offsite modifications as well as the scenario to modification to the driveway?
I think it'd be good to call it out as a separate condition regarding
you know, in the event that the access permit isn't approved.
Okay.
You know, an unrestricted approval.
Gotcha.
Okay.
I'll write something up for that.
Okay, so going over the conditions,
want to take a shot at the conditions before right before I recommend the motion for special event and the site plan review.
Do we want to take a shot to make sure that the board is okay with the conditions either the city or Peter
Just one second to finish this sentence on our last thought.
All right, so this is what I have for draft conditions.
Appliant shall comply with standard city conditions regarding control plans, modification approvals, and recordation.
Applicant shall submit an updated utility plan that complies with engineering department comments as noted.
If MassDOT approval is denied for off-site improvements on Mystic Avenue, approval shall be delegated to the Director of Traffic and Transportation.
And if MassDOT access permit is denied and
The main driveway access is required to change to the scenario 2 access.
As noted, approval shall be delegated to the Director of Traffic and Transportation.
And that's what I have.
And do we want to keep the waterline here for now, Danielle, as well?
Yes.
Okay.
Is that an additional or is that covered under complies with engineering department comments as noted?
With updated utilities, I think that covers- Yeah, that's the updated utility plan, right?
Yes.
Okay.
So I will ask for a motion to approve first the special permit for 400 Mystic Ave.
make the motion along with the conditions as read by clerk house.
Do I need to say that whole thing?
No, you don't have to read that.
I just need a motion and a second.
And I'll second.
Okay.
Thank you.
And we will do a roll call.
Vice Chair Emily Hederman?
Aye.
Ari Fishman?
Peter cows.
Hi.
Marioski.
Hi, Sally Kiki.
Hi, myself, Jackie McPherson.
I'm an eye.
And we have approval for site plan for 400 mystic have with the draft conditions as read by clerk cows.
Any second?
I'll second the motion.
Vice Chair Emily Hederman?
Aye.
Peter Kautz?
Ari Fishman?
Aye.
Pam Mariansky?
Sally Aciki?
Aye.
And myself, Jackie McPherson, I'm an aye.
And I believe that concludes our business for 400 Mystique
have.
Thank you all for being here.
Attorney Baronelli, the design engineering teams, Mr. Hemingway, we appreciate you being here.
Yes, Madam Chair, and on behalf of the Herb Chambers companies, we want to thank you, the board, and also the Planning and Sustainability Department, the Director Hunt and Daniel Evans and Dennis McDougal, who we work with on the zoning board approval.
It's been a pleasure to work with the city over the past
here, and I know that Mr. Chambers looks forward to this investment in the city of Medford and to the redevelopment of the site.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Have a great evening.
You too.
Thank you.
Have a great night.
So our next item is minutes, but we don't have any for approval as of right now.
No, Madam Chair, they're not ready yet.
So at the next meeting.
Okay.
So then unless there's anything else that anyone wants, for one, I believe this is Pam's last board meeting with us.
We want to thank her for all of her help.
and efforts.
Of course.
Thank you for having me.
And thank you for staying along with us as long as possible.
And I wish you well, personally.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
Great.
Great working with you, Pam.
Thank you.
You too.
Thank you all.
And I will, with that, yes.
I want to thank Pam, but I also just wanted to give you all an update on another project, just as an FYI.
Okay.
The raising canes, which went through site plan review with this board, it's getting pretty close to being finished.
There's some pavements and markings that are not done yet.
They're still waiting for a line from
uh national grid to come in but I did a preliminary walk through before signing the occupancy you know going through with the checklist from the conditions from this board and so I would just invite any of you if you want to take a look over there informally if you care to you know if you think I didn't see anything other than obviously not all the paving and markings are in yet um but I just
I really dislike going to a company that thinks that they're 100% and finding things.
So we've been encouraging the department heads to take a look now and just see as they're hitting the last bits.
there anything that we dislike or think isn't correct and I just thought I would share that with you all if you care to take a look if you do ever see anything in that site or any other site where you say that's not how I remember it like how I remember we approved it you are always welcome to reach out to us directly and say that.
And it is much preferred that you do it before they actually open, because we still have authority before we give them the occupancy permit.
It looks good.
I have to take a closer look for the bike racks.
But I go to that stop and shop all the time.
And I've been watching it go up.
Yeah.
I go to that stop and shop.
I go over there a lot.
And my only question is, I mean, this has nothing.
This doesn't take away from it at all.
But they have fans.
I'm like, what's with all the fans in their driveway?
What is that?
Oh, tell them, Gabe, because you went with me and you're familiar with their operations from other locations.
Yeah.
Basically, it's for like when it's the drive through a lot of the staff, they'll go there if it gets busy and just to keep them cool.
Oh, yeah.
I remember that Apple stand out there with iPads.
I remember that when we were talking about when we were approving them, they were talking about their like congestion management.
If the drive through gets really busy is they'll just send people out with iPads.
That is pretty amazing.
Gosh, my husband is going to get a kick out of that.
I just want to know, what did you approve those fans for?
We didn't approve fans.
I don't know what that means.
What is fun is obviously the national grid line isn't in, so they don't have electricity yet, but you do sometimes watch them just from convection, just kind of spinning on their own.
So they have like temporary construction electricity, but not their, not their official reel.
And there's certain things they can't do until their final connection is connected.
I mean, yeah.
And I mean, I'm pretty sure these are just blowing in the wind slash circulating air because they're all going to different, they're all going different directions at different speeds.
Yeah.
I definitely thought that like sort of like a wind chime, chime, whatever.
I don't know.
I mean, if I was looking correctly, and I'm usually just there going back and forth to stop and shop, it looks like, in a very smart move for New England, it looks like they've got fans, and in between the fans are heat lamps.
There was another whole year, right?
There was another very small project that I don't remember honestly, if this board provided guidance to the city council, because the energy and environment committee talked about it extensively is at stop and shop, putting in some electric chargers that are, will have video screens on them as like advertising to pedestrians.
And they'll be very close to the stop and shop.
to the front entrance and that was actually approved by the city council a year ago or more than a year ago.
They've just come back around saying they want to install them now.
I honestly thought that project had gone away, but you'll also see that coming.
There'll be two vehicle charging stations for free at stop and shop.
Add supported EV charging.
Opportunity cost.
Well, I mean, it's better than the gas pumps.
They have ads on them, and you still have to pay for the gas.
I was going to say, the ads are already on the gas pumps, aren't they?
I don't know about Stop and Shop, I can't remember, but I know they're everywhere else.
Yeah, they're there.
For future meetings, it'd be cool to hear updates on projects we've talked about.
This was really cool to hear, Alicia.
Thank you so much for sharing this.
But whether it's H-Mart, Bank of America, I'm trying to think of other projects that we've come through.
Obviously, there's a ton on the agenda.
I will tell you that those two are ones that I get asked a bunch about, and we haven't actually heard from those.
Bank of America is under construction, but they're not close enough to occupancy to be talking to us yet.
Yeah, I don't think, last time I was over by Wegmans, I don't think they're above the fence line yet that I could see.
Yeah, and I know the H Mart's not open.
I drive up by it probably more than you all do.
My dentist is right next door and I keep, that's the only thing I know and I go over there and I don't see it.
They're still alive, they're still
moving forward.
Well, they're busy.
They're popping up all over.
They opened the Davis Square one already, but that was it.
They're popping up all over the place because they took over the old Be Fresh in Davis Square.
Yeah, yeah.
So that was easier for them to move into that space since it already fit out as a food market.
So this is a gym.
So it's taking more time, but the project is still very much alive and it's going forward.
That's great.
Our interns will be glad to hear that they were asking about HMART and that there's a rumor that it was not happening.
But glad to hear that that's not true.
And they're actually, they're telling us that tough students will be over the moon about the Raising Canes, that they're taking the T all the way into the city and back out to go to the one by BU.
So, yeah.
Yeah.
I realize college kids really love chicken, all kinds of chicken.
The other one that we're working with is the Great American Beer Hall.
And we've actually compiled a list from all the departments of things that they were needed and sent that to them, which they found to be very helpful.
And they are shooting for a mid-August opening.
It is unclear from their construction schedule, their status, if that's actually going to hit that timeline.
That's optimistic, given what I last saw of their building.
I saw that they had a sign up in the rear today.
Yes.
And if you didn't see it on social media, they announced a chef, that the chef from Snappy Patties is going to be, is going to run a, basically a restaurant, food services at Great American Beer Hall.
That's great.
Yeah, there had been a question when they came in front of us as to exactly how they were going to do food services and now the in-house show.
I remember them saying they were going to do it, but they weren't sure exactly who and how.
All right.
Very entrepreneurial.
Yes.
And Wackling Fort has applied for their first demolition permit to start taking down buildings so they can, and I wasn't 100% clear that they were, how close they were to actually doing demo, but they've applied for the permit.
So they are moving along.
Nice.
Love to hear that.
The one I can't vote on.
Yes.
It started, it started just because Niche worked on it.
And then I actually ended up writing a lot of that too.
In fact,
Todd had to let me into some cabinets.
You can't come out of them.
I can't take anything out of them.
That's very important.
Unless you want the intersection of Boston Ave and North Street to not work.
And if there's ever you want to like, if you want to email me in advance that you want updates for particular projects, we can also reach out where things stand.
So a quiet night.
But yeah, but thank you all.
Quiet when it's a thunderstorm that's starting over here.
Is it really starting?
I'm on my bike tonight.
Yeah, you should probably go home.
Yeah, right.
I will.
It looks like I could at any moment, but I don't have anywhere.
I need to be imminently.
Can I finish that thought, Jackie, and answer your motion to adjourn?
Motion to adjourn.
I'll make the motion.
I'll second.
So, Vice Chair Emily Hartman?
Aye.
Peter Kiles?
Ari Fishman.
Aye.
Pam Ariansky.
Sally Akiki.
Aye.
And myself, Jackie McPherson.
I'm an aye.
Thank you, everyone.
Have a good night.
Good night.
Let's get home safely, everyone.