So as I said, we do have a full agenda today.
So let's get going.
All right, so we'll start.
First of all, let me say thank you everyone for attending.
We dodged another snowstorm bullet, which is awesome.
But I remember April Fool's, remember April Fool's snowstorm?
We got dumped on almost three feet of snow.
So you just never know whether you're out of the woods or not.
But I do feel bad for some of my team that live out in the western part.
They got crushed.
They got absolutely crushed.
But you know what, better them than us.
I know I shouldn't be saying that.
Before we jump into the items, we need to do some housekeeping.
We have this commission met twice in February.
Bobby and Ben, let's take a look at the set of minutes for February 9th.
As I said, we met twice in February, and just for edification, the February 9th meeting was a special meeting.
It was called by the chair, me, and our plan
is to have these special meetings publicly, of course, the public's invited, but we're starting to review all the licensing guidelines.
I mean, as we're reading through, some of them just didn't make sense.
Some of them said that chairs and tables and booths had to be bolted to the floor, bolted to the floor.
So it's like, I'm sure there was some logic about it a long, long time ago,
But nevertheless, let's just say it's been a while since these guidelines have been reviewed.
That's going to be this commission's task to review the guidelines and start making some corrections and try to get them into the 21st century.
That was the February 9th meeting.
As I said, the sole purpose was to start reviewing the AB guidelines, all beverage, all alcohol,
rules.
So, Ben, Bobby, any questions or comments on Daria's notes for February 9?
None for me.
And none from me, Alan.
Daria, I just want to say you did a great job doing the edits.
I checked out the electronic version as well, and it really stands out where the changes were made.
So nice job on that, Daria.
Yeah, I would definitely second that.
Daria, I don't know if we need to put in these minutes that this was just like the first flyby, so to speak, because now that
you know, we've kind of looked at them, you know, and now you've made the corrections.
We're going to, we're going to sit down again and do another fly by and hopefully, you know, the second pass we'll take.
So, um, if we're okay with, um, what Gary has recorded for us, let's make a motion and let's get this one off the table.
Okay.
I will make a motion on that.
Um, Mr. Commissioner, I will make a motion to accept the minutes from the February 9th special meeting for the license commission.
Very good.
Thank you.
All in favor, say aye.
Aye.
Very good.
Thank you.
Okay, that one's out.
All right, let's go to the meeting of the 15th.
Let's take a look at those minutes.
By the way, for everyone here, that meeting was just a regular license commission meeting.
I don't have any questions on those either.
Yeah.
Yeah, no, pretty, pretty straightforward.
Bobby, what about yourself?
Anything?
No, everything looks in order, Mr. Chairman.
I make a motion to accept the meeting minutes from February 15th of the Lipka License Commission.
Good, good.
Okay.
I second that.
Very good.
All in favor, say aye to accept the minutes for February 15th.
Aye.
Very good.
All right.
Daria, we've knocked those two off the table.
Let's jump to the agenda.
We'll start with the one-day license for April 5th, the West Medford Community Center.
Is that Mr. Garten?
I think I see him there.
Yeah, he's on here.
Mr. Garten, how are you?
I'm well, thank you.
Thank you for attending.
Your package was very complete.
I was impressed with all the extra documents, with the insurance and all the premiums and the coverage.
So I thank you.
I'm in the mortgage business and I wish you would apply for a mortgage because I bet you your mortgage package would be just as thorough.
I'm a CPA.
So can you tell us a little about the event?
Yes.
So it's a Passover dinner.
It's a Passover holiday.
And once we got to, you know, and it's a Wednesday night, it's whatever it is on the Jewish calendar.
You can't just do it on Saturday night when everyone's free.
So once it got to be more than a dozen people.
We just didn't want to have it in the house and this way we can invite some other people and we had had my parents are in Florida and they're coming up.
and they decided that they wanted to, they were coming up for the holiday.
And so we figured that, we had a party there at this West Medford Community Center where my stepfather turned 85, we had a very nice party there.
But when we had the party there, it was last year, there was no problems with any kind of liquor or anything.
But now I guess there is, so,
they changed the rules a little bit so yeah yeah i wouldn't say problem it's just we're just trying to go by you know the letter of the rules that's all but yeah yeah we need to start you know it's a the the it's only wine there'll be no hard liquor or beer or anything like that it's just part of the ceremony so sure the dinner you know sure now i uh i i fully understand um i don't have any other questions bobby um
Ben, anything from you guys?
No, it doesn't sound like.
I'll go ahead, Ben, I'm sorry.
No, I was just saying it doesn't sound like a professional, you know, bartender of any sort is needed here.
And it sounds pretty, you know, like it was just described.
Nothing to be concerned about as far as I'm concerned.
Yeah.
The only thing that just caught my eye, Mr. Chairman, was the insurance.
It's a liability quote.
It's not an actual certificate of liability, but I'm sure that you didn't want to purchase the actual certificate of liability until your license was granted.
And this was basically just so you know how much it had cost.
So I'm fine with all of that, just as long as you do purchase the certificate.
I'm great with that.
And wish you luck with your event.
Thanks.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's a good point, Bobby.
All right.
So why don't we do this?
Why don't one of you guys make a motion to accept the one day license subject to getting our hands on the insurance liability certificate?
Great.
I can make the motion if you like to grant one day license on April 5th for Passover holiday dinner at the West Medford Community Center with just Jaria having received a copy of the certificate of liability form.
Very good.
I'll second that.
Good, good.
Thank you for the motion.
Thank you for the second.
If I don't see anybody opposed, I raise my hand.
So all in favor of approving the one day license for April 5th, say aye.
Aye.
Very good.
Mr. Curtin, you're all set.
Thank you very much.
Short and sweet, right?
That's what my dad always used to say, short and sweet.
I like that I was first.
Enjoy, thank you.
All right, thanks so much.
You're all set, you're good.
Just get Daria the insurance certificate, please.
Oh yes, we will.
All right, thank you.
Thank you.
Okay, very good, we're cooking now.
Let's jump to the next item.
This is the Tufts College.
I believe there are two associated with this one.
Yeah, so there are actually two different events.
The first one is March 24th.
It is an all day event for the National Association of Neonatal Nurses, New England chapter.
They're holding an all day event leading into dinner that evening, which starts at five o'clock.
They're looking to do a cash bar from five to six.
So a quick, quick little bar and then leading into dinner
from six to seven, and then they start an awards ceremony scholarship event for the rest of the evening that concludes at nine.
So it's for about 130 guests.
So we plan to have two bars set up with four bartenders.
And serving that quickly and... Thank you, Heather.
Okay.
So we'll take them one at a time.
We're very familiar with Tufts College, of course.
Heather, you guys have a stellar track record.
No brawls, no fights, no nothing.
You guys are really good, really good.
Kudos to you, because your bartenders are always TIPS certified.
They know exactly what they're doing.
So I do thank you for running a great operation.
I'll pass that on.
Any, Ben, Bobby, any questions?
Or do you want to hear Heather out on the April 8th and then just vote on them together?
Or how do you want to do it?
I'm all ears.
I'm good with that.
Yep, I'm fine with that.
Heather, if you don't mind, just tell us about the April 8th event.
Sure.
The April 8th event is one that we've done probably the last four times with you all.
It's the Fletcher Culture Night.
Yeah.
This one is the Mediterranean night, so they will be purchasing food from local Mediterranean restaurants and are looking to do a cash bar for about 200 guests from 7 p.m.
to 11 p.m.
at 51 Winthrop.
Okay.
Will it be the same setup, two bars, four bartenders, or because of a larger crowd, it'll be different?
It'll be different, yeah.
We usually try to do one bartender per 50 guests, so we will have more on this.
Okay.
So definitely more on this.
But this is Fletcher.
So this school has a lot more over, they're all, you know, everyone's of age.
There are graduate students.
So we haven't had any issues with them for anything in the past.
Yeah, no, that's, that's a good point.
That really is a good point.
All those future diplomats, they don't want to be kicked out.
That's right.
Yeah, I remember this event from the last few years, so I don't have any questions.
It seemed like it was good.
Yeah.
Winthrop Street there.
It looks like the other one, it's at the Joyce Cummings Center.
Yes.
The nurses are in the new building, the Joyce Cummings Center.
That's it.
OK, that's the new building.
Yeah.
On the first floor, we have a ballroom there.
Okay, nice.
Must be.
Yeah.
Any questions from you?
No.
Everything looks in order, Mr. Chairman.
Like you say, Tufts always does a good job.
We never have to worry about what's going on.
Yeah.
And let's not jinx.
We're not jinxing.
We're not jinxing you, Heather.
We're just saying.
I'm going to pass this on to everybody, though.
Yeah.
Stay in line.
I would make a motion to Mr. Chairman to accept the two one day licenses.
The first one for April 8th and the second one for, I know it starts March 24th for Tufts University.
Very good.
I'll second the motion.
Thank you for the motion.
Thank you for the second.
All in favor to approve the one day license with Tufts University, say aye.
Aye.
Very good.
All right.
Heather, you're all set.
Thank you for jumping on.
We appreciate it.
Best of luck with both events.
All right.
Thank you again.
Take care.
All right.
Bye bye.
Okay, let's jump to item three, Friends of the Public Library.
Hi, Leilani Jermaine here.
Hello, how are you?
I'm well, how about yourself?
Good, good.
Do you mind telling us about the event?
Sure, it is our trivia night.
Um, we will have, I think it starts at seven.
And, um, basically from seven to nine, nine 30 ish.
Um, we're going to have stump trivia run by one of our children are actually the assistant director library librarian.
Now, um, Sam said, Nick, we will have two, um, I'm working on getting to volunteer, um, bartenders.
It's wine and beer, probably about a hundred people.
And, um, yeah.
We've done, I mean, this is very typical to what we've done before.
Sure, sure.
Question, are these events, is it open to the public or is it like a private?
So they are open to the public.
We do ask for reservations beforehand because we want to keep it to 100 people just because that room can't have that much capacity.
So yeah, it is open to the public, but we ask for reservations beforehand.
Generally, it's mostly our members.
It is a fundraising event, so that's why it costs money to get in.
We'll have raffle, not raffles, just some baskets and then just wine and beer sold is all we're doing.
Yeah, very good.
Sounds good.
Yeah, yeah.
It's our first time since COVID doing it in person, so we're excited.
I seen you have it in the Bonsignori Hall.
Robert Bonsignori, we were Cub Scouts together.
Oh, very nice.
Yeah.
His mom was our grandmother.
Got it.
Yeah.
Any other questions.
I don't know I don't have any way with the library has had a number of these events and everything's been fine what about the insurance is that.
it's an annual insurance.
So I know that we paid for it, I think we paid for it sometime in the fall, so I know it's an end so it's it's all year round.
Okay, Jerry, do we have something on record for them?
I know we've had a number of events where we're good with the insurance last year.
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
Good.
Okay.
Um, like I said, very straightforward.
You've done it before without incident.
Uh, so I, I don't have any other questions.
Uh, my fellow commissioners, anything from you guys?
No, let's make a motion.
I'm good.
I can make the motion if you like to grant the one day license for the trivia night fundraiser friends of the library on April 1 at Medford public library 111 High Street.
And I would second that motion.
Very good.
Thank you.
I'm all in favor except in the one day license for the method public library on April Fool's Day.
say aye.
Aye.
Very good.
It's approved.
Good luck.
I hope you have a hundred people.
Yes, you do too.
All right.
Have a good day.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Can anyone hear me?
Hello?
Hi.
Who's that?
So I live on Yale street and I'm here about the liquor license.
I've been trying to connect into the Zoom meeting, but it says it does not exist.
Is this an audio only call?
OK.
Well, we certainly can hear you.
Can you hear us?
Yes, yes.
But I don't know if there was a Zoom component or not.
There is.
Yeah.
OK.
All right.
The one that I used says the meeting does not exist, the one that had been sent out on the mailer.
So I don't know if other folks in the area tried to dial into the zoom meeting, but we're unable to.
Well, I believe it's a diary.
Correct me if I'm wrong, but it's, it's posted on the city's website.
Correct.
How to the link to get in.
Yes.
So if you want to, if you want to do that, you can just jump onto the city website and use the link and come right.
And you can see us so we can see you.
Okay.
All right.
That sounds good.
I'll try that.
But I'll hold on to the audio until then.
And I assume you haven't discussed the liquor license yet.
Well, we have a full agenda.
So we're chopping it down as we go along.
So
All right, so let's keep moving forward.
We're going to go to, I think it's St.
Ray's.
That's the next one.
Gina, I know I saw you.
There you are in the top left.
How are you?
Hi, Bob.
Hi, Gina.
How are you?
Good.
Gina, tell us about the event, if you don't mind.
So we have this event every year.
We haven't had it for COVID, obviously, for the past few years.
It's a fundraiser for the school, but it's a parish and school kind of social community event.
We normally have a couple hundred people.
I'm not sure what we're going to get this time, but it is, it kind of wraps around a $10,000 elimination drawing.
So we kind of do the drawing live on the stage.
People come in, we have baskets to kind of like the previous person we have
you know, baskets, it is a fundraiser.
So we have raffles and miscellaneous things.
And we are serving beer and wine.
We do have the insurance.
TIP certified bartenders.
Yep.
Thank you.
I, I got the insurance certificate.
Yeah.
You got a million dollar coverage.
So that's good.
Hopefully we won't need any coverage.
No, no, of course not.
But, but it's there.
That's, that's what insurance is for.
Yeah, you guys have had a good track record with the city.
So I don't have any questions.
I'm glad it's happening again.
Thank you.
I don't have any questions either.
I think it looks good.
And it's good with that amount of people having a TIP certified bartender is the right thing to do.
So that's good.
Yeah.
Bobby, before you opine, Gina, what's this $10,000?
Tell me a little more about that.
We sell up to $300 raffle tickets, $100 each.
Anyone can buy a ticket, I have people mailing in forms to me, and then we, it's an elimination drawing so they eliminate up on stage the numbers and until you get to the final five people remaining, and then they can choose to split or non split.
it's a lot of fun and get.
yeah okay and I was just curious because i'm i'm a Rotarian and we're always trying to think of how to raise money so.
Oh yeah this usually does.
A good thing we we don't always sell out, I hope we sell out this year, so if you sell out you're raising 30,000 and then it costs, you know we give 10 away the.
PB, Lupita D Montoya.
No, not at all.
All the paperwork looks in order they even submitted a sketch which is good.
Yeah, yeah, no every everything is great.
I don't have a problem with it if you like I can make a motion to place.
I make a motion to grant the one day license for St.
Rayfield Parish fundraiser located at 514 High Street.
And that is on March 31st.
Thanks, Ben.
Thanks, Bobby.
All in favor, except in the one day license for St.
Ray's Paris on March 31st say aye.
Hi, very good.
Your one day, Gina, it's been approved.
Your one day license, good luck.
Great.
Hope it's a success.
All right.
Bye, Gina.
Take care.
Bye-bye.
All right.
Let's see who we have.
It's that time already, Boston Glory.
The season starts again.
Coming right up on it.
Yeah, yeah.
I see sticks, sticks requests.
Yes.
So tell us, I know you guys have been very good, but give us a good overview and then try to tell us how you're going to beat the empire because they won it all last year, right?
And they were undefeated.
So, but first let's tell us about the event, how you plan on dispersing the alcohol and what are you going to do to contain
The area so if you don't mind Jay.
Sure.
So, a little, little bit of a wrinkle this year but largely the same so we've got six home games in the regular season, and a few in May, couple in June one in July.
A similar thing, we're going to have the beer garden.
When you come in the gate to the left, there's a little grassed area.
The Hormel staff does a good job of walling it off so that there's a single point of entry.
The remainder of the beer garden is there's a chain link fence around it, so there's no other way to get in.
The last two years we used a brewer idle hands.
This year we're using, it's going to be kind of like a mobile truck.
We still have to go before the city council on that.
And they're going to have a number of different taps.
It's going to be including hopefully some local beer, but it's same setup, same exact setup.
Right there.
It's all controlled within that area.
We try and keep people around.
We actually place some of our concessions right near it.
So it makes it really difficult for anyone to wander out of there.
with the beer a little easier to control we think even with the draft beer this year.
So, that's the, that's the gist of it.
The again Hormel staff has been terrific they help us out a lot with this help keep us on the straight and narrow.
The games we do have a one o'clock game this year to to five o'clock, and
Three seven o'clock, the Friday night games are seven.
So three seven o'clock.
And we're looking forward to it.
We got a new roster this year or revamped roster better, stronger, faster, all that stuff.
We look to give New York Empire a little bit of trouble this year, for sure.
I hope so.
You play them twice in June, right?
Home and away.
Yeah, we got a home and away.
They're very good and they'll be very good again, but the rest of the division is very good.
It's the strongest division in the league.
And we've made significant strides this year.
We've already been practicing.
We get outside starting two weeks from now.
And so we're ready to go.
Good.
So I'm, I'm, I'm pleased that you're going to contain cause our last time we had you guys contain,
everybody in a certain area once they were served, so they don't drift out of this area.
So I'm happy that you're going to be doing that again.
Yep.
Yeah.
Good.
My other two commissioners, any questions about the event?
No.
For those who don't know, this is Ultimate Frisbee, right?
Yes.
American Ultimate Disc League.
AUDL.
Yeah.
Um, no, no, I remember from the last couple years, Jay, and seems like they were successful.
No, we've had, you know, we average about 400 to 600 a game and people, you know, we have had an occasional report where we hear from Hormel staff that someone wandered into the stands and got past us.
And, but we, we quickly controlled it all the time.
No incidents, no one's ever been called.
No one's ever been over-served.
It's it's been a really good experience so far.
Very good.
Bobby, how about yourself?
Any questions?
Is this your first exposure to this?
Bobby, I forget.
Yes, it is.
I made a couple of notes because I wasn't sure if you fellows were familiar with the event, if it was their first time or whatever.
But the two notes that I had, one was if you fellows had a possible sketch just to show us where the Bear Garden is going to be located.
But you did state inside the,
Yeah, and I think we included at least in when we emailed it in a little graphic from the satellite where I did a circle of that little grassy area immediately to the left there.
I'm happy to send it in again.
It's a pretty tight area.
We set up a few tables in there, used some sawhorses to
fold it off and go from there.
We are, I should have said before, we have a few different food offerings this year, not in the beer garden, but near it where we have a number of different food offerings, different ones at different games, a lot of local vendors.
So we try and make a nice atmosphere, make sure people have the food right near where the beer is.
Yeah, sounds like a good time if you contacted the police to get a detail for.
So, we, we, we always have in our first year there was a detail at about half of our games and we rely on the, you know, we make that call every year, and then we rely on record direct department and Hormel staff as to whether or not they feel
We need a detail and we rely obviously on the police department too.
And we've had a few details at a few games, but usually they trust us to do a good job.
And certainly there's always Hormel staff there.
There's always two people from Hormel staff as well.
So yeah.
OK, no, I'm fine with it.
That sounds like you guys have
It's not your first rodeo with this.
So, uh, no, no, it's been good.
We learn a little bit every year, you know, and as always, we hope to get you guys out at, at a game.
Cause it's, uh, it's a lot of fun.
We get a lot of kids out.
Um, it's, uh, it's a fun afternoon usually.
Nice.
Yeah.
I want to come bring my family.
Yeah, you should.
I hope, I hope to see you there.
Yeah.
I hope so too.
I don't I again i'm you know we are familiar with this I Bobby Thank you for for reaching you know, asking questions, because I know you are the new kid on the block, so to speak, so this is this is your first exposure to this.
event.
So I'm fine with it.
Jay, you'll send us another version of the diagram, right?
If you don't mind.
I'll be happy to.
Should I send it to Daria's attention?
Yeah, just shoot it to Daria and she'll make it available to us.
And thanks, by the way, I should have said it before to Daria because she helps us
helps usher us to the various places that we have to get permits and approvals from, and she's been really helpful, you know, wearing a lot of hats in Medford, so it's great to have her on your team to help dopes like us make our way around.
No, no, our pleasure, and you're right, she's a great asset to the city.
So how do you guys want to do it?
Do you want to do all six at the same time?
I think that's what we've done in the past.
Okay.
I just, I think that's more efficient rather than just doing them one at a time.
Sure.
I'm happy to do it.
All right.
Okay.
So I'll make a motion to accept the one day licenses or the dates of May 6th, May 13th, June 2nd,
June 9th, June 24th, July 21st.
That's the last one, I believe.
July 21st.
Yep.
For the Boston Glory Ultimate Disc League.
AUDL, very good.
And I see a $2 million policy.
Very good.
I'll second that motion.
Second it, please.
Thanks.
All in favor, except in the six one day licenses for the dates.
Ben has disclosed say aye.
Aye.
Very good.
Jay, you're all set.
I hope you have a great season.
No rain.
We don't want rain for any of those dates, so.
No.
And thank you.
Thank you all again.
We hope to see you out there.
If you give me a little advance notice, I'll come over and say hello for sure.
Very good.
All right.
Thank you, sir.
Best of luck.
You're good to go.
OK.
Very good.
Okay, number six on the item, on the agenda, I mean, representative from Deep Cuts.
Jeff, did I, I think I saw Jeff.
Yep, I am here.
All right, good, thank you.
How are you?
Good, yourselves?
Good, good.
I thought that informational meeting with the assistant director, ABCC, went well, you know?
I thought it was very helpful.
So let's see here for the new license.
I have looked at it.
Bobby, Ben, have you got a chance to look at it?
Did you have any questions or concerns?
I've got a couple of notes that I made here, Mr. Chairman.
page four of the license application, the application page four.
Just scroll down to it here.
Yeah, it's the number eight, the financial disclosure.
Okay.
It says purchase price for real estate, 17,000, and then purchase price for business assets at 10,000 and other for 15,000 with a total of 42,000, which Jeff, you're going to be,
you know, financing yourself or supplying the money for that.
But are you actually purchasing the real estate for $17,000?
No, that's on that form.
That's, they just want to know where your money is coming from.
So for that, that's what our the down payment for our rent was here.
No, I think that might
should be in the other.
Yeah, maybe this is the same form that's on like the state license.
And that's I've filled that out.
Yeah, for four or three other locations.
This is my fourth time.
And that's how I've always done it.
They're really just they want to track where all your money is coming from and where you're getting financed and stuff.
So they want to know if you're buying the property or renting it, and just kind of putting those buckets of money into the different categories.
But you're not buying the property, correct?
But you're not buying it, yeah.
Because Jeff, that's how we looked at it.
We said, wow, what a deal, $17,000.
Yeah.
No, it's usually because they want to know
like equipment and stuff is usually financed.
So that comes from a separate set of money.
But, you know, your real estate is, you know, almost always has to be cash, unless it's a mortgage.
And then you have to put that information into the form.
Yeah, just kind of caught my eye on other
on other new license applications, unless they've actually purchased the land or the property, that's usually zero.
So that caught my eye.
That was one of the questions I had.
Another question I had was, I didn't see a layout for the basement drawing.
Was that not on with your architect drawings?
Let me see what I had for the basement.
I might not have attached that one.
Because I was kind of looking for the layout of the brewery, you know, I imagine it's similar to what you have now.
Yeah, sorry, I might have attached the wrong drawing.
I'm sending out these drawings to a million people.
So yeah.
Yeah, Jeff, if you don't mind sending it to us, that would be great.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
The one you did send us is the first floor.
And it's only the first floor, but it shows the kitchen and it shows the bar and it shows the
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, so I can I can send one with the basement.
It's basically just the brewing space.
Plus, there's the walk in cooler for the beer is down there and then some storage spaces.
Yeah, but I'll shoot that right over.
Just so we have complete records of
of your business, that's all.
Yeah.
Okay.
We're at storage.
That could be, you know.
And the other thing, the certified email receipt at the end, what is that for?
I saw Ray, just the receipt for an email, not an email, certified mail.
Steel mail, postal, yeah.
I don't know what it was for.
Did you notify like tenants?
Not butter.
But neighbors?
It was for the butters.
And the ad in the paper, right?
Yeah.
And there's one butter that I had to send a certified mail notification to.
OK.
Yeah, I didn't know if that's exactly what it was for.
The monetary transmittal form that they're supposed to submit, is that the receipt from the ABCC for the $200?
Yes, that they paid for it.
Okay, because I didn't see it on in our paperwork.
I didn't know if you had it or not.
But that's the only other question I had.
Yeah, but you can verify that it's in a current right area.
If it has an ABCC will ask.
Yeah, I was gonna say it's not gonna get by them.
No, I know.
I know.
Okay, so
Jeff will rely on your past experience on the 17,000 where it's plugged in under purchase price for real estate.
If you're saying, will ABCC ask about that entry or will they just know from past experience with you?
That's how I've always done it, and it's never been a question before.
If I've been doing it wrong this whole time, that very well could have been the case, but they never brought it up to me.
Yeah.
OK.
All right.
I just hate to see them come chasing after you, saying, oh, you purchased real estate?
Where's the taxes?
Yeah.
Whatever.
OK.
Good.
Good, good, good.
I'm sorry, Ben, go ahead.
Oh, no, it's just so question.
So license type.
So this is a section 12 saying that, right?
All alcohol.
Just the license type.
I was just so I'm reading this clearly.
Is is what exactly the restaurant?
Yeah, it's her restaurant, right?
All alcohol, AB, all beverage.
And we have the on-site brewery.
There's a brewery in the basement as well.
Well, he can't have both.
So once the all alcohol license is issued, then he'll have to surrender the other one.
Can't have two.
Right.
This one is going to take over.
Yes.
Correct.
I know that.
Okay.
Yeah, it'll be.
Yeah.
Like I said, it was very helpful having that informational meeting with ABCC kind of helped Jeff and helped us understand how to put this together.
So kudos to Ralph, the assistant director there.
Yeah, he's a great guy.
Yeah.
Ben, Bobby, any other questions?
No, no.
How's it going there?
How's the renovation going?
Um, it's good.
We should be wrapping up in the next couple of weeks and then we just have to make the beer and get all of our staff trained up.
So we're, we're shooting for, uh, middle of April right now.
Okay.
Good April.
Ribbon cutting.
Good.
Yeah, great.
Well, best of luck.
Yeah.
Thanks.
One of my fellow commissioners want to make a motion to approve the new license request.
Sure, I can make the motion to approve the new license for deep cuts LLC located, that's 21 main correct, the actual location for that.
Yeah, 21 Main Street, Medford.
And that's, that's it.
Very good.
Good.
Thank you for the motion Ben thank you for the second.
Jeff, your new license request has been approved by the city.
Best of luck.
We can't wait until you open your door.
So good luck.
Best of luck.
Awesome.
Thank you so much.
All right.
Take care.
Before I go, though, I just wanted to touch base.
We had submitted for the entertainment license also.
I don't know if we're going to do that at this meeting or the next meeting.
Yeah, Daria, I don't see that in the package.
We can do that at the next meeting, no?
Daria?
Yeah, that's fine.
OK.
We'll do it at the next meeting, Jeff, because we don't have the information.
Yeah.
OK.
Sure.
You can always add that in.
That's nothing that ABCC needs.
That's just the city of Medford.
So we can do that any time.
Wait, Ellen.
OK, yeah.
Alan, I think I remember definitely scanning in.
That's I had gotten three of the signatures and it was Board of Health was the only one who was hadn't sent it to me yet.
I don't see it in the package.
I didn't either.
Maybe I must have not scanned in.
Sorry about that.
I definitely scanned in yesterday.
Hold on, let me check.
Because yeah, he didn't get the last one, but.
You were breaking up.
I couldn't hear exactly what you were saying.
What was your concern?
No, I was just saying, I definitely scanned it in yesterday, but I don't see it in my scan.
All right, we can go over it next time, because I have a ton of scans in here, and I'm not going to be able to find it right now.
Apologies.
But I know Jeff definitely had the three signatures he was just missing one more because I was helping him out to get on top of those.
Okay.
So when you get to when you confirm the third one and away it goes right.
The fourth one.
Fourth one.
I'm sorry.
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay, so we have a motion on the table, and like I said, the new license has been granted.
Subject to, I guess we could subject, we can tweak the condition subject to that fourth signature once you have that.
Dario, you confirm that fourth signature?
Okay, good.
All right, so all in favor, say aye.
Aye.
Very good.
Jeff, you're off and running.
Awesome.
All right, thanks everybody.
Best of luck.
Item number seven, Ms.
Therafin, do I see you?
How are you?
Good, good.
Item seven, I'm going to, as the chair, I am going to have to recuse myself from this particular item.
Because I don't want to run afoul of the conflict laws.
My wife's first cousin is married to the owner's son.
So I think it would be wise of me to just step back.
Daria, you can mute me so I can't say anything to influence.
the decision either way.
Uh, and, and I will turn, uh, item number seven over to my two fellow commissioners, Ben and Bobby.
Um, and, uh, away we go.
So Daria kind of mute me or do you want me, do I mute myself?
Should I just mute myself?
Yeah, that's fine.
How are you?
Hi.
How do we say your name?
Is it Kayla?
Kayla.
Correct.
Yeah.
All right, Kayla.
Ben, do you want to?
Well, actually, Kayla, can you just tell us a little bit about what's going on?
You know, what your plans are.
We obviously are applying for a license transfer.
Maybe you can just give us the highlights of what's going on.
Yes, definitely.
So I have worked in the food industry for about 15 years now, and we're trying to transfer the license for Bocelli's.
Um, I have known for Charlie's for a good time now.
And, um, we want to keep everything the same.
So the same menu, same food, same hours, same employees.
So everything is going to be the same.
We're not going to be doing any changes.
So no crazy changes to any of the menu.
Cause we know that people in the city love.
Yeah.
Great food over there.
It's been there a long time.
Them deepest qualities before them.
Yeah.
We, I was one of the things I had noticed, I don't know if it came to your attention to Ben, but that Taylor.
Basically, the only thing on your application for work experience was the school that you listed.
So we weren't, I wasn't sure whether you actually had restaurant experience or not.
You know I do.
I have been in the food industry for over 15 years as a manager of a pizza place and they had a little dining area.
They had a lot of deliveries and I also took two years off business administration.
Oh, very good.
And her mother has actually worked in the restaurant for, I think, over 20 years.
In Bocelli's.
In Bocelli's?
Oh, wow.
Yes.
At Bocelli's.
OK.
Wow.
That's good.
Very good.
The other, I had a couple of other questions too.
I noticed that on the applications page number four, let me just scroll down to it.
very or it's.
And the occupancy of premises.
It's on the bottom of box number eight.
It says, will the landlord receive revenue based on percentage of alcohol sales?
Oh, nothing is checked.
So that was an oversight.
That's a no.
It's definitely a no.
OK, that's that's what I wanted to make sure on that just to.
I'm not sure.
I'm not sure
Yes, there was a lease agreement.
So there's an exhibit to the lease which does structure out.
There's a difference monthly 16,000 for the first and second year.
And then there's a differentiation, but that's on the exhibit to the lease itself.
Okay.
exhibit.
Yeah.
Okay, and then the actual purchase is the $300,000.
Sorry, $350,000.
Yep.
Okay.
Bob, I know you had a couple other questions.
You can move to those.
Oh, no, no, that's okay.
We were on that page.
So that's, that's good that we, uh, we could get that information.
The other question I had was on page five at the bottom of that page, number 11 pledge information.
And it says, are you seeking approval for a pledge?
Would you check?
Yes.
And you're pledging, um,
federal to pledge the license, and that's going to be made to the seller.
And I can see why you're doing that for collateral or whatever, but there's no pledge paperwork attached to this whole application.
If you go to the first page, say, of the application for transfer of license and the transaction information number one, you know, what you should have done there is checked pledge of license as well as transfer of license.
so that both things could be done at the same time.
There's a whole separate form.
I believe Daria could actually send you a link to that with that form.
I think that's what I was thinking was that we have to do the transfer first and then the pledge anyway, because the financing doesn't actually occur.
until we can transfer and the agreement is contingent upon the transfer.
It was separate anyway.
Okay, so what we can do in this case in my opinion, Ben.
And like your opinion on it as well, is that, you know, possibly we can grant the license for the transfer, but it's going to have, I would say it's going to have to be omitted, where they said that there's going to be a pledge in what page was it?
At that point, the pledge information, well, I mean, it's just saying are you seeking approval for a pledge?
You're not seeking approval.
We're not approving the pledge.
But I don't know.
How do you feel on that, Ben?
Do you think we should just, we can't say no either because they are going to be seeking approval for a pledge.
we would say no based off of that, because they are, and that's for the, it's a pledge for their license, so.
I think it might be the way it is.
Yeah.
But just that they will have to apply for a pledge via paperwork for the pledge specifically, maybe at our next monthly meeting, that can be approved.
Um, which is, it's not a big deal to have it approved as long as, uh, you folks, um, obviously the, both legal teams, uh, work on that and, and get that done.
Um, and it's just for us to yay or nay it.
Um, but, um, that, that it just kind of caught my eye.
The pledge information was in there, but there was no paperwork attached to it.
Yeah.
And I'm clear the pledge is the 150 K. Correct.
Yep.
Yeah, I mean, yeah, it's chicken, you know, what comes chicken or the egg, I think that that's, in my opinion, that that's okay, because they are seeking financing subject to getting all of these approved.
And then the financing would have to come go through, right for this whole deal to go through.
So I think that that
Looks okay.
So the new entity name, I mean, I see you're keeping the Chelley's the name and that you're allowed to keep that name as long as you have this lease in place or there's some language there.
which doesn't really concern us, but the new entity name is, can you tell me it?
Yep.
Texera Seraphim Inc.
Okay.
Yep.
That's, so that's a new entity name.
So this is, I'm a resident on Yale street and I do have a question or two.
Could I, is this appropriate for me to ask my question now?
Yeah, sure.
You all set with that, with the inquire that you would just.
Yeah, I'm OK.
I'm OK with that part.
OK.
Yeah.
I mean, sure.
We can hear from the resident.
You're more than welcome to speak.
Just kindly state your name and address for the record, please.
Sure.
David Perella and I reside at 16 Yale and I'm the owner of 16-18 Yale Street.
OK.
I am curious, so the Bocelli's restaurant has been sold, and is that what is driving the transfer of the license, the liquor license?
That's what they are repairing before this commission for today, yes.
Okay, so it's not expanding a liquor license, it's simply transferring the existing license from the Bocelli's to Tuxera Seraphim.
The question I have is, is there any relationship of this organization to Oasis?
No.
No, okay, all right.
And will the liquor light, will the bar be expanded in any way so that- At this point, there's no intention to change anything.
It's truly a transfer.
The intention is to keep everything as it is currently.
Okay, all right, great.
Well, thank you.
Those are the questions and concerns I had.
So thank you for that.
And I wish you good luck then with Bocelli's.
It's been a well-loved restaurant in our neighborhood for many years.
Thank you.
And I think with that, folks, I can drop off.
And I appreciate you allowing me to voice my concerns and ask my questions.
Not a problem, Mr. Perella.
And just for your information too, if you're concerned, you know, about the buyer expansion or anything like that in the future, they have to come before this board for an alteration of premises.
And at that point in time, you'd know if there was going to be anything changed in the restaurant.
and they'd be showing drawings and presenting it to the board and you'd have the opportunity to speak at that time as well.
Terrific, great.
Thank you for that as well.
Appreciate it.
Okay, sir.
Thank you.
Bye now.
So Bobby, going through this, I mean, I'm seeing it's a restaurant license, it's gonna be transferred, the same license to new owners, the same building to new owners.
Um, you know, they're going to take over the lease.
Um, and I'm, you know, I'm not, I'm, I'm not seeing, I know that there was almost a deal that happened a few years ago, a few years ago with Pacelli's and now this is, this looks to be the one, um, um, you know, happening now.
And, uh, it looks like, you know, there's going to be some financing in place.
It's, it's clear core reform was filled out.
which is great.
So I'm really not seeing anything that is a question for me.
I mean, it looks like it's pretty, it appears pretty clean.
Yeah, I feel the same way.
It was just that those two items that I had, one, if you could just make sure that the no box was checked with the landlord receiving revenue from the alcohol sales.
And we know now that the pledge agreement and application paperwork will be completed and submitted at possibly the next monthly meeting.
And I don't have any issues with anything else.
Everything looks to be in order.
So I guess, Ben, if you'd like to make a motion.
OK.
Sure.
So.
All right.
Let me say this all correctly.
So I will make a motion to accept the transfer of license from.
But Shelley's.
Restaurant to.
Teixeira, Seraphim, Inc., for the application for a transfer of license that we just reviewed together today.
Very good.
And I will second that motion.
All those in favor?
Aye.
Congratulations, Kayla.
You're on your way.
Thank you so much.
You're welcome.
Good luck with your new place.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
I appreciate it.
Okay.
Mr. Chairman, are you back on?
I am.
Very good.
Thank you.
Thank you for doing that, as I said, I don't ever want anyone to raise any conflict issues with that transaction, so.
Yeah, we're, yeah, no, good.
Good questions, good question.
All right, number eight, we're in the stretch here.
The last one, a representative from GAAB, as we've been calling it.
I saw them, I saw Brian, I saw his team there.
The Great American Beer Hall.
How are you guys?
Good.
How are you?
Good, good.
Excuse me.
Could I ask a question?
Not yet.
Can you hear me?
Let me just say thank you guys for coming on.
I think the
The, our informational hearing with the assistant director of ABCC was, was very smart because not only did it hear me.
Hold on, please excuse me.
Hold on, please.
Hold on.
Thank you.
I think the.
The meeting that we had with the assistant director at ABCC was smart.
And you guys were able to answer his questions and our questions.
And I think it went a long way to help expedite your license request, your all alcohol license request.
So Brian, John, I thank you for
for doing that.
It was very smart.
And actually, I'd like to take credit for it, but it was my other fellow commissioner, Mr. Delafano, who had reached out to them and made that all happen.
So kudos to Bobby for doing that.
So I thank you.
So it sounds like we
Before we jump into, I see other names on here.
Hi, if you'd like to pose a question, do you mind stating your name and address for the record first?
And then you can voice your opinion or ask whatever question you have.
Okay.
My name is Rick Giganti.
Can you hear that?
Yes.
Okay.
I'm going to butter for
Bocelli's, and I was trying to get in and voice my opinion, but I couldn't be heard.
So I apologize for being late.
So I dialed in again so that I could be heard.
I understand what's going on with Bocelli's as far as being sold.
I live at 139 Harvard Street, which is the building house right behind him.
I do have a lot of concerns, but the primary concern I probably have is cleanliness.
We've gone through many issues of cleanliness, both with disposing of rubbish as well as other things, and I'll just leave it at that.
I also have a concern, a lot of people tend to try
to use my driveway, which I'll try to figure out how to fix that myself, but I've been going through that deal ordeal as well.
I wish the people all the luck in the world.
It has been a great institute for many, many years.
I've been living at this house for over 60 years, so I definitely know the neighborhood.
And I definitely know how it was in people's policy.
And I definitely know what I have gone through in the Bocelli era.
Some good, some bad, but like that's like with everything.
I'm concerned.
You know, eventually this is going to have to be revised and renovated at some time.
I'm curious to hear how that all works out where it's just a transfer.
You know, we've had many people look at this property that wanted to purchase this property prior to what's going on now with the transfer.
And they had found out that there's a lot of repairs that need to be incorporated into the building prior to having it sold.
So I'm kind of concerned about that, whether it's just going to be transferred and then, you know, Bocelli's is gone in a way and the new owner comes in.
And none of the repairs get done now.
That's up to the board themselves but the concern on my behalf because if there's going to be repairs or if it's going to get sold again.
The end of the butter.
I need to know that one other item that I want to express concern about at the time put an exhaust fan
On the side of the building which is if you go by my house did see it on the building on the side that goes over.
My garage.
The only way they can clean that then the climb on my garage.
Another happy camper about that I've been expressing my concern about that prior to.
Nothing has been done nothing probably can be done.
I would like to express my concern about people climbing on my roof, and the grease from that flue, and then unfortunately spilling some on the garage, or spilling some behind the garage, or when they use the hose going all over my deck.
So there's a few concerns that I have, a few concerns that I want to address, and a few
If you could express those concerns to others or whoever has to understand that.
I wish all the people the luck in the world.
It's a hell of a restaurant.
It's got a hell of a reputation.
But being in the butter for all these years, I just want to express major concerns in those two, three, four areas.
Okay, that's it.
Bobbie, Bobbie, Ben, do you wanna, anything to add to the, about our concern?
Maybe a suggestion is that we can pass along these concerns to the new owners.
They don't particularly pertain to the liquor license transfer.
Some are building, you know,
Some of them are like building department, you know, stuff, general neighbor, you know, neighbor relations.
But I understand it's a time that they're transferring and there's going to be a new owner.
So we could, you know, we could pass this along with your information, you know, if you would send that in.
Any changes to the building, you're going to be notified through a different
Like I said, I wish them all the luck in the world.
And I'm glad Nick is getting what Nick deserves.
I mean, he's a hard worker.
He's been there such a long period of time.
So I don't want to jeopardize anything like that.
I just want to make people aware that I would like to see how we will go forward in order to
just to keep it clean.
That's all.
Okay.
All right.
Thank you.
I wish them all the luck in the world.
It's a great place.
Okay.
Thank you.
All right.
Mr. Commissioner, can I just say, who's saying
Who's saying that?
Well, it's a good argument for Daria to, where she's the host, to have everybody muted rather than, you know, that way no one can voice their colorful opinion.
Colorful, I like that one.
Like I said, I don't want to, I don't want to make anyone upset, and it's not my point.
Um, my point is definitely not that way at all.
My point is just, I want to make sure that going forward, we're all set.
We understand each other and I know what has to be done, but I just want to make sure that my, my, my voice is heard.
And I just, I wish them all the luck in the world.
And I hope they succeed just as well as as well as Amber.
Yeah.
Talking about somebody else that was somebody else.
Somebody else that keeps swearing.
So, it's not, it's not you we we respectfully received your point.
And we
You know, it wasn't you that we met the colorful opinions.
No, no, it's someone else.
It's someone else who continues to swear on the site.
Daria, is there a way to mute everybody?
How does that work?
I'm sorry, guys, I'm just trying.
The time is running out, so I'm trying to add more time to this meeting.
OK, I apologize.
OK, then let's let's let's move forward with item 8.
All right.
Thank you, sir.
Thank you.
All right.
And thank you.
And thank you very much for your time.
All right.
Very good.
Thank you.
So let's jump to 8.
How are you guys back again?
uh, you know, steady as you go, you just keep, keep moving forward.
You keep doing what you have to do.
So, um, I, I thank you for being on again.
And as I was saying that, uh, informational meeting with the assistant director was, was beautiful.
Just, we all learned a lot.
We all understand what's expected from ABCC and what's, what's expected from the city.
And, um,
Bobby and Ben, basically Ralph took us through the process.
Since nothing exists yet, he said that the team has met the requirements to submit an all-alcohol license request.
but it would be a conditional approval.
It would be a conditional approval by ABCC, and it would be a conditional approval by the city of Medford, and it would be subject to all pertinent city of Medford departments as the project progresses.
And that's kind of, we thought that was wise.
Daria, I see you raising your hand, what's up?
Yeah, I think it's gonna end in a minute.
Okay, so,
I'm Ben Bobby did you have any quick questions or because I honestly I this to me was just a mere formality, because we knew you guys did the you reached out to the butters twice I know you didn't like doing it the second time, but that was the request of ABCC and you did it, thank you and.
As I said, I can't make a motion where I'm the chair, but Bobby or Ben, do you want to make a motion to to make a conditional approval?
How do you want to do this?
Sure, that that sounds great.
We'll make a motion for a conditional approval, especially when we're running out of time for Great American Beer Hall for a new liquor license.
Yeah, very good.
It'll be subject to, you know, ABCC's final and the City of Medford, all the pertinent departments that oversee the project as it progresses.
Right.
Exactly.
Ben, what do you think?
I am in favor of that.
I second that motion.
Very good.
All in favor?
Aye.
Okay.
Guys, you're off and running.
Awesome.
Good luck.
Thank you.
Yeah, we're all excited to see the project progress.
You have met the minimum requirements, as you know what Ralph said, and let's see the project progress.
And hopefully, nobody has a pain in the neck, actually two feet lower as the project progresses.
OK?
Awesome.
Thank you.
I appreciate it.
Good luck.
Thank you.
Who's John Keely?
I don't know, but he, I don't know.
I don't know, but somehow the foul language continues to prevail.
So yeah.
So we're good.
John, you're good.
Brian, you're good.
All good.
I'm good.
Thank you very much.
All right.
Take care, guys.
Thank you.
Good luck.
Appreciate it.
Daria, anything else, any items you need to address with us or any concerns?
I don't think so.
Sorry.
I was so focused on trying to get the time up.
It looks like you brought us a little time.
It wasn't the first time.
I had to increase it by 15 minutes and it wasn't letting me do it.
So, but now it's not shutting off.
So, yeah.
Okay.
Well, no, no.
Like I said, we, you know, how many times have we met?
We met with the ABCC.
you know, I think we've done our due diligence.
I think we've done, uh, they, as I said, they meet the record, the minimum requirements to get this moving for their license.
And then it'll be up to ABCC final recommendations and it'll be up to the city, you know, to make sure they have adequate, uh, the streets wide enough for the trucks and there's enough parking in it meets a health codes and business, um, building zone code, the whole thing.
So in,
In Ralph had mentioned, this is how they do it with the large construction projects and he told us a story about TD garden how you know it was a three to five year project and you know a lot a lot of things have changed so.
And that's kind of how they did it was they got their their approved the conditional approval for their.
They're all alcohol requests, but it was all conditioned upon everybody signing off, all the different departments signing off on the project.
I thought it was a great idea, so we didn't slow them down.
We'll see, because I think the ribbon cutting is sometime in 2024, so there's a long road ahead of them to construct.
So if there's no other, uh, is anybody else there that, uh, I see some other names in here.
Okay.
Well, hearing and seeing no other questions or concerns, uh, addressed to this commission.
Uh, uh, I say, let's, um, wrap it up.
Uh, can I have a motion to, uh, adjourn?
I will make a motion to adjourn this meeting.
All right.
Bobby second.
I will second.
Very good.
All right, so meeting adjourned to 19.
Again, I thank you all for your time Daria I thank you for all your expertise and in guiding us really appreciate it.
And just enough why when people do sign in, I have them automatically muted.
I just don't know how to do it while we're on.
Yeah, yeah, the file languages.
Yeah, it's concerning.
Yeah, yeah.
And when it gets like that, it's not a good environment if people are just gonna continue to swear through the process.
So we're good.
See you guys next month.
Thank you very much.