I can't find anyone from Mustang Report and it's due in two days. I don't know what I'm going to do. I have to go find someone. I think Mateo's in the library somewhere. Ooh, Shakespeare. Mateo, what are you doing? We have to finish the Mustang Report. Come on.
I need to make some copies for the Once and Furniture King. Hopefully I'll find someone from the Mustang Report while I'm here. You know what? I might as well have this book online. I don't need copies. Jocelyn! I've been looking for you everywhere! Come on! I'm sorry. I don't know where Amber is. I heard you had a squirrel problem in school, so I don't know if that's Amber or squirrels. Amber, is that you?
Come on, let's go. We have the Mustang report to work on. You help? Okay. Ooh, this cooking magazine looks good. Courtney! What are you doing? We have the Mustang report. Why are you sleeping? Third period. Third period? Let's go.
Hi, I'm Amber Harbison, and I'm here with the Mustang Report, and we're going to do a little weather report on the snowstorm that happened yesterday. Let's take a look. I'd say we have about, you know, 13 inches, maybe more in some places, maybe a little less, but definitely not as much as Canada yesterday. Amanda, do you think this is great softball weather? Definitely. I think it's never been warmer.
Do you think we could invent like a new sport, like snowball, where they play baseball with snow? I think that's actually a great idea. We'll get back to you on it. Dennis, what's your favorite snow time activity? My favorite snow time activity is hot chocolate and warm fire in a warm bedroom. That's the best kind of activity for the snow time and for the season.
Well, I hope you enjoyed your snow day yesterday with that. I did. I did a lot of plowing. I enjoy plowing, yes. This is really a lot of fun and a lot of aggravation. The answer to last week's Question of the Week is... Two. The Mustang Report Question of the Week is... Where was I on January 20, 2001?
So what's going well is that the fish are growing very rapidly, which is what we want. What's also going well is that we got a grant from the Medford Education Foundation to build our hydroponics.
we're gonna combine they're smart if they think the net is there they're gonna stay away okay this is a little guy actually you got it? yeah so they're growing they're growing nicely
And they're healthy, which is good. And the test part's going well. And let's see. We're actually getting the parts for our grow bed very soon. We're actually picking up the grow bed from a local company here in Medford called Root Down Hydroponics. That grow bed is going to go right over here. So this is the outline.
of where the bed's going to sit. It's kind of big, but we'll make room for it. And this will allow us to grow edible plants. And also, it's going to help clean the water. And that'll be really great, because it means that I won't have to clean this out all the time. This gets a little grody after a while. So the plants will do that cleaning for us, which will be really cool. And we already had a
one student do a mini hydroponic system for a science fair project, and it worked great. It kept the water clean. We didn't have to change the water. We had a little fish named Nemo, who was very happy with his hydroponic system. So in short, it's going great. Hopefully in about another six weeks, we're going to harvest our fish. We're going to take them out of the culinary, and we're going to start making some tasty fish treats.
Do you have a lot of science questions that you want answered? What's a molecule? How does life work? How do atoms work? I don't know how this works. Does your teacher not have enough time to answer all your questions? Yes, my teacher never has time for my questions. Well, I've got the solution for you. A new program called Breaking Science. Wait, when is it again? The first event is April 12th at 7 o'clock p.m. in the science lecture hall. Oh my god, I have to go now.
I'm Victoria here with Marcus Mazzotti, the president of the Drama Club, talking about the upcoming performance of Fiddler on the Roof. So Marcus, can you tell me a little bit about what the Fiddler on the Roof is about? Yeah, so it's about a small village in Eastern Europe, and it's about sort of changing old traditions when new ideas come to town. So when is the performance? There's a performance this coming Thursday at 7.30 p.m., Friday at 7.30, and then Saturday at 2.30 and 7.30.
Well, good luck. I hope you break a leg. Thank you. Not literally, of course.