joke that we settled halfway.
But when we moved here, there was a bit of a culture shock in that it wasn't a town that things were happening in.
We had been living in Berkeley for a long time.
And it was a little bit trying to get used to the fact that the mayor here thought things were great.
And I think things were
And his cronies and people that fought like the mayor.
And in fact, it's a little funny, when we came down to house purchasing, we came down to two houses.
One was in Somerville, one was in Medford, and they were at the time considered to be about the same.
You know, thus giving rise to the old joke, you know, Medford is just Somerville with trees.
But it was very, they were considered to be kind of sister communities.
And Barry and I watched over three decades as Somerville went like this in terms of everything that matters as far as human development and looking ahead and trying to figure out what works best for the community and how do we build community.
Well, memory was kind of in the doldrums the whole time.
I was delighted.
And I have been increasingly interested the last several years as more and more people began moving into Medford and began finding their peace with the people that were scattered here and there to actually be on the cusp of something that I think is finally starting to happen here.
Medford is starting to say, we don't need the old ways of thinking about things.
We don't need to have the, you have to have a certain kind of surname to run for office in Medford.
It's delightful that someone 23 years old who knows about what the schools ought to be looking at, who's actually running for a place of responsibility with the school committee.
I think it's amazing that we've got someone of the caliber of Anna Callahan to be running for city council.
I mean, oh my God, that's just astonishing that people who actually are looking at facts rather than who do I know to get that done.
Or can we do something a little bit more ambitious than filling in potholes?
So I am hopeful that looking at the folks that have come out here today, looking at the caliber of candidates we have in Aaron and in Anna, that Medford truly might become a little bit more than just the trees that separate it from Somerville.