[SPEAKER_01]: And we'd be like, yeah, everything looks good.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we had a procedure that was documented how we were going to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that was in a meeting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I think it's a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: As long as the procedure's documented there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think it was tended to that, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: But it was a written procedure so that we were following the procedure as opposed to just...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I don't think... Well, I will tell you, I do remember signing bodies that we were here a while, way back in the day, but... Well, there was a time when, I think, I mean, hold on, hold on a sec, but anyway, I think we're out of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Shouldn't somebody prepare these boss checks and... Our role at this point is just...
[SPEAKER_01]: confirming that these need our exemptions and we're doing our statutory authority as opposed to saying that three individual people reviewed every single.
[SPEAKER_00]: Agreed.
[SPEAKER_00]: All right, so let's kick it off.
[SPEAKER_00]: We'll call the meeting to order F4-OP.
[SPEAKER_00]: And first on the agenda which you have in front of you is approval of the minutes from the June meeting.
[SPEAKER_00]: And of note, the only thing in those minutes of note for this meeting is there were uncollectible personal properties that came in within 48 hours of this meeting.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it was not anticipated within the 48 hours, which we can add to this meeting.
[SPEAKER_00]: So this additional personal property from fiscal 04 to fiscal 22 from the treasury collector that
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, she was unable to collect those.
[SPEAKER_00]: So there's not from Boston from this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it was carried over, which we, you know, I couldn't reasonably anticipate within 48 hours.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's not on the agenda, but we will be taking up the personal property.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just want to make that enough to carry over from June.
[SPEAKER_00]: The June minutes second.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then moving on, the next would just be the motor vehicle review of a bathements, which are all right here.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only one that was not in the packet that you guys got on email is this top one here.
[SPEAKER_00]: She used that at last minute today.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a few.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you want to take a peek at that, everything else was on the email.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I didn't have to look at them only because I didn't get the review.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have to get my login changed because it only comes into one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I was trying to send it to iCloud account as well, so just to... Oh, okay, so... Did you send it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I didn't send it, so Maria, but you sent it to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I'll get that fixed, but I'll run it out and just go to the... Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it doesn't take long to review these.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you're signing off on us for all of these, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: Correct.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is an example of a procedure that was set up so that these could be done with one signature rather than after it was approved.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like you told to that tonight, this huge backlog of exercise and people call.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now there'll be 12 packets per if it was 11.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do we need a motion to approve those?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, as long as everything's good, she's already signed, so we can just make a motion.
[SPEAKER_00]: All right, third up is the fourth commitment for motor vehicle excise.
[SPEAKER_00]: All right.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then moving on to the big one is the exemptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So
[SPEAKER_00]: I previously, this week, reviewed all of the exemptions that have come in so far from July 1 through today or through Friday of last week.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rita vetted them, I vetted them, put together a pivot table from Excel as well as documentation on each one of the exemptions that came in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So for the record, we have 13, 37
[SPEAKER_00]: exemptions, plus 37 exemptions, two 17Ds, 12 22Ds, one 41A deferral, 17 CPA exemptions for just CPA.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's some exemptions that also get a CPA automatically, the 22Ds, the 41Cs, and then the deferral as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So
[SPEAKER_00]: that gives us a total of 57 CPA exemptions, but there are only truly 17 exemptions that apply only to CPA.
[SPEAKER_00]: 27 41 C's, last 41 C's, 75 veteran 22 A's, that's the 10 to 90 percent, the veteran spouse 22 D's,
[SPEAKER_00]: The 22 capital E, which is 100% disabled, 39, and the 22, 100% disabled that live in a two-family didn't get half of the total amount because of the two-family.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is a total of five.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that is a summary of each one of these pages here that should correlate to that number.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the exemptions are there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, I walked through those with Rita.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this would be a summary of each one of those piles that we can add to the top of each one of those packets.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we can go around if we'd like.
[SPEAKER_00]: We just sign as one by one.
[SPEAKER_00]: So in order, this would be plus 37, which has 13 total exemptions that were approved.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jared, can you give me that sheet that you just referred to the hill?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just curious.
[SPEAKER_01]: How does this compare to
[SPEAKER_01]: prior to this?
[SPEAKER_00]: We are actually a little bit lower currently than we were in previous years.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's because we had the meeting a little bit later last year.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I'd say we were all right on track.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I had asked Rita before she left what we were looking like.
[SPEAKER_00]: And most of them are repeats, specifically the veterans.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're going to get the same ones every year.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we should be right on track.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think we were right around 300-ish last year.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the change, the 22E versus the 22A?
[SPEAKER_00]: The 20, there should be the documentation right next to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, that's my notes here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Joe, that was a correction that I made.
[SPEAKER_00]: So Rita had put in an E as an A instead of, so that was still flipped.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, so it was, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's not really, it's not a status change of the- No, it's just, yeah, it was just a data correction change in vision, but the logs are correct.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: All right.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's this packet there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So what I like to do is these are readers logs.
[SPEAKER_00]: These numbers are all accurate here.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is a previously well, she should be entering them in vision so that we can pull a report out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I try to tie these and this is a check on what we have in vision.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's a full report at the end of the year.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I vetted on Monday along with looking at all the exemptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and just to confirm it, this signature sheet will be attached to each
[SPEAKER_01]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_00]: Each one, yeah, the 37s will be tied to each one of those applications, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, from the side of the top page.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, we've already signed them, so.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, yeah, those are the 41Cs.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So does this go with this?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, the 37s
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, we can do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's adequate in the vision program.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I like to tie it at the end.
[SPEAKER_00]: We can have it total, and then we'll do it automatically.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in this situation, plus 37 is 437.50 per, and we have 13 total.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I'll make some notes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So for the 37s plus 37, it's a grand total of 5687.50.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are the 37 steps.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so you want this with that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, we could.
[SPEAKER_00]: We'll just start making a file.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just set them, flip them over.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we'll be doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: All right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So going down the line, next we have 17 Ds.
[SPEAKER_00]: There should just be two of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sassina, you're not aware.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, we're not.
[SPEAKER_02]: of last year.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, last year, 34.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then next to me to capital D.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is the no tax bill.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we won't have a number on that until we actually commit the values and the tax rate, and then we put them in later.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's a deceased bed.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have a total of 12 of these through last Friday.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, with the national vaccine,
[SPEAKER_02]: No, 22D should be... 22E.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's see.
[SPEAKER_00]: and then on to the next one 41a which is just one it's the same thing it's a senior deferral now we just we counted within the exemption number for the year but this technically it's a deferral they're not giving money away they're just choosing the defer the tax and it should be just the one.
[SPEAKER_00]: So does that impact the
[SPEAKER_00]: uh it does in does not because we don't collect it in the year but it doesn't get it basically gets kicked down the road but it does get it reduces that the overlay that's a good question i don't know how they balance it out in the books because we're not writing we're not saying that it's they don't owe it they just are choosing to defer it at an interest rate i guess that's not our problem but you would think
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so they just, because then the money doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, and it comes back within, I think it's an 8% interest rate.
[SPEAKER_00]: All right, so 41A is still on that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And next up is the CPAs, the 17 that are just being CPs, and that are not tied to another exemption, that the CPA would come off automatically.
[SPEAKER_02]: We'll see.
[SPEAKER_00]: These are the 41 C's, the senior lower income.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there are 27 of those as of last Friday.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have 22 A's.
[SPEAKER_00]: These are the 10 to 90% disabled.
[SPEAKER_02]: It should be great to put it over here.
[SPEAKER_02]: And our 76.
[SPEAKER_00]: most of them were bleached.
[SPEAKER_00]: When it gets to the veterans, right, so anything that has a V in front of it here, most of these are repeats.
[SPEAKER_00]: As of, I think it was fiscal 24, we started requiring them to give us their veterans
[SPEAKER_00]: even if they got it last year.
[SPEAKER_00]: So most of them are used to it now.
[SPEAKER_03]: The first year was like, we gave that to you already.
[SPEAKER_03]: Did they get the same letter or is it one letter that they get and then they never get it again?
[SPEAKER_00]: They get it every year.
[SPEAKER_00]: They get it every year and we just have them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that way there's no confusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right there on the, that's part of the application and says their disabled status or percentage.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then 22 of these, I can go right and use these results here.
[SPEAKER_02]: 20 of those, and this is the various votes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Last but not least, these are 100% disabled, 38 exemptions as of last Friday.
[SPEAKER_00]: Last one, Steven, is right in front of you, the 22 E's.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are the same thing, 100% bed disabled, but they live in a two family and occupy only one unit, so they get half of the full exemption.
[SPEAKER_00]: All right.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then for these, we will have these 12 copies.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll have the staff make copies of each one of these and attach each ones in front of each document to show that we signed each one.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then there were just three denials.
[SPEAKER_00]: They didn't meet the asset rating components.
[SPEAKER_00]: So if I found court income was too high, 14 Honeywell assets were too high, and same here, income was too high.
[SPEAKER_00]: So one signature on each rent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would those be consent?
[SPEAKER_02]: All right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Up next is the carryover that was discussed, that was added to the agenda.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is from, again, Judy was the treasurer-collector of personal property and collectibles.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is a sheet that tallies the totals from all previous fiscal years from 04 to 22.
[SPEAKER_00]: in each one of those ties to a packet that we will pass around.
[SPEAKER_00]: They should be in the order of fiscal year.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just put them all into your density and we'll just make a stack over there.
Bye.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who does the work on these?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it your office or Treasurer's?
[SPEAKER_00]: Treasurer collected those and then we review personal property.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, my understanding of how this happened is that it wasn't cleaned up each year.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there was a backlog and she was working on that backlog of cleaning out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, collectibles are in books that will never be collected again.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is this everything from those years?
[SPEAKER_00]: That was my understanding in the previous meeting.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then I guess there were more that were found.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why this was the unanticipated agenda item that was added to this meeting.
[SPEAKER_00]: She now is saying that it's leaned out through 22.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, it's more of a carryover from what I thought was going to be a one-time from June.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the same exercise which is cleaning out old personal properties.
[SPEAKER_00]: None of these are in any of the four last fiscal years.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're all from 04 to 22.
[SPEAKER_00]: administratively as it comes off of all these, the old fours, because they weren't done in the years they were built, it'll come off in total out of the 26, so we'll get 26 full abatement for that whole figure, so.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are they all for the same reason, non-business?
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, non-business, like they just can't,
[SPEAKER_00]: They cannot be collected and they've exhausted all evidence.
[SPEAKER_01]: I wonder what they do for like some of these like a chain or like an internal block.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I was curious and my inquiry was answered with yeah, they would have exhausted all avenues and to leave them on the books only serves to basically inflate the city thinks it's going to collect one and in fact doesn't have the ability to collect these.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if there is still a business, like an H&R Block, is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Good question.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe it's tied to that location.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can follow up with Judy and ask.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just curious about ones like that, where there's still an entity, the AT&T, whether you're restricted to just collecting from a location.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's a location, you can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: What about Chassis?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's my assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because obviously, H&R Block is still in business.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe not at that location, but so is that non-collectible for another reason, such as, I mean, if it's such a small amount, how do you even go about collecting the correct sum?
[SPEAKER_01]: No one's going to pursue it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't buy it or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's too many months like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: just recently, not in some personal property, but had an issue with the MBTA, where she came in and said that they owed out, it was a water bill for the MBTA over Wellington, and they got the lien put on their real estate, wasn't paid, they accumulated some $25,000 in interest, and she said, well, we can't collect it, they won't pay, so I put on a call with DLS just to see what they, so they're
[SPEAKER_00]: You can try to have them pay it, but they won't pay interest.
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess the state doesn't pay interest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Different topic, but what she's saying is once we exhaust all avenues and can't collect it, we certainly have no other option but to write them off.
[SPEAKER_00]: In specific with the personal property, realistically it's different.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when they'll lean in and take it, but personal property is too hard to track now, is what I was told.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if some of them, they're all listed as not in business, which seems to apply to the vast majority, certainly at that location.
[SPEAKER_01]: But maybe some of the real unspeakable reasons are what you just explained, that all avenues have been exhausted, not that it's not owed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I guess not in business would make it uncollectible, as opposed to if they weren't in business at the time that it was
[SPEAKER_01]: to them which wouldn't have been appropriate.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would have been taken care of a long time ago.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not certain how much of this is just true cleanup work from 2004.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't remember, I don't even remember what I did five years ago, 20 years ago.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I was on that spreadsheet that I asked you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it was about 70?
[SPEAKER_02]: 2019 Austria.
[SPEAKER_00]: All right, got that taken care of.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the last piece of topic, or last topic before we go to executive session is just evaluation update.
[SPEAKER_00]: So beginning of this week, we got our rates and rate of standards meeting with Vision, our software vendor that pulls all our data for real estate and looked at commercial.
[SPEAKER_00]: roughly flat, see cap rates ticking up a little bit in some office, for instance, ticked up slightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Most every other space was flat.
[SPEAKER_00]: We just recently had a hotel sale on the Riverside, just sold 27 million right across the street from here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Residential wise, seeing
[SPEAKER_00]: from two to 7% increase roughly.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just got the rates in today.
[SPEAKER_00]: We pushed them over.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I'm in the process of working on that, but that's the update right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: As we're seeing between two and 7% moves in the residential sector and commercial looks basically flat to 1%, 1 to 2%, which is basically flat.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we'll be working through round one of the valuation for the recertification year.
[SPEAKER_00]: over the next two, three weeks with myself and Mike Torello at Vision, and then Becky Boucher at the State.
[SPEAKER_00]: We'll take the final review being at a restart year, and we will be putting out the values on our website.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it's October 17th, 7th through 17th.
[SPEAKER_00]: Becky, let me check on that.
[SPEAKER_00]: We do a disclosure period on the recertification years.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the 17th through the 30th.
[SPEAKER_00]: We'll have them up on the website.
[SPEAKER_00]: This year 26 valuations for each parcel throughout the city.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's a opportunity for the taxpayers to look at their value.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any questions we can try to resolve it or explain it prior to committing the values.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the final step will be the taxpayer guarantee.
[SPEAKER_00]: And like I said, we'll be working
[SPEAKER_00]: takes their review of it, then we'll disclose it.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do they get notified that their values are out there to review?
[SPEAKER_00]: Public disclosure, we will do, we'll put it on the website, and then they do a, I believe, they reach out, Steve Smurdy upstairs will do a reach out via the website, saying that the public disclosure, which is mandatory for every value here, is on the website.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do they do any other types, like a robocall, their mailing or anything?
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not sure, I looked back,
[SPEAKER_00]: to the last revalue year that was 2021.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wasn't here.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was Ellen at the time and she had saved it as the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was on the website but they just put a banner on the website.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can look here for the link and we did have a list of each of the properties in alphabetical order.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could find your property that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I guess because we're more difficult
[SPEAKER_01]: a short period of time where they can do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So nothing goes out like in a, let me see, in a tax bill?
[SPEAKER_01]: No tax bill, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No tax bill goes out.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, we could try to, you know, it would be an undertaking, I think, for the collector's office to put a pamphlet in the, what would it be, the second quarter bill, right, so before there, or even the October bill, I guess, to get it right before, so even the second or third quarter.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, I don't know how much of a task that would be for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, if you can ask it easy enough, I don't know what it takes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that would be the best way, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sticking it in a tax bill to pre-notify people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I know there's a lot going on in Medford, a lot of changes that affect people's wallets.
[SPEAKER_01]: This could be one of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And a lot of concern that people aren't getting proper notice of
[SPEAKER_01]: of how things are happening, and I know we're probably going to meet whatever statutory requirements that are out for notice, but if this is... I hope with the tax billing system we have a simple way of putting notes in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that'd be great if they could, and I'll certainly pass the treasure collector's sheet to do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if it's not a stuffer, even if they have the ability to do a
[SPEAKER_00]: put a short memo on them?
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll ask if they can.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's easy, certainly.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think that's great to inform each person on their tax bill.
[SPEAKER_00]: Statutorily, the website suffices for the public disclosure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, I think, with outreach from upstairs, they could put out more notice that the values will be out there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, of course, there's still a January period.
[SPEAKER_00]: That always applies every year.
[SPEAKER_00]: but everything's finalized by then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything's finalized by then, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more of like a question and answer period, isn't that right?
[SPEAKER_00]: It would fall into the abatement period.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, do you get the opportunity if somebody picks out something that's an hour from now period, do you have an opportunity to do anything then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is there not even enough time, you know, if you had to go out and do a remanagement or something?
[SPEAKER_00]: There is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we can definitely get that taken care of.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's part of the public disclosure before we
[SPEAKER_00]: the tax rate hearing which is the final setting of the of the rates once the tax rate hearing is done then the rates are the rate is committed and the values are committed so it's basically a second check by the taxpayer if they choose but we will certainly do our due diligence in here and uh you know review each one of the changes and values to make sure they're in line with the market can i just don't get the documentation on the um
[SPEAKER_01]: minutes of the meeting, can I make a motion then that we investigate ways to communicate this tax base through the tax bill?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then to take advantage of any ways we have and work by in that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Notify through.
[SPEAKER_00]: So let's try to think.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the October bill, the third quarter bill would go out.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: The second quarter bill would go out right before that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Second quarter preliminary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go back through the second quarter preliminary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Correct?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: Second.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so that motion is noted and I will make that inquiry with the treasure collector.
[SPEAKER_01]: So what do you refer to those values as?
[SPEAKER_01]: What would they be posted on the website as?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I guess you could call them preliminary FY26.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not committed yet, so they wouldn't be technically certified.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just
[SPEAKER_00]: Once every five years during the revalue, we take the second step before committing the value.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's a second look at your value before it is on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always on every year, your third quarter bill.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's basically a preview, if you will, of what the value will be on your third quarter bill.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I think that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can make a motion to adjourn if there's no other questions.
[SPEAKER_00]: We can do executive session.
[SPEAKER_01]: We'll go on to executive session if you want to do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll stay on that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are we adjourned from... Yeah, I misspoke.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I'm going to go on to executive session.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can probably adjourn after that.
Oh.