short of Herculean compared, I mean, frankly, compared to most years as in COVID, this is a monumental amount of work. We have the negotiations, we have the MSBA project, which will, I think, really be kicking off
once we're through eligibility. We have the supplemental budget, which I mean, we've probably never done a supplemental budget because we've never had a surprise, not surprise, but a mid-year influx of money. And we have the regular budget as well. And so with those gigantic things,
And those are all individually an enormous amount of work, in addition to the everyday running of the district. That's why continuity and minimal disruption in my mind, at least around those things, is important to me. So that's where I'm coming from. And I'll let other people talk.
Just from the chair, add to all the work that needs to be done, the maintenance of our schools, the continuation of the MSBA project. I know that we are actively working on 20 plus million HVAC project, which we hope to include solar on one of the roofs of one of our middle schools.
And I'm sure we can all add a whole, keep going on the list of things that need to get done. So we need somebody, yes, that's gonna continue the hard work of Dr. Edward Vincent and move us along. Member Rousseau. I'm ready to make my motion if nobody else wants to speak.
Member Ntapa, and then I'll turn it over to you, Member Russo. If I could just add, you know, I share very similar thoughts of minimal disruption, you know, in particular with students. When I think of who I would want in the role of the interim, you know, I want someone who
I'm trying to figure out a way to really phrase this, but, you know, someone who during negotiations can work with our, with our, with our, you know, bargaining units, someone who can really work to striving some repairing some relationships and just working towards, you know.
just again, like while we're going through all of this, just minimal disruptions. And I guess I just echo a lot of the same, but wanted to throw my two cents in there of, you know, observing behaviors, looking at who, you know, embodies that spirit of the Mustang Way and the spirit of who can lead, you know, the district in this interim period and possibly, you know, if they choose to apply and get appointed through the search. So those are my thoughts.
Thank you, Member Rousseau. I will make a motion. Is there a hand from Member Greenfield?
Yeah, I just wanted to relay from a comment that I received from the public of looking for somebody who's going to prioritize some of whom maybe are more vulnerable populations. I know that is something that Dr. Edward Vincent was very committed to as well, but to really make that explicit, that we are potentially looking at a fair bit of turmoil as changing federal and state regulations come down, filter down to local districts. And so,
being on top of that and aware of how it affects the wide range of populations within our schools. Thank you, Member Reinfeldt. Member Rousseau.
All right, I'd like to make a, and I'll explain my motion. There's some parts to it. I'm sure some of you will want to know more about, but my motion is to appoint assistant superintendent, Dr. Suzanne Galluzzi as interim superintendent of Medford Public Schools effective January 18th, 2025 through June 30th, 2026 contingent on a successful contract negotiation. I guess I have a second before we talk about it.
Second. Mayor, you're on mute. Thank you, Member Russo. There's a motion on the floor by Member Russo and seconded by Member Graham to appoint Assistant Superintendent Dr. Suzanne Galluzzi as our interim. If there's no questions or comments. Member Adapa?
Could I just, you know, point of clarification ask how, because we mentioned us all giving nominations. So, if our nominations differ, how do we go about. Presenting that effectively and how do we do that as a motion? Do we just do we vote on. Do we do 7 different motions is that 1 motion to a point if you could just clarify that would be great. So I fully understand what what is going on. Remember so.
Yes, just it's like any other meeting, frankly, as weird as that is, because it's not like any other meeting. But I've made this motion, and it's been seconded. So it'd have to be voted on. It could be amended if there was something you wanted to amend, and we'd have to vote on that. And then if you have a different motion, you can make that as well. I think that if this motion is called and passes, you making a different motion for a different person
Uh, I'd have to ask Howard how we handle that because we will have voted already, but. Yeah, so and member Graham will hold the roll call. Do you have additional comments member and topic that you like to just or additional nominations that you like to discuss before I call the roll?
Yes, I would like to additionally nominate Mr. Paul Teixeira to be our interim superintendent of schools. I really liked Member Rousseau's language of, I believe, effective January 18th through June 30th, 2026, contingent on a successful contract negotiation. I'll second.
Okay, one second, I gotta write this stuff down, people, one second. Attorney Greenspan? Yes, just to add that in another district that I represent, when these type of issues come up,
just put, say name. Yes. Yeah. The members just say the name. Yep. Yep. That's where I was getting going to go. I think, um, cause if there's only, I'll just say hearing and seeing two, um, names for nomination, uh, we'll call the role. And if there's no further debate, please state either Dr. Suzanne Galussi or, um, Mr. Paul Teixeira for your nomination as, as interim.
Member Zohey Calderon. Sir. Member Brantley. Tech Sarah. Again. Member Graham. Lucy. Member Ntapa. Tech Sarah. Member Olopade. Lucy. Member Rheinfeld.
Galluzzi. Member Rousseau, Suzanne Galluzzi. Mayor Lingo-Kern. Dr. Galluzzi. So that's five for Dr. Galluzzi and two for Mr. Teixeira. Thank you for your votes. Decision has been made. Member Graham. Attorney Greenspan, do we have to take an affirmative vote
now that we've gone through that straw poll process, or is that sufficient? That's sufficient unless anybody would like to... Sometimes I've seen committees make a motion after that vote to make it unanimous, but that's sufficient. Member Brandley or Member Acapo, would you like us to take a roll call vote for Dr. Galluzzi or leave it as is?
I'm fine with leaving it as is. That's fine. Okay. Yeah, I don't think that's going to change, so it's fine leaving it as is. Okay, I knew it wouldn't change, I just didn't know if you wanted to make it unanimous. Oh, okay, I understand. Okay, is there a motion to go into executive session? I can motion to go into executive session. Member Ranley, seconded by? Second. Member Reinfeld, roll call, please.
Member Bradley. Yes. Member Graham. Yes. Member Ntapa. Yes. Member Olopade. Yes. Member Rheinfeld. Yes. Member Rousseau, yes. Mayor Longo, current. Yes, seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative. We can move to executive session and we will not reconvene in public session following this executive session.