Hello, everyone, and welcome to Method Happenings, a show for and about the city of Medford. I am John Petrella, and the purpose of this program is to give Medford citizens facts and information to help you make informed choices. Joining us today is Margaret Petrella, president of the Mystic Players Revival,
She's also my daughter. I just had to throw that in. Unfortunately for us, Jim Sampson, Robert Lublin. Lublin. Lublin, I'm sorry. That's all right, that's all right. Danielle Herget. Yep. And. That's it. Danielle Herget, who are lead members, could not be with us today due to other obligations. So I want to thank Margaret.
for appearing on Method Happenings. How you doing, daughter? I'm pretty good. You're pretty good. I'm pretty good, you know. All right, we'll get the show going here, Megs. First question for you. Sure. What is the Mystic Players revival and how did it all get started?
that's a big question. Sure it is. So Mystic Players Revival is basically I kind of just came up with the idea. I knew about the original Mystic Players and I had always like wanted to have like a theater company in Medford and
I always, you and mom and my grandparents were constantly telling me, join the Mystic Players. Go audition for the Mystic Players. And when I finally decided to look them up, I realized they had disbanded. And I was so bummed out about it, because it's such a great thing, having an adult community theater and all ages community theater in Medford. And so years and years pass. And I just one day was like,
You know what? I'm gonna do this. And so I started a Facebook group called Bring Community Theater Back to Medford. And I met with a bunch of wonderful people. And that's how I met Jim, Danielle, and Robert. And we came up with the name Mystic Players Revival. And the rest is kind of history. Like we just, we, you know, we,
It just kind of happened. We worked really hard and it took a decent amount of time to get to where we are now.
feel like i'm explaining this so poorly um you're doing a good job just keep going you're fine um we're also like we're a non-profit organization um so we uh uh i i feel like you know jim or robert or jdl would be much better off at explaining what that means um and uh um what was i even saying we might have to cut this what was i even saying you were talking about
You know, how did it all start, Margaret? Yeah, yeah. So it started because, you know, we got together, we met up, did the Facebook group, you know, through the Facebook group, and we met in person and we came up with Mystic Players Revival. Okay. Now, I know what your background is in theater and arts, but can you
Tell our audience, you know, what's your background? What have you done? So this is my first time being, like, in charge of something at this, like, level. Right. But as far as background, I have been doing theater, specifically musical theater and, you know, plays since kindergarten.
I used to do Kidstock when I was very little, and then the schools in Medford, I was born and raised in Medford, had wonderful, wonderful drama programs, and I did
every single show in middle school and elementary school. And that's actually what the first memory I have of, I remember kids talk somewhat, but the first memory I have of theater is in third grade with Miss Wallman's class doing Wizard of Oz. And that is the moment my brain kind of clicked and was like, this is it.
It was a blast it's theater is my life yeah, it's my life and You know still to this day. I'm you know
performing and Doing all sorts of stuff, but I also wanted to you know, do something in Medford that mattered I guess I wanted to Help out my my city like not help out my city, but like that's what you're doing. Yeah, you know like Yeah, I just wanted to do something good, you know, it is good and make people smile and happy so
Yeah, and I, you know, you had a great family too, because I remember, I think they took you to New York. We did a lot, you know. A lot of traveling, a lot of auditions. A lot of fun. A lot of traveling for auditions. Yes, it was a lot of fun. I enjoyed it. Yeah, I know, it was always a great time. I always enjoyed it, yeah. But, you know, I always say,
with the Mystic players to kind of go back, sorry, to the first question. Growing up, like I said, I was born and raised in Medford, never left Medford. I grew up around someone like my grandfather, my mother's father, who did so much for the community that he lived in.
and even you know my mom's siblings like you know my uncles they owned a business in Medford and um seeing them help out their community and do so much for other people it just like growing up and seeing that just like inspired me so much and um it just really made a huge difference in my life and a huge impact and um
you know, something my grandfather always like, you know, said to me was like, you know, just be a good person, you know, he instilled that, he instilled it. Yeah. And, and he just, just be a good person and help others. And, um, I was like, well, how can Margaret do that? What is Margaret good at? And then I was like, Oh, theater. Yeah. Um, so yeah. Yeah. That's good. No. And I, you know, uh,
Let's get up to date. You know, I attended your Mystic Cabaret shows. You better have. They were at the McGlynn Middle School. Really the first performances that your crew put on. The first, like, our first official show. Right. Yeah. And, you know, the performances were excellent.
Thank you. You had a great turnout. And I also, like I said, it was your first production. Yep. So congratulations are in order for you and the team. Yes, we all did so much.
So, you know, maybe you can share what our viewers You know some of the backstory. I mean the first show sure you put a lot of work into it. So how did that all come about? Lot of work. Yeah, and a lot of help from the people that are in the city also
Yeah, so basically it all started with us applying for a grant through the Mass Cultural Council because anything you do with the theater world, it requires funding. And so we were lucky enough to receive the grant.
And we, as soon as we got it, we just started immediately, we sat down with one another and just started planning. You know, we weren't, you know, set like, we weren't like, what are we going to do? Are we going to do a play? Are we going to do, what are we, what's it going to be? And we kind of decided on doing like a cabaret style show. And it was basically a bunch of songs from a bunch of different musical theater productions all put into one show.
uh you know we uh put like a call out for auditions um we reached out to all sorts of places in Medford to you know because with theater you need to hold rehearsals um we reached out to
honestly, everybody we possibly could probably annoyed some people. Yes, I'm sure you did. And we, you know, got in touch, thankfully, with, I want to mention them because they've helped us tremendously. The friends of the Chevalier board have been incredible to us. They have helped us so much. They actually had us perform for them.
at a board meeting, and because of that, we met so many new people, and even the mayor, she has been amazing. She has helped us so much. She got us in touch with the McGlynn, and a few other people as well, but at the end of the day, we got in touch with the principal at the McGlynn, we were like, hey,
We really need a space. We also got in touch with Bob Maloney. He's such a great guy. We got in touch with him about the McGlynn as well. Thanks to both principal Tucci and Bob, we were able to secure the McGlynn as a space for us.
was amazing. And that that was just step like one of a million was getting the space. But we held auditions. And I always say it's funny, you know, we got so many people from all over Massachusetts, like, you know, like, some people, we even had someone come from New Hampshire and audition for audition. Yeah. And it's like, Whoa, you know what I mean? Like, we're this is our first ever show and people are already coming out and like,
you know, to just audition. And so we held auditions, we cast the show really fast, because we were in a very short time frame. And then we had all of our rehearsals, and we put on a show.
And you put on a good show, you really did. Thank you, thank you. I also want to mention, because I love the library, the Method Public Library. Yes, yeah. I know you had a lot of editions and whatever, tryouts, I don't know, but
They helped you out quite a bit. Yes. So we didn't hold auditions there, but we do do events there. So we do an open mic type of event. And basically it's you can come to these events. You can come prepared with a monologue, a song. Sometimes we have themed nights. Like recently we just did like a, um,
We had like a missed cast thing and then we did like a comedy night thing. So we've had like, you know, we try to like, you know, make it more fun sometimes, but people come, they do like performances and it's just like, it's what like community theater really is all about. Like it's just, you know, it brings people together and it's amazing. And you get to see a lot of talent. Yeah. And it's, everyone is incredible. So.
You know, I guess, uh, there's a lot that goes on behind the scenes. You've explained all that. Um, excuse me. Yep. But what about casting? I know you, you guys, you have to find directors, auditions. How does that all come about? I mean, um, sometimes luck, um, with specifically with like directors, but, um, we,
Ever since our cabaret, we have made almost like a family with the people that were a part of our show. And because of that, we had so many people that performed at our show want to direct for us. And so we got very lucky with that. And we've also had people, unknown people, submit their resumes and their ideas for future shows.
and uh basically we just put a call out on our instagram facebook um you know any social media our website and um for as far as you said casting um so as far as like auditions and like casting and stuff um we uh
There is a great theater forum out there called Your Theater 411 where you can post a free listing like for an audition and that's basically like everyone in New England I think uses it or you know maybe not even just New England maybe everywhere and that's how people find you and you know if they are like oh this looks interesting they can come audition.
So if they're interested in something. Yeah. Okay. Yep. All right. That sounds good. Yeah. Simple. Yeah. So I wouldn't have to go to one audition if I wanted to be in one of your shows. Right. No, you would. No, I just wouldn't automatically. I'd have to audition. Yeah. Wow. You would. Sorry. She's sorry.
So, you know, we're sort of up to date here. There's a lot of events coming up. I'm going to mention Circle the Square. You can get into more detail. So what's going on now? And, you know, what plans do you have for the Mystic Players revival?
Well, let's just say for the rest of the year. Let's put it that way. Okay, so, um, recently we just had auditions and, um, cast a show, uh, for Shakespeare's Much Ado About Nothing, um, and they are currently in rehearsals right now and our show, um, that show will be going up July 26th and 27th
at 530 at the Condon Shell in Medford. A little Shakespeare in the park type of deal. And if anybody is interested in going that, definitely bring blankets, your chairs. If you want to bring a picnic, you're more than welcome. Because it's the Condon Shell. I don't know if people know what that is. It's an outdoor venue. So we're doing it there.
that, you know, we, it's directed by Brian Treiber, um, who was, like I just said, um, one of the people who, uh, emailed us with his resume and, um, we had interviews and we were like, you picked him. Yeah, we picked him and, uh, we, uh, we've been working closely with him and we're really excited about this show. Um, you know, we,
like to do all sorts of things, not just musicals. And then as far as the fall plans, not really sure just yet. Hopefully, we will know more by the end of this week. I wish I could give you more details on that. But unfortunately, I just it's kind of that's out of my control right now. Right. And then for spring, we like to do a cabaret. We're going to be doing a cabaret hopefully every year.
Like the one the mystic cabaret. That was great. Yeah, that was a great show So we're gonna be doing another cabaret again no Extra details on that yet. Not sure what we're gonna be doing But we do have a director for that as well And it's just very exciting. Oh and we do we do have a director for fall But we're still decided, you know finalizing details, okay
But the director for the fall and the director for the spring are actually two of our cast members of the mystic cabaret and We love them both very much If people want to get in touch if someone wants to offer you the services Audition for a show. I know you've already said it, but how what's the best way to get in touch? with mystic players revival
Um, so we have a bunch of social media, but, um, we have our website, um, mystic players, revival.org. Um, we have a Instagram, um, at mystic players revival, and we have our, uh, Facebook as well. Mystic players revival. Um, and, oh, we have, uh, we also, I forgot about this. We have, uh, we also have a tech talk, um, at mystic plays revival and a YouTube mystic players revival. Okay.
I know, I know, but repeat it. So people, okay. Website mystic players, revival.org Instagram at mystic players, revival, tech talk at mystic players, revival, Facebook, mystic players, revival, and YouTube mystic players, revival. Awesome. So this way people, every social media, mystic players, revival, mystic players, revival, mystic players, revival, mystic players, revival.
Yeah, well, it's good because people that, you know, aren't, you know, able to, you know, get into the, or know about the theater forums and stuff, they can, they find another way to get in touch. It's always a good thing. All right. So we're going to be closing out the show. And that brings me, uh,
You know, I guess this is my last question, maybe. So I know, Mr. Players Revival, you're appearing at Circle the Square, which is Saturday, June 21st. You already have a rain date for the 22nd. Can you give us an idea? I mean, what is your... There's a lot going on with Circle the Square this year. I think it's going to be...
I think it's going to be a successful event. Oh, absolutely. There's a lot, a lot of exciting, a lot of interesting events this year, as there always is. But what do you guys got planned? Anything? Yes. So they asked us, Cache reached out to us and they were like, hey, would you guys like to perform for Circles of War? And we were like, yes.
of course we were just so excited immediately we said yes um didn't even have a second thought um as soon as they reached out we reached out to our cabaret cast um and we were like hey guys who wants to perform with us again um and we got um
so many people that performed in the cabaret to perform in Circle the Square with us, so if you saw the cabaret you will see some familiar faces, which is very exciting, and maybe hear a familiar song as well.
And we're going to be doing a musical theater review of sorts. Basically just, you know, performances of songs from different musical theater shows. And we've been rehearsing for a couple weeks now. We're so ready, super excited. We're performing right in Medford Square, right in front of the,
the cemetery, that mini, like, the small little cemetery, right where, like, across the street from, like, Ebisu, where Ebisu was, yeah. So,
Yeah, we're really excited, and I don't want to give away too much. You don't want to give away too much? That means you want it to be a surprise. I don't want to give away our songs. I want people to be like, ooh. Maybe I can give away one. We are going to be performing Dancing Queen as our finale. Oh, that should be fun. Yeah.
Everybody loves that. Yeah, that's something to come out for that song specifically. That's interesting. Yeah, that's what everybody knows. I'm going to take part in this, correct? Yes. Yeah. As well as Jim and Danielle, other our other two board members, which I should I totally forgot to even do introduce them with their titles, which I should probably do. So sure. Danielle is our secretary. Robert is our vice president and Jim is our treasurer.
Okay, very good. All right. So, all sounds great. And I'm not a bragging father, but my daughter, Margaret, people have come to plenty of your shows. You're a very talented singer, if I say so myself. Well, you are. You are. No doubt about that. So, I want to thank you, Mags, for coming on the show today.
It's been nice. It's been fun. This was a fun show. It's very casual. Yeah, it's a very casual show. It's like we're just talking in the living room, you know, just chatting. It's sort of been fun. With lots of lights and cameras in our faces. Yeah, and I enjoyed it. I enjoyed every bit of it and I'm glad you came on. I totally messed up that first question, but that's fine. That's okay. That's okay. Stuff happens, you know. I'm nervous.
I got stage fright, shockingly. You did a great job. Thank you. You did a great job. And thank you. Thank you. Thank you for joining us. Thank you, Medford Happenings, for having me. All right, so it sounds good. You got a lot going on. A lot going on. Very busy. And we'll definitely see you at Circle the Square. Yeah. So thank you again. Thank you.
So that's our show. And I also want to take a minute to thank everyone who has been watching the show. And thank you for your feedback, whether it's been positive or negative. It's appreciated. We do look at it. And it helps us form the show and decide what we're going to be doing. So thank you for that.
If you would like to share a comment, we are going to be having some candidates come on, whatever, school committee, city council. I think we feel that it's important to introduce you to some candidates. So we're inviting any candidate.
If you're running for re-election, if you're a new candidate, school committee, city council, mayor, whatever it is, you're more than welcome to join us on the show.
So if you are a candidate for city office, please be more than welcome. You can contact us johnpatroller55 at gmail.com. We'd be glad to have you on the show. If you're opening a new business or you have an existing business,
or you represent an organization with an upcoming event and would like to appear on a future show, once again, you can contact us at johnpatroller55 at gmail.com.
So thank you everybody for watching. You will be able to see replays of this show on Medford Community Media, Monday, Wednesdays, and Fridays. You can view us at 6 p.m. And you can also see Medford Happenings on MedfordTV.org, YouTube, and Facebook.
So from all of us at Method Happenings, I'm John Petralla, and we hope to see you at Circle the Square on Saturday, June 21st. Thank you, everyone. Ta-da! Ta-da!
Ta-da!