[SPEAKER_18]: Welcome to the Mustang Report.
[SPEAKER_07]: Back and better than ever, I'm Kerianne.
[SPEAKER_14]: I'm Andy.
[SPEAKER_07]: And I'm Lydia.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hi, I'm Cheyenne.
[SPEAKER_05]: And I'm Gabby.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hi, I'm Lizzie.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hi, I'm Gigi.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hi, I'm Courtney.
[SPEAKER_09]: Nick Kenniston, the voice of Bedford High.
[SPEAKER_06]: Hi, I'm Hallie.
[SPEAKER_07]: Hi, I'm Dora the Reporter.
[SPEAKER_19]: Hi, I'm Sam.
[SPEAKER_19]: Let's go boys!
[SPEAKER_19]: but i can make an explosion and all those things i didn't say inside my brain i will scream out loud tonight can you hear my voice this time this is my fight song take back my
[SPEAKER_07]: Hello, this is DP reporting here in Mr. Tucci's office for our first edition of Faculty Friday with Mr. Tucci.
[SPEAKER_07]: Mr. Tucci, how are you doing today?
[SPEAKER_12]: I'm doing lovely.
[SPEAKER_12]: Happy Friday to everybody.
[SPEAKER_07]: And I was wondering if I could ask you a few questions.
[SPEAKER_12]: Sure can.
[SPEAKER_07]: All right.
[SPEAKER_07]: So how are you feeling getting back into the swing of things of school?
[SPEAKER_07]: How has it been going?
[SPEAKER_07]: Has it been rocky?
[SPEAKER_07]: Has it been going smoothly?
[SPEAKER_12]: So far, it's been great.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's actually been really nice to see all the new faces with the freshmen of the class of 2020.
[SPEAKER_12]: I'm very excited to start the school year off.
[SPEAKER_12]: And September is full of awesome emotions, but a lot of excitement.
[SPEAKER_12]: And overall, I think the school year has been off to a pretty good start.
[SPEAKER_12]: We have an awesome senior class.
[SPEAKER_12]: Like I said, the freshman class is looking good.
[SPEAKER_12]: And I definitely know my juniors are ready to do awesome things this year, too, as well.
[SPEAKER_07]: Speaking of the juniors, how do you feel about the junior class?
[SPEAKER_07]: Do you think they're doing well with the transition to being upperclassmen?
[SPEAKER_12]: So the class of 2018 has always been one of my favorites.
[SPEAKER_12]: They're a very bright, young group of people.
[SPEAKER_12]: They're also excellent on and off the sports field, too.
[SPEAKER_12]: They're very active with club and athletics and things like that, too.
[SPEAKER_12]: So it's been a pleasure working with them.
[SPEAKER_12]: Look forward to seeing them do awesome things in their junior year, because it's an important academic year.
[SPEAKER_12]: We want to see them do very well and excel on and off the field and in the classroom and in their sports and in the band and in the extracurriculars that they're doing.
[SPEAKER_12]: but we want them to enjoy it too.
[SPEAKER_12]: So we have an exciting welcome back dance coming up at the end of September, September 30th, sponsored by the GSA.
[SPEAKER_12]: And then we also have club and activities fair coming up on this Friday, which is going to be right outside the cafeterias.
[SPEAKER_12]: So we hope that more people get involved with a lot of the great activities and clubs that we have to offer too.
[SPEAKER_07]: That's great.
[SPEAKER_07]: I know most of us here at the Mustang Report, we're all involved in different extracurricular activities, so it's really good that people will put themselves out there to try something new and hopefully enjoy it.
[SPEAKER_07]: I have one more question for you.
[SPEAKER_07]: I know this year we switched to a new system called School Brains.
[SPEAKER_07]: How is that working out for MHS?
[SPEAKER_12]: You know, it's working out.
[SPEAKER_12]: You know, it's been a transition, you know, to learn a new system for our faculty and to also schedule students into that.
[SPEAKER_12]: But at the same point in time, I think the long-term prospects of School Brains is going to help our students, our faculty, and our community and help us better communicate with the community how students are doing and also help you guys see what type of progress you're doing in your classes too as well.
[SPEAKER_12]: So we're looking forward to getting to know the system more and hopefully utilizing it to its best capacity.
[SPEAKER_12]: So look forward to a great year along those lines.
[SPEAKER_07]: All right, thank you for taking the time out of your day to do an interview with us.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'm DP, here with Mr. Tucci for the Mustang Report.
Yeah!
[SPEAKER_18]: Go, go, go, go!
[SPEAKER_14]: yeah oh my god oh no
What do we have?
[SPEAKER_18]: What?
[SPEAKER_18]: I hear something, sir.
[SPEAKER_10]: Region number.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's the first of the shift.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's an expectation here.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's an expectation.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, to our offensive line.
[SPEAKER_10]: He's in.
[SPEAKER_17]: Hi, my name is Karen Luchares from the Mustang Rapport and I'm here with Anthony McKillop, the leader and creator of the Stang Gang.
[SPEAKER_17]: Anthony, can you tell us a little bit about what your club's about?
[SPEAKER_14]: All right, so what we do is we get a bunch of kids from the school that want to have a lot of school spirit.
[SPEAKER_14]: We bring them to two sporting events a week.
[SPEAKER_14]: We get the crowd pumped up.
[SPEAKER_14]: We get the team.
[SPEAKER_14]: We give them confidence, you know what I mean?
[SPEAKER_14]: We just pump them up with cheers.
[SPEAKER_14]: We give them cheers.
[SPEAKER_14]: We give them everything they need to get that dub, to get that win, all right?
[SPEAKER_14]: That's what we do.
[SPEAKER_14]: I want to see everybody else here that watches this to the games, all right?
[SPEAKER_16]: Tell me about singing.
[SPEAKER_16]: You're wearing the shirt.
[SPEAKER_16]: You've got to represent Stanging.
[SPEAKER_16]: Tell me all about it.
[SPEAKER_14]: We just try to get as many people as we can, get them to the sporting events, and go wild.
[SPEAKER_18]: Just go wild.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hi, I'm Lydia Ryan.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm here with the Mustang Report at Medford's High opening football game this season.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm here with Dr. Perrella, our headmaster, superintendent, Mr. Bellison, and student council committee, Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Cuno.
[SPEAKER_03]: How are you guys doing tonight?
[SPEAKER_12]: Fabulous, it's a beautiful evening.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's a great night for the band and the football team.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a great opening night to see everyone here tonight.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm here with the athletic director, Mr. Maloney.
[SPEAKER_03]: How's your night going tonight?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going pretty good.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have a good crowd.
[SPEAKER_00]: The weather's fantastic.
[SPEAKER_00]: We started off 8-0.
[SPEAKER_00]: We had a struggle in the second quarter, but hopefully we have a better second half and we can pull this out tonight.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I also noticed that they have been doing construction in the gymnasium, and I was just wondering what that was.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, we're thrilled.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mia Burke, Superintendent Belson, the school committee and the city council got us some money.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're getting all brand new baskets, all new pulley systems.
[SPEAKER_00]: So at the end of next week we'll have a brand new gymnasium.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to be beautiful.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's so exciting.
[SPEAKER_03]: I hope the basketball team will like it and we can obviously use it for the school too as well during gym.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Volleyball will be happy, basketball will be happy, the phys ed classes and all the rentals.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a state-of-the-art facility once this stuff gets completed.
[SPEAKER_06]: Hi, I'm Hallie Fowle and I'm here with Emma.
[SPEAKER_06]: So Emma, how do you think the game's going so far?
[SPEAKER_15]: I think it's going pretty good.
[SPEAKER_15]: They're playing pretty well.
[SPEAKER_06]: Do you think they're going to win?
[SPEAKER_15]: I have faith in them.
[SPEAKER_15]: I think they have a chance.
[SPEAKER_06]: How do you think the basketball team is going to do this year?
[SPEAKER_15]: I'm hoping we're going to do pretty good.
[SPEAKER_15]: It's looking good so far.
[SPEAKER_06]: Sounds good.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thanks, Emma.
[SPEAKER_10]: What are some of the advantages of joining the Stang Gang?
[SPEAKER_13]: A couple reasons.
[SPEAKER_13]: One, it's a great way to get involved with Medford community.
[SPEAKER_13]: If you're a freshman or sophomore, you're not involved with any activity or club, this is a great way to connect with your peers.
[SPEAKER_13]: Also, students will receive community service for every event that they go to.
[SPEAKER_11]: We've been doing this for four years, the Medford Strong Motorcycle Run for the Crystal Campbell Scholarship Fund.
[SPEAKER_11]: For you guys, the students of Medford High School, the scholarship was designed through the Medford Strong Motorcycle Run in Crystal's name with the sponsors and the bikers who come out today, they pay a certain amount to ride, $20 on each rider, and we get to put that money into the scholarship.
[SPEAKER_11]: Now we'll cruise right by the Peace Garden.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm hoping to get 300 to 400 bikes to really make some noise.
[SPEAKER_11]: I put a lot of work into this.
[SPEAKER_11]: I couldn't do it without the riders, without the bikers who supported me.
[SPEAKER_11]: Of course, my friends, give it up for my volunteers over here on the right.
[SPEAKER_11]: There's too many to mention.
[SPEAKER_11]: They always come out.
[SPEAKER_11]: They always do a great job.
[SPEAKER_11]: Really impressive stuff.
[SPEAKER_11]: And of course, the VFW for putting this together with us and everybody working as one.
[SPEAKER_19]: So how excited are you guys for today?
[SPEAKER_02]: I am stoked.
[SPEAKER_02]: I got to kick it off last year when I was a candidate and now being there it's official.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I'm really excited to kick it off and get them started and start it safe and start it tight.
[SPEAKER_10]: And I'm excited as well because I think it shows that Medford is strong and Medford can get together and we're going to do something great.
[SPEAKER_10]: and we're all excited and waiting for the opening of the Bristol Canyon Park and that's going to be another milestone for the City of Medford and just making everybody in Medford happy that we have an opportunity to remember those who were involved.
[SPEAKER_02]: actually next Sunday we're unveiling the Crystal Campbell Peace Garden and it'll be a very special and very serious offer in some ways and yet looking towards the future of faith healing and camaraderie and peace.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we're really looking forward to next Sunday coming out at 2 o'clock at the Brighton-Medford Queer at the CrossFit Hotel.
[SPEAKER_02]: Crystal Campbell Peace Garden unveiling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_18]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_07]: Hello, this is DP here reporting from the first Medford High varsity volleyball game.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'm here with Bree, Lucy, and Tia, who are three of my fellow teammates on the varsity team.
[SPEAKER_07]: So girls, how do you think the season's gonna go for us this year?
[SPEAKER_04]: I think we're gonna do actually really good.
[SPEAKER_04]: Our team's pretty solid.
[SPEAKER_04]: We're like a family, so I think we're gonna work very well together.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, we're like really excited this year and we're like, like Bree said, we're basically a family and we're all very comfortable and like our coach helps us with everything and it's just great.
[SPEAKER_08]: I know we lost a lot of seniors this year, but I feel like it's still gonna be a great year.
[SPEAKER_08]: New people, new team.
[SPEAKER_08]: Let's go Mustangs.
[SPEAKER_07]: I know, I'm very excited as well.
[SPEAKER_07]: And what do you guys think that our strengths are as a team?
[SPEAKER_04]: I would say helping each other out.
[SPEAKER_04]: We all have certain strengths and I think each one of us helps each other out to figure out what we should work on and what we can do better.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, really coming together as a team and just giving it our all out on the court.
[SPEAKER_08]: It's one of our big strengths.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, we mesh really well.
[SPEAKER_08]: We know how to work with each other and how to help each other out.
[SPEAKER_07]: So here's more of a personal question.
[SPEAKER_07]: How did each of you get into volleyball?
[SPEAKER_07]: Why did you decide to pick volleyball over any other sport?
[SPEAKER_04]: My cousin actually plays volleyball.
[SPEAKER_04]: She plays for Curry now as a sophomore.
[SPEAKER_04]: And she kind of encouraged me to play the sport.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I started my freshman year, and I immediately took to it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, I knew a senior that was on the team when I was a freshman, and she was just super friendly.
[SPEAKER_05]: And she said everyone else on the team was super friendly, like her.
[SPEAKER_05]: And I just really wanted to be a part of a sport.
[SPEAKER_05]: And I thought it would be a good way to make friends before the school year started.
[SPEAKER_08]: Having my aunt and my mom and everyone really play volleyball, especially my aunt, because she played for Great Britain, it really influenced me.
[SPEAKER_08]: I felt like I had to keep the legacy going of a great sport.
[SPEAKER_07]: That's good, that's so nice to hear how different people like inspired you to be like where you are today with all of your success in volleyball.
[SPEAKER_07]: Well I hope that the varsity team is gonna have a first, have a great first game and let's hope for the best.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'm DP reporting here for the Mustang Report.
[SPEAKER_07]: Hello, DP reporting here at the first MHS volleyball game of the season.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'm here with Audrey, Jill, Julia, Hannah, and Megan, and Zimena, right down here.
[SPEAKER_07]: And this is their first game of the season.
[SPEAKER_07]: And how are you ladies feeling today?
[SPEAKER_09]: Great.
[SPEAKER_09]: Very excited.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yes, nervous.
[SPEAKER_09]: Really excited and nervous.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm pretty sweaty.
[SPEAKER_07]: Me too.
[SPEAKER_07]: So, what do you guys, how do you think the outcome of your game is going to be today?
[SPEAKER_09]: Hopefully good.
[SPEAKER_09]: Hopefully we'll win.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, we obviously want to win.
[SPEAKER_09]: Feeling pretty strong.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, feeling good.
[SPEAKER_07]: Feeling good.
[SPEAKER_07]: Good.
[SPEAKER_07]: And, just a little like personal questions, how did you guys get into, like what made you decide to try out for volleyball this year?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I mean, I've been playing volleyball ever since I was a kid, so like it's nice to take it like professional now.
[SPEAKER_07]: I wish you guys the best of luck and I hope for the best of your game.
[SPEAKER_07]: We all know it's gonna be a win.
[SPEAKER_07]: DP reporting here live at the first MHS volleyball game of the season.