Vice President bears president counts of Carabiello counselor Collins, President Council night President Councilor Kelly, Councilor saying, President, President Morrell, President.
motions, orders and resolutions to two dash three zero zero offered by counselor night. Be it so resolved that the city solicitor provide the Medford City Council with a draft ordinance require a monthly presentation by finance, the finance director to review the warrant articles and projected versus forecasted revenues tonight. Madam President, thank you very much. This was a resolution that had been passed by this previous councils on multiple occasions, this information.
has been very difficult to get and has not been coming forth with. So I think that at this point in time, it would make sense that we move forward and codify this request so that it would be part of our local law and therefore a requirement that we be provided with this information so that we can properly prepare for the financial responsibilities that we have as council. Thank you, Councilor Knight. Any discussion? Second. On the motion of Councilor Knight, seconded by Vice President Behrs. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Vice President bears. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
permit parking restrictions while conducting official post office business. Councilor Knight. Madam President, thank you very much. At the risk of being told I'm not in any position to discuss this matter, I'd like to bring it forward anyway. It's been brought to my attention that Park Medfit has been ticketing the letter carriers in our community.
So the individuals that deliver us medications, bills, mail documents and the like, employees of the United States government, not the state government, not the local government, who are exercising their duties for the post office, not being held harmless in the execution of those duties, Madam President. Past practice has always been that our letter carriers would be held harmless when they were using their personal vehicles to conduct post office business.
And this policy has apparently changed with the implementation of the in-house parking program. So I'd ask that the traffic commission take up the issue and create a letter carriers pass so that our letter carriers that are using their personal vehicles for post office business can park on city streets to deliver the mail and medication and the other materials that they so deliver to the residents of the community free of interference from parking.
Thank you, Madam President. Excuse me. I support this measure wholeheartedly. I'd like to propose a B paper just to request that the administration report to us on what communications methods they used to reach out to residents regarding the new parking program and whether or not they plan to include any information about this program in mailings to city residents or property owners.
Thank you. If constantly wouldn't wouldn't mind amending this so if we can provision it if the visiting nurses.
that come to many people's homes also. That's another common call I get is, you know, the nurse comes to visit my mother or comes in to do treatments, and they don't have anywhere to park it, and they get tickets on the street. So if we could maybe look at something for medical personnel who host visits, it would be appreciated.
Do you want to speak on the parking passes? Okay. Any further discussion from the council? Name and address for the record, please. Parking there is horrendous. And I've, I've been to the mayor's office downstairs and I requested parking permits on that street and it's gone without any notice.
When I went to other streets within Medfed, I see parking places all over the place up in East Med, was it North Medfed, West Medfed? They have parking permit, but on that particular street, on 22 Bradley Road, on Bradley Road, we cannot have parking for residents on that street. There's not enough spaces. And what happens is everybody, I've lived there for 22 years, so I know what goes on. People come in from out of town,
People that work into the center of the town, and I understand they pay taxes but I inadvertently pay taxes to rent. You're allowed to park during the day. They come from writing, they work all over Medford Square, they're allowed to park all day during that. I am like a hostage to my apartment.
So, the traffic commission petition for turning streets and department parking. Have you, have you worked with the traffic commission to the mayor give any indication you should give me any indications because I've got numerous tickets there, and now they take it on a Saturday. I come up one Saturday and I had a parking ticket, and I was like appalled. I paid the ticket because I didn't want to deal with the parking office up on Main Street.
Absolutely. So it was horrible. And then I want to say, because I have to get it off my chest. The year of 2010 was the worst winter in this city. And I remember distinctly because I got out of graduate school and I was working and I couldn't get a job because of the economy. And every week I was getting parking tickets and they were putting parking meters on the street and giving out parking tickets to the residents. During one of the worst blizzards
I think that's unconscionable. I understand. I think those decisions predate this most of us on the council I could, I know I have your email I can reach out to the mayor it is petitioning to turn the street department parking goes to the traffic commission. So I can, I can follow up on that make sure you're the right person. Yes, well no it's kind of a new situation now because of what we're here for but I believe we have to wait until the end.
Understood. But I can follow up with you by email. That would be true. Well, we'll see what happens now because I'm going to be forced to move. Understood. Thank you. Yep. Yep. Just name and address for the record. Hello, my name is Donia Goss. I live at 26 Bradley Road. I have a disabled placard. Anyway, whenever the Chevalier Theater has a show,
to having a show Friday night, Joan Jett. Great theater. Whenever there's a show, you cannot find a parking space within a quarter of a mile. And our building has 30 units.
and there's maybe five or six spaces on the street, because there's no parking lot. So it's very, for me, sometimes I go grocery shopping, I come home, I go around and around and around, I can't find a place to park, and then I have to carry all, parking is unbearable. That's all. Thank you. Madam President, if I can. Please. Excuse me. Quick question. I apologize, did you say you were handicapped?
Did you? Yes. Do you have a placard? Yes. And did they put a handicapped spot on that street for you? There is one handicapped spot in front of the senior citizen building, right? But there are other senior citizens that are handicapped in that building. Occasionally I will park there but sometimes I don't find a space there. I hope we get to find a resolution for what
Our neighbors are going through on Bradley Road, but this is something that as we move forward, I think it's something that we should talk with the traffic commission, maybe hold a meeting with the residents of Bradley Road, because this is something that's been going on for years and no one has listened. There's just not enough physical spaces. Well, maybe there's other solutions that we could talk to the traffic commission when the time comes. So let's hope we can find the resolution for the biggest issue and then revert back and circle back to the traffic commission, because that's important.
So thank you. Thank you so much. Any further discussion? Anyone else would like to speak? So on the motion of Councillor Knight, as amended by Councillor Carviello, seconded by Vice President Behrs, and there's also the B paper from Vice President Behrs, seconded by Councillor Scarpelli. I'm going to take the B paper first. The B paper is to get an update from the administration on the communication methods used to reach out to residents regarding parking.
changes, and whether or not they send any communications through mail. Yes. Yes. Vice President bears. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
President Morrell. Yes. The main motion by Councilor Knight, seconded by Vice President Behrs. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Vice President Behrs. Yes. Councilor Kerrio. Yes. Councilor Collins. Yes. Councilor Knight. Yes. Councilor Scarpelli. Yes.
Yes. President Morrell. Yes, seven in front of zero then I get the motion passes. 22-0302 offered by Councilor Knight and Councilor Scarpelli. Whereas the sign posted along Rams Head and Heath Roads restricting parking along the wooded side of the street has displaced vehicles to a similar area of Judgment Road, be it so resolved that the Metro City Council request the Traffic Commission approve similar signage along the impacted stretch of Judgment Road. Councilor Knight, Councilor Scarpelli.
Madam President, yes, as the resolution reads, the traffic commission I directed signage to one ramp said to keep this road that has displaced vehicles. These roads, but measure blitz victory park, the backside of victory park, and there's access to walking trails back there. But what's happening is the street is very narrow street. It's getting overrun by vehicles, residents in the street can't back out of the driveways, can't find parking in the front rows. So it's creating a situation where the
Signage that the traffic commission put up has really displaced a number of vehicles to another neighborhood. It's now feeling a negative impact. So in the interest of parity, the traffic commission will take simple steps to treat this neighborhood as they treat others and ensure that the signage is erected so that neighbors don't have to go through the weekends of recreational events going on in the community, very similar to what's going on now. Thank you. Thank you, Councilman.
for expressing those concerns. I echo all of them. I think it's important that as we as we hear so often, even this evening, that a lot of the issues we're having with parking has nothing to do with method residents. It has people that come outside of method that want to use our recreational spaces or our restaurants or our theaters and, um,
and it really displaces the quality of life of our residents. So if we can, like Councilor Knight said, you know, in the case that we've had in other locations and it's worked, I think we need to follow up on this stretch of road as well. So thank you, Madam President.
on the motion of counselors second by vice president bears. Yes. Councilor Carribelle. Yes. Councilor Collins. Yes. Councilor night. Yes. Councilor Scarpa. Yes. Councilor Singh. Yes. President Morrell. Yes.
22-303 offered by Councillor Carviello. It is resolved that the administration report back to the council with the status of the veteran's office and how the veterans of Medford will be receiving services going forward. Councillor Carviello. Thank you, Madam President. We did receive an email.
you know.
we're interviewing anybody, and that office needs to be staffed immediately, and not by telephone. One life is too many lives, I have to say, for veterans that commit suicide on a daily basis. So, Madam President, I would hope that the mayor would come back with us within the next week or two, saying that they're interviewing candidates for this job. Thank you, Councilor Carvillo. Any further discussion? If you just want to read the last part,
the update from the Chief of Staff, just to read out the contact information so people have it. So currently, if any veteran needs support, they can call the Medford Department of Veteran Services at 781-393-2505, or email seniorclerkdarlingwhite at dwhite at medford-ma.gov, or Wilmington's Veterans Department at 97694-2040, or email Mr. Lewis Maglia directly at lcimaglia,
at WilmingtonMA.gov. So that is the current information. I hope that's also updated all over the website as well. Councilor Knight. If we could just get a copy of the contract between the town of Wilmington and the city of Memphis for these services from the administration. I appreciate it. Do you want that as a just amendment? Please. For the discussion.
So we are the motion. Second by second. Mr. President bears. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
President Morrell. Yes. 7-4-0-0. Negative. Motion passes.
22-304, be it resolved that the Metro City Council requests an update from the city administration on the solid waste task force, including the scope and goals of the task force, opportunities for short and long-term waste reduction, inefficacy evaluation of our current recycling services, opportunities to further reduce waste and more efficiently recycle in our next waste management contract, and how our city's progress towards a zero waste future can be publicly tracked and made available to the public.
be it for the resolve of the administration, provide an update on what, if any regulations and requirements currently governs private waste and recycling collars operating in Medford. Councilor Collins. Thank you, President Morrell. Resolution speaks for itself. I know that we're coming up on, you know, we're a bit more than a year out from when our city's waste management contracts will be up. So I think it's, you know, about time that we start, you know, making sure that the administration is looking at how things are going with our
current contractor with an eye towards how we can improve our overall waste reduction and efficacy of recycling in the next one. That doesn't necessarily mean a new contractor, but I think it's a good time to start re-evaluating. We're always overdue for evaluating how we can be further accelerating towards a zero waste future, evaluating how good we are at recycling all the things that we think that we're recycling. I also want to make sure that that
also takes into account any private waste haulers that are operating on properties in Medford to ensure that across the board, we're doing what we can to dispose of waste, recycle as efficiently as we can in line with our climate and pollution goals. Thank you, Councilor Collins. Vice President Behrs. Thank you, Madam President. Thank you, Councilor Collins for putting this on the agenda. I think this is really an essential effort considering when this contract goes up.
the new contract will be pricier than the current contract. And as I think we've seen, there's a lot of increases in the cost of waste removal and waste management. Since we last signed the contract on this, one of the ways that we can mitigate the impact of the growing cost of waste removal, crowding out other essential priorities in the city budget, is to reduce the amount of overall waste that we are producing as a city. So I think this is a great resolution and I second it and will support it.
I wanted to thank Councillor Collins for introducing such a thoughtful resolution. Measures like this represent the action that we can take at the local level to address the growing climate catastrophe that we're facing. I know that many feel a sense of dread and hopelessness, but I think Councillor Collins shows us today that we can be hopeful, but we just have to act.
And resolutions like this show that our city is acting, and that our city council in particular is trying to get the answers that we need to create the policies that we need to address climate emergency.
At the, at the local level, both overall and at the local level, reducing waste is one of the key, one of the key ways that we can that we can pursue one of the key paths we can pursue towards meeting, you know, meeting a better future that's more sustainable. And so,
I am I full wholeheartedly support this resolution. And I think I would like our city to do in the city administration to do more research into what else we can. What what other measures we can take towards the zero waste goal. Um, you know,
There are a lot of cities that are innovating right now, they've developed textile recycling programs, they've done on different programs with technical, technical parts, and I would like to see our city explore those options and also to make what options do exist more accessible to all Medfordians. Thank you.
spent a lot of time in this area and it's been my day job, so I really thank you for bringing this forward. And a lot of, if not most of the callers contracted these days do have the ability to provide data. So I think this is a really important resolution. It's something that we should be looking for in the city because when we know better, we can do better. So I also really appreciate you bringing this forward. So on the motion, Councilor Collins, second by Vice President Behrs.
Vice President Behrs. Yes. Councilor Kerrio. Yes. Councilor Collins. Yes. Councilor Knight. Yes. Councilor Scarpelli. Yes. Councilor Seng. Yes. President Morrell. Yes. Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative, the motion passes. Reports of- Motion to suspend the rules to take public participation. Motion of Vice President Behrs to suspend the rules to take public participation, seconded by Councilor Collins. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Vice President bears. Yes, Councilor Carvio. Yes, Councilor Collins. Yes. Councilor night. Councilor Scott Kelly. Councilor saying yes. President Morrell. Yes, I never as you're in the negative, the rules are suspended to take public participation on a quarter. At this time, anyone would like to speak, please feel free to come to the podium. If anyone would like to speak on zoom, you can raise your hand but I rotate hand on zoom so folks would like to speak in the chambers.
one at a time when you're ready. Yes, you can, yeah, whoever wants to speak, you can come up. Yep, yeah, everyone can speak. Everyone who wants to speak can speak. There's a lot of us here tonight. Can I just, sorry, just name and address real quick. Sure, I'm sorry, Elizabeth Maloney, Liza Maloney, 26 Bradley Road. So thank you for giving us just a moment tonight. There's many of us here from 26 Bradley.
So you're aware of kind of what's been going on. And I know last week I did speak with you to via Zoom. So we're hoping to work more closely with you. We've been given another 30 day extension, I guess, with our kind of eviction, if you will. It's just not enough time. There's families in the building with children in the Medford school system. It's just, it's sickening to be quite honest with you.
So we just hope to work with you more closely and keep coming to these meetings. You know, meet the mayor next Thursday. We saw that she starts her kind of open house, if you will, again, and just stay together as we get through this process. But it's very upsetting that this kind of could happen in Bedford to anyone. So if anyone else wants to.
do have an update from our planning department is all I can read, but I want to make sure everyone gets a chance to speak. Thank you, Madam President, council members. My name is Sean Temple. I live at 26 Bradley Road, and I may be the senior member of the residents there. I've been there maybe 25 years. We just received a notice, a certified letter on Friday stating that we have to vacate.
the premises. I've been there 25 years and nothing like this. The Donados owned the building at one time and then it was sold to another management company, Sinead, and then in turn sold it to another management company who is now, I guess, I know, you know, residency is a high commodity these days.
You know, we have a lot of senior people here who live in the building as well as myself. And, you know, I just feel, you know, just being kind of railroaded out of the building, you know, without any cause. I mean, they don't really notify us about anything since I took over the building. You know, it doesn't seem right. You know, and whatever.
what I've found out so far is that they've only given us like 30 days and I think it's supposed to give us more time, you know, and I'm not even sure, you know, I'm not exactly sure how much time that is, but I mean, you know, it just doesn't seem practical, you know, and we're here today just to try to state our case about what's going on over there, you know, so that's what we're doing here. Thank you for your time.
Susan Bradley wrote. Well, is there anything that you guys can do? Are we wasting our time? Not not being sarcastic or anything, but is there anything that can be done legally? Or are you guys just listening? Or is there something you can do with this company or to? I think Councilor Morocco has a better
From what I've been told, I spoke to a couple of people that, from what I understand, they've given another 30 days. So B1 has 60 days. They are going to honor the leases that people have also until they expire also. But I know there's some people in there with vouchers that they're in a little bit of a tough spot because if they get evicted, it can affect their voucher. Right. And that's the weird part.
apartments up to like two or three weeks ago. It didn't make sense. But for me, I'm going to find something. But for a lot of people that live there, it's really... And as a city employee, it's really upsetting. It's ridiculous to let a company come in and upset people's lives, especially after what's been going on the last two years. You would think that people would have more compassion, but I guess this is a...
I know some of you may have received some information from the city or some avenues, maybe for some funding or some help.
Yeah, I'm not worried about that. She'll be out of it. She does not want you guys to believe it. Do you see her on here? Okay, thank you. Thank you, and so sorry about this microphone buzzing. We're not sure why that's happening.
To the question of, you know, can we do anything, and I'm really grateful to everybody who's been in contact with the city council and other city officials about this, and we're really glad not to know about it, but glad to be kept updated about what's going on. And I think, you know, I don't want to speak for my colleagues, but I think we all empathize with you and we all accept that this is happening. But to the question of what can we do about it, I think, speaking only for myself, you know, taking care not to speak for anybody else, we want to make sure that you're advocating to the people who have the power to help
you in this position. Unfortunately, we need to make sure that you're advocating to the right people. We need to make sure that you're talking to the people who have the power to either alleviate the expense and the inconvenience and the stress and the work and the anxiety of finding new housing.
When I talk, no, it's everybody's. Yeah. Motion for a five-minute recess. Motion approved. Questions and comments? Any results that you'd like to propose? Subject to approval? Yes. Yes.
Yes, if it's my turn.
Recess has ended, the meeting is back to order. I just want to go back to Councilor Collins. I believe you were in the middle and then we have Vice Mayor Behrs and then we'll come back to the residents. Whatever you want to do. Councilor Collins. Thank you, President Marillyn. Thank you to our AV wizard back there. What I was saying is that, you know, we appreciate the tenants keeping us informed of your situation and, you know, speaking only for myself and probably for
Many other, if not all of my colleagues, we stand in solidarity with you. We're sorry for what you're going through. I think that we need to make sure that you're advocating to the right people, the people with the power to adjust your situation. As it's been stated, since this is proceeding legally, there's nothing that we can do in these chambers
know, to wave a magic wand and give you what you deserve, you know, what you need, what you're asking for. And I think that, you know, I'm certainly speaking for myself, I want to be in contact with, you know, this tenant group to make sure that you're connected with the right people. I know they've already received some very helpful, you know, what I seem to be like helpful pertinent information from our Office of Planning, Development, Sustainability.
I hope that to the extent that's helpful, you can remain in contact with our housing staff, other resources around the city, you know, and I hope that, you know, on an individual counselor basis, we can stay in contact to make sure that you're accessing the resources that are available to see what can happen here, you know, to appeal to perhaps this property owners that are angels. Thank you. Thank you, Councilor Collins. Vice President Behrs. Thank you, Madam President.
you know, I think you're all experiencing very directly the housing crisis that we're in in this area. Something that we as a council have talked a lot about is housing stability and what city resources we can provide. But, you know, I think Councilor Collins was very direct. You know, we are constrained by state law. We can't go in and say you can't do this. It's not within the power of the city of Medford to do that. What is within our power is to do what Councilor Collins said and what I think if
President Morrell may read the update if it hasn't gone to all of you.
provide as many resources and as much information as possible. We do have access to pro bono legal aid for housing situations for residents of the city. We have a program that helps people move within the city with financial support. And to be direct, there's a lot of state laws that need to change around this. I think we've been advocating, at least I've been advocating for some of those changes at this point, even if they were to go through, it's not gonna stop the situation. And I'm sorry for that, but they do need to change.
The other piece of this is I think fully, if you are able and if it, with the advice of legal counsel, I'm not a lawyer and I'm not certainly not your lawyer, but if you're able to get that legal advice, you do have a significant number of protections on the table here. They've provided a notice to quit that's now gonna be active after 60 days. That's the initiation of a process. It's not the end of a process. That process would then,
essentially begin an eviction proceeding, which would then take you before a judge, that can last months. It may not end the way that you want it to, but it may give you enough time to find something in this market. So I would suggest that.
or with the advice of council, if it's possible for you, if it's not going to impact you negatively in some other way, just fully see out your legal rights. And that may extend the process with enough time. But, you know, we as a city also need to take, you know, going forward, this is an example of why we need more resources for housing stability, more than just a couple people, more than just a couple affordable units, because it takes months and months and months.
to find housing in this market and with the very limited supply of housing. So I again I'm also very sorry that this is happening.
you know, big corporate change has just suddenly uprooted your lives. And I wish that we had more power to help, but certainly we can advocate, continue to reach out to this person, ask them to be compassionate, as Councilor Caravaglio said, ask them to extend the time period. And if they won't do anything more there, I certainly would suggest that you avail yourselves of all of the options that come before you in the legal process to extend this and give yourself as much time as you can to find
new housing. Thank you, Vice President Barris. And then actually, if I could just read the update from Planning, Development, and Sustainability, that might just be helpful to any questions that come up. But of course, everyone is still welcome to speak. So this is from Alicia Hunt, who is the Director of Planning, Development, and Sustainability. And some of this is coming verbatim from the person who purchased the property. So if this is incorrect, I apologize. This is just the story that they are getting. So it's a 34-unit building.
So the director of planning development sustainability and the housing planner spoke with the owner and some of his representatives this past Friday. So it's a 34 unit building and the owner let them know that 18 units for tenants at will, 14 have leases until the fall.
The new owner purchased the building one year ago in March 2021, and he said that all units that are tenants at will were in that status when he purchased the building. It's clear that his plan is to renovate kitchens, bathrooms, and redo floors, and that the tenants must vacate the apartments for this to occur as they are one-bathroom units. It was clear that rent would go up after the renovations.
He agreed to extend the notice for the tenants at will an additional 30 days for those who needed an extension. His representative, Jay Walsh, contacted the department on Friday night to let them know that everyone who had received a notice to quit had been notified that they could have an additional 30 days.
The director with the city requested that the owner give the tenants with leases as much notice as possible as it's necessary to look for now. New rental units in September, given this market, look sorry, look now for rental units in September, given the market.
The owner indicated that he understood and would take into advisement and give more notice that he had been planning. The city director requested that he give the tenants the opportunity to stay in the building, potentially by giving them the option to return to the renovated apartment. This seems to be a new idea to him, but he seemed to think it was very reasonable and suggested that once some apartments were renovated, those with longer leases could be offered the option to lease one of the renovated apartments rather than being required to move out.
we emphasize, the city emphasized that we very much would like to retain Medford residents in Medford. And I will make sure you guys get this. There's just like two more paragraphs. The city also presented him with information from the Medford Housing Authority on their opportunity for landlords to receive $1,000 for leasing a unit to a section eight voucher holder that hadn't previously leased to someone with section eight and let them know that the maximum section eight rents are what the maximum section eight rents are in Medford.
It's the city director's hope that he would consider Section 8 voucher holders for the renovated units. The current Section 8 tenants are through the Arlington Housing Authority, and the landlord has been in touch with them to verify that everything that they did was legal. The city director did not ask him about current or future rent rates, as they were focused on keeping Medford residents housed at this time. And they just went out to note that they did flyer every door in the building with the flyers with regard to ABCD and the move in, move out program.
Um, if anyone didn't get that information, we can make sure that that gets to you. Um, so any further questions we can relate to them and as fellow council just said, we, as a, we, as a body don't have any statutory power, but we can absolutely advocate. We can reach out to, you know, the city departments. I put in a call to Senator Jalen to see if there's anything that, you know, we may not be thinking of that can be done. So I think even though we don't have direct power in this situation,
As fellow counselors said, you know, my heart breaks for you guys. This is obviously also this is the tip of the iceberg, right? Like, this is stuff that we've been trying to stave off for the past two years and the housing market being what it is, we're unfortunately going to keep, you know, this is going to keep happening to our residents and it's not right.
we'll do what we can to stop it. But unfortunately, we don't have a lot of power in this situation. But thank you for bearing with me. Please just name and address. I mean, we know the address, but name and address for the record, please.
many people here today. And ultimately, everyone kind of said what we're all thinking, right? Like we all wish that there could be a better resolution, we wish that someone would step in and help us. I think at the end of the day, the biggest issue that we have is that these companies are not going anywhere, they're going to buy more buildings in this town, they're going to buy more units, they're going to kick more people out and leave them without an option. And they're going to do it in a way that
is unethical, is immoral, and I just don't think that this is a direction that the town of Medford, the city of Medford should want to trend in because, listen, I've lived here since 2015. I didn't always live in this building, but I've lived in Medford because I love living in Medford. As of May 1st, I'm living in Brighton, Massachusetts. I didn't want to, but luckily I found a place because I didn't know my options, right? And ultimately, you know, I'm lucky.
other people in our building are not going to be as lucky. And these are citizens of our town. These are residents of our town that love being here. They want to be here. And for someone who has never been in the building to take that away from them and not give them a real option, it's just morally bankrupt. It's wrong. And I understand that there's limited power here for all of us, right? Us as residents, you guys as
as president, as, as, as counselors, we understand that, but, you know, we're an example of what's going to happen to more and more buildings in this town. Right. And, and ultimately you don't want that. I feel I wouldn't want that because I love Medford for everything Medford has. And if Medford ceases to be Medford, why are we going to be here and why are we going to spend money here? Why are we gonna spend time here? So I just wanted to make it known that this company, there's a lot like them, right. And they're not going anywhere. And I just think that there needs to be more sort of
you know, it's a free market, but what are they doing for the people who live here? And how is it trending? Because at the end of the day, kicking us all out, putting a fake marble kitchen in and charging double the price, who are you bringing in really? You're going to bring in people that don't care about this town and don't want to be here and don't want to settle down. So that's all I got to say about it. And thank you for giving me the time. Sorry, I'm not good at this kind of, everyone's in a suit. I feel really uncomfortable. So I'm sorry. Thank you.
Would anyone else like to speak? See if there's anyone on Zoom. Any further discussion from the council? I will make sure, is there, I'm trying to think as far as if just to get, I'll work with the Planning Development and Sustainability Office just to make sure the contents of that email that I just read out gets to you all.
I'm sorry, I'll work with the director of the Office of Planning, Development and Sustainability to make sure the contents of the email that I just read gets to everyone. I know you've probably been given that information in a few different forms, but I'll make sure it's packaged and it gets to everyone. I understand, I know, I apologize.
Any further discussion? If you do want to come up to the microphone.
I mean, this whole process here is a little bit mute, mute, you mean it's, we have no rights, because these corporations come in, and they just take over and they in this has been going on. I've been in the Boston area, 40 years and as councilmen as statesmen, the people, you're supposed to know what's saying that you're not, but people should represent the people and they're not representing the people they're representing the corporations who's got the deep pockets, who can do whatever they want.
And it isn't right. And I'm not mad at you. I think this is the wrong forum. Yeah. So I think, yeah, exactly as the inappropriate for you're in the wrong. I agree with you. I agree with you. So I'm coming to that conclusion. So I mean, what is the next phone, we take it, we have to take it to the next state level. Is that where it goes? I mean, but at that point, it'll be new. I mean, it'll be I'll be gone by then because
No one can throw you out of that apartment but a judge, right? It's not like after 60 days, they're gonna lock the doors, take away the key and take all your stuff. I mean, they can't do that, right? It has to go through a process. I just wanna let you know how traumatizing it was to get a message Monday afternoon at 1258 saying to me, you need to vacate the property and all your belongings in 30 days.
I called the property management, they would not pick up the phone. I spoke with them, I said, you know, I have an ankle injury and I'm in physical therapy because I fell in the pool. And they still said, no, you have to go. I understand that everybody has a personal circumstance, there's 32 units in the building. But you know, ultimately, right, it's, you have to vacate, or what? Well, we're gonna take you to court, right? But I don't wanna be, I don't want on my record to be evicted. I mean, I don't need that on my, I don't need that. But it's a no fault eviction because it's not for non-payment of rent. Right. You know what I mean? So it's not for non-payment of rent, it's not for, you know,
selling drugs out of the apartment. No, no, no cause right it's it's a contract issue right it's a contract issue between the property owner and the tenants that are in the property. Right. So, ultimately, the forum where it's going to be resolved would be in some type of mediation, whether in the court system, you know what I mean as this goes through the process but the notice to quit.
It's just like, listen, in 30 days, we're filing an application. That's really what it is, right? So it's, they're giving you a 30 days notice to say they're going to take action. Right now, through the discussions that have happened here at this body and through the administration, they've said, look, it's not going to be 30 days now. It's going to be 60 days. Correct. Right. And if anybody is a tenant at Willow's leases up, we're not going to move on them. Right. We're going to wait 60 days. Correct. Right. So that's going to initiate the process, but think,
Between the, what was it? 18 units that have leases and 14 that don't? Yes. Or vice versa. It is. Yeah, 18 without leases. 18 with leases, right? All probably expiring at different times. All the 60 day notice to stick with. By the time this building gets empty, how long, how much time is this going to pass?
Right, it's gonna be at least six months because I don't know my name. My neighbor my neighbor just signed a lease. She just moved in and she's the leases over in August. I honestly don't know sir. Right, right. It's just the manner in which they did this was inhumane. Well, and I mean I understand they have a right to buy a building I understand they have a right to do whatever they want with the property, but it's the manner in which they went about doing it to people.
was totally wrong. And they wouldn't knew when they bought the building, how long those tenants were in that building. So they knew they should be dealing with this in an appropriate manner with people who have been residents there for a long time. People recognize business is business, but there's also a humanity part of this too, which is more, it's principle. I mean, yeah, you're talking about public service. You know, it's the principle and I'm not mad at it. It's just the principle matter of this and the manner in which they did it. I'm totally traumatized.
Yeah. And it's, that's fair. I mean, there's the answer that counselor and I just gave you, which is about the specific circumstance in the court of law and your legal rights. I mean, then there's the other question that you're bringing up. You've been here for 40 years. That means that you remember 30 years ago when it, you know, voters in Wellesley voted away, went control for people in Boston, you know,
do you think owns the corporations that are buying up the apartment. And that's where it is, you know, we are extremely limited by state law, there's a couple things that we can try to do, we can try to provide more resources and notice about your legal rights, which is what we're able to do in this case, that's something we can do. I mean, I'm an advocate of asking the state to implement a lot of laws to kind of create
create a better set of conditions for people. I think it needs to go to the state legislature, honestly, because, you know, if it's not me next, you next. You know, if people don't speak up. Right. And there's a, you know, there's a lot of groups. It'll be like California, you won't be able to live here. There's a lot of groups and tenants, advocates and people who are saying, you know, begging the state government, you know, they'll do anything, you know, unanimously they'll pass a law that says, you know, we'll free up this zoning and you can build something bigger, but
They won't attach to it just cause eviction or rent stabilization so you can have a 30% rent increase in a single year, or, you know, the tenant opportunity to purchase or all these other things that would give tenants more of a balance in this fight. And so, you know, that's something that we can advocate for but
we legally can't implement any of that unless the state lets us. And I'm just saying, it's worth going to the next level and saying, this happened in your state rep district or your state Senate district, and we need you to take, we need you to do something. And, you know, it's, yeah, I think you've made a very strong point about the conditions of who's making the law in Massachusetts. And I do appreciate your time and the resources. However, I mean, I did call some of the numbers and I feel as though that,
I called this number and then I could go to this person. Oh, now we're gonna go to this person, then it's like this person. This is why I never became a public servant because I like to produce and I like results. Yeah, I hear you. I don't like passing. And I'm not saying you are passing the buck, but people will take the pass the buck. And when is the buck stop.
Maybe, you know, and I'm just saying, and I'm not saying you know maybe we can maybe we can maybe we can ask, I'm assigned to, I know they're thin but with this being such a dire situation having a assigned member for office.
They're working directly with the families and the homeowners of Bradley will be an advocate even for the state because you know this is really this is this is getting out of control, but I think with this is such a dire situation I think that. And one of the biggest things is having someone on the other line I think that's important.
I think the least we can do is recommend that, uh, Miss Hunts puts a identified representative from their office that's going to work directly with the people of Bradley Road because of because of this die situation. I don't think they'll block at that. I think that they'll they'll really work hard to do that. But I think that's very important.
That, you know, where we were handcuffed, at least you should have an avenue within our city hall that are going to at least point you in the right direction and make sure that someone's going to be on the other line because I can't, I can't even imagine what you're going through right now. And the stress level, at least we can do is ask the city.
to take that stress level out, so they can help you move forward those chores so no thank you if I could recommend that that'd be something that no I appreciate that because you know I did make a call this week and the woman says where you can go live in a shelter. Well that's great. That's what they told me disgusting. My sister lives in a shelter and I used to go to that shelter.
Well, I think if we can do that, because there are avenues and I know that it's easy for us to sit on this side. And it's easy because we have, you know, we have homes right now but the idea of what you're going through. We don't, we can't say we understand because we don't, but we can also understand that if we can do this and we could follow from what I've, I've talked to a few different attorneys I can't.
By law, I can't tell you I get it. I get it. I know that like Councilmate says, this isn't an easy process. No, and you have to go to even as you as residents there if you take advantage of what we have in the city to finance legal representation that that building can stay the same for a long time. And you just what you're doing is banded together that's very important.
have someone direct you from the city to the right avenues and make sure that someone's on the other line and follow through with the resources we can offer you. And I think that at least gives us some time to find out other ways that we can get to the state and have the state representatives
look at different options, whether it's finding ways to, uh, you know, work directly with housing within different state housing, um, processes or whatnot. So there's got to be something out there that, like you said, this is the worst case scenario, and I know what's happening today, and like Councilor Behr says, this is probably the beginning of something more drastic moving forward.
I mean, if you look at the rents out there, the rents out there, and I've already saw four apartments and I just cried. I just cried. I was just like, and what they're charging for $1,700. I mean, it's pretty, I mean, you walk in these carpets are dirty, you go out, you know what I mean, two feet and you get a big plate of salt and use your shovels, you can shovel your own walk. That's really what, you can live in this basement apartment, but we're not gonna clean it. But you can request it to be cleaned. I said, excuse me, it's not clean. No, you're not gonna clean it after I move in.
or before I move it after I said Alicia, I. So at the recommendation of Councilor- Yeah, I appreciate that. I apologize that I'm so upset. No, no, you have every right to. That's the reason why we're here. We wish we could do more, but we're here to listen and help in any way we can. No, I appreciate that. If this is little that we can do, and at least let you know that you have seven people that understand, excuse me,
can be there for you just to listen. That's the best we can do. I hope that can help. But listen, I wish I could do more. You've been wonderful. Thank you. I appreciate you taking the time. I wish we could do more. It's good that it's voiced here. And I think it needs to be representative of the state. I've just seen so much. It's incredible. It's just incredible what happens. I'll call up the director to get you guys a dedicated contact person just to at least try to mitigate the call here, call there.
I can be an advocate because it has to stop. It really has to stop somewhere. Absolutely. Yeah. Thank you. Thank you.
Yes. Yes. Yes.
Yes, I mean, the firm is doing the negative. The motion passes reverting to regular order of business reports of committees to 2-012 March 29 2022 subcommittee on ordinances and rules. Uh, vice president Ferris, if you could provide us a brief overview of that meeting. Thank you, Madam President. Um, last week we met again in subcommittee on rules and ordinances. Uh, I think our third meeting
At our March 9th meeting, we reported out a number of suggested changes. We reported out a number of additional suggested changes at our March 29th meeting. And those will be, I believe, included in packets this week, both a track change document and a clean document.
The other item we reported out was an item for further discussion, which was around our meetings, days, times, Tuesday to Wednesday, biweekly, a number of other matters that the subcommittee felt required the full discussion of the council and not a recommendation from just three councilors. So that will be kind of the agenda is going over the suggested changes, as well as a discussion of the meeting times for the council.
Thank you, Vice President Harris. On the motion of Councilor Knight to approve the committee records, seconded by Vice President Harris. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
Yes, 74-0 negative, the motion passes. 22-078, March 30th, 2022 can be the whole meeting report. This was a meeting on the proposed polystyrene ban. We reviewed the draft that was edited by KP Law. There was no debate over the minor edits that were made. The only change that was suggested and voted on was to adjust the effective date to July, 2023. And that will be coming before the full council next week.
by the motion to approve. On the motion of vice-president Behr, seconded by Councilor Kerrio to approve the committee report. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. I'm in favor of zero in the negative, the motion passes.
Records, the tabled records of the meeting of March 22nd, 2022 were passed to Councilor Carviello. Councilor Carviello, do you have time to review them? On the motion of Councilor Carviello to approve the records, seconded by Vice Chair Behrs. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
Yes, seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative. The records are adopted. The records of the meeting of March 29th, 2022 were passed to Councilor Collins. Councilor Collins, how did you find them? I found them in order and I move for approval. On the motion of Councilor Collins, seconded by? Second. Councilor Kerrio, Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Yes. Yes. Yes.
Yes. Yes, seven in front of zero negative. The records are adopted on the motion of Councillor Knight to adjourn. Seconded by Councillor Scarpelli. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Yes. Yes, seven in front of zero negative. The meeting is adjourned.