Hi, I'm Helen.
Hi, I'm Lydia.
I'm Gabby.
I'm Cheyenne.
I'm Amber.
Hey, I'm Will.
Hi, I'm Courtney.
I'm Sam.
I'm Dora the Reporter.
I'm Carrie Anne.
I'm Anthony.
Hi, I'm McKenzie.
Hello, I'm D.P.
Hi, I'm Nick.
Hi, I'm Nick Keniston with the Mustang Report for Faculty Friday, and I'm here with Michelle Foe, an Italian teacher at Medford High School.
Why did you decide to pursue teaching?
I think it was just something always a part of me.
My mom's a teacher.
I always would volunteer in her classes growing up, and I really just got accustomed to being in school and helping kids out.
I love
seeing kids be successful and I love when they, you know, come to me with a concern for something or they need help and then they get to, you know, realize that they were successful after the fact.
So, kind of the whole progress of the evolution of the student, kind of from the problem through the whole thing.
That's really satisfying for the kid and also for me.
If you could be any animal in general, what would you be and why?
Thinking long and hard, I would say I'd be a bird.
I would like to be a bird because that way I could fly wherever I want at any time, especially like Italy.
Well, volleyball for me personally has been really awesome.
I made a ton of friends and it's just been a really great way to like kind of integrate in the school year because you start in the fall and it's a lot of fun.
We went 6-0 in the GBL and I feel like during states we should do pretty good.
The season went really well.
We had a lot of fun and the kids learned quite a bit.
We played a lot of difficult teams this year, high-ranked teams, and we really, really played well.
really good.
We have a bunch of new freshmen who are thinking about coming in and we have a lot of solid seniors who are going to play really well this year.
It's really easy.
You don't have to have any experience.
You can join.
You don't have to be someone who knows how to play.
It can be a first time and then you can just have fun and you can learn with the group as the season goes on.
Girls cross-country team is doing fantastic.
The season's going pretty great.
The boys team has done good as well and we're grateful that we have our coach Lou coaching for 35 years now.
Last year we got our first win in about 10 years so that was really exciting and we hope to continue that this year and we have a new pool so there's a growing team and we're rebuilding so it should be a good year.
Well our season went really well last year and we had some great team chemistry we all had some really good times together we all made each other laugh we got along really well and for the upcoming season we hope to work on probably just improving our record because other than that we had a really great time with each other maybe just winning a couple more games and it'll be great.
I'll tell you right now, last year was a tough year for the Mustangs.
We actually expected a lot more.
But we're looking forward.
We're actually excited about the new league that we're going into this year, the Northeast Division.
A lot of good teams.
So we're looking forward to that.
And we do have a great group of seniors coming back, upperclassmen, great underclassmen.
So we're looking forward to the 2016 season.
Last season went really well.
We had a lot of really good incoming freshmen that came up and really boosted the morale of the team.
For me, I thought the group really worked well as a team and we were all really cohesive in that sense.
Mostly going from being a younger team to an older team, we should
Be good this year if everything goes as well.
Yeah, I'd like to point out that Makai is not just a member of the basketball team He's elected a captain as a junior Which is an honor to be as an under as someone who's not a senior to be elected captain by his by his teammates And we're looking to build you know like Makai said we were inexperienced last year and now we're experienced So we've set high expectations for us
So I was on JV for most of the season, but hearing about varsity, they did really well.
I got pulled up for states, and again, we did really well.
I think we did really good this season.
We all worked together well as a team.
And for next season, I think we just have to keep doing what we did last year and just win more games.
I think we did spectacular.
What would you say to any incoming freshmen that are thinking about joining gymnastics?
I think it's definitely worth it.
I didn't do it my freshman year and I regret it so much.
I did it my sophomore year and it's probably the best decision I made in high school.
We're doing pretty well at the moment.
Our record's currently nine, four, and three?
Two.
And two.
About joining next year, I really think you guys should join.
I feel like we're not just a team, we're a family and it's really great and you meet a lot of cool people.
I think it's a great way to make friends.
As she said, we're kind of family.
We're all close.
We all hang out on and off the field.
We're having fun, not only winning games, but just having fun together.
I think last season was definitely like a rebuilding season, and that it's just going to get better as time goes on.
Yeah, I have to agree.
I mean, we were just continuing to get better.
And yeah, the show should be pretty good.
We have a lot of new people coming in.
I'd say it's pretty awesome.
I mean, I played on the team since I was in seventh grade.
And we're kind of one big family.
So that's how it works.
It's really good.
We've been working very hard.
We have our competition coming up in a couple weeks and we're excited.
We all want to improve on everything.
Everything's always an improvement like day by day so we all want to try to improve day by day.
Tumbling, stunts, jumps, everything.
It's really fun and it's a good experience to start off the school year when you're trying to find something to do and trying to make friends and you start school with friends so it's really good.
The question for the week is, what sports did I used to play?
We at Medford High School have come together through our sports teams and our school to help raise awareness for domestic violence.
We at Medford High School stand in solidarity to join the fight against domestic violence.
We have invoked a responsibility in our student leaders to come together and spread awareness throughout our school.
No more.
We stand together.
No more!
No more.
No more violence!
No mas.
No more I don't want to talk about it.
No more!
No more.
Speak up.
No more excuses.
No more.
She was flirting with him.
One, two, three, four.
Which one of us will it be?
No more!
No more.
No more