Hey listeners, this is Danielle. And Shelley. Shelley is a radical Dravidian and racial equity activist. And Danielle is a community mobilizer and change maker. And this is the Medford Bites podcast. Every two weeks, we chew on the issues facing Medford and deliver bites of information about the city by lifting the expertise of our guests. Join us in discussion about what you hope for the future of Medford. And as always, tell us where you like to eat.
Thanks for joining me today. If you don't mind just introducing yourself name pronouns and a bit about who you are. Sure. Thank you so much for having me. It's such an honor. I am Paige Baldini she her.
I have lived in Medford, Massachusetts for over 15 years now, and I'm very excited to be running for city council. Thank you for having me. Um, things about me. I own a small business, a skincare salon up in the Hillside by Tufts called page aesthetics. I've been here for over six years. I am a proud mom of a seven-year-old rising second grader at Mississippi elementary school.
And I love that I am on the board of the Chamber of Commerce, which has been such a really cool way for me to use my small business experience, specifically while I was running it opening during the pandemic, and then being a public school parent. And then my husband also is from Medford, and we get to raise our daughter in the house that he grew up in. So I just love all these ties to Medford, which are great.
Yeah, seems like you have, you know, you're in a lot of different areas in Medford. So I hope that'll hopefully, hopefully inform our the rest of our conversation. So thank you. And then the first question I want to ask you that I ask everybody is just what is your favorite place to eat in Medford? And what do you like to eat there?
So this is so hard and I feel like out of this whole prep that because I love to prep before I get to speak with anyone. Because there's as a proud board member of the chamber and a member obviously with my business think there's something like over 130 different
food, restaurant, cafe, pizza shops in Medford. And I was like, Oh, well, maybe I can just like go through every neighborhood and shout out my favorite ones. And I kept going and going, going, and then we would have like an hour of a podcast and we'll do that another day. So I think to just save time, um, I would have to say Goldilocks bagels, which is my neighbor down right down the hill on the hillside.
And our true love story actually happened. It was so funny. They opened a few months after I did. And Lindsey, who we love, Lindsey and Ed, had posted on Instagram that they were short cash. And this is, I mean, our businesses in customer service are a little different now, but, you know, a lot of credit cards are used now, but cash sometimes is too.
So she just posted this story and I happen to have some cash at the moment, small bills and my husband sells beer at Fenway. So he did too. So I just ran down the street and I brought like a bag of ones, like in a Ziploc and she was like, where do you get all this cash? And I'm like, it's not that much. It just is our business. And from there, she has beat Lindsay specifically. And I love it to have become my small business besties. I own a small business. It's hard to run a small business solo. And it's also really rewarding when you find a friend.
who's navigating similar things. So shout out to Goldilocks. I'd have to say their breakfast sandwiches are phenomenal. But my order, if you want to know, is an onion bagel with chive cream cheese, tomato and bacon. Tomato and bacon. Yum. Yes. Goldilocks is like probably the most mentioned. Yes. Well, they're just good. They're good humans and it's good food. Right. It's so easy. Yeah. And they've been on the podcast there. They're very nice people. Yeah.
Happy to promote them anytime. Great, yeah. So I invited you on to talk about your campaign for city council. So I'm wondering if you could share with us a little bit about kind of how you arrived at this moment, how you decided to run for city council.
Yes. And thank you for asking. Um, honestly, a couple of years ago, this would never have been a thought in my mind. And I feel like that's the best thing about really growing up. I mean, I'm 41 and I feel like I'm still just stepping into who I am. And I think once my daughter went into public school, I was able to then realize I love owning my skincare salon. I love being a parent.
And there was just something more. And I got the opportunity to be on the board for the chamber. And I got to be in the room with a lot of really cool business owners and decision makers in the city. And they kind of started listening to some of my ideas. And we got to do some really cool collaborations, which one is coming up with Ron Medford and the Citywide PTOs.
So some of these fun ideas that are bouncing around in my head, I get to actually connect the people. And also because I own a skate care salon, I get to have all walks of life come into my salon.
and they are vulnerable, they are real, and they share, and I get to listen. So I have become a proud, active listener, and I feel like that's a really important attribute of any government, but any person. So I feel like once it all kind of happened, somebody had mentioned it, it kind of got tossed around, and so I did a little bit more research, and I just felt like I have some really great experience through professional, my professional experience, and my family experience, and my life experience.
want to give it a whirl. Yeah, that's great. Yeah, no, I am. My training, my work, I work as a therapist and I feel like it's always remarkable to me like going to different like going to the hair salon or like going to like different places where that like you probably have no training as a therapist, but I do it just as well of a job like listening. So and I do appreciate that. I think that's
I think a lot of people come to local politics because they have some kind of ambition for themselves or they have some kind of priorities already, but being able to listen and hear what it is that the community wants and needs is an important thing. Thank you for what you do, because that is very important. And I have, ironically, have a degree in psychology from a million years ago at a manual college where I graduated in 06 in philosophy.
However, I would never ever say that I'm trained. I think I just through my life experiences like to listen. So the fact that you can do that and help people is awesome. So thank you. Yeah, so I also think like, you know, when people decide to run for these offices, like they maybe have some idea of
what they would do. It sounds like you have an idea of what you appreciate about Medford. You've kind of connected with some of these bigger kind of community groups and probably have already heard from people kind of what they are thinking about, what they're maybe proud of about Medford, what we think what's going well, but also things that they want to see change. And so I'm wondering if elected, what your priorities would be there in terms of what you'd like to work for in terms of changing things in the city?
That's a great question. So I think a really wonderful thing that I have.
via my husband being from here and me not originally being from here is, I think Medford has such deep roots and such great history, but I think we're also on this cusp of like welcoming so many new people in and so many good new businesses. So I feel like as a business owner, I really love making that easier. So I think the easiest way to do that would just make Medford open for business, right? Like make City Hall,
a place where we can expedite, you know, like business, like it's hard to open a small business I guess I could say. So just making sure that the building department is prepared for that permitting is prepared for that. And then also creating that good connection with the chamber so we can nourish that.
I think having strong communication is great. I love the way that I get to talk to my clients, whether it's through social media, through newsletters, so continuing to strengthen that, making our website easily accessible. I talk about it all the time. I promote the caches calendar.
to like 80% of my clients if they need to figure out something to do, cause it's so great. And I love that it's on the Medford city's calendar. You can find it there too, but just making sure that residents can find the information they need very easily. And then I think specifically with when I decided to run for city council, I kind of just literally Googled or chat to BT, what does the city councilor do?
And the three main reoccurring things are that the most not most important, but their main jobs are zoning ordinances and then like the general way that the community in the city government works. So I feel very lucky that I'm stepping into the midst of a big zoning conversation.
And I'm learning so much and I love to learn so that's great and I feel like having the opportunity to have my clients and my neighbors ask me questions. I am a person that really believes in getting as much information as possible.
And it doesn't mean if it's aligned with myself or not, because I will always find something that I can learn. So I think that the zoning reform right now is something that is really important for everybody to just really fully understand and also have an opportunity to have a say.
Another cool thing that I learned about, because again, I'm learning from everywhere, is it isn't necessarily a typical way to have as many public meetings or have as many public opportunities for the community when it comes to zoning. So we actually have a lot. I do have to say, though, it's really confusing to me. I don't know if you're following along, and you might be, and this is not to even ask that of you. So to find a way, I've been advocating for like
you know, pictures of what this real life pictures of or simple zoning, not critiques, but like abbreviations and just really being able to ask those questions. And I just engaged with Medford fire, Medford police and Medford schools. And that's including like chiefs down to the union reps and just ask what, how they feel about it. Cause I feel like including every person that I possibly can to get a good informed
just information is the best that I can do and then by sharing that. So those are kind of my big three. It's pretty much honoring who we are, engaging who we're becoming, smart and transparent growth, small business support, obviously, and then communication are like my four big pillars that I'm actively trying to learn more about and get feedback from. Yeah, I think the zoning issue is a good example of how like this, I think this like common problem in Medford that I've been hearing about
For 10 years is like, how do people get their information about what's going on? And this also the opposite issue of how do we understand what people want? Because we know only certain people go to those meetings. Only certain people are tuned into city council meetings and school committee meetings.
When I was working on the charter review, it was a big push to get input from community members, and it's a very complex issue. First of all, you're like, how many people actually care about this? And how do we find them and educate them about it? But I think that zoning is a really
It's a really important issue I think one of the things that we've been hearing about too is like revenue in the city and our budget and how to like, we have all these new people coming in and how do we also welcome businesses. And so sometimes I think that.
The way that I hear about zoning is that there can be some conflict between zoning for what business owners want versus what people who own homes in Medford want, and people who want to have affordable housing in Medford want. And so I think it's a very complex issue. And I kind of wonder what you're hearing. Yeah, that's a great question. And I feel like no matter what,
there's gonna be opinions that differ. And I think that's really important. I feel like that's the only way that we can get as much opinion and also like enough people that feel like they're a part of it. So I've heard all, I feel like I have really great friends that are excellent affordable housing advocates.
and architects and that's their world. I also have residents that don't feel that this is something for them, or feel that their neighborhood character will change.
As a business owner, so funny, I've newly been speaking at some of these meetings and I have heard public comment, negative and positive, which is fine because I'm putting myself out there and that's what happens, right? And I feel like even if it feels negative coming at me, it's feedback and it's something, even if the delivery doesn't feel kind, there's something I can learn from there and that's been helpful.
And when I'm listening and speaking, I use my business where I'm currently right now, 319 Boston Ave, right on the Boston Ave corridor, which is a business district, as the perfect example of an area that should be rezoned for mixed use. And I'm literally putting my business
out there, also my neighbors. It's one level of nine units. There should be housing and it should be affordable. We're right near the green line, like we're right in 93 and 16. However, as a business owner selfishly, I just was asking questions of, okay, so what were to happen if this building was incentivized to be redeveloped?
you know, how would we support the small businesses? And I have gotten some information. But also another really cool plug that you didn't ask for, but it's so helpful, is the Medver public library, you can rent a librarian. I don't know if you knew this. No. Yes. Now I've done it. I've done it once with Sam, who's awesome for some campaign assistance, and she was great. And now I'm going to do it again with Jenna Barry, who is in the Resource Center.
and you can ask them a question and they will find every resource possible and it could be to like build a like a model airplane or learn how to run a campaign independently or it could be how do we create a business plan and they're saying we're not experts but we will find every resource we can so
Trying to find that so essentially like my hope with this is, again, I don't think everybody will be happy. I personally do feel like I need more information as I keep asking some people. I do think it would be wonderful. I know some zoning of the districts has already gone through like I know.
over the Glenwood, like Salem Street has already gone through that district. I know Misty Gap Corridor has already gone through. So those are things that I don't know what they can do to kind of quote unquote go back. But I do feel like if there was a way to separate them a little bit and have strong business district zoning,
figure it out, make sure we really do it. I don't want to lose affordable housing here. I feel like that's so important. And then really evaluate the residents. I feel like that could be a potential compromise. But again, I know that there's some people that feel like, I want it, let's do it. And some people are like, I don't. So it's kind of this funny place where I'm towing the line. But I do I have publicly asked to slow it down a bit. So that's, that's fair to share. Yeah.
Yeah, it is definitely a complex issue and I feel like if you're following a lot of this on social media, it's really hard to know what's true. I actually recently got this text message that was like a survey and maybe you've seen this. It's full of misinformation.
Like, they were kind of conflating this with saying that the zoning reform would mean that nobody could build a single family home anymore, which is, like, I know not true. And so, yeah, I mean, I think it's hard to, even at those meetings sometimes, like, the loudest people are saying things that maybe aren't necessarily true. And so it can be hard to kind of sift through that. So, you know, I'm not envious of you for trying to figure that out. But yeah, I think it's certainly a complex issue. So I appreciate the time you're spending on it.
Yeah and so I guess I'm curious too like so the theme of this podcast initially was just to sort of examine Medford from a place of like inclusivity and think about how like what things were doing well in the city but also maybe if you had any hopes for Medford in the future around things we could improve around like equity and inclusivity in our city. So I'm curious what you think.
Yeah, so it's, it's so wonderful and timely I had, I can't quote unquote I don't know if I received it or not and I'm thinking positive, but I had a second interview with the Massachusetts women's political caucus. And we spoke specifically about my views on certain things, but one thing that was really wonderful that I could share is as a skincare provider as I shared before I have
all walks of life, every person, whoever they are, can come in here and feel themselves. And I feel like coming at this campaign in the way that we could run the city to find a way, we don't all have to agree, but to find specific ways that we can make people feel valued and seen, I feel like that's great. And I feel like our arts community does a really great job. And as I shouted out with Cashay before, I feel like really engaging in ways that people can feel creative,
can feel themselves. It also supports like within our businesses. I feel like that's a great way to amplify maybe you know bringing in different types of businesses. They don't necessarily all have to look the same and I feel like that would be a great opportunity to diversify but also be way more inclusive and I love that we have that opportunity with specifically even with some zoning changes and stuff that's going to allow some growth.
I feel like within our schools it's been really cool. I'm sure because obviously you know as well, just seeing my daughter within a member public school and the nexus program, and how it shows you know how to be a good friend and how to be a good advocate, and I just think.
she's in first will finish first grade. And these are skills that she's learning. And again, it could it doesn't have to be a big broad thing. But it's coming back and making people feel valued and seen and heard. And I feel like the more that we can kind of show that within the way that we're transparent with our communication, or we're open to show businesses are welcome here. I feel like
or we can continue to incorporate our arts, our music, our sports. I feel like those are just great ways that we can start. I don't necessarily know what Mefford is doing, not even that you asked wrong, but I feel like there's a great opportunity for any of the quote unquote old and new or
different mindsets to actually start. Hopefully either they don't have to look at each other, but we have some, we have a, Medford is on the cusp of something really wonderful. And I feel like if we can continue to honor that, you know, the historic Med we have, but also be welcoming, I think that's a great opportunity.
Yeah, it's always interesting to me hearing from those two sides if we want to think about it like that. And I do think that they have a lot more in common and they want to give each other credit for it. But I think everybody that I talk to, even if I agree with them about nothing, can hear that they really care about Medford. I think it comes across in a different way, but I think that it's a community where lots of people are really invested in.
making the best of our community. So, you know, I think breaking through some of the noise is helpful sometimes. Yeah, and I do, I have been told that people don't necessarily want to come together and that is fair. And I feel like that is not any of our jobs that ever change somebody. I feel like whoever you are, you should feel good about that and be true to your values. But I feel like, and I think like Run Medford is a really great example where
multiple groups can come together to literally raise money for my for public schools, you know, and I feel like there's more of those like Oktoberfest, you know, for the chamber, we had that whole street filled with all different types of businesses. And, you know, like Medford youth sports, and we had your awesome podcast, and it was just cool to see, again, they might not be politically aligned, they might not be
you know, whatever type of their moral compass aligned, but we all had a blast. And I feel like more of those opportunities, again, we don't have to get along, we don't have to be together, but I feel like that's kind of my hope. And that's what I'm good at. I have no idea how it started, but I think maybe it's the active listener role. I just pick up on these things and I'm like, oh, right, like that would make sense for that and refer it out and go.
Yeah, and having the energy for it. I think like, you know, hearing from all the different sides of the, or like, different corners of the community and being able to connect the dots a little bit is definitely valuable. I'm curious if you have any, like, upcoming, like, campaign events or anything that, anywhere we can find more information about your campaign that you want to put.
Thank you so much. So I have my website, electpagefoldini.com. I'm also quite active on Facebook. I have pagefoldini for my third city council. I have an Instagram page, pagefoldini, simple. And then I will be, I have three upcoming barbecues that I will be posting on my newsletter. I mean, my website, I apologize. And then I'm hoping to connect for a night at Colleen's and then my friends at Four Pizza have offered toast too. So I will have that all up on my website
hopefully within the next couple weeks. And then we're just going to start walking around Medford. I'm very excited. I have a little army of my neighborhood kids that are so fired up, which is really, really cool. Um, so they want to have like bike parades, but I have told them that they're not allowed to put stuff in people's mailboxes. So if you get something from me in your mailbox, it was probably from a seven year old and we apologize, but we're going to do our best. Yeah, no, I think like, um,
when kids can connect with, that's the thing that's very cool about Medford is that city councilors are people that we all know, right? Like Emily Lazaro is like Evan and Sally's mom, that's how my kids know her, right? So it's like, I think it's really cool when people can feel so connected to city officials. And I know there's been a lot of back and forth about changing the way that we do our representation in city council, but I do think it's,
I mean, for me, I'm sure there are people that feel differently, but it's easy to access the city council, which means like if we have something that we're concerned about, we know who to bring it to. And I think just feeling, and so it's really cool, like the kids in your neighborhood are behind your campaign.
So, their vote for Paige Valdini, we actually for my kickoff made temporary tattoos, which was a trip. So we had like half of the Miss Tuck school had temporary tattoos, which I was like, sorry. I mean, their parents said yes. So we're having fun. And I guess it's a really cool way to be a role model. Because no matter what, and I'm going to mess up 100%, and I'm going to ask for help. But I'm going to hopefully show my daughter that we can do those things. We don't have to be perfect.
We can work really, really hard, but if it's coming from a space of I'm going to be as kind as I can be, I'm going to work as hard as I can be, and I'm going to try to listen. I feel like that's the best I could do, and I'm excited for it. Yeah, no, that's great. I think it's a good model. It's also a good model of like caring about your community and, you know, wanting to take care of each other. So thank you. I'm wondering if there's anything else that you want to mention before we wrap up.
No, I was trying to think of what I was, so have, I guess I'm just going to keep plugging in the library, but have you been to the Medford room in the library, the little glass room? I've never been inside, no. Everybody? Okay, so Medford Public Library, if you're listening, endorse me, I'm just joking, but that room is really cool. Open it up and it's really cool. It's books that you can't, or items that you can't take out of the library because they're very old, but they have these drawers with files and they have all old press.
It's really cool. I think they're making it all digital right now, so a lot of it is open, but I was looking at the maps. They have the ward maps, and it's just really cool because I was trying to really envision what Medford in the past looked like, and now thinking about zoning and thinking about spots, and it's a really great way, I feel like, to stay grounded specifically with a lot that's going on.
to see like how far we come. And I feel like with some true collaboration, I feel like there's some good stuff that can happen. So, no, I'm just so honored to have been a part of this. So thank you for having me. Thank you for doing this too. You are doing a great job and I appreciate you being open to hear every, you know, whether it's the city counselor or a school committee member, or even just a person in the community, you have a great way of sharing information and we need more of that. So thank you.
Yeah, it's been great for me to learn more about Medford and meet everybody. So yeah, thank you for being here. Of course.
Thanks so much for listening to today's episode. The Medford Bites podcast is produced and moderated by Danielle Balacca and Shelly Kasheman. Music is made by Hendrik Giedonis. We'd love to hear what you think about the podcast. You can reach out to us by email at medfordpod at gmail.com, or you can rate and review the podcast on Apple Podcasts. Thanks so much for listening. Guys, what's the name of the podcast? Medford Bites. Medford Bites. Good job.