[SPEAKER_00]: Hello, I'm Shannon Demos.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am the proud principal of the Brooks Elementary School.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here at the Brooks, we serve approximately 520 students in grades pre-K to 5 and have 88 highly dedicated staff members working daily with our diverse learning population.
[SPEAKER_00]: Along with our general education classrooms, we are proud to house three MEEP preschool classrooms, one developmental classroom, and four language-based classrooms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Brooks Elementary School is specialist in physical education, music, art, nexus, and technology.
[SPEAKER_00]: While we do not qualify for Title I, we do have remedial reading teachers and one EL teacher for students in grades K-5.
[SPEAKER_00]: We are committed to nurturing collaboration, imagination, and creative problem solving at the Brooks.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a responsive classroom model school, we strive to establish and maintain an environment that supports the whole child, challenges prejudice, respects differences, and fosters a deep concern for others.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Brooks educators, staff, volunteers, parents, guardians, and students work together to provide all students and staff with a safe place to learn while allowing them to be curious and take intellectual risks to achieve high academic standards and to grow to their full potential.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every member of the Brooks community pledges to be kind, be safe, and be responsible.
[SPEAKER_00]: These Brooks Bees encompass all that we prioritize in our daily interactions with each other.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I previously mentioned, we focus on educating the whole child.
[SPEAKER_00]: Our staff is committed to the responsive classroom model that shows consistent language and modeling throughout the school.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some aspects that are implemented with fidelity include modeling expected behaviors, using logical consequences, including students in creating class rules and expectations, and creating a safe learning environment where all are welcomed and respected.
[SPEAKER_00]: We value both frequent and open communication between home and school.
[SPEAKER_00]: Please keep your contact information updated with the school and district so that you will be sure to receive our weekly updates and newsletters.
[SPEAKER_00]: On a personal note, I am a proud mother of two beautiful daughters in their first years of college.
[SPEAKER_00]: My husband and I are now officially empty nesters.
[SPEAKER_00]: My educational journey began as a special ed paraprofessional in Medford 29 years ago.
[SPEAKER_00]: After spending four years in this position, I was hired in Tewksbury Public Schools where I spent 19 years in various positions before returning to Medford in 2017.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was honored to be the assistant principal here for three years before being hired as the principal in 2020.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I'd like you to know that if you ever have any questions, comments, or concerns in between communications, to always feel free to contact me at any time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Please know that I truly believe in collaboration between home and school, as it is the key to a successful school year, because when we work together, everyone achieves more.
[SPEAKER_00]: I look forward to working as a team with all of you this school year, and I thank you for taking the time to watch this.