So Dennis, what's the most important clause that isn't in the Constitution?
The most important clause that's not in the Constitution?
Yep.
Santa Clause.
Well, you got it.
Enough with the cheesy jokes.
Let's get back to the Mustang Report.
Mr. President, ladies and gentlemen!
For the performance of the National Anthem under the direction of Ms.
Kayla Malone.
seeing all the faces of people from the past years in the community, and one of the things I think we all pride in is getting to announce the speaker for this year's graduation.
Mr. Andy Miller!
Mr. Miller, we want to congratulate all four graduates for making it through the past few months.
Congratulations to all of you.
Congratulations again on the accomplishments and the
This time I'd like to recognize all our teams.
for the outstanding sports season you've had this fall.
We appreciate all your efforts and we appreciate all of you working in to represent our community in a positive and productive way.
And also to all the people that participated, the folks, our advisors, who are doing a great job keeping our high school a terrific place to go to school.
To all of the 129
meaning I've been through it all in the second almost continuous schoolboy football rivalry in the country.
But go Mustangs!
Gallop through the tornado, gallop through the... Congress tornado, not the golf tornado.
And let's go Mustangs!
Every year, the Beth Tepesco Alumni Association presents a series of awards to recognize certain members of their community for their service to the students of Beth Tepesco.
This is the 2016 Young Alumni Tumor Award Ceremony.
It is being recognized for its dedication as a teacher, coach, advisor, assistant principal, and overall academic supporter.
Please join me in recognizing the 2001 alum, Medvedov, Mr. President.
We have a few more sponsors here.
Our only team to go in 2020 is Carter Rager and Justin Kelly.
Right now we have Ronald Cloud, Ben Keaney, Willa Driscoll, Drew Shane-Anne, and Judy Gail Bass.
So I'd like to take this time to acknowledge the members of the boys and girls soccer teams who are both DVL All-Stars.
For the girls, Isabelle Sanchez.
For the boys in the second team of All-Stars, Joao Lucio Correa, Noah Correa, Ryan Palmer, Jimmy Green.
First team of All-Stars, Igor Sousa-Guerra, Josh Westbrook, and last team of All-Stars,
This is America's fourth time beating our world's farm, three times beating the United States' world's farm, three times on the state board.
Till I collapse, I'm spillin' these racks long as you feel em' Till the day that I drop, you'll never say that I'm not killin' em' Cause when I am not, then I'ma start killin' em' and I am not
You're coming with me, feel it or not You're gonna fear it like I showed you
hear the spirit of God lives in us.
You hear it a lot.
Lyrics that shock.
Is it a miracle or am I just product of pop?
Listen up.
This isn't a whistle.
This is the plot.
Listen up.
Your prayers is for God.
Slizzle does not give up.
Music is like magic, there's a certain feeling you get when you're real and you spit And people are feeling it, this is your moment, and every single minute you spend Tryna hold on to it, cause you may never get it again So while you're in it, try to get as much as you can And when your run is over, just admit when it's in its end Cause I'm at the end of my wits without the shit that gets in I got a list, here's the order of my list and it's in It goes Reggie, Jay-Z, Tupac, and Biggie
I put on this list, this s*** is not a thing That's why you see me walk around like nothing's bothering me Even though half you people got a s*** problem with me You hate it, but you know respect you got to give me The press is wet dream, like Bob and your Whitney, they hit me Till the roof comes off, till the
I feel I ever deserve, but I'll never be served.
My spot is forever reserved.
If I ever leave Earth, that would be the death of me first.
Because in my heart of hearts, I know nothing could ever be worse.
Good job, good job, good job!
Nice job, good job!
Looking good, you're doing great!
Finish strong.
Good job.
Keep going.
Nice job.
Good job, Riley.
Keep going.
You're doing great.
40.
Who's finished for guys over here?
Good job, Ethan!
Go, Emma!
Woo!
Good job, Emma!
Keep going, keep going!
Good job!
You got it!
Good job, Keegan!
Yay!
Good job, ladies!
Nice!
Nice job!
You got it!
Awesome job!
Nice job!
Keep it coming, Aiden!
Keep it coming!
Right there!
You got it!
Anna!
Keep it coming!
You got it, Anna!
Yay!
You got it, guys!
Oh, this one!
Nice job, Zach and Morgan!
I actually turned out six a year ago.
Damn!
Come on, D.B.!
Come on, D.B.! !
How are you?
Hi, how are you doing?
You guys are doing good this year, yeah?
Alright, that's nice of you to say, huh?
We've got to sing some songs to warm you guys up, huh?
7, 6, 5, 4, 3, 2, 1.
Does she look beautiful?
So,
We're going to put some stuff in here to see if we can win it.
I said so I keep big bills up in my heart on the dirty like blood so ain't got no twist in my head but I'm still drippin'
So I go to bed full of lies, end it to end it to end it I'm all in, I might call you my cousin, blood but we ain't kids
Take the dough off your hands, take the dough off your bands, pop, pop, pop for all your friends Man, please, this here ain't cynical, uh-uh, neon or subliminal I'm physical, financial, and mental to be a general Hey, lil' mama claim she want a soldier Not the typeie in the tank, but in that Rover Man, please, I'm in the zone like AIDS full-blown I'm killin' it like a blind man readin', I'm feelin' it like O.M.
Oh, here comes the, y'all don't really want it like that Oh, here comes the, oh, here comes the Oh, here comes the, y'all don't really want it like that Oh, here comes the, oh, here comes the Oh, here comes the, y'all don't really want it like that Oh, here comes the