Okay so the first item we'll call the meeting to order. It's 5.02 on March 15, 2023. This is the Hormel Commission meeting. The first item on the agenda, one of the first, is the field use schedules approved on applications. So Phyllis, did I just see some applications come in through email? Yes, those were the applications that were sent by the Cancer Society and the
softball, you, you girls softball team. Okay. So is Gina and Alexandra. Okay. The American, American cancer. And we have Chuck from the soft, the youth girls softball. Okay. Um, so, so is it Chuck and Paulette? Uh, Paulette isn't here yet. Okay. Yeah. Chuck, do you know if she's joining us? I don't think she is. No. Okay.
Do we wanna wait to see if she is, or do you definitely know she's not? No, no, no. Okay. So we'll take the Medford Youth Girls softball application first. I'm just trying to, is the attachment here, Phyllis? Yes. I got it. Sorry. The drain field.
Okay, so Chuck, you're familiar with the process with sharing the fields with Medford baseball, correct? Yeah, so Kevin and I had sat down with someone from baseball probably about a month ago. Yeah. We haven't connected since, so I think when we had talked, we had talked about there may be some availability at Tuesdays and Thursdays, and I think
A few hours on Sundays. Okay. Kevin is that. Yeah, that's correct. So we've already started the discussion between baseball and softball. I know, in the past it was historically baseball but softball has used it.
some years and then other years they haven't, this would be one year that softball has grown. Their numbers are larger than where it has in previous years. So I'm looking to use that field as well. So like I said, we already started that discussion, just to make sure that we can share the space. And I believe, Chuck, correct me if I'm wrong, softball is really only looking to use one of the fields, not both fields. Oh yeah, yeah. I think it's drain one. Yeah.
Yeah, right drain one is allowed for softball or reconfigured so softball can be used for it. Okay, so we've already just had that discussion with them. I know we once the games and the practice schedule is set, I want to have another meeting with baseball and softball again, just so we have a lot of communication and sharing. But other than that, I think we should be fine.
Chuck, do you have any questions for the commission? I don't think so. So the idea is that baseball and us will work it out through Kevin? Yeah, Kevin and his staff do the scheduling. OK. So I think where we already discussed the days with you on the Tuesday and Thursday, and then baseball, I believe, is used in Baltimore on Monday and Wednesday.
I just want to have, when you guys are ready to schedule out your games and practices, to have another meeting together to make sure there's no overlap or conflicts. And if there is a conflict, we can be able to discuss it before the season. So we get that all straightened away. OK. Yeah. I think we talked, like, it's, for us especially, the first three weeks of April are the toughest, because once we have
We have a U-10 division with five teams. It's going to be playing each other. And so once they start playing games, it'll almost cut the, it'll cut us down from like meeting 10 nights a week to five across, you know, different fields we have. So we really just want to, we especially want to get it lined up for the first three weeks of April, week three. Okay. Sounds like Kevin in,
work with you in baseball. Now, do you use another field? Yeah, besides this one? We have, we use McNally, Hickey, Columbus, and Tufts. Okay. Does anybody else have any questions? Nope. Is that a no? I just had a quick question. Did the permit had all day Saturday and Sunday?
Okay, yeah I think Paul has submitted that we submitted. We hadn't met with baseball before we submitted that so we're looking for as much as we can get. Okay, does someone want to make a motion to approve this application like a motion to approve the schedule for the softball.
Okay, your application's approved, Chuck. Thank you for joining us this evening. If you have any questions, Kevin would be your first contact. Okay, I'll talk to you, Kevin. Okay. And then next, Gina and Alexandra from the American Cancer Society.
Hi, how are you? Good, how are you? Good, thank you for joining us. Sorry about the wait. Oh, no worries, please. Thank you for having us. So I'm just trying to open up the document here. Sure. Can you just start to tell us about the event? Sure. So it is the American Cancer Society's Relay for Life event. It is our signature fundraiser. We actually used Hormel Stadium back in 2015 and 2016. We had a number of events in different communities around the area, and we actually
combined them to become the Relay for Life of Greater Arlington. But over the past year, we've needed to move some sites. We have a good number of representation of participants that come from both Medford and from Arlington. We're looking for Saturday, June 10th from 4 p.m. to 10 p.m. with some time for setup and cleanup. And Relay for Life, if you're not familiar with it, it is really a time where people come together
They fundraise throughout the year to celebrate as a team on our cancer survivors cancer survivors take the first lap during our survivor celebrations. We also remember loved ones lost during the luminaries ceremony of have some different activities, you know throughout the course of the event, you know speakers.
you know, dance demonstrations, different things like that. The teams do, you know, some fundraising and some activities on site, but it's really sort of a celebration of sort of the year-long efforts of the teams to do some fundraising. Okay, great. In 2015, so
Is this the event that starts the night before? Well, yeah, so it used to be a lot of the events at one point in time used to be a 24 hour event because when individuals are diagnosed with cancer, they deal with it 24 hours a day. However, over the years and especially after COVID, a lot of our events no longer do the 24 hours, but we'd like an evening component to be able to have the luminaria ceremony, which is we have
the white bags with glow sticks in them that get lit in honor and remembrance of loved ones. So yes, we used to be an overnight event and probably a Friday into Saturday. The last time I know in 2016, we were just a Saturday afternoon to evening, actually the same timeframe, the four to 10. So we would like that again and we should be cleaned up by about 11 p.m. and ready to get out of there and things.
have you met Kevin yet? No, we have not. We put the paperwork in to Mr. Curley, and then I know he had asked some questions, and then we're here tonight. So I'm sure that, you know, if approved, we'd be talking back and forth. We're happy to answer any questions. But no, this is our first time meeting, so thank you. Hi, Kevin!
Kevin Bailey, the athletic, I'm sorry, the recreation director for the city of Medford. Kevin, do you have specific questions regarding the application? I do have a couple of quick things. The PA system and with music and with noise, just to be mindful of that area particularly, there's condos around that location.
So you don't know when you're planning on doing the announcing, but once it gets towards about nine, 10 o'clock at night, typically if there's a PA system going, I usually get a couple of emails. Well, and our music would be off at 10 PM when we shut down and it actually would start to even be a little bit on the quieter side.
after nine, because that's normally when our luminaria ceremony is, and then we start to have our closing. So when we would be mindful working with our DJ to, you know, position speakers away from broadcast, you know, to broadcast in certain directions too, if that would be helpful. Thank you. And then the other thing is to serve food. Are you planning on having food in the field area? Or what is the plan for food? Well, we're still sort of working the plan for food. We would like to have, you know, a food truck or certain if possible, but we do know
Cause I do have the map from 2016 and I know that there was a certain sort of food area that we had to have off to the side. I guess we, we couldn't have food on the field, which is, which is fine with us. We can make do. Cause a lot of times, you know, teams bring in their own, you know, snacks, they would go off to the side to eat. And right now, because of just some, you know, changes, I'm looking for, you know, a new site. We,
we have not secured the food yet. So it might be one or two food trucks, and we would work with you to make sure that they were in a certain area that would need it to be. All right, great. Thank you. Sure. No, thank you. Good question. You mentioned teams, and there's the relay in your title, and I'm just not familiar with it. Can you describe the athletic component of your event? So it's really, it's in all honesty, just walking.
It's called relay for life because teams sort of take to the track relay style and one person from their team should be on the track at all times walking and so as we do have batons they pass off but it's mostly you know it's walking with just fun activities.
throughout the event. But teams are normally anywhere from a couple of people to 15 to 20, depending upon the size of the team. They have a team captain, they fundraise. Some of the teams are friends and family or a certain community group or teams from a school that might've been a club, something like that. Excellent. Yeah. Awesome. Cool. Well, definitely, hopefully you could come out and you could even form a team.
Yeah, no, I think I might do that. Cool. Is there a rain date or is it rain or shine? It is rain or shine. It is rain or shine because it's a lot of different logistical things. And we've always been rain or shine because we have that mindset. Individuals that are undergoing cancer treatment and different things, they are really supposed to sort of represent that day in the life of a cancer patient
And so that's why it used to be 24 hours. It started in the day, went through the evening, ended the next day. So if it is a light rain, different things, we would still go. If there is a storm coming or different things, we would be very mindful of the forecast, either asking people to go to their cars. There have been times where it's been a huge storm. We've had to sort of call it at that time just because of the weather coming in. So we would always be
We watch the forecast for a lot, a lot of days, you know, leading up to the event and make you know and plan accordingly. Right. I just have one other quick question. I know she checked yes for staging. Do you have a plan are you planning on putting staging on the turf area or are you. That's something that we would work out.
with you, sometimes we do bring in a couple of risers just to make the speakers be able to be seen a little bit more, but that could be over by where the DJ set up or an honesty, you guys are, but you would tell us where things could go. And we do have the map from 2016 and we didn't really, we had sort of the ceremonies and the DJs, it was probably in some areas,
sort of off to the side of the track a little bit, but you know if we couldn't bring in a stage, you know that's not a problem either, but it's not anything like large, it would just be you know some type of risers. Just from past experience I learned we try to avoid putting any staging and the turf area. Yes, yeah. There is some divots and the other thing that we learned to is getting the rises on to even the grassy area, you have to go over the track.
But then you also have to have a truck go onto the grass here, so if it's been raining the past couple of days before he got his wet. yeah huge tire box on that so just things to kind of be mindful and consider, but there are different areas where I think off to the corner like you said that would be the best location for the staging area. Also seen people put staging area right on the bleachers itself, so they close off in the area and they use that for the DJ and announcing but.
Just kind of put that in your ear now when we look at the map set up and everything. Sure. And that would be something that if approved, we'd love to actually set up a face-to-face meeting, you know, with yourself, with Alex, and a few of our leadership volunteers to come out and look at that site map from before and see if things still, you know, work and what some of the specifics are. And I know there are a couple of things still that we would, we actually owe to you guys
because we can't get them once approved, like we need to update our insurance certificate and get that to you. So there's some different things. So yes, we would love to have a meeting to talk about that if approved and to make sure we're doing things the right way. Thank you. Sure. How many people do you expect at the event? We expect anywhere from maybe 150 to 200, could be a little bit less. We're still registering teams.
sometimes even survivors and people just come out that day to see stuff. A lot of times the survivor celebrations during opening and the luminaria ceremony are the times where the most people are there, because sometimes the guests come, but then they leave as well. So sometimes they don't stay the whole time. So we're factoring between about 150 to 200. And then I noticed on the application, it's not checked off that
there will be a need for DPW city to set up for this event. Kevin, in your experience with events of this size, what has been, what do you see the needs of the organization? Like what do you see them needing from the city? Like it's not checked off here, but would we have to have anybody from DPW for the electricity come out, set anything up?
Yeah, so I think when we have a meeting to discuss the details, those are things that would have to be considered. Electricity is a perfect example. Like Commissioner Caruso mentioned, like electricity. I'm not sure how you've done it in years past, but if it's towards the bleacher area, you can always run electricity through the field house. Graduation, for example, the staging is on the other side. So DPW comes in with a,
a generator to be able to hook up electricity. So that would be an additional expense. For an event this size, we would probably need police detail. There's police detail when we request it. This one for 200 will probably be one police officer. And then we would have them connect with you with the billing. Okay. And is that something that if approved,
The commission, or DBW would request the police officer or would we go through the police department to make that request, we will request it from to the police department. Okay, invoicing and the billing will be sent directly to you so that's that's fine. Yep. Afterwards, with all the contact information for the billing. Sure.
As far as other additional expenses, I don't think DPW would need to be here unless we talk about setup where we would need extra trucks or something special equipment, but as far as our field setup, we would have field staff there probably a little bit earlier to be there to help with the setup and open up the doors and give you access to the electricity, the press box and all that. Okay.
200 people cleaning up afterwards, that's going to be a few, a little bit of time. Right. And that was, and that is one of my questions too about sort of trash, like, should we bring in, you know, would we, you know, bring in a dumpster? Because, you know, because we can get trash boxes and trash cans, but is that something that, you know, DBW could provide and we pay for? Didn't know how that all worked. Our field staff can do that. We would schedule,
I would probably tell our facility coordinator to bring in at least four staff members to be there. Might even go a little bit more than that, but they would take care of the bathrooms. They would clean it afterwards, help take out the trash during the event and after the event. And with that, we walk the field and we pick up trash and all that. So we would probably have for additional expenses and minimum
for extra staff members, their pay is usually around $16 to about $20 an hour, depending on the person particularly. But again, it would probably be there for the time of the event, but I would consider an extra hour beforehand for them to get ready. And then I would figure at least an hour afterwards to help with the clean up. Sure. And we understand that those are expenses that we pay for, because that also helps
Although Alex and I are staffed with the ACS, the relay is planned by a whole volunteer planning committee that will do the ceremonies and the activities and different things. So to have some of that logistical help is helpful. So we realize that that's an expense that we are able to pay for. Anybody else have any other questions?
All set. Brian? No. Do you have any other questions for us? I don't think so, Alex. Is there anything that I'm forgetting about? I think electricity and trash are one of the questions that I have, and we talked about that. I think my next question, but that depends on approval, is if we're approved at this meeting, are we able to go and send out an announcement that we're at this
you know, at Hormel Stadium on June 10th, just to be able to, you know, get people start to get signed up and different things like that. But, so I should have said, Alex, anything I'm forgetting? No, I think you got everything, but that was also going to be my next question. I know our volunteers are so excited to hear some kind of answer. And they really liked, because a couple of our volunteers were involved when it was at Hormel Stadium in 2015 and 2016. And they're very excited about the possibility of being back.
So. Good to have you back. Yeah, absolutely. Very worthy cause. Yep. There was one thing I just thought of, and now my mind just went blank. Let me open that up. I want to just open the application. Maybe the application will jog my memory. 1 to 11, right? What's that? Was it 1 to 11?
Well, the event itself would be from four to 10 with one being at the time where volunteers could come in and do some setup. We have some pop-up tents where we do registration and different things out of. And we hang up banners and decorations and things. And then it'll go to 11 for cleanup. I think I know what it was. Kevin, high school graduation, is that
set in stone yet? I have, yeah, I'm actually looking at the calendar. So I do have, John did put a hold for the Cancer Society on the 10th from 1 to 11. So it's on hold right now. Nothing is booked. I will say we do have mass flight football from 8 to 11, but again, that shouldn't have an effect. Yeah, and we wouldn't, like I said, arrive until 1 to start, you know, setting up. And our teams would, you know, come in even a little bit after that.
And then high school graduation, I have the 7th, 8th, and the 9th. So I think if I remember correctly, looking at remembering the past emails, I think it's planned to be on the 7th. Yeah. It's just a case. Yeah. So graduation is before the event.
And then Arlington Catholic, did they use Hormel Stadium for graduation or no? Did they only do it that one time? I don't remember them being there last year, but I wouldn't know anything past that. I might be thinking of the year of COVID when everything was outside. That's what I'm probably thinking of.
I want to make sure there's no other high school graduations that would come up like bubble up in the next couple of weeks. Yeah, and I appreciate that. So if you haven't heard Kevin, I would assume that it's just. We haven't received a request from Arlington Catholic and I was looking at the calendar and I've been looking at it. I know John has done really well with the bookings. We already have even that month we have.
all of our outside renters and stuff are already confirmed. So the schedule is pretty well set. Okay. Okay. So does someone want to make a motion to approve the application? I make a motion to approve the Cancer Society Relay for Life. And I'm happy to second that motion. Great. Awesome. Thank you guys. Thanks for coming.
Well, thank you. And so real quick with, because I remember from the application, we do need, I did submit a proof of our insurance, but we need to update our COI listings to additional people, certificate holders, and additionally insured. Should I send that directly to Mr. Curley, because that's who we submit the application to? Or Kevin, do you want a copy of that or? If you want to submit everything to John, John handles the day to day events.
John is actually usually at these meetings as well. He was out sick tonight. But typically, John, you'll be handling all the day-to-day logistics of the event. Awesome. Wonderful. So we'll do that. And then with the approval, are we able to go ahead and let our committee know and let our teams know and start the publicity?
Sure, yep, absolutely. Thank you so much, we appreciate it. And if you wanna share it with us, please do. Okay, yeah, we'll definitely send over some of the flyers and different things as well, so that'd be awesome. Okay, great, thanks so much, thanks for what you do. Oh, thank you so much. Thank you. Enjoy the rest of your Wednesday, enjoy the rest of your Wednesday evening, we appreciate it very much. And if you need anything else, please don't hesitate to reach out and then we'll be in touch, like I said, to set up, you know, maybe something face-to-face to do a walkthrough and we'll get you the additional COI.
Okay, sounds good. Thank you so much. Take care. Okay. Those are only the only two applications. That's all I had.
Okay. There was something else from the Frisbee applicants from the past, but that was just a license in regards to food and so forth. Okay. And they were past users, so they didn't have to come in front of you. Okay. Okay.
I see Todd Blake on. Yes. Todd, are you going to shut the meeting off on us again like last time? No, I'm trying not to. OK. Don't give Todd control.
Phil has asked me back because I think just in case you had additional questions from last time. So that was regarding the bike station at Hormel, correct? Correct. Okay. Brian, did you get a chance to look at the application from the February meeting by any chance about the request to put the blue bikes, correct? Correct.
the blue bike station down at Hormel? I did look at that, yes. OK. So I think we kind of wanted to make a, we wanted to all be able to ask questions. Did you have any questions on it before we voted? No questions. OK. Kevin, is there any concern that you have with the location? No.
Pat? No, I think it's great. OK. Todd, anything to add? No, just here for questions. OK, so does someone want to make a motion to approve the Blue Bike Station? I'll make that motion to approve the Blue Bike Station down by Hormel. OK. I'll second it. Wonderful.
Congratulations, Todd, on your blue bike location. Now we have the pleasure of working with Steve to install it. Stevie T will help you out. Yup. And we'll all be down to get a bike. Nice. After hearing all these events, I'm like, all right, we're just going to make sure we're not installing it or Steve's doing work the day of one of these events. Right. We'll coordinate that with Kevin, I guess. Yeah.
All right, thanks. Okay. Discussion on memorials. So I was thinking about this earlier. So we still have Mr. Karasiewicz's, the plaque. Kevin, where is the materials? Do you have it all? That's right, yeah.
Oh, you have it? Oh, look at that. Let me see. Let me see. Hold it up again. A little closer. It's a lot heavier than it looks. Come on, Kevin. Use your muscles. That came out nice. Wow. Nice. Where will that go again? Kevin, what was the place that you guys thought was the best? We talked about where the AED was, the AED box was installed.
So right when you first walk in on the right hand side, there's the brick wall where the confession room is. Oh yeah. Okay. There's already a plaque on the ticket booth. So I kind of want to avoid the ticket booth area. So it's not. What is the, what is the work to get it mounted? That's why it's still in my office. I was planning on mounting it myself, but the screws just don't go straight in. You have to like.
Anger backside or something. You better call Stevie T beyond my handyman skills. You got to call Steve. So I guess we have to pick an event when we're going to do this dedication. Is there anything coming up that you know of that is like, I don't know, Kevin, what do you think?
In some ways, I'd like to do it. There's the fifth grade Olympics, the PE department holds. Oh, that's a good idea. On Friday, June 2nd. OK. That's a good one. What do you guys think about that? So it's like fifth grade junior Olympics? Yeah. The kids are down from all the schools. They're all at the Hormel.
Yeah, so it looks like it's Friday, June 2 is also another reservation on the fifth, my assumption is one of them is a rain date. Okay, we can double check that in the fifth graders have all that energy. Yeah.
Can I add something? Does the mayor's office need to? Yeah, I was gonna say, I was gonna ask, the mayor usually attends those events. I would imagine it should be, yeah. So we'd need to coordinate with the fifth grade committee.
I imagine it's more than a few people because of the amount of fifth grade classrooms there are in each school building. So Kevin, do you have contacts that you're working with there? No, I know John, I was copying into an email to John from Bob Maloney about it. Okay. It was either Bobby or Rachel.
I can see if I can find that email and respond to that. If not, I can talk to John and see who his contact was and to reach out to them. Is this like fifth grade citywide? Yeah. That sounds awesome. The happiest years of my life. Me too.
Okay, so do we want to send a communication to Bobby Maloney asking him if this was something they would entertain us to do? They would entertain? I think this is run by the PE department. So do you think it's best to contact Rachel? I would imagine she would be the one. Yeah. So if we can contact Rachel Perry and ask her if during the, you know, either maybe they
have it at the beginning or the end. I can talk to her as well if she has more questions. I don't know of any other events. There's nothing else, Kevin, that's like football doesn't start till the fall. We don't want to wait. Yeah, so I was looking through some of it. There is high school track meets.
It looks like the meets are already scheduled, so you could do May 2nd, May 11th. Are there any Memorial Day activities in the field? Not usually, right? Like Memorial Day weekend? The Cancer Society event, and there is another hold for the Pride Day event. That's on June 25th.
But I don't think that's confirmed, it's just a hole, so nothing's confirmed yet. And into the political season too, so there's people who'll probably want to have their picture taken. The elections this fall. Yeah. I mean, Chris Murphy had a lot of background on
on the history of the stadium. I think I'm gonna reach out to him and ask him if he thinks there's an appropriate event that we do the dedication. That's a good idea. Yeah. What do you guys think of that? I think that's great. Okay. Okay. I'll get in touch with him and have an update for the next meeting. Cool. Okay.
See here. Financial status. Did we get any financials? I didn't see any.
No, I wrote it in the second email today. On the email today, I wrote that the financial people were not in, they were at a conference and could not get the financials to us. Okay. Kevin, is there anything that you wanted to bring up regarding the financials or the Hormel itself? As far as financials, I did email the financial director.
I want to sit down and go over the financials at home. If you remember the last meeting, the money that's deposited seemed much lower than what my spreadsheet said. So we are over $25,000 off of what the finance department had.
So I want to sit down and meet with him. I think just money that's being deposited isn't being allocated directly to Formell Stadium. So I do want to meet with him. He did say that he was really busy at the time, but I think when he was back from the conference, he wanted to sit down and go over that. So hopefully at the next meeting, I'll be able to get.
better update with the finances. With that said, just some updates from Hormel you might have seen on our Facebook post. I want to say it was last Friday we had a company come in to professionally do a deep clean of the turf. This came in with a machine on a tractor
Basically, that machine vacuums up everything, so the little white fibers that you've probably seen at home now and get up close, you know, we have a groomer and a sweeper sweeper we try to use. And the sweeper will pick up any of the big stuff but it doesn't get like the fibers that's one of the things that we're told that you really want a company coming with that special vacuum to get those fibers up so.
The vacuum was able to do that. It also had a magnet there, so any metal that was left inside the turf, that's been removed. And again, it just does a sweep of the turf, and then they actually do a deep groove as well, so to get all the rubberized pellets and stuff being brought back up to the surface, loose fiber, and clean that up. So it looks great. It is relatively expensive. You remember our last meet,
I think it was a few meetings ago. As I mentioned, it's about $2,500 for them to come out. So it's not something that we can do on a routine basis, but it is something I'd like to try to get in the habit to do at least at the beginning of the season. And then maybe somewhere in the summertime before football season begins, just so that we can have that turf deep cleaned every once in a while. Did they give you an idea of like the condition of the field?
Unfortunately, no, it's just a guy that came in, did the work, but wasn't the expert to look at the results. OK, I was just curious. I went down to try to pick his brain, but he was definitely not someone that would be able to give the expertise. How expensive was it? Just curious. It was $2,500.
How much was it, Kevin? Say it again. It was 2,500, but you know what? That's not that bad. I mean, I think it's reasonable if it's for the whole field. Kevin, was this maintenance done before? Do you know? It was actually 2,850. 2,850. Okay. Did, did, um, has this ever been done before? I don't know, to be honest.
In addition, I heard back from DPW, as you know, the press box is in deep need of some maintenance repairs. At this point, the backside of the press box, the vinyl siding is out and is open holes.
Of course, at the point in time, one of the things that we want to prevent with those open holes is we don't use it as much in the winter and we're afraid that animals are going to get in there. So we want to get the press box taken care of. I did hear back from DPW today that that would cost about $4,000 on the staffing that doesn't include parts.
I'd like to get the finances back, but I do know that we do have a net profit right now. I think this is something that isn't necessarily a want, but something that we really need to do at this point, just to seal it and make sure water's not getting in, animals are not getting in there. I feel like if we don't do this repair, it's just gonna create bigger issues later on down the road. So I'd like to spend that $4,000 to get the staff to be able to do that repair, and then whatever the additional cost is on material.
Kevin wasn't the roof leaking at one time, did they fix that. That would be included with the. There i've already talked a little bit briefly with Steve on this and they're not just going to fix the holes, but they're looking at actually doing the repair of that on the roof and do. On the vinyl siding on it as well.
we're also working not the most glamorous thing but we're working on changing out the toilet paper dispensers. Oh, that is riveting Kevin. But also writes pawn and test pool. Really, what it is is the expenses that we have right now, you have to have a special size toilet paper and they are discontinued so at this point I feel like a bar.
to fit a lot of those dispensers. So in addition to OMAL, Rice, Bond and Tuscaloosa are installing new ones. It's the same ones that are right now at the hockey rink, but they are readily available for the right toilet paper. So we won't run into any issues like that at the end of the summer.
We also been working with the school department on updating some of the track and field equipment at Hormel Stadium. If you remember last year, our Discus cage setting fell during a windstorm. We did purchase a new one. Unfortunately, it didn't come in until after the track season, but we do have it in the locker rooms at Hormel.
And I was speaking about it to make sure that before the track season, the staff comes out there and puts the discus cage back out, hook up the new one. I just didn't want to leave it out in the wintertime and have it break during a windstorm or anything again. So we do have the discus net that's coming up very shortly. We also ordered new track starting blocks that was purchased out of the Hormel budget. So we will have those at Hormel as well.
And those actually just came to my office today. So those are just brought to all my stadium this afternoon. And I'm also working with john trying to get a quote to replace the sand that's in the long jump. That's the need for replacement. It looks like there's a lot of Like rocks or gravel that made its way in there. So we want to replace that sand.
And then I also asked john to get a tarp sandbags and just cover it so really it's not used very frequently it's only used by the back so you're talking a few months out of the year, so I'd like to try to have that covered, I think that will extend the life of it. And that is all I have for updates. Okay.
Anybody else have anything they want to mention? Nope. Nope, all good here. One thing I was going to bring up is, Kevin, what was the event that we had not a lot of advanced
Well, we, we knew, we knew they were having an event. It was what last summer that there was some issues with the way that the conditions of the field were left after. With the bone people. Yeah. Yeah. The, uh, it was almost like a reggae kind of party about that one.
Yeah, it was the one that they left like food and stuff in the barrels out in the parking lot. There was noise complaints to the police department. That was D1 soccer. That was D1 soccer. That was their end of the year. That was their championship event. OK. So I think I'm thinking of the foam party. Yeah, that's the one that was like the reggae music one. Yes. OK. So with the nicer weather hopefully going to
be here before we know it. I just was wondering if, as a commission, we want to talk about the types of events that we agree to hold or that we need to look at more closely than others. The stadium is for the purpose of athletic events, but we do get requests for not
athletic events. So I wanted to see what you guys thought about if we wanna establish some guidelines. What do you think? Was it a big religious event? Did that go well? It was gonna be a lot of people there. I don't remember what happened. The church that uses the school too, I think.
That went off okay, right? Oh, last year they had a rock. Rock the night or rock the band. Yeah, yeah, yeah. So we move that over to the Andrews field. Oh, okay. Really are the way john and I feel about it is because formal is synthetic turf. We really are trying to avoid having food on the turf area. I said it was
$2,800 to have a company come out and vacuum and do a deep cleaning. And I know it happens still. Even just like after school, kids coming and playing, food is being on the field. But we really want to try to limit that. We have these big festivals that have food directly there. People will walk around on the field and on the track.
know, it's, it creates a mess, you know, it stays on the on the track until someone physically comes up and picks it out. The same as like having a rug in your house, right? For us, it's $2,800 to get it vacuumed. Right. So do we want to take applications like case by case in
start like discussing them, not in front of the applicant and say, well, we'll take it, you know, table it and have another discussion on it. I just, I don't want to get like, I don't want to get in front of an applicant and us have an issue where we're like, not sure of how we want to move on it. I mean, like events that have food trucks and stuff like that. I think
they're going to, if they're going to rent Hormel, they're going to expect to be inside the stadium, right? There's no way around like letting them use the parking area and then having enough space because people will bring food into the stadium. Like, do you guys think we can limit like food being brought into the stadium? I just don't, I don't, I don't want to get in a position where we don't know what we want to do going forward, but I want to keep it consistent for everything. Cool.
Some of the people that come in, though, I mean, I don't want to say they're not truthful, but some of those fans, we didn't expect to happen what happened at them either. So I don't know how you work that out ahead of time. But we certainly should just maybe when we meet with the people, just listen and then have a team back afterwards and we'll get back to them. At least, like you say, you don't want to be
like we don't know what we're doing if you have somebody sitting there who's, well, this is our 18th year doing this. We've never had it in the same place twice. So the flag goes up there. And I do find it useful when, you know, Phyllis always sends ahead of time any of the documentation to support them. So it gives us time to look them over. And if there are issues,
you know, we can always communicate before, after meeting them. So I think that's very useful. Yeah. Okay. Like a festival or an event, it could be an initial meeting to have Q and A, but then have them come back the following month. So in that Q and A, it might be, we discussed the food issue. What is the food plan? What is the sound plan? What kind of music are you going to have? Right.
planning and then what time do you stop and in that month we could do a walkthrough john and i can meet with them do a walkthrough then come back at the next meeting with the whole plan with a map what everything how everything is going to be laid out the details of the event so it might be a kind of hold them a little bit more accountable of what is discussed in that commission meeting that it needs to follow through if they're gonna
continue to use this facility in the future. But if it's someone like you said, like I said, oh, I've been doing this for eight years, every year it's at a new facility. If it is someone that's been established, this isn't the first time that I'm ever organizing this event. Finding out who they went to in the past. Exactly. Got that information in that month, where they're coming from the initial meeting to the second one for approval.
we can contact some of those places and see how they were as a, as a, as a renter. We'd never have them back again. Yeah. Yeah, absolutely. I'm just curious, depending on the scale of the event, do they live, do they leave a deposit that's relative to the scale of the rental or is it, is it a fixed deposit or none at all?
Yeah, so typically, if you're a very first-time person, we want you to pay up front. If it's someone who's been reoccurring, we charge them each month, we send them an invoice. Festivals and events, I think that is something that we should consider as well. If it's $150 to rent the facility as an outsider, if you're bringing in 200, 300 people and it is a festival, it is an event and it's not
You know, $150 is that thought and consideration when you have a tournament, when you have a lacrosse game, when you have a soccer game, even on the tournaments might have a large number of spectators, but when you start adding festivals, that cleanup time is much greater. There might be two or three staff members at festival might end up being five or six. So maybe even with those festivals, you know, upon approval, we might also want to consider the commission
outline that you know it's not going to be $150 but maybe we need to increase that rate a little bit because the festival does require more hours, more staff to be able to handle it. Where are we Kevin on the on charging like that on the scale of like, I don't know if Jill Boyd does it or whatever but are we high low average, you know, $150.
I know Jailboy is more, I wanna say it's 170 last time I looked at it, but I will say that was probably over a year ago, just did the field over, so it might be even more money. There are places that charge more, there are places that charge less as well. So I don't think we're the cheapest, but I also don't think we're on the high end either. No, I was just curious, $150 doesn't seem like a lot.
Right. No, you know, for a festival and then when it's just a basic dual game, it's, it's, it's reasonable. It's comparable to the other place. Considering what we're making available to them. It's yeah. It's 150 is really good. Free parking. Yeah. Clean field. Yep.
Yeah, the 150, remember, we have to hire staff for it. Sure. You know, if their rental is for two hours, staff are probably there for at least three, depending on the event. But, you know, any time beforehand, they need to stay afterwards and clean. So, you know, you add a couple of people making $16 to $20 an hour, and then you add those extra hours in that they are there before and afterwards. It's not a huge profit,
margin. It's getting closer to the six o'clock hour. Okay, great. We have two minutes. Okay. Much more. I don't have anything else. Does anybody else have anything? Nope. Okay. Do you want to pick the date for the next meeting? Yes. Okay.
The school vacation coming up in April again. Um, I think it's the week of the 17th. So, um, I'm free. Does anyone else have conflicts in April? I'm teaching a class or an April vacation. Do you think about the 19th, Jeanine? I can make that work. If you guys can make that work. I won't be available. Well, John, um, you should be okay.
Brian and, um, does that work for you? Or Kevin, do you want to, do you want to, do you want us to move it to the 12th? 12th is good for me too. It's up to you guys. Either one is fine with me. Well, it is good. I like Kevin here. All right. Yeah.
Okay. Okay, the 12th. Yep. Okay. Okay, meeting adjourn and have a nice time. Yes. Thank you. It was nice seeing you all. Have a wonderful week.