the public meeting of the city of medford liquor license commission for 9 18 2024 will come to order uh we have an agenda to follow and the first thing on the agenda is to review the minutes of the august 21st 2024 license commission meeting um
I reviewed these myself is a couple of things. My number five carried over to this month's meeting. I made a note that was that one day application for deep cuts, correct? Yes. We're going to be reviewing that today. Okay.
And the other question I had, I know there was a question whether we've received payment or not yet from Lifetime Gym. We did, yep. We did, okay. Very good. Other than that, that looked good. My fellow commissioners, if you had a chance to review them, I'll also look to you guys. Mr. Chairman, I did number two regarding Blue Fuji.
I wasn't sure if that was what we, it says the commission will have the liquor license on probation for one year. Was that the language we used or did we say something to the effect that if there was another infraction within 12 years, within 12 months? No, from what I remember, we were doing a probation for all of them, from what I understood.
Bobby, is that correct? So from what I understood, we were doing probation for all of them for a year after the incidents, right? Yes. We followed the same penalty for it. I believe we also added in a one-day suspension and abidance.
Yeah. Because they didn't show when they were supposed to. We can probably correct that and put that in there because that was just one level above what the other ones were. That's a good catch, Alan. Yeah. I knew there was something more to that. When I read that, it just didn't look complete.
Yeah, yeah. And we've arranged just for information, we've arranged a meeting with Blue Fuji. We're still trying to finalize the date. But I wasn't convinced that they understood everything we had to say. And I know there was a language barrier there for me last month. And so we just want to
get together with them with a translator so that we could let them know exactly what we were trying to tell them last month and have them acknowledge that they know what we said and they'll be able to comply, especially with the TIP certification and all that stuff.
That's in the works and it's nothing we need a public meeting for. It's just an interpretation because we've already made the decision. We've gone through all of it. It's just we want to make sure they understand it. It's not going to be anything new other than what we discussed at the meeting.
So, that's that's really about it that I have with the. Last month's meeting minutes, Ben, how about yourself? I was not at the last month's meeting. So.
That's right. That's right. So this is good information for you. I'm just re-read it all. Other than that little tweak, I'm fine with the minutes. I'd motion to accept the minutes for the August 21st meeting and put them on public record. Okay, great. Do we have a second?
Yeah, I'll second it. Okay. Oh, you're right there. I'll second it. I'll second it. All right. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Hearing and seeing none. The ayes have it. Motion passed. Okay. Why don't we get right down to business. We have
On the agenda, Representative from Great American Bayhoe. Do we have Brian or someone here? Bobby, I don't see Brian, but I did email him. Which Brian? No, not you, Brian.
Or do we have a representative from Great American Beer Hall on the call? Yeah, you said that he would be here, so I don't know. Okay, we'll just push him back, that's all. Yeah, we can do that. Let me just shuffle my papers around a little bit. Okay. All right. Now we want the other Brian from Event Dem. I know you're out here, Brian.
How about that? How you doing, Brian? Ah, crazy. September is crazy. Good crazy. Yeah, it is. Yeah. Tell us a little bit about what's going on. Great. So it's essentially it's a copy and paste of another one of our gaming nights that we've done here. Video game focused, but we do other board games and other things. This one's focused around NBA,
NBA 2K, I think is what it's called. So, yeah, it's a video game, Ming Night tournament, copy and paste of the other ones we've done before. Okay. Yeah, I mean, Brian, you always do a great job, never have any issues there. You know, I know all of your documents are in order, everything's good. I just wanted to mention to you, I'm not sure whether you're aware of it or not, but we do have a,
a new online form for one day licenses. Um, you can, it's easy to fill out online, sends right to Daria. And, um, there's a couple of new questions on it about entertainment and things like that. So if you can get on board with that, that'd be great. That's grand. Yeah, sure. Yep. It'll be just trying to streamline a few things. Um, but other than that, it all looked good for me. Um, Alan, Ben,
look good to me it's same as usual you guys yeah so i'm fine.
Yeah, no, I agree, Ben. Very straightforward. I just wanted to remind Brian that we do have a maximum of 30 one-day licenses. So just keep that in mind. I don't think you're there, but you might be halfway there by now, I would think. Is that from January to December? The calendar year, yes. Yeah, I don't anticipate us.
Kidding it, but I mean, I do have an, I do have a counter on some. Okay. Now, you do a fine job. Everything's complete. You know, we have your insurance. We have your. Uh, the design, um. Uh, the layout.
of the building, so I'm good with this. Ben, if you don't mind me jumping in, I'll motion to approve the one-day license for Friday, October 4th for Event Dam Incorporated. I'll second that motion, Commissioner. I'm good with it. Okay. Very good. All those in favor? Aye. Aye. Aye.
All those opposed? Hearing and seeing none, the ayes have it, motion passes. Let's see, Jeff, Steve Cutts, you here? Hey, how are you? Oh, there we go.
Beautiful. Um, okay, Jeff, um, tell us a little bit about what's going on. Um, so we've been asked by the, uh, planning department to provide, uh, food and beer for the, uh, harvest your energy festival. So this is our, our application for, for setting that up. Okay. And, um, with that, there's, do you have a, let's think, I'm sorry, I'm a little, um,
What we're looking for that I didn't see was the insurance binder, the drawing, and the festival location, and if there's going to be entertainment there or not. Yes. I was going to say, Jeff did forward it to me yesterday. I just haven't had the chance to send it to you guys yet. He did the picture on insurance.
Okay, awesome. I need to have all of it. We won't waste any time on it. Jeff, from what I reviewed, everything looks fine. Daria has that, so I'm good with that. She knows what we need. How about you, Al and Ben? Is this the same as last year? Yeah, you might have had it behind McGlynn or something. Yeah, that's where this one is.
OK, so that's it's the same location. Yeah, I guess they're kind of like using this to kind of like celebrate the you know, the new like park and stuff that they did back there too. So yeah, trying to roll all that in together. Yeah, yeah, no, that's good. That's good. OK, I don't have any questions then. That was that sounded like, you know, a good event. Pretty, you know, mild, safe event and didn't no concerns on my end.
Yeah, I'm, I'm fine with this. It's a reoccurring events. I'm good. All right. Well, if you guys are good, if one of these would like to make a motion, Alan, would you like to show up? Sure. I, I motion to accept the one day license, uh, the deep cuts for the event taking place behind the McGlynn school. Can you say the date? Oh,
What's the date? Throw in the date. Dario, put in the date. I think it's October 19th. 19th? Yeah. We'll add the date, October 19th in there. Okay. I second that motion. Okay. All those in favor? Aye. Aye. Aye. All those opposed?
Hearing and seeing none, the ayes have it. Motion passes. You're all set. Good to go. Awesome. Thanks, everybody. No rain. No rain. Good luck, John. Great. Thanks. OK. Next item on the agenda. Mary Queen of Peace Parish. We're looking for Emily Jones and maybe Elaine Rapucci.
Speed dating with alcohol, you know. Yeah, for Mary Queen's Parish. That sounds a little funky. Sorry, my microphone was muted. I apologize. Can you hear me okay?
I can now. Yes. OK. Perfect. So, yeah, I'm here. I'm going to speak for both of them because the girl that is running the speed dating is a teacher and so she can't step away from her class right now. So I told her last night that I would do it for her. OK, that's fine. Well, tell us a little bit about what's going on. I know it's in two separate locations. Yeah. St. Paul and St. Francis kind of like share the parishes or
Yes, so Mary Queen of Peace is both parishes, so St. Francis and St. Joseph together under one nonprofit ID number and everything. And so I'll actually start with the fall festival. So that's on the 28th, September 28th, following 4 p.m. Mass. So it's going to be starting around 5. And this is the same event that we've done for a very long time.
But this year we wanted to add a small bar with some donated beer, wine. We had some, I think Tito's donated some vodka. So we wanted to have a little bar with just light drinks for the adults in the room because it is very kid friendly. There's activities upstairs in the gym, but downstairs a lot of the adults congregate together and spend time. So we wanted to do something nice for them.
And so the bar will be located near the food, which will be in the cafeteria, which is downstairs. I don't know if you guys have been in that space before, but there's like a kitchen in the back. And so the food will be right in front of there. And then the bar will be next to the food. And I think that's pretty much it. Is there any other questions or things you're wondering about that event? Yeah, there's a couple.
I do have a insurance binder for the evidence of insurance for young adults, group speed dating event. That's the one at High Street. I don't see one for the San Francisco location. Okay. I'll have her, she has it. Maybe I might have forgotten to forward it to Daria, so let me do that today.
Okay, and the other thing is I don't see any sketches. It's something that, you know, we require, but... Did I not forward that to you, Daria? I'm sorry if I didn't. I thought I did. My apologies. You did reference you have a sketch, so... Yeah, I know she did. I think because she gave it to me like two months ago, I may have forgotten to forward it to Daria. So I will forward you the sketch, yes.
Okay, good. That sounds good. And now, also, we're still talking about the Felsway, right? St. Francis? So, fall festival is going to be on High Street at the St. Joseph area. That should be 114, I think.
921, I thought. No, 928 isn't the festival of 28? The fall festival of 28? That's the fall festival, yeah. I'm talking about the address, 114. Oh, okay.
Yes, that's 114 High Street. The only other question I had on that application with the hours of the event, you put down three, but the actual hours from what time to what time is what we- Are you looking at the fall festival one? Because I put down five to 10, I'm almost positive. I'm looking at the-
other one, I believe. Yeah, the fall festival, you do have five to 10. Okay, great. Yeah. So I don't, I mean, I can't imagine it will go till 10. But, um, I just put, you know, five to 10, just in case, typically, it usually runs between three to four hours is the typical runtime for our events. Okay. So the speed dating, what time is that starting?
Um, but me, um, whatever she put on the application, I'm sure is correct. So she didn't. Everybody will have three, but I don't think it has an end time. Yeah. He said that check-in is from five 30 to six. Okay. And then it's three hours from six o'clock. Yes. Okay. So six to nine, basically five 30 to nine.
OK. And this is the one that will be at the parish center at St. Francis? Yes. OK, great. And it'll be in the cafeteria. And she forwarded a sketch. I just want to make sure you receive that, Daria.
Yeah, I actually don't have sketch this one. I have the liability as well as the certificate of exemption, but I don't have the sketch. Okay, so I have it, so I'll send it to you. Okay.
Okay. So speed dating sketch. Um, and then just to read you the other information from this event. So you have it, um, it'll just be canned drinks. So they're not like making anything. Um, they're serving them an hour after the speed dating for people that just want to spend time and they're limiting participants to two drinks. So they're giving them two tickets when they get in. Um, and then they're checking IDs at the door and everyone should be checked in by six o'clock.
Okay, and okay, I understand both of them. My fellow commissioners, any questions on both? No, I'm good with both, but if, so we need two, one sketch and two liability or two sketches and one liability? And one liability. Can you just double confirm with me that the insurance that you have on hand is for the speed dating?
The date on beads 921. I just want to double check. It's for 114 high street and it is. Yes, at least to your date. So that's probably mine. That's probably for the 28th. That's probably for the fall festival.
I can double check with Laura at the church and just tell her to send me both and I'll just send you both. That way you have everything and then I'll send you both sketches, both insurances in one year. Yeah, it looks like you need both sketches and we'll have one insurance for a dating event, but not for the fall festival. So I think it's two sketches and one liability for 9-28.
Yeah, this liability does say group speed dating event, so it's for that one. Cool. So I'll send all that in one email just to make sure I got it all to you. Okay. And Ben, are you okay with this? Yeah, I'm good. I'm good. Okay. If one of you guys want to make a motion, we can either accept the both of them at once, or if you want to do it separate, that's up to you, whatever's easiest.
I can just make sure. Commissioner, I can make 2 motions motions here. Okay. Okay. So, the 1st, 1 is I'll make a motion to accept the 1 day license for the September 21st. Event at.
St. Francis and the Felsway, the speed dating event as proposed, subject to clarification on the hours of the operation and a sketch of a plan of what is happening. Okay. Very good. I'll second that motion. Thank you, Ben. Hi.
All those opposed hearing and seeing none guys have it motions passed now we can do the 2nd, 1. Okay, I will make a motion to approve the 1 day license for the September 28 event, which is the fall festival community gathering. Located at St Joseph's on high street.
as proposed here by Elaine, subject to us receiving the one-day license insurance and a sketch of the event. Very good. I second that. Ben, thank you. I second that motion. Okay. All those in favor, aye. Aye.
All those opposed? Hearing and seeing none, the ayes have it, motion passes. Okay, you're all set, Ms. Rappucci. Just get those documents over as soon as Davria receives them. Fabulous. Good luck. Awesome. Thank you guys so much. Good luck. Have a great day. Take care. Okay. Okay, do we have a representative here from Tufts?
I did see Eric. There's Eric, yeah. Hi, Eric. Eric Hamel, associate director of catering at Tufts University, along with Tamara Kenny, will be our manager of record. On behalf of the trustees of Tufts College, we're seeking two one-day licenses in October. First date is October 5th. It's titled University Senior Oktoberfest Events.
We are scheduled to service an event from 4 to 7 p.m. on the 5th, right in the middle of the campus, outside event in a fenced-in area exclusively for seniors. TUPD will be running, Tufts University Police will be running our security. The Sausage Guy will be providing food for this event.
We are running a beer and wine bar with an Oktoberfest theme. We held this event last year. It was the first of this, our second annual event. It went okay. I think we scheduled for 700 guests, students, and we only got about probably 400, so we lowered our bartender amounts here. All the bartenders will be ServSafe and TIPS certified, and we'll have a management onsite as well.
Okay. All right, that's great. And you also are doing another event too, correct? Yeah, yeah. Okay, so the second event is scheduled for October 13th. We have to update the address. We gave you the wrong address. Location is going to be at our Joyce Cummings Center.
which is located at 177 College Avenue. So we have a wedding. One of our staff members here, one of our directors of our music center, Jeff Rawich, and his fiancee. This is wedding scheduled from 6 to 9.30 PM. We expect 200 guests. This will be a full bar application that we're looking for. What can I share here? So we have, it's gonna be on Sunday night.
of October of Columbus Day weekend. So we expect very, we don't expect too many students to be on campus. It's going to be happening in the atrium of the Joyce Cummings Center.
one-hour cocktail party, and then they move into dinner. So we've submitted those diagrams. Let me know if you need those blown up or any kind of square footage. I just noticed that information is not on the diagram. Again, we'll have Tufts University Police will be our security for the event. We'll have upwards to four bartenders working this event, and Tufts Catering is servicing all the food for the buffets, the reception, desserts.
Okay, I had noticed on the sketch that you did a pretty nice job with it. And I did notice the, when you said the Cummings Center, that it was probably the one on College Ave, but glad you brought it back to our attention. I see a kid's drink station, but I don't see,
Adult rank station, I guess. I'm assuming by number 180, is that the table where it's going to be? No, actually, the bar is going to stay out on the atrium. So on that, there should be the atrium. You should have two diagrams for that. Yes, I do. Okay. I couldn't read.
Right. Yeah. Excuse me. Are you referring to the wedding celebration or the October facade? Which one are you referring to? The wedding. The wedding. Okay.
Yeah, there's 2 sketches there. 1 of them is just the atrium area. From what I understand now, it's going to be where the liquor is going to be served. And the other sketch is, I guess, inside now, where the wedding is actually going to be. Right, in the ballrooms.
Let's see, 180, entertainment. Is there going to be entertainment at both or just 1? I believe it's DJ for both.
Okay, just so you're aware, Daryl has got a new one day license online that you can just log on and we've changed a couple of questions in a minute. One of them is asking for entertainment. That's the only reason why I'm asking. Oh, okay. So if you can just, if there's no entertainment, just NA or whatever. Okay.
Yeah, it just may streamline things a little bit. Okay, I'm sorry, I didn't mean to interrupt. I just wanted to run that by you while Alan was looking over the plans there. I know Tufts, you always have your insurance on file and stuff with us, so you're good with that. We never have any issues with any events that you folks run. You do a real good job.
So, I mean, I don't have a problem with it either. The 1 of my fellow commission is Alan. Have you had a chance to review it? I have I'm fine with both Ben. How about yourself? I'd be happy to make a motion to. For each item yeah, please make the motion. I have no issues.
All right, let's start with October 5th. I motion to approve the one-day license to be held on October 5th, Tufts University's senior Oktoberfest event, not to compete with the Medford Chamber Oktoberfest, to be held on October 5th between the hours of 4 to 7 p.m. I second that motion.
All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Hearing and seeing none, the ayes have it, motion passes.
Okay, and then we have the one day license for October 13th, the wedding celebration for Tufts employee, which is very nice. That's a that Eric, that's a beautiful venue up there. The Cummins building brand new. You got to love that location for the hours of event at 6 to 930 PM. At Tufts University.
Yeah, sounds good. I'll second that. Okay. All those in favor? Aye. Aye. Aye. All those opposed? Hearing and seeing none, the ayes have it, and the motion passes. Thank you. You are well set. Good luck. See you soon. Good luck, Eric. Thank you. Bobby, just one more one-day license for the chamber.
For the chamber, that's correct. Let's see, hang on one second. Chamber, Tina Caruso, is Tina here? Hi, Tina, how are you? Good, how are you? Good, thank you. Why don't you tell us a little bit about what's going on, Tina? I know it's an Oktoberfest and you can give us a little bit of information.
Sure. We've been doing this for the past five years. It's a bunch of vendors from the city of Medford and a lot of nonprofits, a lot of for-profits, and we invite the rec, we invite the city, we invite food vendors, and also we have two bands playing.
We have a lot of martial arts, dance schools, a lot of fun. One of the bands is a Hofstra band, so they play that wonderful German music. And we have a beer garden, of course.
And, um, it's just a lot of fun. It's a lot of family entertainment. The fire station brings the smokehouse and people are just some people dress up and wear their, um,
Liedenhosen and all of that fun stuff and just walk around and have a good time. But it's a great time for the people to get together and see their neighbors and have conversations. And honestly, we get a lot of people. It started out as
maybe a couple hundred here and there. And I really think it's grown to maybe a thousand or so passing through and coming from outside of Medford to see what's going on. So it's a lot of good stuff. We've never had a problem and it's well contained, well maintained. And we were asking for a one day license and it's beer and wine.
There's no hard alcohol. Okay. Yep. Very good. Yeah, I went over it and the sketch as well. I do see the beer sales are going to be on River Street. Is that going to be the only station? I know there was a question, possibly two. But if that's the only one that I see, which is fine, it's very containable there.
Correct. And that is, it's only one. Okay. Laura, did that change? No, there is only one station, but since we have the two stages, we were having a flow. Yeah, the entire enclosed area be for consumption. Okay. Yeah, everything looks good, Gary. I know that
believe you have the insurance on file or is that something we need to get? For Chamber of Commerce, I think I would need one, just an updated one, and I know they're for a non-profit.
Yeah, so if you can just get that over to Daria, we can, we'll see how Alan and Ben feel about this, and they can make a motion to grant the licenses contingent upon your insurance paper. Yeah, it's just quite, Tina, River Street, is it blocked off at both ends?
So it is blocked off on the end of where Salem Street is so that the traffic cannot come down. OK. And Riverside is blocked off where Metro and Citizens Bank are. Yeah. And the other end near Harvard Vanguard. Yep.
Thank you. No, I don't have any questions. It's a nice event. I just hope it doesn't rain October 5th. I'm not, not that I'm putting a crest on it or anything, but I'm good with it. Quick questions. Um, does it have police support, police detail? Yes, we do. Yes, we do. Okay. Okay. That's good. Um, and then who is there a brewery doing the beer dispensing or.
Medford Brewing is doing this dispensing last year with their first year, and they did a great job. They seem to do a great job, so that's good to hear. So I have no other questions, then. I think that sounds like a good event. I can make a motion, Commissioner and Mr. Chairman. Sure. OK.
Great, so I'll make a motion to accept the one day license for October 5th, 24. This is for the Medford Chamber of Commerce. This is for the community event, the October Fest, with a rain date of 10-6, if Alan jinxed us.
Hours of event, noon to six, and no further questions. The event is as advertised as well as the plan that they've submitted to us. Very good. I second the motion. Okay. All those in favor? Aye. Aye. All those opposed?
Hearing and seeing none, the ayes have it. The motion is passed. Tina, is this five years, three years? How many years is this? I want to say this is our fifth or sixth year. Okay. Yeah. I thought it was getting up there. Good. Thank you. Good luck with it. Best of luck. Laura works her butt off, huh, Laura? We thank you guys all for your help. Thank you. Sounds good. Thank you, guys.
Nice job, ladies. I want to go. I want to go this year. Yeah, sounds fine. I do see. Brian, are you there? I'm here, can you hear me?
Yes, I can. I can. We were looking for you earlier. We had you at the top of the list. I'm sorry. I was honestly trapped in an elevator. Everett fired to get there and get me out. It was brutal. Oh, wow.
Is that real, Brian? Is that like my dog ate my homework? No, I wish. It was brutal. It was about 48 minutes. It wasn't funny. That's probably one of the best excuses we've heard yet. I'm glad Daria's recording this. Yeah, yeah. I can have him give me a call. Now, I got connections over there. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Anyways.
Yes, basically tell us a little bit about what's been happening. Brian, you know, where you're at, you know, as far as the partial goes, and what stages you're at, as well as, you know, we'll talk about that first, and then we can talk about the entertainment license on a separate thing. Sure, yeah, so as far as the partial goes, the street work is almost wrapped up for DOT.
But that really has not much to do with the building. The building is the elevator. So we're waiting for the elevator inspection by the state. We have paid the 2,500 to have it expedited, but I still don't have a date. So as soon as that happens, I will have final sign off from the commissioner. I would like to think it's going to be the end of this month. September 28th has been our goal the entire time.
If we're going to hit that, I'd say 75% yes, 25% no. If not, then it's the week after that. So I know we're really, really close to getting the building all wrapped up as well as the street work. How it's been going, it's been great. I mean, the turnout from the city has been excellent. We're getting bombarded with private requests. We've had wedding requests. We've had all sorts of people requesting just to have their Christmas parties there, weddings there.
Really exciting, really fun to see. I think the smartest thing we did was get the private security company, Commonwealth Security. They check everyone at the door. So everyone's ID is checked. You have to have a wristband or a stamp to get in to drink in there. So it's been really nice seeing the turnout.
That statement is 100% true because last night I was out with my daughter and the first time I drove by the place that I could find a parking space in there and we decided to go in for a refreshment and something to eat. The security asked me for an ID and I asked them back, do you need glasses, buddy?
And he says, no, our policy. Sorry, sir. They show my ID, stamp my hand. And I tell you, I was very, very impressed by that, which was great. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Yeah. And like I said, everything was good. So yeah, I'm sorry. I didn't mean to interrupt you. It's just when you brought it up, I wanted to.
No, no, no. Thank you. Thank you. Yeah. Yeah. That was the smartest thing we did and they've been excellent. Um, we really, it's really been happy crowds, a lot of families. Um, so it will be nice to get the second floor open cause we are going to be 21 plus up there. It's just nice to kind of have adults enjoy a section and get away from the kids.
Right right and now is that um something that's going to be in the near future or is it just the elevator because i noticed that you had an upstairs patio as well so everything everything else is ready to go the siding is all there i didn't want to put that up and have anyone go up there to think it's going to be okay to go up there as the building commissioner was like if there's anyone up here we're shutting you down so
Until we get that elevator inspection sign off the 1 kind of unknown of the rest of this is that's when the other stuff is very easy. We've got the stairs report. Everything else is really, really quick and easy. That's the 1 thing that I'm waiting on.
Okay. Well, you know, as we've told you before in the past, that if things progress, we would appreciate this coming monthly. Okay. Absolutely. Yeah. Yeah. And in that way there, once we get to the final thing, full occupancy, we don't have to see it for another year. Okay. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Absolutely.
The okay, great that is all I wanted to touch base with you on you. You guys said the other commission is you have any questions for Brian at this point?
No, no, I'm good. I'm glad it's progressing. I hear nothing but great stuff, Brian, about the place. Thank you. I'm not surprised. It's a nice venue, so I'm not surprised that you're getting all sorts of fun requests. That's very good.
It's been awesome. Yeah. Yeah. It's everything the three of you wanted in the city. So, yes. So, is it safe to say that we're in the stretch? You anticipate the elevated pass and inspection? I do. The next 10 days or 60 days? 30 days. I mean, I can't imagine I'd be here at the end of October saying we're still in the same spot, but no, I do. Again, I'm really hopeful for September 28th, but if it's not then, it's the weekend. It's the week after. Okay.
So that's all ready to go. You're just waiting for an inspector to inspect it. Yes, exactly. Yes. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. OK. Now, great. I'm I'm good. Thank you. Thank you for the update. Thank you for coming. Yeah. Thanks. Thanks.
Ben? No, the update sounds great to me. Yeah. I hear nothing but good things about it as well, especially about the security. Yeah. People mentioned that, and that sounds really good that you did that. Yeah. No. No, Mr. Commissioner, so it's just the entertainment license part here. Is this going to sort of cover things that are
This will cover things that are yet to still be opened at the place, which Brian is just telling us about, which is like the second floor patio, etc., right? Yeah. Well, I would imagine the entertainment, it's pretty much what you listed here, and that's pretty much what I saw.
I mean, when I was in there last night, but obviously there were no stages and no performances or anything. So, Brian, if you could tell us a little bit about what you plan on doing with the performers, the patrons and the devices. Yeah.
So Friday nights, we're looking at a DJ from 8 to 11. On Saturdays, we're looking at live music bands from 9 to 12 or 8 to 11. During the day, we were actually thinking about more of like an acoustic during the day, but it's just we need the room. It gets filled in there pretty quickly.
And so that's really what we're doing. We're showing the TVs, those two big screen TVs, Patriots games. We put the noise on for that. Everything else is just background music. Okay.
Um, and then, um, the performers and stuff like that, that's all going to be contained indoors, correct? Yes. Indoors. Yes. Yes. And it's, you said outside, I think just maybe some acoustical, uh, entertainment or whatever. Yeah, we were, we were thinking about, I don't think we're going to do that. Uh, just that the space too valuable as is. Okay. Up the room.
All right, and I noticed too that you had, what was it here? Total number of devices located on the premise 31. You're counting each speaker and stuff. The sound system counts as one versus.
Well, no, the only reason being is because they charge you for every 10, right? So it's got it for every 10. So it is. That's 100 bucks just in speakers. Mr. Chairman, why did you bring that up? You know, I know the city needs the money, right? That area.
But anyways, yeah, so yeah, it's just gonna be, from what I can read, it's just a regular, the $300, it's, you're not gonna be going crazy with all those devices, but yeah, I don't have an issue with it. I looked at the drawing, it was a little difficult for me to see it. I mean, I've got a laser printer and I still couldn't make,
make out what some of the stuff was, but you stated that where it was outlined in black, that was the area that the stages and stuff were going to be. So being in there just last night, it looked very familiar to me and I could visualize what was going where. Up against that, yeah, the green wall all the way to the left underneath the TV. I can do a better job of outlining it.
And then there was 1, right in the middle. It almost looks like where the main entrances that was we're not going to do that. Yeah, we're not doing any. No, no. Okay. All right. Yeah. I mean, I, I, I don't have an issue with it. You know, like, like, I had said, they.
You're doing a nice job over there. I'm very pleased. Alan, Ben, you have any questions on the end? No, no. No, I'm good. No, that cleared it up for me. Thank you. That's great. All right, awesome. Why don't you guys want to make a motion and we'll pass that entertainment license?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So, just just to clear it up, Mr Mr commissioner, we're going to do Mr chair. Sorry. We're going to do. Yeah, 1 entertainment performers patrons and then 1 devices. But that seems yeah, it should be 1 of each. I think. Yeah. Okay.
Okay, so I'll make a motion to accept the application by Great American Beer Hall for the entertainment license for as they appear on this application here, all city
Departments have signed off on this application here. And we are approving the entertainment as provided by Ryan and Great American Beer Hall. Yeah, for the three different, entertainment by performers, entertainment by patrons, and entertainment by devices.
Very good. Good. Yeah. Thank you, Ben. I second that motion. Okay. All those in favor? Aye. Aye. Ayes have it. All those opposed? Hearing and seeing none. Ayes have it. Motion's passed. You're all set, Brian. Thank you. Thank you. I'll see you on the next one. Take care. Thank you. Thanks.
Okay, next on the agenda. Let's see. We've got EST 2024 TBA, the establishment. Is Matthew Greer here? Yes. Good morning, members of the commission. My name is Sean Began. I'm the attorney representing the LLC. Matthew Greer is also on with us as well. Okay.
Very good. Either Sean or Matthew, you want to tell us a little something about what's going on and what your plans are? Sure. Thank you. So essentially, Mr. Greer is going to be taking over the location that was formerly occupied by the Porch Restaurant, if your members are familiar where that is, over at 175 Rivers Edge.
That restaurant is closed and essentially Mr. Greer is stepping into what is a turnkey operation where the landlord now owns all the fixtures, equipment, and furniture within that space and Mr. Greer will be renting the space including all of the furniture, fixtures, equipment that are included therein.
Mr. Greer has approximately two decades worth of restaurant experience. He's managed and operated restaurants throughout the North Shore. He has another current restaurant in Chelmsford, which is a little bit larger occupancy than this one.
although this one is pretty good size as well. 8,000. 8,000. It's larger than 8,000 when in Chelmsford? I'm sorry, Attorney Began. Sure. I'm not sure if the Chelmsford restaurant is larger than 8,000, Matt. Matt, if you could unmute, you can offer a
Yeah. Hi, my name is Matthew Brer. I currently run the establishment restaurant in North Chelmsford. I'm looking to move into the space in Medford. The current footprint is about 15,000 square feet. We have a large restaurant and then we offer four function rooms at our current location.
Okay. Nice. This restaurant, the restaurant that Mr. Greer will be opening at The Porch, it's not going to be an entertainment venue like The Porch was. The Porch was a music venue with restaurant. This is not going to be that focused in that manner. This is going to be more of a traditional sit-down restaurant using the same footprint and using the same layout.
but it won't have the bands and things of that nature that the porch was focused on.
I think this is a great opportunity for Mr. Greer. I think it's a good opportunity for the city of Medford to get what is now a vacant space reoccupied with someone who brings a couple decades worth of experience and who, based on past history, his track record, is going to be able to get this place running and operating as it should.
have another venue in an area of Medford that doesn't have too many restaurants along that particular area. And I know there are a lot of people living in the apartments over there who I'm sure would appreciate something like this.
Is it going to be the same type of food there or is it what type of food they're going to be serving? Matt, do you want to address the menu? Yeah. Yeah, sure. It'll be the same menu. We'll roll out with the same menu we currently use in in North Chelmsford. But it's, you know, primary pizza, steak tips, haddock. It's it's it's American fare.
So it's not like a barbecue place like the other one was, smoker and all that stuff. No, you know, well, it's got a beautiful smoker in there. So we'll we'll offer some smoked items. But no, it's it's a more broad menu. And I think in a in a footprint that big, I think that may have been one of the one of the downfalls there in terms that I took over. It was just an Italian restaurant and they just couldn't fill the space with
So I think that'll be our big advantage, is offering the menu that we offer. Yeah, you know, Mr. Gray, you're right. Now, looking backwards, maybe they were very specific with Memphis-style barbecue. So maybe they kind of limit themselves right at the beginning. Because how many times can you keep going back? Right, right, right, right. Yep.
I've gone through the 108 pages. No problem with the tenants? I guess I see everyone had been reached. Any problems getting the surrounding tenants to be okay with it? Any complaints on them? No. No objections from- No objections. Good. Good.
And just help me understand, I'm looking, I see the LLC established 2024 LLC, I see the managers, just kind of help me understand, is Laura Gerrick Cohen and Dawn Zanazzo, are they your sisters?
Yes, yep. Okay, all right. You got it, yeah. It's a family, family. Me and my two sisters decided to do this first venture in Chelmsford. It was actually seven years ago we opened up yesterday in North Chelmsford and it's just been, you know, it's been a blast, hugely successful. So yeah, it's the three of us and my brother-in-law, Ron, is also on. And your brother-in-law. Yes, yep.
And so I got a big team that's gonna help us out. So I'll be spending a lot of time in Medford, at least 40 hours a week, probably more to get this up and running.
Yeah, yeah. I'm very impressed. Attorney Began's correct over 20 years in the industry. So you've seen it all. And now that you're in your mid-50s, you've probably seen everything imaginable. So I applaud your tenacity and staying with it. And we thank you for coming into that space because your attorney's correct. That when the court started,
Fading, that was huge. Who's going to step in there and give that whole area a shot? Now that the casino's up and running, as we know, everyone goes someplace first and then they go over to the casino. Hopefully, as you get going, that'll be a pre-stop or a pre-casino stop at your establishment.
Yeah, and I just wanted to note that Mr. Greer's history of running restaurants, he hasn't had any disciplinary action in all those years. So I think the city's getting a very good restaurateur, a good business person. No, you're absolutely right, Attorney Began. That's a good point to bring out, because we look back at it, and we saw no infractions, no brawls. So this is very good. You run a tight ship. Kudos.
Thank you, thank you. So I just had a quick question. So the restaurant in Chelmsford, what is the restaurant you have in Chelmsford? It's called The Establishment. It's also The Establishment. And this will also be called The Establishment. This will be called The Establishment as well for advertising purposes and tying them together. And our website is eatestablishment.com if anybody wants to check it out. There's photos and our full menu and everything on there.
Yeah, cool, cool. And then just something I thought was interesting, I did go through this whole lease and everything. And so it looked like the lease was subject to getting the liquor license approved and that it would start or the lease would start four months after the liquor license was approved. Correct.
their focus is getting a successful restaurant in there. And they really liked what I had to offer. So they made the lease very, very friendly for me. Okay, yeah, yeah, great. Were you able to open it up even prior to that? Is that what the- That's what I was gonna say, yeah. He'll be able to get in there. It's just kind of an incentive to give him four months to kind of start up before rent payment. Got it.
So you can start, but that was just a term in the lease. I mean, I'm sort of familiar with commercial leases where if there's a build-out or something that has to happen, they're going to give some free part of it or something like that. Okay. Give them a little runway. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That's a better way to say it. And then I thought it was interesting. So then the US Foods, is that an existing vendor you have a relationship with, US Foods? Is that sort of why that?
It is. It is. Several months ago, I expanded the space in North Chelmsford. So we had two function rooms. We took over some, we're in a big mill building there. We took over some space there. So now we have four function rooms. We can do functions up to 150 people now.
So when I did that, when I started that project, U.S. Food did an agreement with me there to get the funding for there. And I've been with U.S. Food for a long time. So we just got a great partnership. So basically they gave me the funds to open up the restaurant with a commitment for purchases for three years.
years going forward with US Foods. That's kind of what we figured because you must have had a good track record with them for them to extend that line of credit. And without any pledge of the license or anything like that. So again, that speaks to your experience and your time in the industry. Yes. Thank you.
I had to ask him twice just to make sure it was a real thing. Yeah, more for them like they were, you know, the usual thing you see. Oh, great. Yeah. Yeah. So, um,
Well, no, I mean, I would just say I'm glad, I'm glad, you know, I'm glad a quality restaurant is going in there. I mean, that space is more or less new, you know. It was just built out right before COVID. I know the builders who did it and, you know, it's a quality space and seems like a good opportunity. And yeah, yeah, I was surprised that they, you know, a brand new place like that, they actually went out of business. So I, you know,
But you know more about that than we do oh yeah, and then one other thing was I was also good glad to see that there's like You know there's the there's the whole agreement between the condominium association, and you know and that and I'm just say Noise or anything like that and you know that's sort of a you just want to kind of abide by that with the condominium whatever their rules are about I Don't know No, I you know anything like that you're
In the past, some complaints from the porch had come to us, and I actually think that that was more between them and the condo than it was the liquor board. So I guess I'm only saying that as a heads up, maybe, on any questions they ever have about noise.
build a relationship with them. Yeah. I think one of the differences here is where the porters bring in bands, that's not going to be the issue here. Yeah, good point. Yeah. Mr. Greer is going to have TVs, he's got an audio system obviously, but it's going to be, I think, a tamer environment in terms of noise for the other unit owners. You're right, whatever the rules of the condo are is what all the unit owners have to abide by, but I don't think he's going to have any issue there.
Sure. Sure. Yes. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Now, the package that was submitted to us, I don't think, was it the lease that wasn't signed? I'm sure the package that goes to the state will have signatures on all the contracts and everything, correct? Yesterday, I emailed over to Daria the signed copy of the lease. Okay. We do have it.
uh, because some parties were traveling. I couldn't get it till I got to sign coffee. Yeah, good catch. Okay. Okay. I'm good, Mr Chairman. Same here. All right. Very good. I have a few questions. Um, the
The U.S. Foods gave you the $80,000 line of credit on page 4, number 8 and number 9.
Number eight, financial disclosure. The question, source of financing, is the lender a licensee pursuant to MGL 138? You did not check off yes or no.
That needs to be checked off. I believe it's just to make sure they don't hold the license in the state of Massachusetts. Yeah, I'll check. I can check that off and submit that page, resubmit that page.
Okay. The other thing on that same page, number nine, pledge information. Are you seeking approval for a pledge? It's got to be checked. Yes or no. So please check. No. That's no.
And we did those 2 page 10, I see number 11 made a note of management agreement. Are you requesting approval user utilize a management company through a management agreement? I don't think you are. I think you manage your own property. So you'd have to check. No, and that as well. Please sure.
The other thing I saw was pages 73 through 79, which was exhibit A, B, and C. They don't show anything to me. I mean, it looks like a bunch of lines. Nothing says if it's parking, if it's seeding, if it's...
They're just drawings. What I did see was on page 33, it shows me the layout of the restaurant, and I was familiar with it because I've patronized it a few times in the past, so I could figure it out. But on A, B, and C,
I don't know, I couldn't make heads or tails of it. Those exhibits A, B, and C are A, B, and C of the lease agreement. The plan, and I agree with you, they're not entirely helpful, but they were attached to the lease as it came over from the landlord, but the plan,
that you referenced earlier that's on page 33 is a schematic of the layout which shows specifically where the seating is, where everything is within the restaurant and has all the capacity numbers that I think the commission needs. Correct.
Yeah, I agree with you. One of those exhibits, I think, was to show parking. I think that's like under the building packing. That must be all the spaces, because there's a bunch of them. A parking garage, yes. Yeah, exactly. But that was specific to the lease itself and not necessarily this application. OK. And I think it was page 79.
I'm familiar with the area and the building and I just wanted to, it was before it used to be known as 150 Rivers Edge, but I know they've changed things since they're up to 600 or even higher for numbers at Rivers Edge. But is there still parking available under the restaurant itself in that building?
Uh, in terms of for, um. Customers yes. Yeah. Okay. I was just wondering, uh, because I, I did read something about parking, but I just want to make sure that was still available that they didn't close it off or anything for restaurant patrons.
Those were the only questions I had, but I did want to ask you about something else. I know you sent in a last-minute file to Daria. It was given to her yesterday, and I'm grateful that you did it because it needed the signatures with the lease agreement and everything else.
But from what I understand too, there was some additional postal receipts that came in and things like that. What I'm going to suggest to my fellow commissioners is if either yourself as the attorney or the Mr. Greer can put everything
on an electronic file, a PDF or whatever, and scan everything and put it on the file and send it to Daria. Because Daria can't keep pulling apart your files to try and insert stuff and take stuff out and everything else. We need a final application with all of your signed leases and all of your little individual
Mail receipts all scheduled and all scanned in along with the hard copies you're required to submit and just send it to Daria. So we can we can approve this. You know, not a problem with the contingency that we received those.
You know, that type of 5 electronic file, and I'd paper copy file. So, I mean, we can conditionally approve it. It's just that.
In Daria's defense, she doesn't have enough time in a day to do what we ask her to do, never mind putting everybody else's cut and paste and trying to do it for us. So we just want to kind of streamline things, make things a little easier. And it's an electronic file. We have it. Everybody can look at it. Perfect.
Yep, no problem. We can have that by tomorrow morning. That's not a problem for my office at all. On the record, I just want to say Daria has been tremendously helpful in this process and extremely responsive if I've had a question or an inquiry.
Yeah, she is, and that's why we don't want to make her life and her job more difficult, because like I said, and you said, she's been extraordinary. She does great work, and we just don't want to put any undue work on her back. Sure.
Uh, so, yeah, that'll be good. And if any commissioners would, uh, are okay with that and like, let me make a motion. Yeah, no, we can additionally approve it. Yeah, no, no, I, I motion to.
to approve and move forward with the new license request for establishment 2024 LLC conditioned upon a complete and organized package for the city's records and of course ABCC's review. Thank you. And one question before I approve, I second that.
Mr. Chairman, there's the entertainment license also to go with this. Is that something we'll separately talk about? Yeah, we could do that separate if you like, Ben. That way we don't. I mean, if you want to tie it, that's fine too, but yeah. Well, I mean, I have reviewed it and sort of like the last one we looked at, all the signatures are there and.
Yeah, I reviewed it too. It's fine with me. Yeah, so you can tie it into both if you want to add that on to your motion, Alan. Yeah, yeah, no, I'll amend my motion. Let me add, I approve the entertainment requests for the three categories, I believe, for establishment 2024 LLC.
Um, and I second the motion both for the, uh, new license application and for the entertainment license application for establish, um, for the establishment, um, All righty. All those in favor. Aye. Aye. Opposed.
And seeing none, the ayes have it. Congratulations. It's an exciting project. We hope to swing by soon. Thank you all very much. I look forward to becoming part of a community in Medford and working with all the organizations in Medford, especially the youth organizations. So thank you very much.
Yeah, thank you. Thanks. Thank you. Last thing. Maybe I'll just say we'll see more of each other as time goes. So if you ever have questions, just being new, just please ask us. And it's always good. You can always jump in on a meeting every month if there are questions or anything's coming up as just being new to this. So we're here to help. Thank you. I appreciate that.
Mr. Chairman, would Mr. Greer benefit from the compliance meeting coming up? Yeah, you're more than welcome to come, Mr. Greer. We have an annual ABCC compliance meeting for all licensees in the state of Massachusetts, but Medford does their own. We have Ralph Sacramone from the ABCCs, the executive director, he comes and brings
some people with them to basically explain the easy way to navigate through their site and what is expected of the licensees. We're going to have the fire chief there. He'll speak for five minutes about the fire inspection and the building commissioner for five minutes about the building inspection.
and all of that stuff, and it's about an hour, hour and a half. We're having it on the 25th this month. 10 a.m. 10 a.m., yeah. It's kind of a good, somewhat of a good time for restaurants, you know, to get them out of there by noon, 12.30, and you're all done, you know. So you're more than welcome to come. It might be beneficial to you. That sounds perfect. Mr. Grant, City Hall. Yeah. City Hall.
or send your number two person, please do. I would love to be there myself. Thank you so much. All righty. Yeah. Daria, you can send them out an invitation via email if you like. Just add them to the list, if you can do that. Yeah. The application, I think, has to have an email. So whatever that email is, I can- Yeah. Yeah. The one on the application. Yep. I have it. Yep. From that.
Perfect. We'll send you an invitation out via email. Thank you. All righty. Thank you very much. Mr. Blakowicz. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you very much. Okay. Lieutenant Blakowicz, are you there?
Did you leave? We made him wait a long time. I can see that he's still on it. Yeah, I can see him. He's muted. I see Officer Sadas and he's there. Yeah. And who else do we got? Officer Farrell? Yep, there she is.
Uh, where were you there? Yeah, I'm here just trying to figure out how to navigate. Okay, not a problem. I just want to make sure you were there. If you guys happen to be, I think the last one on the agenda, um, save the best for last, I guess. Absolutely. All right, let's see what we got. Um,
Okay, do we have a representative from Paso del Benefica? Is that? Yes. Good afternoon, how are you? Can you guys hear me? Yes. All right, great. Good afternoon.
Okay. Um, well, basically, the reason why, um, we have you in here, Mr Korea is that, um, there was an incident that occurred, um, your establishment and, um, on a 27 and it was brought to our attention and, um, the police responded. And, um, what we'll do is we'll have, um, Lieutenant Locker Woods and, um,
and the officers that responded. We're gonna give them the opportunity to tell us what happened and comment on the police reports and stuff. And then you'll have the opportunity to speak as well on your behalf. And we'll just hash it around a little from there and see what happens. Lieutenant Lockwoods, would you like to take over the meeting?
Yeah, I'm just going to, uh, give a hello and introduction. Rory Lockowitz, a Lieutenant with the Medford police, um, office fashion did the primary focus, uh, in addition to the police report that was written. Um, and with him was officer Farrow, who is, um, for any translation and, uh, a second set of eyes. So I'm just going to turn it over to officer Sebastian. Uh, if that's okay. Okay.
Sure. So I think my video, I'm able only to speak without video for some reason. I'm on my iPhone. I apologize. But so the original incident was a fight. I did not respond to the incident, but I was working that night. I did review the report and it seemed to be due to an intoxicated patron and member.
who was upset that another member was speaking to a spouse or a girlfriend, and then they engaged in a fight. I responded, I believe, on the 30th to do an inspection of the building and make sure they were in compliance.
Mr. Carrera and the other people in there were very receptive. They were very open. One of the first things they told me was that both club members have been banned. I spoke to them about a trespass to have it formally on record with not only them, but the police department, which would
bring it to a point where if these guests return they will be arrested and you know in my opinion would prevent them from returning. The restaurant when I entered had about 25 to 30 patrons.
None were overly intoxicated. None were intoxicated. The noise level was within reason. And like I said, everyone was receptive to even a police officer coming in in uniform. All signs were posted. All licenses were posted. A menu was posted. The bartenders were all in compliance. Officer Farrell was with me.
to the fact that she's fluent in Portuguese. We didn't need much translation, but they were very, like I said, open and receptive. I went behind the bar, checked everything. Everything was in compliance, very clean. The kitchen area was very clean. They walked me down to the stockroom area, showed me everything. Everything was very neat and organized.
I was actually very surprised in how organized and clean everything was. They showed me their camera system, told me that Mr. Carrera has access to it, and there's another manager who has access to it. They don't have any cameras downstairs, but have everything upstairs in the establishment that shows all the rooms.
The only thing that they didn't have that was on the checklist was an employee list, which I don't know how big of a deal that is, but they stated that they were going to have it with phone numbers and date of birth. I just explained to them that it would be easy and it's required.
you know, it would make it easier for police if there is an incident to speak to somebody, if we have to follow up and them being able to tell us who was there and how we can get in contact with them. And other than that, I mean, everything was good. I mean, yeah, that's all. Okay, very good. Thanks very much.
Um, Officer Farah, do you have anything you'd like to say in regards to this matter?
So I didn't really do the inspection. I was there mostly for translation and I kind of just explained to them how the inspection was going to happen and they were very open to that. And from there, Officer Sebastian took it over and he did the inspection and just stayed in front of the bar waiting. So that was about pretty much like that. I didn't respond to the day of the fight as well. So I was mostly there for the translation purposes.
Okay. Thank you. Thank you for commenting on it. Lieutenant, is there anything else you'd like to comment on? It seems like the initial incident, there was a question of whether or not somebody was too intoxicated. Of course, we have no way of knowing or proving
how much was consumed on the premise on the day of the fight. Obviously a concern when you hear somebody was in a highly intoxicated state on the premise where they served after the fact. It's a concern but not something we're bringing before the commission saying that it did in fact happen. What we know did in fact happen was that there was a
a mutual assault and battery, you know, a fight that happened. And as officers Sebastian and Farrow said, since then, they took action and appear to have done everything they could to help prevent this in the future. Okay. Well,
My fellow commissioners, do you have any questions or concerns about this incident? Mr. Chair, I do, but I'd like to hear from Mr. Carrera here.
what his take on it, but I do have some questions. Maybe I'll circle back after Mr. Carrera speaks. Good point. I'm sorry, I forgot to ask Mr. Carrera my apologies. Mr. Carrera, I'm sorry, would you like to comment on what you've heard so far or what might have happened that evening?
I would like to thank the police officers for coming over. I mean, make sure everything that it was up to, like compliance with the city of Manfred and everything like that. It's just that day on that was Tuesday, August 27th. That's when it happened. We can control many things, but we can't control people's emotions. What did happen that day? I think it was a discussion between
One guy's talking to another person's girlfriend. It's just childish things, but we can't control over that. Our bartenders are all tip certified. So therefore, if they were intoxicated, they cut them off. That's what I asked the bartender when I got there. It's like, how much did you serve them? She's like, I served them enough that when I cut them off, it was over. I told him, what did they drink? She said one drink.
three beers, the other one drink, I think it was like a shot and a beer and that was it. And I cut them off because the bar was about to close that night. And it just happened to happen as we're about to close because the person's girlfriend is actually our cook.
um she was like she was just leaving her shift going home and the other person approached her and started talking to him the other the other person did not like him talking to his girlfriend and so therefore they got into an altercation over over that i mean as they say they were extremely drunk i i don't think they were because like i said like our bartenders are tip certified
if they think that the person is too intoxicated to a certain point, like three beers, that should be like the cutoff line for them. Because one of them wasn't very big. I mean, it's just like stuff like that. I can't control over people's emotions. Like I said, both members are banned for life from the club.
The cook did quit because she didn't feel comfortable being there because of what happened. And that the only means that she had to go home is with her boyfriend. So therefore, I told her that he cannot be in the premises while picking her up. And she said, if that's going to be a problem, then I'm just going to have to quit. And she left last week.
That's all I got to say about this scenario. I'm sorry to hear about the troubles that you're going through there. All right, well, let's move on. We can discuss. Alan, you said you'd like to speak.
Yeah, no, Mr. Carrera, I appreciate the, you're absolutely right. You can't control people's emotions. I believe when I read through the police report, it said the individual fled. I'm curious, I've heard from the officers that there is no log
of employees with names and contact numbers and information. But I think the last time we spoke with you, we made it clear that clubs are required to have a book, and members are supposed to sign in. And if they're bringing in guests, they're supposed to be signing in the guests. So as I said, where I read in the police report that the individual fled,
Do you know who the individual that fled was? Because I'm certain Dean should have been in the book. I'm sorry to interrupt you, but both of them are members. I mean, they're newly members, so we do have information on them. We have the contacts, we have all the names and stuff like that. So if that needs to be pulled up, I can give that to the police officer or anything like that that is needed. The person that left, that fled,
I don't know why he fled. He may be having problems with the law or something like that. I have no idea. I don't know people's background. I only know their names and when they're made part of being a member. I mean, that's the only information they give me is their name and their phone number. Most of them don't like giving their licenses because they don't want people to do mischievous things with it. So that's why.
We don't get much information on them, but we do have their names and their phone numbers. So if that needs to be given to somebody, I will gladly get that information out. They were both new members, obviously. And like I said, like when they send a piece of paper saying to become a member, one of the things that says there is any altercations, fights or discriminations, like anything that's
like affecting the environment, the environment around us, it's an automatic ban. There is no like six months suspension. There's not one month suspension. It's an automatic ban because we can always get members again. And people that do that in their establishment, we do not like tolerate. So the dead sign a piece of paper saying that whatever happens in there, if they do whatever it says there on the piece of paper, they're automatically banned from the club for life. And the thing is, we keep these,
and a record because we do like a meeting every year of the people that's been banned from the club. Most of them have passed away. So we have to clear those out because they no longer want us. So there is a list of all the people that have been banned through the years to that club because they keep information of it.
And some of them have pictures, some of them don't. But like I said, these two individuals, they're fairly new, so we knew who they were. And like I said, they've been banned. They're no longer part of the club. They're no longer members. And if people start defending them or trying to say, why are you guys banning them, that person will get banned as well.
Because we don't tolerate defending people that just make a ruckus for no reason. I don't know what else to say. Yeah, no, no. Mr. Carrera, you kind of cut off all my other questions.
Because I was curious about that too, what the penalty was for the establishment. Was there some type of event going on? Was there a soccer game? Or was it just a normal night? It was just a normal night. Like I said, I left there two hours prior.
And I spoke with the bartender, I was like, listen, there's not many people here. So it's the club. It does. There's a set time for the club, but the club usually doesn't stay open until that time. That's that's written down. It's basically like on if the members show up there a certain time.
like just say that if there's three members like left on the club and it's seven o'clock it's just pretty much like just cut them off and close the bar there is no reason to stay open until 10 with nobody in there right so what happened was that night i think was somebody's birthday and they were like he was going back to his country so it was there was a little more people than usual so what i told was like uh try to close the bar by like
10 o'clock, like don't pass that time. And she's like, Oh, they'll probably be out of here by by like nine o'clock. And that's when the altercation happened was around like nine o'clock. As the bartender, I mean, as the cook was leaving, that's when the altercation happened. So
Like I said, I can't control people's emotions. I wish I could. If I was there, it would probably be a different scenario. People did not step in because, like I said, they don't want to get involved, which is a shame because there was one of our people from our committee there that couldn't separate them, but he did nothing. So that made me a little bit upset. And I spoke with him, and he said he was sorry.
I told them just next time make sure you try not to start stuff like that because it's childish. Thank you. I don't have any other questions, Mr. Chairman.
You know, the only question I had actually, I was just sort of curious, my ignorance might be why, but just on the police report is actually that Officer Sebastian wrote, it says at the end of it said, just the suggestion, it was saying that probable cause for an illegality to wit, is that anything that we need to sort of be,
Paying attention to, I mean, as far as the liquor board, or is that sort of. More about the, I don't know the individuals who are involved in that officers Sebastian. I just didn't understand that part so that's just. It's just a term saying that, like.
There's probable cause to believe that they allowed an illegality to happen on their property or that a crime did occur on their property, which is the assault and battery. It's not something that's saying like they're going to be charged with a crime or anything like that. It's just saying that there was there's enough probable cause to say that, you know, a crime did occur on their property. That's all. OK.
That's sort of the hook that brings us together to discuss this matter right now. Okay. I think I kind of understood it that way because like it really did seem like they're complying with everything. And I saw that that was what I was just confused about. Yeah. The choice of file charges in court or not is kind of irrelevant to this hearing. Yeah. Yeah. As I have in the past, I'll forward over a report as I did with a different incident at a different establishment.
where there was really no cause to say any legality was permitted. So just please take this and put it in their file that it exists. We know for sure a place in the property today. We know the event occurred. We know perhaps too many adult beverages in a short period of time.
Mr. Chairman, what are your thoughts on this one? This is clearly kind of an infraction to the point where it turned into a fight. I know this is completely different from the last time Mr. Carrera was with us, but what are your thoughts on that, Mr. Chairman?
Well, I mean, Mr. Carrera stated a few things in the club's defense, which I agree with. And I'm sure we all agree with that you can't control anybody's tempers or behavior. It seems to me losing a cook and a couple of members is pretty much punishment enough.
especially today, is it's tough to replace. So, I mean, what I would like to ask Mr. Carrera is, you are still the club manager, correct? Yes. Okay. And is Mr. Jose Figueredo? Figueredo is the president. He's the president. Okay. Okay.
I was looking over your application that we had on file and you are listed as the manager and Mr. Fugitio is club clerk, but we'll call club clerk the president.
The thing that was very impressive to me when I first read the report was that he responded to the scene and immediately shut down the establishment, which I thought was a very good move. What I was going to ask you to do was do another
another application, but I see there's no need, because he's the club president. Yes. And our records are accurate, so there's no need to do that. That's going to save you $200 to $400 right there, because that's what it would have cost you to create a new application.
The only thing I would ask you to do is just read over the rules and regulations of private clubs for the city of Medford. Daria can send you a copy of that via email or whatever. I appreciate that.
Brush yourself up on it. Make sure you're aware of everything. The guest book, all that stuff. Have a list of all the club members handy. It doesn't have to be displayed, but if someone should come in, like Lieutenant Lockowitz or Officer Sebastian,
And they ask for it, which you did have everything correct. You had your licenses posted. You had, you know, information and stuff for them. So just review it and make sure that you're compliant. And, you know, like I said, I feel bad enough for you now. And it's not easy with private clubs. You know, it's kind of a struggling thing. And I feel as though personally that
We can let this one slide by. You guys have been doing good since we had that last incident with the food and running a restaurant type of thing. But you didn't know, and that's how you learn. Mr. Chair, I'm sorry to interrupt, but I just had one- I just wanted to point out about the chairman and the discussion.
One question out of curiosity, I remember several years ago, there was an altercation, I think, at the Legion. And it was one of those, you can't control people's emotions, I get that. But they took what really saved their butt, so to speak, was they followed the proper procedures. So I guess the only question I have, Mr. Carrera, is did you
or someone there called 911 or did one of your patrons, how did the police get involved in this altercation? Because the bartender is a woman, so she felt helpless, so she called 911 to come and take over the situation because she can't go there and separate them or do anything. So one of your staff initiated the call? Yes.
Okay. So that's, that's another plus. Yeah. That's, that's important that, you know, it wasn't swept under the table. And then as the, everyone left, they decided to call. Okay. Um, Ben, would you like to comment on this as well?
have been made. Yeah, for a second there. Um, is there anybody else present that wants to speak either in favor or against this matter? No. Okay. Uh, Officer Lockowitz. Anything else from the P. D. No, I'm I'm satisfied with the outcome, you know, documenting, discussing and it seems like corrective actions have already been taken. Okay.
Okay, well, I don't have an issue with. Doing like I said, what we just discussed that there's been punishment served already enough by losing a couple of members in a book. I feel as though that's that's more than applicable.
if you feel the same way, Mr. Commissioner. Ben, would you care to comment on any of this before we wrap it up? No, I think everything you said is good, Bobby. I don't think any further action is needed from us. I think it's all been cleared up.
My opinion. I agree. I mean, we'll take this incident, put it in the jacket, in the file cabinet, and if we start seeing a trend as the months and the years go on, then we'll take a little more, not punitive, but we'll take the necessary action.
Yeah, yeah. I think we've seen clubs deal with it way worse, so. So I think you guys dealt with it. Okay, so should we make a motion or are we just good? I think we'd make a motion to like file the disposition as a warning and keep the report on file.
Yeah. That's good advice. I motion to enter the information on file. We're aware of what happened. We've properly discussed it. Mr. Carrera has taken the necessary steps, and as a result, there has been some residual effect as a result of the event. So let's just put it on file, and hopefully we'll never have to revisit another incident at the establishment.
That's what I hope. Ben, you want to second that? I'll second that motion. All righty. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Hearing and seeing none, the ayes have it. Motion's passed. Mr. Garrett, you're all set. I'm very sorry again for your troubles. Keep running a good tight ship like you do, and we won't have any issues. Don't be afraid to call if there are any issues. I always do my best.
It's a teachable moment. You'll know what went wrong, and you'll make sure, as I said, from listening to you, you said you won't. You'll take, hopefully your other members will take the necessary steps to prevent something from escalating like that again. Yes. Thank you. Good. I will. I will see you guys on the 25th. Take care.
Medford Police. Thank you very much for coming. Thank you, guys. Anything else you'd like to comment on? Are you good? I think we're good. I know Officer Farrell and Sebastian are both good for the day, and I don't have anything further. Do you, gentlemen? No. No, I think we're good. All right, thank you. Thanks again. Appreciate it. Thank you, guys.
I got two reports I'll be forwarding to you, both from the Great American Beer Hall. Wait a minute, why didn't you tell us that before? One I happen to be in the building for. Officially or unofficially?
Unofficially, I was in there with half a dozen dispatchers. Okay. But neither one of them were overly concerning. Okay. I've got a feeling we're going to probably, they're going to be a frequent flyer because of the enormity of people in there. It's just so enormous that things are bound to happen. It's so big that things happen. Every time I drive by at night, the place is packed.
Yup. And Mystic Ave is packed with cars. Hancock Ave is packed with cars. It's just like, you can't even get in that joint. People come down Mystic Avenue at night. Yeah. I get to jump off. I will, I got to do some finishing touches and then forward them off. Um, that's all I got. Okay. We'll be looking forward to your reports. Absolutely.
Thank you guys. Thank you. Take care. Bye. Okay, good job. Yeah. Yeah. You know, we, it was quite a meeting almost 2 hours, but, um.
There's, you know, I was a little peed off when I got that email from you earlier that what they did expecting you to do all that work and we got to set something up. You know, that this is how this stuff needs to be submitted from this point forward, because you can't be expected to edit their documents and everything else. You should get 1 packet and that should be it.
So, I, I would yeah, I get it probably should have said something to them too, but I'm just like, I can't when it's a big package like that. It's really hard to. I 1st, have to deal with and.
Because it's so big, I can't scan it all in, you know what I mean? So I have to do it little by little, and then it's just like taking them apart again. So it's just like, it ends up, I just wanted to let you know, this is why I don't have it yet, because I just haven't had the time to do it.
And you're saying you have to scan all those little individual mailings? Yeah, because it's like this. It's like this. If you look at it, it's stapled. So you can't go through the printer. It gets stuck. So I'm doing one at a time. Yeah, you've got to handle it twice. You've got to make a copy of it and then scan it. And then I've got to put it together in a package.
Right. So it's just like I know they probably just didn't think about that. I didn't want to come off as, you know, rude or not wanting to do. It's just it ends up being a lot. And I just don't have between what I need to do. I just don't have that time.
Yeah, exactly. It's just a lot of stuff to do. Hey, we just try and do our best and try and get as much done as we can. I think everything went very well today considering, but I don't think we really have anything going on that's in limbo other than the meeting that's next week, I believe. Next Wednesday, yes.
Yeah, so, you know, you were able to send out another email to the department head, seeing if any of them wanted to do like a five minute talk about what's to expect, what the licensee should, what they expect of the licensee. Yes, I was planning to do that today, because I had to reach out to a few department heads just for a different reason. But yes, I'm going to be asking that today. And I think
Everybody got back to me besides police chief. Okay, I got to ask him next time I see him.
Yeah, I was talking to Ralph and he said that might be a good idea. He says to do, because now the licensees know what the department heads expect. And when it comes time for renewal, it's a lot easier. Yeah, I think it would be helpful information, but everybody else is able to come. So that's I'm happy about that. I just got to ask.
Chief, but I don't think, um, I don't think it would be a problem because I know I, I send the request to, um, Lieutenant Lockovitz to, to have him attend. Yeah. Yeah. And I don't, I don't really know if there's too much for the chief to really. That's why sometimes, that's why sometimes I, um, ask Lieutenant Lockovitz versus the chief, but I think I've asked them both.
Did Rory speak last year? Do you remember? He did. He did a really good job. Yeah, that's why I wanted him to be here again. It'd be nice if they could do that, if he could. It was him and Penny last year, so both of them did a really good job, because they touched on the tips, and then the over-serving, and then all of that good stuff. You said they invited out Sophie Greenblum.
Yes, she said that she will be attending, yeah. And then I'm sure Rory and the two officers, Smith and Sebastian, you know, with their part of our team, they should make sure they get an email at least informing of them if they'd like to attend, you know? Yeah, yeah. I usually will forward to Lieutenant Lockovitz, and then I think he forwards it to the officers, yeah.
cool yeah mr chair i know we're getting close to two hours but um my question um should we be concerned about d1 soccer or not
Yeah, good point. Um, you know, I, I feel as this, this is a 100% police matter. Um, it's disturbing the peace, it's, um, trash in the parks, it's doing all of that. And I mean, we've, that's way out of our lane. What's in our lane is issuing a license. And I believe, I looked through my records, the last license to be issued to them was for the 15th, which was when that whole melee occurred.
So, you know, it's up to the city to deny these people for rent in OML if they don't.
I mean, do we give them the ultimatum? Do you want to start now? Hey, listen, obviously, if client, your attendees are getting hammered every time they go there, and the party's going long after the games, and it's not for the game anymore, it's just to have a big gathering. I think we can deny them a license. Yeah, I'm wondering if you're right. Might be a good question for Ralph.
Yeah. I wonder if it starts with us. If we say no, this dude can have the event there and if they want to sneak drinks out in the parking lot, will they do it at their own risk?
Yeah, it's got nothing to do with us. But then again, you know, I'd like to just run it by Ralph even on the 25th privately just to make sure we're not putting the city out there in discrimination or something. You know, what's the matter? You don't like black soccer players or Spanish soccer, whatever. It's, you know. No, no, no, no. We see the residual effect from those events there.
And, you know, the first thing, you know, honestly, the first thing that came into my mind was the one at the Pats game. The guy stole, he was so drunk from tailgating and partying, he stole the car out of the parking lot and the state police chased him and he went the wrong way and he killed somebody coming the other way. He didn't start to. He didn't start to.
Yes. All right. Well, well, I guess we'll cross that bridge when we get to it. Yeah. Yeah. I don't think they're going to be applying anymore. They share anyways, but no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no
Because the allowing that event to happen, that should sort of isn't our thing. It's more like. City has to decide, do they want to, you know. 2000 person event somewhere 1st. Then, and then issue the conditions around the event, like, you've got to have way more parking control. You've got to have a plan. You've got to have more.
security, you know, and then it can come to us and we can say, yeah, we'll give liquor or not. And I feel like that's proper. It's just throwing a little gasoline on the fire. Yeah. Yeah. It's. Oh, wait, why? What? Gasoline on the fire. Oh, the liquor part?
Yeah, exactly. Oh, I mean of an unorganized event. I don't know if you can hear me, but of an unorganized event, liquor adds to it as a problem. But an organized event that has everything in order, I mean, sure, you know, the city's okay with it, but this one doesn't seem organized whatsoever.
No, and they've got to get tons more security. Once the parking lot fills up, they got to have parking attendance, you know, over to the McGlynn to the Andrews.
I mean, you can't direct them over to where the Meadow Glen might used to be because that's private property, but it's just an event that big, it's got to tell you the city cannot handle it. We don't have the capacity for cars and something that large. Honestly, I don't think they do too. I think they don't realize how big that event is because they certainly don't have the proper staffing,
or equipment to handle that large of a crowd. And as I said, every year, if it keeps growing, I mean, it wasn't that big when they first started having the event at Hormel. It is evolved or it's grown into something much larger. Yeah, exactly. So I think we should look into all aspects of it and just, you know, I don't feel comfortable issuing. I mean,
Issuing them a one day license. I don't feel comfortable doing that anymore after seeing what's happened constantly at first. Maybe it's something that the cities, you know, that parks and recreation department, you know, had an argument with the guys or the organization or something, but you can see it's just over and over and over again. And when you get police reports stating that's unsafe, it's a public.
public issue, public hazard issue, public safety issue is a word, I'm sorry. It's just, we can't have that. We can't have a public safety issue in the city. It's just gonna put the city out there liability wise. And if we get the okay from Ralph that we don't have to issue the one day licenses, we'll discuss it. And if we all feel the same way,
Hey, no more licenses for them if the city wants to give them permission to use the pack. That's got nothing to do with us. Yeah. Okay. Okay, good.
That's the way I feel. How do you feel? I feel the same way. Like I said, I don't think they realize how big the event is. If all of a sudden they start telling us, oh, we have 150 people that are going to be
work in the event and we're, you know, all right, we'll entertain, you know, what they're going to do to keep the whole thing in check. But like I said, we'll cross that bridge when we get to it. It'll be next year, right? Because the season's practically done. Yeah, I think it's done for us this year anyways over here. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. So do I motion to adjourn?
Yes. I motion to adjourn. It's a good meeting and good to see you guys. Yeah. All those in favor. Good. Thanks for all the work. Everybody Daria. Yeah. All right. Bye everyone. Have a good one. All right. Ciao. See everyone. We're going to write the mayor a letter to recommend you for raise.
I make a motion to do that. Bye guys.