Thank you.
The fifth regular meeting of the Memphis School Committee will come to order.
Tonight's Monday, March 24, 2025.
We have a meeting at 6.30 PM.
please be advised there'll be a regular meeting of the Memphis School Committee held at the Howard Alden Memorial Chambers, Medford City Hall, and via remote participation immediately following the budget hearing or 6.30, which is what we chose to do since the agenda says 6.30.
This meeting is being recorded.
The meeting can be viewed live on the Medford Public Schools YouTube channel, through Medford Community Media, on your local cable channel, Comcast 981.
or 22, and or Verizon channel 43, 45, and 47.
Participants can log or call in by using the following Zoom link.
Meeting ID is 989-1291-8617.
Member Rousseau, if you will please call the roll.
Member Brandley.
member Graham present member and Papa present member Ola Pate present member Reinfeldt present members so present Mayor Longo present seven present zero absent do we have any student representatives on zoom not tonight okay thank you and if we all may rise to salute the flag I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America and to the Republic for which it stands one nation under
Member Russo.
folks might be showing up or have shown up thinking that this was when the hearing was.
So if you just wanna clarify for anybody who's on Zoom thinking that what they're getting.
Sure, this is our regular meeting, 6.30.
This was posted on the city and school website.
We also just finished a meeting that was at five o'clock this evening.
It was a special meeting of the Medford School Committee and our public budget hearing.
So that is complete.
that will be probably available on Medford Community Media as soon as possibly tomorrow.
And I'm sure the slides will be put on the website.
So if you have any questions on the budget meeting, this is our regular meeting.
So next step is the consent agenda.
And we have approval of bills and payrolls, approval of capital purchases, approval of grants, Tufts University $1,000 donation to the Center for Citizenship and Social Responsibility.
Vecna Robotic of Waltham Massachusetts is donating $180,000 worth of new and used equipment.
to the Engineering and Metal Fabrication Program at Medford Vocational Technical High School.
We have a donation of $2,250 by Arthur C. Mabbitt of Mabbitt, I believe he's a business owner, maybe that was just left off, Mabbitt, Inc., for 2025 Medford High School Science and Technology Engineering Exposition.
We have a donation of $4,000 by J.S.
Lim Foundation for J.S.
Lim Science and Mathematics prizes.
A donation of $2,594, 94 euros by the Italian Ministry of Foreign Affairs and International Cooperation has approved the Consulate General's request for donation.
This is for the Italy trip.
And the Friends of the Medford Public Library is making an initial donation of 102 books valued at $1,620 to the English Learners Department at Medford Public Schools.
Approval of field trips, approval of meeting minutes.
Our meeting minutes under this consent agenda are regular meeting minutes from February 26th, 2025.
Special budget meeting number one, March 5th, 2025.
Joint session meeting of the Medford School Committee and the Medford City Council, March 19th, 2025.
Committee of the whole meeting, fiscal year 26 budget overview, March 20th, 2025.
Is there a motion for approval of the consent agenda?
Motion to approve.
By Member Olopade, seconded by Member Ntapa.
All those in favor?
Is it roll call?
Member Brandley?
Yes.
Member Graham?
Member Ntapa?
Yes.
Member Olopade?
Member Rheinfeld?
Yes.
Member Rossell?
Mayor Lungo-Kern?
Yes, seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative.
And I just want to, I'm sure, on behalf of the committee, thank all those who have donated to our schools in wonderful ways that I just read.
Our next regular member was out.
Yeah, I just want to say that that's a record probably by three or four times the number of things on a consent agenda we've ever had.
So congratulations, everybody.
It's like a lot.
Yes.
and a lot of good donations.
So yes, great.
We do have our next regular meeting in two weeks.
That's on April 7th, 2025 here in the Alden Memorial Chambers, Medford City Hall, in addition to Zoom.
And next up for tonight, we have
an executive session upon motion to enter into executive session pursuant to general laws 30 a section 21 a to conduct a strategy session on the basis that an open meeting may have a detrimental effect on the bargaining positions of the medford school committee specifically the medford school committee will be discussing ongoing collective bargaining negotiations with teamsters local 25 custodians
Massachusetts Nurses Association, Medford Paraprofessional Association, and Teamsters Local 25 Administrators.
Executive session pursuant to Chapter 30A, Section 21.2, to conduct strategy in preparation with non-union personnel, specifically contract negotiations with the Director of Food Services.
The Memphis School Committee will not reconvene in public session.
by member motion to enter executive session by member Reinfeldt, seconded by member Olaparte.
Roll call, please.
Member Bramley?
Yes.
Member Graham?
Member Ntapa?
Yes.
Member Olaparte?
Member Reinfeldt?
Yes.
Member Rossell?
Mayor Longo?
Yes.
Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative.
Motion to
go into executive session and not reconvene has been approved.
Thank you.