So I say let's kick off, let's start the meeting. Okay, and we're recording, correct? I think I saw the disclaimer. First of all, good afternoon, everyone. Thank you for attending. Happy holidays, everyone. I'd say the other phrases, but I don't want to get into trouble.
So I guess let's, Daria, did I hear you correctly that the minutes are done, but we didn't get a chance to review them so we can vote on them, or? Yes, the last one, yeah, from last meeting. Okay, so we'll do that at the next meeting, or we could do that as a sidebar. Yes, Bobby, Ben, good to see you guys. Good to see you Thursday night at the Rotary Club's 100th celebration.
Thank you for attending. Yes, thank you for the invite. It was very nice. I should have wanted more food because we ran out and that's all I heard. Oh, jeez, I didn't get a chance. I'm like, we should have got there early, you know? Yeah, I didn't eat much. I had another affair to go to. A couple of firefighters retired at Regina's, so I got over there about eight o'clock. Yeah, makes sense.
All right, so we're not going to bat out of order. We're not going to do any housekeeping. So I guess we'll just jump right into number one, Riverside Yacht Club. It looks like change of manager. Do I see Michael Giardina there? Is Michael here?
No, I don't see him. Yeah, I think it's Robert Miller. No, I lied. Yeah, he's not on. I don't see. Okay. All right. Well, you know, maybe he'll come on later. So let's skip over number one. Oh, you might have had a hard time. Sorry. Last time. Did he have a hard time getting on the zoom? And then we like, put him at the end. He did. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, okay. Anyway, well, I haven't heard from him today, so I'm hoping that it's all okay, but... Yeah, well, maybe he'll jump on later. So let's table that, maybe he'll come on later. So let's jump over to number two, which is the Method Firefighter. I see the lieutenant back there. Mr. Chairman, I told Dyer here, I don't know if you were on, but I'm gonna...
recuse myself from this application only because I'm still currently a member of the Medford Firefighters Club and I don't want any conflict of interest to possibly come up and harm what they're trying to do here.
Sure. No, that makes sense. Thank you. Makes sense. Thank you for that. Lieutenant Moore, how are you? Paperwork looks like it's in order. Can you tell us a little, give us a little background since you're going to be the new chief there?
But we just want to incorporate a couple of things, karaoke maybe once a month and a jukebox that we had put in. So that's pretty much it. I'm not sure. I see that. So there were actually two items before this commission, the change of manager, which is going to be you, correct? Correct. And then you're looking for an entertainment license. And Ben, did you get a chance to look at it? I saw on the entertainment license, it's been signed off by
all the proper departments. Did you get a chance to look at that? Yeah, I saw that the entertainment license that had all those signatures, which was great. And the change in manager had, I think, everything on it we need, such as the ABCC license numbers. Yeah. And the quarry and
I didn't have any questions because it was also notarized and everything seems. Yeah, no, I couldn't agree with you more. I looked through it. Mr. Moore even included his passport in here. So it all makes sense in the proper departments. I know you guys run a Stella shop down there, never had any incidents. We've never had any, you guys ever before us with any problems.
I don't have any questions. Brian, I mean, Ben, do you have any, or do you want to make a motion? No, my only question was, have you guys considered getting bigger windows in the place? Seems like there's not a lot of light in there, but that's not. No, there really isn't.
No, it's just a joke. I just always think the windows are so small. But no, but that's not, it has nothing to do with the liquor board. So yeah. Speaking as a contractor, right? These are your buttons as a contractor. Yeah. All right. So you want to make motion to, we'll do two separate ones, one for the entertainment license and one for the change of manager.
Yeah, that sounds right. Okay. Okay, so starting with the change of manager, I'll make a motion to approve the change of manager for the Medford Professional Firefighters Club. The new manager is will be Steven M. Moore, who's currently the president of the club. Secondly, I will make a motion to
approve the entertainment license for this same club, Medford Professional Firefighters Club, Stephen Moore, manager on record, and that's to specifically approve jukebox and karaoke. Karaoke. For the establishment. Okay. Are people, firefighters do karaoke? Or is that? Not yet, anyway.
They're about to. All right. And sorry for your loss there, Army-Navy game. What a way to... Army stripped that ball out of the quarterback.
Thank you, Ben, for the two motions. I second both motions. Bobby's standing down. All in favor of accepting the change of manager's license, say aye. Aye. Very good. And all in favor of implementing the entertainment license for the firefighters hall, say aye.
All right, very good. So those two are all set. Thank you, Stephen. We appreciate it. Thank you for coming. Happy holidays. Thanks, guys. Appreciate it. Merry Christmas. Thank you. Merry Christmas. You can say that without getting in trouble, right? You're good. Thank you. All right, let's jump to number three, the American Legion. Who's here from the American Legion? Hi, good afternoon.
Robert Miller. I'm the senior vice commander and finance officer. How are you, Mr. Miller? Thank you for attending. Thank you for having me. So tell us a little about yourself. Tell us a little about what's going on. We see the change of manager. We see all the correct forms in place. But tell us a little about yourself, please, if you don't mind. Yeah, so I'm a Coast Guard veteran. I've been past commander twice of the American Legion.
I was on the City of Medford Veterans Advisory Board for a year or two. I currently work for the VA in Boston and help veterans every day trying to get their benefits and everything on the outside as well. I've been moving through the chairs at Coast 45 and we've been making some changes and we have a new bar manager that is coming in looking hopefully to help us modernize the club and do the right thing, giving back to the community. Okay, cool. Let's see here.
Bobby, Ben, any questions? I have one, Mr. Chairman. I looked over the application. I just got to pop it back up here again. I believe the 1, 2, 3, 4, 5th page is filled out incorrectly.
uh, under applicant statement, uh, I believe that's supposed to be William Maury, um, whose name should be at the top is the authorized signature for the American Legion. And on the following page under entity note, um, it states that, um, the, the, uh, organization voted William Maury Jr.
to appoint Thomas Moulton. So Mr. Morey is supposed to be on the prior page, the statement page. Yeah, I'm looking at the amendment change in manager and it does say proposed manager named Thomas Moulton. I see it there.
Right, yeah, he's the one that's going to be the new manager, but under the applicant statement, the authorized signature is Mr. Morey, William Morey. Yeah, yeah, Bobby. So change that to just instead of Thomas Moulton, change it to William, have them change to William Morey. Yeah, and have Mr. Morey just sign the top of it under authorized signature at the top. Yeah, yeah. Signature on the bottom.
Signature on the top and let's see. Wait, where do you see the signature? Applicant statement at the top of the page. Yeah. Then it says authorized signatory. Oh, I got you. I'm thinking name. Yeah. Because it's the name of the corporation, American Legion under that. Then at the bottom, Mr. Morey should be signing that with his title.
which I'm not sure what it is. I probably, I'm not sure, one of the corporate offices. Okay, so it all pretty much needs to be filled out by William Morey, this whole page. That page, correct. And the following page, the entity note is fine because he's the one authorized to appoint Mr. Moulton. And I was questioning it and I went back a couple of,
to a couple of different change of managers, and one of them, I don't know if it was Shake Shack or one of them that was a corporate, I checked the way that their corporate lawyers filled it out, and that was the proper way. So I just want to double-check on it. It's funny that you say that because I was paying attention to the entity vote, because last time we ran into that issue, where they did the opposite or didn't fill it out. Interesting. So I was paying attention to that one, but I see why. Yeah, that was a good one.
And the Riverside Yacht Club hasn't come up yet, but they are correct. They filled it out the way that we explained to them last month, so they're fine with it. And I wasn't involved with the Firefighters Club, but since Lieutenant Moore was, I believe he was one of the principals, so he was able to fill that page out the way that he did.
So with those very minor changes, do you want to approve the change of manager subject to those tweaks? And then, Dary, you can get that page tweaked. And then you could email it to us. And we can just kind of say, yeah, we're good with it. And I'll put it in the rest of the package. Ben, Bobby, this sounds good? That works for me. That's reasonable. OK.
Anything else? Bobby, you had eagle eyes, I'll tell ya. Good catch, Bobby. They're getting a little slow though, the older I get. I can't imagine you in your prime then. No, I didn't think there was anything, I thought it was, that was a good catch. I was looking at the, you know, I thought it was all legible and it looked,
looked fine and you know Tom Moulton's information was in here and it seems all good besides just that, you know, the signature page. Okay. Yeah. Good. Mr. Miller, any questions? Are you following us, what we're doing?
Yeah, I'm still here. I can make it down to sign, uh, to correct those documents whenever I live, uh, right up the street. So yeah, yeah. William, William Mori is the actual commander. Um, so what happens is the commander, um, uh, appoints a new bar manager. That's why his name was in there. I'm just filling in for him in this meeting. Sure. No, we understand. Yeah. If, if you guys get it done so we can get it off of a diary as a desk by the end of the year, that would be great. Absolutely.
All right, cool. All right. Makes sense. Yeah. It's just such a minor tweak. We just have to reverse the order. I don't have a problem. The rest of it is fine with me. Bobby, Ben, you want to make a motion, please? Yeah, sure. I can make a motion. I can make a motion that we grant the American Legion a change of manager.
Um, provided that, um, Mr. Miller's signature is on, I believe it was page 5, uh, at the top and the bottom of the page, uh, statement. Yep. Yep. And, um, yeah, I make, yeah, so we're good. I'll second the motion for change management.
All right. Well, thank you for the motion in the second. Um, all in favor of accepting the change of manager for, uh, the American Legion subject to that minor condition and tweak. Say I I very good. Uh, all set, Mr Miller. You guys are great. Happy holidays. Um, and, you know, if you could, if you could take care of that with diary, that would be great. The sooner the better. Absolutely. Thank you for your time. All right, cool. Take care. Thank you.
Have a good holiday. Okay, number four on the agenda, there's two items to say with the event them. Did I see Brian? Yeah. I'm here. How are you, Brian, with the little one? Yeah, me and Emmy today. Good to see you. So tell us a little about what's going on. I see a request for a one-day license, and then I saw something else. Is it another one-day license?
I'm not sure. I just wanted to go through the process. And so they were both kind of just instances where I wanted to make sure that I was clear on the process. So one is a reschedule date. So the event that was supposed to take place on December 1st, we applied, our application was approved. Our host got COVID. And so to, you know, we just kind of made the call that it wasn't worth it because they needed to be present for that event.
So we rescheduled it and, you know, this time of year gets really tricky. So we rescheduled it for Wednesday the 20th. Um, and so my, I just, you know, I couldn't, I can do the, I did the new application, but I didn't know if it was a move of an application or if it's a whole new process and either way is fine. Um, the one thing I just want to do is I just think. I want to make sure that I respect in the integrity of the board and everything. It's like,
You know, the events tonight, like, I don't, there should be more preparation. And there was, but again, I don't expect anybody to be presenting an application to be approved and say, oh, it's tonight, by the way. It just doesn't seem like something I want to do. So I guess my question was, how do I handle that, you know, and make sure that it doesn't become a problem for you guys?
Ben, do you want to fill in? This is just a do-over, so to speak. We vetted it once, so we were comfortable approving it. So I don't have an issue with that. But let me hear from my other two commissioners. Anything?
No, you handled it fine, I think, because it's not even a rain out date, which sometimes we do for a one day. It's hard to predict a reschedule, and you've got it on technically before even the event. So I don't have any issue with it.
And plus it's six to nine, Brian. I mean, if you tell us it was eight in the morning to, you know what I mean, before one o'clock, then it's like, hey, you put the car before the horse. So we're, we're fine on the same day. It just happens to be the same day. Yeah. Okay. I just wanted to make sure just in case in the future, there was something that just landed on the day of the meeting and I don't, um,
No, as long as the meeting's before the event, you're fine. You're fine. Yeah. All right. I'm going to make a motion for it. Yeah. I'll make a motion to accept the one-day license for December 20th, 2023 from 6 to 9 p.m. at Event Dem Studios, which is the same,
same one-day license we've approved at the last meeting. Right. Yeah. Okay. I'll second. Very good. Thank you, Ben. Thank you, Bobby. All in favor of approving the one-day license for December 20th. Is it local cuisine? Is that what I'm reading, Brian? Cuisine and locale, yeah. Yeah, locale. Okay.
Gonson, yeah. Okay, so all in favor of approving the one-day license for December 20th, say aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. That one's set. All right, and then let's look at the other one, the December 21st, right? Is that one still? That's honestly, I put in the application because I wasn't sure. So essentially, it's just me having people over.
You know, again, it's, I guess the debatable thing is it's friends, family, and some local business owners that I've invited to kind of celebrate. And I didn't know if it's something I should do the application for. No, I think when you run into murky waters as if you advertise it or you make it open to the public, I think that's where it gets kooky. But if it's just family and it's a private party,
I don't have an issue. Ben, Bobby, do you see anything there? Christmas party at the business? Exactly. Exactly. It's invitation only within our system. Yeah. Yeah. It's not like if you walk in there, you're going to sell me a beer. Right. Or you're going to serve. Yeah. Somebody off the street. Or we'll have a curved office. Invitation only. That's fine. Is the process the same? Should we set up exactly the same?
Of course, with the ABCC, with safe serving, I mean, I'm fine with that. I just want to make sure I have clarity in that.
Um, you know, again, um, my take is you would, you take the necessary steps. You don't let your nieces and nephews sneak a bear or something. You know what I mean? Just the normal steps, you know, and you can't, you can't go wrong, but since it's, it's a Christmas party for family and friends and relatives, you're, you're fine. Just, you know, you, you know, which uncle and cousin and, you know, you know, who's home, you know, all the parties. So.
Agreed. Again, I just wanted to run through the process because it was something new and I just wanted to make sure that I did it right. That's all. Yeah. Yeah. No, that's fine. So you're all set, Brian. We okayed the other one and happy holidays. You too. Everyone, thank you so much. Take care now. Take care, Brian. Bye now.
Number five is City of Manfred. Who will be representing the city? Oh, this is Teresa, how are you? I'm doing well, how are you? Good, good. Tell us a little about the event. Yes, so very similar to Brian and EventStem, this was an application that we submitted for a, we were being optimistic for a November event. At that time, you had approved the one-day license. This event is, just as a reminder,
It's a city organization, it's the Community Preservation Committee. We're celebrating five years of funding EPA projects here in the community. It's technically open to the public. It is a ticketed event that is free. We're not looking to recoup any revenue here at all. It's just serving some beer and wine while we celebrate the good stuff here in Medford.
Yeah, we vetted this once already back in November, right? November? Yeah. The one change is in the venue. The reason that we were unable to move forward with our November date was due to some accessibility issues in the venue. So it was previously Shiloh Baptist Church. It is now the Unitarian Universalist on High Street.
Ask that address, but I just looked it up to so we see that it's at the universe, the Unitarian Church. I just called the church because I always mixed up. Yeah, yeah. I got Teresa people going to complain about the parking. Oh, yeah.
Um, we don't anticipate that we'll have to, you know, a large mass amount of visitors. Um, we're, we're hoping for around 50 to 60. we will be asking folks to utilize the public parking that's in the in the square.
And then walk up, sure. Well, that's the reason, you know, last Thursday, the Rotary celebrated its 100th anniversary at the library. And people kept saying, oh, where am I going to park? Parking stinks. You know, all of that stuff. It's like, please. So, all right. Good, good. Ben, Bobby, you want to, any questions or you want to make a motion?
Um, I don't have any questions, uh, just as just an FYI for your parking. Um, I happen to attend, uh, the, uh, the rotary function and I parked.
down where they have the farmers' market behind St. Joe's. And it was great. I just walked up the stairs at St. Joe's Church, and I was right there. There's plenty of parking. There was nobody in the lot. So, you know, if somebody's questioning where they can park, it's an easy park, and it's free. They don't charge you, and, you know, there won't be
getting bottled up in the square at the same time, but just a suggestion. I will take that advice. Thank you. Just in case someone moans and groans about the parking. Good. One of you want to make a motion? I can make the motion to grant the one-day license for the city's organization anniversary celebration.
that's gonna be held at 147 High Street at the Unitarian Universalist Church on January 21st from approximately 3 p.m. to 5 p.m.
Very good. Thank you, Bobby. I'll second the motion. All right. Thanks, Ben. Thank you for the motion and the second. All in favor of approving the one day license of the city of Medford, say aye. Aye. Ben, is that a hand up? All right. Very good. All set. Teresa, you're all set. Thank you, gentlemen, so very much. I appreciate it. Good luck. Happy holidays. Happy holidays, Teresa. All right. That was number five.
I'm sorry, I see some housekeeping at the bottom here. Is there anything in particular order you want us to address or is there anything you wanted to talk about that we should pay attention to first? So I think Riverside Yacht Club might be on. I think. I don't know who the phone number is. It's 617-480-2865.
Yeah, I don't know. Brian Patrick, is that any of your numbers? Oh, here comes somebody. That's Rory. That's Rory. Oh, that's Rory, even with my glasses. You're right. Hi, Rory. I would say keep them on. If they come on, but we should move everybody else from waiting here alone. So I don't know if you guys want to do
the officers first and then do the rest of the stuff? I'm open. To me, they were all of equal weight, so I don't know. Ben, Bobby, any of these items you wanted to talk about at length first? Because to me, it looked like they're all equal.
I would be fine doing the officers first since they're in. Yeah, that's fine with me. All right. That sounds good since Rory popped on. Yeah. Is Rory still here? Rory. Officer Lakowitz, how are you? Thank you for jumping on. Hi, everybody. How are you? Good. Sorry, I had a little family emergency. I couldn't
Couldn't complete quick enough, but I'm good now. Hi, everybody. How you doing? Good. So we understand where you're adding to the team. There's going to be three officers in total. Is that our understanding? That's the plan. The two new faces on the call are officers Pat Smith, Patrick Smith, and Brian Sebastian. Ah, OK. Very good.
Welcome to the team, Officer Smith and Sebastian. Thank you for joining. Did Rory have to bribe you or anything just to get you on his team? But no, I'm just kidding, of course. But thank you, thank you. It's a long time coming. The three of us attended a two day training at the end of October. I believe the certificates were sent to Daria. Great.
for agents of the local liquor board. So they're fully trained and ready to go. And we're excited to be a little bit more proactive in the coming year.
Yeah, no, this is fantastic. The city's evolving, and it's growing. I was just looking at the census track. You're projecting by July of 24, we'll be at a little over 65,000 for population. So things are happening. It's all moving in the right direction. And every time I go down Mystic Ave, I see the, I call it the arc, the great American bear hall, the monstrous thing that's
And it's moving. It's moving along. So, uh, this is this is exciting. We, you know, there are times when sometimes, uh, I think you're, you know, you're being pulled in 100 different directions and this will be good. This will be good for, uh, for the city and for this commission. Absolutely.
Thank you. Yeah. So I, Daria, do we, do we have to take an official vote to accept the other two officers or, or is it just, yes. Okay. So, uh, Bobby, Ben questions, or do you want to make a motion to, um, for the other two officers to join the team? Just a suggestion. If they'd like to like introduce themselves just because they've been on the call, that'd be fine with us. No, no pressure though. Yeah.
So I'm Brian Sebastian. I've been with the Method Police Department for 10 years. I originally grew up in Cambridge. I actually didn't play hockey with Ben, but I remember Ben from hockey and his brother. And I'm married, five kids, and I've actually talked to Lieutenant Walkowicz about this for a few years. I've been very interested, and I'm glad to be with the team now.
Thank you, Officer Sebastian. Officer Smith? Hi, I'm Officer Patrick Smith. I've been a police officer over 10 years, born and raised in Medford. My father was a police officer. I did the underage buys when I was a teenager.
And before I was, I joined the Medford police in 2016. Before that I was a police officer in the town of Saltboro. And I actually was on patrol and I was, my cruiser was hit by a drunk driver, by a person that was over surfed. So it is a little personal to me. And when I met Lieutenant Larkowitz many years ago, he informed me that he was in charge of this and I wanted to join the team and I'm glad to be here. Thank you. Cool. Thank you for that. Great.
Bobby, any questions or concerns, anything? No, this is great. Brian and Patrick, welcome aboard and look forward to working with the both of you with Lieutenant Lockowitz, who's always done a fine job. Yes. Yes. Thank you. Let's get a motion on the table and let's vote on it and the three fine gentlemen can go back to work.
So is the motion to just approve? Yeah, I believe the motion is to declare the officers as agents of the litter board, if I'm not mistaken. Okay.
Okay. Do you want to, as the chair, do you want to do that, Ellen, or do you want to? Yeah, no, I'd be happy to. I make a motion to accept Officer Smith and Officer Sebastian as agents of the Liquor Board, and they will report to Officer Lockowitz, and Officer Lockowitz will help us through the hard times and the good times. So I motion to approve and accept the two other officers.
Second that motion. Yeah. Thank you, Ben. Gary, you get all that? I hope so. It's all on public record. So good. Good, good. So I think we're all set with that. Thank you, guys. We appreciate it. And hopefully, we won't need any of your services next year, right? Yeah. You can be optimistic.
All right. Thanks, guys, for that. Thank you. Happy holidays. Happy holidays to everyone. Happy holidays. Thank you. Thanks. Daria, let's jump to an easy one. The commission will discuss and adopt Chapter 138, Section 33B. I went to Ralph's site and I printed out actually what's written.
And then I printed out what's the difference between off-site and on-site premises, just to see what the, I don't know if I was missing something. It seems very simple and very straightforward. Bobby, do you have any, is there something I'm missing? Because it just seems, it seems very simple. And I, honestly, I thought we already were abiding by chapter 138, section 33B.
From what I, well, first we wanted to wait for you this meeting, which discussed a little bit last meeting, but we felt as though the three of us should be here to approve it. But I did some investigating into it to Jim, our former chairman, and he,
I knew right off the bat that the city had accepted it years ago because there was a women's football or soccer team or something at Hormel that needed it for Sunday mornings after their game.
And I guess the commission granted it for the season when the women were playing. But I had gone to the city clerk's office and the city clerk looked up all of their records and there was nowhere in the records that it was ever adopted. So.
Basically, all we need to do is adopt it and that allows on premise, which is any section 12 license to be able to open at 10 am on a Sunday morning. Basically, it was going to come up because the firefighters.
had approached me, they were going to have a function when the Patriots were playing in, what was it, England or somewhere? I'm not sure. Germany. They played in Germany. Yeah, in Frankfurt. Yeah. And they were going to have a time.
wound up that there was a conflict in schedule and something else was booked at the club that day, so they never had to have it. So, you know, I kind of felt as though it'd be a good thing to have in case anybody wants to come up with an early brunch they want to serve or something on a Sunday.
You know, at least it's adopted and then they still have to bring it to us. I would imagine just like a 1 day license or strong. I don't think there's any official paperwork that we have for it. They just probably just come before us and we can grant the, uh, the extension, you know.
Sure, sure. No, it's smart. I remember going down this road ages ago. But yeah, if we want to get it into the official record, then yeah, it makes sense. And that way, it's in the notes and it's official. And then you're right. If somebody needs to bump the hour, we can always take it one day at a time or one meeting at a time. Sure.
Yeah, and, you know, I mean, just for us approving it, you know, we, we should put in the language also that, um, you know, to have diarrhea and make sure that it goes down to the city clerk's office and gets filed. So, if, um, you know, in the future, we have to reference it or anything, they'll, they'll have it on record. Okay.
Jerry, you get that? Does that make sense? Yes. Okay, cool. All right. So who wants to, you want to make a motion to get this official language or chapter 138, section 33B onto our records or our books, however you want to say it.
I mean, we can probably say something like the commission would like to adopt Chapter 138, Section 33B, which allows the sale of alcoholic beverages to on-premise licenses on Sundays and certain legal holidays between 10 AM and 12 PM.
Section 33B, the local licensing authority. I'm basically just reading what's there. That's fine. Yeah. That in a nutshell, Christmas and a couple of other holidays may affect that a little, which is also written in the 33B. I just make a motion to adopt Chapter 138, 33B.
Yeah. It's already been adopted, but to place it into our records, so it's official. Okay. Yeah. That sounds good. You'll second it, right? Thank you for the motion. Thank you for the second. All in favor of placing Chapter 138, Section 33B, sale of alcohol beverages by on-premise licenses, say aye.
Hi, I approved. So we'll, we'll, we'll get that on record. And, uh, you know, and you're right, Bobby, if someone wants to tweak it by an hour or something, we address it as, as it comes in. And if they need it for like a season, like you guys did, you know, for a sporting team that plays, you know, every Sunday morning and.
You know, something like that, we can grant that just for a season. I mean, I'm sure at 1 point in time, it might even come up a restaurant in the city would just like it permanent, which we can appoint it permanent as well. If they want to do Sunday morning branches.
and they open at 10 o'clock or 9 o'clock, then they can start serving alcohol at 10. But right now, there's no need for it, so I don't think we should put it out there unless there's a need to. Yeah. Well, you're right. We'll address it as it arises. Would you notify us when it gets recorded?
Yeah, I'll ask the clerk on how to handle that. All right, cool. All right. Good, good, good.
So we do have Michael on from Riverside Yacht Club. But he's having, I don't know why we had the same issue last time. He's unmuted on my end, but he's able to do the volume thing. And I can make a call to him again. That's what we did last meeting. But you can barely hear him. He said that he had a vocal surgery, I think. You can really barely hear him, so I don't know how to. OK.
I mean, you can, if you want, just translate it. No, I mean, back and forth. Yeah. Well, we did meet. We did. He did come on last time. Yes. Sent him away and asked him to correct the application. Bobby's Hawkeyes caught a number of things. Great. But he has brought them back. And I believe that everything
at least to what I saw looked good.
It also looks fine to me, all the corrections that we suggested that he made. I did have a couple of issues that he needs to do is basically he didn't give Daria a proof of citizenship. He did. Oh, he did. Okay. Yeah. I don't know why it wasn't in the paperwork. Yeah. No license, no. Yeah.
Okay, and what about the payment receipt from the ABCC? Yes, he has that too, yeah. Then I'm good for both, I'm good. Yeah, okay. He did a great job. Everything we asked him to do, he did. Yeah. That's fantastic. He did the tip certification too, so. Yeah, that too was good. Yeah, yeah, he's good to go. Good, good, good. So everything seems to be in order. You want to make a motion or a second?
approve the change of manager? Yeah, I can do it. So I'll make a motion to approve the change of manager at Riverside Yacht Club. The new manager being Michael Giardina. And that we're accepting this updated application and submit.
Very good. I'll second the motion. Very good. Thank you for the motion. And the second, all in favor of accepting the change of manager for the Riverside Yacht Club, say aye. Aye. Aye. Very good. You're all set. Michael, thank you for enduring the paperwork, and thank you for getting back to us. It's been approved. Congrats.
I'm going to call him now to just let him know, because I don't know if he cares. Well, it says iPhone 5 Michael. So OK, cool. All right. So that one's set. Good. I'm glad we were able to take care of that. What's left here? You want to vote on the renewals, the 2024 renewals? Sure. I just had a question.
Well, maybe Alan or Bobby, did you guys cross-check all the signatures with the list? Or Daria may have. When you say signatures, do you mean, I'm not following. I mean, I did print out all the licenses. Yeah, so all these renewals, I mean, they all look,
They all look good. Do you mean like some of them might not be signed? No, they all seem signed. I was just making sure that that lined up with that list, because they're on two different documents. What are you talking about? Sorry. I'll stop now. Because didn't you have a? There's three different things. Maybe I'm misspeaking. I thought we had a list of all of the entities. Yeah, yeah.
Not you guys, no. I can send it to you. That's not a problem. I mean, that's fine. I saw, I mean, I see all alcohol, all beer and wine, all the one farmers brewing. I mean, it seemed right. I was just like, does it line up with our master list? Yes, yes. I checked them off. I get it with the list that I have.
So the only two that didn't renew was Salvatore's and Smashburger. Yeah, I saw that too.
Yeah, yeah, they- Smashburger turned in their license, what, in the summer? June, May, June, July? No, they never did it. They never did it. So I did talk to Denise, who's the licensing person there. She said that they were going to do it officially because her and I were talking. I was like, it might be better if you just do it officially versus just like kind of letting it go. But I don't know where, you know, that ended up. That was before Thanksgiving that we talked about that. I see.
Okay, well, Ben, if I think I understand you're concerned, what you're saying is the individual license renewals, do they match up with the master list that Daria keeps or the city keeps, right? Okay, and Daria, you said yes, you've gone through the list. So nobody has slipped through without, yeah, okay. And wouldn't there be a catch to that? Wouldn't ABCC have noticed
something to in their records if we had missed something. Yeah, they would they would reach out to us and ask where's the signature for this person. Yeah, the whole the whole pick all the things that are signed. That's all from ABCC what they are for us from it. That's what I thought. So there is like redundancies built in. So if we miss something, they would have caught it. Yeah, theoretically. Yeah. Okay.
Just a question too, so, because with Officer Smith and Officer Lockwood, would you guys know that Smashburger doesn't have a liquor license anymore? Or that, would we have to tell you that? That's a good question. Yes, I have two action items here I wanted to ask about. One of them was an updated list of every license that we have.
Hopefully a digital copy, maybe, Terry, that Pat and Sebastian, Brian and Sebastian could get. Yeah, I have it on my Excel, so I can send it to you guys. Awesome. In the actual renewals, Lieutenant Lakowicz, I think this is in a PDF also, so you can see the different categories also. Yeah.
So, yeah, that's one of the things I have written down is, you know, sometimes I'm if I'm not at the meeting and I didn't hear it, like all of a sudden a store pops up and I'm like, hey, they sell liquor. I should probably know about that. So, yeah, if we could update that every now and then, that'd be great.
While I'm babbling, Daria, this is slight sideways from Likert, do you have a list of all retail commercial properties in the whole city?
That's a good question. No, I do not. That's, I know we had an intern working on like the square businesses, like the actual, who owns the building. The only thing that I can think of, maybe assessor's office has it, or planning development and sustainability. Gotcha. I'm thinking those two. Assessor's, what was the other one? What'd you say? Okay.
uh, the assessor's office and what was the other one? Uh, planning, development, sustainability. Planning and development. Okay. Yeah. I have an idea, something, a project for download. Okay. Thank you. Okay. Very good. Um, Ben Bobby, you want to, um, make a motion to approve the, um, the 2024 liquor license renewals?
Oh yeah, and now just obviously also, Lieutenant, the vaults lapsed too. No surprise, but that light lapsed, so that's no longer. Yeah, I was a little curious. I submitted a report and then it seemed like two days later there was a poster on the wall that said that, I don't know if it was the property owner. Yeah.
Yeah, the 18th, they kind of padlocked the door, so to speak. But that was the property owner. The city of Medford didn't close that down, right? No, it was the landlord, the owner. Oh, interesting. Yeah.
And it's been lights out since October 18th. I get a few questions on that as far as what happened. And of course, the rumor mill starts flying around. The city shut them down. This happened, that happened. And I'm like, I don't think any of that happened. It had nothing to do with it. And the signs are still on the doors. They're on the front door, the back door, and the side door. It has the management company's name right on it and the date.
Okay. Yeah, I think as far as we're concerned they didn't renew their license. I mean, there's a more way more to that story but like that's that and so hasn't smashed burger so I just thought it's, it's seems important that we communicate that to the officer so they know what's what's what. Yeah, sure. Sure. Yeah, that's all I have.
Let's make a motion. Let's approve the liquor license renewals. Yeah, I can do that, Ben. So I'll make a motion to approve the liquor license renewals that have been submitted this year. This is for all alcohol license.
This is for beer and wine. This is for club renewals. And this is for farmers brewery renewals. Yeah. Yeah, but the I think would be safe to say for all the license types and license categories. I think I think because there's the hotel and in
category, so, and then there's the clubs. So I think we'd be safe if we just say license type and license category. Oh yeah, because there's package, I didn't say package stores. Yeah. So for all that, so I'll make a motion to accept all of the renewals for, yeah, all the renewals for all of the different categories submitted this year.
I'll second the motion. Very good, thanks. All in favor of approving it, the retail license renewals for 2024, say aye. Aye. Very good, all set. So it goes on record. The last thing is the population. Does that sound right, Dario? Certification of the population, yes. Yeah, yeah, okay.
So those two go together. Yeah, yeah, that one. I'll tell you that one almost knocked me out of my chair. I can't believe how fast the city has grown because I thought it was, wasn't it like 63,000 last year at this time, something like that? It was 62. 62? Yeah, 62, 63, but I think it was like on the lower side of 63. Yeah, yeah.
And so now they're projecting as of July 10th, 2024 will be 65,000, 399. So will that bump us up to another package though? Yeah. I wonder because it's one for every 5,000. Yeah. Out of curiosity. Yeah. I think that's, what is it, every 5,000? Yeah. It's one for every 5,000. Yeah.
You know, for the longest we've been hovering at, you know, 60,000, 58,000, 59,000, 60. So one for every 5,000. This would be good. Hey, that's good. The city is growing. They are. So any concerns, questions? Like I said, I, you know, I almost fell out of my chair when I saw how fast
We'd bumped up from 62, 63 to 65, 400, you know? Now, do we have to apply to ABCC to obtain another license? I don't know. Do we have to check with Ralph?
I don't believe so. They do the quota based on what we send in. Okay. We send in the population increase form, because I do that together with the renewals. And then they send us the quota around March. Yeah. So they'll tell us. I believe so, yeah. What's available, yeah. So now with
vaults in Smashburger, I think that puts it at 32 all beverage licenses now, or? Smashburger was only wine and malts. Ah, okay. Okay. That will free up because I know we didn't, we had like two or three left of wine and malts and then all alcohol will have a bunch still. So yeah. Okay, good. All right. Well, let's, uh, Ben, Bobby, if you have no questions about the, um,
the estimated increase in resident population. Let's make a motion and let's get this on record so Derek can submit it to ABCC. I can make a motion if you like that we accept the population increase estimation of the census of the city of Medford. Is that tied in with the renewal certification?
Okay, along with the renewal certification for 2024. Very good. Thank you, Bobby. Ben, you want to second the motion? Yeah, I'll second that motion. Good. All in favor of accepting the 2024 seasonal population increase estimation form, say aye. Aye. Aye. Very good. So away it goes.
Daria. Perfect. Thank you. I just want to say great job. You, you work really hard on this since November. You've been to the grindstone with it and you did awesome and got done. And, you know, I don't know where you get the time or the patience for it, but you make this commission shine. Thank you. Very good.
That knocks that one out. And then any and all other businesses that may arise, Dari, anything that we should be aware of? Any questions, concerns? No, I was just going to say I'm going to do electronic signatures for you guys for those forms.
So I will send it to you. I wanted for you to look at it first and then send you the signatures requests. So you did that last year too. So just look out for that. And then once it's signed, I can send it to the, I'm gonna do the packet so I can send it out. Just get it off my desk. Okay, good. All right. And that's it, I believe. There was nothing that I can think of. Okay.
That's easy, I think we've got everything covered. 138, two police officers, approve the renewals, certification, population increase, yeah. Yeah, I think we've covered all the loose ends. Good. I think it should be said that Mr. Delafano, in a couple months time,
has become like an expert in the, he set up trainings. He found those holes in that application that I think all of us would have missed. We thank you for your service, but I think you would have made a fine police officer, Bobby. Yeah, he was swayed by the dark side, the fire department, so. I don't say that to very many firefighters, but I think you would have done fine.
I second. I was happy with the fire career. If I was 40 years younger, I'd be right back there. But thank you, Rory. I appreciate that. Yeah, thank you, Rory. That's good. Well, Officer Smith, welcome aboard. Can someone make a motion to adjourn? And we can go and celebrate the holiday. Yep, I'll make a motion to adjourn the meeting.
Very good. And I'll second the motion. All right. Motion approved. Hi. All right. Thank you very much, everyone. Thank you. Happy holidays to you. Thank you for all the work you've done this year. January starts a new year. It'll be time to slay the dragon all over again. Yep. There you go. Right. Ciao.