to the flag of the United States of America, and to the republic for which it stands, one nation under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all. Mr. Skerry, would you please call the roll? Mrs. Cuno. Present. Mr. Benedetto. Present. Ms. Kretz. Present. Ms. Mustone. Present. Mr. Skerry, present. Ms. Vander Kloot. Present. Mayor Burke.
6 present, 1 absent. We have a forum to connect meeting. We're going to start with item number 1, approval of the minutes of March 7, 2016. Move approval. Move approval for Mr. Skerry, all in favor? Second. All opposed? Motion passes.
Mr. Cuneo. Yes. Mr. Benedetto. Yes. Ms. Kretz. Yes. Mr. McStone. Yes. Mr. Skerry. Yes. Ms. Vander Kloot. Yes. Mayor Burke. Yep. She's right there. Approval of payrolls. Motion of approval. Do we call the roll? Yes. Yes. We'll call the roll. Mr. Cuneo. Yes. Mr. Benedetto. Yes. Ms. Kretz. Yes. Mr. McStone. Yes. Mr. Skerry. Yes. Ms. Vander Kloot. Yes.
I'd like to move so Mayor Burke can please note on the agenda that Mayor Burke is in attendance and I'll step aside. Thank you very much.
Report of the Secretary. There's none. None. Report of the Committee. Committee of the Whole report, March 9, 2016. Mr. Superintendent. We can either waive the reading or the Secretary can read it or someone else can read it. Waive the reading. Mr. Superintendent, the notes were included in the file. I believe all the members have read them. If there's any questions, we'll let them take them. Motion to waive the reading. Second. It's been moved, seconded. All those in favor? Aye.
approval of the minutes of March 9, Committee of the Whole. On the motion for approval, all those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Motion carries. Community participation. Hearing and seeing none. Reports of the superintendent. Report on EOS Healthy Start Award. Mr. Superintendent. Madam Mayor, members of the committee, we'll call in our assistant superintendent.
Dwayne Caldwell to deliver this report. Good evening. Good evening. We are very proud that the Columbus Elementary School is the recipient of the 5-year College of Health and Humanity award. This award is going to be used in our mission to develop a quality foundation that is great in the psychological quality of our children.
is mass school-based leaders who contributed to the educational success by addressing their nutritional needs. So more than 80% of the children at the Columbus Elementary School participated in a breakfast program. So these successful breakfast programs require the investment and the collaboration of a group of people. It is the secretary,
the administrators, the teachers, the school cafeteria workers, and the school nurse. So it was a team effort done by everybody. The following members of the Columbus Elementary team will be going to an award ceremony on May 5th at the Statehouse. And the people that will be attending
are Nancy Sherman Hudson, the assistant principal, Rory Douglas, who is head of the cafeteria at the Columbus Elementary School, and Karen Roberto, who is the Columbus School nurse. Medford State representatives Paul Donato, Christine Barber, and Sean Garberlee, and State Senator Patricia Jalen will also be in attendance. So we're very proud of the Columbus Elementary School. This is an unrestricted $500 that they get to spend as they wish.
have to take any questions. Ms. Cuno? No, I'm all set. Thank you. Ms. Mastone? No, you're good.
Mr. Benedetto. Thank you. I just want to comment that this just shows what teamwork does in our community. I'm so happy to hear that everybody works together to make this such a great success. Our children really, some children really, the only place they get food in the morning is at school. Either they're too quickly out the door or some families might not have the money. So these things really do matter to everyday life of our children.
And as we all know, breakfast is the most important meal of the day, so it's great that our kids get started. The McGlynn Elementary School also has a breakfast program, and the Roberts School now qualifies for a breakfast program. That's great. I hope someday all our schools can get breakfast for us, too. Well, we do serve breakfast, but this is Universal Free Breakfast, so it's a great thing.
Thank you. Thank you. Is there a motion to receive the report? Motion to receive the report and seconded by Ms. Vandekloot. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion passes. Report on Park MCAS 2016 schedule and related matter. Mr. Superintendent. Members of the committee, we're in the middle of MCAS season. Park season is on the way. And there are a number of issues associated with it. Our director of curriculum, Bernadette Riccardelli, will be giving you this report and informing you how things are going.
Good evening, Mayor Burke, Superintendent Bellson, and members of the Medford School Committee. So I'm here tonight to give you some information on the standardized testing schedule. So in your report, the first page is a cover page, and then beyond that, the next six pages, front and back, is the statewide testing schedule put out by the Department of Education.
It was put out on January 26th, so it is the most current schedule that is available. So it identifies PARCC testing dates as well as MCAS testing dates.
Following that publication from the Department of Education, so on the following page, where it says 2016 Park MCAS testing dates, that's for our district, for Medford. So what I've done is I've gotten the information from each one of the principals, and I've put it in a succinct form so that you can see the testing dates for each one of the schools. On that first page, we have the Brooks, McGlynn, Columbus, and Roberts Elementary School.
For English Language Arts and Mathematics, PARC will be taken and for Science, MCAS will be taken for those dates. You will see that there are also dates in several cases for makeup testing and in some cases the makeup testing dates are still TBD to be determined.
On the next page, we have the schedule for the middle schools and the high school. And as you probably know, because I think it was mentioned before, the Andrews Middle School is the only school in the district that is going to do computer-based testing. The McGlynn Middle School is doing paper-based testing. Again, both schools are administering the PARC for English Language Arts and Mathematics and MCAS for Science.
Medford High School, Medford Vocational Technical High School, and the Curtis Tufts School are all administering MCAS. Last week, we had the English Language Arts test that took place on the 22nd, 23rd, and 24th of the month. In May, we have mathematics, and in June, we have science. And the makeup test dates for that assessment at the high school level are to be determined.
Moving on to the second part of my report, which has to do with the Park MCAS opt-out option, if you will, or information. Much of this report comes directly from the Department of Education, from Commissioner Chester. So in his publication, in the commissioner's update that he puts out, he has identified state law as the basis
for saying that participation in standardized testing is mandatory. The statute, he writes, does not contain an opt-out provision for parents to remove their children from participating. So he's citing Mass General Law's Chapter 69, Section 11 for that statement. And he references the landmark 1993 Massachusetts Education Reform Act as the basis.
As you know and as I've mentioned, we have selected PARCC for 2016. So again, grades 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, and 8 are administering PARCC for English Language Arts, Arts and Mathematics, and Science for MCAS. So we had that option. We are held harmless for our participation in PARCC.
So I'm going to go down to the next part of the report where, and I'm going to read this verbatim because it comes directly, again, from the commissioner.
So in his guidance, he has written the following. In some instances, a student may refuse to take a test either of his or own volition or at the direction of a parent. In these cases, the Department of Ed, or I should say the Board of Education, asks principals to encourage parents to rethink their refusal and remind them that the assessments are a valuable gauge of their students' and schools' progress.
We ask principals and test proctors to handle refusals with sensitivity. Students should not be pressured to take the test, nor should they be punished for not taking the test.
They may sit quietly and read in the testing room, but if they are distracting others in the class who are taking the test, it would be appropriate for them to move to another location within the school with adult supervision. There is no requirement to provide formal or informal instruction to these students during the test period. Having them do work or read a book is sufficient, provided that the material is separate from the content being assessed on that day.
So he issued this guidance in response to a number of inquiries about whether or not opting out of mandated state assessment was required. He then identifies why student participation in these tests is essential, as you can see in your report. The results of these assessments provide valuable feedback to districts, to administrators, and to students and parents about
about their achievement or lack thereof.
They write, he writes, legislators and taxpayers expect an objective assessment of student and school performance in return for very significant investment of public funds. So in other words, the public wants to know how our students are doing. We are concerned about the following. A low participation rate on the statewide assessments can adversely affect a district's performance rating in the state and federal accountability system. So we are concerned that if our accountability, excuse me, if our attendance
participation rate is low, it could affect our accountability. We don't anticipate that the high school will be a problem. They are taking MCAS, but in the event that a parent were to opt out of the MCAS test for a grade 10 student, they would have a very difficult time earning a competency determination. Towards the end of the report, I reiterate that concern or that effect on accountability.
So it is important to keep in mind it is a mandated test backed up by law. However, as I have identified for you, the Commissioner of Education is cognizant of parent concerns and that's why he has issued the guidance that I presented to you. I'd be happy to take any questions at this time.
Mr. Benedetto. Um, through you to the superintendent, when we voted for the park, one of our, one of my colleagues had mentioned that we voted for our schools to take pen and pencil. Is the Andrews taking it electronically and do we need to revote if that's the case? The Andrews opted to take it on the computer because they felt they had the capacity to do it.
We allowed it because it would give us an opportunity to see how it would work. Paul DeLave is very good with computers and technology. We felt that it would give us a chance to explore the use of computers. I believe we mentioned it to you at one point.
I think that we voted for a pen-and-pen paper, so I think we might have to re-vote in order for that to happen. I think we voted in general to do that, and I think we did tell you that the answer was, but if we didn't, we can always vote.
I think we should. But I think it's a good idea to have at least one school try it so we can understand. I agree. And if we have a principal with that expertise and willing to take that on, and then we can determine what we need as a school department to move forward to have all of our tests done this way, I think it's a really good idea. But I just want to make sure that we follow the procedures and the will of the school committee as directed is carried out. Sure.
So I would like to make a motion at this time to allow the Iandros School to take the park test using computers. Ms. Cuno. Well, point of information, I believe I was the colleague that was discussing it because I was part of the committee at the ASC. The discussion was the frustration of schools taking the test at the time.
that were being told to take it via computer when they didn't have the facilities or the capability of doing it. I believe the discussion here was to allow our schools, if they have the capability of
do it online, then they should do it online. And I really don't think that there's a need of a motion because it's the principal who actually has requested that he does want to do this online, because they are able to do it with the computer systems that they have. The frustration was the opposite side of DESC just selecting or
I don't know if that's a good way to put it.
So thank you, Ann Marie, for that clarification. That makes a lot of sense. So technically, you know, I don't necessarily think we have to vote on it, but if my colleague wants to vote on it, there's no reason not to just vote on it and take it off, get it off our deck. So I'll second her motion so we vote on it. On the motion that the Andrews School be allowed to take the park exam this spring now on the computer as opposed to pen and paper. As planned. On the motion,
All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? The motion passes. Is there a motion on the floor to receive this report and place it on file? I had a question. Ms. Vandeply. So at this point, our principals have all been informed about how they should respond to a parent who requests that their child should not take the test.
So yes, at our last full administrative meeting, guidance was provided with the principal. I would defer to the language of the commissioner. It's pretty straightforward. It's public. It's on the site.
Again, our position is it's, we think it's an important test to take. Bernadette, yeah. I just, I guess, I just want to make sure that if a family does come forward and not want their child to take the test, that it's handled. And I did appreciate the line, you know, with sensitivity, so that neither the parent or the child is made to feel guilty about their choice not to take the test.
So I believe this exact text was presented to the administrators. I'd be happy to send it to them again. Do parents need to put it in writing that they don't want their child to take the test? Actually, they should put it in writing, and the commissioner would like principals to keep track of any request to opt out.
So again, there is concern that it could affect the accountability. But in one correspondence from the commissioner, he said document it. So I'm not sure if there is a great amount, if that would affect any decision. But parents should submit a letter to the principal stating an opt-out preference if that's what they want. OK, we don't have a form that they sign.
So I understand how important it is and we encourage parents to take it. I also understand all the arguments of the opt-out people. So I just want to make sure that students and that it is handled appropriately. And I would also like this committee to receive
after the testing cycle is done, obviously not names, but simply numbers at each school, if there are opt-outs at the schools, if we could receive a report. And at grade levels, please. Thank you.
On the motion as amended to receive a report subsequent to test taking of those, the numbers that opt out versus take. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? The motion passes. Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
Mr. Benedetto? It's about items that we request. Can I make a motion at this point to put that on our agenda? Requested items and any items that are tabled so that way they're a list of things every week and that way when someone requests something it's on the list and as we receive those documents it would come off the list. It's much easier to track.
On the motion to keep track of papers that are pending as well as papers that have been tabled, it would become part of the committee's meeting agenda. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Motion passes. There's a recommendation to approve vocational school MSBA statement of interest. Mr. Superintendent. Madam Mayor and members of the committee, this is the season where the Massachusetts School Building Authority
asks us to submit a statement of interest if we're contemplating possibly submitting a project. And the project we're contemplating submitting deals with the vocational school. Our director of the vocational school, Dr. Heidi Riccio, is here, and I'm going to ask her to come up and talk about the SOI that we want to submit with your approval. Ms. Riccio. Thank you, Superintendent Belson, Mayor Burke, and District Committee.
Medford Vocational Technical High School is seeking school committee approval to submit a statement of interest to the Massachusetts Building Association for the renovation of existing space and the increase of lab space for the STEM-related fields. Medford Public Schools opened the vocational school in 1970 after a major build that included the high school being on the same complex.
Throughout the years, MVTHS has added new programs based on workforce demands. However, there was not a strategic plan created to develop and grow programs or logistically place programs with like clusters. MVTHS intends to implement a strategic plan that would reorganize the vocational campus to embrace the need to move programs in cluster or academy type models.
The following are the potential academies. The Construction Academy would house carpentry, construction and craft labors, electrical, and HVAC. The Design and Visual Academy would include graphic communications, design and visual communications, media technology, which is also often known as TV production, computer programming, and web development.
In the Human Services Academy, it would house Health Assisting, Early Education and Childhood. In the Service Academy, it would house Business Technology, Cosmetology, Culinary Arts, Hospitality and Marketing. And the STEM Academy would include Biotechnology, Environmental Science, Robotics, Engineering, Metal Fabrication and Advanced Manufacturing.
MVTHS is planning to seek funding under priority number seven of the MSBA priorities, which states replacement of or addition to obsolete buildings in order to provide a full range of programs consistent with state and approved local requirements. This can also be found on the msba.org website.
Medford Public Schools believes that the following reasons are in order to seek funding under priority number seven. Number one, technology.
As the workforce has changed into the technological age within all technical areas, MVTHS must be able to provide access to its students and the community to sound technology advances. Additionally, appropriate security of the equipment and updated shutoffs are needed to ensure the safe operation of the building during school hours and through our growing adult education program.
Equipment. As part of this renovation and add-on space comes equipment that meets the demands of a changing workforce. While the district committee has been generous in its support of programs and the school has done a fabulous job of accessing grant funding and other alternative funding sources, there is a significant need to replace existing equipment that is obsolete with equipment that is currently used in industry.
Being a vocational high school in Massachusetts, it is essential to meet the needs of the existing and future workforce. To do this, MVTHS is seeking MSBA funding to add equipment that is part of each program and is consistent with other vocational schools across the commonwealth. ADA compliance. Accessibility to the building is in need of enhancement. Currently, the door handles, locks, and some areas of building access are not ADA compliant.
Additionally, hallway doors are in need of replacement, and doors leading into and through vocational programs need appropriate access points. Flooring in the vocational programs are mixed, as some have tile, which is in disrepair, and others have concrete. The intention is to replace the floors to meet current standards, and put appropriate flooring in vocational programs that meet industry needs. An example of this would be epoxy flooring in the auto technology program.
Additional space, MBTHS would like to add on to the existing third floor science lab space above the vocational main entrance to increase vocational offerings to both vocational and high school students. Currently, two programs are situated in one lab space. As enrollment grows, the need for additional space is necessary.
Adding to the third floor space would offer new labs and classrooms for biotechnology, environmental science, robotics and engineering, and give the option to add other STEM-related programs. Existing space reorganization.
When programs were added to MVTHS, Medford Public Schools considered open space that was available and not necessarily what was in the best interest of the program or service to the community. One example of this was the Construction and Craft Laborers Program. This program was situated above academic classrooms, yet they were using heavy equipment. The school plans to reorganize space so that it is logical and makes sense for all programs.
MSBA funding would provide the opportunity to incorporate deeper collaboration with the high school, expand our adult education offerings, and make certain programs like cosmetology, culinary arts, hospitality, and marketing accessible to the general public with separate entrance space. That is actually the first part of our MSBA. So we're going to save the second part on the studio until the next report.
OK. Thank you. Ms. Cuno. First and foremost, let me just say how amazed and thrilled I am. This is great news. The other things I do want to ask is, I know when we did the science labs in the science building, that particular grant was for that particular area. However, if there was anything that
overlapped or touched that building, it also was refurnished or redone. I remember the lights in the office of the high school because the ceiling of the high school office was actually the floor that abutted the science buildings.
was redone. So in this particular project, is it like that too? Is there anything above the other parts of a room that maybe isn't technically under the vocational school? Will they get redone? The first part is the intent to apply. So for us, it's to seek that intent. And then we would go into that phase of the actual space and what we would be looking at in altering or changing.
And when you're looking into this, are we going to make sure that everything matches? So since we have the science labs done, I know we're going to call them the new science labs probably for 50 years. But are we going to match that with the new renovations at the vocational side? So everything starts looking coincidentally the same. Absolutely. I think if you've walked down the building of the vocational school in the past couple of years, I do like matching.
Furniture and matching colors and we actually have a color scheme that is now specific to the school, which is nice because now you're not looking at a variety of different colors that may not be complementary to the eye.
However, an example of that is when we redid the health assisting lab, that door is actually the same door, and the keys are keyed the same as the science labs. So yes, the doors would look the same, the same color grain, et cetera, and the color schemes would be similar. Okay, that's great. And the other thing, I guess, because we are going to be touching
The cable station. How would that work out while it's under renovation? That would be the next topic. We're doing it in the next section? That's fine. Thank you. Thank you. Ms. Vander Kloof. So, Ms. Rich here, once again, you have brought us to the point where you have just pushed us forward and now have us...
headed into a direction for the future of our students and the well-being of them and what we offer in Medford or the possibilities of what we offer. Obviously, this is just the first step. First, a technical question. When do you have to file this statement of interest? What's the first deadline? April 10th. And could you need our approval on saying, yes, we're interested in moving forth?
There is no, obviously, no dollar amount or anything at this point. It's just simply we're interested. And what is the next step?
complete the letter of intent, the next step would for the MSBA to actually look at that letter of intent and look at the needs of the school and the why we are seeking it. And the vote, I believe, is not until 2017 for us to then move forward into the next phase. Does this need to go before the city council? Eventually. Yes. Eventually, but not before the letter of intent on April 10th.
I believe that we will, um, I'm going to let, I'm going to defer because I haven't been through this before in Medford. So the way it works is, is that the statement of interest goes in state, you know, to this, to the state, they determine whether or not it's even eligible, whether they would be willing to entertain it. We then, if we get to the next round, we'll start to put some other plans together and little by little, it'll move forward. If we get invited to submit some design, then we have to go to the,
to the City Council for money for design. And then if we get beyond design and they accept that, then we would go to construction documents. But right now, simply for tonight and to be able to move on, it's just, we can vote on this. And so I make a recommendation, a motion to approve. There's a motion on the floor for approval by Ms. Van de Kloot, seconded by Ms. Cuno. Mr. Benedetto. I just want to thank you for all your hard work in taking
us to these great opportunities. I know you've brought in a huge amount of grant funds already for our vocational school.
I appreciate the work of yourself and your staff. The school looks great. I was up there recently. All the colors do look great. And I hope that someone pays attention and sees our need and comes and really gives us money to help us build this, because this is a dream come true. Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you for being here. I also want to just make note that our staff member Richard Cormier did email all of us telling us how supportive he was. He unfortunately couldn't be here, but I just want to make note that he's excited and supports this project. The question I was hoping maybe by the next school committee is that I know vocational schools are becoming more popular. I hope that out of my six, half will be at the vocational school to have a
a trade after that. Is it possible to have a number of students in each program in what the capacity is? So if you have 10 in business technology, but what's the capacity if you've got a full house?
So the Department of Ed comes out with a recommendation per square footage and per program, and I can email that to you. It's pretty black and white. I would want all six of your children actually at the vocational school, because as you can see by the programs, they are college and career ready. And I thank Rich Cormier. I also have a culinary arts. I don't know if you saw her in the paper.
yesterday, but it was in the paper as well as in the Boston paper, but the Culinary Arts Program has been very helpful out in the community, and I can't, any of these grants were all co-written by the experts that are in the field, so I just have fairly good grammar, but really they're the ones that are giving me the content for the grant, so I have to thank all of the teachers and staff, because they've also renovated all of the space up until now, so everything you see was done by the staff and our students.
Good, thank you. There's a motion on the floor for approval. Roll call vote, please, Mr. Skerry. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Seven in the affirmative, none in the negative. The motion passes. Good luck. Thank you. We await the answers. Report on the construction status of the multimedia community access channel. Mr. Superintendent. Madam Mayor and members of the committee,
We've been working on this project for a little while now in conjunction with City Hall, Louise Miller, Scott Payette from the architectural firm, and Dr. Riccio and members of our media and technology staff to put together various aspects of this program. We're about to begin
some early construction with abatement process during the school vacation, so that we can get things going. You see from the charts up there, we have a timeline that we hope to finish construction sometime by the end of the summer, and then begin the process of populating the place and getting things operational sometime in early October. So we're going to turn it over to Dr. Riccio again to tell you a little bit about how that's going to proceed, so that you get an idea of where we are with the multimedia,
and with the Access Channel. Thank you again. I will say that when we did start this process, we went out to at least five different schools across the Commonwealth to look at what their TV studio looked like, and many of them did have the public education and government component within those.
programs and that kind of jump started our thought process on location and what they learned from having it on site at a school. So we did get some very helpful information that started two years ago. Over the course of the last two years, we worked with the former mayor as well as the new mayor, Mayor Burke.
school department and other members of the community to really look at what we need. We knew that we wanted to start a Chapter 74 vocational program. The actual certification is called radio and TV production or broadcasting, but we wanted to incorporate media technology as well into it, knowing that this is really a digital world.
and how we could do as many crossovers within the curricular as we could with other programs, including design and visual. So as you saw in my last report, looking at that whole entire academy model, the TV studio would encompass that. So the report on the TV studio is that MVTHS is excited to report that construction will begin on the new access television studio in April.
During April's school vacation, the studio will receive abatement of asbestos. Timing was determined for April break as to minimize the disruption in programming. Plans are in the final stages of development, as you can see in your packet, as well as on the storyboards. And the bulk of the work will be done during the summer months, with the studio scheduled to open in September of 2016.
In 2014, MVTHS applied for program approval through the Massachusetts Department of Elementary and Secondary Education Chapter 74 process. This approval was put on hold until there was progress with the TV studio renovation due to classroom space.
While the high school currently has strong media courses, the intention is to work collaboratively with them to increase availability of courses and offer students a program where students can get certified in various software platforms. MVTHS will also be working closely with the local Access TV to bring educational programs to the community when it is fully operational.
The current plan is to have day access for students and evening access for local access, so there is no scheduling conflicts. Since the renovation project has a timeline for completion of September of 2016, MVTHS has posted for a teacher position that is dual licensed in TV production, but also design and visual communications.
We will be having an advisory board meeting for this program on April 26th in conjunction with the annual spring advisory meeting for other programs. The intent of this meeting is to receive final guidance as we move toward this program approval.
Once the licensed teacher is hired and the studio is near completion, the Department of Elementary and Secondary Education will be scheduled to come in for a site inspection. It is during this site inspection that the Massachusetts Department of Elementary and Secondary Education reviews the facility, curriculum, and instruction in support of the community for the program. And as you can, I think you have it all in your packets. It's a color.
duplicate of what these storyboards state and we can certainly review those if you would like. So the first section is the timeline, as you can see in your packet. We are scheduling the construction and the first phase would be the asbestos.
And we chose to do this during April vacation when students are out of the building, but we will be completely containing that area so there is no access to that area while we are doing that.
We will then move into, obviously I can't speak for the whole RFP of contractors because that's all done through the City Hall and Louise Miller's office, but once that is complete, the idea is to begin construction since we do have the final phase drawings in the summer of 2016 with completion of September of 2016. Ms. Cuneo?
Again, this is wonderful news. I know before we had discussed it, it was going to be open to both sides. I just want to make sure that both the high school side and the vocational students have the opportunity to work in this studio. So that's one that I want to confirm. Absolutely. And the other thing is that I know that it's also open to our public.
And in the lieu of it being renovated, is there another place where anybody could go to use any of the equipment per se? Maybe not in the whole realm of the spectacular way that we're going to be doing it, but at least some place where our students and maybe even the public could go and do something.
So I'm going to defer, because where I'm the director of the vocational school, my primary focus is to start programs within the school setting, so the educational component of it, and not necessarily the government or public access. All right. So through the mayor to the superintendent, yes?
What was your question again, please? It was just basically, is there any place that anyone could go to while this is under renovation so they could do it? There's no equipment set up right now, so it will be upon the opening, which we're projecting October. OK. Mr. Benedetto. Thank you. Do we have any cost estimates of this?
through you, Madam Mayor, to the superintendent, what the estimated cost of all of this is gonna be and how we're funding this. I just want it to be clear and out there so all questions are answered.
We have quite a bit of funding in our community access account, and that's what we would be using to build out this, because that is the purpose. That's what I assumed. I just didn't. So there's no cost to the taxpayers. So that way, it's on record that this isn't coming out of the school-specific budget. It's a program that's going to generate education and value to both our school and to our community.
And I think it's a great program for our students and a great educational value because there are a lot of jobs that we can send people out and a lot of students will study this forward in college as well as use it as a technical skill if they choose not to go to college.
So I think it's a great opportunity for both the school district as well as the city as a whole. I know at some point it's not gonna be just the school committee that decides on all of this and we're gonna have to work either with the city council or bring it forward to them after we do our share. Is that correct? The contract lies with the mayor's office. Okay. Thank you. Thank you.
Are there any other questions from the members? Ms. Biandiclu? I'll hold mine. Excuse me? I'll hold it. You'll hold. Thank you, Ms. Riccio. Thank you. I believe there's a citizen that would like to speak. Name and address for the record, please. Yes, Your Honor. Joe Villione, 59 Garfield Ave. I want to thank Ms. Riccio for her presentation.
As many know that I've been fighting for this, and I've spoken to the school committee for many years, I'm a little shocked that it's going to take until September or October. We need access TV now. We have students playing sports that are just not going taped, not going preserved. There's many, many reasons why we need public access television in the city, and I propose that we have a satellite office.
Very simple, we get a van, very small van. We work with the library and the Chevalier. We can get $7,000 cameras, very inexpensive. They run over the cellular lines. So I've been at the mass access conference and I met with many dealers there. They have this equipment. We could be up and running immediately.
We could have a city-operated station. We could have a privately-operated station, a nonprofit as we had before, only one that runs correctly. I know that the mayor is on board with this. I think we really owe it to the public to expedite this. Now, a van with these cameras, these beautiful new cameras, would fit perfectly with what you're doing. So we're not altering the plan at all. We're just adding to it, having a small van. I estimate we need about $60,000, $70,000 for two or three of these $7,000 cameras.
Maybe put some computers at the library, and I did speak to Barbara Kerr about this, and I said it would be very easy because you can help renovate the library with some of the access monies we have. Have two or three computers here so the kids can edit, but they can tape from the van. I just asked this honorable school committee to consider it.
It's important. We would have access right away. We would work with the Chevalier, the library, and then it would fit so nicely. It's perfect synergy with the high school. Thank you. Thank you. Ms. Zantaclou.
No, I just wanted to express my thanks to Heidi once again for bringing forth our report. I think that the proposal from Mr. Biglioni sort of almost goes outside of the school committee purview at this time, because right now our project and our sites are really looking forward to
what we're doing at the school and the educational benefits to the students. And I don't want to throw something together even if it has merit that we're not really quite ready to do at this point.
know how quickly the rest of the school year will go. And while I know it's been very, very frustrating for you and many in the community who are looking forward to a broader access TV, I think that, you know, I'm really putting, I want to put my eggs in this basket right now.
Again, I don't know because there's a lot of things I simply don't know about the proposal, how much a van would cost, who would drive the van, all of those sorts of issues, and I think that goes actually beyond us right at the moment. Thank you. There's a motion on the floor for approval, receive and place on file. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Motion passes.
Report on the construction status, I'm sorry, report on new opiate bill House 4056 and Medford implementation. Mr. Superintendent. Madam Mayor and members of the committee, I passed out this evening some additional documents. One is from the legal office of the MASS, along with the Detroit LLP, Leslie Carey being the particular writer. Another is a document that I gave you.
two-sided, that update some of the substance abuse programs that we have put in place this year based on last year's budget, including the Michigan model, and other things, programs that are coming up, including mention of April 2nd's meeting on the addiction program that will be held in the Caron Theater. But we'll go into that a little bit. So there's additional programs.
and things that I want you to pay attention to. There's also an item on the city council tomorrow night asking for some information on what we're doing and, with the mayor's permission, I might send some of this material along to them to keep them involved and perhaps invite them to the
Angle's second presentation. Dr. Robert Brooks is there. Dr. Robert Brooks is perhaps one of the most eminent psychologists in the area. We're dealing with adolescents and children, and he was the director of McLean's, but he's also very well known for all his other work, including with substance abuse. So... Point of information, Mr. Benedetto.
So today was the deadline for registering for the April 2nd. So you may just want to call. It's wide open. I called today just to register to make sure that I had space. But that's what the brochure says. So if there is more room, we should let people know. We'll just put out more information.
they should at least call and register that they're coming and that they plan to attend and which of the five speakers they want to hear. So it's just helpful to them for planning purposes for Saturday. We'll put that up. OK. Thank you. Put that up. Now, on March 14, 2016, Governor Baker signed House 4056, which is entitled NAC, relative to substance use treatment
education, and prevention. The legislation passed both House and Senate unanimously. The act is more popularly known as the Opium Bill. It's formally listed as Chapter 52 of the Acts of 2016, and with a few exceptions, it became effective immediately, and a preamble to it that makes it effective immediately.
So I've attached the legislative bulletin that you would normally receive from MASC. You may already have it, but just in case you haven't seen it yet, it's attached as well from legal counsel Stephen J. Finnegan. It highlights the pertinent portions of the new law that impact the schools of the commonwealth. So I'm going to talk about some of the specific elements that affect public schools and provide you with a status update as to where we stand as a school district. Schools are required,
to notify parents, guardians, and all attending students regarding our substance abuse policy. This policy must also be posted on our website. This policy must be filed with DESE. We will be posting our policy after tonight. And of course, we'll also hold a meeting to review it and see if we want to make any changes to it, or adjustments to it, or upgrade at any given point in time. But we'll use the current policy to at least meet that immediate requirement after this evening.
And then when Destiny gives us some more guidance, we will follow up the policy to them. They have some of their own ideas, and I'm sure that we will try to incorporate them as well. It's in the handbooks, distributed to students and families. It's also contained within our online policy manual.
And we'll highlight that policy to make it more prominent and visible to students and parents by putting some kind of thing on the front page so people will go to it without having to go into each school. Dessie, in consultation with the Department of Public Health, is instructed to provide guidance and recommendations to assist schools with the development of effective school policies and practices regarding substance abuse prevention and education.
ESRI tells me that DESI will take five, six months to get there. Because that's typical, you know, as they convene meetings and so on and so forth. So we can generally expect a five to six month time frame for DESI to give us real guidance. They may give us some preliminary things, but real guidance will take a few months. And we'll continue to work cooperatively with DESI and DBH as we go forward.
Currently, we have taken the following steps with DPH, and this is done through Tony Vento's office. Some of this you already know, but I'm going to repeat it so that everyone has a chance to hear it as well while we're listening at home. All nurses are now trained to administer Narcan. Narcan supplies are available at each of our schools. Training was provided by Armstrong Ambulance at no cost.
Narcan was purchased through CVS at a reduced cost using grant funding from our Central School Health Services grant funding. It's a grant we get every year. Naturally, we track it in the budget. It's in there right now in the governor's budget, but we'll see what happens when it goes through the legislature. I would expect them to sustain that particular line item. We also got a grant from the Central Schools Health Services grant.
of $9,700 for support student screening planning costs under HESPR. That's the screening tool where parents can opt out if they want. It's like a five to 10 minute screening and we would keep it confidential and we report to people who have need as to what they can do. High school nurses have been trained on this particular screening procedure to meet initial DBH requirements, working with grade nine students to start
We expect to implement the training and screening during the 2016-2017 year at the high school as per DPH recommendations. Now, if you go into the actual state law, most schools don't have to do it in 2017, but we're ahead of the curve. We're going to start a little bit earlier. We're planning to train middle school nurses to meet the 2017 mandate for grade seven students.
Additional training to elementary nurses is possible, depending upon DPH mandates and recommendations. We don't know what their, what their preference is at this time. At our professional day on March 1st, 2016, we provided motivational interviewing training to our nurses to get them to work with the students and others to get them to be forthcoming. And we'll continue to prioritize social and emotional learning as one of our key initiatives in the school district.
We have to do this on an annual basis at two different grade levels by law. Parents can opt out in writing. All information obtained through the screening is confidential, except in case of medical emergencies. If something happens in a medical emergency, obviously you can't keep it confidential, you have to deal with it.
We're well ahead of the act. As explained above, we're moving in the direction of the law. The implementation of screening is subject to state appropriation and will not be generally required until 2017, 2018, if it's funded. So again, unfunded mandates are often the case in the Commonwealth. If they don't fund it, it may not be required, but we will try to keep it in place, and like I said, we're ahead of the curve right now. There is a good Samaritan cause.
Section 12FF that absolves any person who in good faith attempts to render emergency care by Narcan from liability except for gross negligence and or willful or wanton misconduct.
So I've attached additional information for you. On Sunday, April 2nd, 2016, the Medford Public Schools, through the Bloomberg Center for Civic and Social Responsibility, will offer a workshop program on addiction, and Dr. Robert Brooks is the featured speaker. I have his resume and some information here for you. As you know, the Medford Public Schools has implemented the Michigan model curriculum. The program is a comprehensive approach to health, wellness, and good decision-making.
We're giving great emphasis to social and emotional learning. We've added counseling assistance to our faculty, and we're close with many external agencies. So we're committed to working with the community to move this forward. I'll call your attention to some of the things that I brought to you tonight. This document is a memo from me, an update, and I just bring a couple of things to you. The Michigan model is piloted in all our elementary schools this year. There are 13 teachers who are
piloting it at this point in time. They're also comparing it to second step and to see which things cross over. They'll evaluate each lesson and choose lessons that they think will be most effective with the students. Middle school and high school students are in full implementation of the MidMichigan model at this time. If only a Wahlberg Foundation opiate awareness video was added to the sophomore curriculum at the high school.
Vaping, more dangerous than you think, or vaping, if you will. Video is added to the sophomore curriculum as well. Youngsters who inhale things. Presentations. End the stigma of addiction. Substance abuse prevention projects were unveiled at an event at Memphis C Hall on February 3rd, 2016. Michael Sporker of the MHS team and MHS students of the Gay-Straight Alliance shared their stories of family and friends with addictions.
There's an addiction symposium on the second, I've already referenced that. Grants, partnership for success grant for preparation, prevention of prescription drug misuse among youth was awarded to the city of Bedford. Penny Bonioli, Brooke Hoyt.
Lisa Van Doyen, Rachel Perry, John Perot, and Heidi Riccio, Amelia Jensen, and Tony Vento are working on a plan to implement evidence-based prevention programs, policies, and practices to reduce prescription drug misuse amongst persons age 12 to 25 years old. So another initiative underway. The Safe and Supportive School Grant, we applied for this at the end of November 2015. It's yet to be awarded for all four elementary schools. We'll wait to hear what happens with that.
We've got an MIA workshop, The Face of Addiction, The Opioid Crisis, The Journey from Painkillers to Addiction. It'll be led by health teacher Ellen Ridden, and it'll be done in May of 2016. There's another program called Heat Heroin Education Awareness Task Force Conference on Friday, June 17th, and we will have people from our staff attend that conference. So we're very active right now. There's a lot going on. This is something that we take very seriously,
whether it's drugs, alcohol, whatever it is, we're taking it very, very seriously, and we believe we're ahead of the curve. I'm willing to answer any questions you may have. Mr. Skerry. And if I may, through you to the superintendent, Mr. Belson, I would suggest that a copy of this package be given to our director of public information. I found this package to be very stimulating and
I think that we should have a concerted effort with our media to get this message out to parents and concerned citizens and anyone that might have missed it and to reassure them that we are working towards hopefully not having any tragic cases here in Medford. But if they do, at least they'll know where to go to get information and they know that we do have a substance abuse policy in place and who they might contact or how they might gain further information to help their own children.
It will be on the website this week. It will also be out to the media this week. And we will also be sending things with the permission of the mayor to the council tomorrow night.
This is absolutely wonderful. This is something that I know is a collaboration of the school district and with the help of everyone in the community. This is something that we've all been waiting for because, again, it's wonderful that people do things and we have different clubs and organizations that do things separately, but I think the power in this is that we do it all together and I think this is a great program to start with, or not actually start with because I know
We've been doing quite a lot for quite a while. I just wanted to clarify, Mr. Superintendent, you said Sunday, April 2nd, and I just want to make sure that people understand it's Saturday. Saturday the 2nd. We'll clean up. Thank you. You're welcome. Ms. Mastone? I know at the Roberts, some of my kids have the Michigan model, and it's just that the classroom teaches when she has time to fit it in. It's not really
It's up to the classroom teacher. But when does the middle school and high school get Michigan model? Is it more structured? They have it part of their health classes. OK. So is that once a week or? Depends on how the schedule is set up, but generally once a week. So it's probably more consistent than? It's consistent. Each school has a little bit different approach to delivering the health program. OK. But they schedule it generally once a week. OK. Mr. Benedetto. Thank you. Mr. Bell said?
I didn't see a copy of our policy. We'll send it along. We didn't encode it with this. Yeah, I'm asking you to please. It's a little different to school to school. I mean, from high school to now. OK, I'd like to see that before it's posted. You can send it up. OK. Thank you. On the motion to receive and place on file, all those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? The motion passes.
Report on Brooks Maintenance Issue. Mr. Superintendent. Okay, we're going to call on our assistant superintendent, Diane Caldwell, to deliver this report. It was partially put together by John McLaughlin, who's covering you on camera, so if you need John, he's on the other end. Okay?
Maybe I could do the cameras and John could do the microphone out here. I just wanted to provide you with a timeline on the Brooks maintenance issue that we had. On Wednesday, March 9th at 8.30, water began to come up through the floors in the student bathrooms and in the kitchen of the Brooks Elementary School.
Mr. Kevin Andrews is the principal of the school, and he contacted me immediately, as well as John McLaughlin and the superintendent. And we decided to call in the drain doctor to see if it would be a quick fix.
Mr. Andrews contacted Medford School Food Services after we realized that it was going to take a little more time, and we knew that we had to have lunches prepared by the food service. Jewel Bradley and her staff, very quickly, this was maybe at 10 o'clock, Mr. Andrews and I decided it was time to provide 300 lunches for our students at the Brooks Elementary School. And they were sandwiches and yogurt and other fruits.
Ms. Kim Fowler from the Board of Health investigated the Brooks School site, reviewed the food preparation, and then recommended next steps for us.
Mr. Andrews was very good at sending emails out to the families of the Brooks School, and he also sent a hard copy letter home just to inform our families of what was going on. And overnight, the blockage was cleared. It was determined that a large amount of paper towels were stuck in the waistline.
The evening custodians clean the remaining water on the kitchen floor and in the first floor bathrooms. And I really have to congratulate the custodial staff at the Brooks School. They work very hard, the day custodial staff as well as the evening.
So on Thursday, March 10th, Ms. Fowler visited again to review what needed to be completed in the storeroom. The principal and John McLaughlin developed a work plan that was approved by the Board of Health, and this included using plastic to block off the storeroom and kitchen office, removing wallboard and insulation, allowing it to dry, and then replacing it with wallboard and insulation.
Mr. Andrews sent another email out to families just to notify them that the kitchen would still not be available and would remain closed. So for the next few days, we communicated with Ms. Jewel Bradley, and she was able to prepare lunches for our kids, peanut butter and jelly and yogurt, as I said before.
Ms. Fowler returned on March 15th for another inspection. She determined that the unpainted wall board would need to be covered with plastic and taped to the floor, and all the surfaces needed to be re-cleaned. At 3.30 p.m., the school was cleared for food preparation.
And Mr. Andrews then sent an email out to the school families at 7 o'clock that evening to inform them that food preparation was good to go for the next day. I'd like to call your attention to the attached report, which is from John McLaughlin, our Director of Buildings and Grounds. And he could tell you a little more about the maintenance and the cleanup and the cost. In the last week, all drains connected to our schools have been inspected and flushed.
This preventative measure should help to avoid a similar situation going forward. Thank you, Ms. Caldwell. Are there any questions? Hi, Madam Mayor. Mr. Skerry. To either Ms. Caldwell or the superintendent, was there any investigation as to why there was a large amount of paper towels stuck in the waistline? This is probably a John McLaughlin question, but
I don't know the answer to that. I mean, they tried to get it out with just the drain doctor, and that didn't work, so they had to call in Paulette. It seems like an awfully large amount of paper towels to be where they're not supposed to be. It was an awfully large bill for the city. There was work being done on the street. Excuse me, Mr. Scott. There was work being done on the street as well, so I was wondering if that had any input, but I was told no, it didn't.
I just want to comment, if I can, that with the help of the DPW and the mayor's office, we had all the drains cleared going into every school. So it became a preventative kind of thing in case it was happening someplace or about to happen someplace else.
I can certainly do that for you, Mr. Skerry. Thank you. Ms. Krentz? I have a point of information that I know at the vocational school, they have some of the power dryers now in some of the bathrooms. So that might be a nice thing, a nice change for the future, instead of the because they were having problems with paper towels. So yeah. Thank you, Ms. Caldwell. Thank you. Is there a motion to receive in place on file?
Seconded by Ms. Cuno. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion passes. We also have a few announcements that the superintendent wants to comment on. Mr. Superintendent. Thank you, Madam Mayor and members of the committee. You have a paper in your folder about the field trip to Washington and the reimbursements. The checks are out there.
And we'll find out if they didn't. But right now, Pat did a great job pulling it together, and we're sitting all to ensure that everyone got their check. And the total amount was $3,680. Thank you, Pat. That's one. The second thing is, is that the day on the Hill is in 2016. There's now a paper in your folder. It's April 26. If you want to go, you've got to let us know so we can make
arrangements for you to sign up, and I want you to go to the Day on the Hill as a registered member as opposed to somebody who just walks in and has to leave, okay? You did it yourself? You didn't ask permission? I'm just kidding. No, it's okay. I just wanted to know what happened from the Day on the Hill.
On the day on the hill, basically it's a day for the school committee members to meet legislators, to talk about issues, and to perhaps share with other school committee members from other communities things that are of mutual concern. You know, Ann Marie is former president of NASC, Paul Wetzel has been a member of the executive board for a period of time, and they can certainly share ideas with you as to how to make that day effective if you want to come. Okay?
So Then we've got something on the Mathematics middle school mathematics and pathways to high school mathematics on Thursday April 14th from 7 to 8 p.m. The science lecture hall we're inviting up Middle high school students up to see things and to talk about
It's scheduled for the middle school. So middle school students can see our science labs and see what's going on. It's April 14th.
It's listed here, it's 7 to 8 p.m. Thursday, April 14th. Okay, so that's that. And you also have in your packet a copy of the latest teacher's contract that's been made, so in case you need a copy of that. We can't get these on the city side. What? I said we can't get these on the city side. It's quite nice. Name was spelled incorrectly?
It must be the Teachers Association did this. Blame the Teachers Association. Where's Shelby? All right, so we'll try and correct it. Mr. Benedetto. I also wanted to announce that the Method Against Addiction annual, second annual candlelight vigil is April 17th. And just to keep people up to date what's going on within the city.
We have a meeting next week and the week after. So we have a number of things coming to you. And we'll be working on that over the next few days. So we've got a busy schedule over the next two weeks for the holiday break. And we're giving you stuff as well. Mayor Byrd, last item on the agenda is negotiation.
Okay, so that's a subcommittee. Well, it's up to you. Let me know and we'll schedule it.
So we'll schedule it whenever you schedule the last one. Whatever you want to schedule, we'll schedule it. I'll talk to you.
Ms. Cuno. I just want to recognize a couple of things that happened that we haven't had the opportunity to speak about, but I did receive a few emails today stating that parents had gone up to the high school and they were very impressed with the fact that they had to buzz themselves in and that they needed to get guest passes to go where they needed to go. So they were very pleased and the feedback on that has been very positive. The other thing I just want to throw in is,
We sit here this evening and we listen to what's happening as far as these projects that are coming. And you go outside of the district and then you see really how lucky we are. I've been on the college tour right now with my twins.
And we just went to a smaller college, but it was really interesting seeing the reaction of students when the students that are there are saying that they're graduating in about a month and a half. And they're so excited because they're going to be building a new project.
And that building is going to be about $5 million or $6 million. And it happened to be adjacent to one of their science buildings. So I kindly sat there proudly and said, you know, we're from Medved. And we just built one for $17 million. So it just opens up your eyes of what we have, where we're going, and how fortunate we are on many things that sometimes we really don't see the big picture.
Very good. There's a motion to go into executive session. Moved by Mr. Scarry, seconded by Ms. Van de Kloot. Roll call, please. Yes, seven in the affirmative, none in the negative. We are entering executive session. We may possibly come back out to the floor.