[SPEAKER_06]: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20!
[SPEAKER_06]: 20 different things!
[SPEAKER_06]: Miss Dunphy, how many yoga poses can you do?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yoga poses?
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, over 100.
[SPEAKER_06]: Let's go with 20.
[SPEAKER_05]: 20 different figures!
[SPEAKER_05]: Miss Glosser, how many stars are up here?
[SPEAKER_05]: Um, like 100, 150 maybe?
[SPEAKER_05]: No, 20.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mine is the 20th star.
[SPEAKER_02]: And we're happy to welcome you to the 20th Mustang Report.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hi, I'm Gigi Braga here with MHTV 15.
[SPEAKER_04]: Today we're here with Julie Grimm, who's the new mindful instructor with us here at Medford High.
[SPEAKER_04]: How are you today?
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm doing well, thanks Gigi.
[SPEAKER_04]: So Julie, tell us a little bit about what brought you here to this program to open up at Medford High.
[SPEAKER_02]: So actually, coincidence brought me here.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's another meditation teacher who maybe you'll be interviewing later, Seth Monk.
[SPEAKER_02]: who invited me to a professional development day workshop about a month ago.
[SPEAKER_02]: And we helped the teachers discuss about what is meditation and then also have a short meditation session themselves so they could experience the benefits.
[SPEAKER_02]: And well, I guess I only heard back from the people who really loved it, but it seemed like it was really well received.
[SPEAKER_02]: People really felt like it was making a great change in their day, just this few minutes of meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: helping them to relax and to center.
[SPEAKER_02]: And started talking with Dr. Perella, your headmaster, about how we can bring this in on a more consistent and regular basis and give teachers tools for themselves that they can then bring into their classrooms to help with students.
[SPEAKER_04]: All right.
[SPEAKER_04]: So give us a little bit of like a snippet of what this program is that you are introducing to our high school.
[SPEAKER_02]: All right, so the program, it's pretty new.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was just born.
[SPEAKER_02]: Today is my first day.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it's still really in this process of unfolding.
[SPEAKER_02]: But essentially, two days of the week, Wednesdays and Thursdays, either I or another teacher, Seth Monk, who you'll probably interview, will be in the school as a resource for students and teachers to help talk about meditation, mindfulness,
[SPEAKER_02]: and the different social and emotional components that come with that added awareness.
[SPEAKER_02]: So in the mornings, both he and I will be teaching teachers meditation with the option of maybe doing that in the afternoon as well and maybe also for students if there's enough interest.
[SPEAKER_02]: I know the seniors seem to have a lot of stress on their plates.
[SPEAKER_02]: But otherwise, we're available during the day for different periods of time to either come in with the classes and work with them or have them visit us.
[SPEAKER_02]: We're mostly in the gymnastics, gymnasium, and as it gets warmer, I also really hope that we can do walking meditations outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: The answer is a pre-assembled base foundation.
[SPEAKER_01]: What that means is this goes into the ground, the base goes in this slot right here, and the dirt level is right to about the top of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you take the base out,
[SPEAKER_01]: You put the flowering in, so the next day when you're looking for the bass you'll find it.
[SPEAKER_04]: The question of the week is... How many marathons have I run?
[SPEAKER_06]: Hi, I'm Lydia, back again at the construction site for the Boston Care Project.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I'm here with Mr. Brown, the construction teacher.
[SPEAKER_06]: And he's here to give us a rundown on what this project is and what it's all about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hi, yes, today we are having volunteers from a software company locally called Nuance, and this is like a team building day, and they are here working as volunteers for an organization called Boston Cares.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they're actually building and fabricating beds that we manufactured the parts and pieces for in this shop.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're putting them together, assembling them, and then they will go out into the community, and they will be for needy families that need beds for children.
[SPEAKER_06]: What do you hope your students working on this project take away from doing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well of course we want them to recognize the importance of community service and doing things for other people that need it, but also they're getting some good practical skills and just the collaboration is really nice, working with professionals from a large corporation locally.
[SPEAKER_06]: Hi, this is Lydia Ryan again, and I'm here with Sean, a vocational student working on the Boston Cares project.
[SPEAKER_06]: Sean, what is your responsibility on the project?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, I'm painting right now, and we're going to do a first coat and then a second coat, and then put them away.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then we're going to disassemble them, put them on the truck we're standing in right now, and then they're going to have the matting put in.
[SPEAKER_05]: And what does this project mean to you?
[SPEAKER_05]: Helping out people, making a difference, helping the homeless in different communities.
[SPEAKER_05]: feeling really good about what I've done.
[SPEAKER_05]: I've noticed you have a hashtag be the change on your shirt and I was just wondering what that's all about.
[SPEAKER_05]: Being the change is making sure that you're the reason why the world's a better place or making a difference as we're doing right now in helping homeless kids.
[SPEAKER_05]: So I feel like I'm changing the world this way.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm here with Noah, another vocational student working on the project.
[SPEAKER_06]: Noah, what is your responsibility on the project?
[SPEAKER_03]: My responsibility is to move the finished pieces of wood over to the pile so they can be painted.
[SPEAKER_06]: What does this project mean to you?
[SPEAKER_03]: It means a lot because it's helping out the homeless families of the area and it's just great.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's great to see them have vets.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Glasser, Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Peter-Paul, I got into Harvard!
[SPEAKER_02]: Seriously?
[SPEAKER_06]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_06]: Bowler, I was not able to voice Mr. High.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh no!
[SPEAKER_06]: April Fools!
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh good!
[SPEAKER_03]: Jeez, this is really heavy.
[SPEAKER_05]: April Fools!
[SPEAKER_05]: Attention MHS, school has been cancelled for the remainder of the day.
[SPEAKER_06]: Mr. McLaughlin, there's no school!
[SPEAKER_07]: April Fools, guys!
[SPEAKER_07]: You're cleaning that up.