[SPEAKER_02]: your first and last name, your Medford street address, your question or comment.
[SPEAKER_02]: Roll call member Rousseau please.
[SPEAKER_00]: Certainly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Bramley.
[SPEAKER_01]: Present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Graham.
[SPEAKER_01]: Here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Ntapa.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Olapade.
[SPEAKER_02]: Here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Rheinfeld.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Rousseau present, Mayor Lungo here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Present, seven present, zero absent.
[SPEAKER_02]: If we all may rise to salute the flag.
[SPEAKER_02]: I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America, to the republic for which it stands, one nation under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all.
[SPEAKER_02]: and we have executive session pursuant to chapter 30A, section 21.2, to conduct strategy and preparation with non-union personnel or contract negotiations with non-union personnel, which is our superintendent of schools.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there a motion to go into executive session?
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion to go into executive session.
[SPEAKER_02]: Second.
[SPEAKER_02]: Member Reinfeld, seconded by Member Graham.
[SPEAKER_02]: Roll call, please.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Braley?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Graham?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Ntapa?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Olapade?
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Rheinfeld?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Members of the guest, Mayor Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, I'm in the affirmative, zero in the negative.
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion to go into executive session has been approved.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do we want to tell anybody who's watching that we will not be returning at the end of executive session?
[SPEAKER_02]: Correct, we are going into executive session and we'll adjourn in executive session.