All right, sounds good.
In that case, I call the, I believe this is still July, yes, the July 2025 Medford Bicycle Advisory Commission meeting to order.
Secretary, will you please call the roll?
Daniel Nizzle-Miller, chair.
Present.
Emilio Bryan, vice chair, not present.
Bruce Kulik, secretary, present.
Jared Powell.
Present.
Bernie Muneer.
You are muted.
I see you.
Noam Uveni.
Not present.
Mary Kate Gustafson.
Present.
Right.
You are listed as someone else, right?
Leah Grodstein.
Not present.
Rebecca Wright.
Here.
Adam Shire.
Present.
Chris Stivers, is that Stivers or Stivers?
Stivers, present.
Chris Stivers, thank you.
Anna Renkers?
Present.
Okay, we have a quorum and we can proceed with the July meeting.
Bruce, I have a quick announcement.
I believe Lisa's son, who might be on your list, responded to me and told me that she is no longer interested in being part of the Medford... Yes, I was on that thread.
I received it and I removed her.
Okay, great.
I don't ever listen to you in the minutes either.
Okay, perfect.
Sorry.
Guest introductions are next.
Yep.
I think we have a guest, Paul Morgan.
Hi, I'm Paul Morgan.
Are you a Medford resident?
No, I'm a resident of Somerville.
I'm on the Somerville version of this committee and, um, I'm here just in case there's any time to talk about a ride that I'm going to organize, which is going to promote the Clippership connector, but I may have to leave because, um, my two kids, my wife's out to dinner.
So, and I have two kids here, so I don't know.
Okay.
We will have announcements coming up shortly.
I think we'll be able to figure in, uh, briefly in that period.
Okay.
Yeah, Bruce, we've got an agenda item for that.
It's the 740 thing, but maybe if you all are okay with it, we might be able to shift it.
We might be able to shift it forward and after the announcements.
Would anyone, after the announcements, perhaps someone wants to enter a motion to move that forward for Paul?
So moved.
Okay.
Anyone seconded?
Seconded.
Okay.
All in favor?
Aye.
Uh, I opposed who seconded it.
I think you're right.
Thank you.
Sorry, opposed.
Okay, hearing none, I say the eyes have it.
We will move that to immediately after announcements.
Okay, announcements, I guess, in that case.
No, approval of minutes.
Oh, I'm sorry, skipped over that.
Approval of minutes.
Do I hear a motion to approve?
I did see one note that you had in there, Bruce.
Yes, so moved.
We can discuss that after the second.
Okay, do I hear a second?
Aye.
Okay, I hear a second from Mary Kate.
All in favor?
No, not yet, we gotta discuss.
The problem I've got, somehow or another, I neglected to retain the record of who attended last week's meeting.
I think because I was paying attention to the new people.
And so I just wanted to go around the room and recall who was actually present at the meeting.
Daniel, did you recall that you were here?
Uh, I was here.
I'm trying to remember all the names off the top of my head.
Emily was here.
Uh, here she was here.
Yep.
Mary Kate was not here.
Is that true?
Mary Kate?
I was not there.
You were not there.
Okay.
Thank you.
Rebecca and Ernie was late.
Jeopardy.
I was, I was here first.
Anna, were you here?
No, I wasn't.
You were not okay.
And I think no one was here, wasn't he?
I think I recall him being here.
You do or you don't?
I believe I recall him being there.
And Adam, I don't think you were here at the last meeting.
Is that correct?
No, I was there.
Oh, you were.
Okay.
Thank you.
And Chris, you were there, right?
Yeah.
And Rebecca, you already said you were.
All right, thank you so much for all that.
And I think we had two guests, Caitlin Robinson and Simon Alcindor.
Anyone recall anyone else?
OK, that is it.
Otherwise, I am good and we can proceed to approve the minutes.
OK, in that case, moving back to all in favor.
Aye.
All opposed?
Okay, hearing none, motion passes, minutes are approved.
All right.
I guess moving on to announcements.
ClipperShip Connector is officially open.
I'm sure we've all seen that.
There are a couple of final things that are being finished up there, but it is open to access.
I believe that the Contraflow lane on Mystic Valley, or sorry, Riverside Ave has been officially approved by the city.
It will most likely go out to bid, I believe, next year and then will probably be constructed near the year after that in conjunction with the main street redesign that is going through MassDOT.
So that is all I have there.
I'm sure we can cover that a little bit more later on with Paul.
Bruce, would you like to cover the landline Mystic Ride recap?
Yeah, there were about 50 people there.
It was really well attended.
We started down in Assembly Row in the park there with the steel uprights and rode up one side of the river.
and examined exactly what we were talking about, crossing Main Street and coming across the Clippership and actually rode, formally rode the Clippership on the first opening day.
Was able to work our way down through it.
And let's see, then what did we do?
We worked our way up, basically on Revere Beach Parkway.
And let's see if anyone will...
Revere Beach Parkway, and then up along the Northern Strand Trail until, and we stopped at the bike kitchen, which I was actually quite impressed with.
It's a couple of containers that have bicycle tools and some spare parts and is occasionally staffed by volunteers.
So that was quite interesting.
And then we made our way over to Idle Hands.
and had a good social time.
So it was a good fun Mystic ride and I do recommend if you're able to make it next year, they do this every year.
And there are also other landline rides that are of interest.
There will be another one tomorrow leaving from downtown Boston.
is the North Station area going up to Salem.
So that's going to be a pretty aggressive ride to look at some of the paths and so forth that are going on there.
So I'm looking forward to that if we don't get rained out tomorrow.
How does one get clued into these rides?
It's put on by the MAPC, which is the Metropolitan Area Planning Council.
They have a website.
And I don't remember if I was specifically placed on a list or whether I was able to subscribe myself.
But let me make a note to look up that information for you.
All right.
Thanks.
All right, yeah, so that's that.
And then the other announcement I wanted to make is that we will be reviewing the MBAC goals later in the meeting, just so we have enough time to really talk about it.
Sounds good.
All right.
With that, I believe we have moved the clipper ship connector forward.
Sorry, I haven't had a chance to look over this yet.
Clipper ship connector access.
Sorry, Daniel.
I think the thing we moved forward was the 740 fall family bike ride.
That's correct.
Oh, I'm sorry.
I have connector access.
Related topics, right?
So that was why Paul is here.
Perfect.
Paul, would you like to give a preface to this?
Oh yeah, so I'm part of a group that organizes rides marketed to families with children.
And we're working on our fifth annual Halloween ride.
The Halloween rides tend to be in the 300 to 400 person range.
They rotate.
around.
They don't repeat the same routes.
This fall we want to highlight the Clippership Connector, promote awareness of it, and we're working on permitting for that and planning for that as we speak.
And the structure of the event is a gathering spot where there's bike-to-bike trick-or-treating
The attendees bring their own candy and then the kids go around to the different bikes and people do trick-or-treating.
There's a costume walk.
And then we start a ride, which is very conservatively planned.
with as few auto crossings as possible and as marshaled as possible, often with police details.
And then we end at another location where there is play that might be a combination of a playground, our own play equipment, some crafts activities that we have some craft stations, and sometimes some musical entertainment.
It's sort of like a mini festival.
So if anyone's interested in being involved in this, either in planning or volunteering on the day of,
It's a fun event and a good way to promote awareness of the infrastructure that's along the Mystic River to people who are not like us, who are not heavily clued into what's happening in this world.
So that's about it.
Is that October 31st?
Is that Halloween?
No, Sunday morning, October 19th.
Okay, thank you.
Just for the notes.
A permit spending.
Exactly what permits do you need for a ride of this nature?
I wasn't aware that in Massachusetts, permits were actually required.
I know if you want to get police detail, that's a different thing.
Maybe that's what you mean?
Well, we are at a public park and we have 400 people.
It's hard to see how that doesn't require a permit.
I mean, I know that there are Boston Park Party doesn't do permits and that's great, but I don't see how I can get away with that.
And we often have food, in this case, trick-or-treating doesn't require permit, but we often have in our summer ride.
We have ice cream.
9 a.m.
So just as a matter of course, we get permits from the towns and in this case also DCR.
Okay, that's fine.
I'm just curious about that.
One other question is I saw on a thread that you had said something about the Arlington start site was not going to be in effect.
What happened there?
We had wanted to start at, uh, Waldo park in Arlington and, uh, Arlington staff have, um, told us that that is not going to be doable.
Um, and I don't have enough time to lay the groundwork to make that work.
So, um, I need to move on.
And, um, so we're potentially going to start at either deal boy or.
Condon shell, and I don't want to speak in a public forum too much about the pros and cons of each 1 of those locations, but there are some and then are in location was going to be a Mr. mystic riverbend park, but we may move it to assembly square.
I haven't decided yet.
This is all.
sort of happened today.
I had my dream route for about a year, and I'm having to regroup based on my starting location not being an option.
So I'm going to figure out something else, but it's going to highlight the Clippership Connector and some Mystic River Pass nevertheless.
And what do you need specifically from us?
Um, right now I'm doing well on Medford permitting.
I figured out, um, who I needed to talk to for the most part.
And I need, uh, you know, if I, if I get stalled,
Then I might need help with some escalations if I'm not getting a response to emails or whatnot.
But right now, it's not a problem.
Gotcha.
Paul, you can escalate those to me if needed.
I can... hold on.
I will send you my personal email if you do happen to need it, and I can
Um, try and follow up with the city of Medford if you're having issues there.
And I can loop in the rest of them back if needed.
Jared, sorry, go ahead.
Well, that's fine.
I just wanted to say for anyone who is unfamiliar with these events or the work that Paul does, it is an amazing event.
It is not to be missed.
We should absolutely be a part of it.
The work that he puts into this, along with the volunteers, is ungodly in its scale.
There is so much work that goes into this.
He's a huge contributor to building awareness of biking in the region and infrastructure.
It's a big boon to all the kids who are going to grow up and see how normal it is to ride everywhere.
It's a big benefit to the city to get people who are predominantly
I would expect on this particular ride, probably not from Medford, though there'd probably be an arty portion, but lots of people from outside of Medford come to these rides, or outside of the point of origin come to these rides.
And we should, as many of us as possible, should volunteer to help with marshalling and all that kind of stuff to make sure that
crossings are safe and whatnot.
I've been a part of several of these rides as a participant and a marshal once.
Bruce, you did too.
And Mary-Kate, I think you did as well.
It's so much fun.
It's really great.
And it's a really good time to get our elected officials to be a part of it too and let them see all the
all the voters and the wallets that come riding into the city, you know, ready to spend their dollars in our lovely city.
So that's my spiel.
We should get behind this strongly.
What I'd love to hear is when people say to me like, oh, I didn't know how to get here.
I didn't know this path was here.
And then, you know, once they know, then they'll do it again and they'll tell their friends about it.
And so we're looking for a repeat.
Repeat trips from people going on these rides or even if they don't go on the ride, they'll see the map about it and just builds awareness.
So just in case I missed it.
Do you have an approximate time from and until.
uh gathering starting at 9 departing at 10 a.m uh the ride lasting from about 10 to 10 45 or 11 a lot of times a lot of waiting um and then about a hour
an hour of play at the destination, maybe two hours.
It'll start petering out after an hour or so because people have already had the front end trick-or-treating time.
So about like 9 to 12-ish or something like that.
Okay.
Sounds good.
Um, just so people know what they can or can't, uh, can't sign up for.
I assume that marshals, if needed, could, uh, just be present for the ride portion.
Okay.
Great.
Um, just, just so that we know, just in case anyone here is only available during certain hours of the day.
Yeah.
Awesome.
Thank you very much.
And we appreciate that you are putting this on going through Medford.
Thank you so much.
Oh, thanks.
We're excited.
Should be fun.
Good luck choosing and finding some destinations.
If you need to talk about any of that, I mean, you know them better than anybody probably, but, you know, happy to chat about those options.
All right.
Great.
Thank you.
um and i'm not uh i we will have a couple of meetings before that uh ride so we can probably nail down who can or can't show up for that but um we could possibly put uh an agenda item for uh yeah i guess or we'll only have one more meeting but i guess we could put an agenda item on uh bruce for next month just to see if uh
Who can commit to those dates if people can't commit?
We may end up with police at the auto crossings, but we might need people to just stand at forks to make sure people don't get lost.
So, if they're not comfortable, stop being a crossing guard, then there's things like that.
So.
I'd like to point out it's a great idea to have people at strategic points even along the route.
I know last year there was actually a key point that in retrospect we could have done better with right where we made the very sharp
I should say hard right turn to go under the Route 16 bridge.
Traffic had to slow down and there was one collision without any serious injury, but the potential could have been there for a little bit more of a pileup.
So I think one of the things we should consider is actually running the route and making sure that there aren't places that could be of that ilk.
I'm thinking, for example,
Where am I thinking where they might be?
Any place where you're crossing and queuing up, stopping, that kind of area is right for it.
You were going to come from Arlington, but I guess if you go from Delaware, we might still.
Cool.
I would love it if anybody wants to do some rides with me and go over the personnel planning.
That would be awesome.
Yeah.
I'd be willing to do that.
you can make a note, put an email for me so I know when you're planning to do it.
Thanks.
Perfect.
And also feel free to send me an email if you need to coordinate with the commission here, Paul.
I can forward things and or send mail on your behalf.
You can also reach out to us at, what was that?
Medford Bicycle Commission at gmail.com if you need to reach us.
I think it's medfordbikes at gmail.com.
I'm sorry.
Medfordbikes at gmail.com.
Thank you, Bruce.
OK, I think we've covered that.
Paul, thank you very much.
Unless you have anything else, feel free to take care of any other business you have in your personal life.
We appreciate you coming in.
All right, let's see, go through that.
So I guess the next order of business would be the farmer's market recap.
Bruce, if you have any statements there, let me know.
I can also cover in at the later point of this.
It was pretty straightforward.
You know, we show up, we put the table up, and people come by and we chat.
I think we're still missing some good collateral to hand out, and we need to figure out kind of how to do that better, just so we have something.
Ernie eventually showed up with some bike lights at my request, and we were able to hand out some of them.
I have an agenda item later about helmets.
We'll discuss it there.
And that's basically it.
We talked to a handful of people, and I had to leave about 6.30-ish.
So I'm not quite sure if anything exciting happened after that.
But we had like three people at the table at all times.
So it was good.
Oh, there was also a ride.
Maybe Emily wants to know.
Emily's not here.
Was anyone else involved in the Clippership ride?
that came to the farmer's market?
I believe that was Leah, but she is not present.
She's not here either, OK.
Well, they arranged a ride, and I think there was about a dozen people, kids and adults, that showed up at the market having ridden on the new Minuteman, the new Clippership Connector.
Yep, that's I got a quick recap from Leah.
It sounds like there were a couple of tense moments along Riverside Ave with the crossing, so I think that just reinforces for us that we do need to
press the city to not delay on perhaps choosing a bid and moving forward with construction in the next year.
Let's see, other items to note.
Yes, I mean, I was there as well with you, Bruce.
I think there was good attendance there.
I agree that our materials are getting low.
I think it might
makes sense for us to put together possibly a working group to come up with a couple of new items to both print out and possibly some new signage.
I know that our budget might be relatively limited, but if we come up with a couple of items that we need, I can probably go to the city and make a request for the budget for those items, or we can otherwise find a way to sort of fit those in.
So I agree with you, things are kind of sparse as things stand.
So that's all I have really to add into that.
If there aren't any other additions to that, Hormel Stadium follow-up?
I don't know.
Should we do a working group like you're suggesting, Daniel?
As chair, I cannot raise that, but if you would like to make a motion for that.
As a new member, I'm still getting the lay of the land.
All you do is say, I'd like to move that we, and then you say what you'd like us to do.
I would like to move that we create a working group to replenish our supplies.
Do I hear a second?
I hear a second.
All in favor?
Aye.
All opposed?
All right, hearing none, we will create a working group.
Is there anyone who would like to join this working group specifically?
I am not sure how city commissions work.
I'm not sure that I can directly be on this working group if I am going to bring this to the mayor for a budget request.
I do see Adam there.
Yeah, I could be on it.
Yeah, I'll help.
OK, so I see Chris, Bruce, Adam.
The only requirement on this is that we cannot have a quorum.
So if anyone else would like to join.
Okay.
So we cannot have a quorum on the working group?
Correct.
I'll go over this a little bit later, but a working group cannot have a quorum because then it'd be a meeting.
Exactly.
So a working group has to be less than a quorum and they can come back and bring their suggestions to the meeting for a vote, or sorry, to the entire commission for a vote at a meeting.
So that is the way it currently works.
So three does not make a quorum, and that is enough for a working group.
So if there are no other hands, I guess in that case, Bruce, do we need to have a separate vote on the actual members?
No, I don't think we've ever done that.
I think we just, you know, we create the group and
and then the three of us will decide who should chair it.
It's pretty informal, that's why it's just a working group and not a quorum.
In that case, let's put that together then for Bruce, Chris, and Adam.
Cool.
Thank you very much for offering to do that.
We've needed to do this for a little while.
So come to us with whatever recommendations that you have, and we will see how things can work with the budget that we have.
It is not that much, but I can possibly make a request
I, uh, Daniel, I don't know if Dennis, you might know what our budget is, but I feel like we don't spend it when we've got it usually.
Right.
Like I think we should be spending it or in theory, we'd be spending it on bike lights, but, uh, Ernie gets those made up, I think, out of the city's budget through, through donations from corporate entities and whatnot.
So we might be sitting pretty, I don't know.
I will check on the number right now and get back to you.
Tell us more at the, uh, at his slot.
Awesome.
Okay, sorry.
I had jumped right to the Hormel Stadium, but I guess in that case, is there anything else that people would like to bring up with that?
Okay, hearing nothing.
Um, for most stadium follow up.
I'm not sure who brought that into the I brought that up just because it was in the June meeting.
We had an action item and I'm going to take.
make a habit of putting action items in bold in the agenda so that we can review them, maybe nudge people or find out if they're no longer an action item, et cetera.
My note was that Dennis said he would check with the Hormel Commission to see how to proceed.
And I know people get very busy and sometimes don't get to it, but maybe you did.
I went over and asked your secretary and they were not meeting in the timeframe that I think we were sort of looking at.
So they were, she said the next time they meet, she's going to bring it up to them.
Okay, cool.
Well, that's good action then.
All right.
Do they need our input for anything?
No, I just gave it to her and I said, like, have her talk to the chair and see if they want anything.
I said, if the chair does want stuff, then we'll come back to you guys.
Okay.
Anything else with Hormel Stadium or shall we move on to the Police Working Group?
All right.
Moving on to the Police Working Group, me and Emily are discussing what we want to bring up with the police during our next meeting.
We have not actually officially established a meeting with them.
One of the items that we want to do is push the police to come up with a recurring bicycle patrol.
They have done so in the past, and we would like to push them to actually commit to having on some sort of recurring cadence a bicycle patrol done by their officers to help
you know, provide officers a way to see what is going on on the ground.
We are also going to push them to move forward with at least some sort of bicycle training.
These are things that we have not at this point
reached out to the police with yet, but I intend to do that before the next meeting.
So that is an action item for me is to consolidate all of my requests to them and put those forward and set up a meeting to see if we can push forward with that.
Sadly, there hasn't been that much movement on that front, but it is on my list of things to do.
So that is my current set of requests that I will push out to them.
Bike patrol, what was the other one?
So we are going to try and put them through a bicycle training program.
So educate them as to the rules of the road with regards to cyclists and drivers so that they are aware as to what a cyclist can do, what a cyclist can't do, and
just where the vulnerability points for cyclists are on the road and what they should be on the lookout for.
And who presents that information to them?
That is still TBD.
It would most likely be me or Emily.
I do know that, Bruce, you've done the League of American Bicyclists.
That's correct, yes.
I'm a certified league cycling instructor.
And for each state, we do talk about and refer people to the laws of the state, not as legal advice, but basically saying, here's a summary and here's where you can look for information.
Most groups, most state groups will have an advocacy group that's actually summarized everything by their legal staff.
And we can usually just crib from that and go through it.
I believe the goal is,
how to say it, a lot of people have what I'll call default attitudes with regard to bicycling.
And that means that they don't fully understand what the rights or the responsibilities are for cyclists.
And that can create tension and can result in, you know, particularly with police officers, if
they're not aware of what an issue is and then they get called to a crash or something like that, they might not be aware or fully understand whether the cyclist was operating properly or not.
And sometimes people will blame a cyclist no matter what without really understanding it.
And so I would like to see that information be provided so that they at least have a better sense of what's actually
you know, important.
Bruce, as a quick follow-up to that, is there still a League of American Cyclists training situation that I could go through?
Yes, yes.
It's possible.
I would need to look up exactly what the well you could either go on the League of American Cyclists website and find about becoming a bike instructor, but basically they have a typically it's a two day session where they walk through.
At the time they walked through a lot of operation on the road and what some of the pitfalls are and how to actually operate in a vehicular manner so that you can get through situations that might otherwise be uncomfortable.
I think that the curriculum has probably been expanded now to understand some of the pitfalls that you have to watch out for even when operating an infrastructure, whether it's a shared use path, bike path, or separated bike.
All these things have their own perils that you need to be aware of.
But anyhow, you would learn about all that and learn how to present that to people, as well as the basics of how do you learn how to ride a bike to begin with.
It's a fascinating course to go through.
I did it five or six years ago, as I recall, maybe more.
It'd be kind of interesting to see how they do it again for it.
But yeah, if I don't remember to connect to you about it, let me, you know, look on the web, the league website, and you can probably find information on that.
All right, that's good to know.
I will try and follow up with that and investigate whether I can become an instructor myself.
I presume probably both me and Emily should investigate that if we're the ones who are liaising.
Yeah, and that might be the kind of thing where you could get a stipend perhaps to help offset the cost of
either lodging that you have or the actual cost of the training.
I don't recall that it was very expensive, but it also wasn't free.
Sounds good.
Daniel, one more thought.
I know that there are in the area a couple of attorneys that specialize in
supporting cyclists who've been in an accident or whatever.
And I wonder if those people might also be good resources for information or even presenting potentially to the police.
If you have any of the contact info or names I can reach out to, Adam, I would gladly welcome that.
Yeah, I'll see what I can dig up.
okay that's a great idea yeah mass bike has some materials on that point including some of those people yeah um any uh any information that you can dig up is much appreciated i wish i had more time in my life to dedicate to only bikes but sadly work is
Work eats up a lot of it right now.
Anyways.
Daniel, given that, I don't know if I could be so bold as to suggest that Bruce take on some of the responsibility of presenting to the police if he would be up for it, given his experience with this and encyclopedic knowledge of all of the streets of Medford.
I'm happy to do so.
I fully intend to Bruce in if possible.
My thought more goes to us.
Probably wanting to have.
a backup, a secondary person with that knowledge if needed, even tertiary if needed.
But yes, I will 100% rope Bruce in.
That was our original intent between me and Emily, was to set this up and at some point see if we could rope Bruce into doing this.
You're not roping me.
Okay.
All right.
Well, that's wonderful then.
So I will keep that in mind.
Wonderful.
Let's see.
Are there any questions about the police working group or any other comments?
It's a bold move.
I'm glad you're doing it.
Asking them to take a crash course in the laws of the state is a strong stance.
It's appreciated.
We can try.
As we all know, we can do our best.
It doesn't mean we'll succeed.
Let's see, Ernie, would you like to give a bike lights report?
Sure, sure.
Let me tail off of the league.
It was a reminder for me to check supplies there.
The informational material, training material that's in the bike light kit is of course the league's guide, which I hadn't talked about.
for quite a while because we had a surplus of those booklets.
We're now down to less than I would need
maybe less than half of what I would need for this fall's distribution.
So it's a good time to order those.
So that's a note to the working group that was just formed to order a case of 500 of the league's quick guides.
At that level, they drop from $4 each to $1.25 each.
And that's what we've been ordering.
And that's why they're not ordered too often, because 500 is a large quantity.
But it's time to get those.
So that sits also into the discussion about what our budget is.
I happen to run into Alicia, who is, I think, supposed to disperse and manage our budget.
But the
Attitude I get is that there's no one currently watching it or tallying it as a fixed amount to be managed throughout the year.
In that, and I'll now go to the bike lights.
Last year, I fronted the funds to buy and assemble all the bike lights, and I had sufficient quick guides to do so without having to order any.
she is finally saying that she will reimburse me for that.
Running on its heels a few weeks ago, as I mentioned I think at the last meeting, the lights themselves for the next fiscal year arrived as we agreed to order them early because of the threat of tariffs.
That's been wonderfully successful in that they've arrived with only an increase in cost of 4% from last year.
So I will have to present through JRA cycles an invoice for the next coming year.
Following Jared's comment about corporate sponsors, I've only been able to
consistently get Brookline Bank to give us $500 a year toward these expenses.
So we have some work to do to get more corporate benefactors, as well as to figure out
what kind of budget we have and how it's to be spent and whether it's not just loosely monitored once in a while by the development office.
So that's all sort of interesting.
I have never been
in the last at least two years been told or operating within a referred balance sheet showing what funds we have available, total spent, et cetera.
I know that we had been told years ago that we had a $1,500 per annum balance, and that was what prompted me to seek, as well, corporate sponsorship for the bike lights, because that and the other supplies we've purchased and promotional materials and hardware exceeded that amount per annum.
There was talk of doubling that budget,
maybe to two or three grand a year.
I don't think anything became of that.
So now we are operating in this open without restriction area as far as I can see.
Alicia, when trying to decide how to pay me for last year's lights, said she would come up with the money from somewhere.
and not indicating that it's working off of a budget that is bequested to us.
So there are the subtleties around that.
I have in my front hall, all the lights we'll be needing for this fall and next spring.
They just have to be assembled.
I get the city to pay JRA for that invoice, smaller,
expenses like for Ziploc bags and printing and that kind of stuff, I just donate that because I'm not going to go through the bureaucracy of getting POs from the city for $30 or $40 or $50 amounts.
here and there.
I'm just getting too old for that shit.
So just the larger invoices have to be washed through the city and that's for the bike lights themselves at $1,100 per annum.
And maybe, yeah, almost once a year, $625 for the 500 League Quick Guides, which I think we should have as a standard giveaway at events.
And maybe include, I know this isn't the promotional
working group that you just put together, but you know, we could put our 10 cent MBAC sticker on the back cover of that as an example.
That's something to have as a handout.
So that's that.
If anybody wants to help me assemble a couple hundred or so kits we'll need for September and fall events,
you can come over, we'll have pizza and go to Espresso and put together some kits.
So that's, I think that's all I've got.
Thanks.
Thank you, Ernie.
Anna.
Hi, everyone.
This is my first meeting, so it's nice to meet everyone.
I just wanted to say, Ernie, that in my day job, I do fundraising and communication, so I want a little more time to get my head around the commission and everything we're doing and also would need some guidance surrounding how the commission differs.
I work at a nonprofit in terms of asking for donations, but I'm happy to help with that in the future, and I'm also happy to help put together bike lights.
So, yeah, we should connect.
I can definitely help with that.
Well, thank you.
I've... Recording stopped.
Standby.
Yep.
Recording in progress.
In the couple of years of doing this, I've noticed that larger potential donors, big banks, corporations, even real estate firms tend to have such boilerplate around the application
process that they never come through or put you on a waiting list even to communicate with them.
It's the small mom and pops who are apt to support us, but don't come through with a $250 or $500 ask that I put forward.
So sort of run out of steam there, Mr. Wenderman.
So yeah, it's like nonprofit fundraising.
I understand, and you understand.
what I'm talking about too.
Yeah.
That sounds good.
Maybe if I can come over and help with the bike lights, we can discuss what you've done and any ideas I have and talk about it.
Great.
Should be in about a month or so.
I'll get around to this early September.
We hit the schools in late September, early October and stuff them with these.
If there are any events where bike light kits would be needed,
in the next month, please let me know.
I have nothing on the calendar.
Quick question for you there, Ernie.
Do you have limitations on types of businesses that you will work with?
I mean, obviously, you work with JRE, our local bike shop.
Will you work with cafes, real estate, hardware store?
Do you have any limitations on that sort of thing?
I don't think so.
I would like a sponsor to be oriented philosophically to what we're doing.
So, you know, I haven't approached automobile dealerships as an example, who might have an anti-bike lane agenda for all I could tell.
No, I remember that that was the case in the past, but I don't recall specifically.
I was really hoping to get, as an example, Waste Management as a corporate sponsor.
And once again, they just put you in line and you never hear from them.
But yeah, I can certainly, with Anna's help, restart this process of trying to get, if not the full, let's say, $1,500 or $2,000 worth of supplies covered each year.
more than just a quarter of that.
So that's the answer to your question, Jared.
I'd say about a quarter of this whole activity is sponsored.
JRA put up a couple hundred dollars in the past, but since they're doing now the shadowboxing with the city in terms of getting payments through the system, I'm not gonna ask them for,
any actual funds anymore.
It's generous of them to act as the purchaser so that I can be reimbursed for outlays.
The city has it such that no member on the commission can actually
be reimbursed for large outlays.
It has the money has to go directly to the provider of materials.
So that's how I got the lights from Singapore to be washed through JRA.
and how maybe a check in the future to the league for 625 bucks may have to come from the city to the league of bicycles rather than wash through any of us buying them.
I'm not so clear on that, but we do need 500 more of those guys this fall.
Sooner the better.
So I should put that in as a proposal that we, as a commission order, another case of 500 of the league of American bicyclists, quick guides at what had been a dollar 25 each.
I suspect it still is.
So a total purchase of $625.
Is that a motion?
Yes, that's a motion.
I'll second that.
Okay, should be noted, Dennis did send to me, we have a budget for this year of $1,500.
So do I hear any ayes?
Aye.
All opposed?
Okay, hearing none, the ayes have it.
Ernie, that expense is approved.
Why don't you reach out to me if you need anything on my side in order.
The question will be whether I, since they know me from past purchases, should make the purchase and submit the bill.
to Alicia or whether she will want to go through the process of getting a quote from me, issuing a PO, and then making the purchase directly, which might take months or years.
And that's my fear.
So I don't mind fronting the money because, you know, eventually, maybe I'll get paid.
Well, let's see if we can't.
We'll try and move that along.
We'll try and groove in again.
Yes, indeed.
Thank you, Daniel.
That's it for me.
OK, helmets.
I believe, Bruce, that was you.
Yeah, that was my item, and that came up because one of the questions I was asking at the farmers market was, didn't we used to give away helmets?
And so I just wanted to figure out, I think Pat might have been coordinating all that in the past.
I wasn't certain about that, but I wanted to know if anyone recalls how it is that we ended up with a bunch of helmets, whether we still have a bunch of helmets, and if we can get more.
I can speak to that.
Jared might also have a little bit of info on that as well.
I believe Berkshire White & Gluck was the law firm that sponsored the helmets.
Breakstone White & Gluck.
They run a non-profit called Project KidSafe that provides the helmets.
They're active across the state.
But they're in Boston, I think.
What is the name of that organization?
Breakstone?
Breakstone, White, and Gluck is the name of the law firm.
Project KidSafe is their helmet distribution initiative.
What was the stipend or support amount each year?
It was a bunch of free helmets.
Yeah, OK.
That's it.
How do we get back on board that train?
Just contact them?
That was my understanding, unless it was Jared.
I think that's right.
I think, I think Daniel, you might have had contact with them most recently.
So it probably would be, I would hope, fairly trivial to, to do just that and get back on the wagon with them again.
I vaguely remember that.
I, Bruce, will you add an action item for me to reach out to
BWG, for lack of my being able to pronounce their name properly, just to reach out to them about getting a new shipment of helmets.
One thing that I would like to note is that the helmet shipments are difficult to store.
In the past, we have stored them at the Tufts Pool, I think.
We were able to get storage location there, but that meant that we would need to retrieve them from there if we ever did events.
It might be helpful if we could distribute those helmets across multiple different people for storage purposes so that they could be brought to events from not just a single location or have a single person need to coordinate with, I believe, the Medford Recs Department, who were the ones that basically stored those.
So if there's a way that we could get those
distributed to one or two separate members just for ease of access, that would be probably pretty helpful.
Was there any administrator reason we were storing them on city property as opposed to not?
I think specifically because helmets in large quantities end up taking up a large amount of space.
For any of us, I'm sure space can sometimes be at a premium, and we did have free space there.
I just meant, was there any city policy with regard to that that we had to adhere to?
No, I believe that the rec department did offer that up freely.
They did have space that they were willing to donate to that.
Maybe we can figure that out as well and just have a handful at members' places, like a dozen or 10, so that we can arrive at the events with them more easily.
I was going to say, I don't know if it has to even stay with members, but I think a lot of the
Local like walk bike to school groups would be a great place because they're already doing events with kids I know we would love we would hand out if I had bike helmets I would hand them out at like our fall festival when we have a biking table So that might be another way to think about distributing them.
Not just through us.
I think that's a great thought as well.
So yeah, thank you Mary-Kate.
Ernie and then Anna.
Yeah, two parts to this.
We talked about this years ago as well, that the law firm was giving us what, 200 helmets a year or 125?
We had some discussions about how, or I wanted to at least ramp this up to several hundred a year at least.
And storage was an issue.
I know I can easily store
I don't know, 100, maybe 200 helmets and accessible to the members, basement, outside free entry area, you know, with bulkhead doors, dry for the winter.
So I'm not sure storage is the issue, but I would like to see this part of a,
Well, in addition to hitting up the law firm and seeing what they will provide for us, I would want to tipple them to see if the mass can be increased and if necessary for us to pay for them.
On the other side of that, since we know that on the retail level at stores, Schwinn provides really good helmets in the $20 area.
Maybe that's before tariffs.
And so those have to wholesale at 10 or 12 bucks a piece.
And indeed, the supplier of the bike lights in Singapore has been offering to me
you know, a whole bunch of different styles of kids and youth helmets in the $10 to $12 per helmet area.
So that's just some information we should use in procuring helmets, whether we're buying them or trying to max the donation from our current supplier.
I don't see that 100 or
200 helmets a year is sufficient.
I would like to see this go up to the bike lights level, whereas you say with all these events we have, we should at least for a few years trying to put helmets on all the kids in a sort of large effort.
But they're tough to store.
The police officers have already told me there's no way they want to carry them in the back of their SUVs.
Bike lights are easy, but our liaison of the police department said, no way are they going to carry helmets around.
They're just too bulky.
So that's all I got there.
Thanks.
I'll make it a note to ask for, see what the upper limit of helmets are from BWG.
Anna?
Yeah, I was just gonna make a comment kind of going back to what Adam was talking about with the lawyers who might know information on this link that Jared sent for this project KidSafe.
They mentioned working with police departments, so they could also, when you reach out about helmets, could be a good thing to just ask on the police front that we were discussing earlier, just to ask if they have any resources or if they ever do trainings.
OK, so I guess I can make a side request to them to see what they have.
Chris?
Yeah, just real quick.
What's the mechanism for handing out helmets right now?
Is it at our various events?
Or are there other means of doing it?
So generally, we hand them out at events that we table at, or any other events that we happen to be at.
They typically should be given out to kids who may not have a helmet, typically for free.
Same thing with bike lights.
Yep.
I think, does that cover your question?
Yeah, it just makes me think that maybe, if it's like trying to get helmets on kids, then maybe there's an opportunity for,
events focused on at a school, for example, that's both educational in nature and outfitting with lights, helmets.
So I didn't know if we had focused events like that, or if that's something that we consider in the future.
In the past, we have.
I believe, someone correct me if I'm wrong, that was the bike rodeo that we would do.
Possibly.
I'm going to chime in and say that I think a lot of, again, the school site bike and safety activities are often put on by the safe routes to school groups.
So I lead one for the Brooks Elementary School.
And I know that there's the representatives at each school are the ones who are working to try to get those pedestrian safety classes and biking safety classes put into the school day curriculum at second and fifth grade.
I just want to remind everyone that whereas the bike-like kits are sort of self-explanatory and you can't really get into trouble or safety issues, with helmets, we've been giving them out at the Spring Rodeo, as an example, as part of helping to teach kids how to maneuver and ride a course.
but also to very carefully and personally hand fit on each child the appropriate size helmet and adjustment of straps.
So we have to be careful about how we do that.
It's a fitting, not just a tossing of a product to a parent who has a kid at home, as an example.
Yeah.
Fair call out.
Final thoughts from me, it seems like maybe there's an opportunity then to connect to some of these safe routes of school groups to have a more targeted impact if we're going to be giving away helmets in that fashion.
So maybe it's trying to link up with that.
What I don't want to see is a big box of helmets at the back door of the gym of a big school where kids just willy-nilly grab the color they like and run away with it.
We want to be more careful about the safety aspects of being properly fit.
Yeah, I think you're right, Aaron.
Agreed.
Sorry, okay, that covers helmets.
We already covered a family, fall family bike ride.
I'm sorry, were there any other comments on helmets before I move on to the clipper ship connector?
All right, moving on, clipper ship connector access.
Yes, the Contra Flow bike lane has been approved by the Traffic Commission.
It has not gone out to bid.
It will most likely go out to bid, I believe, for next construction season, which means we are most likely not looking at completion until 2027.
It will probably coincide with the MassDOT Main Street 93 underpass improvements that are scheduled.
So as much as I know that a lot of us would like to see that get added in sooner, we will most likely have to wait for that.
As that was just recently approved, it's not even part of the bidding season right now.
So this is sort of where we are.
interim improvements.
We do have some signage that will be getting added in the short term.
There were discussions over whether there should be signs added to the end of the path along Riverside Ave that say cyclists stop and dismount.
That was an item that we as the commission pushed back on
against adding that specific signage or having that signage moved as far down towards Main Street as possible since we don't want to add on additional encumbrances for cyclists who are coming through that way since it is a relatively long walk along Riverside Ave.
There will be wayfinding signage added as part of that and other directions, so that is at least a positive on that front.
That is all I really have to report there.
If anyone has... Oh, Chris, go for it.
Yeah, I'm just curious.
Is there any way to see what that way signage will look like?
And as our function with the Advisory Commission, do we get to weigh in on that?
And it would be great to prototype it and ride around and see what does that look like?
Because there's so many times where signage is just either not in the right place or it's just hard to see.
And so is it going to be effective is the thing I worry about.
Also, what is the preferred route that we're being directed to?
Having done that a whole bunch of times, I'm still not even sure what I would say is the best route.
At the moment, I don't think that we have.
I'm actually in the process of pulling up the email thread that I had been brought along on.
I'm trying to make sure I have all the images before I do this.
Sorry, so I guess to follow up with that, right now the email is only between
Me, Todd Blake, Emily, and Carl Alexander.
I'm not, I'm actually, I don't know enough about Carl to be able to comment on, he's part of the Mystic River Path, I believe, group.
Let me, I can show some proposed signage.
I think Carl is with the MWRA based on-
No, no, no.
He's with Mystic River Watershed Association.
Thank you.
What did I say?
You said Massachusetts Water Resources Authority.
Right.
Similar initials.
That's not what I meant.
Thanks for the correction.
This is the current signage.
We are pushing to have, there are still some discussion points to be had over this sign.
I think that we have successfully pushed them to push back the decision, at least, on what that sign should look like.
Todd, the city traffic engineer, had suggested a sign that was, I realize I'm sharing the rest of this, he had suggested a sign that looks similar to this Oak Park, but just with bicycle and dismount, which was a suggestion that I had made as being there, sorry, there we go, dismount instead of Oak Park, less words.
So these are some proposed changes that
or these are the proposed signs that are being brought up here.
I think that the current decision is that we will move forward with the wayfinding signs, but not the dismount signs, and that is an ongoing discussion point.
I don't need to necessarily belabor that point.
I'll move on to Bruce.
Sorry, you have the floor.
I think someone was ahead of me, or are they set?
Oh, I remember.
I guess it's me.
Yeah, so I just wanted to say that I have been riding the Clippership Connector currently at every opportunity.
I've been coming almost exclusively westbound at this point, and tried several different routes just to see how they fared.
And the one that was actually the worst
was to go down to the police station and try to cross there.
And I found that crossing the street at that point, it's very difficult, especially with a bicycle.
As a pedestrian, you can kind of step into the street and people will actually stop.
And I found when trying to do so with a bicycle, you can't really step in far enough without your bike kind of being in the way.
And therefore, I didn't seem to get as much cooperation, and it took a while to cross the street.
So that was one.
Then further, once I crossed the street... Sorry, Bruce, could you clarify exactly where you're talking about there?
Yes, at South Street, the South Street intersection with Main Street, right across from the police station.
Do you guys mind if I just pull up a map and share with you?
Please do, sure.
Yeah, thanks.
I can allow you to, you know what, my Zoom is... So I think, Bruce, you're talking about coming
Yes, a connector along Clippership this way.
I actually stayed on the sidewalk on the side of the lane yet.
Yeah, down to.
Oh, sorry.
No, I guess it wasn't quite that far.
It was just north of the police station at that light right here.
Right.
And crossed over to South street.
and then had to ride along the sidewalk a little bit there to dismount and get into the not quite contraflow lane that's at least marked with a yellow line currently.
And I found it to be incredibly awkward and would not recommend it for people who were trying to serve who don't know how to work their way through here.
It really was not
a good idea to do it that way.
So another approach I took, and this was on a Sunday afternoon, so traffic was quite light.
I was able to simply pull off the curb and make a left turn, similar to what will be proposed once the signal is in place.
And that worked pretty well.
I then took the bike lane south on Main Street and picked up the river path with the awkward kind of U-turn that you got to make to get on the path.
And that wasn't so bad.
The third approach that I took was to actually go down to the crosswalks in Medford Square proper, cross over those crosswalks, and then pick up the bike lane southbound on Main Street.
So while that worked quite well,
It was not very efficient.
It really took a while, because in order to get through those lights, there's got to be like three or four different things you've got to coordinate.
And they're not designed so that you can just sort of go through.
And I got frustrated and just had to cross one of them, even though it wasn't green.
I've done that, Bruce, on a cargo bike.
There's like no space in here.
Yeah, right.
That's the other thing.
One time I found people standing here and it's pretty terrible.
Yeah, so I think what we're looking for here is the least worst of all the ideas that we have.
The thing that I found to be the most
And this is why I think a conversation around what the way signage should be is pretty important, because it's such a terrible, your choices are really bad.
But I found that, honestly, the best way is just going following the road around here, taking the left.
I was going to tell you that that was my fourth approach.
This way, and then just staying in the central lane here to go right across here.
And it's like the, it's actually,
It's not great, but it's not that bad.
And Chris, I'll say that that works great for experienced riders, those who aren't timid about it.
We've had reports that Medford Square is one of the more intimidating places to ride your bike through if you are not an experienced vehicular cyclist.
If you are, it's not so bad.
I do it many times and I find it works well.
And so from my standpoint, what you said is totally true.
I was able to go up, do my standard route through City Hall as if I was coming from Riverside Avenue and that all worked.
But I'm not going to recommend that as sort of a family or kid or inexperienced cyclist way.
to get through the area.
So I think we need to really figure out what's the least problematic of all these choices that still allow inexperienced people to get through.
And I think, unfortunately, it's probably to go to the lights in Medford Square, even though there's not quite enough room, like you said, with a cargo bike.
because I think, I don't know, Chris, did you try going to the crossing down at South Street as well?
And that technique, because that's just as bad.
There's no space in the middle.
I haven't tried that so long.
I try not to go.
Sidewalks with a cargo bike is really hard.
And so it's not a great stretch to go down.
I think, yeah, I mean, this is, I think it's fine without people, without not other people waiting in that little island here.
Otherwise, it's...
We could propose different solutions and basically say, if you're comfortable riding on the street, this is the best way.
If you're not, this is the best way, or at least the worst way.
It's hard to put that on a sign though.
Yeah, it is, it is.
But maybe just suggesting alternative paths.
And the two alternative paths would be up around on Salem Street, and then the other would be going through the crosswalks.
So that way, people who aren't sure where to go can say, oh, yeah, there's no way I'm riding on City Hall Mall.
I'm not going to do that.
Or people who are comfortable and say, oh, there's no way I'm going to ride down the sidewalk and through the crosswalks.
So that would at least give some wayfinding guidance to people on how to get through.
So that's my observation from what I've done.
Yeah, I mean, to be honest, I think what I end up doing most of the time, and I'm usually coming from my son's karate school here, but I just go through the parking lot, up the street here, and then onto the sidewalk here.
Yeah, right.
So that's another technique.
And that's, I mean, you could kind of just do from the clipper ship, come into this parking lot area, through the parking lot, all the way through where
It's a little more protected.
Oh, that's an interesting point.
Yeah, I see your point.
So that's another alternative would be to use the parking lot, which has its own perils, but at least you're going in the right direction.
Yeah, it'll be less traffic, but you get cars backing up, which is tricky.
Does the thought of having differentiating signs like bike
Yeah, I concur with that.
feeling.
I feel like adding multiple different pathways may just lead to confusion, though I do agree with the sentiment and more advanced route.
Maybe the thing we would do would be suggested off-road route through Medford Square.
Or like safest route?
Safest is a judgment, you know, because I don't consider it necessarily safest.
I often find that riding in traffic is the safest approach for me, given my speed and abilities.
So, you know, if you say it's off road, you're not
You're not making any judgment as to which way is safest.
And that provides guidance westbound.
I'll continue to do these experiments eastbound, which, again, I haven't done, and offer my view of how that all works as well.
But where do we want to go with this, I guess, is the next question.
I think it's probably worth giving Adam a chance to speak.
He's got his hand up.
Oh, yeah.
Sure.
Yeah.
So, uh, two things.
I think I lost the plot a little bit, but I think what we're trying to, what we're discussing is now that the Clipper ship connectors open, there's going to be signage there.
Someone's asking us for signage recommendations.
Is that, am I close to what we're?
Yes, effectively.
We have a chance to weigh in on signage here.
Okay, so two questions I had.
Bruce, when you're going down however you want to get on to Main Street going south and then you're kind of jumping on South Street, do you have a destination in mind?
West.
Just west.
So, I mean, so for signage, you know, maybe it's
Maybe if we could think about the destination for some of the signage or information, like the library could be a destination.
Let me add another clarification.
When I came down Main Street from the crosswalks, I went through what we've called Sleepy Hollow and across the dangerous crosswalk on Mystic Valley Parkway.
And then across this route-studded path, that was not very fun to ride on.
No, I didn't go that way.
I went on the path.
Yeah, I'd recommend going through the parking lot, and then I picked up the Contra Flow lane.
Yeah, okay.
Basically, the only reason I did that
is because that's the natural way to go.
I think actually one of the times I may have, yes, one of the times I also went along Mystic Valley Parkway and picked up the Mystic River Path by the Condon Shell instead.
Yep.
I like that better.
But that's still, yeah, that's a little bit better choice.
Of course, the bridge and the sidewalk are kind of a pain in the butt there.
But that's another approach.
I've crossed.
Mystic Street, both at that crosswalk and gone down to the path itself and crossed, those are six of one, half dozen of another.
There's not really any benefit to one or the other other than maybe you have a crosswalk light if you're on the path as opposed to crossing by the ballparks.
Right there, you don't have any light, you just have to go, whereas up at Mystic Valley Parkway, you actually have a crosswalk light.
So those are different ways.
Normally, I just go through Medford Square and down High Street.
But I've been, as I said, deliberately using the path just to get a sense of what people are facing.
So my two cents was if we're thinking about what goes on the sign, a destination could be one of the things to think about putting on the sign.
I think there's probably a couple of places.
Eventually, you'd love to see Minuteman bike path on there, because eventually, hopefully, all this connects out to there.
But right now, it could be Mystic River Path, or it could just be Main Street.
I mean, I suppose we could have a series of, right, a series of paths that basically point in the direction, sorry, a series of signs, rather than having a diagram or something like that, that basically say, you know, Mystic River Path continues and direct them through the crosswalk directly.
And then once you're through the crosswalk, they can decide, you know, what is the best Mystic River Path to take.
Actually, that would work well.
You'd go through Sleepy Hollow, cross at the crosswalk, and then continue across the narrow bridge to pick up the path at the Condon Shell.
That's probably actually the closest to the real route, the ideal route that we would ultimately want this path to take.
Yeah, it's actually not too bad if you don't cross that
that flashing yellow thingy on Mystic Valley and you just stay on the north side of Mystic Valley Parkway and cross at the crosswalk with an actual red light.
I find that one, I usually take that one.
Yeah, I take that one in favor of the other one.
Interesting.
I'll try that sometimes just to see how that fares.
I hadn't considered that.
That feels like a lot safer, like the cars like don't blow through that as much as they do the other one.
Yeah, good point.
Cool.
So, I mean, what I'm hearing from this is a series of wayfinding signs.
Sorry, Jared, do you have something you want to add?
I do.
One, I agree.
I like that crossing behind the church there.
I use that to get to the library, connect between the library area and the convent shell all the time.
Don't tell the church that I ride through their parking lot.
But the other point I had was that Adam's point about destinations reminded me that either one or two years ago, the city had a small amount of money.
I believe it was grant funded.
for wayfinding signs, and they put up wayfinding signs in this area with destinations that provided walking and biking distances and estimated times from the point of the sign to whatever the destination was like.
And it had things like the library and the condensation and stuff like that.
They were made out of corrugated plastic, as I believe these are proposed to be for now.
uh and i don't think they made it through more than a year and they tended to twist around on the pole and point you in the wrong direction that kind of thing um so well that's that's too bad but it does seem like we're talking about coming up with locations and distances and where to put them at least
And to some extent regarding, it looks like we're maybe recreating the wheel a bit.
And some of this work has been done.
So I'm not sure why leveraging some of those past materials wasn't on the docket.
But I feel like it should be.
And our job then, I feel like, should maybe be let's resurrect some of those old wayfinding materials if we believe they were effective and supplement them with specific guidance here in the areas where we're concerned about people not being able to get through.
Do we know where those specs are?
I don't.
I mean, the city should certainly have them.
It was a city thing.
Maybe Todd knows.
Yeah, I just, I don't feel like I saw any comment about that, which kind of is surprising me now that I'm recalling it.
Did we get corporate destinations to help out in this?
I'm thinking, especially in the Contra Flora, South Street, and then getting back on to go West.
I would think Amazon and Whole Foods would be very interested in having wayfinding
to that location.
The other one has no idea.
Sponsored destination signs?
Yeah, it's a destination sign.
Well, yeah, if they put up, you know, we'll put up one for them, and if they pay for the other four, along the way.
I guess what I'm imagining, you know, for right now, for the next, until the contraflow lane is built, at least, because that provides a little bit clearer visual indication of where to go.
Right now, come off the Eclipse ship connector here,
And you have no idea where to go.
And so it's sort of a series of signs that at least lead you to the next place where it starts to make sense where you can bike.
So it's like, all right, bike path this way with a couple of signs along the way here.
And then the left here, this is the way we suggest.
Go here and then cross here.
So just along the preferred route to guide people.
Because otherwise, at every intersection, you're left wondering, where do I go?
And it takes doing this a couple dozen times to figure out what works.
I think the more mature ways of finding stuff could come along with a contraflow lane in the future.
I think ultimately that is what we are going for with this iteration.
It is a temporary solution until the contraflow lane is installed.
probably our first iteration, we should just focus on optimal way wayfinding to continue along the Mystic River path.
And then I presume we should have an opportunity to add more wayfinding.
But in this case, I think that it might be more of a question as to what we consider to be an optimal path to continue along.
I propose that I can put together a draft
based on what I've heard us discuss and maybe circulate it.
We wouldn't be able to make primary decisions, but we can gather information to bring to the next meeting.
Hopefully everybody will have reviewed it by then, and we can have a quick vote on how to proceed at that point.
Maybe making a recommendation to Todd that they purchase these
either temporary or perhaps a little bit more permanent wayfinding signs until the contraflow is available.
So I'm willing to do that and distribute it.
I don't know if we need a motion for that.
It's just an idea I have.
What do you think?
I would love that.
Ultimately, let me see, I'm looking into this.
I just got added to this email thread nine days ago.
I believe they're trying to put these out to print in short order, so I may need to make an executive decision.
So Bruce, if you would like to start on that and send me your recommendations, if I don't reach a deadline, if we don't have a deadline by the time the next meeting comes around, we can vote on it, but otherwise I'll have to.
Okay, so here's what I'll do.
I will
I will go back out, maybe even take some pictures and figure out what signs ought to be where for eastbound and westbound.
And the goal will be directing people onto the Mystic River path, as opposed to any of the other solutions that we've said.
It basically will be, how do you get to the next part of the Mystic River path?
and people can decide, you know, how they might peel off and use a Chondroflolane or anything like that on their own.
But I think that would be at least helpful to people that have no clue, you know, they get to the end on either side, it's like, now what?
So... Helpful and required.
Say again?
Helpful and required.
Yeah.
That's nice of you.
Yeah, thank you.
Okay, I've got that as an action item for me then.
My general thought on this is I don't really see how our proposal that we come up with as a really short-term thing, recognizing that it's terrible, but as a really short-term solution is really anything other than getting people up to Riverside on the sidewalks and using the horrible crosswalks to cross over and get back.
When you say Riverside, do you mean Clippership?
connector at Clippership Drive?
No, no.
I did mean Riverside, actually.
Like, if people are going... Share my screen again, because that's the question I'm wondering, too, Jared, about what's the... Okay, so your red line there, that.
Something to that effect.
Basically along this sidewalk all the way over here, and then you cross one... Oh, that's what you mean by getting to Riverside, okay.
Yeah, either that or cutting up through... What is that little, like, cut-through driveway street there?
Roland Pothier way right there.
Yeah, one of one of those two options.
But something like that, just because I'm trying to think about like, people are going to start flowing in whatever way appears to be like the best choice.
These are terrible choices in general, as we've all talked about.
But that seems to me because there are existing crosswalks there.
That's probably the thing that when people start looking like, where do I go?
Well, the first thing they're probably going to do is look for a crosswalk.
So I feel like that's going to be the natural inclination of people.
It's a, it's not a, it's not a great, but you know, I'd almost pick an option.
I'd almost prefer something that's a little bit of a hybrid of these, which is like, go on this side, cross over here, and then.
Sure, yeah, you might know that path a little.
Point of order, we're coming up on 7.40, 8.40, and one of our main things we wanted to do today was to review the goals of priorities, which I think is going to take us half an hour.
And I'd like to move that we curtail discussion on this particular item and pick it up on our standing Clipper Ship Connector Access agenda item in the future.
Fair enough.
That's a motion.
Seconded.
All in favor.
Aye.
OK, all opposed.
OK, motion passes.
OK, thank you.
All right.
Review of the, I actually put together a slide presentation for this.
Don't worry.
I go through slides relatively fast, especially because.
What item are we going to?
Sorry, we're going to 750 or there are no infrastructure updates.
I have not gotten anything from Todd, so we're just going over to review of goals, priorities.
I move to table this item until the next meeting.
I am happy with that too, unless there is opposition.
So is there a second?
I second.
OK, there's a second.
All in favor?
Aye.
All right, all opposed?
Okay, hearing none, the ayes have it.
That means we are- Now we're on review, right?
Oh, I'm sorry.
You are tabling the infrastructure updates.
Yes, yes, yes, yes.
Okay.
Sorry.
I'm good with that too.
Oh.
It's in favor.
I was- You jumped.
That's why I went back to it.
Sorry about that.
Fair enough.
Watch out what you vote for.
Fair enough, there wasn't much table there in any case.
All right, moving on.
Let's go through slides, because everyone loves slides.
This is effectively a recap of what we had before.
Okay, Medford Bicycle Advisory Commission.
This is mostly for our new members.
Okay, going on.
Let me see, I've got the whole presenter's view over here.
Sorry, Daniel, just a quick question.
Are all of our new members on the meeting now?
We don't have any more that missed this meeting, do we?
There was only, I believe, Lisa Sun, who is not from the commission.
So I believe we have everyone.
Unless, Bruce, you'd keep me honest there?
I think that is correct, but let me go back.
The new members are Adam, Chris, Anna.
Yes, all set.
Cool.
Sounds good.
Thanks.
Okay.
And I'm mostly going to be reading off these slides.
So we're an ad hoc commission, not established by charter.
We're appointed by the mayor.
We serve at her pleasure.
She also appoints new members who we recommend to her.
And then she sends out the official invites, which I think everyone here has gotten.
We do provide an official function to the city of Medford.
We are not a non-profit advocacy organization.
advocacy group, though we do do advocacy, or advocate at least.
I'd like to augment why that's important in our experience.
People have come to us as if we are an advocacy group only, and we need to know that we're not.
Right.
All right, conflict of interest.
I think many people here at least understand the broad strokes of this.
The law governs our operations.
We are officially considered municipal employees, although we, of course, don't make any salary from this or any money from this at all.
Rules regarding self-dealing, bribes, nepotism, so on.
So as you all know, you cannot accept bribes.
There is more on this, and you will all probably at some point go through the training for this, but do not accept wraps because you have so much control over the city.
We have pretty straightforward guidelines, probably covered that before.
There are some resources for conflict of interest law.
I will send out a link to this later so you can click on these links.
And we do have a city solicitor who is available to answer questions, provide best practices.
We do reach out to them every now and then when we have questions about the legality of certain actions or things that we are allowed to do and or say.
So when in doubt, please reach out to me and I can reach out to the city solicitor on your behalf if you think you might be
treading into, you know, murky legal territory.
You can all stop me, but I, you know, stop me as you need and ask questions, but I realize we all have other things, so I'm going to continue on.
Open meeting law, right?
As I'm sure you've probably picked up by now, meetings by public bodies must be conducted in public.
So we cannot meet as a group outside of these public meetings.
This is why we generally don't text, email,
do barbecues, so on and so forth, outside of our working groups or as a full commission at these meetings.
So as much as I'm sure everyone here is a wonderful person, try not to create conflicts with this.
uh as you all know point point point of clarification we we can get together even as a quorum we just cannot discuss anything that is bicycle commission related and you gotta be real careful there because it's real easy to stray into something like that right we can't we can't deliberate right and we can't deliberate right under under the law of almost everything counts as deliberation could be construed that way
So be careful when you discuss that pothole.
We can talk about pets.
Yes, no bikes.
You all know how this goes.
And of course, as people who are probably somewhat into bikes, bikes do come up from time to time in our discussions.
What about tricycles?
No, barbecue sauce.
Barbecue sauce.
And no unicycles.
So yes, I don't know.
I'll double check on unicycles and tricycles at some point.
OK, so as we all know, Bruce is currently filling in for secretary.
I'm sure that at some point someone will perhaps offer to unload Bruce from this.
I think I'm actually officially secretary.
We voted on that a couple back.
OK, I know that you had expressed some, you've been in this role before.
I know this is your second move through this role.
So just offering up if anyone would like to express interest.
Bruce does a great job as secretary, but I will note that.
really quickly right here.
In any case, and sorry if I'm overstepping my bounds here, Bruce, but I just thought I'd put that in in case anyone needs that or would like to act on that.
Yep, so emails, as we all know, we still need to abide by open meeting law rules.
And we have to always do that at normal businesses.
Resources for open meeting laws and the trainings.
Gosh, got this bug that keeps flying through my screen.
Okay.
Sorry, quick question.
Daniel, when you get a chance, could you put the link to the slideshow in the chat just so I can make a record of it?
Yes.
Why don't I do that now so that... And is it publicly viewable?
It is not publicly viewable, but it should be.
Okay.
Maybe I can move it into our collateral material point and make it publicly viewable or make a copy of it.
One second, I'm making this.
Are there other, what are the formal roles within the bike commission other than secretary?
Chair, vice chair, secretary, we have a somewhat unofficial position of a social media coordinator.
Here I will, sorry.
Who serves as each of those?
I am the chair, Emily is the co-chair, Bruce is the secretary.
We do not have a social media coordinator unless someone stepped in for, oh gosh, who is that?
Pat used to be, but then it moved on to... Kevin did some of that, but that's a title with lowercase letters.
It was never an official thing, really.
Right.
Yep.
All right.
Bruce, I just placed it.
Got it.
Thank you.
Okay, great.
Sorry.
Here we are.
All right, so generally meeting conduct and structure, we follow Robert's rules of order.
Slightly more flexible, as you can see, I just say, you know, all in favor, all opposed.
I don't typically take a count, sort of do it by voice vote.
Bruce can probably give a better overview of that, or you can just Google it on your own and figure out Robert's rules of orders.
Zoom meetings.
Be mindful of others wanting to speak.
Avoid talking over others.
Be responsible and considerate.
Subcommittee meetings.
Smaller working groups.
You know, we do have those from time to time.
Regular meetings are the fourth Wednesday of every month.
As I'm sure you've all picked up at this point, sometimes we will skip meetings if it seems that we do not have enough people or it's during specific holiday times where it's difficult to coordinate.
It's possible that we have cancellations.
I don't think we've had technical problems in a while.
As you have all seen, we try to coordinate the best we can.
We do have a requirement of a 48-hour notification to the city.
when we ask for agenda items to be sent in, that is sort of important that you send any agenda items that you want to Bruce so that he has enough time to send the agenda to the city.
And it has to be in a specific way.
We have to send that 48 hours before our meeting so that it can be posted online on the city's calendar.
I generally put the agenda in by noon time on the Monday before the meeting.
Yep.
which is a little bit more than 48 hours, but that's right.
If we ask for items, please send items as soon as you can and be mindful of that.
So if it's a Wednesday, make sure you get them to Bruce.
But I mean, Bruce, you can say this latest Sunday night or... That's preferable.
That effect should just be put up to the prior slide on open meeting law.
You'd like the previous one?
Yeah, because that's what it's about, the 48 hours.
It's about the open meeting.
So add it as a line item.
I will do that after this.
Just wanted to cover that so that everyone knew the general guidelines for submitting agenda items.
Great.
uh main goals and functions we contribute to the bike master plan that the city has it has been a while since we've gone back over that that's generally recommended bike lanes bike infrastructure and the like that is on one of our large like sort of fold outs um i'm sure people may have seen that but we also need to improve that it's also on the website if you need to go there
We provide feedback to the City on road designs, work with the City on infrastructure.
We do try to attend other public meetings, including the Traffic Commission and the City Council when called upon.
Traffic Commission is actually somewhat important because the Traffic Commission hears from other residents of Medford and makes decisions on things such as bike lane and parking.
So if you do have a bike lane that you would like to see approved keep an eye out for it.
I will generally get a heads up and send out you know that as a FYI item for people to be aware of that there are upcoming bicycle related infrastructure changes that are coming to the traffic commission.
It is helpful if you show up for those because adding voices in there does actually make a difference and differing points of view.
So please
If you can, join the traffic commission meetings.
Generally, we serve as consultants to the city and we do other public liaisoning, as you could see with who was at Paul earlier.
We do organize some events, we go to other events, and we do act as a voice to the mayor and other members of the city government to give them guidance.
Daniel, what's the comment about new dedicated bike officials?
Sorry.
Sorry, Ernie.
I said my question too.
I don't know what that means.
Sorry, am I... In the middle, with new dedicated bike officials.
The third to the bottom.
Oh, that might have been an accident added in there.
Apologies.
I will correct that in the slides later.
I would capitalize planning and engineering in the last line.
Okay, real departments.
You noted in your original note, City now has dedicated bike related officials and engineers.
I think that probably means Todd and to some extent,
DPW Director Tim.
And there used to be an engineer that was largely in that role who is no longer filled.
Yeah, I forgot about it.
We did have a city engineer who was specifically dedicated to bicycle infrastructure.
But yes, I blinked on Amy right there.
OK.
That is a role that we're hoping the city will fill again.
Okay, this is good.
I'm getting a quick run through.
I had to set these up relatively quickly, but I will improve on them in the future.
Okay, boom.
Key engagement, social media.
If anyone is interested in helping out with the social media, that would be great.
We also do our best to spread news about things like, for example, the Clippership Connector or new bike lanes going in on social media where possible.
I do have access to the social media accounts.
If anyone would like to take on the role of being the social media organizer, that would be great.
Please reach out to me if you are interested in that.
Generally, key contacts.
Tim, he was a former member of the Bike Commission.
He is the Commissioner of the Public Works.
Todd Blake, he is the Director of Traffic and Transportation.
He shows up in this meeting every now and then.
He's very supportive of bike lanes and other bike infrastructure.
Alicia Hunt, Director of Energy and Environment, also a good contact person, you know, and as Ernie has also pointed out, she has helped us with
several things including you know funds um and the mayor point of information there i think she might actually be a different title now part of community development or if she returned to her role strictly as energy and environment okay i think she was called the director of planning and development yeah they changed they changed the department name uh okay noted um i will
Let me... What is it then, currently?
Planning, Development, and Sustainability.
She's the director of that.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Just a newer name for the department.
They restructured a bit.
Sorry.
Planning... What was that?
Planning, Development, Sustainability.
Yeah, Planning, Development, and Sustainability.
All right.
Taking a note for myself.
I threw a link in the chat just to the web page on it.
Great, thank you.
Otherwise, it sounds like she runs a Zoom course.
Class.
All right.
And last slide.
My objectives as chair.
I would like to try.
Got it.
I don't know if you all saw that.
Chrome needs relaunch.
Good.
I'm almost done.
My objectives as chair are to
get the Medford Police Department to actually commit to bicycle patrols on a regular basis.
I intend to get bicycle BRAC installation at least started in the city.
I need to follow up with Todd and Tim to see how that can be done, but that is a goal of mine.
And I would like to also try and promote efficient meetings where possible, as I know we all have a lot of time.
I or we don't have a lot of time.
I would like to see us move to the point where meetings could possibly be slightly more frequent if we needed them to be without being too much of a burden on everyone who joins them.
So that those are the three main goals that I have.
I don't need to belabor the point as we are approaching 9pm and I would feel sort of bad not being efficient with this.
Those are the goals that I have personally set for myself as chair.
That's the end of the slides.
There we go.
That is my attempt to get through those relatively quickly.
Comments?
Thanks, Sam.
Bravo.
Thanks.
I don't think you need to go back to the slide.
One question I had was,
How we engage with the city council and what I'm sort of thinking about there is I don't exactly know how the budgeting works, but I think the city council has something to do with the city's budget.
And there's sometimes I hear like, oh, there's not money for bike racks or whatever.
maybe a pathway to having that money for bike racks is through the city council.
If the city council is like, hey, we should have a, you know, every year we should have like this line item for like bike infrastructure.
Yes.
You are correct that we have to raise these to the city council to get a line item specifically.
We missed the deadline of this year.
And that is on me for not following up with that fast enough.
That is something that I...