Hello, this is Mayor Brianna Lungo-Kern.
Happy Monday.
I hope you all have a wonderful week.
Just wanted to start the week off with some great news.
I'm going to talk a lot about a number of grants that we received this week, and then next week I'll do a good news video on all the amazing events that are coming up this fall.
So first up, everybody's excited that we have groundbreaking for the Clippership Connector.
That will be in September, where the City's working with DCR to do a groundbreaking ceremony.
but that is going to connect our bike path and be an amazing addition to the city of Medford.
Also, please keep an eye out or look above, click the link.
Please take our charter study committee survey.
That is now open and will be open for several months, but we want anybody and everybody's input so we can update our very, very outdated charter.
Next up, I want to thank the senior center and our director, Pam Kelly,
for applying for and receiving a $45,000 digital literacy grant that will help our seniors throughout the fall and winter and into 2024 to help them with tech access.
So thank you, Pam, for applying.
We're so excited you got that grant.
Next up, we had our tree warden, Aggie Tudin, and our DPW commissioner, Tim McGivern, apply for an urban forestry grant to strengthen the resiliency of our urban forest network.
And we did receive that.
That's an over $100,000 grant.
So congratulations.
Very exciting.
And it definitely goes towards all the work we're doing on municipal vulnerability preparedness.
Next up,
Todd Blake, our director of traffic and transportation, has applied for a number of grants and received two community connection grants, one for over $30,000 for bike parking and one for close to $150,000 for blue bike stations.
As you know, the city, with director Blake and planning, has expanded our blue bike network and we are not stopping.
So we're trying to get them at our schools and some of our parks.
City Hall, Police Station.
We have a lot in the works and we're excited about that.
So congratulations and thank you to Todd Blake.
Last but not least, I want to wish every student, faculty, families the best of luck.
We start school on the 30th of September, which is Wednesday, and we hope everybody has a great day and a great week and a great school year.
Thank you.