[SPEAKER_00]: 7 present, 0 absent.
[SPEAKER_00]: The meeting is called to order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Please rise to see the flag.
[SPEAKER_04]: I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's very, it's a limited, it's a limited agenda.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we have time to talk.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is an emergency.
[SPEAKER_00]: Motions, orders.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're offered by Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Be it so resolved that the Medford City Council extend its deep and sincere condolences to the family of Jerry DeCristofaro on his recent passing, Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_02]: Madam President, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_02]: Jerry DeCristofaro, who passed away February 26th, he was a lifelong resident, lived in Summit Road, the father of Barbara DeCristofaro from Metro Police Department and Dr. DeCristofaro Registrar.
[SPEAKER_02]: Jerry spent 45 years in public service for the Commonwealth of Massachusetts.
[SPEAKER_02]: He served as Chief Investigator for the Licensing Board.
[SPEAKER_02]: He was responsible for establishing the rules and regulations there and enforcing standards for our licensees in the Commonwealth.
[SPEAKER_02]: known for his classic resemblance to Luciano Pavarotti.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mr. De Cristofaro was someone that was loved by many.
[SPEAKER_02]: He had failing health in his later years, but I remember him fondly growing up in metropolitics as someone who's always been there to lend an ear and lend wisdom and lend advice.
[SPEAKER_02]: He's certainly someone that did a great deal for this community.
[SPEAKER_02]: He raised two wonderful children who
[SPEAKER_02]: believe in service, as evidenced by their work, and he will be sadly missed Madam President.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, Jerry to Christopher our dear friend who served this community in this Commonwealth of Massachusetts for the better part of 50 years, I'd ask that this council joins me in extending condolences to his family on their recent loss.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any further discussion on the motion of counselor Knight seconded by Councilor Caraviello, Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_06]: Vice President Bears?
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Caraviello? Councilor Collins? Councilor Knight?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes, Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes, Councilor Tseng, Yes, President Morell?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative. Motion passes, please rise for a moment of silence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Petitions, presentations, and similar papers.
[SPEAKER_00]: 22-281, petition for common victorial license by Starbucks Corporation, doing business as Starbucks Coffee at 177 College Avenue, Metro Massachusetts, 02155.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do we have a petitioner on the line for this?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_03]: My name's Dan Brennan.
[SPEAKER_03]: I handle permits and licenses for Starbucks.
[SPEAKER_00]: Great, can we just get your address for the record as well?
[SPEAKER_03]: Sure, 50 Holt Road, Andover, Massachusetts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you, Mr. Brennan.
[SPEAKER_00]: I turned over to Councilor Scarpelli, Chair of the Licensing Subcommittee.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you, Madam President.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you, Mr. Brennan, for being here.
[SPEAKER_05]: I do see your paperwork is all in order and it's acceptable in my eyes.
[SPEAKER_05]: I know we have a few questions.
[SPEAKER_05]: The location being one, I know there's some confusion.
[SPEAKER_05]: It says 177 College Ave, Mr. Brennan.
[SPEAKER_05]: Is that located inside?
[SPEAKER_05]: facility.
[SPEAKER_03]: And we do have an exterior storefront.
[SPEAKER_03]: So it's on the first floor level one level.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, and it obviously will be open for the public.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, sir.
[SPEAKER_05]: And not students that was a question.
[SPEAKER_05]: What are the what are the hours of operations you're planning on having.
[SPEAKER_03]: So right now we're going to go with 7am to 11pm, probably end up closing earlier than 11pm.
[SPEAKER_03]: We may in the future file for a special permit to open up a bit earlier, but for now we're going to stick with the 7am open to 11pm.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, and there's, I see everything's in order.
[SPEAKER_05]: I know that one of the biggest issues in that area is traffic and that has been approved with no hindrances.
[SPEAKER_05]: So I move approval.
[SPEAKER_05]: I open the floor to my colleagues.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any further discussion?
[SPEAKER_00]: Councilor Knight?
[SPEAKER_02]: Mr. Brennan, I wish you the best of luck.
[SPEAKER_02]: I certainly have no problem with this application that's before us this evening.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm looking forward to seeing the Cummings Center come to completion.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think this will be a nice, what they call, anchor store to bring some foot traffic through the neighborhood.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a couple with the opening of the Green Line Extension.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hopefully in a few short months, we'll transform that neighborhood to make it a little bit more vibrant and
[SPEAKER_02]: We all know if there's a Starbucks, people go there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it'd be nice to see us put traffic down there and another opportunity and an option for an amenity for some of the college students and neighborhood residents.
[SPEAKER_02]: So thank you for your application, sir.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you, councilor.
[SPEAKER_00]: Councilor Tseng.
[SPEAKER_04]: I just wanted to know to someone in the area, I'm excited to have this option open to me.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm excited to see my own neighborhood get more vibrant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you, councilor Tseng.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any further discussion?
[SPEAKER_00]: On the motion of Councilor Scarpelli to approve the petition seconded by Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_06]: Vice President Bears.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Collins.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Tseng.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: President Morell.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So in the affirmative, zero in the negative, the petition is approved.
[SPEAKER_00]: Congratulations, Mr. Brennan.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Reports of committees, 22-075, March 7th, 2022, committee of the whole report to follow.
[SPEAKER_00]: This was a committee of the whole meeting we had last Monday to discuss the flooding issues at Woolard and High Street.
[SPEAKER_00]: We had a representative from the Department of Transportation, as well as a representative from the design firm, I believe, to walk us through this.
[SPEAKER_00]: We left with the decision to meet again as we were near completion so that we can have input from residents.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the motion of Councilor Caraviello to approve, seconded by Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_06]: Vice President Bears?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Caraviello?
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Collins?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Knight?
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Scarpelli?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Sang?
[SPEAKER_06]: President Morell?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, seven in favor, zero in the negative.
[SPEAKER_00]: Motion passes.
[SPEAKER_00]: 22-012, March 9th, 2022, Subcommittee on Ordinances and Rules.
[SPEAKER_00]: Report to follow, Vice President Bears.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you, Madam President.
[SPEAKER_01]: Councilor Knight, Councilor Collins, and myself met in the Ordinances and Rules Subcommittee.
[SPEAKER_01]: We reviewed a number of papers before the committee, as well as proposals.
[SPEAKER_01]: previously existing and new proposals around the rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: We agreed to a certain number of minor changes and also developed a list of further topics to discuss, and we will hopefully be having a meeting in the next few weeks to go through that list of additional items to discuss, and then reporting something out to the committee of the whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you, Vice President Bears.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the motion of Councilor Knight to approve the report, seconded by Vice President Bears.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing none, moving on to records.
[SPEAKER_00]: The records of the meeting of March 8th, 2022 were passed to Councilor Tseng.
[SPEAKER_00]: Councilor Tseng, how did you find the records?
[SPEAKER_04]: I find them in order.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sorry, someone might have to mute.
[SPEAKER_04]: I find them in order and I move approval.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the motion of Councilor Tseng, seconded by Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_06]: Vice President Bears.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Collins?
[SPEAKER_08]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Knight?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Scarpelli?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Tseng?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: President Morell?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative, the records are accepted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Further?
[SPEAKER_00]: On the motion of Councilor Knight to adjourn, seconded by Vice President Bears.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_06]: Vice President Bears?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Caraviello?
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Collins?
[SPEAKER_08]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.