[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, the public meeting, the City of Medford Liquor License Commission for March 20th, 24th will come to order.
[SPEAKER_01]: We do have an agenda to follow.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the first thing on the agenda is to approve the minutes of last month's meeting, plus we have
[SPEAKER_01]: some additional minutes that were sent to us by Gary to approve as well.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_06]: Agreed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Alrighty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why don't we start with last month's minutes.
[SPEAKER_01]: I did have a chance to review them.
[SPEAKER_01]: They looked perfectly fine to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ben, I don't know if you had a chance to check it out.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yep, Commissioner, I did have a chance to check them out.
[SPEAKER_06]: I saw the minutes from January 11th and then the other minutes from February 21st and they were really detailed and those were, you know, fairly extensive meetings and from everything I can remember, they look accurate and they look good.
[SPEAKER_06]: So thanks Darya.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, I agree.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was a lot of work, especially we did cover a lot of stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's great.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So what we can do is approve the minutes for the February 21st meeting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ben, if you want to make a motion for the minutes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Can I approve them both?
[SPEAKER_06]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_06]: Make a motion for both?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, so I'm going to make a motion to approve the minutes for the two meetings we've had so far this year.
[SPEAKER_06]: The first one is for the January 11, 2024 minutes.
[SPEAKER_06]: The second one is for the February 21, 2024 minutes for the License Commission meeting.
[SPEAKER_01]: OK, I second the motion.
[SPEAKER_01]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_01]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_01]: The motion to accept the minutes is an order and those are all squared away.
[SPEAKER_01]: What I'd like to do, Ben, if it's okay with you is just go a little out of order.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the agenda because we have a couple that are going to involve a little bit of time and we don't want to tie too many people up.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what we also have to do is, well, what I'd like to start with is new business first.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only reason being is that we seem to be having an issue lately with people coming to this commission for not only one-day licenses, but other items as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: and they're coming in after the 48-hour round agenda.
[SPEAKER_01]: The agenda's got to be posted 48 hours by law before the meeting, and we are not allowed to vote on anything unless it's on the agenda.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when we're receiving
[SPEAKER_01]: applications for one day licenses or anything else that's coming in the day of or a day before, it's not good.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we shouldn't be voting on it unless it's on the agenda.
[SPEAKER_01]: So what I was going to say is maybe we can have Daria put on next month's agenda that we can make a motion to strictly enforce the 48-hour rule.
[SPEAKER_01]: And maybe set even a deadline, you know, for the Friday prior, because sometimes you have a Monday holiday and she can't get legally.
[SPEAKER_01]: We can't we don't have enough time for the 48 hour rule.
[SPEAKER_01]: uh the open meeting law rule so i i would suggest that maybe just put it on the agenda that we can talk about it next month when the chairman's here as well and um and from that point forward um we can enforce it i know we had a couple today um and and you know i don't think we i don't have a problem with putting them through but
[SPEAKER_01]: It's very difficult, especially we've got a couple of fairly large things today.
[SPEAKER_01]: It took me a while to read through a lot of this paperwork, so we can't get it an hour or two before it's not going to happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Plus Daria, God bless her, she's wonderful.
[SPEAKER_01]: She's doing a regular job at City Hall as well as handling this stuff for us and keeping everything in order.
[SPEAKER_01]: She's what makes everything work.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's even doing a,
[SPEAKER_01]: I would imagine a strain on down here as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So anyways, that's enough for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that was the new business that I had.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you have any new business?
[SPEAKER_06]: No, I agree.
[SPEAKER_06]: We wanna process a lot of business in here and we just need them in on time so that we can get them on the agenda and just get it done right and help everybody out the best we can.
[SPEAKER_06]: So no, I'm totally in favor of that.
[SPEAKER_06]: So say we add that to next month and we'll move on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, sounds great.
[SPEAKER_01]: All righty, let's see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Next item on the agenda.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am going to go to, we have Leilani from the Medford Public Library.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hi, how are you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Did I say your name right, Leilani?
[SPEAKER_08]: Yes, perfect, thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Could you tell us a little bit about what's going on?
[SPEAKER_01]: I know you're looking for a one-day license at the library.
[SPEAKER_08]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_08]: So it's the same event we did last year.
[SPEAKER_08]: It's our trivia night.
[SPEAKER_08]: We're expecting about 100 people.
[SPEAKER_08]: They will all be pre-sold tickets.
[SPEAKER_08]: It's a fundraiser, Saturday, May 4th in the evening, and just beer and wine and volunteers that are pouring beer and wine.
[SPEAKER_08]: Just snacks, nothing substantial food wise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, great.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we know you folks always do a really good job.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've sent us layouts of the.
[SPEAKER_01]: of the functions and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all good.
[SPEAKER_01]: You also, I believe we have on file your insurance for that as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I don't have an issue with any of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ben, how about yourself?
[SPEAKER_06]: No, I concur.
[SPEAKER_06]: You guys have never had any problems, and we're happy that you're having good events at the library, great space.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I'm good with it.
[SPEAKER_06]: I can make a motion to move this one along.
[SPEAKER_01]: All righty.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will second the motion.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, so I'll just say it.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'll make a motion to accept the one day license that's for the Friends of Medford Library for the one day on May the 4th.
[SPEAKER_06]: And we have the insurance on file, we have layouts on file, so I'll make a motion to accept that.
[SPEAKER_01]: All right, I'll second that motion.
[SPEAKER_01]: All in favor?
[SPEAKER_01]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_01]: Motion accepted.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_08]: Have a good day.
[SPEAKER_01]: All righty, thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Bye.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good luck.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thanks.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, next thing on the agenda.
[SPEAKER_01]: We had just a quick
[SPEAKER_01]: We just need a favorable approval of the Ocean State job lot.
[SPEAKER_01]: The DUA certificate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is Ocean State here?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_04]: Good afternoon, members of the Commission.
[SPEAKER_04]: Mike Ross.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm an attorney for Ocean State.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hey, Mike.
[SPEAKER_01]: How are you?
[SPEAKER_04]: Good.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thanks for having me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, my pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: We did receive the DUA certificate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything looks in order.
[SPEAKER_01]: Daria, you are satisfied with that as well?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, all good already.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I don't have an issue with, I know we have had to revisit it and you folks, you know, we were able to get the information that we needed and it should be good to go unless Ben, you have anything, anything to say on it?
[SPEAKER_06]: No, no, we discussed it and I'm in agreement.
[SPEAKER_06]: I think we're fine.
[SPEAKER_06]: We're good to go there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, if you want to make a motion to accept the.
[SPEAKER_01]: The certificate from motion state job lot, we should be good to go.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, so let me just word this correctly.
[SPEAKER_06]: So.
[SPEAKER_06]: Um, where are they.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, sorry.
[SPEAKER_04]: Could I just make one suggestion here?
[SPEAKER_04]: This may help out.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think we need, and you can certainly correct me if I'm wrong, but I think we need a motion if the commission is willing to approve the applicant, the change in manager application, the DOA certificate was just that we didn't have it the last time.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I don't, so I don't know that it was ever approved.
[SPEAKER_07]: It was approved.
[SPEAKER_07]: It was approved last year.
[SPEAKER_07]: Oh, I see.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then the commission rejected it because of the DUA certification?
[SPEAKER_07]: No, the commission approved it, but it was the ABCC that rejected it.
[SPEAKER_07]: Oh, that's right.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: And they worked with Nicole, but they never got anything in a timely manner.
[SPEAKER_07]: So that's why they said that this would be a consideration from them to get the, once they get the updated DUA certificate.
[SPEAKER_07]: Great.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once once we approve that area, you send it back to the and it gets approved through them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: Awesome.
[SPEAKER_06]: And so we already, because the manager, we already looked at that.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, that was all that was like, back in August of last year.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_07]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: So.
[SPEAKER_06]: Sorry, there's a lot of paperwork on this one.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm just trying to pull up the... Okay, so we're going to... I'm going to make a motion that this commission is going to favorably approve the DUA certificate that was provided to us from ABCC for Ocean State Job Lot.
[SPEAKER_06]: at 30 Commercial Street in Medford that completes the change of manager process, which we already approved.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is correct.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will second that motion.
[SPEAKER_01]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_04]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_01]: Motion's been approved.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're good to go, sir.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Next, St.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rayfield's Parish.
[SPEAKER_01]: I thought I saw Gina there somewhere.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hi, Bob.
[SPEAKER_01]: How are you?
[SPEAKER_02]: Good.
[SPEAKER_02]: How are you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me just pull this up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why don't you tell us a little bit about your event, Gina?
[SPEAKER_02]: So this is an event we have had for many years.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is a $300 raffle, elimination raffle.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then we want to serve beer and wine.
[SPEAKER_02]: We'll have some snacks.
[SPEAKER_02]: We're expecting about 200 people.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's on April 5th.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it is people buy $100 ticket, and then the last couple standing either split the raffle or the last number drawn wins the $10,000.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it's a $10,000 prize.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wow, very nice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very nice.
[SPEAKER_01]: I remember that.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think you might have come way, way back in your day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yes, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was doing it then too.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a lot of fun too, which is great.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you folks have been doing this for a while.
[SPEAKER_01]: We never have any problems with St.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ray's.
[SPEAKER_01]: You always do as we ask.
[SPEAKER_01]: I even see that you submitted your insurance certificate and a sketch of the layout of the event, which is great.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I don't see any issues with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: How about yourself, Ben?
[SPEAKER_06]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_06]: So you'll get a licensed bartender to serve?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, a tip serve bartender.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: Is it someone you bring in or is just somebody that's part of the congregation or part of the... It's someone that works, someone at the school works, their relative comes in.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: They work in a restaurant though, they do catering and stuff, so... I vaguely remember this.
[SPEAKER_06]: Is it somebody's daughter?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, Juliana.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, okay, okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, I remember asking this last time.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's that's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, we used to use parent volunteers, which didn't work out so well.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we've had this lady for.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, just because, you know, can be that's a pretty good crowd and and outside of church is not we're not worried about it, but it's just a good crowd of people.
[SPEAKER_06]: So good to have somebody very confident doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm seeing the layout, I'm seeing the insurance, and I'm not worried about anything.
[SPEAKER_06]: I don't have any questions.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm good with this one, Bob, if you want me to make a motion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, go right ahead.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: All right, so I will make a motion to accept the one-day alcohol license for May, no, April 5th.
[SPEAKER_05]: April 5th.
[SPEAKER_06]: April 5th, right, for St.
[SPEAKER_06]: Raphael's Parish.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that's from the event from 6.30 to 11.30 p.m.
[SPEAKER_06]: This is for the parish and parent social fundraiser.
[SPEAKER_06]: We're accepting the insurance and the layout that has been provided by Gene.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I second.
[SPEAKER_01]: The motion?
[SPEAKER_01]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_01]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jeanne, you're up.
[SPEAKER_02]: I have one question.
[SPEAKER_02]: In previous years, I didn't see one last year.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do I get a paper copy of the license?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or did you stop doing that?
[SPEAKER_02]: I used to get one from a little certificate.
[SPEAKER_07]: Jeanne, if you need it, I can provide it to you, but it's up to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, if you don't need it, I just wanted to make sure that if someone comes in, I used to post it like I would put it in a little frame by the bar, just to say we're legit.
[SPEAKER_02]: But as long as it's okay with you guys, I don't have that up there.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's whatever.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah, nobody has that issue.
[SPEAKER_07]: So I don't okay, unless they asked me for it.
[SPEAKER_07]: I don't give it because we know it's approved.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_07]: So now minutes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_06]: I hope it's a good one.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, moving right along.
[SPEAKER_01]: Representative from Boston Glory, are you here?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's me.
[SPEAKER_01]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is your name, sir?
[SPEAKER_00]: Jay Tallerman.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm one of the owners of Boston Glory.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is year four for us.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so you're back.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're back.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, made the playoffs last year.
[SPEAKER_00]: We had a good year.
[SPEAKER_00]: No incidents again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Happy to be back.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's great.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's awesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this is basically just the series of events.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we have, I have the 6 states here and the times.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only question I had what I really like is.
[SPEAKER_01]: the layout you sent to us that you keep the alcohol in one section.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think you guys were the first ones that did it last year.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's when I saw it is that you rope off a portion of the stands.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now people want to sit and have a refreshment while they're watching the game.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're contained just to that area, which is- Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: We were really thankful that
[SPEAKER_00]: you know, between Kevin Bailey and the Hormel Commission and you all, we were able to, it helped us a bunch because the beer garden itself is kind of a tough view, whereas that roped off area, the stands, they get a better view of the game, but still allows us to control, you know, where the patrons are going to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it kind of corrals everybody, which is nice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it makes it a lot easier, I would imagine.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that worked out well for you last year, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it really did.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, our crowds are pretty good and pretty respectful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every once in a while, do we say to someone, hey, you can't stray with that glass of beer.
[SPEAKER_00]: But everyone's been really respectful of our rules.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's great and I noticed too, that you get a decent crowd estimated 200 to 800 patrons.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and it's going up every year as we get more and more traction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we've kind of.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, when it's a tough weekend or we don't have a great opponent, it can be as low as 300.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this year, we've got a really good schedule and we made the playoffs last year.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we think we could be pushing that 400 to 500 per event pretty routinely, which is a good result for us.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good for Medford.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we're really happy.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's awesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I trust that you did reach out to the police department for any details.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, we always do.
[SPEAKER_00]: We work closely with Kevin.
[SPEAKER_00]: We work closely with the Hormel Commission.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then we also go before the council because we bring in five different food trucks.
[SPEAKER_00]: We did five last year.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know if we'll do five or six this year.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we got the Board of Health on board.
[SPEAKER_00]: We coordinate all that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mayor has been really supportive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's been good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Awesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: That sounds good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, no, I don't have any issues with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ben, how about yourself?
[SPEAKER_06]: No, no, I haven't.
[SPEAKER_06]: I don't have any issues.
[SPEAKER_06]: The events, the same basically range kind of like past years.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, and there's a range of times of the day that we're doing it just to accommodate teams that are traveling to us.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yeah, it's a flow where it's essentially a five hour event, but we really wrap up.
[SPEAKER_00]: way before that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's been pretty good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, you know, Kevin Bailey's team has been good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hormel Commission's been good.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have it down to a good routine now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's been fun.
[SPEAKER_06]: Good.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm good with it.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm glad you guys are back.
[SPEAKER_06]: I remember you guys did this and then I was like hoping you wouldn't
[SPEAKER_06]: The whole thing would remain, and I'm glad it has, and being able to be in the stands, having a drink while you're in the stands, so you can see the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you know, it was a little bit of a leap of faith for us and for you all to let it happen, but it's, um, everyone behaved themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, we have a, it's, you know, it's not a particularly rowdy bunch anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, people shout for the, for the players, but it's not that kind of crowd.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everyone's pretty respectful of what's going on over here.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, so we have what, six of these, right?
[SPEAKER_06]: Six events?
[SPEAKER_00]: Six of these, yep.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have a new brewer.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're going straight with Night Shift.
[SPEAKER_00]: Last year, we had kind of a middle tier brewer who served other people's beer, but this year, we're going straight with Night Shift Brewery.
[SPEAKER_00]: They have their own TIP certified staff.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we're excited for the partnership with them.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, I mean, they're good.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, pretty local.
[SPEAKER_06]: They're good.
[SPEAKER_06]: They're okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I would make a, I can make a motion to approve these Bob, unless you have more questions, Bob.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I actually have all the six dates and times and everything here.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to do it?
[SPEAKER_01]: You want me to make the motion?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know because we would have had to do a lot of shuffling with the different dates and papers, but yeah, I can make the motion.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm going to make a motion to approve the six one-day licenses to Boston Glory.
[SPEAKER_01]: uh, Jason Tellerman, um, for six sporting events, uh, located at Harmel Stadium.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, uh, we can approve all six at once.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first one is for, um, April 26th from 5 to 10 p.m.
[SPEAKER_01]: The second one is May 4th from 3 to 10 p.m.
[SPEAKER_01]: The third one is May 17th from 5 p.m.
[SPEAKER_01]: to 10 p.m.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fourth one is June 2nd from 11 a.m.
[SPEAKER_01]: to 4 p.m.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fifth one is June 8th from 5 p.m.
[SPEAKER_01]: to 10 p.m.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the sixth one is June 22nd from 5 p.m.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all of them.
[SPEAKER_06]: And just that one question, it's not really, but that one Saturday, May 4th, it says everything's like 5 to 10.
[SPEAKER_06]: This one's 3 to 10 p.m.
[SPEAKER_06]: Is there any reason for that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, that one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yes, because it's possible that we may change the time of the game.
[SPEAKER_00]: The game is slated to start at five.
[SPEAKER_00]: Um, but we are trying to push it to 10 if we can get Toronto, which is flying in to be a little more flexible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Regardless, it wouldn't be any more than 5 hours total.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so we can make that note or you all can make that note that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It'll either be a 3 to 8 or 5 to 10.
[SPEAKER_06]: 3 to 8 or 5%, okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: If we just make that note, then that's, and you guys abide by that, then that's- 100%.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, I'm okay with that then.
[SPEAKER_06]: All right, then I will accept that motion made by Commissioner Delfano.
[SPEAKER_01]: All right, call in favor.
[SPEAKER_01]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, motion passes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're all set, Jake.
[SPEAKER_01]: Great.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you all so much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hope we see you out at game.
[SPEAKER_00]: And thank you to Daria as well for all of her help on this stuff.
[SPEAKER_06]: Right.
[SPEAKER_06]: Hope it's a good season.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Talk to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, let's see.
[SPEAKER_01]: It looks like we have Brian.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Hey, team.
[SPEAKER_01]: How are you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not too bad.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hey, guys.
[SPEAKER_01]: I take it you heard my little speech at the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what we're going to talk about next next month.
[SPEAKER_01]: We want to try and keep.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just one day licenses, but all business that we have to vote on has to be in to apply by the 48 hour law, open public meeting law.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to go on the agenda and anything on the agenda we have to vote for.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have to be within that time frame.
[SPEAKER_01]: If somebody called you up last minute, you got to explain to them that you can't put it in.
[SPEAKER_01]: prior to when we speak about it next month.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're gonna see if we can set some hourly limits, a cutoff date, because a lot of times there's a Monday holiday, and if they on in by a certain time on Friday, it just affects everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you know, it doesn't, we don't wanna have any more issues.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we,
[SPEAKER_01]: We just want to let you, that's why I kind of kept you and Heather near the end, just so you get a little gist of it that we talked about it earlier and kind of give you a heads up.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be familiar with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But other than that, the ones, you know, the one that you submitted, we're cool with doing that today.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not a problem at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's see if I've got it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can tell us a little bit about the event if you like.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sure, it's actually, it's becoming a monthly event.
[SPEAKER_03]: To be honest with you, we've been doing it for a while.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then last month, we did it with a one day license as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's just, it's growing.
[SPEAKER_03]: So it's become kind of a series.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the gaming, the FIFA themed gaming, gaming event.
[SPEAKER_03]: And yeah, so we sold out last time, we're pretty much sold out for this next one.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's great.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The new drawing too, which is good.
[SPEAKER_01]: It looks very good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very professional.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thanks.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's getting there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So we're actually looking for a local establishment to host something at the end of, excuse me, at the end of the year, probably like October, November, and we'll do like a big event there, you know, because I think, uh, I think we'd be too small to do an annual event of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, uh, yeah, it was a great thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Awesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, as usual, you know, everything is in order.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, I know that we have your insurance certificate on file.
[SPEAKER_01]: And like I say, the drawing, the updated drawing was very good.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't have any issues.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ben, how about yourself?
[SPEAKER_06]: No, no, I, uh, sounds like it's a good event and you're coming back for more.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, uh, so cool.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm good with it.
[SPEAKER_07]: Bobby.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: I think the drawing, it was for Tufts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Um, no, there was two of them, Derry.
[SPEAKER_01]: I believe one for Tufts and one for event them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you get the one for event them?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, you sent us the event then one.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, it was like with Brian's other attachment.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, and it's as a JPEG, it's as a JPEG, not a PDF.
[SPEAKER_07]: Got it.
[SPEAKER_07]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_07]: It didn't print for me.
[SPEAKER_07]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_06]: But I'm looking at it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Looks good.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I would make a motion if that's all right, Commissioner.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we can move this one along.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, so I will make and then we have the insurance and everything on file.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I'm going to go with the assumption of that.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I'll make a motion to accept the one-day license for Sunday, April 14th from 1 to 7 p.m.
[SPEAKER_06]: This is for Event Them, 344 Salem Street, Medford.
[SPEAKER_06]: This is for their FIFA video game event.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I second the motion.
[SPEAKER_01]: All in favor?
[SPEAKER_01]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're good, the motion passes, good luck.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thanks guys, thanks everyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: See you Ryan.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good luck.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, next on the agenda do we have Heather from Tufts?
[SPEAKER_01]: Heather West?
[SPEAKER_01]: Somebody from Tufts?
[SPEAKER_01]: Samara from Tufts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: All right, this is for the senior bingo.
[SPEAKER_01]: Could you tell us a little something about the event?
[SPEAKER_10]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_10]: We did this event, I think, back in December as well.
[SPEAKER_10]: It is a pretty tame event.
[SPEAKER_10]: We do have food.
[SPEAKER_10]: They will be checked in.
[SPEAKER_10]: They will only be allowing people that are of age and that are seniors.
[SPEAKER_10]: They will only have 1 entrance as you can probably see on the floor plan there.
[SPEAKER_10]: We will have tough police detail here on site.
[SPEAKER_10]: The only caveat with this event is that unfortunately, there was a mix up and my coworkers submitted the incorrect date.
[SPEAKER_10]: It is actually a day before.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I need to know what.
[SPEAKER_10]: You need to do to kind of rectify that is actually on Thursday, March 28th.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so it's the prior day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Daria, how do you suggest we handle that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can we just pencil that in and grant the license for that, so they don't have to make out a whole new application?
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah, I think that's fine, because in our minutes, we'll say March 28th, Thursday.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, 28th.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Sounds easy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, we can correct it on our end, and like Daria says, in the minutes, it'll be in there, so it'll be fine.
[SPEAKER_10]: I really appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you heard my little speech at the beginning or no about submitting the one day licenses.
[SPEAKER_10]: End of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, basically what's been happening lately is we've been getting inundated with the last minute licenses, one day licenses and are basically anything renewals, change of managers, stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what happens is they have to be in 48 hours before the actual meeting.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so the agenda can be posted and, um,
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, if we don't, we're going to be in violation of the law if we don't post the agenda for 48 hours prior.
[SPEAKER_01]: So next month, we're going to discuss it at that meeting that we're going to be strictly enforcing this from this point forward.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if we're going to set a cut off date, maybe sometime on Friday, the Friday before, just in case there's a Monday holiday or something so that we can comply with the open meeting law and.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it'll be unfortunate, but any last minute, a day or two before, we can't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: We won't be able to accept it till the following month.
[SPEAKER_01]: With us, Daria's got a lot to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: She wears a couple of hats at City Hall.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this can be very frustrating for not only her, but for us, because we have to read all of this stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most of the stuff isn't as simple as a one day license, but legally it has to be posted.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that was the heads up we just wanted to give you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So for next month, if anything should be arising, just make sure you get it in like the Friday before meetings.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, that makes sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so, you know, I saw senior bingo and I'm saying, jeez, I only live around the corner.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe I'll go play some senior bingo.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm a senior, but I think you meant the seniors are tough.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, well, so much of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm only kidding.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, everything looks good.
[SPEAKER_01]: My question to you was, obviously, you have been in touch with the Tufts PD for details.
[SPEAKER_01]: Other than that, Ben, I don't have any issues.
[SPEAKER_01]: How about yourself?
[SPEAKER_06]: No, looks good.
[SPEAKER_06]: Good name, Senior Bingo.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: No, I'm okay with it.
[SPEAKER_06]: So Thursday, March 28th.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can make the motion if you like.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I'll make a motion to accept the one-day license.
[SPEAKER_06]: This is for March 28th, 2024 for the event called Senior Bingo for Tufts Catering and Dining.
[SPEAKER_06]: Based on these plans and the insurance that we have on file.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, great.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will second that motion.
[SPEAKER_01]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_01]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, motion passes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're all set.
[SPEAKER_01]: One day license has been issued.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good luck with the event.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think the only thing I see left would be Semolina.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that correct, Daria?
[SPEAKER_09]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hi there.
[SPEAKER_01]: How are you?
[SPEAKER_09]: Good.
[SPEAKER_09]: How are you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Good, and you are?
[SPEAKER_01]: Christina?
[SPEAKER_01]: Christina, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hey, Christina.
[SPEAKER_01]: Could you tell us a little bit about what's going on?
[SPEAKER_01]: What you're requesting today?
[SPEAKER_01]: I know you approve a change of stock interest.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, so...
[SPEAKER_09]: My partner Dave and I, Dave is starting the process of retiring.
[SPEAKER_09]: And so we, over the past couple of years, have been working on some succession plans for both of our businesses, for Dave's in Somerville and us in Semolina here.
[SPEAKER_09]: Um, and, uh, that's involved, um, working with, uh, some long time employees that we want to, um, uh, you know, lock down and, and incentivize them.
[SPEAKER_09]: And, and, uh, cause I don't have kids and Dave's kids, uh, don't aren't interested.
[SPEAKER_09]: So, um,
[SPEAKER_09]: our goal is to have this restaurant uh you know last past my working uh lifetime and bruno and jackie are both uh bruno's been here since day one even before and jackie's been here for uh you know four or so years now and um
[SPEAKER_01]: and yeah we're making them both part you know minority partners share with bruno's 10 going to be 10 now jackie's going to be five percent that's great yes very good it's uh it's good that you know today especially like you said you have some good help there and some good people you want to hang on to them absolutely very very difficult to do nowadays but um that's a smart way of doing it i guess
[SPEAKER_01]: I, Ben, do you, did you have a chance to read over?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, yeah, it was a lot.
[SPEAKER_06]: A lot, I know.
[SPEAKER_06]: So there's like, yeah, so in basically- Lawyer's very thorough.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, you know, I mean, it looks like in a contract, you know, it looks like a, you know, multiple contracts.
[SPEAKER_06]: So it's, so it's 20 shares,
[SPEAKER_06]: So it's five shares being sold.
[SPEAKER_09]: I can kind of easily lay it out.
[SPEAKER_09]: So Dave and I were 60-40 partners.
[SPEAKER_09]: I was 60%, he's 40%.
[SPEAKER_09]: And so he, as he's retiring, he's selling off 20 of his shares.
[SPEAKER_09]: 20%, 20, same thing, there's 100 total.
[SPEAKER_09]: So we're not issuing any new shares.
[SPEAKER_09]: um so i i bought five of them and bruno bought five like wrote a check for it and then i am financing um
[SPEAKER_09]: Bruno and Jackie each to buy the remaining 10 from Dave.
[SPEAKER_09]: So Dave's share drops down to 20.
[SPEAKER_09]: Mine jumped up to 65.
[SPEAKER_09]: Bruno is 10, Jackie is five.
[SPEAKER_09]: And a lot of that paperwork was the promissory notes between myself and Jackie and myself and Bruno about the loan for them to buy the shares.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay, so yeah, there I.
[SPEAKER_09]: I have money saved for a project down the road, and I thought it was a good way to get them on board and to help them, because neither of them has that kind of cash to just write that much of a check to date.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: OK.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, thanks for that explanation.
[SPEAKER_06]: Hey, it makes sense.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's good.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm glad you guys are doing that and keeping...
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, I'm keeping.
[SPEAKER_06]: So is it just for Semolina or is for Dave's Pasta too or it's just, it's just.
[SPEAKER_09]: No, it's just Semolina.
[SPEAKER_09]: It's two completely separate businesses.
[SPEAKER_09]: We are coincidentally going through the same process at Dave's because our other partner that's just involved with Dave's is, we're doing sort of the same thing with him.
[SPEAKER_09]: He's a longtime employee and he's buying shares from Dave.
[SPEAKER_09]: So, it's a little convoluted, but.
[SPEAKER_09]: All right.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, but this just pertains just to some of them, which is what I was like.
[SPEAKER_09]: So, Jackie and Bruno don't have any interest and it's just here.
[SPEAKER_06]: All right.
[SPEAKER_06]: Well, I'm sure this took quite a little while to get it all.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, point where it's submitted to us and we're seeing everything and I'm not.
[SPEAKER_06]: From what I can tell, nothing is missing your explanation sort of matches with what I'm seeing.
[SPEAKER_06]: from a non-legally trained eye.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I don't have any problem with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just have one issue, Mr. Commissioner.
[SPEAKER_01]: I had noticed on page 29 of PDF number two is a
[SPEAKER_01]: DUA certificate, and the DUA certificate is expired.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I know that these things are a pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's issued January 30th, and it expires on February 28th, which doesn't give you much time to get to us with a unexpired certificate.
[SPEAKER_01]: What I'm willing to do, Mr. Commissioner, is approve the change of stock interest with the condition that a new certificate be issued to Daria before she submits this to the ABCC.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I just, you know, the reason why it's because we just had earlier with the ocean.
[SPEAKER_09]: So, yeah, I think because we were trying to get on the earlier, remember Daria, we're trying to get on the February meeting.
[SPEAKER_09]: And then, yeah, so we had put all this.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, we put everything together a long time ago, but yeah, I can get that.
[SPEAKER_09]: No problem.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah, because the only reason is Bobby has a good point.
[SPEAKER_07]: They.
[SPEAKER_07]: The ABCC, if it's like, not within the 30 days that they get it to, it's not considered valid.
[SPEAKER_07]: So if you can send that to me and I'll submit it when you get it to me, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: You guys, I can get Jackie and Bruno up here.
[SPEAKER_09]: It's the middle of lunch, so they're down there.
[SPEAKER_09]: But if you need to talk to them, I can grab them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I'm satisfied.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything, you know, like Ben said, we're not legal experts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything looks fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just the documents that we normally see on a monthly basis, like the DUA certificate and other documents like that, it's pretty easy for us to pick out.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I know that
[SPEAKER_01]: the ABCC had kicked this back to Daria.
[SPEAKER_01]: And like I said, we can approve it contingent upon a valid certificate.
[SPEAKER_01]: And like Daria says, the sooner the better, because it'll give her a time to get it out to the ABCC before the new one expires, you know?
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: I think they're pretty quick when you apply for it.
[SPEAKER_09]: I think you get an email like a little while later or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, other than that, I don't have any issues with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ben, did you want to, was there anything else or do you want to make a motion?
[SPEAKER_06]: No, I think it's good.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, so I will make a motion.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: So CTDG.
[SPEAKER_06]: DJ.
[SPEAKER_06]: DJ, sorry.
[SPEAKER_05]: Ink.
[SPEAKER_06]: Ink is similar to kitchen.
[SPEAKER_06]: OK.
[SPEAKER_06]: OK, so I will make a motion to approve or accept this change of stock interest application based on these five documents that we have here for the stocks being sold.
[SPEAKER_06]: for CTDJ Inc.
[SPEAKER_06]: doing business as Semolina Kitchen.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, I will make a motion to approve or accept, I think rather, these applications.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, pending the valid... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...way certificate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, and I will second that motion.
[SPEAKER_01]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_01]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, your application has been approved.
[SPEAKER_09]: Great, thanks so much.
[SPEAKER_09]: Dari, I'll get back to you as soon as I can.
[SPEAKER_07]: Alrighty, good luck to you.
[SPEAKER_07]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_07]: Just email it to me and then I will add it to the application.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay, thanks.
[SPEAKER_07]: Take care.
[SPEAKER_01]: Take care.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I think that just about does it for us, correct?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Great.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything that you may be thinking about, Ben, or anything that's come up now?
[SPEAKER_06]: Well, since you guys last saw me, we had a baby that came early last week.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, good for you.
[SPEAKER_06]: Congratulations.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I'm home this week, yep.
[SPEAKER_06]: And thank you, baby girl Cassidy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good for you.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which number is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Two, three?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Wow.
[SPEAKER_06]: God bless you.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: So they're upstairs.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm home.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I wanted to... I saw Alan bailed last minute.
[SPEAKER_06]: I didn't want to have to have this whole thing rescheduled.
[SPEAKER_06]: So if we're done, I've got plenty to do right now.
[SPEAKER_06]: But yeah, everything's good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's good.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's good.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's awesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's good to hear.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and next month we'll discuss this whole last minute thing, the 48-hour meeting law and all that stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: But maybe we can, in the meantime, just in our heads, put together something, maybe a deadline or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But other than that, I think everything else is running pretty smoothly.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing pending that we're working on, and I think we're good.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: I like that Friday deadline.
[SPEAKER_06]: Um, uh, yeah, we can, we can have, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I was going to say holiday, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: My Friday anyways, just more reasonable Monday morning, everything piles up.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's more.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: Cause Monday morning it's like everything from the weekend, like it like hits you sometimes.
[SPEAKER_07]: And right.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: I feel like Friday is better because then it gives me time to put it all together, send it to you guys, and then just get it your way too, and then you have time to review it and all that good stuff too.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I think that'd be good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, this chair thing ain't as easy as it looks.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think I remember half the stuff I was supposed to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were good.
[SPEAKER_01]: I made some notes just in case from one of Jim's meetings, and I said, just in case I have to cover it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, I'll read the last line to end the meeting.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all I have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anyone else?
[SPEAKER_01]: I make a motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_01]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_01]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it's been accepted.
[SPEAKER_01]: All right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, well done.