Um, welcome everybody back to these for 49.
I'm going to read the meeting notice and then we can call the, we'll call the role.
Please be advised that there'll be a full committee meeting of the member building committee in person at 489 and Medford be healthier.
The meeting can be viewed live on Metro Public's YouTube channel, through Metro Community Media, on your local cable channel, which is Comcast 98 or 22, and Verizon channel 43.5 or 47.
The meeting will be recorded.
Participants can log or call in by using the following Zoom link.
Meeting ID is 946-5096.
I will call the roll.
Jenny Graham here.
Mayor Longo Carter present.
Dr. Galluzzi here.
Marta Cabral here.
Libby Brown here.
Marissa Desmond here.
Maria Dorsey here.
Brian Hillier here.
Tracy Keene here.
Emily Lozaro here.
Nicole Morrell here.
Yeah.
Uh, Lisa Miller here.
Hi, Lisa.
And Dr. Kim Talbot here.
So we have 13 present, 2 absent.
So we have a quorum and we're here.
Thank you all for being here tonight.
We have some.
Preliminary business to take care of and then the best majority of the discussion will be about the proposals that we received.
It will.
Before we do that, the next thing on the agenda is the approval of the August 11th committee meeting minutes.
Is there a motion to approve?
Motion to approve.
Motion to approve by Member Okade.
Second.
Second by Dr. Pelosi.
Okay, I will call the roll.
Jenny Graham, yes.
Mayor Longo Clark, yes.
Dr. DeLucia, yes.
Marta Cabral, yes.
Libby Brown, yes.
Marissa Desmond, yes.
Maria Dorsey is absent.
Brian Hilliard, yes.
Tracy Keene, abstain.
Emily Lazzaro, yes.
Nicole Morrell, absent.
12 the affirmative, 0 in the negative, 2 abstention, 2 absent.
Oh, no, 11, sorry.
Okay, item number three, we actually are welcoming two new members to the building committee.
So, as you all know, Dr. Cushing has taken a job in Beverly as the superintendent of schools there.
He was a voting member of the committee, and he has been replaced by Ken Lord, who has joined Bedford as the chief operating officer.
And Dr has also joined the team.
She is our.
yourselves at all, it can become like wheels of experience in this space.
So it might be nice for everyone to hear.
Sure.
So this is a little deja vu.
So it's been really interesting for me.
I'm excited to participate in this project.
I've been involved in technology for over 30 years.
So it's probably six years.
Welcome both of you.
If there's anything that happens along the way and you're like, what are you all talking about?
Please feel free to stop us and ask because we're happy to answer.
So welcome.
And if there's things you need, just let me know.
Tracy can you hear me okay?
I can hear Jenny okay but I could not hear Ken and Dr. Talbot at all.
So everyone just use your teacher voice and let's see how it goes.
Tracy just keep us
will do thank you um item number four is approval of the august 2025 opium invoice um so i'm going to turn that over to matt you would like to walk us through what's here uh yeah so this is just our our third invoice uh last meeting we were
So this is a continuation of our OPM services for the month of August.
It's our refund on sum of $25,000.
We don't have any additional sub-consultants or other reimbursement costs at this point.
It's very straightforward.
Any questions for Ken?
Is there a motion to approve the invoice?
Motion to approve by Ken, seconded by Luke.
I will call the roll.
Jenny Graham?
Yes.
Mayor Longo Kern?
Dr. Galussi?
Yes.
Marta Cabral?
We're absent for now.
Libby Brown?
Yes.
Marissa Desmond?
Maria Dorsey?
Yes.
Okay, welcome Maria.
Thank you.
Brian Hilliard.
Yes.
Tracy Keene.
Emily Lazaro.
Yes.
Nicole Morrell.
She's on her way.
Aaron Olopade.
Yes.
Luke Pricer.
Joan Bowen.
Yes.
Pam Lord.
So that is 13 in the affirmative, two absent, motion passed.
Okay, so we're going to move on to the meat of the meeting and hopefully it will be a meeting by the time we're done here.
As you all know, we got 4 proposals from designers and the goal for tonight is for myself for the mayor and for Dr Lucy to really
questions.
We are not ranking.
We cannot rank.
We cannot do that.
We should not do that.
All of these four folks are watching us either now or in the future.
And the MSBA is really explicit about not wanting us to be talking in terms of ranking favorites, et cetera.
So what we tried to do was
Give you all a set of questions to think about and they're up on the screen there.
So what I would like for us to just go.
1 proposal at a time and go through these questions.
I think we're really interested in hearing from all of you.
We're sensitive to the fact that we are 3 of 13 votes.
So we have our work cut out for us when we go to designer selection next week.
However.
You know, there's a lot of collective experience at this table and we want to hear from from all of you from from your lenses, from your impressions of the proposals that were shared and that will help us get ready for that for that meeting.
And there's 2 meetings.
1 is where we will talk about all of the proposals and then the 2nd meeting where there will be a short list of some kind.
interview to accept the DSP.
So the questions that we did want to talk about with all of you and I'm thinking we should just take them one at a time so that we give everybody equal shape.
What did you like about the proposal compared to others?
What stuck out as advantageous?
What did you dislike about a particular proposal as
advantageous?
And then what questions would you have for this applicant about their proposal?
So those are the three questions
Let's start with DLR.
I couldn't find any of it.
Okay, hold on.
We're going to do one question at a time so that everybody can stick with us.
Okay, so let's everyone has DLR's proposal.
Okay, so this proposal is from DLR in collaboration
And then, Will, can you keep track of who is raising their hand online?
It's a little hard for us to see.
What do we like about this proposal?
I like that they have experience working together.
I recently had a large project that took it, and I think that bloody shows really strong design skills.
So I think that's the example of the fact that they're a successful team.
Great.
Anyone else?
I like that they were pretty explicit in their stuff.
Everything can move on.
Let's do that, shall we?
Anybody else?
Thoughts, questions about what you liked?
Any questions online, Will?
I'm seeing.
OK.
What did you dislike about the DLR proposal as compared to others?
Or what did you view as being less advantageous, or less than advantageous?
Well, less advantageous, yeah.
I can find evidence that it's not sincere.
I can see that it's important.
Yeah.
It's certainly a consultant.
But the prime contractor team seems to have a bigger experience base spread across the country.
And also, even to the US territories.
I haven't dealt with as much of that case.
I also thought the relatively large full-time employee account, about 5.5, was less advantageous than a 10-year team.
So it's true that it's tough to get that full-time account for a 10-year team.
You also have a very high consultant fee.
I've seen that people are having a hard time hearing us.
So Emily, so far the comments in the less advantageous category are that this group is light on experience with MSBA, that they seem to have a relatively large headcount, and that there are two
That's what we've covered so far, just for those of you trying to listen here.
speak loudly for the crowd.
I meant to speak up earlier, but then I got distracted looking at the paper.
But I actually think the fact that it's two firms is actually something that could be seen as advantageous.
You have a lot of different voices, and you get to take the expertise of each of those firms and leave behind the things that the firms aren't as good at.
So I think looking at them as one entity, it's not on us to figure out how that firm
how they're going to, like, who's going to be in charge of this part of design, who's going to be in charge of that part of the design.
Having worked on both sides of projects where I've been either the architect of record or the design architect, all of this would be hammered out between two firms in advance.
Skipping ahead a little,
proposal, how are they going to handle these things?
They have extensive experience working together already, which leads me to believe that they already have this process in their minds of how they're going to handle it.
And so I think it is actually very advantageous to take a firm that's really rooted in the programming and analysis, and then a firm that's really rooted in
really good design and bringing them together to create one super team.
Thanks, Marissa.
Will, is there anybody online who's got their hand up?
All the members of the, oh, Marissa, Maria Dorsey.
Maria?
Hi, from an educational angle, I had the feeling that this group, their focus was more on
CTE than on the classrooms, as opposed to the other groups.
A lot of them, the others were either on equal footing or had a strong sense of what the needs of the classroom are with CTE combined.
This one, I felt that they were, they had a leaning, more leaning towards the shops.
So that was just my impression on what I read.
Thanks, Maria.
Is anybody else online?
Anybody else?
Ryan?
I think one of the things I feel is a little bit advantageous is that they're prime candidates, I think.
So a little bit of a problem there that we don't know how it turned out and how that can manifest itself.
So for those of you online, the comment was that they're like sort of
prime example for us is still a work in progress, and it's not yet complete.
So we don't know how it turned out.
Luke?
When I looked at all the consultants, I didn't find a library consultant.
I didn't find a lab consultant.
I didn't find a school consultant.
I didn't find a landscape consultant.
Is that typical?
Matt and Jen, can you talk a little bit about what is typical in terms of how teams get put together?
So they need to provide consultants.
One of the questions that we received after the walkthrough was whether or not a pool consultant is required or not.
It's not something that we asked that it was required.
They can certainly include one, so I think we need one for our Canada pool consultant and the resident pool consultant.
So that's typically, and I can pull up the sub-spreadsheet of where I found everybody, just to make sure that they didn't fall off.
I do think they did.
Some of them are maybe a little hard to find, next to some of these.
But I'll take a look and see what it is.
Sometimes they have in-house experience, so they look to themselves for those categories.
That makes it a little less clear.
Let me do that.
For the CTK experience, for example, they have somebody else that says they're a CTK.
So that answers every question, but for some.
So it sounds like the teams will not necessarily look at this because of how they come together.
Is that right?
Right.
OK.
Thanks.
Other not advantageous things?
Also, a lot of the projects that they're looking at, the student count is really low.
So just so you know, this is the spreadsheet that we're required to fill out for the MSBA.
This is all there.
You can see them here.
I did have a question.
Lucy and her team.
I feel like what I hear about vocational is that what we think of as vocational in Massachusetts is quite different than what vocational looks like in other places in the country.
Can you respond to that from a programming perspective?
Because a lot of their vocational experience seem to be
Yes, and I think that we're in a unique situation where we are a comprehensive high school, we're not a single vocational school, so all of our programs are Chapter 74, which means that there are requirements and regulations pertaining to
Content that we provide our students the number of hours that they have in shop as well as for their academics.
And then the number of hours that they are doing in the industry fields, whatever that may be to go to the shop.
And I know that we are to expand our programming and that some of the vocational programming standards have recently been increased.
A lot of what
I would just say that from the lens of me reviewing a lot of these proposals would be looking at that experience that the firm does have with the CTE programming that is aligned and parallel to Medford, not a standalone CTE school, but one that's comprehensive, that at this time has full Chapter 74 shops.
and wants a space that is unique and brings with it a lot of flexibility.
Do you need more detail?
No, I'm good, thank you.
I just wanted to, not being in that world, understand, is it the same everywhere or is it different?
So, thank you.
I also would say, maybe also for me, I do not have
a lot of MSBA experience coming into this project.
So I think for someone like me, reading these proposals, I found it very difficult to get a true understanding from the visuals of this based on the clarity of the image, the detail or lack
It was really hard for me to get a true understanding as to what the vision was for the proposals.
Third question, what question would you ask this applicant about their proposal?
Obviously that we haven't already talked about, but a question she would ask.
Okay.
Questions?
Libby?
I think I'd ask just how frequently do they expect to meet physically?
Because it's awesome for those who are not local.
So they might be flying in or doing remote meetings, just how often do they meet?
That's right, this was the team that was not terribly local, is that right?
Yeah, Libby's local.
Okay, some of them are local.
Awesome.
What other questions would we have for DLR?
For those of you at home wanting some more information on their cluster design concept.
Other questions for DLR?
What did we like about Perkinsville?
Luke?
I like the big wood.
I like that they included a
estimated timeline for the various modules, including this design, as well as the cost-incentive for house-wide construction.
Certainly more to it, but I'd like them to do the effort.
Things people liked about Irvingsville, Aaron?
I liked that they tried
had a kind of central space in between the additional renovating space today, the first kind of slideshow, trying to incorporate the idea that this is an opportunity for the community to be involved in that, as well as outdoor learning spaces.
We're learning a lot now that there's a huge benefit to having that available space for students and teachers to kind of get outside the classroom from time to time.
So to be able to incorporate that and have that be used as a shared space with the community
I like the way you put the geofederal right in the picture.
Overall, I think the students are very clear, the graphics are very clear.
This gives me hope for and faith for our team for how we can move forward as a student community.
And I just think that there's some great clarity
I also like the idea that we take into account interdisciplinary learning.
That's not just about CTE but about all partners.
So for those of you online so far we we've heard the likes include
Students experience working with left field, that Salem High School is ongoing and ahead of us, that they took a stab at a timeline, that they're prioritizing community space, outdoor learning, geothermal.
Their messaging was quite clear.
They are not splitting their team with other projects like Salem, and they are focused on interdisciplinary learning, just so that you, in case you all were having a hard time hearing.
When we were doing the tour, there were lots of questions about those kinds of things.
And we really tried to paint a picture for everybody who is here that there are some interesting spaces in this building that we should be looking at to say, is this worth preserving?
Or is it not for some reason, but that was one of the spaces we talked about wanting explicitly to be able to evaluate
Does it stay, does it goes what happens that also included the gym because it's quite big and it includes some of the CT spaces as well.
So that certainly seems reflected in their design as well in terms of how they were trying to serve.
I'm going to answer that question in a bit.
things that seem less advantageous.
So to the point of the importance of this area, there aren't a lot of CTEs.
And their team also,
didn't seem to have lots of vocational experience.
Am I remembering that correctly?
I'm sorry.
I'm so sorry.
I'll just make it a point that I saw two consultants sort of talking about that.
Marissa, I think kind of splitting this question into the next one.
For some of the firms that have less experience in CTE, a question for that would be how
that you think would be beneficial to help CTE.
Things like performing arts and just like fine art have a lot of details and explicit requirements similar to CTE.
I mean, not the same things, obviously, but like the same, just like nonsense stuff that you don't necessarily need in a regular classroom, like that type of experience.
I think this one, that their experiences span beyond public schools and beyond high schools.
And while it might answer the question to you, while that may not be a negative, there were other design teams where their experiences are strictly educational spaces.
Week 12.
in Medford with a very unique site and the possibilities of being able to do something maybe different in here.
Other things we thought were the last advantageous
Okay, what questions do you have for this firm?
Questions for all firms, especially this one is what experience they have in renovating jibs, or CTE, or anything else for that matter.
Do all firms have experience in some sort of solar
Other questions?
in the building, what their thinking is with that, so I can get some clarity on what their vision would be and how that kind of plays into the work we're doing, which is well, but that's perspective-appropriate, because they clarify everything else, so.
Thank you.
Other questions?
Two down, two to go.
I'm gonna do AI3 next.
Happens to be one right in front of me.
Okay, what did we find advantageous about AI3?
Great.
I did.
I like the innovative way they looked at underground parking, but also a separate club.
If that's something that we're going to continue to have, like have that separate for the community schools, you know?
do you have examples of bids on your budget?
That's your question.
You can dream, right?
I just am really in love with the use of wood inside the building.
So there's that.
knowledge that we're on a hill, so I think some of the designs were trying to kind of lay it all at the same level.
But I think this one, I think it gave the site the opportunity to use multi-level construction builds, either for the additional, like additional renovations or complete construction.
So I think it's an interesting way to kind of consider what the vision would look like and how it would be useful.
I wouldn't have to founder a firm, because I don't have 75% of this company.
I serve some of the charge.
A smaller project with a contractor team, a smaller consulting team.
the founder and partner of the integral project.
So I thought that was a good presentation.
They're a task force.
They have worked with and blessed with.
So they're just people involved in a larger scene, which I'm quite interested in.
This is a very large lot.
It's 40 acres by 60 acres.
And if you look at the pictures of these various high schools, you can see the aesthetics vary quite a lot.
So they're very capable of executing a stock.
Watertown is home to the City of Spring, their schools are at Tarim and Rosewood.
I would say what I think is very advantageous about AI3 is that, as you mentioned previously, during the tour, I felt like this proposal captured a lot of what we have said in our profile as well as what was mentioned on the tour.
So they were very specific to call out some details about how we want to make sure we have a collaborative space for teachers and staff.
how different options for how the learning environment can be stacked while maintaining some of the CTE spaces and how they can be creative, to Aaron's point about using the scope of our band, I just felt like they were listening and
For those of you online, I'm going to give you a quick rundown of what has been said, if you all can hear me okay.
Thumbs up?
Okay.
So here's the list that I've captured.
They've done six CTE projects.
They have an in-house CTE expert.
They had creative ideas around underground parking at a separate aquatic center.
They've identified bids that are under budget, which is exciting.
Their aesthetic design appeals to more than one person in the room.
They sort of
Worked with our on the Hill idea rather than trying to plan it as well as the founder being directly involved in the project and a tighter stack of consultants.
So, hopefully less tension and more cohesion on the team.
They have worked with left field before the watertown building that's set to open in the spring is a net 0 building.
And that they were very clearly listening to the tour and the kinds of things that we were talking about that were important.
Like an expedited time.
And overall, their clear commitment to
public input.
So that's what's been going on here in case you all have been having a hard time hearing us.
Are there any likes from the group on the phone that you wanted to share?
I see a comment from Maria.
They have a strong focus on integrating CTE in the classroom.
Thanks, Maria.
Jenny, this is Tracy.
I just listed because you may have already gone through this, but I've listed 4 questions that I think should be asked to each consultant and I just dropped them in the chat.
Okay, great.
I will grab those out at the end.
Were there things that we saw about this presentation that were not advantageous?
on the team, I didn't see very much diversity in the group, which is always a little concerning to me.
Obviously, they will talk about involving the community, but not having any diversity on your team is problematic, I think, sometimes.
Thank you.
It's kind of contagious to me.
consultant or an expert.
Other things that were not advantageous?
This is a little bit personal, but I think just compared to other firms, their designs just feel a little bit leaning towards an entry line and something that was over-elevated towards not higher education, but
So, go back.
Flush that out a little bit.
Colors, just materials, chaos, it's not a thing.
When you get to a high school level, things get a little more refined.
It's just a personal opinion, and sometimes things skew a little bit too far.
Fun and silly, that's better for kids.
You have narrow labels.
Narrow labels.
Other, not advantageous.
For those of you on the phone, the two that came up is that the team is not very diverse in its composition, and then that the design leans towards younger children rather than towards young adults and almost adults, nearly adults, which gives me a little bit of a heart attack, personally, with two kids in this building now.
OK, what questions would we have for AI equity
It may be the way they structure their team, but they're a person they call project manager.
So they have 25% of their time available for the project.
Now, they have other people that have more.
So it might just be that that person isn't doing the same manager job that someone else is.
But I always wanted to be very, very clear about who's doing what.
If someone's going to get 25%, that means that those tasks are being done by someone else.
OK.
Other questions?
So the only question I have as I'm looking at them, so the school that you'll design, compared to the other two, the amount of space in their brain for student learning in general, seems visually smaller than the other two suggested designs.
So we're trying to make them understand where the space is going a little bit.
Thank you, guys.
OK, cool.
Thank you.
I retract my question.
So the question I'm going to ask is whether it will
on top of the glass back in the city.
That makes pretty fun sense.
It will allow you to fabricate a new structure.
I'll say that pushing the money on, that's not a good thing.
I'm talking about, there's a lot of space on these streets that I guess are probably
Yeah, and I do think whoever works with us, I think the first thing we'll do is tell them everything we hate about what was in their proposal, so that when they start thinking about what else it is that they want to hear.
So just because something was not in a proposal that got selected doesn't mean we can't be like, we actually did really like this thing that this other editor did, and tell us about that.
So I think that's a good thing.
There's many reasons to rule things out on the site, like in terms of timing, and landscape, and ledge, and all the other things that could be going on, that they just may have some perspective on.
So we can put that on the same questions.
There are questions for, were we talking about AI3s?
I had a question about that.
Nobody in any of their thoughts thought about addressing the entry, the traffic entry.
Everybody just maintained one driveway.
And I know that that was like a big thing that we all talked about already.
So I think the question would be, why?
Why?
And if you have thought about something, what would it be?
That's actually a great question.
It was like a lot to take all of this in and be like,
Now, which one am I in?
Where is it?
All the pieces and parts were hard to keep track of.
So, an additional thing was that the driveway that is incredibly long to pass through the property, which I think has to be helpful for conveying the product.
Yeah, yeah, I mean, they all definitely addressed a lot of things on site and slow, so there wasn't just like one way in for everybody, one way out for everybody, once you get into almost the road, but I think the like, road coming in is what needs to also be addressed.
Right.
The other questions about AI, great.
What did we like?
Well, I really like that they had an all-on solar memory service.
Okay, what else, Ken?
It felt like a really cohesive proposal, like all of the parts
We're cohesive with the artworks.
It didn't feel like they just grabbed things from here and there and put them together.
It all was well thought out.
I thought the choice of agency as a landscape architect was smart, because that's what our comprehensive master plan would say.
It's not the same person that's a landscape architect, but the firm.
I don't want to jinx it.
I appreciate the fact that the concepts are still pretty open.
I carry a lot of weight with it.
So it's interesting as a conversation going.
I like that the concepts are pretty open.
It's getting things going.
It's a lot to work through.
I appreciate that they're specific and generic at the same time.
information doesn't have a
just an engineering design background, I was wanting just a little bit more detail as to where this is headed.
So I guess that's a double-edged sword.
I honestly think some of these are better than some of the past experience.
Yes.
It's a long process, so this is... I like that they have a lot of disabled projects at a wide range of price points.
I like that for their one of their design plans, their site's actually a continuum of discovery.
It's like this growing experiential learning opportunity.
So the whole, again, they kind of try to
what we want to accomplish in the next few years.
I really like the side cut view on the bottom.
Because I also really like it.
It just gave me so much information.
Any more likes?
I know it's hard to separate them.
Okay on to things that are less advantageous.
This is all pretty flat, like the top floor at the very beginning is really just, it's only like one or two floors up across the very steep grade, and so that makes it wonderful.
So, what's the plan there?
Is it just not going to budge down?
So, I'm a little confused by how flat things actually are.
But I'm just counting the stories.
Or it's probably something like 25, or whatever.
Something like that.
When I look at them like this, they just look like pancakes.
Other dislikes?
Luke?
Certainly, I don't feel like we've let them from talking to us, but certainly
And I saw some evidence of that actually materializing in their estimated schedule.
Certainly, I compare it to Perkins-Wilson.
They're not exactly honest about this, but you can tell where the science-based tests result.
So I was just looking at that.
and it seems to be maybe six to eight months after inducting.
So that's been treated as such, but I only bring it up because it sort of reinforces the concern that I have.
They have these ongoing, large documents that may take away from
For the folks on the phone, I'll just do a quick recap so that we can make sure you're still with us.
For advantages, they have done three CTE programs very recently.
They've got Whole Hog on solar.
They have the largest in-house team.
They, their proposal was cohesive from beginning to end.
They do have some sub consultants who were involved in conference plans.
So they would have a connection to that.
Their concepts seem very open ended.
They had a wide range of projects in terms of price points.
So that felt.
And then on the dislike side, so far, we have some questions about, like,
clarification about that, and then that they are simultaneously doing Wakefield and Lexington at different phases, but there are shared resources in this proposed team that also are working on Lexington, and Lexington is going to be a monster of a project based on what it's a very, very large high school.
Lexington yes, they do.
They did.
They did put a visual in their proposal about.
I think, trying to tell us that the timing, the phasing of our project versus Lexington was different.
I think that's what this visual was trying to tell us.
I actually had some questions much like Luke about doesn't this sound like it's longer.
So I think that visual just probably needs some clarification questions list.
Anything from the folks online?
between those big old moves, but sometimes it's harder to get all the program programming into those spaces, and it gets too much into constraints.
And some of the other projects, some of the other proposals, aren't getting in their space, they just chip each other.
Other dislikes?
To me, one of their designs seems like a lot of walking for a student to come upstairs.
Respectfully.
I don't want us to do this at the beginning of the afternoon.
I don't want that five more minutes in class.
Nobody wants the five minutes?
So that is a concern.
And then my question was going to be, it'll come back.
So I'm just wondering, is Leftfield allowed to suggest questions for us, having worked with some of them or not worked with Leftfield?
Are there questions you think we should be asking, or are you allowed to say that?
I think a lot of the questions that are coming up are along the lines of what we typically ask, and who we think does various project to project, designer to designer, projects on the stage.
So the questions seem to vary from what I've heard here, I think.
The questions that are being asked are very good.
with these design and collection panels.
And the questions are going to be asked across the board of all firms.
So it won't be specific to one proposal or one architect.
It will be questions in relation to the project.
Let me follow up to that.
You said, so I know originally, if I believe, please correct me, the thought was to get
Do you think the idea is too narrow for you to interview?
It'll be those three voices on the panel.
So they will decide if they want to be in it.
It might be all four.
If they want to see it all.
You have this kind of discussion.
Relatively close to today, but more to a few days ago.
But that would be that.
At the end of that meeting.
but there will be a ranking with all of the DSP members.
And at that point, if they see there's two better squad runners, and the other one starts ranking so far below, they might just pick two, where everybody has the same field ranking.
I have a question.
This question asks me, what's a two-body carbon reduction for post-design and body?
It's on page 71.
It's on page 71 and on page 72.
Along with the pictures.
It's on the top right corner.
Oh, it's like a little pie chart.
the energy that it takes to put into the materials.
But I think what this is saying, my chart is the proposed design, body carbon is 20% less than my typical project.
So say that the body carbon reduction is green, 20%.
So bigger green is good.
Bigger green is better, yeah.
But that's not, that's good.
I went through use of sustainable materials, like certified wood.
I guess I was confused by the carbon design.
Other questions that we would want to be asking?
And then I think, are there other questions that we feel like, that you're feeling like you would want to ask of all of the potential proposals?
spend a lot of schedule on home training and self-education.
questions on behalf of your experience, because I know some call that out that they don't have experience doing that in their previous projects.
John?
My biggest thing that I do is about storage and places to put supplies and things of that nature.
Are there any questions online about either SMMA or maybe the field overall?
Questions you'd want to be asking everybody?
Yes.
Oh, I'm capturing them right now.
I do have a question.
Yeah, so.
Oh, sorry, sorry about this, but how is parking need forecasted?
Is there anything in your design that would change the parking need, or is that like a... The question was from a parking need perspective, is that a formula, or how is that determined, and how does that integrate into their design?
How does that get determined on these projects?
A lot of it will just be through discussions.
They can go, we currently have what's desired.
And it's not working.
That way, they will have a specific number of ED spots that they have.
And it's just a discussion.
So yeah, there's no real MSBA won't say, like, no, you don't need that kind of money.
Okay.
Got it.
Other questions for vendors?
Hello?
If you can identify the concepts, which
which concepts would absolutely require blasting, and which would absolutely- Blasting?
Blasting.
I said blasting.
I'm like, that's not a word I know.
I just remember there being some issues with- Oh yeah, there is.
My bones rattle twice a day.
So there are concepts that absolutely require blasting.
Other questions?
One thing that's come up with this kind of difficulty in my office is that for towns that have adopted the stretch code, the MAP stretch code, sorry, energy code, it's been something I'll make sure they're engineering or ready for.
So, or they maybe need an extra consultant to help them navigate that.
But it's pretty ambitious.
I think we're going to stop at this.
Anything else?
All right, well, I think we have our work cut out for us.
So the first designer selection panel meeting is next week, this Thursday.
And we will know once the meeting is over what our finalists are.
Is that correct?
And so we will let you all know what the outcome of that meeting is so that you're aware of what's coming next.
And then on October 6, we will
we'll interview and then we will know during that meeting who the selection is.
Okay, we'll let you go to the top right corner.
Okay.
So, are the interviews in person?
Oh, sorry.
Everything is virtual.
We can, as members of the public, we can join.
We can request a link ahead of time.
We do, probably.
We can collect a list if there's anybody who would like to participate.
they usually ask us in advance for that list.
So we'll send out an email if you want that information.
I did have one thing.
Sure.
Like you just said, the first DSV meeting on the 25th was on the 23rd originally.
The MSDA did from the 23rd to the 25th.
We had originally scheduled a committee meeting for the 23rd just to kind of sync up and talk
the first CSPA, but that happened now that it's on the 22nd, so I don't think we necessarily need to be on the 24th.
But I wanted to just let everybody know that there was a slight schedule change for the MSBA, so that meeting on the 24th will be on that same day.
want to schedule that or just wait until the October meeting, which I think is quite late in the month, so I can maybe get that on the move.
But I just wanted to kind of see what people saw.
Maybe we see if we can look that up.
send out an update.
Is there a motion to adjourn?
Second.
Okay.
I will call the roll.
Jenny Graham, yes.
Yes.
Joan Bowen.
Ken Moore.
Yes.
15 in the affirmative, zero in the negative.
The meeting is adjourned.
Thanks everyone.