Uh, let's start with a quick roll call to get started and then we should just go into probably some introductions.
Talk about what's going on.
Um, but it feels right to start with a roll call anyways.
I'll go right down the list here.
Uh, starting with Josh.
Present.
Hi folks.
Hello.
Uh, Lois here, Benji.
I'm here.
Barry here.
Loretta.
Here.
Kathleen.
Not yet.
Luke.
Present.
Hello.
Prabita.
Here.
Dan.
Bob.
Present.
Jessica.
Not yet.
Kathleen just jumped right in, so I'll add her to our list.
John, I'm not seeing John.
Will Sherwood is here.
And Paul.
Not seeing.
That's all right.
We still have plenty of folks here.
Everyone here was able to look over the minutes from last month.
Any addendums, any notes, comments, concerns, haikus?
I could offer a follow-up on something.
Please.
Remember I brought up the question of the stretch plastics down at Whole Foods?
So I went down to Whole Foods and talked to somebody there and there's an online website.
I talked to somebody on the phone or chatted on the computer and they sent me to a website.
That was not very helpful.
The man I spoke to at the store was not one that I usually see there.
He might've been a regional manager and for the day,
He said that the plastics are collected in-house by Amazon, well, by Whole Foods, which is Amazon.
And he doesn't know what they do, but whatever they do, they do in-house.
And that's as far as I've gotten.
He says they do recycle them, but he doesn't know how.
And I haven't been able to,
get high enough up the corporate ladder to get a person who does know.
But it's in-house is that much I learned.
That is a good addendum.
I'm glad you followed up.
We will maybe have time to discuss more of that soon.
Yeah, I do appreciate that, actually.
All right, I would entertain a motion to accept our minutes and move forward.
So moved.
Fantastic, we'll go down the line.
All in favor.
You need a second.
Oh, yep, thank you.
I second.
Thank you.
All in favor, let's go down the line.
Josh.
Abstain.
Thank you.
uh lois except benji except barry yes loretta abstain i didn't read them i didn't see them actually oh we'll make sure you're on the mec mec watch list um kathleen
Oh, Luke.
Accept.
Rebita.
Abstain.
Dan.
Accept.
Bob.
And I accept as well.
The yeas have it.
I'd love to begin the meeting formally.
I think something I'd like to start off with is just a brief introduction from our 2 newest members, and then we can maybe go around and just do a quick who's who in all these boxes here.
our name, what we're doing, maybe a focus we have.
Yeah, we'll start there.
So we'll start with name, maybe what you're doing for work, and how long you've been on this panel.
Seems fitting.
But I'd love to start with Josh.
Hi, folks.
Thanks, Will.
I'm Josh Eckert-Lee.
I use he, him pronouns.
I live over on Main Street between Bob's and Oasis in South Medford.
I'm really excited to be with you all tonight and hopefully for some amount of foreseeable future as I get involved here in Medford.
In my day job, I bike
10 minutes down the road and work for the city of Somerville as one of their sustainability planners, where I mostly work on sort of emissions reduction work, green building review, green zoning initiatives, and then electric mobility.
So as we do that kind of work here in Medford, I'd love to get stuck in with you on that.
I'm happy to be here.
I've been doing climate organizing with XR Boston and the Sunrise Movement for a number of years, so I'm glad to be
getting involved directly and civically with the city.
Thanks for having me.
Fantastic.
I'd also love to hear from Prabita.
That is correct.
I'm Prabita.
I'm very happy to be here.
Nice to meet you all.
I think I've met some of you, most of you, in a one-off meeting in November of last year, so very happy to be here.
part of this group.
And like Josh said, hopefully I can be a part of this team for some time in the future as well.
In terms of day job, I am a clinical scientist working in clinical trials and drug development.
Currently in between jobs, but I'm doing some consulting for small startups as well.
my main focus, passion or something that's been consuming me since the pandemic has been sustainability as well but in terms of waste reduction, zero waste, low waste initiatives and quite passionate about that and I know you guys all are as well so I'm very excited to work with you all.
Fantastic.
Now I'm just going to run right down across my screen.
We can just do a quick name, pronoun, and just a quick 30 seconds about yourself.
I missed the pronoun, sorry.
She, her.
Thank you so much.
And we should start in my top left with Brenda.
I hope everybody knows me by now, but Brenda Pike, she, her, I'm the climate planner for the city of Medford.
A lot of what I do is working on building improvements for the city and also in the
Other on the flip side of that, um, outreach to residents about things that they can do themselves to their own homes.
Um, and I, I, I work with this, uh, committee and also with the climate equity councils, and there's a lot of overlap in the, in the things that we talk about with both groups.
Going right along, uh, Lois.
My professional work is Spanish language, formerly teaching, currently editing.
I was on the first environmental committee that the city put together back in the last century, I think.
And I,
Now I'm serving on this new version and enjoying it very much.
And I'm passionate about recycling above all.
And I'm really interested in getting better recycling out of restaurant takeout containers.
Fantastic.
I'm going to throw it right to Bob.
I've been on this committee and the predecessor that Lois was on, the wind turbine committee.
We started in 2004, so it was still this century.
So I am a consultant with AECOM as a air quality consultant.
So I deal with air pollution issues and advise the committee, advise the wind committee on meteorology and this committee on air pollution issues.
and is one of our Electrify Medford coaches.
Right.
I may have to call you up on some of those.
I will need a consultation at some point.
I'm gonna throw it to Benji next.
I'm a retired lawyer.
I did toxic torts and other plaintiff's personal injury cases.
I've been on the committee for, I think it's almost three years now.
My energy environment interest comes from having worked with the Clamshell Alliance back in the 70s and 80s.
And actually there's a sort of rebirth of some folks who are still involved in fighting a rear guard action against the attempts to revive the industry.
Up next, Luke.
Hi, Luke McNeely.
I am an architect and energy and efficiency guy, formerly a renewable energy guy for eight years.
I'm amazed to find, and he, him pronouns, I'm amazed to find that I have been on this committee for more than 10 years now, which is fun to think about.
And I currently work for ICF.
We are an energy and environment consulting group that in Massachusetts runs the Mass Save residential new construction incentives.
And my focus in that program is on the passive house multifamily, so big multifamily buildings.
uh, energy efficiency.
And, uh, on this committee, I've been, uh, part of the TREES, uh, effort with Loretta and, uh, General Beck since we did Solarize Medford a while back, uh, just generally supporting many initiatives.
Fantastic.
Uh, Barry, you're up next.
I'm Barry He.
I've been on the committee for 10 years.
I'm retired.
I spent I'm a lifelong advocate for social justice and environmental justice.
And I spent my career working in the nonprofit sector, primarily on, but not exclusively on energy issues and low income issues.
And
One of my accomplishments was I founded the Green Energy Purchasing Program that is now the major state
program that you buy your green energy from through our Medford aggregation or elsewhere.
So I was the executive director of what was then called the Boston Oil Consumers Alliance and after several name changes is now called the Green Energy Consumers Alliance.
Welcome name change.
Loretta,
Hi, Loretta James.
I've been on the committee over 10 years also.
I was involved with the committee on the tree report that we did.
It was a research project that's online on Go Green Medford.
I worked with Luke and a few other people, members that have left.
I'm also
One of the lead people for the annual Harvester Energy Festival that we have, and I help coordinate that.
And I'm also interested in the past few years, besides tree preservation of our tree canopy and education about the issues with using rodenticides.
that are killing the natural predators.
So that's something that I've been thinking about the past few years.
I've also worked with the health department in educating people on using rat poison and other measures to control, help control the rat population.
And there's a video about that on the city website under the health department, which is excellent.
It was a public education meeting.
I have a background in art and design, but also in elevators, and I'm a real estate agent.
I've been on somewhat of a leave recently, but I think I covered everything.
Oh, she, her, and I think that's it.
That's great.
Kathleen.
I see her my background in mechanical engineering degree, and I've worked as an energy engineer consulting with see power right now and demand response.
done energy audits.
Let's see, what else?
I've been on the, with the group for 10 plus years.
I was a co-solar coach in 2013 for the Solarize program.
That was very exciting.
And what else?
I'm interested in recycling and reusing.
And I've noticed at home, my garbage is always smaller than my recycling.
But where it goes, who knows?
Thank you.
All righty.
Dan, you're up next.
Hey, I'm Dan Papo.
uh, he, him, uh, so for my day job, I work in the energy industry.
Uh, currently focused on optimizing grid scale storage batteries in Texas, California.
Uh, but it's been most of my career in renewable energy, uh, developing wind and solar plants and trading around them.
Uh, so something I'm very passionate about, and I think I've been on this committee for probably a little bit over a year.
Uh, I see Jessica's up next.
Jessica, she, her.
Currently, I'm a project manager for pretty much any energy project on a university campus, but my background is in urban planning and sustainable design and
My main kind of passion or focus is allowing kind of more, I don't know, complex concepts become more easily understandable for anybody, residents, kids, you name it.
I really want people to be able to understand all sorts of different concepts that we talk about.
And I've been on the committee for almost four years, I think.
And last up is Paul.
Can you hear me?
Loud and clear.
Yeah.
I'm a biochemist by training.
I've been at it for 40 years.
I'm interested in
educating people on how chemicals affect our lives and how they affect the environment.
So science education is a big passion of mine.
Educating people is a priority for me.
And I think that just leaves me.
My name is Will, he him pronouns.
I've been on this committee for, I think it's about a year.
I stopped keeping track.
Recent chair, but before that, um, I was a outdoor educator, uh, teaching environmental science for, for kids, uh, both here in Boston and out in Alaska.
Uh, and now I am a policy advocate, uh, particular around right to repair, uh, making sure you're allowed to fix your stuff.
Uh, cause that's better for the planet, better for your pocket, the whole bit.
But I think that's it for introductions.
I'm still new enough that that was actually really helpful for me.
So I appreciate you all taking the time to do that with me.
Let's see.
I want to be mindful of time because I'm not trying to rush, but I am going to make sure that we're cooking right along.
I see an opportunity for some administrative updates from Brenda.
Anything you'd like to throw in now that we all kind of know each other a little better?
Sure.
I just want to let people know that we have an opening for an economic development planner in the planning department.
We did have someone in that place and she's recently moved back to California.
So we're looking to find someone to do what she's been doing.
So in addition to the regular economic development work
that this person would be doing.
They'll also be working with me on a small business outreach for Electrify Medford through the Community First partnership that we're going to be doing with Mass Save.
So I have a definite interest in making sure that we get somebody good for this.
So definitely pass along anyone that you know who might be a good fit.
Fantastic.
And the final piece, I see we have 15 minutes allotted for this, but I think we can do it in five if we're feeling brave.
We discussed how difficult it can be to be a chair all by yourself.
And some people had thrown in their hats for potential co-chairs, but under duress.
Wasn't sure if anyone had, over the course of the last month, thought it over and decided that this would be a good fit for them.
If so, I'd love to open the floor to that conversation, if anyone's feeling brave and would like to help me out.
You're doing too good a job, Will.
It's exhausting.
It's hard work.
But with that, I'd rather give the extra four minutes to Bob, who's been waiting oh so patiently to give his presentation.
And I've been dying to hear it.
Let me see if I can share my screen here.
I can't do it because I'm not
I'm disabled and screen sharing.
Yes.
Oh, yeah.
Let me.
Okay.
I've made you a co-host, so you should be able to do it now.
Let's try.
Okay.
Here we go.
Actually, before we jump into that, I think we skipped over.
The next meeting is February 3rd.
And I think we had said that Matt Barlow will be presenting to us.
Were you arranging that, and is that all set?
Yep.
Perfect.
Oh, fantastic.
If anybody has any particular requests of what they would like Matt to cover,
let me know, either now or shoot me an email, but.
Mary, could you remind us and the new members what is he speaking on?
Okay, so Matt is a climate scientist who lives in North Medford.
He was one of the, he was a lead author on, was it the,
The COPS public, it was on one of the international reports.
So he knows his, he knows his climate science.
And I figured that people here would, I mean, if
We know what we want him to cover.
He will cover that.
Otherwise, he'll probably just cover what we can expect here in Medford and whatever he feels like talking about.
I think it's a nice idea to let him have the floor to speak about what his interests and current research might be, or whatever he thinks is important for Medford.
But yeah, it was the IPCC sixth assessment report.
That's a five-year thing, right?
Yeah, and that's kind of what
Yeah, that it is, it is like the major report on the environment.
Right.
And if I remember correctly, he was the lead author on rainfall precipitation issues.
Oh, great.
I put his UMass Lowell profile into the chat there so that we can look at what publications he's worked on and things like that as well, in case anyone wants some light reading.
He actually has publications that are light reading.
He is interested in public education.
So kind of like Paul on chemicals, he wants stuff to be understandable too.
people and like Jessica.
Yeah.
Fantastic.
So we should all, I think it's worth preparing some questions, making sure we're in the right space for it.
I think it'd be very insightful.
All right, I don't think there's any other notes for February 3rd.
I think we're looking good.
Bob, it's all yours, please.
Okay, can you see the presentation on your screen?
Yep, looks great.
This was this was law was signed.
It was after the actual session on the legislature, which, which was ended in July, but they actually came back and finish the job, if you will, although there were some elements that weren't included, like this third party.
electric provider issue, which I sent a note about a few days ago.
But let's go through it.
The key source is a WBUR summary.
So I'm not going to say I did all this research myself.
I just plagiarized what they provided.
So I'll plead guilty right now.
The overview is it builds on previous climate laws.
and provides basically what I would call a mid-course correction for issues that have emerged in the implementation of these earlier laws.
And supposedly it should be now easier and faster to build out some of this infrastructure that is required to meet these goals, which is, I think it's 50% reduction in greenhouse gas emissions from like a 1990 baseline by,
2030 and then 75% by 2040 and 100% by 2050, which is pretty aggressive.
The current permitting process has been determined to be complicated and tedious, so the new law is trying to make this easier to do, to actually build out what we need to do to stay on track with the climate plans.
I think you all got a list, maybe except the new members got an email with this.
This file, but it can be, we can also provide it again.
This this PowerPoint file anyway.
The the state energy officials are now getting organized to rank siting preferences for some of these renewable energy projects and to develop a help municipalities to evaluate setting proposals in their towns.
And
Developers are now required to do community outreach and hold public meetings before they obtain permits.
And there's a new state agency, the Office of Environmental Justice and Equity, which Barry will be happy to see, to help individuals, community groups, and municipalities participate in this process and affect
The law creates a fund to help stakeholders pay for any intervention in some of these permitting processes.
So if you oppose something, you're supposed to get a fund to help you participate in that.
We'll see how that works out.
The cumulative impact analysis is required, CIA, for large renewable and clean energy projects.
And the typical thing is how a project might impact local air quality and water quality issues.
But also whether there's a community has been experiencing a lot of industrial development, and this project might add to this burden, sort of like an environmental justice issue.
In some cases, developers may have to compensate communities with such a program, like a community benefit agreement.
But the law is trying to go for simpler, faster permits, sort of like, on the one hand, you get a fund to oppose these permits, but they want it to be simpler and faster, maybe to consolidate the reviews into one.
First of all, the permits into one master permit set the deadlines for how long the review process can take and put limits on the appeals process.
So it's sort of like,
opposing things here.
You get money for appealing and opposing a project, but there's limits on the appeals process.
And there's time limits.
They have a definition of what a large clean energy project is, is more than 25 megawatts of power generation or 100 megawatts of battery storage.
In which case, the state board will be in charge of the review and has to issue or reject the permit within 15 months.
But for small projects, municipalities will retain control.
And I don't know whether Medford is even has experience in this, but I don't know if there's any Medford projects anyway.
The master permit for such projects must be issued or rejected within 12 months.
If a town doesn't have the resources to conduct the review, the state board can handle this anyway.
If the deadline for the permit issuance or rejection is not met within the deadline, it's automatically approved.
except that if too many projects get this automatic approval, the legislation might have to revisit the process anyway.
All right.
Benji, you're not going to like this, but now clean energy includes nuclear fission.
And Governor Healey is in talks with Connecticut to see if they might get power from Millstone nuclear power plant.
So nuclear is back for clean energy.
It's going to be crucial to find ways to store the energy.
Obviously, that's always been the problem.
Renewable energy, you cannot dispatch it.
You cannot say, I want 100 megawatts in the next hour, because the solar energy obviously is diurnal.
Depends on if there's clouds.
Wind, of course, depends on the winds blowing.
But if you can store it, you resolve such intermittencies in the availability of renewable energy.
That's the big challenge.
You could do various ways to do this, not just batteries, but pumping and such.
The state has to ramp up a lot in
adding the storage.
I can't – I don't know if they're going to be possible to do this by a factor of 10 by 2030.
It's only five years away from roughly 500 megawatt hours to 5,000.
So, there's going to be projects on this.
They have to study the question of how to bring
important resources like offshore wind projects and batteries online by July 1.
Now, under the new law, it should be easier to get permission to go solar in historical districts, because now historical commissions have to give substantial weight to the threat posed by climate change.
They just can't say, I don't want to see these solar panels.
There's going to be more solar canopies, maybe.
And there's going to be studies on how to do that.
The Office of Energy and Environmental Affairs has to monitor EV chargers and make sure they're reliable, widely available, and distributed equitably, and track the prices and frequency of use, et cetera.
And they want to be able to forecast the charging demand.
maybe make electric utilities, make infrastructure investment plans to meet the anticipated demand.
Also, the law wants to have the state allow more pole-mounted and right-of-way chargers so people who park on the street have a way to charge their vehicles, and restricts the ability of homeowners associations to block installations in places like condominiums.
So there's efforts to make charging more widespread basically and overcome what has been basically resistance to that.
Also, the issue is, are we gonna be able to ban car dealerships from selling gasoline or diesel powered vehicles after 2035?
They're gonna review the feasibility of that.
Of course, I know the Trump administration is not going to like that either.
So, it should be interesting to see how the state and the federal government work on all this or clash on all of this.
Transitioning from natural gas.
We don't have a ban on gas companies from building more pipelines and etc.
in their service areas, but there's some new restrictions
Utilities could build more network geothermal projects.
And there's also, it's more difficult for loan owners to petition the Department of Public Utilities for a natural gas hookup under the state's right to service laws.
There's the issue now of does the request comply with the goals for reducing greenhouse gas emissions and whether there's feasible alternatives.
There's incentive to gas utilities to replace leaky underground pipes.
That'll be good.
Then the priorities are instead of encouraging costly pipe replacements, Massachusetts will help prioritize short-term repairs or retiring.
Totally retiring stretches the pipeline.
Other notable changes, the Department of Public Utilities
will establish a cheaper electric rate for moderate income residents, like it does for low income residents.
So that'll be good.
Massport has to prioritize greenhouse gas reductions and environmental justice when making decisions about transportation infrastructure.
Companies building new electric transmission or distribution lines have to consider hardware and software updates that can make existing power lines more efficient.
And every five years, electric utilities have to file a report about their vulnerability to climate change and plans to increase resiliency.
There's going to be a commission to study how the clean air energy transmission is affecting fossil fuel workers, because there could be less demand for such workers.
And it mandates the state to develop new flood risk maps that more accurately depict the risk of inland flooding.
And that's my quick summary.
Could I add a couple of things to that?
You may.
There are a few things that affect us or could affect us more directly, which I was excited to see and hear.
One of them is allowing procurement of electric school buses and charging infrastructure together, which is a bizarre,
thing problem that that has crept up where where some municipalities have been waiting a long time after purchasing their buses to actually get the charging infrastructure installed for them, because they weren't allowed to procure them together in the past.
The pole-mounted chargers that you mentioned, Bob, I think that's gonna be a great thing moving forward.
Up until this point, I think there's been a limitation on the ability for incentives to cover pole-mounted chargers.
Josh, you might actually know more about this than I do.
I think it's because of the efficiency of them or something, right?
Yeah, you're right on the money, Brenda.
So this should make it easier for us as municipalities to roll them out on our sidewalks where the curb's already kind of busy.
That's great.
It directs the Department of Public Utilities to approve smart meters, which enables two-way communication and it helps to modernize the grid.
to better manage demand, which way back when I was at National Grid, we were trying to get smart meters included and the DPU shot us down.
So I find that pretty exciting.
And it's allowing net metering across service territories between different utilities, which is a game changer, I think.
Is there any effort to have meters monitored by people?
Like, you know, have an app that says this is how much energy you're using.
Because I think that'll be just a tremendous help to people in saving energy.
I have your meters report to you how much energy you're using.
I know you can buy equipment to do that.
You can actually rig up your electrics panel
to give this information to you, but that's an expenditure.
I don't know.
I think I think these step these smart meters could be a step in that direction.
OK, I know when national and national grid installed some in the Worcester area some years ago, they were able to use them for demand response and they could do some real time communication with residents to encourage them to reduce their usage in times of peak demand.
And on another point, Bob mentioned nuclear energy being back.
Was there any discussion about where to stick the waste?
Because I know we dug up several kilometers down into the desert.
set up some storage facility in a salt mine.
I think it was Utah that said, not in our backyard.
Is there some initiative to, if this is back, then do we have some means of dealing with the waste or did you hear any talk about that?
This is Bob.
I think some of the newer
modules that are being contemplated may have the ability to take the waste and actually consume it.
I'm hopeful that that is the case.
So some of these new nuclear modules that are being considered
This is this a new technology may have the capability and I'll have to look into this more that you've triggered my question now that I'll have to look up whether they can actually take the waste and actually somehow consume it as part of their energy input.
So I'll look that up.
That would be a good thing.
And if I may add to that, I did just put a link to a webinar that I saw of women in energy.
It was really quite an interesting kind of overview of advanced nuclear energy that the National Renewable Labs have been supporting for quite some time.
And they are looking at safer system types.
And yes, indeed, they do talk a little bit, although not enough.
And I asked a bunch of questions about waste on that.
But yes, with that idea that the waste
would be a part of a process in which the most valuable fuel gets used first and then it kind of downgrades in different systems of varying importance, but always being used until it becomes basically a
minor issue, I guess.
So anyway, I don't know the answer fully, but it seems like that is a key concern.
And they recognize, of course, that nuclear energy comes with this major challenge.
And so it does need to be part of any opposed nuclear systems.
Waste management, that is.
Interestingly, it also mentions incentives for nuclear fusion, which made me wonder if we're closer than I thought we were to that, or if that was just wishful thinking.
I think it's the perpetual 20 years.
It'll be here in 20 years, I think, as they've been saying for the past 50.
I think now it's just 18 years.
just around the corner.
And Luke, I'd love it if you could expand a little bit on your comment on the network's geothermal, just so I can get a better grasp of it.
I actually went to a commercial utilities in-person
discussion on network geothermal.
The utilities are very keen on seeing it work because the pressure to reduce gas is very strong, but the need for some gas
capability will remain and the idea that they could retool large percentages of their gas workforce to water workforce is very appealing to them.
And so the idea that a neighborhood, just pick a few blocks in your area of Medford, might have a central plant for producing hot water that then is basically run through the streets and instead of a gas line off of the street to run a boiler and
domestic hot water system, you might just have a line of hot water that comes in.
And so that would basically tie to a heat pump that is just like a geothermal heat pump that currently goes into wells underneath a facility.
It would simply be tapping into this network of water.
And so it would give the potential that you're drilling wells in the streets, you're drilling wells in areas where there is kind of space for that, that is otherwise unused.
You're maintaining the utility kind of rates of way.
And the utility then has this, it gets to keep itself alive as well.
Certainly that is a part of it.
They are keen on being able to continue to be a utility.
But it is a very appealing concept that instead of a fuel, you're literally just tapping into heat that is available to you in the street.
And as Josh pointed out, yes, there's another one also in Framingham.
The National Grid's definitely big on it and Eversource is very big on it.
And there are a number of projects that I see come through Mass Save, the large multifamily projects, where they have multiple buildings on, you know, what was formerly a campus of some sort.
And they're very seriously considering how do we network this all together with a big geothermal
system, so.
Luke had a quick question, maybe in the weeds for some, but how do they bill each individual customer?
Do they have BT meters with flow and temperature?
I don't know that.
I think it's not fully developed to that level, although I wouldn't be surprised if these pilot projects, that is a key part of what they're trying to confirm in the implementation of these projects is that they can reliably bill for this.
Right, right.
Actually, a friend from INGRID who's working somehow on some aspect of the Lowell project was asking me that question.
I'm sure they'll figure something out.
Right.
I am confident that they will.
And Barry?
Yeah, I guess I'm not really grasping this really well.
My question is, is there really a need for a utility in order to employ this technology, or is this a bailout program for the gas utilities?
I think it certainly could be a bailout program.
Well, I mean, could it be done more economically efficiently without them is kind of the question.
Or would they simply be replaced with a different utility, in which case, yeah.
And that's what I'm not understanding.
Yeah, and that's been my understanding of it is the utilities under law have rights of way.
They have control of certain areas and distribution
Uh, you know, running lines in the streets, et cetera.
Um.
And so for a private company, for instance, to attempt to do that.
I would get quite complicated and would basically be.
Would need utility permissions, uh, would need to basically.
Displace or replace a lot of that.
So, unless we were to set up a geothermal utility program totally separate from, this seems to be a way to just retool the gas companies towards that.
I don't know.
I think it's still really early days.
So, if I'm understanding
you, it sounds like most likely, we aren't sure, but most likely we would need either a geothermal utility or we would need a gazillion private little companies that were competing for our street in our neighborhood.
or we could use the existing utilities, in which case it doesn't trouble me to bail them out.
It sounds like that might be the most efficient way to do it.
My question is more if we're adding an extra layer of capitalism to something that doesn't need to be.
Well, I think there would be economies of scale, too, of doing it at that larger size, rather than each individual residential person, household doing their own.
Well, maybe, except if each residential household has it just as part of their, it's part of the building, then you're not having to have pipes going up and down the street at all.
I mean, you're just doing it locally.
These are engineering issues that I don't know.
Geothermal on a residential scale is quite costly.
And I mean, there are huge incentives for it at the moment, but it's still, as an owner, you would have to fork out many tens of thousands of dollars to drill a few wells.
And then you might find out that it's not a great site for you, unfortunately.
So there's risk and significant investment on an individual scale.
Barry, to your question too, it sounds like an interesting idea for something like a public utility district or like a municipal co-op kind of structure that could still operate on that scale, but would be, you know, more beholden to, you know, having an elected board or something from the community it operates in.
It looks like Paul is speaking, but his sound is off.
Oh, I'm sorry.
How deep can a homeowner drill?
Can I drill a mile down?
On deep drilling, actually, that's a good question.
Cornell University and a couple of other universities have ultra deep wells to see if they can actually get to true geothermal.
So there's misnomer there, geothermal.
is what you get in Iceland, where there is actually like lava nearby.
But what we are currently doing here in Massachusetts is called ground source heat pumps, where basically we're just using this layer of earth to dump heat, like a radiator into that space, rather than into the air, which the air source heat pumps do.
And there's also water source heat pumps, you can do it into the ocean or into a lake or into a river.
But that's basically just running coils into a medium and dumping your heat there.
Whereas geothermal is like, yeah, you're taking heat from a heat source.
But Cornell does have like a super deep... That puts to sleep my plans for the well I had in the backyard they discovered.
I think it is challenging to get that deep.
Institutional scale.
Alrighty, I'm gonna grab the reins for a second.
I think we've gone a little over, but I think that was really interesting conversation.
I do appreciate you taking the time on that.
I wanna throw it to Brenda to talk about our monthly updates, what's going on in the world, going on in Medford.
Please tell us what's happening.
Sure, I'll try to run through this relatively quickly.
For Electrify Medford, so far we've had 95 signups.
We've coached 35 people.
We've had a couple drop off along the way as well.
I was speaking with someone from Heat Smart Alliance a couple of weeks ago, and they said that's not a bad ratio of signups to coaching session, but we're still hoping to do better.
So we'll see if some tweaks we're making can change that.
But we had a bunch of people trying to get coaching sessions in right before the holidays.
So in the last week before the holidays, I coached four people.
We were accepted into Mass Saves Community First Partnership Program for 2025 through 2027.
52 municipalities are going to be part of it.
We'll be signing an MOU and an NDA and other paperwork soon, and then we'll have an orientation on February 6th.
But from my perspective, I think the most useful part of this is just the connection with the Mass Save program, getting up-to-date information, getting data on installations in Medford, and doing outreach with them, including bill inserts and things like that.
So I'm really excited about that.
Um, we had a table at the winter extravaganza on December 4th.
Um, that was interesting because there were, there were a lot of people.
who were really in need.
There were a lot of people there to get winter coats and hats and things like that and get connected to services.
But they were less interested in Electrify Medford than in a lot of the other programs that were represented there.
So although it was maybe the audience that we were looking to reach, it wasn't necessarily the best place to reach them, I think.
We are going to have an event at the library on January 16th.
Steve Bright from the Heat Smart Alliance will be speaking about heat pumps.
And then we'll do an office hours type of setup with energy coaches sort of distributed in different areas so people can do sort of abbreviated coaching sessions with them instead of just doing a sign up and then us trying to reach them later.
And what time is that event?
Oh, it's 7 o'clock.
Thanks.
I think that's it for Electrify Medford.
For the Andrews and McGlynn HVAC upgrades project,
The $5 million bond for that passed the first reading in city council on December 17th.
Then we're going to be doing a committee of the whole meeting to discuss it in more detail with them, hopefully on January 14th, although that hasn't been scheduled quite yet.
And then they'll do a third reading soon after that.
And this is for the pre-construction services through April and pre-ordering some of the equipment with long lead times.
So we're hoping that if we are able to pre-order the equipment, then we'll be able to get the bulk of this disruptive work done during the summer and that we'll have cooling in the classrooms in time for the new school year to start.
We're anticipating a $25 million bond in April for the actual construction work, but we'll have a more precise number for that once we've onboarded the construction manager and had a guaranteed maximum price agreed on.
And we're putting out an RFP for that construction manager at risk tomorrow.
And we are expecting to onboard them by the middle of February once we have that bond approved.
And yeah, I think that's it for that project for now.
Um, Andrew's solar project, we finally signed the contract for that, um, which is good because it needed to be done by the end of 2024 in order for us to use the ARPA funding for it.
Um, and now for the ARPA funding, the project needs to be done by the end of 2025, but we expect it, it'll be finished before the summer.
Um, and it's 258 Watts.
And then also for Andrews.
Also for Andrews.
The electrical work was done there to put more circuits on the emergency generator so that the building can be used as an emergency shelter during a power outage.
So that's something that we've been talking about for a long time, too.
So I'm happy that that's done.
So right now, it's just a regular generator.
But we are hoping in the future to have that be
that backup be battery storage instead.
So this was a first step.
So it can be off grid if necessary right now, and then we can work towards making it more environmentally friendly as well.
I wanted to mention this isn't Medford specific but I did want to mention that there was a public meeting in December about recommendations for a statewide building decarbonization clearinghouse.
that would be operational in 2028.
So VEIC created this report for the state, and so they had a couple of different options that they were discussing.
One being just using the current Mass Save electric PAs as the
as the administrators of this program.
So this would take the place of Mass Save, essentially.
So one thing would be just using the electric PAs, cutting the gas PAs out of it completely.
And municipal light plants would be served as part of this.
either by an existing program administrator or they could select one.
If they didn't already have one, they could select one together.
And they would still be accountable to the Department of Public Utilities.
Another option that was discussed was creating a new statewide entity that was quasi-governmental that would be accountable not to the
Department of Public Utilities, but to a board of directors and the executive and legislative branches here in the state.
Sort of like a Efficiency Maine or Efficiency Vermont, something like that.
So they were getting feedback about what preferences people had in terms of those options.
This would be focused more on greenhouse gas emissions targets rather than energy reduction.
It would be not just looking at three-year plans, but also creating 10-year plans as well.
So looking farther out.
possibly removing the cost effectiveness requirement, which really limits a lot of what the Mass Save can do right now, and pulling in additional non-rate payer funding.
So I think, yeah, I think that's part of the thought of it not being utilities sort of broadens what people are thinking about in terms of funding for these programs.
So I think this is really interesting.
I'm really intrigued by the idea of a new statewide entity that's not run by the utilities.
And then, so MassSave back in October filed their three-year plan.
We don't have any updates on that right now because the DPU hasn't decided what they're approving and they won't be doing that until the end of January.
But part of what the program administrators filed was no fossil fuel incentives.
And that was required in the last climate bill that by this point, we're not gonna be supporting fossil fuels through the program.
Heat pump incentives would drop for some people instead of there being like a flat $10,000 incentive for whole home heat pump.
Um, it would be $3,000 per ton up to $10,000.
So for a lot of people, especially ones with smaller homes, they would, they would have less incentives.
And the heat loan, the 0% interest heat loan, would still be 0% interest, but the term of it would change based on your income level.
So if you are, you know, more moderate income, then you would still have the full seven year term.
But if you have higher income, then it could be as low as three years.
All of which I thought was pretty reasonable, actually.
They also designated 21 equity communities.
Medford isn't one of them, unfortunately.
These communities would have more incentives, especially for low and moderate income residents.
which people are very excited about.
It's also the most expensive plan ever for over the three years.
It's $5 billion, which makes me wonder if the DPU is going to approve all of it.
So we're just waiting and seeing until the end of January to see what happens there.
But we'll get training directly from MassSave on the programs at our February orientation for the Community First Partnership.
And that's it for me.
Any questions, comments on any of those updates?
Cool.
Oh, Josh.
Sorry, they hid the hands up in the React tab, and I haven't yet gotten used to it.
Brenda, I just want to ask, is there a best way for this community and this committee to engage with the Mass Save Community First partnership?
How do you expect us to relate to, or is it just information sharing?
And you're muted, I'm sorry.
There we go.
Yeah, so I mean, a lot of it is information sharing.
A lot of it is through, a lot of what we do is going to be through Electrify Medford.
So if you want to get more involved in Electrify Medford, we're always looking for more coaches.
So we'd love to have you.
And if you have any suggestions as we're going along for ways that we can get the word out to people,
definitely let me know.
Thanks, I had a great time being coached by one of your coaches, so thoroughly into it.
Nice.
Alrighty, any other thoughts, questions, concerns?
Alright, seeing none, I'm going to launch into a brief
Discussion of what I. A vision I've had for this committee in many ways that we.
Meet every month and we discuss a lot of really interesting ideas.
We talk about problems in the world and things we'd like to see done, but I'm.
Coming from a background in advocacy, and I see a lot of very talented and smart and committed people in a room, so I want to.
potentially for the foreseeable future, set aside a little bit of time at the end of every meeting to discuss certain initiatives that people are opting to take on.
I have put together three action plans for myself.
One very easy, two a little harder, but things that I'm holding myself to and want to get your opinions on and get your volunteer and expertise and input on as well.
The hope is that we have a space at the end of these meetings where we can discuss progress we're making, hurdles we're facing.
And ask for general advice going forward.
So.
I know I sent out an email blast to everybody to brainstorm ideas for initiatives, things that they want to see done throughout the course of this year.
So I'd love to open the floor if people have thoughts of things they'd like to tackle throughout the year.
We'll keep this brief because I want to be respectful of your time.
Just know I will be
doing my absolute darndest to keep us all accountable to each other and talking about these projects so that we can make recommendations and use this position productively.
Will, are you talking?
I mean, we are new, so how do you propose we
Yeah, so the example I can give here is I have a pretty simple version I'm calling the Better Bag Ban.
We had discussed last month our bag ordinance was incomplete.
We banned those super thin film plastic bags from restaurants and stores.
But I think one of the easiest things we could do is make recommendations to our council members and to the mayor to finish the job and push for a thicker bag ban for Medford so that no plastic is being used.
For any of our backs.
So there's 1 that we can begin using our position and our.
Ability to commune with the council people to make that recommendation.
And if things are not moving along, we can also begin the groundwork of petitioning.
And talking to folks and neighbors about getting something like that done.
So that's sort of an example of a nice, easy initiative that I think we could push forward and hopefully generate something that is productive in the next couple of months.
That's great.
Well, I know we had like a priorities list from last year.
I just dropped that into the chat.
Are you collecting these in that list or another list or how are you doing that?
Something I was ready to do, time now being of the essence, I was ready for people to potentially read off the things that are most interesting to them, seeing as things like our priority lists through Google Docs and Excel sheets kind of struggle.
But the idea is to hopefully have projects that we can come back to over and over.
So if people would like to add an official statement of a thing they want to get done, I would love to use the priority projects list here.
So you want us to add to the priority program or against whatever is written there already?
I would love it if you found an action that was most motivating to you, something you'd like to take on.
These are examples.
These are things that we've talked about in the past, but if they don't inspire you, drop them.
I'd rather you do the thing that motivates you and that we can then help you towards going forward.
But this doesn't have to be now.
We have about a minute before I want to move to new business and towards a journey.
But I wanted to at least vocalize this to everybody to begin thoughts churning, people thinking about what they want to get done, and hopefully setting aside time for these kinds of projects going forward.
Yeah, Barry.
Well, two things.
One, and I don't want to put either of them on the list.
The first one is simpler and I'd consider putting it on the list, which is, is there a way for our committee to publicize that information that Bob sent out or
the meat of that information, which is the scamming involved in door-to-door and phone sales of electric supply, and also the scamming involved in a lot of sales of solar.
We need to protect our residents from this, people who are either trying to save money or who are trying to save the planet.
and who are doing nothing for either of those purposes but padding the pockets of scammers.
And I think we have a role there.
The second thing, which I definitely don't want to put on the list, is just to make people aware that
Luke and I have been working for, I don't know, two years more on trying to expand the solar roof ordinance.
And we've hit some barriers, but we're still working on trying to figure out how to make that happen, how to
ensure that development results in the creation of solar panels that benefit the community instead of benefiting private enterprises.
And I had like a five second conversation with Josh at an unrelated meeting and he expressed interest.
So Josh, you should give us your email or get in touch with us and we can, I can send you some stuff.
Yeah, Brenda's got it.
I'd love to get stuck in.
I think I would.
Oh, yes, Paul.
If you need me.
I'm sorry, one more time, Paul.
I'd like to get involved in that, too, so if Barry and Luca need
We're trying to avoid having it be an official committee project is part of what we're doing.
So I'm just afraid that if we have, so we're trying to find people with expertise, whether they're on the committee or not in this arena.
But I mean, if we get to the point where we have a half a dozen committee members, it's clearly a committee project.
And there's reasons that we don't want it to be that.
But Paul, if you're dying to be part of this,
I'm not dying.
I'd like to discuss that.
But yes, anyway.
I'd just like to, that's all.
So if you need any help, even if it is administrative, I'll be happy to help out.
OK, thank you.
Loretta?
Yeah, I like Barry's idea.
And I don't know who would take the lead on that, but I have a lot of knowledge about the do not knock policy that I worked with.
So Barry, if it ends up being you, so it takes a lead on, I'll call it do not knock.
Please feel free to reach out to me and I can share the knowledge I have about that.
Fantastic, and I'm starting to add some of my things into this doc as we find useful.
Yeah, are you going to email that again and we can add our thoughts to it?
Yes, it's currently in the chat, but I will send out an email once again.
We should double check though that your email is correct.
At some point during the week, if you weren't getting the minutes, we should make sure that that's ameliorated.
Well, one quick question.
Oh, sorry.
At one point, Brenda was sending out everything to the MEC email.
Is she still, so we should send it to Brenda and then she forwards it to everybody?
Uh, well, I had also sent out something through the MEC email list.
Uh, so hopefully that was received, but if it's not, we should double check it.
Okay.
I mean, I had some thoughts, you know, things, you know, we're running out of time here, but it would be nice to continue working on the rodenticide issues, but, you know, it can't just be me.
I'm working with the Trees Medford group and a few other projects that are coming up.
So one you're aware of that you attended a meeting on, which is a private thing, but environmentally focused.
So with the rodenticide, it needs more time for people to research some of this information.
Like I've heard that Arlington has banned the SCARS rodenticides and a few other towns have too.
So it'd be good to get a copy of their ordinance, but I don't wanna go against the city and the health department and what they're doing.
So, I know some of the alternatives have been very expensive, but maybe not because you could just say, we're not using these anymore.
They kill our natural predators of rodents.
Yeah, so I mean, collecting that information is a great first start.
I think it's one of those things we have time to mull it over and begin that work.
But you shouldn't have to bear it all by yourself.
That's why we're all here.
I see Lois has had her hand up patiently for a minute.
Yeah, as I mentioned at the beginning, I'm particularly interested in this restaurant business.
And I just wondered if anybody else is.
I'd be interested in working on it with you.
Pardon?
I would be interested in working on it with you.
OK, it just we we can get together privately and come up with a plan and run it by the group.
Sounds good.
Great.
I haven't figured out how to do the raise hand on this.
So I'm just going to quickly interject.
I'm very passionate about Zero Waste Medford and I see already the waste reductions.
I would love to speak to folks to potentially have like a, not official, but like dedicated Zero Waste Medford volunteer team.
Yes, I'm putting myself as a point person for that, but please add yourself as well.
I have a mini action plan I'd like to see done by the end of the year, and I'd love to get your help.
And I saw Josh had their hand up in the final moments.
Yeah, I just wanted to say,
Loretta, I'm more than happy to connect you with Colin Ziegler and Alicia in the city of Somerville who are doing some pretty cool innovative rodenticide rat birth control efforts now, which are interesting and don't affect sort of higher tier species.
So I don't wanna do that work like a lot with you, I'm sorry, but I'd be more than happy to act as a connector with the resources I have access to.
And who was that in Somerville?
Colin Ziegler runs that program.
Oh, okay, because I know Winchester was trying it too.
Okay, maybe we can email each other.
All right.
I've successfully thrown that, accepted that idea, thrown that grenade into conversation, but I think we're nearing the end.
I'd love to open up the floor for new business.
Any parting thoughts, things we are thinking about as we head into the new year?
Well, this is Bob Payne.
We usually, maybe we did establish a date for the Harvest Uranogy Festival, but we usually do that early in the year.
And we usually do it the Saturday after Columbus Day, or well, sorry, Indigenous Peoples Day.
Yeah, I will add that to the agenda for next month.
I didn't know.
And I guess usually Brenda, you should check to see if the mayor is available.
If the mayor should be involved, see what her schedule is.
Yep.
I'll confirm with the mayor and with Alicia.
Yeah.
And I will be hopefully pushing to get her to join maybe our March meeting or March, maybe April.
Yeah, I know she has school committee every other Monday night, but it sometimes overlaps with this meeting and sometimes doesn't.
So maybe we can reach out to her about coming in March.
And if that doesn't work, we can say April.
Yeah, well, we'll push and pull and make sure that it works out.
We had talked about having a presentation from someone from Zero Waste Melrose.
I haven't had any luck contacting them.
Have you, Bob?
I sent an email.
All they did is add me to their Google list.
They didn't respond at all.
So they don't want to talk to me.
We'll keep that up.
Pravita, do you have any contacts there that you could reach out to?
I've been in contact with Zero Waste Arlington, Zero Waste Cambridge.
I haven't spoken to any, definitely more so with Cambridge.
I don't know any contact in Melrose.
Yeah, it doesn't have to be Melrose either.
They don't have a monopoly.
I could reach out to Zero Waste Cambridge and Arlington.
OK, we'll try those.
Maybe they can make a presentation or something in a future meeting.
Sure.
All righty, we've hit eight o'clock, the bell tolls.
Do I hear any movements, any motions?
Motion to adjourn.
And seconded.
Fantastic, anyone opposed?
All right, seeing none, I bid you all farewell.
Wonderful meeting.
Please, if you need anything, reach out to me.
I can resend this priorities list.
Hopefully everyone has my email, but if not, I'll just throw it in the chat.
Do with it what you need.
Do with it what you will.
I think maybe I should send an email, a list out of everyone's contact info so that the folks can talk to each other outside of this.
That would be great.
And don't feel hemmed in by this existing priorities list from last year.
Oh gosh, yes.
It's such a patchwork of things we've just talked about.
I was like frantically taking notes, trying to piece it together, change whatever needs to be changed.
And then we should be golden.
But again, also it's all optional.
Like if you're overwhelmed, work's got you down.
Don't take on more than you can handle.
Take on the things that inspire you and we can help out.
All right.
I have no more sway over you.
You are gone.
Have a wonderful rest of your month.
Take care.
I'll see you all February.
Thank you.