Dial in number is 1-301-715-8592. Additionally, questions or comments can be submitted during the meeting by emailing shays, that's s-h-a-y-s, at medford.k12.ma.us. Those submitting questions or comments must include the following information. Your first and last name.
your Medford Street address, and your question or comment. As approved by the committee on February 1st, 2023, the evaluation subcommittee will meet to review and develop the process for the 2022-23 superintendent evaluation. Today's agenda, as approved by the evaluation subcommittee on Thursday, February 16th, 2023, the evaluation subcommittee will meet to finalize the template design and instructions.
So at our last meeting, we determined that we would, this year anyway, try using the evaluation tool that DESE provides. And we looked through it. And one of the concerns was that on some of the pages, the information is kind of wordy and knowing for the members to know specifically on the standards which
indicators we've chosen as the focus indicators, and I will share my screen in a minute to show everyone. But there was a question of whether that might be difficult to see, so that we wanted to look at highlighting those, the focus indicators that we've selected this year, so that it was just really clear which ones people should be rating. So I did that, and I will attempt to share my screen.
All right, can everyone see that? Okay, so it's further down. I did fill in also, just so we could see what it would look like when we actually send it to the members. I filled in the superintendent's goals on this page here.
and the focus indicators that went, that we selected to go with each of those goals. And then the, there's the highlighting. So I highlighted on these pages the selected indicators. So there's the ones for instructional leadership. And then the one for management and operations.
And family and community engagement, there were three. And professional culture, three more. I think that's it. Yes, that's enough. That's it. So I had just emailed these to everyone last, just last night, I think. So I don't know if anyone has any thoughts, comments. Does that seem to work better?
to have them highlighted. Melanie, member McLaughlin, sorry. Excuse me, member McLaughlin. I think the highlights are super helpful, thank you, but I wanted to know if you could go back up to the top and show me, I wasn't quite getting where you were saying you would put in the superintendent's information on the indicators, so if maybe you could. On the goals, I filled in the goals here.
Okay. Oh yeah. So all of that information there is from the superintendent is what you're saying. Yes. From her goals that she gave us. Yep. Okay. And do you think, I mean, I don't know what it looks like printed out, but is there a way to potentially make the text bigger in the early literacy and leading now sections or is it just not going to happen? Do you know what, it automatically makes it smaller to fit in the box.
Yeah. Okay. Yeah. I was just wondering, I guess we'll just, some of us anyway, probably not all of us will have to get our magnifying glasses out. It's not too, too bad. I do have it in front of me. Yeah, no, that's good. And then maybe, and you're not able to add, oh, you are able to add text. Cause you were able to add it in the boxes. Right. So, um,
Nevermind, I guess this could be part of our instructional sheet. I was just going to say, I think it'd be helpful for folks to know that, you know, following our goals identified by, you know, Medford Superintendent Maurice Edward, whatever. So people aren't thinking that this is like part of the basic form, if you understand what I'm saying.
But that could be in a sheet sharing a member Hayes, where it's the instruction piece so like if we, if we have a sheet that's just giving our colleagues instruction and it's just under superintendents performance goals. You know if we want to just let folks know that these are goals that have been previously identified by the superintendent and so that folks are not thinking that
So if I could just interrupt, I think, you know, up here, it says it right down. I know, it does say, I'm reading that. I mean, I think there's only so many ways we can really kind of hammer it home. I mean, this is. Yeah, I mean, is there anything that identifies this as Medford, though? Like, that's what I'm wondering.
Cause this could be anybody's, I mean- No, we do put the name of the superintendent. Okay. All right. Yeah. Yeah. Good. All right. And maybe Medford Public Schools or something. So, cause you know- I can't change the form itself. So I can't put in a line that says Medford Public Schools. After Dr. Edward Vincent, that next line there, can you put, nope, up top, go back up where it said Dr. Edward Vincent. After her, the next line, can you put Medford Public Schools? There's no way to add to the form.
There's no way to add that kind of stuff to the basic form. Member Hayes, I'm not asking you to add something. I'm asking you to put text in the box. So after where it says superintendent, there's another line, not under evaluator, but to the right. Yeah. Can you add text there yet? Could you put Medford public schools in there? Yeah. I mean, that is supposed to be the space for her to sign.
That's signature. Oh, that's her. No, I think I didn't need this. Okay, why is it going to need might be signature. Anyway, I'm just, it's probably just, I'm just picking on little things but I think it's important, and one of the things I try to do best practice and my own stuff at work that I always try to use page numbers and identify what the document actually is and where it's from so that
Should somebody have to look at this later and not know was this one Dr. Edwin Vincent was the superintendent of this school district or another school district or what have you so I just like to make it as basic as possible but maybe I'm just being a little too.
There's something I'm thinking about that, but let me let the superintendent speak. She has her hand raised. I just was going to suggest maybe just after my name, if you're able to put a comma, I know it will make the font get smaller, but maybe if Medford could fit right there, comma Medford, if that could be a compromise. We can. I mean, absolutely, we can. There's no reason not to. This isn't going to go. I think the thing is this is going to be live on our website.
and go to the DESI from us. So I don't know if there's anywhere else it's going to be that people wouldn't know what it's for. I'm not sure it's letting me go any further. It's not letting me go any further. Just a suggestion. Yeah. No, thank you. I mean, I can look and see if there's something. I'm not a tech wizard with this, but it doesn't look like you can add that much to it. But I mean, the next step for us, of course,
I guess, to identify, after all of this is said and done, how it lives on our website, on the Medford Public Schools website, so that the community has access to it. Any other? Let's see, two participants raising their hand.
I have my hand raised. I don't know that's it. I think it's both you and the superintendent. Yeah. I do. I had another question. Superintendent, did you have a question as well or do you need to learn. I just was lowering my hand right now. Okay, so no member he's just going back to the highlighted pieces, so thank you for entertaining the Medford piece and I do think that
you know, yeah, this form's not necessarily going anywhere other than our website, but it will go into a DESI file somewhere and who knows, you know, some time from now, you know, Dr. Edward Vincent gets famous or something and people are trying to figure out when, you know, this evaluation was or where it was or whatever. People know that it's Medford, just a, again, a little picky thing for me, but I like page numbers and as much explained as possible.
But I do like the fact that these are highlighted. So thank you very much. I think that's great. And I think that will be helpful. And I think that if we're just doing after this, I'm assuming a one-page sheet of instruction for our colleagues, although I think it's pretty self-explanatory, but I think it would be helpful to have just a brief explanation as well. What do you think? I had sent that piece with this too last night when I sent
I did make some instructions which I can show, I can share that screen too, or I don't know if anyone else has any comments on the actual form, the highlighting, or anything else. Member Graham? Oh. I don't have any comments. Thumbs up. Yeah, I got and reviewed the instructions as well. So yeah, I did get them. OK, so let me share that then. And we can take a look at that if there's no other.
Oh, did it come right, is it already up? Did that work? No, we're still looking at the evaluation. You're still looking, okay. Sometimes when you share the screen, if you only share the one, yeah, there you go. Stop sharing on that one and then open another one. Wait a minute, that's still in. Sorry, technical issues. Fine, take your time. Thank you.
All right, there we go. There, did that work? Yes. OK. So I can scroll down after you read. And I remember Graham said she already got a chance to look at them. So I don't know if she already has some thoughts. Tried to be as specific as I could, but it's hard to always anticipate. I thought it looked great. I don't have any questions. Oh, OK.
And there were some places just so where I mentioned the materials they would need. And I have those all in a folder, so I figured I could send them so everybody has everything they need in hand. We don't have, of course, the self-evaluation yet, but I can take that and make sure that gets attached to the email too, just so people aren't trying to look around for the things they need to be able to fill out the evaluation.
Yeah, I love the materials needed added. Thank you. I would just again at the heading member Hayes, I would recommend having it as superintendent summit of evaluation. Spell it right.
Yeah, I think it looks good. Thank you. All right. Oh, I didn't scroll all the way down, Melanie, for you to see. Let me know when to scroll. Yeah, scroll again, please.
Just going back up to the, I just wanted to make a, on the comments, comments are required further up. I think where it said comments, every, you know, the evaluation process is really helpful when we have comments, each member should be putting in comments or whatever. Have we talked about how those comments are going to be conveyed or is that part of what we're going to talk about next? When we do the, you mean when we create the compiled? Yeah.
Is there an explanation in here about what happens with those? No, because we haven't actually talked about that as a group yet. OK. And is that on the agenda for today, or is that another meeting?
Oh, you know, we didn't really put that in as a specific topic. It's not on for today. So we have evaluation subcommittee compiles individual ratings and draft summative evaluation. No, so it's number five, we draft something. Yeah, it's not specific. It's not. Yeah, but I think maybe I would add. So my suggestion to the to the subcommittee would be to add
Maybe we can come up with some process now is like either five day or something like that, that says, you know, how will we, how are we going to condense comments that are inclusive.
and a narrative, what that process will be, or are we just gonna dump comments? Like, are we just gonna cut and paste comments? That's what I guess I'm asking, what folks think. Maybe that can be 5A of this so that people know. You know, the other thing about the comments is that one of the things that we talked about is that this is an overall committee evaluation. So when people, one of the other instructions we might wanna include is that when people are putting comments in,
perhaps to not make them personal and not use first person. So in other words, I really think Maurice did, you know, Dr. Edwin Vincent did this right or whatever. I'm not sure that like that was problematic, particularly in the past, because when you are marrying those comments, like one member may feel that way, but another one may not. So how are we addressing that? Like there's, there are definitely pieces of that. So I don't know.
I don't know how you guys want to, I just am raising it. So I would like to hear some feedback about it. And I do think that it is part of the agenda today because it is number five, but essentially it's a 5A that we're adding, we would be adding to this process of what, how are we drafting the summative evaluation? So clearly, drafting ratings are not difficult, right? Because if we're doing,
you know, whatever, you know, exemplary needs improvement, whatever, in each of those items, we already have categories that are not subjective, but the comment piece is going to be potentially more so and might need to be, I don't think curated is the right word, but wordsmithed or something. But again, I defer to you, to the rest of the subcommittee to see what you guys have to say.
So my one thought would be in terms of the one piece you said about talking about how to word, not using the I statements. While I agree with that, I think at some point, I guess personally I feel like if we start getting too directive about how you should word your comments, there's a part of me that feels like we're, you know, being a little, not trusting the professionalism of our colleagues in a way.
I don't know. I don't recall there being specific I statements or I don't. I don't know. I guess that's just my feeling is I feel like at some point we start to get a little too.
intervening too much, maybe, in how a particular member chooses to word their comments? Yeah. I'm sorry. If I may, I was just going to say, it's not so much how a particular member chooses to word their comments. It's that when we're doing the summative, you cannot use the I statements, right? If we're doing summative comments, right,
how are we summarizing comments on all of the different categories? And so if a school committee member says, you know, you know, did great with instructional leadership or whatever, and another school committee member says, or writes in comments, you know, I think, you know, instructional leadership needs improvement and, you know, here's why and whatever, we're not necessarily gonna use the I think piece in there, but we're gonna have to, you know,
I would assume include those comments in some narrative that is cohesive. And so I'm asking what that process is going to be. And so we're not typically writing in the first person when we're doing it as a whole committee in terms of comments. So thinking about that, how are we doing this? And this was an issue last time because I remember clearly that was a discussion that we had because when we were seeing the summary narrative, when we were seeing
Qualitative data, it wasn't cohesive and it wasn't a narrative because it was littered with individual statements instead of an overall comment. So I guess the question is, how does the whole committee summarize or does the subcommittee summarize the comments giving the whole committee copies of the individual comments? That's what I'm asking.
So in looking at other cities and towns, I've seen it done any number of ways. I have seen ones where they just dumped members' comments in, obviously not all of them, but they dumped some comments in. Other ones where they created, and it was whoever, whether it was the chairperson of the committee who was the one doing the final composite, or whether it was a subcommittee like us that we're doing,
I've seen ones where they did create just a narrative based on the comments. So really we could go either way. And I think the intention is that the subcommittee is going to do that, that we're going to be the ones to create the composite. But of course, then we take it back to the full committee and they have their opportunity to comment on and change any, if they feel like we've miscommunicated something or if we use their comments and they felt like, well, that wasn't a comment that
I wanted to put in, I don't know, I was trying to think at one point whether we could put in the instructions somewhere in here that if there's a particular comment that someone feels is, one of their comments that they feel is most important, that they'd like to have included, that we could put in there that they should highlight that for us somehow. But I don't know how do others feel about that. Yeah, that's what I'm trying to figure out. Or may I, member? Yes.
So that's what I'm trying to figure out is like, are we doing a, you know, a total text dump where everybody's comments get put in to the overall evaluation or are we summarizing the comments? And so if we're summarizing the comments, you know, I think the subcommittee has the, you know, can do that. I think that's part of what, you know, has been suggested. And I think the overall committee obviously reviews and approves, but,
I just think that we need to be clear on what that process is as a subcommittee before we do it and then we also need to schedule time to be able to do that because I did feel like, and especially for asking people to make comments explicitly which is what this form is doing to please add comments which you know in the past some people have and some
more people some people did more and other people did less and some people may have done little or none so um which doesn't i guess doesn't matter either way but just knowing that we have a process and so i guess i'm leaning towards i would be leaning towards creating a narrative um that would be inclusive um where we can refer and we already said that we were going to have the original individual
evaluations as part of the packet as well. So people could refer to it, but I think that we're entirely capable of making a narrative of the comments. I just want to be clear that that's what we're doing, or if that's not what we're doing, that we're explicitly cutting and pasting. Okay. Member Graham? I think we should take the approach of, for each of the, whatever it is, like three or four things, say,
you know, representative comments include. And then just a couple of bullets where we're taking like verbatim what various members said, because we're going to send everybody, everybody's like detailed comments. And I think if we did that, we would have an opportunity to like, you know, truly like pick like the gamut of feedback without saying the same thing three times. So if three people say,
I really like that the superintendent did this very specific thing. We just put that once and move on. But I think maybe a little bit of culling that we would do, but otherwise, I would frame it as comments from the committee include and just leave that like that. Are you saying a narrative plus the comments, so we would do the narrative? No. No, just the comments? That is how I would frame the narrative.
Is my audio better? You're a little echoey. Oh. OK. Understandable, though. I think it was the same thing as the other night. I don't know what's going on. I don't know if it's a speaker or something else, a phone or something in your room. But it's definitely echoey. It only happens in full committee meetings. All right. So then we're looking at just including, saying we'll include representative comments.
Oh, superintendent. If I understood correctly, member Hayes, what I heard member Graham say was that following our representative comments of the evaluation or whatever, and then I think being as inclusive as possible. So yeah, I'm OK with sort of it's like an in-between for both and not necessarily having to create a narrative. And like member Graham was saying, there are a lot of times when the same comment is repeated throughout.
several members, I just, I think that it's going to be a little bit more challenging if there are very disparate comments, but we can still say like what member Graham was saying, these are representative comments. So one might be this and the other might be that. And so they're representing both. I think that's the value of, of not trying to create something completely independent of
What the comments are, because then you can say, you know, these are representative comments. And, you know, maybe each of us can take. 1, 1 or 2 or whatever, and, you know, when we have a meeting schedule, so we can each take 1 or 2. Do what we think is the consolidation and then we have something to review. Sounds like a good plan superintendent. You had your hand raised at 1 point. Are you.
No, I just was gonna agree and say that I thought that that was a very beautiful compromise to everyone's gonna submit their individual evaluations and just to compile it, the representative comments and just have it bulleted. So it's whoever the final person is, it makes it a lot simpler and then it's just bulleted. So it represents what everyone said.
All right. So that's, that's, that's all I was agreeing there. I don't know if you needed to type that. I'm thinking maybe put it in here. The subcommittee. Well, I would say select representative comments for the final evaluation.
That works for me. I just want to double check on the next meeting to make sure it's in my calendar. I'm sure it is. But what is the date? Do you guys know? May 8 is the subcommittee where I'll be presenting with with artifacts and links. I'll be presenting to you. Do you mean this that that's the cow? That's the cow. Right? Is there another I don't think there's another subcommittee on the 22nd. Yes.
Thank you. So the members are, the deadline for them to return to us, which, oh, I'll have to put that in there too. I have it in my calendar, it's good. Yeah, the deadline should be on there for when they return it, that's right. Good thinking, Member Hayes. Yeah. And we're getting this to them for this Monday, or are we waiting until the Monday of the 8th? I think we had it that we would give it to them and talk about it on the 8th as part of that meeting. Yeah, yeah, that makes sense, okay.
All right, so I will add individuals rate. Trying to think of the best place to add that date. I would put it right there. OK. They rate individual overall performance by the state. I would put it right in the header of number four. OK. I would also highlight it.
you know, make it really clear. Individual. Sorry. Evaluations. I'll fix the spelling are due to the subcommittee
Well, I don't think they should send it to this subcommittee I would say to member Hayes. Okay. Because sending it to all three of us could be an issue. If anybody responds so by May 21. Well, there we go.
All right. So I think that's what we have on the agenda. Is there anything else, any other comments on either the form or the instructions? I just want to say thank you for doing this. I thought this was really helpful and I think sets out a good process moving forward and is pretty self-explanatory and appreciate the work that you did on that. Thank you.
Thank you. Yeah, we'll see. Oh, sorry, go ahead. Motion to approve and place this on the May 15th agenda. Second. For school committee approval. All right. Second. Roll call, member Hayes. Yep, okay. I mean, so. Question. Since. Yes. I apologize. On the May 1st agenda, we do have the minutes.
For this, we have it because on May 8th is the meeting that I'll be presenting to you. And I think May 8th is where if the committee approves this, they would need to approve it by the 1st in order for you to use it on the 8th. Is that correct or not correct?
Was it? Yes. So it's it's already on the agenda for Monday at the minutes to be approved for this meeting is listed. So you'd be able to report out on it on Monday. But we will have to, we will have to make a motion to approve this process on Monday as well. Can you can you make an update to the agenda to put a motion to approve?
under the subcommittee report. Okay. But we can make motions on the floor. I'm not sure what you're saying, that it is a motion. I just think it should be noticed that we are going to vote on this. You said it's on the agenda. Approving the minutes is on the agenda. Oh, approving the minutes. Yeah, no, that's different.
Voting on the evaluation process could be part, yeah, would need to be part of the agenda. So motion to approve the- Motion to amend. Well, sure. Well, we didn't vote on it, so I'm withdrawing my motion. Okay, motion to approve. So- Second. Motion to approve.
the evaluation process and instructions and place on the May 1st school committee agenda for committee approval. For committee consideration, right? Because they can't approve. We can't say, yeah, they're either gonna approve or disapprove, but for yeah, committee vote. Yeah, for committee vote, not approval. I would second that with the amendment.
for committee consideration. So under new business, or would you like it under the approval of the minutes? Where would you like me to have it added so we can work on that immediately? I would put it under the minutes. OK, motion to approve superintendent evaluation instructions and process. OK. I'm sorry, Member Graham. Yes, you're right.
Are they approving the template too? So template, instructions, and process. Instructions and process, yeah. Okay. All right, I should take a roll call vote just to make it official. Can you say again what you're, just so we have it out there, Jenny? Motion to approve the template and process and place on the May 1st school committee agenda for consideration.
Okay, so roll call vote. Oh thank you. Member Graham. Yes. Member McLaughlin. Yes. Member Hayes, yes. All right, motion approved. Excellent, thank you. Motion to adjourn. Second. Motion to adjourn, roll call vote. Member Graham. Yes. Member Hayes, yes. Member McLaughlin. Yes. All right, thank