And it is the Saturday Coffee Clutch with Heather Lofthouse and your truly Robert Reich. I guess I want to start out, Heather. This has been another grueling week. I don't know how you feel. How are you doing? Can I ask you how you feel for once? After you tell me how you feel. Oh, gosh.
I'm actually, I'm okay. Better than last clutch. I was like, it was a low day. Today's a medium day. My family's coming back from having been traveling. So that's nice. So that's personal. We can talk about the personal later. I think we should talk about the political and the personal. Right. But so that's me. Wait, but back to you. How are you today? Well, I'm, I'm, I'm okay. But you know, the other day somebody asked me how I'm doing.
And I just blurted out shitty. And I realized that I'm shitty because of the person who's in the White House and the effect. It's almost subconscious. It's the kind of negative.
you know, awful, sadistic effect that everybody is feeling. Again, even subconsciously. You go about your day, and people are busy, and I'm busy, and a lot of nice things happen. But this is, you can't get away from it. I know, he's infected so much.
I mean, he's just, it's awful. But what are we going to talk about today? So, so much to talk about. Big economic news. I really want your two cents on this, please. But I think the first thing we should, tariffs have been, so he's been threatening Trump. By the way, hold that.
I want us to talk about tariffs as import taxes because they are not – nobody knows the word taxes or tariffs. But import taxes, that's what they are. They're import taxes and they are paid for by us, by Americans.
And so tariffs, let's get away. Okay, we'll do a rebrand. Okay, rebrand. So these tariff import taxes that Trump has been threatening, and then he moves the date, and then he doesn't move the date, and then he moves the amount, and it's so just handshaking with all these different people.
And it's so personal, it's like each deal, you know, everybody's waiting, but what's Trump going to decide? We're getting to the final hour, the final minute, and the Canadians, what is he going to decide? And it's not based on rational data analysis, it's what's he going to decide in that moment? That is the point. We are in a, and this is really a theme that I suggest we talk about today. Okay, let's do it.
The theme is that we, you and I, were brought up in a world of law and a policy that is rational, that people had to justify the laws and the policies on the basis of public interest. I got a master's in public policy. That's how I met you. Two years studying how we carefully assess the scenarios, what's happening in the world.
Heather, I apologize. I want to apologize to you now. What am I doing with that degree? Because public policy and law, I know a lot about public policy and I have a law degree. It's irrelevant. We're dealing in a world in which we have one person who's making personal deals and they are at his whim and everybody else is trying to figure out what he's going to do next and why he's going to do it. And we are so far away from a world of law. You know, the rule of law
that it's sometimes staggering to think about where we used to be. I mean, the Constitution, you know, you sometimes kid me for... Do you have it with you? I don't have it with me, but I know it by heart. I mean, Article 1, Section 8 says the tariff customs, all duties originate with Congress. Congress has the power to decide on tariffs.
Well, nope, that's not the case these days. I mean, he's he has using he conjured up an emergency, a national emergency based on the balance of payments. And the that feels like ages ago, by the way. And the yes. And the national debt balance. And so that's a poster board. Yes. And that's so-called emergency.
creates his authority to what? To deal with every individual nation and strike a different deal? And we don't even know what the deals actually are? And nobody's publicizing the deals. And for all we know, he's pocketing money off these deals. Or maybe he's pocketing some, I don't know, some future agreement to have a Trump resort in wherever this
country is. We're so far beyond the rule of law that it's hard to even talk about it. I know. It almost feels more like you would see this at a corporation or in the mafia. Mafia is closer. This does not read democracy.
It's the opposite of Darwin. This is what we fought the Revolutionary War about. This is taking on a despot who has his own view from one minute to the next of what he wants.
And the guy at the top, that's, it's the guy at the top. We really got to, it matters about the guy at the top and we can't, and mergers and acquisitions. You mentioned that in your sub stack, these Wall Street people who are like, you know, I really, as I'm working on things, I really got to take into account the intrusions of the people at the White House.
All these lawyers are advising their clients, and we're talking about big corporations and the big corporate lawyers. They're saying, well, let me see about what I can find out about what they want in the White House, whether they're going to approve this particular merger, this particular acquisition. Columbia University, I mean, all of that, Harvard University, all the universities.
all the individual law firms, all the individual media companies, all the, you know, they're all vying for Trump's attention, his good graces. They want to avoid pissing him off. What are we living in now? This is, this is, it's so personal, Heather, that it is, to me, it resembles everything I know about fascism. This is fascism.
I know it is. And this week, so Canada, our neighbors to the north, have been talking about a lot of things. But one thing is they were talking about Palestine and the fact that they would say it was a free state potentially the end of September.
And then Trump says, excuse me, what? Watch me with my tariff card. Forget about Article 1, Section 8. Yes, I'm going to put a 35% tariff on everything coming from Canada. And I'm sorry I used the word tariff. Oh, right. Import tax. A 35% import tax on everything coming from Canada. Think of the oil. Think of the lumber. Think of the auto parts. I mean, all kinds of things.
And this is vindictive because, why? Because he doesn't like the Canadians and they haven't been cooperating and because- They're not saluting. They're not saluting and they decided because it's their right to decide whether they recognize a Palestinian state and under what circumstances. So what does this fascist in Washington decide? He's going to just do what he wants to do.
and charge Americans a 35% import tax on Canadian everything coming from Canada. While he's supporting Netanyahu. Let's be clear about that. While he is supporting Netanyahu. And this is why you can't separate out, you know, one issue like import tax tariffs from other issues like what's happening in Israel right now. It's all
It's the same. It all comes together around this fascist in the White House. So there was some movement on American soil with regard to Gaza this week. We talked about it last week on The Clutch, but seeing these kiddos, Americans, I mean, there's been murder that we've seen, but somehow watching starving children.
That's it. Makes people rise up in a way that they hadn't previously. Well, here's where my age comes in, because I remember so distinctly a turning point in Vietnam, in the public's feeling about why we were in Vietnam, whether we should be in Vietnam, when you saw these photos of these little children kind of fleeing from Napalm.
And, you know, naked. And the public saw these photographs and said, no, this is wrong. We are not going to allow this. And the starving children in Gaza, I think it's just changing public opinion, even Jewish public opinion. I mean, I can't tell you how many people are now saying to me,
You know, I'm Jewish, you're Jewish, we are obviously not anti-Semitic, but we are anti-Netanyahu. You know, this is an authoritarian
fascist regime doing some of the terrible things that resemble, not the same obviously, but it's that resemble what was done in the 1930s in Germany to the Jews. I know. And Trump and Netanyahu, I mean, they're these two authoritarian leaders. And Putin. These are the three. I was going to say synchronized sinners.
synchronized centers, synchronized swimmers, but not exactly. No, no, it's not. It's pretty good together. It's really ugly. But back to the military industrial complex that America loves to support or some Americans.
make happen. And so this week, 27 Dems, right? In the Senate. In the Senate, voted in support of this resolution by Bernie Sanders, which... To not give any military aid to Israel. This is a huge deal, Heather, because you've got the AIPAC, the, you know, the Israeli lobby that, you know, has spent huge amounts in these campaigns.
And the Republicans are in their pockets, and the Democrats have been, but the Democrats are now saying, no, we are not going to allow this, this kind of mass starvation.
And Netanyahu has already turned Gaza into rubble. We are not going to allow this humanitarian crisis, this indecency. I've talked to members of the Senate, senators who are talking about Netanyahu now as a war criminal. And he is. I know, but it took a long time for us to get here, right, in terms of the language. You saw Angus King wrote that terrific letter
You know, Angus King, he's an independent. But like Bernie Sanders, these independents from New England, hey, they are in the lead. They're taking the lead. And I wish the Democratic Party was as courageous as a whole. But they're getting there.
And what was that Eisenhower quote? Remember? Oh, yes, yes, yes. I have it. I have it. OK, this is this is from 1953. He says every gun. This is Dwight Eisenhower. Now, you're right. Right. And 75 years ago.
I mean, you don't have a direct memory. No, he's not in my speed dial. He was the most boring speaker. I mean, when you listen to Dwight Eisenhower, I mean, I remember I was a little kid, I would go, oh, do we have to listen to Dwight Eisenhower? He would say every, but he's had good things to say, every gun that is made, every warship launched, every rocket fired,
signifies in the final sense a theft from those who hunger and are not fed, those who are cold and are not clothed. In other words, the military industrial complex was taking away resources that we needed and the world needed. It wasn't just the United States, the world needed to avoid the starvation and hunger and I mean all of the worst miseries of mankind.
Right, and he's saying one gun and we're talking about millions of guns, tens of thousands of assault rifles. There is no justification, let's be clear, for sending military aid to Netanyahu and this horrible regime. This does not make me anti-Zionist or anti-Semitic when I say that. And let's separate these issues.
So here we have, it's been so interesting to watch how long this is taking, right? We've talked about ceasefires. We've been watching the horrendous, horrific happenings for ages now. But having the zeitgeist catch up, or the politicians catch up to the zeitgeist, or having all Americans see it in a similar way. So the other thing that's been happening is we have, the tariffs are about to hit, right?
Is it this week? Is it tomorrow? Are they prepping? Is it yesterday?
Not tariffs. Import taxes. So the import taxes. I feel like we have to say import tax, the tariff import taxes. Whatever you want to say, but I think it's important that people see these as taxes. Totally. Okay, so these tariffs, these tariff taxes, these import taxes, under the guise of tariffs. Is that better? Yeah, that's pretty good. So they're coming in, but when are people going to see the prices affecting them? We're starting to see this. There's been new economic data out that we have to talk about this week.
Well, this was a big week for economic data. And it showed the consumer price index and other indices. The inflation. Prices showed an uptick in inflation. Trump is saying to Jerome Powell and the Fed, you've got to lower interest rates. Well, you don't lower interest rates when you see inflation on the horizon and when you see all of these import taxes being just about applied.
including 35% and we didn't even talk about 50% on Brazil. Oh, I know. I mean, coffee clutch? Hello? I know, how are we going to drink anything? This is going to be so... But that's another personal, right? Goodbye, coffee. I mean, he doesn't like what they're doing, Bolsonaro judge. No, it's personal. It is personal. This is another example of personal because Trump doesn't want... Trump hates Lula.
in Brazil and he's going after Lula because of Lula's efforts to hold accountable Bolsonaro. Lula's predecessor in Brazil who did just what Trump did, tried to overturn an election and urged people to go and go after the government officials and attack government office buildings. In other words, Trump is using tariff policy
Sorry. Import tax policy. To punish Brazil. This is, again, this is one man. This is Donald Trump, fascist, one-person rule deciding what he's going to do. Vindictive and kind of all over the place. But Bob, so if his goal isn't economic, it's just power and watch my whims?
It's – yes, I have the power. I want everybody, whether you are Canada or another country or Columbia University or a law firm or the Smithsonian or whoever you are, I want you to come and beg me. I love people coming and begging and just making deals with me. By the way, if the deal happens to be a little bit of a pay to play, you know, like – I
Maybe a giant jumbo jet that's a palace. That's even better. But also, and I will punish those of you who aren't coming to beg at my feet. It's the malignant. And if you criticize me, or if you allow people to criticize me, if you are CBS, I might not even allow you, CBS, to sell yourself to be part of a merger
your parent company, Paramount, to be sold. I have so much vindictiveness and so much control over government that I can basically make your life miserable. If you're Jeff Bezos, you have antitrust. I can use antitrust against you, Jeff Bezos. So you make sure that the Washington Post doesn't say anything critical of me. But it's on such a huge scale. I mean, this is global personal.
global personal. And this is not, again, contrast this with the rule of law, which is predictable
which is based on some facts and it's based on the public interest. This has nothing to do with any of that. But the other thing about all of this is it creates a fog around Epstein stuff. Oh, well. It creates a fog around the jobs report. I'd love for you to talk about that too. But you don't even have to have much of a fog around Epstein because what did they do this week? I mean, the Justice Department, it's again, a personal deal, personal deal.
Yeah. And Ghislaine Maxwell has just been moved to a softer, more minimum security situation. A minimum security. Now, you look at that, why do you suppose, why has she moved to a minimum security prison? Could it be that she has some agreement there that she might not implicate Trump?
I know. OK, the jobs report, can we talk about, so we have, I'm tired of talking about the .0000 percent. Can we talk about everyone else for a minute? How is everyone else in this country doing? I mean, the jobs report was not good. No, I think it was the worst jobs report we've had in some time.
in terms of the number of new jobs being created. So with regard, this is important, with regard to the jobs report, yesterday's jobs report, 73,000 new jobs, Heather. Now without context, that's meaningless. The context is that the average new job growth
is about 200,000. I mean, that's what you expect. If the economy is doing halfway decent, you get 200,000 new jobs because of population growth. But no, we had 73,000. And the Bureau of Labor Statistics, they very often do this. What they do is they get more information from previous months. They had to, as they have before,
but they revised downward the actual job growth for May and June. So you've got 73,000 for July. In May, the job growth actually was revised down to 19,000. That's from 125,000 down to 19,000. And for June, from 147,000 down to 14,000. So you had, in other words, 238,000 jobs
258,000 jobs. 238,000, 258,000. You are a mathematician. I try. You are so good. So that was subtracted. And this is what the Bureau of Labor Statistics, they are so careful to modify when they get additional information.
Also, of course, you revise something that comes out on the first of the month for the previous month. I mean, imagine in all of our accounting, have you ever found someone that can close a month the first day of the next month? Well, no. But what they do, they try to be as accurate as they can. And their accuracy, they are known for their accuracy. And they're politically, they are insulated from politics. I once made a terrible mistake. It was on an international.
discussion of jobs and it was in Paris and they called me in my office at the Labor Department when I was Labor Secretary and they said, a translator from French, how many new jobs do you expect the Labor Department is going to show in its monthly labor report tomorrow?
And I said, well, I don't know. I mean, obviously, they don't tell me and I cannot know. But my guess would be. And I gave them a guess. And it was translated back into French as I expect. And then it went around the world.
Interesting. And people were so upset with me as if I had seen the figure. Right, a sneak peek. So they really are careful. But here's the other thing. When these revisions came out yesterday, what did Donald Trump do? This is in line with our theme about personal. I know it. Everything is personal. Personal and loud. Vindictive, angry. And taking over. So he says that the commissioner of labor statistics
This woman who is very, very careful, very diligent, who has been absolutely, there's no reason to think anything other than professional. He says that she should be fired. This is on True Social immediately. I mean, this is Trump's response to bad news. Yeah. Well, to news that makes him look bad.
news that makes him look bad. That's right. And it's just he goes after the messenger. Always, always do that. Well, when you do that repeatedly, what you're doing is reducing the public's trust and faith in institutions of government like the Bureau of Labor Statistics that you need
We need to have so much faith in those numbers. I mean, the same thing with the Fed. I mean, he's going after the Fed. He just goes after the Fed because he doesn't like what the Fed is doing. And he just undermines the credibility. That's his M.O. I know it. OK, let's get back to some other things.
At the same time, you've got the financial economy getting more and more frothy, more and more risky. Yeah, I saw you say frothy in your sub stack. Frothy, it's just, it's not, when I use the term frothy, what I mean about the financial markets is that it's bubbly. It's just bubble, bubble, bubble, bubble. It's not the real economy. They are just speculating. And there's more and more big money speculating. Look at,
What we know now about Microsoft or Meta, they are putting huge amounts of money, gambling billions and billions and billions on artificial intelligence. Is that good? Is that bad? Well, if everybody is betting on artificial intelligence.
and those huge bets turn out not to be particularly good, or if somebody else, like China, exceeds us, well, what then? You've bet the entire house on something. But also the junk bonds are coming back. Do you remember them? Those are high-risk loans, they charge
a huge amount of money, if you're not getting a big return on those junk bonds, what then? I mean, you might not be able to pay them back. And then there's crypto, of course. Crypto. And we have this new, you know, the comptroller. The comptroller of the currency. Controller. Controller, I know, but there's an M, I mean, come on. Controller of the currency. Yeah, but I mean, it's a different word than controller.
Well, it depends on how you say it. Comptroller. How many times in a normal conversation do you talk about the comptroller of the currency? Especially this one. I try to not go there. But he's, you know, another Trump.
Here's another Trump appointee, a buddy, who now has authority under the so-called Genius Act, just passed by Republicans in Congress, to regularize, I mean, what we all know what he's doing is basically going to take the hands off crypto. And stablecoin in particular, which Trump has a huge stablecoin company, Endeavor. And this is, again, go back to our theme. This is personal. It's all personal.
personal. This is all Trump. What benefits him? What makes him mad? His family is raking it in on crypto.
It's so focused on him. This is malignant narcissism, 101. It's malignant narcissism, and it's corruption. And we're going to look back on this era, assuming historians in the future can write the truth. They will be able to, Bob. I think so. Come on. I think so. We have to. Well, OK. Promise me? I'm not going to promise anything, because I can't guarantee anything. But I think that they are going to look back on this period in time and just say, well,
You know, what was this? Was this, you know, that we went through a period where we had policy, public policies and laws and we had restrictions and we had a constitution and now we're having a kind of, you know, the Republican Party, they're all zombies.
And the personal vendettas, right? So Jerome Powell, he's bullying Jerome Powell. He's thinking and he's bullying. This is how he does it. He uses another part of government. In this case, he's saying Jerome Powell approved some renovations at the Fed that are very, very expensive.
Talk about hypocrisy. We'll get to that in a minute. So Jerome Powell kind of did something wrong. And Jerome Powell, sotto voce, what Trump is saying, I'm going to get you. You don't do what I want. You don't lower interest rates. You are in trouble because I'm going to embarrass you. I'm going to humiliate you. I'm going to create a scandal around you. I can do that because I know how to do that. I'm Donald Trump.
Well, Trump, Powell and the Fed so far are saying, no, we're not going to cut interest rates because prices are inching upward. That's not what we are going to do now. But consider what Trump
is doing even to the Fed, let's assume for the sake of the argument that he gets a Fed chair in there who plays his game, who does exactly what Trump wants. Trump says reduce interest rates, he does it. And yet also assume that you're an investor.
in the market, or you're a corporate investor or whatever, and are you going to be feeling secure about interest rates and inflation? No, you're going to say to yourself, the cop on the beat is gone. Right. I don't like this hypothetical game. No, but this is real. I know. This is what is actually happening. Jerome Powell has said he's not going anywhere.
And Trump has kind of flirted with the fact that he could or could not try to fire him. I mean, Jerome Powell still has some time left in his term, but not forever. And Trump is already auditioning other Fed chairs. I know. And the data, people are a little worried about there are so few people working around the data that it's problematic. We really need to have people crunching the numbers, being able to check on the prices of things. Yes, over the Bureau of Labor Statistics.
The Bureau of Labor Statistics, which I am not enamored with most government agencies, but I'll tell you, when I was labor secretary, that group of people had so much talent.
and so much integrity, and they still do, but they are being starved, just like most other agencies. And it's a problem, because you need data to make financial decisions. You do. You absolutely do. But the hypocrisy you were referring to a moment ago, Trump is saying Jerome Powell is pouring money into renovations of the Fed building. Meanwhile, what is Trump doing at the White House?
Let's build a $200 million ballroom. Let's model it off Mar-a-Lago, Louis Quatorze. It's going to be even bigger than the White House in terms of square feet. Where else is one going to let them eat one's cake and toast one's... This is the people's house.
We're getting away from the people's house when we're trying to create a ballroom that is larger than the White House, that is gilded in gold leaf. I know, filigreed. Filigreed, that's exactly it. Filigreed. Full of greed. Full of greed. Full of greed. That's pretty good. I know. And also, what about when he went to Scotland on our taxpayer dollars?
He was there for his golf course. I mean, it's become normalized. We now think, well, of course he's going to rip us off. Well, that's dangerous thinking itself. A lot of people say, well, of course he's going to be making side deals for himself. That's dangerous. We can't allow that to be normalized.
Okay, what do we do? Should we talk about this? Oh, first, yeah, this is perfect. What? Because, I mean, when I think, what do we do? And I ask you, and I think, what do we do? And I try and tell people, I do think about the midterms. I think about elections coming up and the gerrymandering. We haven't talked about that. I can't, we can't finish our cups. You're not quite done, neither am I, until we talk about the gerrymandering that's happening, which is also personal, right? So this is in Texas this week.
where Trump basically says, Governor Abbott, I need you to find me five seats. I need you to go ahead, remap. Governor, this is the president. We're going to need five. I want five more Republican seats out of Texas. I mean, can you? Again, this is so counter to what we believe in, in this country, in terms of rule of law. Now, people ask me, should California
Gavin Newsom, governor, try to counter what Greg Abbott is doing in Texas. Not just Newsom, but a lot of Dems in a lot of states and some more important. Should New York and Illinois try to gerrymander more radically?
So if they gerrymander, we gerrymander. Eye for an eye. This is actually a subtle question. It's an ethical question. It's also a question about democracy. I mean, if Democrats and progressives do the same thing, you know, they say, well, we have to fight fire with fire. I understand that.
But it also means that we are denigrating and undermining constitutional norms and values the same way they do. It's hard. I go back and forth, Heather. How do you feel? I find it very difficult. And I think of examples that so many people bring up when the Democrats sat on their hands and could have been more aggressive and could have gone up against the traditions and protocols, and it would have been better for democracy.
Well, I think of Michelle Obama, when she said, when they go down, we go higher. And I worry a little bit that that attitude may be making it harder for Democrats to do what they need to do to conquer this fascist.
But also, I mean, I know it depends what models you're looking at. But this is going to be fascinating, the midterms. And it is all important. We know that for democracy. But is five seats enough? If it's enough in certain scenarios, I mean, how is all of this going to play out?
I obviously don't know. And there are special elections between now and the midterms. There are also very important mayoral contests like New York City. And when I look around the country at the way voters are moving,
I am encouraged. I think there are more and more people who say, these Republicans, all they want to do is go after immigrants and after transgender kids. That has nothing to do with my life. What about prices of things? What about making things affordable to me? What about helping me with child care? And the Democrats are getting it. This is what Mamdani actually talks about.
And I think that other Democrats are beginning to say the same thing. It's bread and butter issues. It's kitchen table economics. It's what people want and need. And get away from your scapegoating, your boogeymans. Exactly, your othering. Your othering. But he's so good at it, the conman's conman.
He's very good at taking over language. This is an era of anger, anti-establishment anger. I understand it. I've been chronicling it for years. But what Trump has done over his first and now his second term of office, and he's doing it even more crazily, is to channel that anger.
into really the scapegoating of them, them and them and them and them. Instead of what the Democrats ought to be doing is saying the real problem – you want to know what the real problem is? It's corporations are too powerful and rich people are too powerful and they are
They are taking their wealth and their power and they're abusing it by destroying our democracy, undermining our democracy with all their money, their campaign contributions. That's why we are in the fix. We are in. It's not just Trump. Trump is the consequence, the culmination of all of this. Did you read about at the Smithsonian, there's an exhibit about
presidents who have been impeached, and so there were three, and then Trump was there, and so they adjusted the exhibit so that he was added, but now we might adjust the exhibit so that he's not in it. The Smithsonian. The Smithsonian, well, because I think we have serious reasons for impeachment. It's a matter of words. But this is, again, the surrendering in advance, the desire not to piss him off.
So what can we do not to piss him off? His power is not just direct, it is indirect. It is all of the chilling effect he is having all over the country. All these institutions don't want to make him upset and angry because he could do anything. Right. So you mentioned that you've been chronicling
how we got to Trump, you've been talking about these things. We have, pardon me while I stand up, I think Michael and Jordan are gonna get mad at me. Your new book, if I may, is coming out, coming up short, it comes out this coming week, this coming Tuesday. Is that this Tuesday? Look at the time go. But so, Inequality Media Civic Action is gonna be raffling off a couple signed copies, so thank you for scribbling your name for us. Tell us about it.
It is coming up short is a double entendre, of course. It's about me. I didn't grow full growth. I came up short. But the country, my generation also came up short.
My father's and my parents' generation, they bequeathed to us my generation. And when I say my generation, I'm talking about boomers primarily. George W. Bush and Bill Clinton and Donald Trump and Clarence Thomas and I, we were born about the same time. When was that, 1946? Can we talk about that? 1946. Heather, everybody who's anybody was born in 1946 share
I mean. Dolly Parton. Keep it going. I mean I could keep going. No reason to keep it going. I mean everybody. That's everyone. I mean everybody. Who matters. But the reason we were born in 1946 is not complicated. There was a war. My father came home. There was my mother. And boom. Boomers. Baby boom. I mean that was it. But they bequeathed to us a
a country that was not perfect. I mean, women were still second class citizens. Black people were still second class citizens. But we at least tried. We were beginning on the path. And then we blew it in the sense that in the late 70s and the beginning of 80s, particularly with Ronald Reagan, the country did a U-turn. Instead of building,
and strengthening the middle class instead of making it a land of opportunity and diversity and equity and inclusion.
we became top heavy. More and more of the wealth of this country went to the top. More and more of the income went to the top. And out of that came more and more inequality of education and inequalities having to do with healthcare and inequalities having to do with everything you can imagine. And I think that it led ultimately
to the 2008 financial crisis in which the bankers and the people at the top who were responsible for gambling, they got away with it. They got bailed out by taxpayers.
And millions of Americans lost their homes and their jobs and their savings. And that's when a lot of people began to say, the game is rigged. And this is not my democracy anymore. This is, well, that's what I try to get to in the book. I mean, I'm trying to explain it because I was there.
But that's what I like. You interweave the personal history and the country's history. There's kind of broader themes and then individual stories. I didn't have any choice. I wanted to talk about what I learned, particularly in the public sector and the teaching, which is very important to me.
I know. That last chapter is pretty great. Oops, did I say that out loud? Also, you and I are going to be talking about the book and other things at, for those who are local, Wednesday, August 13 at Broadway SF, which is at the Golden Gate Theater, an event with book passage. And so we will be in San Francisco on August 13, if anyone wants to come. Well, in fact, I'm starting my book tour.
Is that the kickoff? Monday. I'm going to be on Stephen Colbert's show Monday night. Are we allowed to tell people that? I don't think so. Great. And then I do a lot of other things. You know, I don't really like book tours. Can I confess this to you? Keep it to yourself. Can you keep it to yourself too, please? It's just us.
I think it's the logistics, but you like to see the people. But it's also you feel like a traveling salesman. I know you do. You're flogging. I know, but people are so excited to, they are. I don't know. I mean, it's one thing, a movie is one thing, and you did the movie, you and Elliott Kirshner, a beautiful movie, and I was very touched by your movie. Oh, I'm glad. But it's different. It's in so many theaters. When it's a memoir, it's personal, it's me. I see. Yeah, but it's very,
Historical. It's not just this was me and my feelings when I was in middle school and my feelings when I was in my 20s. You know, it really, it's crafting a narrative that's important to read. Well, I mean, it's all me and it's all very sincere. And it's what I lived, what I saw.
But we do dovetail in terms of the movie, because the movie is a personal side of you, too. And it's you looking at the decision to retire from the huge course you taught. Just to be clear, you do a few little classes here and there now. But this big course of 750 students, you had 30 teaching assistants. That's 30 graduate student instructors. That's a class in and of itself. It was. We would get together every week. We'd have our own seminar. Such an undertaking.
But the movie, I just have to say thank you to everyone seeing it. And it's in 50 theaters in 24 states. We're doing more in Florida, more in Alaska. One of my sons saw it recently and said, I said, what did you think? He said, Dan, it was like a memorial service for you. Oh, no. I find it has such hope.
Well, other people have said it's uplifting and it's hopeful, but he... Well, I think everyone should see it. TheLastClassFilm.com is where you go to see where it's showing and it is not a memorial site.
What is that? Can you give us that site again? Of course I can give you the URL again. TheLastClassFilm.com, which is also, this has not been announced yet, we are going to be doing a live watch-along of The Last Class Film. You and I are going to be watching it together. We might invite some other people. I don't know, we'll see. People are going to be able to watch us watch it.
Yeah, but it's so fun. This is what the kids do, watch-alongs. So we'll do it, and because we want people to be able to see the film and help get their friends into theaters, it is going in all of these independent theaters. Tucson sold out 370 seats. This is unbelievable, but I just have a question. When people watch us watch the film, are they going to be able to see the film?
Yeah, of course. Do you think Michael would do it any other way? So what happens is we talk at the beginning. We have some popcorn. Then we watch the movie. Maybe we cut to us just twice watching the movie, crying, laughing, choking on our popcorn. And then we do a Q&A afterwards. So this is August 12th. It is going to be Tuesday, August 12th, 5 p.m. Pacific, 8 p.m. Eastern.
Anybody can do it. Yep. And we're gonna say pay what you will. It's zero dollars. If you want to just watch it for zero, you can chip in to help support the distribution of the film if you like. And we'll be announcing it soon. So sign up at thelastclassfilm.com. We'll also say the URL for it, the website for it, nextclutch, because we have time before the next clutch, because we do these weekly. We should do the last clutch.
No, I want to do the first of many clutches. But we could have a film, The Last Clutch, if we ever have a last clutch. There's too much to cover. There is too much. But with the tariffs and the coffee, it's going to be harder to clutch, but we won't stop. It is import taxes.
But I'm not going to flog this book. No, but I'm going to flog the movie. Coming up short. I'll put it back. Don't tell anyone I took it out of the shelf. No, no, but it's not actually – that copy is just a – That's the paperback galley. It's a galley, yeah. But there is so much more to talk about.
There really is. And the irony is that your movie and this memoir are coming out, or have been coming out, just at the time when so many people, so many of you out there, understandably, are just so upset. And you have every right to be upset. And I'm upset. And Heather, you're upset.
We started talking when we started this particular clutch today about how
This fascist Trump regime is making us all, all, I think including many Republicans, feel that something is fundamentally wrong. It's immoral what's happening. It violates all the ideas and ideals that we accepted and took for granted.
That is so disorienting. It is so disorienting. It's so heavy. But let me just say this. I want to thank you. And I want to thank you. Thank you. Thank you. And Michael Lohannes Calderon, thank you. Three cheers. But let me also thank all of you. Because despite being so disoriented and upset and despairing, and I know many of you are,
You also are maintaining your sense of hope and your sense that we will get out of this, we will emerge. And I think when I mentioned a moment ago about we had taken all of this for granted, we had taken the rule of law for granted, we had taken democracy for granted, we had taken much that we
had been born into in America and the world for granted.
The word of hope that I want to leave you with is that we will no longer be taking it for granted. We see what happens when we become so indifferent to it, we don't see it, we don't appreciate it, that we allow somebody like Donald Trump to take over in every respect and become a personal fascist, authoritarian, monarch,
instead of a president. And I do believe that that recognition, that understanding of how important the Constitution and the rule of law and democracy are to us will be something that we will not forget, our children will not forget, their children who are now, for some of us, we have grandchildren, they will not forget.
In fact, it lays the foundation for a stronger democracy and a stronger America that respects the rule of law and also seeks social justice. So let me thank you again, and on that note, have a good week.