All right, Chris, if you'd like to start. Okay, good. Let me just get this thing open up. One second. Oh, there it is. Okay, good. All right. Let me just get in front and center. Fantastic. All right. This meeting will come to order. Pam would like to do a roll call just to see who is here.
So if we could have, uh, just everybody say, say their name and present or such if they're here and I'll start off with, uh, Chris Grandy. I am present. Thanks Connie. Nikki Gregory and Pamela Kelly. John Elaine Hickey. Okay.
Okay, great. We have a we have a quorum, right, Pam? Yes, we do. Yes, we do. Great. Let's let's get rolling with let's start off here. And let's start with the meeting and minutes of the previous meeting. Do anybody have any comments about the minutes of the previous meeting? make a motion to accept the minutes of the February second motion. All those in favor?
Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye.
All those in favor? Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye
Peter and his team have assisted nearly 100 people to date complete their tax forms. The last date for appointments will be Thursday, April 6th. We will continue to receive telephone inquiries for appointments, which are no longer available. And we just continue to add them to the wait list. After April 6th, we will be back in our own mini library at the senior center for our future board meetings.
We celebrated a very special birthday at bingo on March 1st for Connie Spinelli, who turned 103 years old. We celebrated with a cake, singing happy birthday. The mayor presented a certificate and gifts to Connie as well. It was a joyous bingo. A quick summary of our numbers for the month of February, 2023.
Our daily attendance has averaged 161 unduplicated participants per day at the Senior Center in the month of February. This is a 4% increase from January.
Our bi-monthly food pantry continues to be well attended in February. 149 filled grocery bags were handed out to Medford seniors. Bags consist of a protein, produce items, canned goods, rice, pasta, cereal. Bags on average contain 10 different items.
Our daily lunch program served 527 congregate meals and handed out 475 grab and go meals in 18 days. Grace Albert continues to outreach for new Medford residents to assist with volunteering. During February, 37 volunteers worked and provided 597 hours of service for the senior center.
During the month of February, we captured how many people drive to our center and require parking daily. 718 people in 18 days drove to the senior center. That is a duplicated number. That is an average of 40 cars per day that require parking at the senior center.
I completed a two-day Zoom workshop on race, equity, and inclusion, sponsored by the Executive Office of Elder Affairs and Massachusetts Council on Aging. We have recently put together our request for funding for FY24, which will begin on July 1st of 2023. We don't have any funds guaranteed yet, but we are currently requesting the CDBG fiscal year 24
of 30 that should be $37,000 has been requested. And that is under federal funds. Municipal the initial request is $255,495 for the city.
And the state, our fiscal year 24 has been requested of $167,400. I will keep the city, I'm sorry, the council board apprised to when our meetings are held into what they will lock in with. I do, hold on one second, Tom Coloner is calling us. I'm gonna put it on hold for a moment, sorry. Hi, Tom, are you having a hard time getting on?
Okay, do you remember how to get into Zoom? I can give you the link, the numbers. It's 852-997-01673. And yes, that's the meeting ID number, okay?
Okay, if you have any problems, just call the office and ask Suzanne to walk you through. Right, right, because she doesn't have the link, but she should be able to lock, yes, okay. Okay, thank you, bye-bye. Okay.
I'm sorry about the interruption. All right, continuing on the funding, the meetings will start to be held between the end of March, April and into May. And I will keep the board apprised to the outcomes for these budgets as they are an important role to how the Council on Aging does run. Now I would like to welcome our newest staff member,
Her name is Nikki Gregory, and Nikki started with the Senior Center as our part-time social worker last Monday, March 6th. And welcome, Nikki, please. Thank you. Glad to have you on board. Very glad to be on board. Hello. All right. Nikki, can you tell the board a little bit about your history and what you're expecting for the Senior Center and going forward?
Sure. So I, let's see, I have my undergraduate and master's degree in social work. I am a licensed clinical social worker with the state of Massachusetts and New Hampshire. I also interestingly have my certification in animal assisted therapy and activities as well. So that's kind of fun and one of my interests. I've been practicing social work, both clinical, so like therapy, social work, as well as case management,
since 2001, and I just, oh, siren's going by. For the last 15 years, I've been working as the director of an outpatient counseling center in downtown Boston, and really enjoyed that, but recently wanted to work in the city that I live in, which is Medford. So yeah, I'll be here at the senior center part-time.
I think that one of my visions is just simply to let every single person who walks through the door of the senior center, if possible, know that they are seen by me, that they are offered services, and that their presence there is so important. And I'm just wanting to make myself as available as possible within the hours that I work there.
to help as many people access services in the greater community and also to provide direct services as needed in my office. So I'm really looking forward to working with everyone and I've received such, thank you, such a warm welcome so far. It's been wonderful. Thank you. And there is Tom. Thank you, Tom. We can see you. I think his audio is still connecting,
Wonderful. Good to have you, Tom. All right. So that is the director's report. Any other questions or comments? All those in favor? Aye.
Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye.
All right, so I'm not sure if many of you have heard, but the government, the federal government is trying to get the word out. If you are on MassHealth, you should be expecting a blue letter in the mail. And we're trying to make sure everybody's well-informed that they cannot, do not ignore that letter. We've posted it in the newsletter as well. For the past three years, MassHealth has been auto renewed because of COVID.
This round, people that are on MassHealth must complete the redetermination process, or they could lose their benefits. So actually, I believe Iki is going to be hopefully attending a seminar to teach how to help our participants if they need help, because the MassHealth forms are not easy to maneuver around.
So the redetermination letters and the paperwork is going to be excessive because you're going to have three years of people that are all going to have to get their paperwork in on time. So if you, yourself, a family member or neighbor talks about MassHealth and receiving a packet in the mail, it will be a blue letter and it's really going to stand out. Tell them do not ignore it.
And if they need assistance to either stop by the senior center or give Nikki a call to set up an appointment, it's important. We cannot have people fall between the cracks and lose out on their mass health insurance. So that is what EOEA has been asking the council on aging to really step up and assist with at this time. Okay, great. Thanks Pam.
In legislative report. Yes, so the governor's initial budget release for FYI 24 governor Healy has included the $14 per elder request that the Massachusetts Council on aging has put forward.
So she did include that in her initial budget. And Governor Healey also in her budget funds a tax relief package of $742 million. And one of the big assists for seniors is the senior circuit breaker credit, which will double the maximum allowed.
So we're hoping that that stays in not only the $14 per elder because that'll help the senior center with our budget, but also that this tax relief package.
goes forward and is approved because that will help so many. The house voted to permit remote and hybrid meeting options through March 31st, 2025. So they're giving us two more years to offer this hybrid virtual meeting option, which as we can see, helps out. We have three people that have joined us
virtually. So we have two more years of offering this service. Not clear when the Senate will vote on it. So it hasn't, it has gone through the House, but it hasn't passed the Senate yet. So, but that is what I have for the legislative at this time. Okay, great. Anybody? Tom, anything on your end you've seen for related to seniors and legal matters that
would be related to legislative or any kind of department initiatives? Well, the only, I'm usually watching out for scams and something that's been advertised on TV and things like that, the news has been, the scam that's been going around for a while, now it's becoming more prominent. Elderly people getting called that their grandson or granddaughter is being arrested or needs bail money.
And a lot of people are falling for that. It's like a billion dollar industry. So if there's some way to spread the word on almost a weekly basis to people just to be careful of that, to contact their relatives if they get a call from someone asking for money in a situation like that.
Absolutely. It's unfortunate that the scams are getting more elaborate and affecting more of our senior participants. Actually, one of my next projects is to work in getting the Attorney General's office, the Sheriff's office, the local Medford Police Department, and others to come and do a very large scam seminar presentation for our participants.
I'm hoping that by the summer, we can pull it together or even early fall. We're always having like the smaller banks come in and offer about protecting yourself with your banking issues, because that is another way that our seniors are being affected. So if anybody sees any great information, I'm very happy to add it into our newsletter, as well as put it on flyers and posters throughout the center.
Just when you think you know how to protect yourself, they come up with something new to worm their way in to our population. Excuse me, Pam. Yes. What they're doing now is they're checking Facebook and TikTok to pick up the voices of kids, grandkids, and they're locating and they're able to reproduce that voice. And it sounds just like the voice of your grandson or your granddaughter.
So yeah, the technology is ridiculous now. Yeah. What we try to tell people is try to stay calm, tell that person you'll call them back, get a number because as soon as you try to get a number, they'll hang up. And second, just take the time to call your family member, make that call, call your family member because nine times out of 10, they're going to answer the phone and be like, what? So that's important.
Yeah. These guys are professionals. It's not design amateur with technology.
often in foreign countries with whole call centers and multiple levels of management. It's pretty ornate when they get good at this stuff. Anyway, okay, so any- One other thing, Chris, I'm sorry, Chris. One other thing that happens when unfortunately somebody is scammed, they're embarrassed and they don't report it.
And because of the lack of reporting, it can continue. So we try to tell people, you know, even if it happens, you have to report it because then the police will know, how did they get you? You know, did they come through your phone number? Did they mail you something? Did they come through your email? But it's important to tell people, don't be embarrassed. They're professionals, like you said. They are professionals and they're gonna find their way to get their money from you. Not their money, but your money from, you know,
from you. So getting the word out and talking about it more is important for us. No, no, that's important. Great. Well, thanks guys. Any, any old business? Yes. So as everybody knows, we med pet lot fee passed away.
And we ordered as a memorial for him, a gold leaf to be added to our tree of hope at the senior center. And I did bring it and I'll try to put it up to the camera to show everybody then I'll pass it around. We had all agreed a month or so ago to add to his leaf.
Valued COA member, Medhat Lotfi, a true gentleman. And I really, I'm gonna try to get this up as close as possible. I don't know if you can read it, but it came out really nice. So when I bring this back, we're going to have our handyman add it to the tree of hope so that everybody can see it when they come in. I'll also send a letter to his family to let them know
that it is then added to the tray. And just going back to Med, that is a loss of a person on our board. So we do have an open seat. So I'd love for the board members to think about who they know that may want to fill a seat.
Um, I have been tickling some people, so it's, Oh, thank you, Chris. Not successfully yet, but I do, I do know some people around town that, uh, we know would be, would be good community members, but, uh, so far, so far, no takers. So, okay. I understand it. It is, it is a commitment and, um, you know, not too much of a commitment in our, they might think it's more than, yeah, they might think it's more than what it is. It's, it's actually, it can be a lot of fun and it's just making sure that, you know, you understand.
I'm doing nefarious things so we're you know that's the job of the board and I think it's it's I don't think they realize how enjoyable, it can be, but I'm trying to convey that but who knows.
Maybe people don't like commitments these days. We talked about it. I remember talking about it for years at the board meetings of declining memberships and things like Elks Clubs and stuff like that. So it's just the idea of people wanting to commit to anything is tough. So you just got to break through that first line of resistance to get people to realize it's not a problem. Thank you.
Joy has not made it on to the meeting yet, but I wanted to thank joya in the Tufts health medicine. As we spoke about Sarah, the Medford go to health nurse has left her position, and she was a weekly blood pressure nurse facilitator at the senior center. So that
was a big loss to us, but Joya has a Tufts Health medicine nurse who will be coming in. Unfortunately, it's only once a month, but I'd rather have somebody once a month than nothing at all to offer a blood pressure clinic. And actually today is her first day. She'll be at the center from 2 p.m. to 3 p.m. the third Thursday of the month offering blood pressure checks. And also if anybody has any questions about other nursing needs.
We welcome her and I continue to look for another nurse to offer blood pressure clinics on another day as well. The other old business I have, Shirley, you inquired last month about line dancing instructors because our previous line dancer instructor retired. I have three potential people that I'm going to call in,
see if their schedules are available to add the Medford Senior Center as a
new line dancing facilitator for us. And hopefully in the next month or so. Now that I have Niki here, that was a missing link to our staff. We'll go on to exercise and other openings that we're looking to fill. You're welcome. Excuse me, I have a lead on another nurse who might want to do blood pressure. Wonderful. So I'll follow up with you when we get back to the center. She might be interested in it. Excellent, thank you.
Yes, I will. Anybody can do blood pressure. Yeah. Yeah, it's just their time. And I know like, we used to have nurses from like the visiting nurses that would come in and offer once a week.
but their staffing is so short right now that they can't give somebody, because we're not paying them, they're doing it as a volunteer opportunity. So I can't expect them to take a nurse from their schedule to just have them come over, but we are looking. I'm also working with Sandy Savini from the Medford Vocational School Health Program, and she's going to have her students come in
on most Wednesday afternoons from like one to 2 p.m. where they'll practice their blood pressure and other social engagement with our seniors. So I'm working with Sandy because the schedule sometimes of getting the students to the senior center can be difficult. They don't always have transportation. Wednesday is one to two. So it is, right, it is during bingo.
Right, right. So we're working on different avenues to fill that gap as well. So that's my old business. I don't know if anybody else has any old business to add to the... Not I. Any new business? Yes, actually, we do have some new business I'd like to talk about. So Medford is,
going on to their next phase of transforming the square with parking lots A, B, and C. I'm gonna have Nikki pass around this little flyer.
Okay, thank you Nikki, which shows those parking lots, A, B and C, and where the senior center is located, where the city is going to hold an open house on March 30, which is
uh is it two no it's thursday it's thursday from 1 30 to 3 30 at the senior center and at the open house they're going to talk about the development that is the future of lots a b and c there is nothing that has been defined yet however
something will be done on at least one or two or possibly all three of those lots and it will affect the senior center as we know. So I'm really trying to get the word out for as many people as possible to attend these public meetings
so that you understand and the city understands how important it is for us not to lose those parking spots and not to diminish all of the people that come to the senior center. As I spoke about in my director's notes, we do check every day of how many people drive to the center.
and how many spots have to be utilized. And on average, we do have 40 spots a day that are needed. Now, granted, not everybody stays from 8.30 in the morning till four in the afternoon, but people are coming in and out all day. For example, tomorrow, we're hosting our St. Patrick's Day party, and we will have 100 people attending the party.
And we do average 40 to 50 people that will drive themselves to the center. So those are parking spots, basically, that are going to be taken from 11am till 3pm straight through because the event goes that long. So this is my concern.
As the city moves forward so open house March 30 from 130 to 330 at the senior center, and then another they're calling it office hours on Tuesday, April 4 from one to 3pm so I did put that on the copy of the flyer.
And for those that were unable to attend in person, I can forward this information to your email, and Donna, I can give you a copy of everything when you come in. Are you coming later on this afternoon? I may, yes. I could get it from you, Pam. I'll get it from you. Okay, absolutely. Thank you. Because I think it's important, especially as a board, that we stand together in what we need and make sure that the senior center
not forgotten about. Okay. So that is one of my new businesses. And actually, for me, that is probably my most important business that I want to continue on our top priority as a board going forward. Anybody else have new business? Thanks, Pam. That's a that's good stuff. Yeah, parking, obviously. And so the
And from what you're seeing, Pam, you mentioned last time, they're going to significantly reduce parking. Or is it more just a lot that's closest to the senior center you're worried about?
Well, of course, the lot that's closest to the senior center, I'm worried about. Lot A is the one that's directly across the street where we have parking along the fence line that curves around and then goes on to Riverside. I think we only have 20 spots over there. Ticketing, we have a parking department and they do promote ticketing, so yes.
We have, if you have a sticker and you're parked along the fence line for the senior center, or if you have the city-wide sticker, you do not get a ticket. But if people don't have those appropriate stickers, you could get a $25 parking ticket. We don't want our seniors to get parking tickets. So lot A, there's several different options. And just to give you a quick,
quick breakdown. This project is still is in the very early stages of transforming the square, and they're still seeking to advance the vision of a connected accessible vibrant and resilient Medford square set by the community.
At the end of this project. The city expects to prepare a request for for proposals and RFP for the redevelopment of up to three city parking lots that reflects the community's goals and priorities established through this process. So,
Again, they're still at the very early stages of transforming the square, but this is the three spots that they're looking to engage and transform as their starting point. So again, it will affect the senior center. And as we have talked about many times,
our senior community is growing and will continue to grow. From the 2020, from the 2010 census to the 2020 census, Medford itself grew by almost 20%. We went from 11,000 seniors that are aged 60 years of age or older up to over 13,000 seniors
I think it's 13,490. I don't know the exact number, but it's 13,490 seniors aged 60 years of age and older. And that will continue to climb every 10 years. Longevity of life and more people staying in the community, which is a great thing. And we're a small building, so
We are a small building, but we do quite a lot for many of those people.
DM, it sounds like we need protesting. I won't go that far, but I want them to know that we want to work with them. We want to work with the development project on developing the square, but how do we do it so that we're not losing parking, that we're not losing the accessibility for the senior center? Because as we know,
Not only will they drive off, Shirley, but people don't live in those two housing units, those two senior housing units. We have everybody sitting here today. Not one of you live in those housing units. So you all drive in from other locations. So that just shows, you know, our reach is throughout the whole city. And we want to continue that. And we don't want to
have people feel isolated or left out because they can't get to us. No, the Hyatt only owns one portion of that parking lot. The rest is city owned. So that's a very weird shape.
So I was on a meeting the other night, the other afternoon, and they talked about the possibilities of different projects that may, and again, I say may, become options for lot A, B, and C. Lot C, the person said, because of its shape, that may end up being more like a garage possibly, because they wouldn't put housing there, because it abuts 93.
And who would want to live in a building that abuts 93? Although we do have 121 Riverside that abuts 93. So I don't see that happening. And lot B and A, they're looking at a possibility of a structure that could go up to five stories with one or two stories being parking, with shopping on the street level, and then residential above it.
That's another topic that they're discussing. So we don't know. It's still, again, very early stages. But again, they are looking to do development on those three sites to bring opportunity to the square and to the riverfront area. This will be a multiple year project.
You would think that the senior center would be first and foremost, you know, grandfathered to a certain amount of spaces, I mean. Well, that is true. They are keeping us in every meeting that I've been on that has been one of the requirements they do tell me that it will
made known that the senior center must have X amount of spots. It's just where are those spots going to be located? Will it be accessible enough for our seniors to drive into? Will it, you know, they still have the ease of just walking across the street from the parking lot over to the building. Those are concerns that we will all have, of course.
Well, I don't know if you heard that but Mary just said maybe the city should build a new senior center. Well, yes, that right the with the where is the problem. So still have accessibility for everybody. I agree with you, Mary, and
you know, unless somebody leaves a very large endowment to us, I don't know if that could come to fruition in the next 10 to 15 years. The bottom line, PM, is we should get at least the spots that we have, but we really need more. I agree. I agree. Donna, that's a great,
You know, nothing less. Right, don't change it and give us less or make it more difficult. We should have the same accessibility for what we have now. We shouldn't lose out on the long run, as they say, right? Because, yeah, and even that crosswalk, I mean, you know how the cars speed through there and stuff. You really, you know, I mean, it's a quick change in light.
but still you have to, you know, have you aware, you know, you have to know what you're doing. That is true. I agree with you on that Donna, but we'll have to, one step at a time as they say, right? Right, right. Okay. I guess that brings us to announcements.
Well, I have a couple of quick announcements myself. Our friends group, MSCI, Medford Senior Citizens Incorporated, will have their yearly scholarship applications, again, to all the schools with Medford seniors in them. So that would be the Medford High School, Medford Folk, Arlington Catholic, Malden Catholic, the Charter School,
they'll be handing out $1,000 in June to one student who is going to continue their education in the medical field. So I have those applications and we can send them out online as well. If anybody has anybody interested, they can have them contact MSCI to fill out the scholarship. It's a great opportunity for somebody continuing their medical field.
As I did speak about earlier, our annual St. Patrick's Day party will be held tomorrow. We're going to have our luncheon catered by Kelly's with corned beef sandwiches and coleslaw and pickles and chips and dessert. Entertainment will be by Big Smile. We'll have some door prizes donated, and we're very excited to have over 100 people in attendance for the event.
You can talk to Grace about that. Grace does the party events and yes, sometimes we give out little gift baskets, door prizes, things like that. So yeah. Pam, can Italians go? I would want her to go, but I figured I wouldn't be able to get a ticket.
Well, Tom, do you want to dress in green tomorrow? You can dress in green and be Tom. The big leprechaun. Tom Kalani. Tom Kalani. Tom Kalani. I love it.
With the Boston accent it probably sounds like that sometimes. Yeah, that's true too. We have, we have a lot of events that will be coming up for the April, May, June right through the summer.
great opportunity with entertainers. So even beyond our annual parties or monthly parties, Grace has entertainers that are just going to pop in on Fridays to entertain us. We have an acapella group that's coming in from Tufts University that will be singing during lunch one afternoon. So you have to look at our newsletters and make sure that people understand we
have so much going on and so many different opportunities for people to enjoy themselves and socialize. And of course, with Nikki, our new social worker, great resources and information to keep people living in their homes safely and comfortably. That's our goal. No, our seamstress retired and we don't have anybody else. It's hard to find anybody.
Yes, she was Friday afternoons because she lived nearby. But when COVID hit, or even right before COVID, she moved in with family members up in the North Shore area. So it was too much of a drive back and forth to come down for an hour. But if anybody knows a seamstress that would like to stop in and offer their services, it was a great opportunity for many people.
Anybody else have announcements that they'd like to share with the board? Okay, well, there being no further business, the meeting is adjourned. And we will meet next month on April 20th at 10 a.m., back at the senior center, right? That's correct, back at the senior center. Okay, great. Thank you all. We're so happy to have you. Thanks for coming, everybody.
Have a great day. Thank you all. Thank you. Thank you. Bye now. Bye bye.