Yeah. I had to have Paul have the cleaners, because they spent literally four hours in there cleaning the gas. Justin, can you hear me? Yes. Yeah, I can hear you. All right, great. All right, how does this thing work? You ready? Yeah, I'm just trying to. Yeah, how does. So you would just in a. Oh, yeah, Mike is six, right?
All right, cool. Just keep our mics on for this. All right, Jim, you ready? There will be a meeting of the Medford City Council of Resident Services and Public Engagement Committee. Mr. Clerk, when you're ready, please call the roll.
Councilor Azarro. Councilor Azarro is absent. Councilor Scapelli. Councilor Scapelli is absent. Councilor Singh. Present. And Chairman Lemming. Present. Three present, two absent. We have a quorum. Committee.
It's called order. Only thing that we're going to be discussing today is the draft of the Medford City Council newsletter. Councillor Sang. Thank you. Thanks for putting this together. My main note is just to add one more item to general business about the trash. Yeah. Can you hear me now?
Yeah, just repeat what you just said, sorry. Yeah, so my main thing is just, my main suggestion is just to add one more point to the general business section. I can paste in draft language in the chat, but basically just about the trash resolution that we passed as a council. Right.
Yeah, let me let me paste that into the chat and read it out for you guys. I just need to make sure I have the correct date for it. Okay.
At the November 18th meeting, the City Council passed a resolution. Oh, I forgot to take out the word detailed. Passed a resolution responding to the administration's plan to shift to bi-weekly trash collection as part of the Zero Waste Initiative.
Noting significant resident concerns that unanswered questions about the fees of or we can also just have for that language a little bit, but noting significant resident concerns. The council formally requested clear public communication, comprehensive reports on operational.
public health and equity implications, and a public forum to gather community input. The resolution also urged the administration to evaluate alternative waste reduction strategies, outline a mitigation plan for potential negative effects, including rodent issues, and explain how services will be sustained once the $200,000 grant expires. And we can just edit it down a little bit. I know that's a little long. Yeah. Okay.
Yeah I mean I think we can cut like and answer questions about feasibility and impacts of the proposal. I know administration has been working on that. Okay. What about.
I'm going to shift to my weekly trash collection.
OK, that's still still a bit of a lengthy. Meeting but. It's not as lengthy as some of the other some of the other things on there, so I think it's acceptable.
So the, what I just proposed and what I just tried to edit it down to was the November 18th meeting, the city council passed a resolution responding to the administration's plan to shift to biweekly trash collection. The council formally requested clear public communication, comprehensive reports on operational public health and equity implementations in a public forum to gather community input. The resolution also urged the administration to evaluate alternative waste reduction strategy and explain how services will be sustained once the $200,000 grant expires.
And feel free, Councilor Callahan or Councilor Sang to just speak up since it's only the three of us. Yeah, I think it looks fine too. Okay, cool. Thank you. And I'll also note that I didn't, this was originally drafted by Council Vice President Collins and I didn't
I realized that when I was adding items to it, that occurred since she passed me this draft. I didn't go through all of the regular meetings, commemorations and acknowledgements. So I would request when we do pass this, that you just give me a, like, let me just include whatever other commemorations and acknowledgements we had since that I may have failed to put into this current draft. That sounds great by me.
Okay. Beyond that, does anybody else have any, do either of y'all have any other concerns, comments, questions, edits? Should we put in a point about the committee, the whole that we had yesterday? I don't think I saw that on here. Yeah.
I'll just write something.
It was the Roberts School, right? Glenn. Yeah. Glenn.
Okay, I don't love this language, but if anybody has any other suggestions. At the December 9th Committee of the Whole, the Council heard a presentation on a plan to put solar panels on the McGlynn in preparation for potentially approving a 20-year contract with, what was it called? Okay. Yeah.
At the December 9th Committee of the Whole, the council heard a presentation on a plan to put solar panels on the McGlynn School in preparation for potentially approving a 20-year contract with Select Solar. Does anybody else have any suggestions for? Yeah, I would just add in the power purchase agreement to purchase electricities produced by said installation. Wait, sorry. Can you repeat that just word for word?
I'm just taking it directly from the text that we got. Let me just paste it in the chat. Yeah, yeah. So I would just add in the power purchase agreement. And if there's a good way to
combine this information from the slides.
December 9th committee, the whole council heard a presentation on a plan to authorize the city to enter into a 20 year lease agreement to allow for installation of solar photo. They lick PV on the McGlynn school roof, as well as a power purchase agreement to purchase electricity produced by said installation, uh, installation of solar photo. I think you could probably just say solar panels. Yeah.
I added some information in the chat that might be helpful for residents. There might be a way to synthesize it shorter. Just the last three messages I sent, I think those would answer some questions that residents might have.
about this. I'm seeing your notes. I feel like that gets a little bit too into the weeds for a newsletter. I could link to the documents. Yeah, if you could link to the documents. Yeah, some of this also assumes that we will agree to the contract extension. And it says installation will start fall 2026. I mean, yeah. I was thinking you added the word would. I mean, it's all hypothetical.
But yeah, I mean, I wasn't saying that you should copy and paste. I think we would have to say would. But yeah, if you could just link it, I think that'd be helpful. Yeah, I haven't had time to, yep. Yeah, and maybe if you could just add in that, like, we did requests more information ahead of the, like, yeah.
And that's for next week's December 16th meeting? Yes. Okay. How about this? That works. Okay. Cool. Okay. Anybody else have any other suggestions for this? Do we have any motions on the floor?
Motion to approve with the, allowing you to add any of the commemorations. Do we have a second? Second. On the motion to approve with the caveat that I'm allowed to add in the additional commemorations and acknowledgements. Mr. Clerk, when you're ready, please call the roll.
Councilor Callahan? Yes. Councilor Singh? Yes. Chair Lemmon? Yes. Three approved, two absent. The motion passes. Do we have any other motions? Motion to adjourn. On the motion to adjourn, do we have a second? Second. On the motion to adjourn by Councilor Singh, seconded by Councilor Callahan. Mr. Clerk, when you're ready, please call the roll.
Councilor Callahan? Yes. Councilor Singh? Yes. And Chair Lemme? Yes. Three yeses, two absences, a motion to adjourn passes and the meeting is adjourned. Thanks guys. Thanks.