All right, it's enough for me.
I am going to go ahead and pass this on to a voter in the district, Mr. Greg Nadeau.
Hi, everyone.
My name's Greg.
And 30 years ago, I was legislative aide, campaign manager, then legislative aide for a state rep.
Worked in the statehouse and observed firsthand how the concentration of power in both branches really prevented progressive legislation from moving forward.
In recent years, I've been pleasantly seeing that the State Senate, ever since Stan Rosenberg has been president, has improved substantially, but the House really hasn't.
And so I've been saying for a number of years that you cannot be a progressive and vote for the Speaker.
And no matter how many times progressive legislators say that they co-sponsor wonderful things, vote the right way,
The only vote that matters is the vote that prevents all progressive legislation from continuing, and that is the vote for the speaker.
So, I got a phone call from one of you, I'm not forgetting whom.
Someone can identify themselves who called me and I was driving along doing some errands and said, voting for Anna Callahan or support Anna Callahan.
And I said, no, I'm with Christine.
You know, Christine is a great rep.
She's my favorite in the delegation.
You know, I like her very much.
I think she's smart.
I think she's got integrity, blah, blah, blah.
And then, then I just sort of had this pause of like, well, wait a second, you know, from the message that the person said about reforming state house.
I said, well, okay, well, I'll come to a house party, went to a house, you know, attended a house party, um, ask some questions.
Um, my son, Max, um, was also there and, um, really, you actually grilled me.
Which was late.
Well, you've completely passed.
And then I said I would, and I did talk to Christine a couple of days after that.
And Christine did not respond with a firm commitment to oppose the speaker and to dilute the concentration of power in the House that prevents all progressive legislation from falling.
So I said that I would now be shifting my support.
So here I am, happy to be involved.
I'm pretty involved in Somerville in a lot of ways.
I've been here for 20 years.
definitely know every city councilor and school committee member and mayor and everyone else very, very well and tend to talk to all of them and say, look, either you're with the speaker or you're with progressive causes.
There's no in between.
It's like racism.
You cannot be neutral on racism.
Either you're actively opposing racism or you are part of the status quo that is perpetuating.
And so everyone who is supporting Christine is fundamentally supporting a status quo as preventing climate change, racial justice, and everything else that we care about from progressing.