Hello, I'm Justin Tsang. I'm honored to serve as a voice for you on the City Council. Over the last four years, we've made record investments in our schools and streets, saving 40 teaching jobs and hiring a new road repair crew. We've made once-in-a-lifetime reforms to make housing more affordable and made City Hall the most transparent it's ever been. Even as towns around us are cutting basic services, we've made it a priority to invest in you.
But now, too many politicians are gambling with our economy and threatening our safety. The instability and fear they're sowing are trickling down, leaving it to us to pick up the pieces. Through these uncertain times, Medford needs steady hands and bold leadership. That's why I'm running for re-election, to keep standing up for who we are and to keep building a city that truly works for us all.
I'm the son of immigrants who came to Medford chasing the American dream. My parents stretched every dollar and raised me paycheck to paycheck. But my parents always made sure that I knew that it was our public schools, our neighbors, and this community that gave me so much. Our schools gave me the chance to attend Harvard University, where I've led policy commissions, and as a law student, I'm fighting for civil rights.
That's the story of Medford, a city where hardworking families supported by their community can make their dreams real. A city that knows diversity isn't just a slogan, it's our strength. But that diversity is at risk. From Wellington to West Medford, residents of all ages tell me they're feeling priced out and left behind. Rents keep rising and the dream of home ownership is slipping away.
Young people, my classmates, are moving to Central Mass in New Hampshire because they can't afford to stay. As someone with student loans and medical bills who hopes to buy a home here myself, I understand how hard it is. That's why I've worked to make Medford more affordable.
We've created an affordable housing trust, expanded the senior tax deferral, and strengthened rental protections. For the first time in 60 years, we passed major zoning reforms to remove barriers and require housing that's truly affordable.
We've already permitted hundreds of new affordable homes and laid the groundwork for vibrant mixed-use neighborhoods near transit. And soon, we'll see that same progress in Medford Square, with new shops, restaurants, and homes that will breathe life into the heart of our city while keeping parking accessible for seniors and theatergoers. We've come a long way, but the work isn't finished. The road ahead will demand tough decisions, but it's also one of opportunity. The opportunity to build consensus around our community's shared commitment to affordability.
The opportunity to hold big developers accountable through stronger linkage fees, community benefits, traffic management, historic preservation, and tree protections that build on the climate reforms we've already passed. The opportunity to create an affordable housing overlay, build safer streets, support small businesses, and grow our commercial tax base so we can better invest in city services.
The opportunity to bring City Hall to the people by giving residents more seats at the table and building upon my work to create City Council listening sessions and newsletters. These days, many of our neighbors live with fear. I worry for my parents and friends, and I even keep my passport card in my wallet in case someone ever questions my right to call this place home.
While some leaders are turning neighbors against each other, labeling immigrants as criminals, we're building a city that welcomes everyone. I was proud to pass welcoming city ordinances, ensuring Medford won't hand over our neighbors to federal or out-of-state officials, punishing them for who they are or the care they receive here. True safety starts with trust. Trust that residents can turn to the city without fear of discrimination or deportation.
Life is rocky enough. Our job is to smooth the path. We're fixing roads and sidewalks neglected for decades. We restored vital bus routes because getting to work or school safely shouldn't depend on owning a car. And our record investments in schools haven't just saved jobs. They're laying the foundation for more after-school and extracurricular opportunities. There's more to do, more roads to pave, more sidewalks to fix, and a high school to rebuild. But our brightest days are still ahead.
When I first ran four years ago, City Hall was a place where it felt like you had to know someone to get things done. The status quo wasn't working. Our schools suffered massive cuts. Medford is finally turning the page, and we can't afford to go backwards. Today's world is challenging, but this election is our chance to take control and turn progress into lasting momentum. It's been the honor of a lifetime to serve the city I've always called home. I've worked to give back and pay it forward, and I hope to earn your vote on November 4th.