Hello and welcome to the first ever season of Bedford Bites.
My name is Danielle, and along with being a mom and a social worker, I'm a resident of Medford and your host for this podcast.
My intention behind this podcast is to provide information bites about current events in Medford, as well as discussion of where to get the best bites to eat in town.
This podcast is beginning only weeks away from the city's municipal election.
Residents are voting on November 2nd for Mayor, City Council, and School Committee.
On future episodes, you may hear more from me about other topics, but for now, I'm going to let the candidates do a majority of the talking.
After this episode, you will see several interviews in your feed of some of the candidates that are running in the upcoming election.
If you have feedback about this episode, ideas for future podcasts, or businesses you want to be mentioned in the podcast, you can follow the link in the show notes or email me at medfordpod at gmail.com.
You can also follow the podcast on Instagram at medfordbytespodcast.
Hope you enjoy the interviews.