Testing, testing. Thank you. The first regular meeting of the Medford School Committee will come to order. It is January 13th, 2025. We have executive session at 5 p.m. and our regular meeting at or about 6 p.m.
This meeting is being recorded. The meeting can be viewed live on the Medford Public Schools YouTube channel, or through Medford Community Media on your local cable channel, Comcast channel nine, eight, or 22, and Verizon channel 43, 45, 47. Participants can log or call in by using the following Zoom link. The meeting ID is 971-0396-1191. Member Russo, if you could please call the roll. Bless you.
Present. Here. Member Ntapa. Here. Member Olopade. Present. Member Einfeld. Present. Member herself present. Mayor Longo Kern. Present. Seven present, zero absent. If we all may rise to salute the flag. I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America, and to the republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all. We have executive session.
Upon a motion to enter into executive session pursuant to Mass General Laws 30A, Section 21A.3, executive session of the Medford School Committee to conduct a strategy session on the basis that an open meeting may have a detrimental effect on the bargaining positions of the Medford School Committee.
Specifically, the Medford School Committee will be discussing ongoing collective bargaining negotiations, executive session pursuant to 30A, section 21.2, to conduct strategy in preparation with non-union personnel or contract negotiations with non-union personnel, our interim superintendent of schools. The Medford School Committee will convene in public session immediately following the conclusion of the executive session at approximately 6 p.m. Is there a motion to enter executive session?
by Member Olopade, seconded by? Second. Member Ntapa, roll call, please. Member Branley? Yes. Member Graham? Yes. Member Ntapa? Yes. Member Olopade? Yes. Member Rheinfeld? Yes. Member Rousseau, yes. Mayor Longo, current? Yes. Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative. We will enter executive session room 207.
member in Tapa. Thank you, Mayor. Um, so it came up the other day about possible conflict of interest due to some familial ties within the schools, especially since we are going into union MTA contract negotiations. I'm here to say that after talking with the lawyer of the day with the state, they have advised me that due to the severance of how far
We are in terms of, you know, being family that and because there's no financial gain on my end. The only thing I have to do is file disclosure of appearance of conflict of interest as required by general law 26 a section 23 b3.
And I basically just have to file that that's been filed with the city clerk and I just have to read this on the floor and then we're fine. But I do not have to abstain from union negotiations with the MTA. This is just the thing I have to do in order to actually be a voting member when it comes to that. So it's basically, this is on file with the city clerk, but I basically am just an in-law relative to Ms. Jacqueline Gatto, the teacher at the Brooks Elementary.
I'm a second cousin or first cousin removed. I'm not really sure to miss Nicole Sulo, teacher at the books elementary. I'm also technically a member of the math teachers association, but I'm in the association of professional administrators, which at the state level. So there's a completely different subgroup than the MTA Medford teachers association. My union gets no financial gain from any, you know, negotiations that happen between the city and the teachers. So we've read this on the floor. I'm fine to continue, but just wanted it in record.
Um, and if people want to see the full thing, they can contact the city clerk, but thank you. Thank you. Member Antapa. So noted.
Okay. Dr. Cushing, do we have any student reps?
Oh, that's right. Sierra Isbell, thank you for joining us. That's our student rep for the evening. Thank you for your patience as we finished up an executive session. Is there a motion on the floor to approve the contract for our interim superintendent? By member Olapare, seconded by? I'll second. Member Brandley, roll call, please.
Who first and seconded it? Member Olopade and Member Branley seconded it. Thank you. Member Branley? Yes. Member Graham? Yes. Member Ntapa? Yes. Member Olopade? Yes. Member Reinfeldt? Yes. Member Russo? Yes. Mayor Longo Kern? Yes. Seven the affirmative, zero the negative. Paper passes. We have good of the order.
which is our fourth item on the agenda. Hearing and seeing none, we have our consent agenda, which is approval of bills and payrolls, approval of capital purchases, approval of grants, approval of field trips. One field trip is Dartmouth Model UN Conference, which is April 4th through the 6th, 2025, and approval of the regular meeting minutes from December 16th, 2024. Motion on the floor.
by Member Rousseau, seconded by Member Reinfeldt. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? The consent agenda is approved. We do not have any reports of subcommittees this week. We do have reports of our superintendent. First up is Dr. Edward Vincent's updates and comments. Turn it to you.
Good evening, everyone. For all those joining us tonight, at tonight's meeting, I hope everyone did have a wonderful holiday season and a joyous start to 2025.
We recognize there has been much excitement and curiosity within our Medford community since election day, when questions seven and eight were passed by the voters. We will use time during tonight's meeting to discuss the supplemental budget appropriation, and there are lots of exciting news and developments happening across the district.
This week, kindergarten enrollment, it began on January 2nd. Building Bridges to Kindergarten is happening this Wednesday, January 15th at 6.30 p.m. at Medford High School. Parents can register for kindergarten beforehand in the registration office, and the Medford Family Network is offering childcare during the event.
grade nine CTE students. They are set to choose their program. The students have explored all 15 CTE programs. They will choose their top three CTE programs or choose to take arts or technology electives for the rest of the year.
Principal Fallon is offering an informational Zoom this Thursday, January 16th at 6 p.m. All that information can be found online. Also this weekend, Sunday, January 19th is the sixth annual Tufts University Classic. The girls games will start at 12 noon and the boys, their game will start at 1.30 p.m.
It will be held in the cousins gymnasium at Tufts University. Also next week, Wednesday, January 22 at 7pm, there's going to be the fifth grade orchestra concert. It will take place at Medford High School, and the tickets are $5 at the door. So please come out to support those events.
As a reminder as well, this Wednesday, January 15th will be an early release day for all of our students. Middle schools are dismissed at 1130 a.m. and all other students are dismissed at noon. Additionally, Medford Public Schools will be closed on Monday, January 20th in observance of Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. Day.
Before we hear from Mr. McHugh on the supplemental budget appropriation I'd like to use this space to say thank you. As you all know this is my last school committee meeting in my role as superintendent and Friday is my last day serving in this position at large. These past few weeks have offered an opportunity to reflect on the past seven years.
Ultimately, what I keep coming back to is that the Medford Public Schools are in a better position academically, operationally, social, emotionally, and financially than we were when I joined in 2018.
Together we created the district's first ever strategic vision built on the ACES model of achievement, collaboration, equity, and support. The vision included district wide alignment on measurements of academic success, alignment on observational and evaluative feedback, and alignment on instructional practice.
culminating in the district's new instructional vision, which was presented to the school committee and all MPS staff last fall. Since I've started, we have hired seven new building principals across our eight schools who are each tremendous in not only what they do, but how they do it and how they treat people. A healthy school climate begins at the top.
and I am so appreciative and thankful for the work our building principals and district administrators have done to guide Mustang Nation to where it is today. When reflecting on the most unforeseen challenge any of us will ever experience, the COVID-19 pandemic, my mind races back to one of the most famous quotes and messages from Dr. King.
To me, his quote, the ultimate measure of a man is not where he stands in moments of comfort and convenience, but where he stands at times of challenge and controversy, speaks on how we approach the pandemic. We strived to not only meet the needs of all students, but we specifically championed to have our special education and English language students back in the classroom first.
I am immensely proud of the work I have done in this district, in collaboration with so many others, to champion the civil rights and freedoms of all of our students. I know that this work, along with the other wonderful events and goals happening in the district, will continue and grow under the leadership of Dr. Galluzzi.
Medford is a beautiful place to send your students to school. The work towards building a new Medford High School for the students in the city of Medford has only just begun. Tonight's agenda is reserved for explaining how we will use money from the city specifically earmarked to invest in education. Last but not least, the educators and staff in our school community
are all deeply passionate and committed to enhancing the lives of our students.
Throughout these past few days, I have visited our schools and seen our staff members in action. I'm happy to report they are, of course, doing a terrific job in visiting the schools, though I realized I am going to miss seeing pencils drop on the ground and the artwork that decorates classrooms. And yes, even at Medford High School, hearing the word bro 500 times in the hallway.
However, these past few days and weeks since the separation announcement was made has truly shown me that the district is in a good place. It's a tremendous place to work, to live, and even a better place for students to earn an education.
And so as I begin my final week and on the heels of Martin Luther King Jr. weekend, I hope I have championed the rights and educational opportunities in a way Dr. King would have been proud.
I believe all students have the right to an equal education across all of our schools through achievement, collaboration, equity, and support. I am honored to have worked in a community that strives and works towards those values. So in true Mustang fashion, I will share with you one final poem, the Mustang Alma Mater.
by the starry mystic waters flowing to the sea. Rise our hallowed halls of learning, rich in memory. Bold traditions, truth and honor, alien to all fears, sheltering our fond ambitions through the toiling years. As we now in contemplation view the scroll of time, hearts astir with recollections, wake in worlds sublime.
Sing of many sports triumphant, proms of courtly grace, deepening friendships without number, time cannot erase. In honor of final parting, this our prayer shall be, guide our strivings, broaden vision,
ordain victory. Thus united, firm in purpose, resolute in might, stand we now in dedication to the truth and right. Hail to these our alma mater, long her praises sing, loyalties to proud traditions we in honor bring. As her stalwart sons and daughters hold fond memories bright,
Join we now united voices to the blue and white. I thank you again and I am forever grateful for this opportunity to have served this wonderful city for seven years and I too am Medford. Thank you.
Thank you, Dr. Edward Benson, and hopefully anybody that is going to be around will stick around at the end. We're going to present you with a gift, and we have a cake to thank you for all you've done over the last seven years. We have our report on the implementation of the budget reductions included in the 2024-2025 annual school budget. This will be presented by our budget analyst, Mr. Gerald McHugh. Welcome.
At the request of the school committee, a report was requested to summarize how we implemented the cuts that were adopted in the FY 25 budget. So you do have a copy of the report. I can go through it and summarize it.
If that's acceptable, or if you have questions. Okay, fine. So I tried to outline the various categories that we approached these reductions. In the elementary schools, we had originally proposed to reduce classroom teachers by five. Two of these positions were added back in the final budget.
as a result of an extra allocation of funds from the city for a net reduction of three. And these were basically designed to take into account low enrollment in certain classrooms.
In the middle school, we reduced two guidance counselor positions and one physical education position. The guidance counselors reductions were adopted in the final budget and the PE position was eliminated.
However, it was not ultimately reduced due to issues around seniority and bumping and couldn't be resolved before the beginning of school. So the decision was to go with that position for an additional year. And there'll be a proposal in the supplemental budget to fund that position in FY25.
At the high school, there was a proposal to reduce classroom teachers by six. Two of these positions were added back in the final budget for net reduction of four. Of these, three had become vacant.
during the course of the year were not replaced. One of the vocational program positions was reduced due to low enrollment and adjustments were made to teaching schedules in FY25 to make sure there was coverage in all classes. For administrators, the original proposal was to reduce the administrator ranks by
by six, four of these were restored in the final budget. Two positions coordinating finance and music were consolidated for one of the reductions, returning to a previous management structure. To implement this cut,
A district wide music teacher was hired to cover some elementary classrooms that the coordinator had covered, and also to take on the director responsibilities for the high school band.
Funding for this teaching position is included in the supplemental budget proposal. The other position that was eliminated was the director of professional learning and assessment. And this work was distributed among nine administrators for a total of $23,000 in stipends.
The distribution of that work was by design, so it wouldn't be burdensome on any one particular administrator. And one of those stipends is only through the end of this year and will not be carried into FY 26. For administrative assistance,
Seven positions were supposed to be eliminated. Some of these savings allowed us to convert two 10-month positions to 12-month positions and to create a position that was responsible for transportation.
And then we combined certain programs like health services was combined with the guidance program in terms of support. Multiple curriculum departments were handled by one individual instead of two.
And then there were four stipends, three stipends created to take on any work that could not be distributed to other administrative assistants. In the total of those stipends, there were three stipends for $950 each.
for a total of 28,050. And then of course, the school committee provided a early retirement program for administrative assistants, which was quite successful. And five individuals retired under that program. And that meant that we only had to make one layoff out of the administrative assistant ranks.
For nurses, we had proposed a reduction in nursing staff by four district-wide. One of these positions was added back in the final budget, and we are proposing to add back an additional nurse as part of the supplemental appropriation.
Other positions included five positions that were formally funded in the ESSA program, two literacy coaches, and three paraprofessional behavior specialists. These positions were not originally carried into FY25 under our initial budget proposal. And all these positions were added back in the final budget due to the additional city funding.
So I hope that provides you with the context you were interested in, and I'm happy to answer any questions on it. Thank you, Mr. McHugh. Member Graham? Thank you. Just one quick question or clarification. I believe the one administrative assistant who was laid off was pretty quickly recalled.
to fill an open position. Yes. Is that correct? Yes. And she declined. Okay. I just wanted to make sure that the committee knew that because it happened within like weeks of July one. So thank you.
Thank you, Member Graham. Member Reinfeld? Thank you for this overview. I think I was the one who initially wanted this report. And one thing that I don't see a lot of here and I imagine will be coming up in presumably that some of it is going to be addressed in the supplemental proposal. But part of the reason for this report was to inform the fiscal year 26
budgets, particularly around the impact on students. I know at the elementary level, it ended up tweaking some of the class sizes. Middle schools, I'm still concerned about the loss of the guidance counselors and bringing that back. I think I have a middle schooler I've seen
It's working, but I think we've lost some of the aspects of student support because these guidance counselors are spending their whole time teaching, and it's affecting also other classes in teaching. And so I'm hoping to see a little more information about the impact on the students.
Member Graham mentioned what was happening with the administrative assistance and the, you know, these stipends were, I talked to a few of the people who received the stipends to cover some of the responsibilities from the Director of Professional Learning and Assessment, and that seems to be working reasonably well. I'm curious where you see
needing to invest in fiscal year 26 for some of the less budgetary impacts, but the student experience.
Yeah, so first of all, this report just really addresses the cuts that were made. So over the course of the year, we're responding to the needs of the schools as they come up. If somebody resigns, if somebody is out long-term and needs coverage. So there's always that.
that issue when you implement the budget is kind of your best theory of the case when the year starts and then you have to make adjustments as you go along. So we do make those adjustments when it's necessary. For the supplemental budget, we're also at the same time evaluating proposals from the directors and principals. And so some of that has informed
our supplemental appropriation proposal. We wanted to identify things that we thought we could get going now versus waiting until July 1st. With respect to the guidance counselors, that is a proposal from the director.
And so we're addressing that as part of the FY26 budget. Of course, there's a lot of needs. There's some, I think, exciting new programming too in some areas. And so we have to crunch all those numbers, get it all together, and then kind of collectively figure out what is affordable or sustainable.
So thank you. That's useful to hear kind of what are the urgent needs that are being addressed by this immediate infusion of override funds, but to note that this is still a conversation that we're having about the next budget. Yes, correct. And with fidelity to the way the questions kind of directed us, we are to make the investments. Great. Thank you.
Thank you, Mr McHugh. We're going to go on to number three, which is also a presentation by you, our supplemental appropriation presentation.
Next slide. So this is two sums of money that were approved by the voters. Question seven provided the $3.5 million, $3 million to the schools.
for operational costs, but called out certain areas, funding for the cost of teachers, literacy coaches, behavior specialists, administrative assistants, nurses, and regular facilities maintenance. Another $5,000 was directed to the city's Department of Public Works. Question eight.
specifically provided for compensation for teachers and paraprofessionals, funds that might be needed to develop a new high school schedule. Such a schedule, thank you. Such a schedule will be designed to improve access to the arts and vocational programming and to expand classroom instructional opportunities.
and that it's presumed that these funds will carry forward into future fiscal years. The next slide is more of a value statement of how we look at
look at how we distribute fundings, and we wanted to be first, what's in the best interest of students, and then making sure that all areas of operations are adequately funded. For question seven, the
We have kind of broken up question seven into five different categories. We have money that was advanced by the city at the time the FY25 budget was adopted. You might remember that,
Early in the process, I had identified, I think, a little over $2 million in cuts that would have to be affected to balance the budget and that there were still an additional $4 or $5 million cuts that weren't addressed at that time when I was just trying to communicate to the school committee kind of the magnitude of our budget problem in FY25.
the city heard that and proposed new money and then proposed an additional sum of
$1,750,000 as more or less a down payment in advance of the override vote. So it was a bit of a risk for the city to undertake that because it wasn't necessarily sure that it would pass.
Now that it has passed, we will reserve that amount of money to allow the city to retain those funds for things that it's already, for expenses that were already provided for when the initial budget was passed. And as I alluded to in my previous report, there were,
handful of positions that.
We're not originally funded in the FY25 budget, but we're still retained in FY25 that have to be funded now. We've identified certain new positions during the course of the year that we would like to use these funds to balance our budget. We're proposing new positions as well.
as a result of budget discussions with principals and administrators and other expenses for facilities, technology to shore up funding in those areas. So in terms of the money that the city advanced, $1,400,000
Positions were added back to the budget to elementary teachers, to high school teachers, to literacy coaches, a nurse, four curriculum administrators, and three pair of professionals, behavior specialists. 500,000 was also provided to do a refresh of our Chromebooks that our students use.
And this will, in this, you know, provides a budget now for the annual refresh of our, all our deployed devices. The positions that were not originally funded in the FY25 budget include a kindergarten teacher,
that was retained because of projected enrollment. The PE teacher at the middle school had talked about an administrative floater, which was a position that had existed but was funded in the food service budget.
That person did some work for the food service department but was frequently deployed out into the other schools as needed. This position, however, we failed to provide for this position in the general fund budget in FY25 because we
depended on having that position when we reduced the administrative assistance staff. So we're looking to reinstate that position on the general fund with the supplemental funding. We had also positions that were identified
is needed after the FY 25 budget was adopted. These include two swing shift custodians that were provided for in the custodians collective bargaining agreement and this provides
Medford Public Schools with coverage over the weekends when we have different community groups in using the schools and reduces our reliance on overtime to provide that coverage. We hired an additional
payroll administrative assistant. During the course of the year, there were medically related leavers' absences. In the payroll department, there was only two administrative assistants that provide payroll, provide that payroll function.
And we think that you probably were aware of payroll problems within the payroll department in FY 24 and prior. And our view is that was related to understaffing in that department. And we feel like the payroll supervisor and three payroll administrative assistants is really the proper staffing to the amount of
people that are on the payroll fee for the variety of fringe benefits that Midford offers to its employees and the issues around payroll have been greatly reduced now that we have a staffing up to snuff. And of course, we talked about the district-wide music teacher that we hired to make sure we had adequate
teaching capabilities for our students in the middle school and the Medford High School band. Continuing on, these are new positions. Sorry, let me think. I may have missed a page.
So new positions we've identified since the passage of the supplemental appropriations should say FY25 budget. We feel like we, based on community input, we're proposing a teacher to identify and implement inclusion opportunities.
for our students with disabilities. And this will be paired with another program that we'll talk about in a minute called the Best Buddies Program, which is kind of provides or links up special needs students with kind of peers in the
general ed program and that is designed to support student growth for both students that are participating in that program. We're also proposing that we add back a nurse floater.
Since the implementation, the one coverage issue that we still have is that the McGlynn School has two full-time nurses and a part-time nurse for three days a week. That position, we feel, really should be five days.
nursing office suffers, you know, during the two days that part time person is not there. So, we could add a part time nurse, we feel like.
And we could ask the part-time nurse to go full-time. But this is a person who's been in the district for a long time, has had this part-time position for a long time. So we feel like the best way to go would be to bring on a nurse floater that could fill in for those two days.
There's certainly a need, particularly over the winter when there's so much colds and flu and everything, and that doesn't just affect our students, it affects the nurses who are seeing those students. So this would provide us some extra coverage and get a nurse on board, kind of train her up in the Medford Health Services. And then when it comes time for the part-time nurse to,
retire or resign, we can evaluate the need for that part-time position at that point in time. We did cut one administrative assistant from the McGlynn. And while the paperwork seems to be
being managed correctly, it creates an issue if that one administrative assistant is out or if there's other needs in the school. So we are proposing that we add back that administrative position at the McGlynn at this time.
And we're also proposing an assistant director for buildings and grounds. So it's one thing that we're also looking at in the FY 26 budget is to kind of look at the management structure that we have.
in that department, it does need some more oversight, not only for the staff, but for the maintenance projects, the construction projects that are underway. We're anticipating putting more money in to address maintenance problems in the district. So we have to build up our management capacity in that office to handle that.
The salaries for the new positions that we identified have been prorated and anticipating, you know, if the budget, if and when the budget, the supplemental appropriation is passed, they'll be hired in February or March.
In this budget proposal, the value of the prorated salaries is a little over $400,000. And annualized, those salaries would be $750,000. So it would mean an automatic increase in FY 26 of $350,000 for those positions.
In terms of expenses that we'd like to provide in the supplemental, we talked about the Best Buddies Program. That would be a stipend for a gen ed teacher and a special ed teacher to coordinate that program. The stipends on a prorated basis at 2,500 through the end of the year, but would be about 10,000 in FY26.
We're also proposing a project that has been developed to implement electronic key access controls and video intercoms at all schools in the buildings as a safety measure, refinishing the gym floor at the McGlynn.
conducting facility conditions assessments at five of our schools. This is a project that will provide a lot of very good information about our
our maintenance needs in each of the schools and help us to prioritize when those maintenance needs should be addressed. That facilities conditions assessments is projected to be about $125,000 and the balance of that appropriation would just go into ongoing facilities maintenance needs.
We're also proposing an E-rate project to replace all the wireless network access points in our network. So these are beyond their use of life and have limited availability.
bandwidth capacity. So we will have, it's a project that I think is going to come in around $600,000 to $700,000 an hour. The Medford Public Schools share of that would be $140,000 balance coming out of E-rate funds.
We're also proposing a camera system for the Curtis Tufts to provide hallway coverage, and this exists in all of the schools except for Curtis Tufts. We're proposing to fund new and replacement musical instruments, $12,000 district-wide
I believe that the budget for that is about $2,000 right now, and that would give us a budget of $14,000, and it could be a little more when we come around to the FY26 proposal. And a new van for the vocational program
They do have a couple of older vans that are battling needs of service and there's no way to take those vans off the road so we can address the maintenance needs properly. So the thought is to buy an additional van and get those other vans up to snuff. These vans take the students to different programs and work sites that are part of their program.
So the next slide is just a summary of how we allocated the question seven funds, 1.7 reserved by the city to fund those, that supplement, that appropriation, that additional appropriation to the FY 25 budget. And then another 1.8,
$1,250,000 in other expenses as identified. Maybe I'll stop here if people have any questions on the question seven part. Member Bramley? I think it was slide four, question seven, slide four.
Let's see. Can you just say again what you said about the nurse floater? You said there's two full time and one part time right now? At the McGlynn. At the McGlynn. And then it would be beneficial if we had another part timer as a two day floater, correct?
That what you just said, make sure I made my notes correctly. Yeah, no I said I said one option would be to hire a part time nurse to fill in for those two days. Okay. But we think a better option would be to use these funds to hire a full time person.
I think you get a better quality of candidate. That person could fill in for the other two days so the blend would be fully staffed. And then the question is, what do you do with these persons other three days so we would say, use that position instead of hiring.
day nurses for coverage. This person would be a floater, so they could go to different schools. So at McGlynn, two days and then three days. Right. Where needed. Right. Okay. The director will assign that person where he or she is best needed. Is the nurse at the McGlynn shared between both McGlynn Elementary and Middle School? I don't believe so. Laurie? She's shared.
Oh, okay. I thought you meant the Andrews and the McGlynn. Did I say McGlynn and McGlynn or did I say Andrews? I could have very well said the wrong thing. Yeah. Right. Okay. So McGlynn all shared. Yep. The whole complex. I think that was it. Thank you.
Member Olopade. Thank you. So a quick question. I know that you said, and I think it's on slide nine, about the Best Buddies stipend. That's the $2,500 per advisor. That's prorated. So that would go up for $26,000? Yes. OK. And you said it was $10,000 across each student? Yes. Yeah. The position we'll request is $5,000 for each student for the whole year. All right. Thank you.
And then, and this might be talked about a little bit in question. I know there's been some discussion about bus monitors. I know some people in the community have been wondering about what that may look like. I don't know if you have any, if that's gonna be further in the brief or if you have any suggestions about that. We'll talk about that when we get to question eight. We are attempting to address it. Thank you. Member Reinfeldt.
clarifying question on the restoring of the administrative system at McGlynn. Will that end up being two administrative assistants for two schools or will it be one per school? Is it designated?
I think for the funding, it will be one per school. So one will be funded. And I know people fill in for their person next to them. I know how that works. Some of that school runs as kind of one whole facility too. So I don't know if there'll be, I'm sure there's backup and sharing. But in terms of funding, it will be one for the middle and one for the elementary.
Great. Member Branley covered my other clarifying question. And then one last one, you mentioned that the administrative floater had been supporting food services. We're not leaving food services in the lurch by transferring that. No, no. That was, and really that we shouldn't have been using that position the way we were. Okay, we're correcting.
But one of the, we talked about some work that was left over that had to be distributed amongst existing administrative assistants. So one of those pieces is for food service. Thank you. I just wanted to make sure we were in.
And from the chair, if I may, I believe you had mentioned you'll be working on some sort of draft, even if it's just for staff that outlines which sections of this were prorated and which sections were one time funding so that we can make sure we're budgeting accordingly and don't land ourself.
in the same spot a few years down the road. So just reminding you of that, hopefully I'd love to be able to check it out. Our FY26 proposal will be full funding for all the positions that we're requesting.
It seems when I reviewed it a few days ago, it seems that the prorated is even dealt by the one time funding spent within the next six months. I just want to make sure we're going to need one time funding for different things down the line. So I just want to make sure we're not overspending. Yep. Our budget will be balanced when it's presented. Thank you. Thank you. Was that the end? Yes, question eight. Oh, question eight.
Continue, thank you. So question eight provided for $4 million in funding. And it can be used for compensation. It can be used for expanding educational opportunities and for the costs associated with developing and implementing a new schedule.
for the high school and potentially other schools as well. So in this instance, we're also providing
for $170,000 for a curriculum, ELA curriculum, that was purchased in FY24. The cost of that curriculum for ELA was $170,000 per year for three years.
Before I came to Medford, the business office had attempted to fund the full contract using ESSA funds, which was a good idea because we had to spend down our ESSA funds by the end of FY24.
However, because of the way the proposal was developed, the city's purchasing department would not allow all three years to be funded in a single year. So the first year was funded by ESSA. But we were surprised when we got an invoice last fall for $170,000. This was not covered in the budget.
So we're going to ask for money now to cover the FY25 portion. And of course, this will be part of our FY26 proposal to get the final year of that curriculum purchase finally funded.
As part of our FY 2060 discussions, the vocational program director was seeking to have three teachers added, one metal fabrication, one in automotive, and a culinary teacher. It turns out that these metal fabrication and the automotive teachers have
mandated lower class sizes for safety reasons. So we can only have, if we only have one teacher, we can only have 15 students in a class at the time.
adding these positions now, we'll be able to offer these programs to more students during the course of the year. The culinary program is very popular. We have two teachers there now, but those teachers are unable to take their
prep periods because they're 100% in teaching mode. So this additional teacher will allow us to make sure the teachers get the benefits they're entitled to in the contract and be able to adequately cover that program.
We kind of stayed away from adding new teachers in the supplemental because we don't feel that we're going to get quality candidates right now and we might be able to get them a few months down the line, but sometimes the
For the vocational positions, there's other kind of non-traditional sources that we can attract teachers based on the programming that's offered. As a matter of fact, I think we do have a good candidate for the metal fabrication teacher right now. So we're requesting to create those positions now rather than wait till next July. The balance of the funds,
are really lumped in to reserve for negotiations with the teachers and the paraprofessionals. And those negotiations have begun. And these funds will have to be spent by June 30th, but they'll be part of a
multi-year agreement, hopefully that gets resolved before the end of the year. And including in those negotiations would be the new schedule, a potential longer day. We added the
idea of the bus monitors in this category. So in discussing this with the leadership team, there's a couple of different ways to provide monitors on buses. We could make it a condition of the contract and have the contractor
higher the bus monitors. We could kind of open it up to other staff part-time, maybe food service or other staff at school might be interested in those extra hours. But we think if we could work it out with the paraprofessionals, that paraprofessionals might
provide us with a quality bus monitor. They know the kids, they know the school. The complication is that depending on how many hours are added to the day, we could be bumping up into kind of overtime requirements, and it would have to be negotiated. So we're kind of throwing it into the mix here as part of negotiations, and then we'll see what works out.
And then we'll just have, we'll make sure that there's funding provided in the FY26 budget. If it doesn't work out within the negotiation context, we can have funds to possibly hire people in a different way. And it's kind of an open question as to whether we need bus monitors on every route,
every day or are there specific bus routes that are problematic. So kind of all that will be looked at as part of the negotiations process. And then, you know, should the new schedule be adopted, there's going to have to be
human resources developed because student schedules will have to be input into our school brain system. IEPs will have to be rewritten, IEP meetings will have to be held with parents and caregivers. And so there'll be funding carved out for that as well.
Is there any questions on question eight? Hearing and seeing none, I'll see if member Graham.
Thank you. I actually had a question. I think it is back on question seven, so my apologies. The facility conditioning assessments, that number looks different than the numbers that we had in our capital plan. So can you just give us a rundown of what that looks like?
what number it is. Sorry, on page nine. So it says 146,000 for the facility condition assessments. And other, I think other maintenance needs. So, okay, so it's, it's not just the assessment. Yeah, so they,
To kind of balance things out, we're saying $125,000 for the facilities assessment, and that's based on $125,000 for five schools. Okay.
$25,000 per school, roughly. And then we expect to get, we've been in talks with one of the house doctor contractors, and they're providing us with some preliminary pricing. So, you know, the passage of the supplemental will kind of dovetail nicely with that process. But that's the difference there.
Okay, and then my other related question, which again I think is question seven. Is there were three there were three specific.
capital projects that we identified in our capital plan as things we wanted to see accomplished in FY25, which includes fixing the issue that causes flooding in the kindergarten classroom at the McGlynn, the drainage at the Brooks School, and then the freight elevator motor
And I didn't see those in this presentation. Is that because they're somewhere else, or are they not able to be accounted for in 25? So we're, as part of our regular budget, we're moving on the Brooks flooding issue, mini splits, which we'll start this year and finish in FY26.
The flashing issue, I think, because it involves, the roof was part of the HVAC work at the McGlynn, and the freight elevator we're moving forward on as part of our regular budget. Okay, great. Thank you so much. And then, Mayor, I think there might be some people in the audience who wanna speak when the committee's done. Member Reinfeldt, then Member Russo.
Yeah, I was just hoping you could speak a little more about the logistics of how funds reserved for bargaining for a future contract gets spent in the bargaining fiscal year. You alluded to it for a couple of these items, but just explaining how that works. Yeah.
Well, I don't want to get too deep into kind of strategy or topics, but once there was an agreement
We would, to utilize these funds, some of that agreement would call for payments to take place before June 30th as part of a three-year contract. So it would be all, you know, if you look at it in terms of what is the total cost of three years, some of that funding will come in FY25.
Member Rousseau? Thank you, Mr. McHugh. I'll open it up to the floor. If you could just state your name and address for the record and have about three minutes. So please come on up. Do you need more? A little bit, maybe. Although I have a new best friend, Mr. McHugh. I'm so happy to hear all the stuff that he just mentioned. We're all like little kids in there. Patricia Cherry, 20 Wellesley Street, Medford.
I have to switch it up a little bit because I thought we were going to be coming to ask for these things to be put in the budget, and now we're finding out that you guys, after meeting with you, already put them in the budget, so this is a huge thing for us right now.
We are so late. Yes, I know, I know. But I just need to let you know that we're all caught off guard here. I had this whole thing written out on why these things are so important to our kids and to our families and why they need to be passed. And it's time that they get passed. It's time that our kids and our families have a seat at the table.
We need to be supported by the community. We need to be part of the community. And we're here to say, we're not gonna take anything less. The bus monitors is a huge thing. I will read a little bit on that because I think it's very important that people know. Our children are among the most vulnerable students in the district. The bus ride is often one of the most concerning experiences in terms of safety for our children.
It's deeply unsettling to rely on a bus to take your child to school when they may not always have the ability to communicate if or when they are being harmed.
Whether that harm is sexual, emotional, or physical, it has come to light that one of our students endured such harm for an extended period of time. And it is likely that many others have faced similar situations. To us, this is unacceptable and, quite frankly, appalling that the safety of our children with special needs ranks so low on the list of the budget priorities.
That person didn't come tonight. I know that they were speaking on behalf of multiple families. It was devastating to hear that that was being done to a child, especially one in what we consider our community. So bus monitors are a must.
It should be. It's something that for safety, for just everything, just overall, we need the bus monitors for our kids. As far as the inclusion specialist, that was another ask that we had. We need an inclusion specialist because right now the gap between typical and
atypical children is too wide. We need somebody to come into the schools and close that gap. We need somebody to come into the schools and start programs for our kids where
We're not coming in as, oh, the kids with disabilities. We're coming in as equals, where these programs are, the participants are all on an equal playing field, where they can learn from one another. Because each child has something to offer. That's what we need an inclusion specialist for. We don't have any programs.
There are no real programs that our kids, even afterschool programs are very difficult because there's always an extra ask if you wanna join the afterschool program. There's always, oh, well, is there gonna be an aid for my child? Oh, is this afterschool program gonna fit the needs of our child? And a lot of the times it doesn't, because there's no staffing, they don't have the extra paras, they don't have somebody who can work with our kids.
So it brings it back to needing someone who has the ability and the education and the knowledge on how to tie that all in so that the schools can be a more inclusive place. Because we always hear about inclusive in Medford. We just don't ever see it. You hear so much about the most vulnerable, you know? Oh, we need the money for the most vulnerable, the most vulnerable. Oh, this, you know, everybody talks about the most vulnerable, but the most vulnerable never get it.
And that's gotta stop, that has to stop. We have to put our kids as high a priority as everybody else's child.
We understand programs need money. You need money for instruments. You need money for drama clubs. You need money for whatever other programs you have in the schools. But all we're saying is before you give more money to those already funded programs, fund some programs that are non-existent, the ones that we want for our children. That's why the two asks that we have were the inclusion specialists and the bus monitors.
I can only speak to my experience. We also have a large group of children that aren't even in district, including mine, who also goes out of district for school and also out of district for all of her activities, because there are none in the city, but that will take up tomorrow with city council. But we lose that. My daughter, I have to make sure
to keep this group of people so that our kids can remain to have the small group of friends that we have because there is no opportunity for that in this city. I'm kind of all over the map because I'm just shocked. I'm so happy.
I need you to push this through. We need you. We are saying enough. We're here. We are going to now be here. We're not going anywhere. This isn't a one-shot deal. We're going to represent this group going forward. And it's time. It's time that we have a seat at the table just like everybody else. I'm going to end it there. I think that was a motion for approval.
I ask for your approval. Oh, and I appreciate, I appreciate Aaron, who worked with us, and Jenny, and Suzanne, and Joan. We had meetings about this, and Aaron showed up to our library event, and I appreciate all of you guys for doing that. And please, yes, do I say, can you please approve this? Yes, that's perfect. All right. Member Reinfeld? Oh, I'm sorry, Member Branley.
So I just wanted to say you had made a comment. You said our community, but I want you to know you're part of our community that we are all one community. And that includes you. That includes every child in this district and every single parent. I work in special ed in Somerville. I've never made that a secret. I love working for special ed because I say this all the time. And I think that sometimes there's this, you know, differential. I don't like it. I don't like it. It's not fair.
And I feel like everybody in special ed, every student, every adult, everybody that works in special ed, every student in the district, every student outside of special ed, we're all a piece to a puzzle here in this room and everywhere else. And at the end of the day, the pieces of that puzzle get put together and it's your child's name, you know, and that matters. And I take it really personal because I think that,
You are part of this community. So I just never want anybody to ever forget that. So thank you for coming and advocating for your child. I've stood there and advocated for my own child. I know how difficult that is. So thank you. Thank you all for being here. And I will be at city council tomorrow to support you. So thank you very much. Thank you for your words. Thank you.
Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
And because of that, I have talked with a lot of parents, especially about the need for bringing a lot of our services in-house and how we need to have programs for students that can equal the playing field, have an equitable experience in our schools, because it's just not there. So I want to thank you personally for a lot of the advocacy work that you're doing and for coming here and giving your point of view and thought process. So thank you. Thank you. I appreciate that. One more thing.
This is a whole group. I'm just the mouth, because I have the big mouth. There are people that we've learned for that came before us, like Tonya Sullivan, Melanie, Alex. They've been doing this a lot longer than we have. It's just we're a small group, and because we don't have the resources that we have, we're very tight-knit. So there's a bunch of us. I just have the big mouth.
over the years that I've been involved in the conversation that I'm just really happy to see where it's at right now. And I'm excited to see where he's going forward. Yes, yes. So is there a motion for approval on the floor? Motion to approve and before we call the roll, member McLaughlin.
I'm former member of McLaughlin. Yeah, thank you. Melanie McLaughlin, Alston Street, Medford Moss. Thank you all. I just wanted to say thank you. This has been 10 years in the making. And Trish, you did fantastic tonight. I felt like a proud mother, I have to say, myself. And the community is really grateful. And this has been a long time. A couple of different special ed directors over the years, and a lot of teachers and hundreds of children have passed through this district.
And it's done. I know, and I love that, you know, I can guarantee you Trish is not going anywhere. So, and neither are any of the other families so you know to the families that are watching tonight and to those out there who might hear about this later what have you and
who work every day as caregivers with their children, who do extra homework, who advocated IEP meetings, who do all those things that we know how hard they are. We just wanna say that you're not alone and that this is really important that every child matters and that we know that this school committee feels that way and we wanna thank the school committee for that. And one of the things I wanted to mention is that, it was actually the former special education director that used to say this to me and would remind me and I thought it was really important. And she said, there are no special education students.
everyone is a general student in our district. There are students who receive special education services. So we're all part of the community, and we know that, and we appreciate that, and we'll continue speaking up. So thank you all, and thank you guys all for what you're doing. Appreciate you. Thank you. Motion for approval, I believe, was by Member Graham, seconded by Member Olapare.
Hi, everybody. Okay, motion to amend. I know that some of our staff representatives from our nursing union were here earlier and they had sent an email asking for support because, you know, looking at how the budget's been and the positions that have been reestablished just really isn't doing it for them. And, you know, personally, you know,
I have my full support for reestablishing the positions that we lost. That was one of the big talking points that we had talked about, or that had been happening. So I would actually motion
to pull from the undistributed to either restore at least one floater position, motion to amend the supplemental appropriation of the 2024 just to give them at least, I know that probably having all four positions back isn't something we could swing, but I feel like having at least one other additional floater within the unit might be, especially because as it relates to question eight, with extending the day, we may need some additional staffing needs when it comes to that.
That was one of the proposed recommendations for Mr. McHugh.
to add a 1.0 position instead of the halftime position. And that person would fill in the two days at the McGlynn and be a floater for the remaining three days. So that would add a 1.0 FTE back to the nursing ranks. Right. I'm sorry. I didn't mean to interrupt you. So then it would go from, so we lost four. We brought in one more. So then three were missing. We lost three. We lost three. So then now we're missing two.
So by adding in the one more, we would have added the two positions back. OK. OK. OK. So we'll take that motion to amend off. Motion for approval by Member Graham, seconded by Member Olopade. Roll call, please. Member Brandley? Yes. Member Graham? Yes. Member Ntapa?
Member Olopade. Yes. Member Rheinfeld. Yes. Member Rossell. Yes. Mayor Lungo. Yes. Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative. Paper passes. Yep, thank you for coming and being advocates for your kids and many others. And hopefully you stick around. We don't have a long meeting and we want you to enjoy some cake with us.
We do not have any presentations of the public or continued business or new business or reports requested. We do have one condolence. The members of the Medford School Committee express their sincere condolences to the family of Ralph A. Evangelista, father of Lisa Evangelista, former public informations officer for the Medford Public Schools. We all may rise for a moment of silence.
Thank you. And before we let you know when the next regular meeting is, or maybe after we let you know when the next regular meeting is, which is January 27 2025 here in the Alden Memorial Chambers, Medford City Hall, in addition to Zoom. So before we adjourn, I'd like to
ask everybody to stay and have some cake with us to celebrate seven amazing years put into the Medford Public School, our district by our superintendent, Dr. Maurice Edouard-Vincent. Thank you so much for all you've done for our students, our faculty, staff, everything we went through alongside you. Some of us, some of us, some of you brand new with the COVID crisis. You are a worker and we appreciate everything you've done for us and the district.
Yes, come on up. Member Rousseau, and then please. You wanna yield? I'll yield to the most senior member in this room. No, no, please.
So I'm here tonight and I've lost Melanie. So on behalf of Melanie McLaughlin, and also former school committee members, Sharon Hayes, Mia Masone, and Kathy Kretz, we're all here tonight with you, Superintendent, to thank you and to say,
give you our profound thanks for the seven years that you've given to Medford. And, you know, I was on the committee when you joined us in a rather difficult time, and it was so wonderful to have your enthusiasm and your joy and the sense of pride in Medford and in our students and just excitement.
Former athletic coach, and some of you will know who I'm talking about, but it was quite a long time ago, the late Bud Kelly used to say that he'd always be talking about Medford pride, and he'd say, he'd pull up a shirt and he had drawn blue and white on his arm and said that Medford pride runs in his veins. And to you, superintendent,
Medford pride runs in your veins. And so we are very thankful for the time that you have been with us. We are so thankful for the role model you were to so many of our students for your, again, I come back to the word joy, but just, I think about the opening of school.
outside when you had all the teachers, all of us sort of lined up and the teachers came in and there was so much excitement and your commitment to learning. You took us through a very difficult and dark time with COVID when everybody was scared and anxious
And you were our leader, and that was just amazing. So we are here tonight to thank you. It seems like it went so fast, but we so appreciate your dedication, the gifts you have brought to Medford, the gifts that you are leaving with us, and that we are better for you having been here. So thank you so very much, Maurice.
I ditto, I couldn't say more. I mean, I think that you've brought so much to the district, the first female in the district, the first black woman in the district after decades of, you know, the same leadership and having to take on an entirely new district and do all that you did.
And the short time that you were here has been remarkable. And I really valued working with you. And I know that I will, I really look forward to see where you're going next. And I will be watching you and looking out for your next successes. And I know that we'll be proud of you wherever you go. So thank you. Yes. Member Rousseau, then Member Graham.
Why? Oh, that was loud. I'll wait for... So to limit myself, I wrote it down, because otherwise we'd be here all night.
So over the last seven years, I've had the privilege, I'm sorry, over seven years ago, I've had the privilege to be part of the superintendent search process where we selected our first new superintendent in a generation. And from the very first round of interviews, it was evident to me who our next superintendent should be. And I was pleased that the members of the search committee and finally the school committee agreed with me.
Dr. Edward Vincent was hands down the right choice for Medford, and I was thrilled when she accepted the job. Working with Dr. Edward Vincent has been a pleasure, and I cannot thank her enough for all that I have learned these past seven years. No one could have foreseen what a wild seven years this would be. Dr. Edward Vincent's focus on curriculum instruction was what we needed in Medford, and she delivered.
She started Learning Walks in the fall of 2019, and I am still sad that I did not get to partake in a Learning Walk thanks to the pandemic. I know that former member Vandra Kloot did, and she spoke very highly of it, but that wasn't meant to be. The pandemic could easily have been the defining event
of your tenure with Medford Public Schools, but your focus on curriculum and instruction, which began before the pandemic, continued through the pandemic, and after the pandemic, is what I believe will be your lasting legacy here. And I am pleased to remember you for this great work. Obviously, you didn't do it all alone. There were many other leaders and teachers who were a big part of that, but you had to lead, so.
The job of the superintendent is truly massive. The day-to-day lives of thousands of students, staff, and families are in your hands. Dr. Edward Vincent gave her all, and no one could ever have questioned whether she was doing what she thought was best for students. The pandemic was a trying time for everyone. Many people lost their lives. Many more lost their ability to support their families. Focusing on providing food to students in need,
When access to our school meals program was suddenly shuttered was something I'm proud of. And Dr. Edward Vincent was all in on this critical issue. There was no playbook for what to do next when the pandemic began. Dr. Edward Vincent led the district through a very trying time. And for that, I am forever grateful.
It took a village, but we limited the amount of learning loss as best we could. Expectations for students, teachers, staff, and families about what public education meant were turned upside down. Dr. Edward Vincent has continued to lead us as we continue to work to mitigate learning losses caused by the pandemic, and I'm grateful for the focus on the mental health of our students and staff. Education is truly a unique domain. Everything changes every day.
That is not hyperbole. Federal, state and local laws, regulations and rulings change how education is implemented with breakneck speed and often little time for implementation. Research on best practices and education is released at a completely uncontrolled speed. Our students, staff and families themselves change too. The saying that the only thing that is constant is change is true in education as well.
I would further add that each of us from one moment to the next is not the same nor entirely different. Dr. Edward Vincent has led thousands of people for seven years through never ending change and we are better for her efforts. On a personal note, I will miss the welcoming nature Dr. Edward Vincent brings to every interaction.
She arrives with joy and spreads it liberally. Whether welcoming teachers and students back for the first day in person, for the first day of in-person education during the pandemic, or at a pep rally, or riding school buses, she is always proud to be a Mustang, and in my mind, will always be a Mustang. Thank you, Maurice. Thank you, member Rousseau. Member Graham? Thank you.
I also had the chance to sit on the superintendent search committee. I was not on the school committee at the time. But one of the things that was so striking during that process is every time we talked to you, I thought to myself,
Dr. Edward Vincent has a coaching mindset. And it was one of the like prevailing things I thought about you as we were interviewing what felt like an endless number of candidates. And they all were so different. There was not two people that were the same. And one of the things that is so evident about the work that you've done here is that coaching mindset. So you truly look for your entire team to deliver. It's not just about you. It's not just about,
any one person, and I've always appreciated that. I feel like that hasn't always been easy. And I think there have been times where you have brought forward an idea like investing in professional development so that our evaluators could do a better job evaluating our staff in their service to children. And I do remember you getting considerable pushback about that. So the other thing I think about when I think about your time here
is that you weren't afraid to start the ball moving in a direction that it hadn't moved before. And being the person that starts things is really hard. It means convincing people that it's gonna be okay to do this new thing. It means convincing people that we can do this and the other things that we were doing. And it also means saying no to the way things have always been done before.
And I have really appreciated your willingness to hold the line and to say no to the way things have always been done here in this district. It's incredibly important in a district like ours. It is the way change gets made and the people who are willing to start the ball rolling up the hill have the very hardest job. So thank you for that.
Lucas asked me the other day what you were going to do next. And I said, whatever she does, I hope she has time to take a nap because it's been seven very long years. So thank you. We do have a gift to present you. I don't want to fully unwrap it because we want to get it home safe, but we'll at least unwrap it.
Oh, sure. So it says, Maurice Edouard Vincent, Superintendent of Schools, presented with gratitude for seven years of dedication, service to the staff and students of Medford.
have a
There's more flowers here. There you go.
It's only seven thirty five.
Thank you. With that, we'll cut a cake. Motion to adjourn by member Reinfeldt, seconded by member Graham. All those in favor? Aye.