Hi, everyone. I'm Frances. Welcome to the December 2022 Human Rights Commission meeting. Handing it over to the chair, Shelley. Hi, everybody. Frances, did you want us to just do a quick intro, if you like?
Sure, that would be- We're all ready. Do you want to, I mean, I feel like we're already kind of team members here. Yeah, maybe for those that could be listening and aren't familiar.
Okay, maybe I'll just go real quick first and then popcorn. Hi, everybody. I'm Chelly. I am the chair for now. I'm Medford mom, two kids, I grew up here, I do a lot of equity work. It just came off of a nonprofit and hopefully next year brings grad school. So that's me. Kelly, do you want to take it next?
Kelly Cunia, I'm the co chair for now. And I am also a Medford mom and I have, I'm a social worker. And I care deeply about social justice and human rights. I will popcorn to Diane.
Thank you, Kelly. I'm Diane McDonald. I'm a Medford mom and longtime resident of West Medford. In my professional work, I use stories to build community.
I've created anti-racism programs for our Harvard alumni community. And civil rights, history, social justice are important to me. And I've also been a seven-year tour guide at Royal House and Slave Quarters. I love Medford. I will popcorn to Munir. Hi, everyone. I'm Munir Jamaris, a longtime resident
retired physicist, full-time grandparent with four grandchildren. That's really full-time work. I've been on the Human Rights Commission for about five years. And I'll pass it to the chief.
Hi everyone, Chief Jack Buckley, been just finished my 25th year here in the city method, member of the Human Rights Commission for the last four years, my anniversary as chief of police's December 19 so I got a couple of days but a lot of anniversaries. And what's something else new, I am still parenting to grown adult kids who just.
It costs me a lot more money now, 18 to 21. It's more money than you will ever spend on any child that you raise. Thank you. Who else do we have left here? Steve, do you want to introduce yourself? I know you're- I can, but let Rob go next. Is he here? Rob is calling in. Rob is on the phone. Sorry, I just saw the cell number.
That's all right. Despite that area code, I too am a Medford resident, been a member of the commission for two and a half years now. Really passionate about advancing equity throughout the community here in Medford, especially being a transplant and moving here, settling with my wife. I want to have an impact on the community for everyone here. That's why I'm here today. Unfortunately, I'm going to have to drop a couple of minutes early today at six.
But I'll be attentively on the call until that time. I'll go next. Steve Schnapp, volunteer. I take notes at these meetings. I am retired. I live in Medford Square with my wife. We have two grown kids, three grandchildren.
And we've lived in Medford for going on 12 years now. And I think Judy's the last person. Sorry, that's fitting. I am no longer a member of the HRC. My term has ended. So I'm here as a community member, community observer.
Oh, about me, I've been living in West Medford for 33 years, and I'm an editor, and I guess that's enough. Thank you, Judy. Frances, did you want to share a quick intro before we move to approval?
Yes, I thought I did. Frances here, Director of Diversity, Equity and Inclusion for the City of Medford. And I do want to say thanks to Munir. I caught the error referenced in our upcoming minutes, and I will make the dates change. I had our next meeting listed as December 9th, which is already come and gone. It really should stay December 14th. So I will make that change.
Sounds good. Um, so moving on, did folks get a chance to review the minutes from our last meeting? Um, if we are in to approve with the change, it was exactly what I need motion to approve with the, uh, changes that Francis just mentioned. Second. All in favor. Yes. There we go. Thank you.
Okay, here I am pulling up this agenda one more time. Somebody fill me in, of course, right now it won't open for me. While we're waiting, can I just ask, what happens to the minutes? I know I send my draft.
to the secretary, ICC, the chairs, and Francis. If the public, can they access these notes after they've been approved as minutes?
It is my understanding that because after you send them to me as you're speaking now I'm making that change because I'm about to forward them off to the city clerk's office as the approved meeting minutes and then I have to print a copy and walk it down that they stamp. It is supposed to be stored somewhere.
I'm just like, all the meetings, I know that there are hard copies here at city clerk's office, but I cannot speak to how the city historically stores its commission meetings in an online format. I'll chime in. They're supposed to be placed online.
on the city website under the HRC, but they have not been. Somebody at some point stopped storing them, but that's what they're supposed to be. So I used to keep copies of minutes of previous meetings for the past three years, but I don't know who the right person to contact the city to make sure that they do that.
But that's what they're supposed to be. And I apologize I may have stirred some of this stuff because I was looking for the April to, you know, the April are to now archive of minutes, based on.
you know, the notes from the last meeting, Francis, where you recommended we all go back and look at the minutes, and then I couldn't find them. But if there's anything I can do to be helpful, I'm happy to help and post them in the Google Drive if that's where they belong, if I see the copies. So just let me know how I can help as well.
I'm wondering if that's maybe a question for Neil or if he might have advice about the right person to get in touch with.
I think it could be Neil. I could think it could be city clerk. I think it could be communications. Um, I don't, I actually don't think it's Neil. I think it's more, more city clerk and communications because from my other commission, there are some agenda items that are there from my time, but the rest of the agenda items from my time and not there. Um, so I think that that's something, you know, maybe it's, maybe it's broader. I don't think it's unique to the human rights commission.
Got it. That makes sense. But I do know, though, that the hard copy, according to the Roberts rules, the hard copy piece with the time stamp and everything. I do know that we definitely do follow because I personally not only email it, but I personally walk it down myself as well. So they are always available at the city clerk's office.
Sounds good do we want to move on to our next bullet and start with meeting protocol maybe. Sure and I had brought it up. Over e-mail it was just. I mean I don't know this kind of goes along with what we're doing in terms of taking the the feedback and
work that has been done about just identifying our role and our vision and our purpose. But I wonder if, you know, a general, like, I don't want to say code of conduct or something. That sounds so almost infantilizing. We're all, we all are professionals. And I think, I think that's clear, but I feel like sometimes just a conversation about how, if we're feeling defensive or if we're feeling
attacked being open and just having open and honest communication about where we're at. Last meeting, it felt, I felt uncomfortable. I don't know how other people felt. It felt at times that the work that Safe Medford had done, like I was really excited and happy about it. And I don't think, you know,
And I wonder about, it just didn't seem like it was received by everybody so well. And it just, I don't know, it felt uncomfortable to me. It felt a little uncomfortable. Maybe I'm the only one that had that experience. And then maybe that's a me, a Kelly thing. I don't know if anyone has any other thoughts that either to disagree or agree with me, I'm not sure.
As a social worker, one of my things that I do daily in my job is I say the thing. I like to put things out there. I like to have open and transparent conversations. And when things feel uncomfortable, I like to put it out there and open it up for discussion.
Thank you, Kelly. I appreciate you sharing. This kind of also makes me think about just like a general conversation that we've had for a while around designing just some like HRC tenants. I think we had talked about like, who are we? And definitely one of the goals, but like the whole, this seems to fall under the sort of heading of who are we, and that includes who are we with each other and who are we like when we're working together. So.
Thank you for sharing the email. I don't know if folks have thoughts. So I just need to look at some of my archives of some of the work that I do with a lot of different audiences and I can share with everyone some recommendations that just that's really good ground rules and just culture of respect when we're in meetings that might feel like they could potentially be a little
You know, complex and especially when you know this, this is a topic that everybody's very passionate about and we all come from different places, so I'll find that and send that to everybody later but I think that's great feedback Kelly and and.
I think that, you know, as a new member, I'm finding that I'm having more questions than answers. So if I came across in any particular way, you know, it's probably just me trying to just get an understanding. So perhaps I can just set up like coffee meetings with all of you, you know, after today's meeting and before we all meet again in January, just to get a little more orientation if anyone has time.
Yeah, Dan, I just want to echo that. I mean, at least for myself, when I started, I also felt like I had more questions than answers. And I was connecting with folks and saying, literally, I have no idea what's going on. And it took a little bit of time to find a groove. So I understand and can empathize with maybe the moment you're feeling. I am certainly available to connect by coffee. Perhaps others are too.
Um, should we MLK talk for a little while? Ready to move on? Yeah. Francis, did you want to share any MLK thoughts?
I remember at the last meeting, it being said that the Human Rights Commission has historically been involved in what would be very helpful to me is to find out exactly when and where the Human Rights Commission was involved. And to do that in a manner that is ahead of time.
The expectation that an encounter is going to go around is going to pass on more knowledge. It's really not ideal. It's really more realistic.
And I'm coming up against a lot of situations where I'm hearing that, oh, this is how it's been done. But when I go back and I look into it, I can't find any protocol, any avenue, anything that's put on paper. Yet a date is approaching, and something has to get done. And it's not just with the Human Rights Commission,
Yeah, let me jump in. I think if that's okay. And everybody else specifically Kelly. So I think maybe it was around Halloween time. I had emailed Francis. So Dan, let me back up and share that for two years running. I'm sorry.
Hold on, it's my little one. Folks are having trouble here. Fine. Apologies. So, this is already 2020 or it's some year that feels like it was 100 years ago already but Kelly and I,
ran, co-ran MLK, we called it Medford Celebrates MLK. And essentially what happened is that we hit October or November, and Neil said to the commissioners, hey, we don't, the city of Medford is not going to host MLK if HRC doesn't find the energy to kind of take the reins. And there's, there have been different entities that have collaborated to host it in the past. And people were understandably sort of
you know, in, you know, whatever spaces they were in and didn't have the energy to give. Kelly and I stepped up. Kelly like crazy stepped up. This woman was pregnant and dealing with family stuff and COVID and was like co-planning and sending me like map avenues for like where black history stuff is. It was incredible. So we killed it. And then last year I very much ran it myself.
And I think they were both different events, but I think they were both very strong. They were academically informed, they were detailed, they were organized. I also, last year and then Kelly and I the year before, bent over backwards to include stakeholders that wanted to be included, and that went different ways for different stakeholders. And it was, it took a lot of energy, especially when you feel like you're already giving
a lot. So, say all that to say, I think around Halloween time, maybe slightly later, I emailed Frances and Brianna the sort of like toolkit, so to speak, that I built over running MLK. And both times that I did it, and we did it, we began sort of at November 15th and gave ourselves two months.
As we all know, the more practice you have running something, the sort of less time you need and you build the formula and you have pieces left over that will still work and you just change dates. And so some of that could exist now. I think I'll channel a little inner Kelly. And if I'm blunt, if I'm being like blatantly honest, I really appreciated the sort of independent nature that we had. And I'm not sure if that will be the case this year.
The way that we sort of hosted it was super organic and really centered Black history and who MLK was as a person and as a politician, sort of, and as a revolutionary. And I'm not interested in participating in an event that feels performative, that sort of glosses over nuance. I understand the need to have events that
serve families versus professionals versus adults, but I would hope that that doesn't sort of dilute the quality of an event that we can share. So I had said to Francis and Brianna, we actually got to sit down and there were a number of solid ideas proposed for events that could be hosted, but I'm not totally sure
where it's gone from there and we haven't gotten a chance to connect. So that's my update. And I can just speak to the fact just for your own, Frances, asking for the history of it. When Shelley and I took it over in 2020, we did a very drastically different, first of all, it was COVID, so we had no choice. We had to figure, we had to be creative. So I think that lent itself to being different. But I think prior to that, it was a very much
pageantry of, let's have some speakers, let's talk about MLK, let's bring out the Boy Scouts. There was a lot of that performance and people loved it because that's what they know and expect and that was their typical, and I think at some point there was even food involved. I don't know where they got the budget for that.
But we really wanted, with everything that was going on in 2020 and the realization for many people for the first time about race in the United States, we wanted to really capitalize on that and try to bring it. And I think we worked well because I was trying to like make it family friendly and also real. And Shelly was really great at talking to the big guns and the Harvard people and the fancy, fancy words.
Um, so we tried our best to marry that, but we wanted it to feel realistic. So I was done last year. I was like, I'm, I was on maternity leave anyways. Um, but even if I had been, I, I was, I couldn't have done it. Um, I am happy to help in any way, shape or form.
I am also not interested in the performative pageantry. That's, and again, I'm not saying that's, that is so fine. If people want to do that, I personally just, that's not, that's not, it doesn't align with my values. Um, and so for more detail, um, well then Shirley, do you see Judy's got, um, the icon for her raised hand? I just wanted to. Oh, I'm sorry. Go ahead, Judy. Judy, you're up.
Is it okay if I? Yeah, of course, I can see you. You raised your hand so I can see you. Okay. I want to say prior to the last couple of years, which was, you know, which were influenced by COVID and also a different orientation, that originally my understanding is that this was a West Medford community event.
way back, way before my time. And in my time on the commission, what I've seen is that, again, prior to the last couple of years, there would always be at least three people on a committee. I mean, there would always be a committee of five or six from different, you know, different
organizations, and at least three of them would be people who were doing this on work time. So that would be Neil, that would be Reverend Wendy, that would be, I'm forgetting, oh, the director of the West Medford Community Center. It also used to be held at the West Medford Community Center. So
I think it morphed into a different entity, but I think there was a lot of energy in those events when they were held at the community center. I think it changed its flavor when it was held at the church, the big Catholic church on High Street in West Bedford.
I'm not saying for better or worse, it just had a different flavor. And over the years, we've had fewer and fewer and fewer and fewer people of color attending these events. So I just wanted to give that little history without any interpretation. Thanks, Judy. That's actually helpful to me. So as a committee,
What are you interested in doing and how do you see the HRC fitting in? Because the city is really a partner to work with all. So the city is available to work with all. Francis, can I circle back to just share with specifically Dan. So just for reference, when Kelly and I ran it,
we sort of had to answer to sort of Floyd energy that you would be tone deaf and should go back to your cave if you weren't going to do that in 2020. So we ran a discussion about the poor people's campaign and racialized capitalism. And we ran conversation around how King was acknowledged as a leader insofar as he was discussing race, but wasn't acknowledged as sort of a threat to the status quo until his public discussion tethered
money, and race. And we had a panel discussion, and Kelly was great about being like, nobody knows what you're saying, so take that to David Harris. And building family programming, and she did like a tour of the city. We pulled in the Arts Council. We absolutely checked in with Neil, Wendy, the director of WNCC, and they all said, take it and go. And we did. We had the superintendent of schools attend the planning meetings. We
We had CCSR kids, we did a lot of work. And frankly, like the kids were incredible and they were the only ones who answered to deadlines and like did everything that they were supposed to. And then so last year I ran a discussion on, so I think last year I had hoped that we could center the discussion around
diasporic anti-imperialism because there was the sort of events that went on in Haiti and I was hoping that our new Haitian ambassador Darlene Raymond could join us. So just making, giving light to the discussion that King, yes, is a huge figure in the U.S. but had also begun to put down roots internationally and explain why that was seen as threatening as well. But so like, just to say, moving forward,
I would love to see this trajectory continue. I think Judy's right. There is an energy that existed in the past. And Kelly's also right. It is absolutely status quo. And to remember that legacy organizations often see discussion of liberation as disruptive and are not interested in collaborating in that. And that's absolutely what we found from my perspective. So yeah, just, I appreciate you listening to the background.
that it sounds like you did amazing work as two people and just noticing, you know, the city and, you know, intellectual leaders to just- They were both recorded. I'm fully able to send you the recordings of both events if you wanted or folks wanted. Oh, I would love to see them. So my quick thoughts are, you know, maybe even for next year is because I, you know, I've always believed
MLK Day was also a day of national service. So, you know, perhaps have, you know, this intellectual programming to really ignite people, but also just bring people out in the act of service for our community to do what needs to get done. And it, you know, and is it, you know, like an activity with the elderly housing, you know, a food drive,
You know, in years past, you know, I spent so much of my day in Cambridge that for a lot of years when my kids were younger, because I couldn't find service opportunities on MLK Day in Medford,
for years, I would take my kids to do a service day in Cambridge and maybe like thinking about food security needs, like what are our human rights needs in Medford? Let's work with the nonprofits and the churches or whatever, whatever institutions, or even, I mean, I could talk to Kara Singleton at Royal House Enslaved Quarters and say, can we open up
the quarters space for an activity, and maybe it's several different places in Medford, and we get some PR out about it, and have people get involved so that MLK Day in Medford's not simply a day off, and it could be a morning or an afternoon, and you can do a two-hour service.
you can attend intellectual programming, maybe it's a menu of options. And that probably sounds like too complicated, but maybe there are organizations we can help within Medford as well and spotlight them. Because I know I was always looking for that in Medford and I went to Cambridge for it, but imagining getting that off the ground with intellectual programming component that's relatable for families,
I think that'd be awesome. And we did, um, we worked with the, the, the royal, um, house. They were part of our, we did a scavenger hunt and the panel and spoke on the panel spoke on the panel. And then they were a site. So I, that, so I defer to the intellectual, not that I'm not an intellectual, I'm an intellectual as well, but I, where my, where I, Francis, when you said, how would you want to help? I feel like.
because I'm an elementary social worker. I think my area of specialty is working with kids and families. So that's an area that I would be happy to like grow and make it so that it's a part of the larger whatever. But I think Diane, that to me, that sounds like a great, I know like the Boy Scouts are always looking to, cause it is a day of service for them. So they're like desperately looking for stuff to do. And I'm sure like me, even me as a mom, I would love to do something with my kid
that's meaningful. So I'm open to, if that's a piece of it, I would love to be a part of that piece. And then Shelly help you in any way on the other end as well. But I mean, I know it's coming up, but like we can whip something together. I don't know. I'm not feeling like, I guess my question is, is there going to be an event this year, like an in-person event, Shelly? Well, so I,
The three, Brianna and Francis and I sat down and shot up a bunch of strong events. The one event that I said that I could hands down take responsibility for was hosting a discussion of Dr. Joseph's The Sword and the Shield that compares and contrasts Malcolm X and Martin Luther King. And it was written by Dr. Joseph, who was on the race and equity, at the race and equity department at Tufts until just a few years ago. And the book exploded in 2012.
2020, 2021. And I didn't get a chance to check in with David about it. And I said, come co-host this. And he was like, why? You are more than qualified. And plus, I don't want to. So I'm doing 100 things. And he said, I know everyone's doing 100 things. But I don't want to bite off more than I can. And I also would like to do a few things really well instead of a bunch of things maybe less well. So I can offer.
we had talked about like a wine and cheese at the library, give folks as much time as we can to read the book. And then, and yes, this is an academic thing. Yes, it's an adult thing, but maybe the kids could be in the library. I don't know, but that's the piece I has. Okay. That is, that is for Saturday, the 14th. I was looking at that as part of
I know you were very excited about that piece of it because we had spoken about it numerous times looking at a timeframe. So exciting. This is where you come in. Can we drink wine at 11 o'clock in the morning? I mean, I don't know, like, you know, Shelley had a vision that she shared with me and it sounded great, but there are, you know, what time, right, would be best to have this activity?
I mean, yeah, I mean, I think that a mention of food brings people out more than a lack of food. So it may not have to be a wine and cheese, but if it's like a coffee and a muffin thing for 11, awesome. If it's a wine and cheese for five to seven, awesome. I just like, I don't like any meeting without food should just be an email. And that's just basically on everybody's t-shirt at this point. So it's bonding, it helps people chit chat. Yeah, I don't.
I feel less connected to the time of day than I do that just the structure of having it being the library and having something to munch on and also having it like hold a culture of just connecting over the material instead of being like testing folks to see how much they read or whatever, like we're going to need spark notes.
So what I can commit to doing for that day is because I have to get on the library's schedule ASAP, so I will reach out to Barbara about availability.
No, this is not for MLK Day. This is actually for Saturday before. This is for the Saturday. I think that's the 14th that we have in the notes, on my little notes here. So we're thinking two, are we still thinking two hours, Shelly? Is that the vision? So like a two hour? Yeah. Yeah. Look for 11 to one. And if that's not available, then I'll look for 11 to one for the day.
And I'll be able to get back to all, you know, get back to you more like via email that says, hey, we've got the library. And then. Yeah. For folks who have literacy stuff or language stuff or just don't have the time to read 280 pages, I also found an excellent keynote speech of Dr. Joseph discussing the book. And that feels maybe like a happy medium for folks who want to participate but can't give it.
What the book what they might want to or what it requires or whatever. Could we get child care and I would offer my services for child care. For it to be more accessible. I, when I was sickly, when I was at the.
arts and crafts thing, I jumped on whatever childcare option they had. And I was like, hey, want to come through to MLK? And they said, yes. So I got the right contact for the people at the high school who manage the volunteer hours. And this is for Saturday, for the 14th.
Yeah, that and I'm saying Francis, because I think let's try to remove as many barriers to participation as we can. And I think one barrier for me is, and I'm super privileged is childcare. So I can, I can provide childcare, and I can even provide for someone else or for me, but I'm happy to provide like, we can read books about MLK have MLK storytime and craftivity, while the parents are
learning on that deeper level? Without a doubt, I mean I think that's something that we had chatted about when we were briefly shooting the idea route was even seeing if the library does have something that they're going to be doing on that day that the little ones, you know, up until the different ages could become involved in.
I mean, so that's also a good reason to not plan for the evening. Like toddlers wanna be doing something at nine, really at 7.30, but people are prepared for this by like 9.30, 10 o'clock. So maybe a 10 to 12 or an 11 to one or something will allow people to bring their kids out.
Okay, so I've got my to-do list, which is to reach out to the library. Shelley, you're working on childcare. I will, in parallel, see if there are additional hands on deck for childcare as well. We're really going to push for an earlier time, more like an 11 to 1, so maybe like a brunchy type of session, see if the library is able to co-join us.
So I will work on this and hope to get back to all of you as soon as possible. And as soon as I get a yay. And the reason that I'm pushing it is because the city does want to partner with multiple facets within the community and ensure that we are providing as much communication as much equity and sharing of materials. I would like to see one calendar of events.
that for what is happening so that people have options and we do not have competing events on different days. That's how they used to do it at seven mile beach in the group, right? You have a place you go for Monday, a place you go for Tuesday, you know, so Kelly can bring the children over to me because I work late on Wednesday and I can't go out and Kelly can go out and enjoy herself. And I would really like to build that.
Me too, speaking my language. Yeah, but I just have to say something. The city of Medford, you were costing me a tremendous amount of money with all your activities on the weekend. I came to, you know, a weekend activity and I left needing like a whole nother job.
And everything that I purchased on behalf of everybody else has now ended up in my own closet. But it's fabulous. There's like so many different things to do here.
So that is great, and I feel like, Shelley, that that creates a perfect balance, because the West Method Community Center, West Method is historically the African-American space, and they really should be the ones to be taking the lead on this. And the city will then be able to support their plans on Sunday, and we're not rushing.
Yeah. You know, Shelley, I know that we had briefly talked about something for Friday, but when I thought about it, I was like, how is all this going to work? You know what we, what I can also get. Yeah. I, I, I just saw, I saw, I saw your mom today, by the way, Kelly, sorry, everybody needed to know. Yeah. So I just want to put it out there. Like I can, I got people that are Corey checked, like, so if
We can work our networks. I feel like we all probably have our own little networks. Say hi, Vera. Hi. I'm happy to help Frances, Shelley, and Kelly in any way. And I'm happy to lead. I love kids. I'm happy to lead an activity. If you need me to sign anything for a Corey check, I'll do that. But you can count me in to help as well.
Thank you. And that's wonderful. It gives the HRC an opportunity to stand and shine in its own contributions. I mean, we had a very, what I would say, a very ambitious dream. But as the year comes to a close, I just want to go to bed.
I don't know. I think that this is so much better. I don't know how we would have pulled off Friday, Saturday, Sunday, and Monday. I need to sort of like save that energy for the afternoon.
that I can fully support and partner with you for the full team and I can fully support. So as director, have you heard from WMCC? Yes, we actually met with them and that's why I needed to find out what we were doing first because I'm also being asked internally by the Office of Prevention and Outreach. So I don't know if there is something that they plan on doing, but I've asked everybody to be on hold because I kept remembering
Historically, the Human Rights Commission has always done this.
Okay. I, I'm wondering if I'm like pulling Diane's comments, um, two of our black owned businesses have reached out to me to talk about the small business facade grant that the city publicized. And I'm just wondering if there's any way that if we can design a day of service that informs supporting our local Medford black owned businesses, um,
because folks have said like, I don't hear from the city, I don't see the city. Yes, Steve's point is super important too. Yeah, let's think through that some more because when you say design a day of service, are you talking about adding another day in? I'm not quite sure. That would be on MLK Day directly. It's a national day of service and so that's when you
step out into your community and if there's a food drive that we need to do, if there's, you know, like, we would make blankets.
for shelters. So, you know, what are our, what are our needs in Medford that we can ask residents to come do? And is it, you know, going to where, you know, like the, where the elderly housing is and I don't know, getting involved in a program or helping in that regard, something. So, I mean,
There's also, to that exact point, when Kelly and I ran our panel, a lot of the kids said to us, like, look, the city shows up at school to talk to Black kids on MLK Day, and then we don't hear from you again, maybe for like three minutes during Black History Month, but that's it. So maybe
given that we have so little time and everyone is pulled in many directions, maybe there's a discussion of yes, a day of service, but how do we build that into our whole year and that there's a presentation on what it could look like for our city, but maybe it may or may not come to fruition for that day.
Steve has his hand up and put something in the chat that I was reading and also listening to you, Kelly. I mean, Shelley, because it really does, what Steve has to say is very, very important. I don't know about that, but my thought is that
service works best when there are partners. And it's the partners who are saying, here's what we need, whether it's a public housing tenant group or the West Medford Community Center, or name a half a dozen other very worthy groups or organizations that need assistance. I feel the,
the service should be driven by that organization, should come bottom up. And the HRC is a catalyst for sort of driving energy in that direction. But I would feel personally uncomfortable deciding what somebody needs and then mobilizing people to go there and help.
Right. Oh, you're so right, Steve. We need to partner with these, you know, with the leaders of these different organizations. And maybe we can start understanding what the organizations are and doing outreach. And then that just speaks to, you know, who are we as the Human Rights Commission and being able to have our elevator pitch to everyone.
about it and say like we're here, you know, and maybe there's an opportunity later for an umbrella, you know, because I think public service can be such a way to bring community together, you know, under the context of Medford serves or something like that, but
And I think it could be a win. I, you know, I'm wondering if that is why the Office of Prevention and Outreach has been wondering about timeframes of different activities. So I do, you know, I do need to get back to them because I kept telling them that they needed to hold off. Would it be, would it be all right if I got back to them to find out, because they are on the ground and they, don't forget there could be snow that day, Judy.
Yeah, there could be snow that day. Very true. You're right. They are on the ground and very much in tune with the community. So I could find out from them if they had something planned as a day of service and share that with the committee by email. Would you be open to that?
Steve, your hand is still up. I don't know if you had something to say. Oh, no. Okay. Would everybody be open to that with me providing an update via email? Sure. That works. Okay, great. And I'm sorry to push it along. I've got to make sure that I give Munia's section enough time. So you're all going to laugh, but here I was thinking that I was still waiting to hear about
The other funds requests, because in my mind, we've been still waiting to hear but the reality is that we weren't waiting to hear the funds, it was approved. But I was just too tired when I was reading the email. So I only thought that one thing was approved. So I am happy to announce that.
The commission has enough money for the things that were previously discussed. So, making the purchases of the portable table and folding chairs, so that when you are out and about at events you can have a proper presence. I'm going to defer to Kelly and Shelley to assist with the
logo and logo for the table cover, and the table skirt, because there is money assigned for that.
miscellaneous items that the commission might be interested in aka swag charge case everybody has a different different language share with me your thoughts and ideas because there is money for that and the idea would be that the logo would go on that so that when
members of the Commissioner out at an event tabling, you know, somebody takes something away and that thing is a reminder of an interaction of some sort of engagement.
And there are some, there are limited amount of funds. Oh, and this also includes printing our brochures. So yes, I can print brochures on my tiny little printer here, but you know, if we wanted to have like each a copy of like nice ones, you know, proper type set, we could do that. And some funds for,
to double check some funds for speaker support or engagement support for a conference. Because it's not fair to keep asking people to do things for free. But now I have to go back and look at what I wrote and make sure that did I just limit it to like a conference that the Human Rights Commission does, or does you know something that we do for like Martin Luther King
Junior Day count. I think it's more for like a human rights conference, if I remember. Shelley, I'm looking at you because I think that we were having a conversation. Yeah, we had said that in the name of the Day of Human Rights that we could host a seminar, something from the size of a seminar through a conference at some point.
So that is all approved, and that doesn't include some of the additional things that I requested for under the Office of Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion, i.e. accessibility-related things, money to pay, proper ASL interpreters. I will only use ASL interpreters through the Mass. Commission for the deaf and hard of hearing. There is a two-week leeway.
Well, Steve, it's a little bit broken down. I would say that just for the commission alone. It's almost 5000 dollars. However, remember. That does not include.
The accessibility piece that was under the Office of Diversity, Equity and Inclusion. Right. And then it doesn't include some of the other pieces that I, you know, requested separately, like if the commission has a project right that they really are focused on and want to work on.
Everybody's already working. I might need, you know, the commission might benefit from a short term intern for a month that's dedicated to that project. That money was requested under the Office of Diversity, Equity and Inclusion.
Oh, so the commission. I did do 2 different types. So the commission does have money for. Event support.
Well, the Office of Diversity, Equity and Inclusion does have money for event support. So if we wanted to do like light brunch at the library for Martin Luther King Day, it is actually listed. Again, please just bear in mind that these are ARPA fund requests. So once this money's done, it's not gonna be re-upped.
Anybody have any questions about that before I turn the floor over to Munir? Local restaurants. I mean, it's great to know that local restaurants have donated food, but it's even better if I know the who and the where, you know?
because it's easy to go back to people that have done it before. But I don't know who those people are. And as a city employee, I actually technically cannot make the requests. In the past, at least, before COVID, there were two places in Medford that contributed food. One was, I think, Chicken and Rice guys. I don't even know if they're
still open in Medford. The other place was the, I think it was an Pakistani or Indian restaurant in Medford Square. They donated some food as well. But I suppose somebody has to ask. Also one year Snappy Patty's.
Is that how it's called? Although it wasn't very good.
And then there's a place on Main Street that everybody loves and I don't remember the name of it but they donate like massive amounts of food if I remember. So if somebody wants to take on securing the donations of food for the
events at the library. I do believe that we can have food there beyond just the muffins and stuff. That would be great. I cannot take that on. As a city employee, I cannot request donations, so. Are we saying it's definitely going to be at the library or do we have to really finalize that to see if that's available?
I'm going to email Barbara beg and plead, but I am hoping that there will be space on that Saturday. It's very short event. So I'm going to go first choice. I'm going to go for the morning. Right. And second choice, it would have to be what they have available. If the morning that we want is not available.
I'll reach out to Bob's once the library confirms. Thank you. And if they'll make a donation. Okay, great. And if you don't mind, like once you start your conversation, Munia, I'm going to go off camera and see if I can reach somebody at the library just to find out, so that at least I can report to you a, you know,
So I just, I think that asking for donations is an understandable approach, but I also think it's very time consuming. Um, and I think if we want to evolve into an entity that can throw multiple events a year with a version of a formula and a version of a budget that's come in years past, it might make more sense to make use of these dollars and sort of get a sense of
what something like this would take fully paid for. And keeping in mind that these are ARPA dollars and they won't come our way again. But it just feels faster to just know that you can pay for something than have to make an appeal, I think. Does that make sense? Okay.
Why don't you think about that? I'm going to turn it over, Shelley, to Munir. Sure. Because it looks like it's another robust discussion. I'll go off screen and just make sure the date is available at the library before we go ahead with all this planning. And it's not. So I'll be right back listening to you. It's over to you, Munir. OK, thanks. I mean, I don't know how much of a robust discussion this will be. But the thought occurred to me that
If folks have had a chance to look at, at least in more detail, at the recommendations that came from the Safe Medford discussion and the notes that were sent out. So I'm just trying to think of what the next steps we would like to
take or do as far as these recommendations are concerned. Now, it's so my thought was that if people had, I mean, there are certain recommendations that involve the city. And we obviously don't have control over that we can only ask. But then there are other recommendations that are more specific to the role of the commissioners themselves.
what they can do, how much time they can spend, you know, the various activities. So I was hoping that people would come out, and it doesn't have to be done today, it could be done over the next whatever, meeting or two, think of what priorities they think are important
that they can bring forth and we can have a discussion on how practical or, you know, where we would want to go with these recommendations. So that was my thought on that. And I, you know, I welcome comments from anybody just to sort of start this discussion going.
I mean, I was so in for it. It was, it, to me, it sounded great. I, I, and also we don't have anything else to work with. So my thought is like, we go with this and I'm, I'm of course, interested and curious and open to hearing other people's ideas and thoughts. But to me, it resonated with me. It feels like a path forward.
I mean, are we, I mean, I was hoping to start talking about individual recommendations and prioritizing them. Because, I mean, to put it mildly, this is a very ambitious goal that was set out by these recommendations. And I'm a practical type of person, and I like to see
you know, what specific roles that we think that we can actually all agree upon, and then see where we want to move from there. I mean, obviously, at some point, we might even decide, okay, well, we need to contact the city council and have them look at recommendations for rewriting or reconsidering, you know, the existing
write up about the Human Rights Commission. But again, I mean, I mean, if people think this is a reasonable approach,
then maybe if we can't do it today, maybe starting next time we pick out, have everybody pick out whatever three or four things that they think are really, really resonate with us and see if we can move forward on them without waiting for any, they say, any real change coming from the city council.
What is the change we're waiting for from the city council. Well, I mean, I mean, theoretically, there's an ordinance that, you know, it's, it's old and it's been around for a few years.
If we were going to really work on the recommendations that the Safe Metro Committee suggested, eventually you'd have to have the city council approve a different ordinance.
So, but rather than wait for that, I was thinking that we could act on the recommendations first that involve us, just the commissioners, and then we can later on move forward to see if we can rewrite or modify the ordinance and then
contact the city council to see if they agree on that and then move forward that way. Chair, please, I think Steve has his hand up. I don't want to be running. Go ahead, Steve. Thank you. I just want to remind folks that there are two parts to the recommendation.
The first are four directions, goals. I forget what we call them, roles, four roles. And the second part are, I don't know, a dozen or so operational suggestions. And we did it in that sequence.
So the HRC could consider first the roles that it wants to occupy, and then whether any of these operational recommendations make sense. So my suggestion is to tackle
If the four roles identified by safe Medford are what the HRC now wants to pursue as major, major roles or goals.
Well, I'm happy to say that, you know, the community engagement piece really resonated with me and I looked through all of it. And Steve, I'm just going to use a word that you shared, I think that the community engagement piece that getting the pulse of the community and giving ourselves more visibility.
And, and then learning and understanding what everyone wants, but also setting up partnerships across the city. And that's partnerships with the Medford police, you know, because I think that when we have positive partnerships across the city, you know, and it, you know, and I'm just using, you know, the police as an example, you know, and then partnerships with our nonprofit organization, um,
I think that that'll raise our visibility and we'll understand the needs of the entire Medford community and all of the demographics more. And so, I know that just the very first one to tackle community engagement really resonated with me and I would love to really help in that area. And then I think because I knew, I just,
felt there was also a strong governance piece that was just coming up throughout with, you know, who are we, what are our roles and responsibilities? And so that just speaks to us all determining and deciding together, you know, who, you know, who and what is the human rights commission for the city of Medford. And then, you know, I look at,
you know, all of us, like who, who do, who do we want to be, you know, even before we bring it to the city councilors and then, you know, I would love to hear Francis, you know, and she, she Buckley answer the question of, you know, like what, what is a thriving, successful human rights commission to you? I think Francis must be on the phone, but I mean, I I'd like to hear what your thoughts on that chief Buckley.
So, thank you. And so I was, while I was just doing this I was just reading the recommendations, and I also have had my trying to pull up my responses to the, to the survey and the question asked me to put forth. I feel very strongly that the first aspect of the educational pieces is extremely important part of the Human Rights Commission, and it into that educational.
role that the Human Rights Commission can play. We can reach out to a number of members of our community. It's not just, you know, an adult-centered. It could be focused with children and youth, and it could be centered with the police department, as mentioned, and other city organizations, and then the religious organizations. And that sort of partnership can grow in the education rules. And it's essentially what the MLK Day, in one sense, represents, right? There's an educational part to that that we invite people
So I'm all for that, and I'm very willing to participate in any part of that. And that, to me, to answer the question, is kind of what I keyed on when I answered the survey, what should the role of the Human Rights Commission be? Now, I do look at the other part, and this is kind of extending the answer. I really worry about some of the things that were suggested there, because it's a lot of work.
It's just five or six of us here, right? And it's a tremendous task and it's all sort of important. And I don't know if it should be built in steps or like take that as an agenda and each year have a mission or a goal to kind of accomplish certain things that are on that. But if we look at it and just simply read that whole report and say, hey, we want to adopt it as a whole and try to accomplish it.
I don't like doing those things, because we'd set up we're setting ourselves up for failure, and that's not what we need to do for it but if you're asking me what how I would envision this human rights commission in the future we've had this conversation, you know, months ago when we first started this and how do we, we take the next steps and define our role, it is about education and community involvement and partnerships and that that's, that's what I see that that's.
It's what we strive, even on the police department. We do that at different levels, right? But not necessarily always on a human rights level. And I think we could take that next step. Years ago, when we first started pre-COVID, we talked about holding a, maybe in the city hall chambers, but have some guest speakers that talk about certain issues and answer questions back and forth, and whether that was just a police community type event, but it would be hosted by the Human Rights Commission. I still thought, I still think,
back on that and say, No, that's not a bad idea to host these sort of events where the police can answer questions we can have guest speakers and talk about different roles and why police, you know, have certain policies and rules in place and what the laws are certain things and it's hosted by the Human Rights Commission it's a, it's kind of bringing communities together, and through the Human Rights Commission so.
That's my thoughts, anyway, as to what I envisioned. But secondarily to that, I just think there's a lot there in that document that I'm worried that we're not going to be able to do a lot of that. And it puts a lot of pressure on different departments, too, right? And it demands on supplying information on a regular basis. But just my thoughts. Thank you. Francis, I was just asking, oh,
Is she? All right. I would just love to know, you know, and Francis, I think she's relatively new to the city. Shelly, she's been in her role for a year or two years. No. I think she'll be coming up on a year come April. Yeah. Yeah.
Um, one piece that I might add to what's already been said is that I think it's really important to know our own city really well, but also to build a discussion of our identity in the context of
the Medford area of Metro Boston of what our state looks like to just start to build concentric circles of who we are and why and connect thinking to larger systems. So we don't get stuck in the Medford new show all the time. I mean I I agree with Jack that
there were a lot of things that these, you know, a lot of recommendations. And that's why I was hoping that we could look at them and say to ourselves, yeah, these are the most important, at least as far as we're concerned, personally, these are the most important things we want to concentrate upon and then act on them maybe this coming year. One thing's come, one thought that comes to mind is
the participation of the Human Rights Commission in meetings of other city organizations to bring a human rights perspective to these. So that's sort of part of, in a sense, that's educational, as Jack said. So that's one thought that occurred to me. I don't know, I mean, it will take a lot of work. And at some point, I might say,
Hmm, I can't do that. Get a commissioner who has the power and the energy to do more, which is fine. I mean, but that's my two cents on this. And, you know, this document is a great opportunity to create a one and a three and a five year plan, right? And then as new leadership comes on board, they can adapt it.
but it is a very good starting point and we can do what's actionable. We can start to work on what's actionable and accomplishable. And some of it's really big stuff that is a little way beyond our control. And so some of it's aspirational, and then some of it's right in front of us and doable and very tactical.
If I can add one more point and I do agree with that last part some of it is aspirational, but if we, if we want to attract more commissions, we should have a, we should be able to answer some of the basic questions where are we going what do we want to do and I think we fell into that trap.
over the last couple of months trying to find new commissions, right? I don't think we were there kind of explaining ourselves very well to potential commissioners. And a document such as this, you know, and maybe we focus on it here and there, may be beneficial, right? What is it that you're trying to do? What is it you're trying to accomplish? If we didn't have an identity, it's harder to find people who will be willing to participate.
Hi everyone, I'm sorry I'm sort of late, half late to this party. I'm sure you got my message. The 14th is available in regards to our previous conversation and the time frame is 1.30 to 3.30. Diane, I heard you say my name just as I was unmuting myself and unfortunately I didn't get
the rest of what you were saying, but has your question being answered? Yes and no. I wanted to hear from you and Chief Buckley, to have a thriving, inclusive, diverse Medford with a thriving Human Rights Commission
What is that Human Rights Commission to you? What does that look like and feel like to you, especially as someone who's new to your role coming up on a year? What are your hopes and dreams for us to accomplish?
So I don't, I see myself as a liaison from the city sitting on the commission and lending support where I can. So it's not really my dream. Now, if you want to know about my experience of what has made human rights commissions committee successful in the past, it is the self identification, the understanding of the
limitations right and it sounds like a horrible word limitations but when you understand what your limitations are you actually realize where your power is and you can leverage your power being your skill sets to move things along that are within your power to do so so you create more of a step-by-step way of accomplishing goals
reaching goals, things of that nature. I mean, I think that it is also very, very different in a community environment, such as a city town versus a business corporation. But very important to be neutral. You have to keep the politics and the noise and everything else that is going on in the world out of the real focus of what you're trying
And then you also have to think about, you know, things that you're doing, how do they tie into the real broad based human rights, when you start talking about the United Nations interpretation of human rights. And, you know, this we have nine people on the committee as commissioners.
And so you could end up with nine different passions ring. So, my job is to be the seamstress yet again, and we have a beautiful fabric that represents all those nine different passions.
to help continue to move the mission of the commission forward. So it's not so straightforward. Steve, I do see your hand. Diane, I hope I've answered some of your question, but I did notice that Judy did put something in the chat. And I didn't know if Judy, you wanted to,
Judy said, would it make sense to discuss the operational recommendations first? You want me to speak to that? I thought you just made an excellent point, Frances, which I cannot restate very well, but that you have to know who you are and what your strengths are, what your numbers are, and so on before you... You just said it very beautifully, but...
That's why I'm wondering if you, if it would make sense for the commission to first decide, does it want more members? Does it want, you know, whatever is involved in those operational recommendations. And then get that down and then go from there with a better understanding of the capacity of the group.
That's all. Steve, you had your hand up. Thank you, Judy. Steve, you had your hand up. Yeah, thank you. I come at this exactly from the opposite direction as Judy, although that's a valid approach. If I was a commissioner, I would want to know what the goals of the commission are and agree to that, recognizing that doing it all is impossible.
It may even be impossible with 15 members. You can't do it all. That doesn't mean these aren't the goals or there aren't goals for the HRC to sort of use as guides for specific activities. All the, you know, there's a short paragraph
explaining each goal or role, and then there are a bunch of suggestions. I'm not sure that the HRC needs to go into every one of these suggestions and think that it needs to do all this. It is impossible, and I appreciate people's concern about that. But from my perspective, it would be helpful to know, here are our goals, whether it's number one, community engagement and education,
And that's it, whether it's all four or some other goals that we haven't considered. I think that would be my first task. What do we want to accomplish as a human rights commission?
And once we're clear on the broad goals, we don't have to define each one or give all these examples, but then to say, all right, let's look at these recommendations, which will operationalize these goals. What makes sense here? Which one do we want to tackle first? Which ones are more important given prioritizing these goals? Let's say the priority is education engagement.
What would enhance that? What would implement that? What would enable that to happen? And I don't think anyone in Safe Medford thought that the HRC, tonight, tomorrow, next year even, this would be the work plan. We completely understand that. It's totally unrealistic. But you do need a map.
or at least some guideposts to say, here's where we're going. And I love Diane's notion, and I think I heard this at the last meeting, that once you're clear about what our goals are, you then can say, well, here are the steps to take this year. And maybe here are the steps to take a few years down the road, which we can evaluate periodically.
And, you know, proceed recognizing that resources are limited and you're not going to be able to do everything, but we're going to, the group is going to move in that direction. That's how I personally make sense to me, but just one voice. Thank you, Steve. Sorry. And I was not smiling, laughing at you. I was laughing at Santa's little helper over there.
I love when people laugh at me. Thank you so much. So, we, it's, I don't know, you know, where we are with the conversation I have a sense that we might have to pick up at the next meeting because we are at six.
Well, now at 6.59. And I just want to run by quickly just to make sure that I have my asks correct. Library date check, that's done. And I need to follow up and send an email to two people to get that fully confirmed. So I'll handle that before I leave this evening.
Did I hear right that the commission is saying no to requesting donations of food items for that day? I just want to be clear that that's off the list. Is that what I'm hearing? I think I read some people don't feel comfortable asking for food donations from the various restaurants and some feel that it will just be too much, too time consuming.
I don't think that it's off the table. I just think some of us might be better with that task than others. So maybe I should just simply ask, is there anybody that is going to be asking for food donations? I can't do it. Chief Buckley can't do it. Okay. I think Steve is willing. Thank you so much, Steve. So Steve, circle back with me so that I can help to offset like what you're not able to get, able to get food and not able to get the drinks and I can use the funds to get the drinks.
Okay, thank you. I'm willing to make a few phone calls. But before doing that, I'd like to have more specifics to say, all right, here's roughly what we're expecting. Here's the timeframe and things like that. So but, but, but I'm not personally able to go out and solicit donations from restaurants, but I'm willing to make a few phone calls.
know if yeah if you're able to make some phone calls when you get the specifics that you know that is great as well, I just wanted to make sure that I was we were all heading in the same direction. Okay, so that's that's.
I changed the I updated the meeting minutes that's already gone to city clerk. And then after this meeting, I'll be walking down the hard copy whether any other asks for me that I missed when I was on the phone with the library.
So it looks like we are not going to be meeting again until the year 2023, which, wow, exactly. I can't believe that it's already around the corner. So I personally want to take this time to wish you a joyful celebration of whatever it is that you celebrate. And even- I think Kelly's waiting on sharing something. Oh, sorry. I'm so sorry, Frances. I just wanted to ask, should we like have a,
What's it called? What are those little committees called? Thank you, subcommittee for the MLK, because if we are going to work on it, I don't think we can wait until our next meeting. So I don't know if that's
No, make sure, make sure you don't violate open meeting laws. So the subcommittee, that would be the way that we wouldn't violate open meeting laws, but you're going to work together on stuff. Does that make sense? But if you have more, if you have a majority, I think that was the issue when the air, if I'm not mistaken, when I came on board, that was the issue.
Muneer and Judy ran into when they formed the subcommittee for safe method. Well, I mean, if there are three people working on it, I think it'll be perfectly all right. OK. Is it just is it you? Is it you, Diane and Shelley? Is that who you're thinking?
Yeah, just for the library event that we're talking about. Yeah, that's it. Yeah, perfect. I think that works for me guys if it works for you too, and everyone else. Yeah. So that way we can meet and actually do other stuff in between the meetings. Yeah. Okay, great. And I'm open to receiving emails like updates Francis how this didn't work we need this, you know, like, I don't, you know, I don't count in.
Francis, you had mentioned sort of coordinating a calendar, one calendar amongst WMCC, us, and others. If Kelly and Diane and I are spearheading this library event, will you be the one who communicates the sort of fruition, get it on the calendar, and tell the other organizations that this is what HRC will be doing?
There'll be nothing held at this time that has to do with Martin Luther King celebration, because it will conflict with HRC it will again, instead of bringing unity, it will create a split and force people to have to choose.
No, no, I hear that. I'm just wondering who am, do I need to take responsibility for communicating that? Everybody wants a calendar that is going to showcase all the different events that are being held by all the different entities, right? So if we need help with graphics, that help can come from the city as well. We can ask comms team to help with like the graphics, the design, the
you know, the social media blast. So that way, if it's a calendar that's been sent out, then boom, the city is supporting as equitably as possible. And it will showcase the Human Rights Commission.
If you were asking that you, Shelley, and Diane be named mainly, then I think that that is a conversation that you need to have with other members of the commission. I can't make that. No, no. I'm just asking if...
The other potential organizations will learn about this event ahead of when it gets posted in public spaces, so that they are not booking the time. Yes, because if somebody else attempts to approach the city to work in partnership for this specific date and this specific time, it's going to be a no.
You know, it's not going to work. We can't support two events. And what if there are organizations who don't approach the city? I wouldn't know what those organizations were planning on doing, so I couldn't support those organizations anyway. The city can only support what it is aware of. So I would still, the city would still be supporting where it has made its commitment.
Got it. Anything else?
All right, so I want to wish you all a fabulous whatever it is that you celebrate and if you don't celebrate just by being up as a cause for celebration. Peace, love, and harmony. Good health to all of you as we transition I'm sure Chief Buckley I'll be seeing you soon.
And, you know, same old, same old for all of us. We can celebrate the Human Rights Commission. How about that?
Yes, we can celebrate the Human Rights Commission and a happy belated International Human Rights Day that happens on December 10th. So when you ask about my dreams, Diane, it's, you know, things like International Human Rights Day, the City of Medford Human Rights Commission in collaboration with, you know, whether we do it regionally or whatever, or statewide, right? A big event, big conference.
But that's the dream, you know, it's not an Oscar. So that's it. Okay, thank you. Good night, everybody. Thank you, everyone. Good night, everybody. Bye.