So, Daria, if you could read the preamble.
Somebody's playing something in the background.
Okay.
All right.
Just give me a second to read it.
Okay, so pursuant to Governor Baker's March 12th, 2020, order suspending certain provisions of the open meeting law, general law chapter 38, chapter 18, and the governor's March 15th, 2020, order imposing strict limitations
oops, on the number of people that may gather in one place.
This meeting of the Medford License Commission will be conducted via remote participation to the greatest extent possible.
Specific information, the general guidelines for remote participation by members of the public and or parties who are right and or requirement to attend this meeting can be found on the City of Medford website at www.medfordma.org.
For this meeting, members of the public who wish to listen or watch the meeting may do so by accessing the meeting link contained herein, not in person attendance, no in person attendance of members of the public will be permitted.
but every effort will be made to ensure that the public can adequately access the proceedings in real time via technological means.
In the event that we're unable to do so despite the best efforts, we'll post on the city of Medford or the media community or media community media website an audio or video recording transcript or other comprehensive record of proceedings as soon as possible after the meeting.
That was small writing.
Thank you.
Thank you, Daria.
So the meeting will come to order and the first item on the agenda, Daria.
Okay.
So the first, second, it will be to approve minutes for March 17th, 2020 license commission meeting.
I'd make a motion to approve the minutes.
As presented, I'll second that motion to approve those minutes.
All those in favor.
Hi.
Okay.
Thank you.
Next will be a representative from the porch.
will present an application for alteration of premises at their establishment located at 175 Rivers Edge Drive, Medford Mass.
Is Jonathan on here?
Anybody from the porch?
Okay, we'll hold that one aside.
Okay.
The next one is Real Gusto.
Anybody from Real Gusto?
Okay, I guess we'll hold that one off to the side, Daria.
Okay.
Bistro 5.
Anybody from Bistro 5?
Yeah, he's here.
Nice to see you.
Good to see you guys.
So we have your plan.
Is your plan any different than what it was last year, Vito?
Internet is a little spotty here.
Okay, might be better now.
Thank you.
Did you have a question?
Yeah, it's just one question for me.
Is your plan any different than the one you presented last year?
Same as last year, but last year we did have an issue with the barriers where we put a trellis.
have to take those down.
But we have to do something else this year to separate the dining hall from the barriers.
So what we basically want to do now is put along the sidewalk, put basically just flowers, really.
But the flowers would be just kind of like a continuous planter.
But besides that, I'd say same exact spot.
Same number of tables?
Yeah, same number of tables.
Thank you.
Yeah, that's it.
Okay.
And I assume what you're working out with the trellis, you're working out with the building department or somebody else?
I was saying the issue that you're having with the trellises, you're working that out with somebody at City Hall?
Yes, I think the traffic commissioner was here, and I will be in Todd, actually, I think.
And then, yeah, I will be talking to him about it, what I'm gonna plan on doing, so I can get it approved through him first, and then can go on with whatever.
Fine.
Yeah, because the main thing, we just need a little bit of privacy, really, you know, as long as, without obstructing any view, that's really it.
Understood, understood.
I don't have any other questions.
Yeah, no, I don't either.
I'm looking over the application and I remember this from last year and I don't know that the trellis is really in our domain anyway to comment on.
So, I don't have any issues with the gym.
Okay, so motion to approve the license for Bistro 5.
All those in favor?
Aye.
Thank you.
All right, good luck.
Good luck.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Next on the agenda, Daria.
Sorry guys.
Didn't realize I was on mute.
Um, next one is Bertucci's, but they have not sent me an application.
Okay.
And I send them a reminder last night as well.
So I haven't received anything from them.
That's fine.
I think they might have outdoor dining, but I just got to check.
I just haven't had the chance to come around it.
Yeah, Petucci's does have outdoor dining by means of their own regular permit.
Okay.
So with alcohol.
Right.
Okay.
So they're kind of like Regina's Pizza.
So they're all set.
Right.
That's right.
Okay.
So we'll keep them out.
I kind of figured that, but wasn't 100% sure.
That's okay.
Next one is C-Bar.
C-Bar?
I'm sorry.
C-Bar.
Yep.
Anybody from C-Bar?
Anybody present from SEBA?
Hearing and seeing none, I guess we'll put that on hold.
Yep, okay.
Next one is FIORI Italy.
FIORI Italy?
Anybody present from FIORI Italy?
Yep, he's here.
He's just on mute.
Andrea, you're on mute.
You're gonna unmute yourself.
Okay.
Okay, thank you.
Just a question as I asked the prior petitioner, is there any change from your outdoor dining plan than what it was last year?
No, it's the same, the same.
Gotcha.
Okay, have the barricades been installed already for you?
No.
Okay, all right.
All right, so same plan as last year?
Yeah, we have a lot of people calling that if they can sit outside.
Right, hopefully the weather stays in our favor to do that.
Yeah, we deserve it.
Yeah, you do.
No question about it.
No, I mean, everyone, everyone deserves it.
No, I know.
I know what you mean.
We all do.
Everybody needs a break.
I get it.
Especially from this COVID.
Of course.
I don't have any other questions.
No, we just met about the premises and we're familiar with that and how that worked out last year.
And so same as Jim.
I would make, Jim, I'd make a motion to accept the alteration of premises here.
Yep.
So all those in favor.
I oppose none.
Your license has been granted.
Very good.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thanks.
The next one is Carol's Carol's restaurant.
Maury.
Good afternoon.
Mary, Mary, you got to unmute yourself.
Mari, you're on mute.
There we go.
Now you got it.
How are we doing today?
Good, thanks.
How are you doing?
Doing well, thanks, Jimmy.
That's good.
Mari, just the same question I had for the prior petitioners.
Any change in your outdoor dining plan?
Everything's going to be the exact same.
Thank you very much.
I have no further questions.
No, I remember it last year.
No, there's no issues with that.
You guys had it along the bridge.
When will you start it, Mari?
Uh, I think we can start on the 15th.
So I wasn't permitting.
Okay, good.
All right.
Uh, I'll make a motion to approve the license as presented all in favor.
Yep.
Okay.
Good.
Mari.
Good luck to you.
Thank you very much.
Nice to see you as well.
Thank you.
Next one is Salvatore's anybody from Salvatore is present.
Thank you, Denise.
Denise, same question as before.
Any change from the outdoor dining from last year?
Same number of tables?
Everything's the same.
That makes it easy.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Ben, any questions?
No, I was just looking for the Salvatore's application.
Is it in there?
Yes, it should be, yep.
Okay.
No, I don't.
And it's in the back still?
Yep.
Yeah, just waiting for the barriers from the city.
Yeah.
No, seems like a good place for it again.
And, uh, I don't have any further questions on it.
Great motion to approve the, uh, license for Salvatore's would be an order all those in favor.
Great.
Thank you.
Thank you, Denise.
Good luck.
Okay.
Next one is Asian taste, Asian taste.
Anybody from Asian Taste wants to speak on behalf of the license?
Nobody from Asian Taste?
Okay, we'll put that one aside, Daria.
Okay, and then Tanak?
I know Alvaro's on.
Yup, Tanak.
Yup.
Alvaro?
Can't hear you, hold on.
You're on mute.
Yup, thank you.
Alvaro, same question as the prior petition.
Is any change in your outdoor seating capacity than it was last year?
We did not apply last year.
We did not have any other city.
Thank you.
How many tables do you have under this scenario?
We have, we applying for three on each of the parking spots.
So we're looking to have two parking spots and then two tables on each side of the windows.
Fine.
So, so eight?
So there will be three, six, eight.
Yes.
Has the city approved the two parking spaces?
I submit the application and this is what I have first.
I think this meeting, I'm still waiting on them.
That's fine.
Do we know anything about that Daria?
I'm not sure Miranda.
Yeah, we're reviewing tomorrow internally.
But yeah, so far, I haven't heard any issues from transportation on the parking places.
So far, so good.
So Alvaro, the only thing is we'd like to have the city on board before we issue the permit for the outdoor dining.
We just don't want to give you a permit for the outdoor dining and then find out the city, I'm not suggesting they do, that they have a... So my suggestion for getting around it, in the future diary, we should make sure that the city's on board with every application before they come before us.
And I understand we're trying to move this on a fast pace for everybody, and I get that.
Um, so my suggestion is we approve it subject to the city and the traffic department approving or ever else Miranda has to do that.
Um, you know, being on board with that, if that's okay with you, Alvaro.
Yeah, that's totally fine.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, um, so we'll do this, uh, approval subject to, uh, diarrhea, getting confirmation from the city, um, that they've approved the two parking spaces being dedicated for your outdoor dining.
That okay, Ben.
Yeah, that makes sense.
That's what I think we had to do last year a couple times.
So this is kind of the same for you since this is your first year.
So that's, but I'm in favor of it.
Uh, yeah, as long as you can get all the barriers up and in place and it's just safe for all your, um, customers, that seems, seems great.
Yep.
So a motion to approve the, um, the outdoor dining license for, uh, uh, Tanosh would be an order all those in favor.
Hi.
I, again, Daria is subject to the city's approval, okay?
I just have one very important question though.
Is it Tanach or is it Tanach?
Tanach.
Tanach, yeah.
Good to know.
Debate at my house.
I love it too.
Thank you, that sounds good.
Thank you guys and be safe.
Thank you.
Thank you, you too.
Thank you, Alvaro.
Bye.
Thank you.
Next on the agenda.
Well, that's it.
We have a couple more people on.
We have three people on, but I have no idea where they're from.
Can you guys let us know whoever is on?
I'm from Sabar, Mexico.
Yeah, Sabar, okay.
Oh, Sabar, okay, hold on.
Yeah, so go back to the Sabar one.
Do you have that application, Daria?
Yes.
Okay.
So, say bar is your outdoor dining plan, any different than it was last year.
No.
Same number of tables.
Yeah, they remember tables.
And I assume in every one of these instances diary I'm making an assumption.
And maybe I shouldn't make the assumption that the city is signed off on all of these that we're looking at.
They're gonna, so like Miranda said, we're gonna talk about it, all of us tomorrow.
And then I think we're gonna probably hear back on the approval next week, but I'm not gonna issue anything till we get a final approval from the mayor.
Well, I thought we scheduled these meetings so that it was subsequent to the city's decision.
This week was a weird one.
We wanted to meet before you guys did, but half of our team was busy.
Okay.
But we've been talking and I don't think they're,
I would have flagged anything for you all.
I got it.
So I think the only thing diary is I don't want to hold these public hearings and inconvenience the customers and think they have a license when in fact, you know, it's preemptive, it could be preempted by the city's action.
So let's in the future, unless there's something happening on the day, you know, let's hold until the city approves.
Um, all of the, um, barricades and whatever's necessary, and then we take our action.
Okay.
So just to be consistent, what we will do with say bar is what we've done with the prior, uh, applicants as well as we will hold all of the applications today, pending approval, uh, of the city by the city.
And the city should notify you if there's an issue, uh, before next week diary.
Okay.
Yep.
Ben, any questions for Saba?
No.
Yeah.
All right.
I have no further questions.
A motion to approve would be an order.
All those in favor.
Aye.
Opposed.
None.
Your license has been approved subject to the city approving your outdoor dining plan.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Thank you, sir.
Good luck.
Yep.
Next on the agenda, going back to the agenda, Daria.
Those that weren't here before.
Stephen Napolitano.
Hi, yes, Stephen Napolitano.
Daria, email.
I can't hear you.
Can you hear me?
Yes, now I can.
Yeah, now we can.
With Pizzeria Regina.
Okay.
At 44 station landing, I had emailed Daria just want to make sure that everything is all set.
Yes, yes, you're all set.
So you have outdoor dining already as part of your license.
That is correct.
Yes.
Yeah.
So you are all set.
I thank you for coming to this meeting.
But there's no need.
Thank you for participating.
Yes, you're all set.
Thank you.
So then we're just to go back.
Who wasn't here that was on your agenda?
Could you just
We just talked about those names?
Yeah, it was the Porch, Real Gusto, Bistro 5 we had.
Real Gusto, they're not doing an outdoor dining setup.
They're just using their balconies, I believe, this year.
They're not going to do any parking spaces or outdoor dining.
So it'll be like private premises.
Oh, I think, Miranda, I think they did the same thing last year, but they still had to come in front of us.
Sorry, I was just letting you guys know.
Yeah, because he did reach out to me and I told him that he still has to fill out the application and he did, so I don't know why he didn't.
And the reason for him filling out the application is because what he's licensed for,
It's just inside, yeah.
Right, just inside.
And I explained that to him, like, yeah.
Okay.
It was the same issue that we had last year, trying to explain that it was still, even though it's on the property, it still has to be.
Correct.
The license was just for inside.
That's fine.
And who was the other one, Daria?
Hold on, Fiora.
Take your time.
So, Sabar we had, Fiorita we had, Carol, Salvatores, Asian Taste was not on here, right?
Yeah.
Uh, yeah.
So those, so it's porch, porch, real gusto and Asian taste.
Okay.
So I would suggest diarrhea.
You, you contact them and tell them that, you know, they were on the agenda today.
No action was taken because nobody appeared and we will put them on next week's agenda.
Okay.
Um, and, uh, but they have to appear.
Yep.
Okay.
All right.
Miranda, any issues with any of the applications as they're coming through?
Do you see any issues?
Nothing so far.
I think it's all looking good.
We have a handful of new places, which is exciting.
Yeah.
I know one is Neighborhood Kitchen.
That was a new one.
That's a new one.
And Daria's in contact with the owner because they need like a full new license, I believe for beer and wine.
But yeah, Tenoch is new.
We have a few places that aren't going to do alcohol that are just like little shops.
So yeah, it's looking good.
So far so good.
Good, good.
Okay.
All right.
So is it next week, Daria, or is the next meeting?
I'm just looking it up as I'm asking you the question.
Hold on.
I'm trying to pull up on my zone too.
No, I don't have it on the 22nd.
Um, hold on, hold on.
Yeah.
Hold on.
So the next meeting is going to be on Thursday, April 22nd.
Okay.
But, so that's what I was gonna ask you guys.
Hold on, one, two, three.
Our regular day is usually the 21st.
So should we, should I still keep the 22nd?
I would like to consolidate them all into one.
Yes, yes, yes.
So just do one on Thursday.
Okay.
That's right, on Wednesday.
On Wednesday.
Wednesday, the 21st.
Okay.
Because that'd be a normally, regularly scheduled meeting.
Yeah.
Right, so let's bring in the outdoor dining on the 21st after the regular scheduled meeting.
Immediately following that.
So tell them 1 o'clock.
1 o'clock?
1 o'clock, yep.
1 o'clock on the 21st.
So it's all in the same meeting?
Yep.
Then we'll skip the 22nd.
Okay.
22nd.
Oh yeah.
Meeting on the 22nd.
Yeah, because we had that one on too.
Yep.
All right.
I just changed my zoom.
So I'll send that around one.
I sent out an email.
So the 25 makes sense.
Yep.
And we'll have somebody else, um, doing an actual applications, like one of our, one of our, um, clubs I think is changing a manager.
So that's perfect.
Yep.
No problem.
Any other business to come before the commission?
No, I think that's it.
Okay.
All right.
Motion to adjourn would be in order.
I'll make a motion to adjourn.
Great.
Thank you very much.
Thanks for all your help, Ben.
Yeah.
Thank you.
No problem.
Thanks guys.
Sorry, I was a little late guys.
That's all right.
No problem.
We'll just stock your pay.
I know.