We probably don't need to live stream this one to YouTube since it's going to be an executive session.
iPhone, that's you, George, right?
It is, Zach, yep.
Great.
Could you make iPhone a co-host, please?
Thank you.
All right, we'll give Councilor Seng a second.
And Councilor Callahan.
I think that's everyone.
Great.
All right.
Medford City Council Committee of the Whole, March 4th, 2026 is called to order.
Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Councilor Kelly.
Present.
Councilor Lemi.
Councilman Lane present.
Councilor Scott belly present.
Councilor saying present.
Vice President was our president.
President is present seven present none absent the meeting is called to order action and discussion items 26053 submitted by the mayor litigation strategy to attract her talk the city of Medford.
request entering executive session per mass general law section 21 a three votes may be taken.
This is an executive session pursuant to general law chapter 30 a 21 a three purpose three to discuss strategy with respect to litigation or an open meeting may have a detrimental effect on the living getting position of the city in Chertog v City of Medford at all U. S. District Court.
Is there a motion to enter executive session?
Um, motion to that purpose.
Motion to enter.
And then can we just say that we adjourn at the end of the executive session?
Yes, we will not return an open session, so we will adjourn at the end of executive session.
So moved.
Motion of Councilor Lemming, seconded by?
Second.
Seconded by Vice President Lazaro.
Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
And president bears, just for clarification, the council's entering executive session as an open session would have a detrimental impact on the council's litigation position, just for the record.
Yes.
Yep.
That's what we have in the motion.
Yes.
Councilor Sim.
Vice President Nazaro.
Yes.
President Beers.
Seven in the affirmative, none in the negative.
I'm going to open a breakout room.
And Rich, you'll have to join that room.
OK, you should be a full host now.