[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Medford School Committee has a special meeting on September 25th, 2024 at 4 p.m.
[SPEAKER_00]: to be held via Zoom.
[SPEAKER_00]: The purpose of this meeting is provided in the agenda section below.
[SPEAKER_00]: The meeting is being recorded.
[SPEAKER_00]: The meeting can be viewed live on Medford Public Schools' YouTube channel through Medford Community Media or on your local cable channel, Comcast 9.
[SPEAKER_00]: 8 or 22 in Verizon Channel 43, 45, 47.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, the meeting will be recorded.
[SPEAKER_00]: Since the meeting will be held remotely, participants can log or call in by using the following information.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Zoom link is provided on the city and school website, and the meeting ID is 975-6605-8577.
[SPEAKER_00]: Questions or comments can be submitted during the meeting by emailing medfordsc at medford.k12.ma.us.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those submitting questions or comments must include the following information, your first and last name, your Merfitt Street address, your question or comment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Rousseau, if you could call the roll.
[SPEAKER_00]: Certainly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Brandley.
[SPEAKER_00]: Present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Graham.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Antapa.
Member Olopade.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Reinfeldt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member so present, Mayor Longo-Kern.
[SPEAKER_00]: Present, seven present, zero absent.
[SPEAKER_00]: If we could all rise to salute the flag.
[SPEAKER_00]: I pledge allegiance to the flag, United States of America, to the republic for which it stands, one nation under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have executive session pursuant to chapter 30 a section 21 to to conduct strategy in preparation with nonunion personnel or contract negotiations with nonunion personnel, superintendent of schools.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there a motion to go into executive session?
[SPEAKER_00]: Motion.
[SPEAKER_00]: By member Rousseau, seconded by?
[SPEAKER_00]: Second.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Graham, roll call vote please.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Brantley?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Graham.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Atapa.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Olopade.
Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Member Rangel.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Members say yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mayor Lingo-Kern.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative.
[SPEAKER_00]: Motion is approved to go into executive session.
[SPEAKER_00]: And will we be coming back to regular session?
[SPEAKER_00]: I assume now.
[SPEAKER_00]: The room will open now.