Welcome to the first edition of Mustang Report. I'm Victoria Rasche, one of the men reporters. We will be coming to you with different school events and community events throughout the year. And now here's a word from Dr. Perella. Good day, Mustangs. This is the Mustang Report on MHS TV. I hope you enjoy it. Ladies and gentlemen, welcome to Community Day. We are going to start the program with the singing of our national anthem.
by junior student from Medford High School, Sam, sophomore, Hannah, and what else did I come for? Oh say can you see, by the dawn's early light, what so proudly we hailed at the twilight's last gleaming?
Whose broad stripes and bright stars through the perilous fight, O'er the ramparts we watched were so gallantly streaming? And the rocket's red glare, the bombs bursting in air,
Gave proof through the night that our flag was still there. Oh, say does that star-spangled banner yet wave o'er the land of the free and the home of the brave?
I'm here with the Mustang News. I'm Cariann Luchares and I'm here with Captains Katie Covino and Tia Morrow. How are you guys feeling about community day today? We're excited that we get to expose our program to the community and see how they react. How are you guys feeling about Friday night? We're really excited, especially because it's the first home game and we think the boys will do really well.
So how is your season looking being in competition this year? Well, this year will be our first time competing in three years. We're really excited. We finally raised enough money and our team is strong enough to compete and I'm really excited to see what we do on the mat. I'm excited to compete and perform with all of our lovely teammates, all 22 of us. I'm excited to show off what we've worked hard on.
Hi, I'm Joss McCarthy and I'm here with Elsa and Anna and I want to know how your experience at Community Day is. So, so far we've seen a lot of little kids and it's been a blast. They've all sang with us and they've all talked to us and they all just get really excited when they see us and I'm really excited to see them and so is Anna, of course, but we're having a blast.
Taking a lot of pictures. The little kids love us. Thank you, Alsanana. Hi, I'm Cariann Luchares. I'm here with Aiden and Tripp with Troop 416. Can you guys tell us a little bit about your program? So we're based off Medford, in Medford, Massachusetts. And recently, well, we just came back from summer camp up in TL Store. How was that? It was really fun. One of my favorite years so far. Do you guys have any upcoming events that we should know about?
Well, recently we're going to help a fellow scout complete his Eagle Scout project. We do a lot of community service projects, such as marking the trains out all over the city of Medford. I'm here with Captain Trisha McLean from Medford Girls Hockey. Trisha, how are you feeling about community day today? It's great! Not so good weather, but everyone's still out having fun.
How are you feeling about this season? It's gonna be good. A new one. It's gonna be good though. Are you excited to be captain? Definitely. It's gonna be good. 10 out of 10 pizza. S.A. Scott Andrew rates it 10 out of 10. Very good. We are selling cheese pizza and we are selling pepperoni pizza.
Which would you recommend? It all depends on the person, you know? They're both extremely good. If you like pepperoni pizza, then get pepperoni pizza. If you like cheese pizza, get some cheese pizza. We have... Captain McCourt. What's it like in there?
Well we fill it with smoke and try to teach people how to get through a house if there's ever a fire at their house and also there's things such as we duplicate what would be a bedroom door and we want people to know what they have to do if they're at home and they're sleeping and their door's closed hopefully to their bedroom.
how to touch it to feel if it's hot and to see if there's fire on the other side of the door and whether or not to open it. And sometimes if we have enough time, we'll talk to them a little bit about safety in the kitchen. We have a mock kitchen here and there's a phone on the wall, what number to dial if there's an emergency. Of course, everybody knows what that is. 911.
MHTV 15 and the Mustang Report. Today we're here with Ciara and Sebastian at Medford's Community Day. How are you today? Good. Good. Very good. So, Ciara, what has been your favorite part of this entire day? The motorcycles. And now, Dad, how do you feel about the motorcycles?
They're great. They do a lot for the community and a lot of the kids like it out here. You know, it's fun to get out here and have some fun. The motorcycles are, you know, a very unique part of our force and they do a lot to keep the community safe and the roads safe. And how have you, how do you think that the day has gone today so far as well as all the events and everything happening?
As you can see, it's very successful. There's a lot of kids out here, a lot of smiles, so as long as I see smiles, I know it's going good. Are you going to come back next year? Yes. Alright, now back to you. Hi, I'm Allison Goldsberry. Hi, I'm Dan Costello.
We are part of the MHS Alumni Association. We are a new organization, so we're here just to get our name out and to let people know that we primarily raise money for scholarships for graduating seniors at Medford High. That I want to mention is that we're having our fourth annual Medford Night on Friday. It's November 27th.
The day after Thanksgiving, it's become an annual tradition that everybody comes to John Brewer's Tavern. It's like a multi-year reunion, doesn't matter what year you graduated. We always raise a lot of money for our scholarships on that day. It's a fun night, people are in town, it's a holiday, and it's just a great night to be out. So John Brewer's Tavern, there'll be trivia, there'll be raffles, you'll see people from all different class years, so you guys should definitely join us. Friday night, day after Thanksgiving at John Brewer's Tavern in Malden.
Okay, thank you so much. Bye
She didn't cry.
So how are you guys enjoying community day so far? It's awesome. I think my favorite part of community day is this petting zoo right here. What's your favorite animal? I like the goats. We met a couple animals but my favorite is by far Kevin the goat. Which one is he?
He's the one right there with mostly white, and he's pretty cool. I named him myself. Look, Kevin! What up, Kevin? I told you, Kevin loves us. What I figure is, the llama, he runs this place, and the turkey is like his right-hand man. The llama's like the nice guy, but the turkey's very mean.
Hi, I'm Amber Harbison with the Mustang Report. Today we're here with Max Charles. He's one of the top runners and soccer athletes for the Medford High teams. Max, how are you doing today? I'm doing fine. What kind of training have you been doing for soccer and track this summer? So I had a soccer camp over the summer, and we did a lot of running and practicing with the ball. And all that running and stuff gets my legs strong. So when it comes track time, I just get faster.
Thank you, Max. We hope to see you running soon. Hi, I'm Amber Harbison, and I'm a reporter with the Mustang Report. Let's talk some volleyball with the girls captains this year. Hello, this is Amber Harbison with the Mustang Report, and I'm here with the 2015 girls volleyball captains. They started their season about a week ago, and let's hear from Victoria about how their season went.
Okay, so, so far we've had one game against AC, Arlington Catholic, and then another game against Lowell. Both of those games weren't GBL games, luckily, because we lost in three matches on both games. But I think we've learned a lot from both games, and what we've learned is going to help us on our GBL games and the future games to improve and become a better team. Katrina, how do you think you can improve for your next game, and when is your next game?
So our next game is today. You all should come. It'll be a lot of fun. We're going to beat Malden. I think we need to improve just communication-wise. We don't talk a lot on the court, but I think after our practice yesterday, we really connected more. So we're definitely going to be talking more.
And I think cheering. We need more fans there. We need more people to come. So if more people come, you guys at home, you all should come. It'll be a lot of fun. And I think we could potentially win GBL again and be the only winners. And Jocelyn, how do you think the rest of the season is going to go?
I think the best of the season is going to be pretty good. We lost two games, even though that was our first two games, but we haven't glued as a team yet. So today is going to be our first game to win, and it's against Malden. And we still have a long season ahead of us, 13 more games, I say. And we're going to do really good at them. And we'll all glue together eventually, and I think today will be the day.
Thank you girls, I'm excited to see how the rest of your season goes. This is Amber with the Mustang Report. Hi, I'm Jocelyn McCarthy here with the Mustang Report. Here's Mr. Nascimento talking about the MHS football team. Hi, I'm Karianne Luchares and I'm from the Mustang News. I'm here with head coaching guidance counselor Mr. Nascimento. How does your season look so far?
Well, we were only one game in so far. We did not get off to a good start Friday night, but that's in the past. We're on to the next one. And I think, you know, as a coaching staff, we're still very optimistic about this season. And I still think we can continue to progress and go in the right direction. So what is your football philosophy and what kind of things do you believe in?
I have a lot of philosophies and a lot of things I believe in, but we preach discipline, commitment, toughness, effort, and pride every day. So if all of our guys can bring those five things to practice and game night every week, we'll be successful. And it's not just about the football aspect. It's about how these things carry over into the real world and after they graduate. And it's about preparing them for
the next step of their lives afterwards. So discipline, commitment, toughness, effort, pride. So how do you handle the criticism from other people and how do you help your players overcome that criticism? We just completely just we get the blinders on and you know any criticism from the outside I mean
We don't really pay any attention to that. It's on to the next one. Win or lose, when we lose it's on to the next one and when we win it's on to the next one. Either way it's the same message. We don't really pay attention to what people are saying outside of the people in the locker room. Katrina Rashia, I'm here with MHS TV and we're interviewing Miss Horn about DreamFar. So Miss Horn, why did you decide to start DreamFar?
So I just started DreamFar. I wanted to have a running program at the high school that could train kids for a marathon. And I met someone who was already up and running with this program. It started in Newton, Massachusetts. And so I heard all about it. I met this woman who began the program. And I thought, we've got to bring this to Medford High. So we started it, I think, four years ago. Medford's been involved. So kids have run.
three to four Providence-Red Island marathons. That's what they train for. But I really believed in the physical fitness, the camaraderie within the group, the health things they learn along the way with hydrating and nutrition. It's not just running, there's so many aspects to it.
So how do you train for a marathon? So you start small. That's the main thing with the kids. So the kids start training, and adults, because there are teachers who've been involved. So we start with, at the beginning of October, with a mile. And they do a mile for three days a week. And then their first group run, they meet with 10 other high schools on Saturday morning in Brookline. Their first long run with the group is, I think, four to five miles.
And that's around the end of October. But then, right before the marathon, which is May 1st, in mid-April, they do their long run, which is 21 miles. So they work up from late October, a four miles is their long run, to mid-April, where 21 miles is their long run. But it takes them seven months to get there. Thank you so much. Back to you. Mr. Merrill's essay is killing me.
Oh, guys, I hit another teacher! I'm definitely voting him for worst driver. Me too. When do we take superlatives? We should start thinking about who we're going to vote for because we're doing them Tuesday, September 22nd in advisory. When are we going to take pictures with the senior cars? We should listen to announcements because next week after school we're going to take pictures with the seniors with their own cars. Hi, I'm Katrina Rasche. I'm here with the Mustang Report. Let's go over to Amber Harbison at the cross-country race against Arlington Catholic.
Let's go! Good work guys!
How'd it go? How'd it go, James? Ryan, nice to meet you, Ryan! How's your daddy? Come on, daddy! Nice to meet you, Ryan. Nice work, guys. Nice job! Let's go, James! All right. Nice job, Kyle! How'd it go, Ivan? How'd it go, John?
Let's go get it!
Hi, I'm Lydia Ryan with Channel 15 News and we're here to see some clips from the Kimball Farm outing for the seniors.
Alright, how do I throw it to you? You're gonna fold it up a little bit and get it nice and sitting in your palm. It's all that flick of the wrist. Alright, one more, one more.
¶