Esquerra y Casco, and to close this first International Asset Forum, we welcome again Yolanda Díaz, Vice-President II and Minister of Labour and Social Economy. A round of applause.
Good afternoon, dear Minister of Senegal, Secretaries of Brazil, Kenya, France, dear Vice-President Dakari and Government Delegate, dear President Cepes, dear Juan Antonio, dear Director of ASED, dear Inigo, dear members of the International Council of ASED,
Dear Directors-General of the various autonomous communities that you are here presenting, in short, friends of the social economy. We have reached the end of this valuable forum with the certainty of having opened a new cycle.
A fertile space of meeting, of shared thinking that drives us to look, as I said before, with audacity, at the deep meaning of our work, which, in short, is to take care of life, democratize the economy and transform the common.
We do it in a time marked by the polycrisis, an ecological crisis that questions the very continuity of life on the planet... ...a crisis also of a fundamental right such as housing, which turns a basic right into an unattainable luxury for many people in our societies...
...a food and energy crisis amplified by speculation and extractivism... ...and a youth that seemed condemned to precariousness... ...care taken to the limit and an increasingly distant citizenship from the decisions that determine their lives.
In the face of this landscape, we do not settle down, we rebel and we do it in the hands of the social economy. We do not want to resign ourselves, we want to move forward. We are friends and friends of hope. We do not do it with nostalgia, we do it knowing that there is a common material called hope, which is what makes the moods change without a doubt and makes societies move.
The social economy, as I said, is not an ornament, it is not a qualifier, it is not even a nuance in the capitalist economy. It is a structural alternative, it is a way of life, it is a different way of inhabiting the world... ...that is based on solidarity, cooperation, equity, sustainability and social justice.
In the face of the mandate to compete, I believe that the social economy shares that it cooperates, that we support each other. In the face of the save-it-who-can, which is nothing more than a trajectory of failure, we propose to take care of each other. In the face of those invisible hands and the chainsaws, we propose to democratize every corner of our lives.
And above all, we propose to build, to build in a positive way. Because it is not enough to break everything, to destroy. I insist, it will not resist. We need to build a new architecture that is economic and that starts from the bottom. And the social economy, if you allow me, has the values, the practices and the democratic legitimacy precisely to do so.
We have seen it in all the areas where large social fractures are concentrated today. I have mentioned it in the right to housing. We have social economy initiatives that guarantee access worthy of sustainable and community models. Also, in the energy transition, with proposals that understand the energy, democratized, distributed, as a common good, not as a commodity.
We see it in the financial system, with alternatives, as I pointed out before, in the ethical, solidary and democratic interventions that prioritize people, projects, and not the form of speculative capital. Let me share an example that illustrates it clearly. After the DANA, in the days of the DANA, you, as you know, in the face of the suffering of the Valencian people,
The SEAS network boosted a solidary fund in record time that raised close to 60,000 euros to support the most affected social economy initiatives. We are always where we have to be. There was no last-minute rescue. There was solidarity from the first minute. Real cooperation, mutual support.
That is the social economy. That is how this model of social economy works. Where others retreat, the social economy advances. Where others speculate, we take care. Where others divide, fragment and generate hatred, we weave community.
To speak today about this project is to remember that another economy is possible when the need, the dignity of work, the decent work of the ILO and the collective intelligence are combined. I am going to allow myself to tell you, being here today in Donostia, that in the middle of the post-war period, from Mondragón, with barely any resources, I was able to imagine and build a profoundly transformative alternative.
Today, you are an inspiration for our country and for the whole world. Those were very difficult times, certainly more difficult than now. Your legacy, therefore, is multiplied today by hundreds of experiences shared around the world.
The social and solidarity economy is neither a memory nor a promise. It is present, it is action, like the call to action, the manifesto that we signed today with Professor Piketty and with Professor Ferreras and with so many people who label that call. It is a living reality and it can and should also be the future. Look, in the past, when the future was projected,
It was a desirable imaginary. They talked about youth as the future and it was something positive. And today they want us to think of that future and youth as something dystopian, as something negative. And we are not going to allow it. And the social economy knows that the future, the present and the future is full of hope.
I finish by thanking you, with a sincere emotion, sharing these days, these hours, which I also think do us good, from the love and humanity, this is also to make public policy from affection, and I want to thank those invisible people, dear Carmen, who have made it possible that everything we have here, nothing fails, is possible, and I think it is the invisible ones who are also
friends and sisters of the social economy.
And if you allow me, thanks to SET, which was born with a global vocation, from the local, dreaming, but from an inclusive and transformative vocation. Thanks to CEPES, as always, and to all the Basque institutions that are here today. For me, this is very important because we are demonstrating that many administrations, which, well, we will think differently, we are able to help each other.
And this is democracy. Democracy is walking with people who make synthesis, who don't think alike. Dear Íñigo, sharing projects with people who think exactly like you, first of all, no one thinks exactly like the other, fortunately, but that doesn't make much sense.
...public policy, public networks, is to make a synthesis, and not because I like social dialogue... ...that I like social dialogue. But the other thing is not public policy, it is to stay at home... ...reflecting on a truth that, by the way, is quite impure. Therefore, thanks to all the Basque institutions, the commitment of the Spanish government in this project.
And I'll finish. Thanks to those people and families in the social economy who, in a Mayan way, are all over the country doing wonderful things, from Galicia, I have to talk a little about Galicia, I'm Galician, going through Murcia, which Juan Antonio is already doing, who is there, but all over the country. In short, I think you are the ones who make it make sense. In short, thank you for being part of this network and for giving an example
to the world of hope. I also end by thanking the work we are doing at an international level. Today we are a source of inspiration, of light in the whole world, and it is not a small thing. I think we have sons and daughters who deserve to live with dignity and, of course, on behalf of the Government of Spain, if it depends on us, it will not. Thank you very much and good luck.
Thank you very much, Minister Andréa. Thank you all for coming from so many places around the world to participate in this first ASET International Forum.
We close this forum with these words, with the Minister's thanks and thanking you once again for coming here to Donostias.