Hello, everybody.
Hope you're having a great week.
Have some good news.
First up is that we had a groundbreaking at Gillis Park.
That's a $1.4 million project that our team was hard at work over the last year and a half getting ready for.
That's going to be a 12 to 18 month process.
So thank you for your patience as we work through that.
But it's going to be wonderful.
Next up, we have a ribbon cutting at Morrison Park.
That is done.
The work has been done, and that will open
officially on August 7th at 10 a.m.
so please come on down and visit us while we cut a ribbon and let the little ones play on the new tot lot.
We also have Car Park, Cape Inn, Hickey and a few others to follow so a ton of work being done by our amazing staff here at City Hall and beyond so I want to just throw a shout out to them and thank them so much for all their hard work.
Next up, I don't know if it's good news, but the good news is we are preparing for a heat wave.
We have a heat wave coming tomorrow, the 26th, the 27th, and 28th, and we just want to let people know that there are places in Medford you can stay cool.
First up is the Medford Police Department, who graciously opened their doors 24-7 to anybody that needs to catch an hour or two of cool air.
Then we have the Senior Center that will be open Wednesday through Friday of this week from 8.30 to 6 p.m.
That's extended hours for the Senior Center, so please grab a book and go down and get cool.
And we also have our library on the 26th and 27th from 9 a.m.
to 9 p.m.
and Friday the 28th from 9 a.m.
to 6 p.m.
Next up, don't forget, hopefully cool off next week a bit.
We have National Night Out put on by our police department.
That is Tuesday, August 1st from 5 to 8 p.m.
And yours truly, myself, will be in the dunk tank with another few people at different times, obviously.
I'll be in about 6.45 to 7.15, so come on in and show me what you got.
And last up, we have named our next Poet Laureate.
The Poet Laureate is Vinjaya Sundarum.
We are going to install her officially on the 8th of August at 4 p.m.
here in City Council Chambers.
Please join us.
That term is 7-1-1.
23 to 630, 25.
We're so excited and it's going to be a great ceremony.
We're going to have Vinjaya who will read a poem and also do some music and then we have our outgoing Poet Laureate Terry E. Carter who will also be here sharing his poetry.
So please join us and otherwise have a wonderful week.
Thank you.