Ladies and gentlemen, I'm back
Cheers!
Yoooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooooo
Yet again, once more, again, yet again, once more.
Blue hoodie!
Yo, DayDayKeso247, Pringle, Salon, Reku, Connor, Kim, Ano.
K so's Luna hat life Tiffany trash Alan hybrid moon Riley Shanice I think that was the name Shanice Courtney appreciate y'all W subbers man chat house everybody's day going on a scale of 1 to 10.
Let me hear it.
Huh?
How we doing chat?
Austin do again frown appreciate y'all why my heart beating weird.
I'm about to die
Chad, my heart beating weird.
Chad, y'all's heart ever skip a beat and you feel like you're about to die?
Like, could you imagine like, say your heart skips a beat, and what if it skipped like three in a row?
Is that like instant death or can it restart itself if it skips like three in a row?
Yo, yo, and with the five gifted, Renzler with the five gifted, who just gifted a bunch?
Who was that?
It was Kenzie.
How many subs Kenzie give chat?
Yo Kenzie with the 25 gifted yo, give me some W's for Kenzie with the 25 gifted appreciate you Kenzie.
Thank you W Kenzie appreciate that Kenzie Heather with the five as well appreciate you Heather with the five as well.
Thank you Heather.
Um
Okay, 1,000 bits from Egghead.
I got done feeling food review.
I tried flavored pretzels and one of the flavors of Frank's Red Hot.
Wait, for real, that sounds kinda good.
I'm not gonna lie.
Some Frank's pretzel action?
Yo, MC Dawg Dawg with 10,000 bits as well.
Have you heard of Beneath, a solo survival game set in the deep sea?
I don't know if I've heard that.
I'll look it up though.
Appreciate you, MC Dawg Dawg with 10,000 bits.
WMCDawgDawg with the 10,000 bits as well.
Appreciate you, thank you.
Um, is that 20,000?
Y'all's 20,000 bits from mc dog dog wmc dog dog with the 20,000 bits.
Oh my goodness I'll look up that game though for real.
Thank you.
Appreciate that Sharky with the 500 bits i'm doing a presentation on overfishing um words of encouragement on overfishing Like is overfishing like you talking about against overfishing hey Don't be overfishing
Hey, don't be over fishing, bro.
Okay.
Did I do good?
Did I, did I do good chat?
Don't be over fit.
Yo MC dog dog with a hundred get the yo, give me some W's for MC dog dog with a hundred gifted lollygagging with the five, uh, meet with the five WMC dog dog with a hundred gifted for real.
Appreciate you.
MC dog dog with a hundred gifted as well.
W get this real.
I appreciate y'all, man.
Thank you.
Um,
Did you see the new gifted sub option?
The new option is to give 200 subs.
What?
How do I get the sub?
You can give 200 subs?
Don't do that though.
Don't do that.
Don't do that, chat.
Don't, don't, don't, don't do that.
That is kind of crazy though, but don't do that for real.
That's actually wild.
They let you give 200 subs?
That's actually crazy.
Yo Egghead with the five, appreciate you.
Reverse psychology, own everything I love, don't do it.
If I'm lying, may I be struck down.
Do not give 200 subs.
Chat, have you ever seen me ask for a sub?
Huh?
In your whole existence of being in here, have I?
If you're saying yes, you are quite literally spreading misinformation for absolutely no reason, because I never have.
What are you talking about?
I literally never have.
Never in my life.
Subway?
No!
Dude, I could use some subway chat black forest ham on some toasted bread action.
Oh my goodness With some dad gum, you know, yo g bigs with the with the 50 gifty Yo, give me some w's for g bigs with the 50 gifted subs Appreciate you g bigs with the 50.
Thank you w g bigs for real.
Thank you g bigs and nova
With the two and sad boy with the 10 as well.
Appreciate you sad boy with the 10 as well An mc dog dog with another 100 gifted as well.
Appreciate you mc dog dog with another 100 gifted as well.
Lord have mercy W gifters for real are absolutely insane.
I appreciate y'all bro.
For real.
Thank you.
Look at david with the 10 gift as well w david With the 10 gifted as well as well.
Golly, that's a bad amount of breath from talking.
I need some help
Golly, I need some help, bro.
Lord have mercy.
That is a crazy name.
Thank you for the five gifted.
What?
Appreciate you.
Heather with the five as well.
Appreciate you, Heather with the five as well.
Thank you, W Heather.
Bro, why are y'all constantly typing jinxy, bro?
Like,
He's in a Discord call with multiple people and for some reason you're just interjecting me and everything.
That ain't none of my business.
Oh, a guy that Kace knows is in a Discord call with a bunch of people.
Get Kace in there.
Well, what?
Do you not know me?
What is wrong with y'all?
If you think I'm joining a discord call with multiple people, more than one or two people in it, you have absolutely lost your mind.
And if you do not know me by now, knowing that I'm not going to do that, I don't know what you do know.
Okay.
Y'all barbecue water with the five gifted.
Thank you.
Barbecue water with the five gifted introvert.
Dude said introvert question mark.
You just now figuring that out, bro.
You just now figuring that out.
Like, hello?
It's for charity?
Okay, he wants some money or something?
I got him with that, but you think I'm joining a call with a whole bunch of people?
You got me messed up!
Yo, Morganic with the five, appreciate you.
W Morganic, for real, thank you.
Chat, if you see a big, large group of people with one of my friends in it, you are not obligated to be like, hey, go join that.
Hello?
Like, hello?
Life may throw some bland cucumbers your way, but I know you can turn them into delicious pickles.
Again.
Your hard work and perseverance will pay off in the long run.
The future belongs to those who believe in the beauty of their dreams.
In a pickle, just remember you're not alone.
Again.
Life's journey is like a pickle.
That surprising crunch ultimately makes it more enjoyable.
Extroverted activities I'll never understand.
And you know what's crazy?
Me being on stream doing this every day may look like I'm an extrovert, cuh.
If you, if I was ever went to a club or something, I'd be the dude sitting in the corner, drinking some water, talking to nobody.
Yeah, I can get on here and talk to y'all every night, but if I was on a stage and all of y'all was physically in front of me, you think I'd be able to get up on that stage every night?
Absolutely not.
Now, if I know you and I got like one or two people I know real good, oh yeah, I'll do, you know, I'll do whatever.
But no No, you know chat, hey Hey, i'm not no extrovert Trust me.
Do y'all think i'm an extrovert?
Do I give extrovert vibes chat?
Do I?
No way I give extrovert vibes No way Somebody made a crochet plushie of you and it's dude i've seen that big old giant
Crochet action that they was talking about no joke.
I've seen that That yeah, she made that big old giant crochet action, bro.
That thing looks crazy Check y'all seen that I literally seen that for real Like no joke I seen it it looked tough And she pulled the draws down on it too.
You can see some straight-up cheek action.
I
You can literally see some straight up cheek action.
She pulled, she pulled the draws down and she literally, yo, somebody got the video?
Can somebody link the video?
Yo, if one of the mods got the video, I'll straight up, I'll straight up look at that.
No joke.
There was some cheek action going.
Yo, Furious with the five, appreciate you.
There's some what action?
There's some huh action?
I'm uncomfortable?
You're uncomfortable in here?
What did I do?
So you mean to tell me I made you uncomfortable?
Big Mac with the five, thank you.
Wait, is that it?
Wait, wait a minute.
Day five of crocheting is- This it, this it, this it, this it, this it, this it.
Look how big this thing is, bruh.
Child, look how big this thing is.
Look at this thing, bruh.
Look how big that thing is.
Jumbo cake.
That thing bigger than me for real.
So this is the moment everyone's been waiting for.
The reveal.
Look at him.
I love it so much.
And just look at this.
The buns for those ones.
That right there, that right there.
And just look at that.
That is actually unbelievable.
That's crazy.
Chat that that that is that that right there is kind of unfathomable if you ask me Case read my get this up with the five get to thank you appreciate you case.
Please read my get this ups.
Thank you Did you want me to read that you gifted that you gifted or what?
Because if that's the case, hey, I appreciate you Thank you, uh chopper with the five as well appreciate you chopper with the five as well.
I buy one I don't even know if she's selling them.
Thanks.
She's selling them
buns!
For those wondering about the materials that I used, I'll get into it right now.
So, out of the two skeins of the Hobie Honey Bunny Big Yarn that I got for this project, I used 551 grams.
SHE DID GOOD ON IT THOUGH, IT LOOKED PROFESSIONAL!
I used 181 grams of Premier Parfait XL.
For the hair, beard, and eyebrows, I used 563 grams of Bernat Brown.
I don't know how people even do something like this, bruh.
There's not an artistic bone in my body, bro.
No joke.
There is legitimately, dude, I can't, dude, the what's it called?
The masterpiece shirt with my face on it that I drew for the t-shirt, that was actually, no joke, my best work I could ever attempt to do.
And even then, I used like the circle drawing tool.
Yep.
Blanket extra.
And lastly, out of the two skeins of sweet snuggles, I used 460.
Yeah, that, that, that emote.
Yeah, that emote, look.
Chapa, thank you.
This emote right here.
If you don't know, chat, I drew this right here.
And I'm here to tell you one thing.
This emote right here, I drew it.
And it is literally, I'm not kidding you at all.
It is the best.
I like how somebody just said cap like this is a masterpiece or something.
You saying cap is literally a compliment to me.
I'm not going to lie, but no chat this right here as horrible as it is and it's bad.
Okay.
It's bad, but I'm here to tell you one thing.
This is the best that I have to offer the world.
As far as artistic vision goes As long as i've been on this earth i've been on this earth for 19 years Right i've been on this earth for 19 years And this is the best thing i've ever i've ever created On everything i love I don't know what y'all saying cap about but yeah That's that's me.
That's the best of me right there
For the stuffing, I used about 420 grams of polyfill.
The total weight of the jumbo queso is 634 pounds?
I'm kidding, it's actually 4.8 pounds.
Which actually, like, believe it or not- THAT THING'S FOUR POUNDS, YOU KNOW HOW- YOU KNOW HOW HEAVY FOUR POUNDS IS FOR SOMETHING LIKE THAT?
Yo, Amina with the five, thank you Amina with the five, appreciate you.
was a surprise to me because it doesn't feel like five pounds it feels like three and a half maybe don't let that go to your head queso anyway the final excuse me mentions are 20 inches tall 22 inches wide arm to arm is she creating you no this somebody else
I think I'm retiring from streaming.
Because what you mean is she creating you?
I'm done.
You know what?
This is my retirement announcement.
I can't do this no more.
There is legitimately no way you just asked, is she creating you?
Would you?
See, I ain't even trying to be rude, right?
Like, look here.
I'm not even trying to be rude right now.
I'm not.
But what on this planet Earth, who else would this be right here?
Certified Gooberologist with the five gifted, that might be, that is a top 10 name in the history of this channel.
Yo, wait, that is a top 10 name in the history of this channel.
Certified Gooberologist.
There is no way somebody just now made that name.
Just now.
As long as we've had.
Dude!
and 13 inches thick, which is measured belly to the booty.
If you want to make your very own queso plushie, it doesn't have to be jumbo.
My pattern has been officially released today.
Hey, uh, yo.
Hey, you're doing a real good job.
Hey.
If you are interested, the pattern is on my Etsy, and the link to my shop is in my bio.
I am so proud with how this came out, and I'm so excited to see everyone else's queso plushies.
And a quick thank you to all my testers.
Hey, it look good for real.
That's cool.
Can I have one?
You're gonna have to ask her about that, cuz.
For helping me out with this pattern.
You all made incredible quesos, and your feedback was incredibly helpful, so thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you all so much for watching and coming along for this series.
Did you see all the other ones?! !
Dechicotator with the five gifted.
Was good, Dechicotator.
So much fun with this and let me know if you have any ideas for my next jumbo project.
I definitely will be doing more.
And with that all said, bye.
You did a real good job.
You did a real good job on that.
I'm not gonna lie.
You did a mighty fine job on that right there.
You did.
SchoolboyRunaway2 was out.
What did you just say?
What, what did you just say?
Wait, what did you actually just say?
There is legitimately no way what you just said is factual.
CheekseekingMissile with the five gifted.
Hannah with the five and DirtySnake with the 10, thank you.
Wait a minute.
Dude, if you literally are serious about this, this just made my night, this is the best night ever.
Schoolboy, run away.
Okay, so you're getting banned.
All right, yeah, you're done.
I don't think you understand how happy I was literally about to be when you said that, and to go on here,
And to see that it's that it's not there Can we get a release date for this yo devs look Yo slap with the five.
Thank you.
Yo devs Y'all know y'all know i'm a fan right I done played all y'all's games I beat the joker game.
I beat school boy runaway got almost every ending in that game silly potato with the five And dreamy with the 10 preset you silly potato and dreamy And i'm a big fan, right?
But is there but is there any way?
If there's if there's there any way you could give your boy release date for this here I'll cut you a deal right you ain't even got to make a public release date just DM me be like a This when the game comes out I ain't gonna tell nobody I Ain't gonna tell nobody for real I'll sign an NDA
I'll sign an NDA if you want me to.
You didn't beat the Joker game.
Yo, Judy Big Booty.
I literally did.
Did you see Jelly Roll's wrestling tomorrow?
I think I heard something about him wrestling, yeah.
W Jelly Roll though.
Oh, Jelly Roll, man.
Yo, Big Boss with the five gifted.
Appreciate you, Big Boss with the five gifted and Cheeks with the five.
Thank you.
See, I see stuff like Jelly Roller, somebody doing the stuff like that, like these wrestlers and everything, bro.
These people are straight up crazy.
Like, bro, how you gonna get out in front of all these people, do like a bunch of flips and stuff?
You better than me, bro.
Bro, people brave for real, Chad.
Anybody that can go out in front of real people,
and do like some stuff like that with like a live crowd.
Bro, y'all brave for real, no joke.
No joke, y'all brave.
I'm serious.
Wait, is there a new puppet combo game out?
People have been saying puppet combo too.
Expert cheekologist with the five, thank you.
Hold on, let me look at puppet combo real quick.
Hold on.
Are y'all lying about this too?
Like Lord have mercy, man.
Chat, name a Puppet Combo game.
Hold on.
Wait.
No way there's gonna be... Oh!
I'm going to check Puppet Combo, hang on.
Y'all can't see my screen, right?
Cause I gotta go to that Patreon again and if y'all could see it, it'd be over.
It'd be over.
Hold on.
Puppet Combo Patreon.
Should I say my password out loud?
The Taxi Driver Horror Game is out.
Okay, here's the thing with Puppet Combo though, I gotta look through the pictures.
So it's a Puppet Combo game,
Except you drive a taxi, but the thing is some of these patreon games that they got on here Straight up.
I'm talking like actual naked action.
I've seen before So I gotta you know what I'm downloading it.
Oh my goodness, that's a virus.
Oh
I'm hitting the download all button, Chad, it's over.
Chad, it's over.
Dude, I know I be saying this a lot, but I'm gonna say it again.
If you could see my screen right now, do you understand?
I would be in a pickle.
Wait, why is it not downloading?
Chat, what does zipping one file mean?
Help.
What's going on?
Do a pickle quote?
I got you right here.
You ready?
Don't be a cucumber.
Be the best dang pickle you could ever be.
That's just true, bro.
I'm hitting y'all with another one.
In a world of cucumbers, be the extraordinary pickle.
Absolutely.
One more.
You want another one?
Here you go.
It's never too late to set another goal or to dream a new dream.
Absolutely.
You want another one?
Right here.
Your journey may be tough, but so are you.
Chat, where would we be?
Yo, happy birthday, Tyler.
Chat, where would we be without the pickle action?
Would y'all be in a worse place without the pickle?
We'd be in a pickle.
Dr. Twerk with the five, thank you.
Wait, hold on.
Hold on.
Hold on!
I think we're actually gonna be able to play a new public combo game tonight.
Chat, that is on the menu.
Let's go, that's on the menu.
Okay, good.
We have a puppet combo game.
Yes.
We have a puppet combo game on the menu tonight.
Type one if you're crunk about that.
I'm kinda crunk.
We got some puppet combo action.
Yo, I'm not sure leviathan.
Thank you for the thousand bits Uh, hey case would have an artist block for the past week And I was wondering if you could give me an idea on what to draw with you in it Ban the guy that just said naked by the way What to draw with you with me in it
Who just said tournament to a jalapeno popper?
I was about to say something insane.
That's horrible.
Hold on.
Let me think.
I'm thinking for a second.
No, I can't.
I can't.
I'm not saying it.
No, that's bad.
I have had one too many horrible things said this past week.
I can't do it.
Um.
Oh, I got an idea for you.
Nevermind.
OK, it's not going to involve Chris Redfield.
Actually, yes.
I heart ear infections with the five gift that your band.
draw me and Chris Redfield like as a team side by side.
We both got like blinkies and stuff and we're facing Albert Wesker.
We're going to fight them together like a like it's a boss fight starting off.
No joke like actually no joke.
I think if you could get that going that that could be that could be generational.
I'll be real with you.
That could be that could be generational right there.
Don't y'all agree with that chat?
Y'all mess with that?
Throw Arthur Morgan in there too.
Me, Chris Redfield, Arthur Morgan.
And we're all side by side, we got guns, we're looking out in front of us, Albert Wesker's out in front of us.
And then when Albert Wesker's out in front of us, have like a little speech bubble coming out of him and having to say seven minutes, seven minutes is all I can spare to play with you.
And then the speech bubble for me is gonna be like, uh-oh, Chris Redfield's speech bubble is gonna be, we got this guys.
And then Arthur Morgan is just gonna be smoking a cigarette.
Desi dude, see I can come up with stuff, but I just can't like I could think of something like that But I just can't put it into action, right?
Yo, little monster with the five gifted.
Thank you Tanner no Tanner does no Tanner does not deserve to be in there.
No Tanner Tanner does not deserve to be in there stop
Y'all are, I'm actually for real this time when I talk about Tanner, I'm dead serious.
Y'all are legitimately giving Tanner too much aura than he literally deserves.
He is not even in the same universe of aura as Chris Redfield or Arthur Morgan.
I'm so serious.
Like I'm actually dead serious.
He's not even same, like same, like legitimately same universe as those two guys.
Okay.
Ted, unfortunately, unfortunately, Ted doesn't have nowhere near the same universe of aura as Chris Redfield and Arthur Morgan either.
I would go as far as to say that Arthur Morgan has the most aura out of any character that was ever written, ever.
I'm for real.
Like, I'm so serious.
I'm serious.
Arthur Morgan is the best character, fictional character.
Arthur Morgan skid mark with the five gifted, thank you.
Hey, Arthur Morgan, you know, I'm not rage baiting, I'm actually dead serious.
Arthur Morgan is the best fictional character ever created.
On my mama.
And that's no rage bait, that's no nothing.
There is no other fictional character that has, he's the greatest fictional character ever.
I cried.
I'm talking snotting.
I'm talking one of them cries, you're like.
I did one of those.
not only went at the very end, but like for the last entire hour of the game, I was sniveling.
Like I was legitimately sniveling.
Once I realized what was about to happen, I was actually like sniveling for real, like sniveling, no joke.
And I'm gonna keep it a stack with y'all.
I wasn't gonna tell y'all this, but like,
Like four months ago, I replayed Red Dead 2 again, and I cried again.
I cried.
On my mama.
I didn't cry when he turned to the sunset.
I cried when he was telling Sadie and who was the other girl that was with Sadie?
Who's the other girl that was with Sadie that he put him on the horse and said, get up out of here?
Abigail, crying, crying.
On my mom, I was crying and this was, no, it was Tilly.
It was Tilly, yes.
When he loaded up Tilly and Abigail onto the horse and said, get up out of here, I was crying.
on everything I love.
I will.
I'm talking not just like I was shedding like some tear action.
What y'all talking about?
GC what?
What are y'all saying?
Hold on, let me call him.
He just texted me.
See, when the man himself texts me, that's when I'm like, okay, you know what I mean?
But you got a whole bunch of people in chat talking about, go over.
I ain't listening.
K3 might get this up with the five.
Thank you.
Yo, what's good G.
I hope you're having a great night real quick.
Um, there's this, we're doing this charity thing.
Uh, well, mr. B set it up and he's basically just calling a bunch of streamers and a bunch of people I've donated, but it's for this clean water thing, like worldwide water action.
Uh, wait, what'd you say?
Some water action.
Yup.
So just, just clean water.
And, uh, we, uh, a lot of people were saying to ask you if you'd be, uh, if you'd be down, what you mean like some water action.
Like, yeah, like just stuff through it.
I'm basically a donation.
It goes to team water.
It's for this, uh, charity that basically gives people clean water, like worldwide.
Oh, so like people, so people that's like somewhere that ain't got no like clean water action and like literally exactly.
Yes.
It's a very beautiful.
It's a very beautiful thing.
Okay.
Well, how much you do?
Um, well, okay.
So I did a 100,000.
All right.
I'll do that too.
Yeah, I got you.
Yeah.
Yeah, I'm gonna do what you did.
Huh?
All right, bro.
All right, Pete.
Hey, WGC.
Hey, I think people do need some clean water now.
I do think people... See, I told y'all I'd give to the charity, but as far as jumping in the car, no.
You know what I mean?
So that's what it was, chat.
See, he called me, and you see what happened?
Things happened.
It's legit, though, right?
Expect, are you sure?
He didn't stutter?
He didn't say $100?
He did not stutter.
He donates to charities a lot.
Call him back.
I want to hear from him.
Well, I don't want to call him again, but I just called him.
I just called him.
It's 100 grand.
You can call the dude.
Alright, so he's locked in his word is good.
Trust me.
Hey, tell him is good.
Oh
Should I call St.
Claude Barclay?
You good?
Alright, thank you, Jinxy.
You can leave.
Thank you so much.
Thank you for the $100,000 donation.
He good.
And last thing I'm gonna say is this was a beautiful stream.
Yeah, he good.
It's not real?
You think I got scammed?
No way.
Nah, Jinxy wouldn't call me and get me scammed.
No.
Nah, he would not do that.
No, Jinxy would not get me scammed.
I promise you that.
Ain't no way, ain't no way my boy would get me scammed.
Okay, I trust Jinxy.
You know what I mean?
No, no, no, no, no.
Hey, you know what I mean?
Join?
I done told you I ain't joining.
Now I ain't gonna tell you again.
Minus 100K?
Oh, I thought he said $100.
No, I'm playing, I got it.
Yo chips and queso with the 10 gifted appreciate you chips and queso with the 10 gifted.
Thank you W chips and queso as well.
Thank you more capacity.
I'm keeping stacked.
I'll consider watch these for four hours.
I'm not going more cupcakes The kitchen aid bowl lift stand mixer w goat action for real No joke though
Six most disturbing things caught on home security camera footage You know what I mean in 2015 a couple in San Jose, California were the victims of a home invasion Intruders were never identified the police recommended the to invest in some home security cameras to protect against future break-ins and So they got money though.
Look at this little outdoor area right here.
I
They set up a total of six different cameras around their house.
Then, on May 8th of that same year, these cameras would capture a second break-in.
Two men wearing black clothes climb a fence into the backyard, where they're shown finding an unlocked sliding glass door.
They walk inside and immediately go into the kitchen.
One of them is seen disconnecting a phone setting on the counter.
They proceed to search the kitchen, opening different cabinets and drawers.
From this, they find kitchen knives, which they take with them to arm themselves.
Why?
Imagine getting stabbed by your own kitchen knife.
Camera, their next scene running upstairs, kitchen knives in hand.
Imagine stabbing somebody in general, you know what I mean?
Like, how you gonna stab somebody?
As they're searching the rooms upstairs, one of the men comes across a locked door.
It was the door to the master bedroom.
He puts his ear to the door, and hears a baby crying.
Inside the room was a family friend named Rosie and the two homeowners' child.
Rosie was babysitting for them when the intruders entered the home.
Hearing the crying, the man alerted his partner that people were inside.
Instead of getting spooked and leaving, the men go up to the door and aggressively start kicking it.
They hit it with such force that they managed to kick a hole in it.
They then thrust knives through the hole.
Rosie took the couple's child and retreated to the bathroom, locking that door as well.
She screamed out that she called the police.
This would work.
The men finally started running away before they could fully break into the bedroom.
Police reviewed all of the footage, but were never able to identify the men.
Their true motives remain unknown.
Oh, we can tell what their true... Any man... It's hard to believe they were only trying to rob the place, seeing that they disconnected the phones and felt the need to arm themselves with kitchen knives.
They also didn't immediately leave upon finding people inside.
Instead, they tried breaking down a door to get to them.
This is the footage from a home security camera in Vacaville, California.
Doc's license plate ain't blurred out.
It was April when this footage was taken, and during that time of year, it's common to see a lot of activity in the form of kids walking home from school each afternoon.
On this day, at some point, a girl with a backpack on is shown walking into frame.
She was walking home from school like everyone else.
However, she had been being followed for several blocks by a man in a dark-colored Pontiac.
She noticed this, and so she used a large truck parked on the side of the road to hide.
Bro.
She abruptly stops walking while she's out of view of the Pontiac.
The driver stops, expecting her to come back into view.
When she doesn't, he stalls there for a while before slowly driving off.
The girl is left standing there, unsure of what to do next.
What you doing eventually she sees the car coming back and decides to stay put behind the truck Yo w survival this dude came back around Yo w survival skills over I
The Pontiac drives by, and then reverses to try and talk to the girl, but she continually repositions herself out of view.
Finally, he drives off again and the girl makes a run for it.
After receiving multiple tips about the driver and his car, the police started an investigation.
A 24-year-old man was identified as the driver.
He was interviewed, but not arrested.
He technically hadn't committed any crime, and therefore police couldn't really do anything.
run that by me again 24 year old man was identified as the driver he was interviewed but not arrested he technically hadn't committed any crime and therefore police couldn't really do anything whether or not the man was actually planning something that day is unknown
First, we offer overnight boarding.
Your pet will stay overnight in your sitter's home and not only be treated like part of the family, but treated like a king or queen honey.
I am absolutely- WHAT?!
He technically didn't- he- wha- Let me- let me make the laws, buddy.
Not only would have this dude been arrested, he'd have been de-headed in public.
That is unbelievable!
13 years old and one three years old.
On the night of February 20th, 2022, the three of them went shopping together.
Their home security camera would show them returning home.
They're seen walking inside and closing the door behind them.
Shortly after, a man walks into frame from around their parked truck.
The very first thing he does is try to open the door.
Okay, so yeah, you need to start shooting.
If the first thing they do is try to open the door and not knock, you gotta start blasting.
Who are you talking to?
You leave no question.
Why?
You shoot first, ask questions later if somebody's trying to get in your house.
After knocking a few times, the man walks away.
However, they later found out through a neighbor's camera that for the next five minutes he walks around the house on his phone.
Allie further reviewed the videos and found that it appears the man had been following them in his car all the way from the store.
Two seconds after they park in the driveway, his car drives a bit further and parks a few houses down.
After a few more seconds, he gets out and starts walking towards them.
Thankfully, they were able to get everything inside and the door locked before he got there.
Allie ended by writing, I don't know what this man's intentions were, but I don't think it was to rob us.
I do believe that this was random and that we are not specifically targeted, but that he saw an opportunity when he saw a woman and two girls go into a house alone.
Man... Police were alerted, and they did search the area, but the man in the video was never found.
Lord have mercy!
In October of 2016, a family in Florida noticed multiple things missing from inside their home.
The night before, everything was there, but when they woke up, stuff was missing.
How you be caught on camera?
Plain as day.
Plain as day, and you wasn't never found, bruh.
To figure out where it went, they reviewed their home security cameras.
At 1.30 in the morning, this is what the cameras captured.
Dude, there's literally somebody sleeping on the couch, bruh.
There's somebody sleeping on the couch in the bottom right, too!
There's no way you're brave enough to do this with people literally sleeping less than a foot away from you.
There's no way.
A man walks around the house while three children are sleeping on couches only feet away from him.
He walks around them looking for valuables and hands what he finds to another man standing just outside, this one armed.
Dude.
The family immediately called the police upon seeing the footage.
Police opened an investigation, but never found the two men in the video.
Police believe that had anyone in the house woken up during the break-in, they likely would have been shot.
Man.
We can just assume that they was never identified every time we see one of these chats.
No joke.
Every time we see one of these, we might as well just assume they got away with it.
A woman in Hudson, Wisconsin opened her blinds one morning and noticed something in the snow outside her window.
She went outside and realized she was looking at footprints.
The prints walked right up to her bedroom window and then back the way they came.
Worried someone deliberately looked inside her window, the woman set up a security camera outside pointed towards her window.
A few nights later, the camera recorded the man who made the footprints coming back.
Dude, this reminds me of the Hinterkeifeck.
Y'all ever heard of the Hinterkeifeck action?
Where that dude found them footsteps in the snow leading to his house, and he didn't see no footsteps leading away.
Next day, whole family was killed.
With an axe.
Or something.
Not an axe, but like a big ol' like, tool.
Y'all ever heard of the Viscula, uh, the Viscula axe murder house too?
Somebody just walked in their house, killed all of them with an axe, dead.
Bro, how you gonna walk in somebody's house, kill everybody in there with an axe?
Oh man, there's an axe right here.
I'm gonna walk in his house and kill everybody.
Like, what you mean, bruh?
What you mean you about to walk in here and kill his whole family with an axe?
Like, it makes you wonder if somebody would've ran into somebody like that.
Be like, hey bro, what you about to do?
Oh, I'm about to walk in here and kill this whole family with this axe I just found.
And if they was like, bro, you shouldn't do that.
You think they'd be like, well, you know what?
You right, I ain't gonna do it.
Play the video.
I cut the video off!
The man is shown clearly peering in the window.
Police were alerted and shown the video.
After doing some digging, they were able to trace the vehicle leaving the scene to a man named Robert Cessna.
Oh my goodness, they caught one.
Reputable executive for the company 3M.
It must not be that reputable because I ain't never heard of it.
LinkedIn profile, Robert Cessna is a global key account vice president at 3M.
He ain't nothing.
He shows similarities to the man in the video.
Robert was contacted by police, but denied it was him.
Police then interviewed several neighborhood witnesses, and along with other evidence were able to confirm that he was lying.
He was the man in the video.
Robert Cessna was ultimately charged with felony stalking, and later fired from his executive position.
So this dude gets felony stalking, and the guy that rode by that little girl multiple times while she was walking home from school technically didn't commit a crime?
Like, what you talking about, bruh?
Oh, 3M, oh yeah, you right, nevermind.
Yeah, I have heard of them, my fault.
Yeah, my bad.
Yeah, you right.
Man, that's an old lady with a scooter!
And you go, man!
A total of five had occurred, and so she finally took the advice of- THERE AIN'T NO WAY YOU TAKING THE STUFF OFF HER SCOOTER ON TOP OF IT!
OH BUDDY!
OH- On home security cameras.
Caught on the cameras, a sixth break-in occurs around one in the morning.
A man is seen silently walking around while Margaret is sleeping in her living room.
HER NAME'S MARGARET DUDE!
THERE AIN'T NO WAY YOU STEALING SOMETHING FROM OLD LADY MARGARET!
YOU DISGUSTING!
Oh, you, you, you, you disgusting.
Did he have a moment of clarity?
Are we witnessing a moment of clarity?
No, no moment of clarity, he's still looking for stuff.
NOW YOU'RE COOKED!
Unreal.
OH, MARGARET'S ABOUT THAT BUSINESS, BUDDY!
Don't hurt him, Miss Margaret!
Hey, you lucky you got out of there before Margaret got ahold of you.
Hey, hey, she would have tied him up to the railroad tracks and ran him over with that scooter about 50 times.
He's lucky Margaret didn't get ahold of him.
She was about that business for real, bruh.
No joke.
Did we see that one?
Yeah, that's the one we seen.
But I eat healthy, but I want to every time we watch one of these bro.
It makes me lose faith in humanity, bro.
I'm for real.
Like I'm for real, bro.
Like why?
That's why you go somewhere, bro.
You got to keep, if you can't carry a blicky on you, carry some pepper spray, carry a knife.
You got to have something on you, bro.
No joke.
keep something, you gotta keep something.
If you can't do no blicky action, you keep your big old jug of pepper spray or like a little, or like not a little knife, like a knife for real.
Cause you never know who's going to try to run up on you, bro.
A jug of pepper spray?
Yeah, they make them big ones.
The big ones with the squirt cap on it.
Yeah, like that bear spray action.
Somebody run up on you.
Hey, how you doing?
Sprayed.
I ain't taking no chances.
In this first video, an avid cave explorer on YouTube known by the channel name, Exploring Abandoned Mines and Unusual Places, is exploring an abandoned mine for the simple purpose of reviewing a flashlight.
During the video, you can hear as the explorer goes into detail about the flashlight, and demonstrates its use in the mine he's exploring.
He's doing a hashtag ad for a flashlight in the middle of a cave.
However, while talking to the camera about both the mine and the flashlight he's reviewing, the explorer hears what he first thinks to be wind blowing through the mine.
Though many believe the audio sounds like a very disturbing whispering or talking sound.
Huh?
Okay, this is a review and demonstration of the Thrunite TN-12 handheld flashlight that you see here.
Okay, that's the portal to the wall deck mine.
I'm inside.
The wind has kind of died down a little bit, and it's not raining, so I managed to stay dry.
I think you've went far enough.
The flashlight looks like it's doing a pretty good job.
Of course, I'm inside this little alcove, kind of.
But anyway, you come down this little incline path.
You come down this little path?
Are you talking about me?
I know you ain't talking about me.
What do you mean, you?
No.
And big boulders here you have to climb over, and then the tunnel's right behind me, this way.
So let's check it out.
Let's get in here.
Like I said, this light has five levels.
I believe it's on medium right now which is level three, so this would be high, and this would be turbo.
Yep, that's going in the cart.
Medium seems to be the best one.
Do you see the amount of light that little flashlight gives off?
Not too bright, not too dim.
And then, you can see how big these timbers are.
Those are, that's about,
Almost a foot in diameter.
It's going down!
I'm yelling timber!
You better move!
You better dance!
Let's make a night!
You won't remember!
I'll be the one!
Do you hear that?
My fault.
My bad.
He said timber.
I had to.
All of this rock.
You can see right here where some of these boards are bending.
I did just hear some whisper action.
Y'all heard that?
Do you hear that?
Sounds like a. All fake video.
What is that wind?
Can you hear that on the camera?
The moment it went through the direction of paranormal, it's fake.
Now, if you see the butt naked dude run around the corner with a club, I'd be like, oh, whoa, stopped.
Well, I don't know what that is.
That doesn't sound like wind, but that's crazy.
Don't know if that's a bird or I don't know what that is.
It almost sounds like snakes.
Wait, wait, is he for real?
Wow.
I've heard some weird stuff in mines, but that is definitely creepy.
I don't know what that is.
There's no way.
So let's get out of here and head back out to the portal.
That was weird.
Roku ads manager puts Roku's reach within your reach.
Sign up at ads.roku.com.
Are you tired of uncomfortable bras that poke and just don't fit right?
We deserve better.
These next two videos come from the same exploring YouTube channel shown earlier.
This time, however, the explorer visits an abandoned, supposedly haunted mine in Nevada known as Horton Mine.
The first time he visits, he claims to feel negative energy coming from the mine, and what he witnesses goes to support his claim.
However, with the popularity of the first visit, the YouTuber decides to visit the abandoned mine a second time, this time hearing something very disturbing.
Here are both of those visits to the mine.
Okay, here's a lower adit at the Victorine Mine.
I believe this was an older mine that once they dug the upper tunnels, this got incorporated into the same claim or whatever.
Okay, we can go in here and just take a quick look.
I don't think I'm going to explore this particular mine.
There's a little bit too much water in here, and I know this mine is really old, but... You're old!
Don't talk about that mine like that!
I do see other footprints here in the mud, but I just don't think it's wise to go in here when there's water.
I'll try to avoid this if I can.
Yes, this looks pretty sketchy.
I'll go a few feet further in and check it out, but I think I'm going to pass on this one.
This is one of the creepiest mine tunnels I've ever been in just because of how dilapidated it is and all these chains hanging down.
from the overhead, and there's a shot looking down the tunnel.
Bro!
Here's a shot looking back towards the entrance.
I'm a little bit further in.
And uh... Bro said this is about as far as I'm gonna go.
Next shot, he's 200 feet deep looking at the exit.
Looking down the tunnel here.
Move that chain!
I don't know why that one chain is swinging back there.
I don't know if you can see that in the video or not.
This mine definitely has a very spooky vibe to it, so I'm going to head back out and check out the other stuff that's here.
This is just too wet and too muddy.
You saw.
Honestly, something is making the change.
I like how, I like how what the, I like how the thing stopping him from going farther in here is that it's too wet and too muddy.
Like, okay, bud.
Swing.
So time to get the hell out of here.
Yo, Lid with the five and Taco with the five.
Thank you.
Okay, the Horton Mine still has some water coming out of it.
You can see it kind of pooled up here outside.
Here's the portal.
Have you ever heard of steel water?
Yeah, that's them brain-eating amoebas!
So, let's go check this out and see if it's any drier than it was a year ago when I was last here.
Okay, I'm further in than I was a year ago.
And that's how far I've come.
Why?
Okay, here's a final parting shot of the Horton Tunnel.
And there's the ore pass with all the cascading water.
What the heck is that?
That's a radio or something.
I don't know what that was, but there was a sudden blast of cold air.
See, now you're just lying.
I'm getting out of here.
I don't like liars.
A man named Clem Schultz and his wife lived in Fairdale.
Oh my goodness.
I know this video.
This is that dude.
Yo, this is that dude that didn't refuse to go to the basement.
He said, forget it.
I'm going to sit here and film this tornado killing me.
Y'all remember this video?
This dude literally filmed this tornado until it got, he didn't even go to the base.
He filmed it all the way until it got to his house.
during one of the most destructive tornadoes in the history of Fairdale.
During the storm, Clem took a video from the top floor of his house as he saw the giant tornado get closer.
Clem thought the tornado would miss his house, when in fact it was coming directly towards him, all while he was still recording.
Unfortunately, Clem's wife would pass away because of the intensity of the tornado.
While Clem would receive a terrible spine injury, the phone he took the video on was later discovered in the rubble of his home, and this is what the video was able to capture.
Like, at some point, it's gotta register, like, oh!
Like, wait a minute.
I'm in danger here.
Maybe I need to go to the basement.
And I feel like I would be at that point right here.
As soon as that light goes out, go.
He's still filming.
This next video He didn't die either
shows a man exploring the Paris catacombs, which is a place very well known for causing people to get lost.
They are essentially the most complex series of tunnels in the world, definitely not somewhere you'd want to find yourself exploring without experience.
The video shows this man getting lost and going into a full panic run as he doesn't know where to go to get out.
Like some dude actually went into the Paris catacombs by himself, ran around, got lost, went crazy, and was never seen again.
He was never found, but his camera later was, with no trace of the guy.
It's very bizarre.
These arrows point in a direction.
So how'd they get the video?
You just blow in from stupid town, bud?
Somebody else went in later and found it.
Occasionally also he stops to photograph he fell into a black hole or something.
It was unrecoverable You're banned gracie with the five which means that he's very very deep inside the catacombs So basically he's filming what he's seeing very deep inside the catacombs Other than the point of view shots or pictures
catacombs for centuries.
Man it's so scary.
So it is possible with these paintings that we may be able to be traced back to Tinderary to some extent.
After about four minutes we hear his breathing get louder and louder as though something was scaring him.
He's frightened, he's frightened.
Occasionally he stops perhaps to try to decide which way to run among all the many different corridors.
He's running faster and faster and faster, deeper and deeper into the catacombs.
And all of a sudden... He drops the camera.
You hear his breathing get louder and louder, as though something was scaring him.
He's frightened.
He stops, perhaps, to try to decide which way to run among all the many different corridors.
He's running faster and faster and faster, deeper and deeper into the catacombs.
This is fake, but it's literally not fake, though.
Like, it's not.
And all of a sudden...
Gone.
You gotta think, it's completely dark down there.
You literally can't see nothing.
He ain't got no flashlight, no nothing.
Dropped his camera, gone.
R.I.P., bruh.
Either he's dead or he's still down there living in them catacombs somewhere, like, surviving off, like, like cockroaches and stuff.
I don't know.