[SPEAKER_08]: The 15th regular meeting of the Medford City Council will come to order.
[SPEAKER_08]: Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_06]: Present.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Falco.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_06]: Present.
[SPEAKER_06]: Vice President McGurn.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_06]: Present.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_06]: President Dello Russo.
[SPEAKER_08]: Present.
[SPEAKER_08]: Seven members present, none absent.
[SPEAKER_08]: Please join us in rising to salute the flag.
[SPEAKER_08]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_08]: I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America.
[SPEAKER_08]: to the Republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: 1516-357, public hearing, location of poles, attachments of fixtures, and underground conduits, Medford, Massachusetts.
[SPEAKER_08]: You are hereby notified that by order of the City Council, a public hearing will be given at the Howard F. Alden Memorial Auditorium, 85 George P. Hassett Drive, Medford City Hall,
[SPEAKER_08]: on Tuesday, 7 p.m., April 19, 2016, on a petition by Light Tower Fiber Networks, 80 Central Street, Boxborough, 01719, permission to dig a 40-foot service lateral from National Grid manhole number 666 to existing private telecom manhole located at corner of River's Edge
[SPEAKER_08]: and Cooper Street Light Tower will place one 17-by-30-by-18-inch handhold in the sidewalk before entering the private manhole system.
[SPEAKER_08]: The purpose of this is to provide an internet conduit for the new customer management sciences for health located at
[SPEAKER_08]: 200 Rivers Edge Drive.
[SPEAKER_08]: Underground utility work, one, place schedule 40 PVC conduit, 24 inch deep.
[SPEAKER_08]: Electric manhole number 666 to private manhole depicted in proposed civil plan, 200 Rivers Edge Drive at Cooper Street.
[SPEAKER_08]: did February 2016.
[SPEAKER_08]: Two, place one service hand hole, 17 by 30 by 18, in the sidewalk of Rivers Edge Drive.
[SPEAKER_08]: Number three, light tower will backfill with suitable fill, free of large rock, and will restore roadway and sidewalks to equal or better condition than before construction began.
[SPEAKER_08]: or to the exact specification of the City of Medford approved chief engineer with a provision that no city-owned or private utilities or other structures are adversely impacted.
[SPEAKER_08]: Lightow shall ensure that all sewer, water, and drain lines are marked prior to any excavation.
[SPEAKER_08]: Any disturbed concrete sidewalk panels shall be replaced in kind as a built sketch
[SPEAKER_08]: must be delivered to the 200 Rivers Edge General Contractor for inclusion into the overall as-built plan for this site.
[SPEAKER_08]: Copy must be delivered to the city also.
[SPEAKER_08]: Roadway restoration must meet or exceed city of Metro requirements and shall be coordinated with the general contractors, restoration of other utility trenches.
[SPEAKER_08]: is the intention to have one large surface repair that fully encompasses all the trench work.
[SPEAKER_08]: Light Tower at Alia shall coordinate with the City of Medford regarding this work.
[SPEAKER_08]: Before beginning work, the contractor shall notify DICSAFE and shall obtain applicable permits from the engineering division.
[SPEAKER_08]: The contractor shall utilize City of Medford regulations and standards for restoration as well as removal of all debris
[SPEAKER_08]: related to this work approved by the superintendent of wires call 7, 8, 1, 3, 9, 3, 2, 4, 2, 5 for any accommodations.
[SPEAKER_08]: Sincerely yours, Edward P Finn clerk city of Medford.
[SPEAKER_08]: Uh, is the petitioner present?
[SPEAKER_08]: Welcome.
[SPEAKER_08]: Good evening.
[SPEAKER_08]: Uh, we are calling opening up this, uh, public hearing and we, uh, invite all those in favor of this,
[SPEAKER_07]: to present themselves before us.
[SPEAKER_07]: Are you in favor?
[SPEAKER_07]: I'm in favor.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'm Ryan McDonald from Access Engineering here on behalf of Lightower Fiber Networks.
[SPEAKER_07]: Anybody else in favor of this project?
[SPEAKER_08]: Anybody else here in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: Hearing and seeing none, we declare this portion of the meeting closed and open it up to those to present themselves who are in opposition to this.
[SPEAKER_08]: Anybody in opposition, please present yourself to the podium.
[SPEAKER_08]: Anyone in opposition?
[SPEAKER_08]: Hearing and seeing none, we declare that portion of the meeting closed.
[SPEAKER_08]: If you could, sir, welcome.
[SPEAKER_08]: Please state your name and address for the record and tell us about this project.
[SPEAKER_03]: Once again, Ryan McDonald from Access Engineering out of Westborough, Massachusetts.
[SPEAKER_03]: The purpose of this project is to provide internet service for management health services located at 200 Rivers Edge Road in Medford.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pretty much that's it.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilors, any questions?
[SPEAKER_07]: Councilor Lungel-Kern.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thank you, President DeLaRusso.
[SPEAKER_13]: So this is to service the new projects that it is going up currently?
[SPEAKER_03]: We actually just got contacted by Management Health Services, so it's just for their purposes, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_13]: And are they located in the new building?
[SPEAKER_13]: They are located in the new building, yes.
[SPEAKER_13]: So if you have to provide power, is this line going to
[SPEAKER_13]: extend to everybody in the building, be able to extend every time?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_13]: Okay, so you won't have to come before us again for every unit that's occupied.
[SPEAKER_08]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_13]: Great, thank you.
[SPEAKER_13]: Council Meyers.
[SPEAKER_19]: Councilor Martins.
[SPEAKER_19]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_19]: So when will the bulk of the work be done?
[SPEAKER_19]: Will it be done during the day or is this going to be... We're flexible.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whatever you guys will allow us to do, we prefer to do it during the day.
[SPEAKER_03]: Worst case scenario, five days.
[SPEAKER_03]: Best case, three days, which that's, you know, more the case is going to be three days, but we like to just prepare for five days just in case anything happens.
[SPEAKER_19]: Is there any interruption to the traffic flow in the area?
[SPEAKER_03]: Uh, we have a engineered traffic plan.
[SPEAKER_03]: I believe we'll have a police detail out there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So at some point, uh, yeah, at some point we'll have to close down now one portion of the road and then dig one half of the road and then move over and dig the other half of the road.
[SPEAKER_03]: But there will be one lane open at all times.
[SPEAKER_19]: Just one lane of traffic.
[SPEAKER_19]: So you won't be able to go east or west at a certain period of time.
[SPEAKER_19]: or one or the other?
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a double lane there on either way.
[SPEAKER_03]: So we'll have to close one side down while we're on one side.
[SPEAKER_19]: So on the other side, you'll have traffic on both ways?
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes, we'll have traffic on both ways.
[SPEAKER_07]: OK, thank you.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_11]: Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_11]: Is there going to be a project manager assigned or a point of contact assigned to make sure that the project is performed
[SPEAKER_03]: On time and according to City of Medford standards.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, I have the contact of Mark Pavone, Phoenix Communications, and Scott Harnois of Light Tile Fabric Networks.
[SPEAKER_03]: I can provide that information to you if you need it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That'd be great.
[SPEAKER_03]: I appreciate that.
[SPEAKER_08]: That was all I had, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_08]: I see the papers were in order.
[SPEAKER_08]: Everything seems fine to me.
[SPEAKER_08]: Motion moved by Councilor Knight, seconded by Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_20]: Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_20]: One last thing, and I'll assume that you'll put the road back in the same condition that it's in, because that's a fairly new road there.
[SPEAKER_20]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_20]: If there's any problems, feel free to reach out to us and we'll amend anything that you need.
[SPEAKER_08]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_08]: Motion for approval, seconded by Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_08]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: Congratulations.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Last week,
[SPEAKER_08]: City Council met with the Committee of the Whole to address a number of papers that were in committee.
[SPEAKER_08]: The paper was reported out to us and the clerk, over the week, created a list that came out into our packets.
[SPEAKER_08]: So we have this matter before us for consideration.
[SPEAKER_08]: Dozens of papers were received and placed on file, many of which had been in subcommittees in Committee of the Whole for several years.
[SPEAKER_08]: And some of them had been addressed in a lateral way, but never, according to parliamentary procedure, been moved out of committee.
[SPEAKER_08]: We have all the recommendations before us.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm sure the councilors had a time to review that lengthy list that we went through.
[SPEAKER_08]: Some of the papers are remaining in committee and are being addressed by the committee chairs.
[SPEAKER_08]: So with this paper before us, 16-418, the chair awaits a motion.
[SPEAKER_11]: Mr. President, a motion to waive the reading of each individual matter that's on the paper, and a motion to accept the committee report.
[SPEAKER_08]: I motion that Council elect to waive the reading of each individual matter, thanks be to God, and to accept the paper as whole.
[SPEAKER_08]: Second?
[SPEAKER_08]: Second, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_08]: Second by Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_08]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: Congratulations.
[SPEAKER_08]: Motions, orders, and resolutions.
[SPEAKER_08]: 16-404 offered by Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_08]: Be it resolved that the City Administration provide the Council with the following information.
[SPEAKER_08]: Listing of all roadways and sidewalks where public utilities have been performed or are scheduled to perform any digging or excavation work from January 1st, 2014 to date, including the street address of where the work took place or is scheduled to take place.
[SPEAKER_08]: A listing of all roadways and sidewalks where public utilities have performed any digging or excavation work that have not been completed in accordance with the established City of Medford standards from January 2014 to date, including the street addresses of where the work took place.
[SPEAKER_08]: Three.
[SPEAKER_08]: schedule of repair for all roadways and sidewalks where public utilities have performed any digging or excavation work that have not been completed in accordance with established City of Medford standards from January 2014 to date including the street addresses of
[SPEAKER_08]: where the work is to take place.
[SPEAKER_08]: Four, a listing of all trees that require pruning or removal that are the responsibility of public utilities, including street address of where the work is to be performed.
[SPEAKER_08]: And five, a schedule of repair for all trees that require pruning or removal that are the responsibility of public utilities, including the street addresses of where the work is to be performed.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_10]: Mr. President, thank you very much, and I appreciate you bearing with my long-winded resolution this evening.
[SPEAKER_10]: However, I feel as though it's very important that we begin to hold our public utilities a little bit more accountable to the work that they do on our roadways, on our sidewalks, as well as dealing with the trees that end up getting wrapped around public utility wires up in the sky, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I bring this resolution forward based upon a constituent call that I received back about a year ago.
[SPEAKER_10]: Doonan Street was done over, and public utilities were on Doonan Street, and they dug quite a large trench, and it was a trench that went up the whole length of the street.
[SPEAKER_10]: And the size of the equipment actually damaged the majority of the street up there, and the street's still not been repaired, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_10]: And I know that there are a number of other streets in the community that have this same situation happening.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'd like a list of the streets as noted in the resolution.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'd ask my council colleagues to join me in supporting this resolution.
[SPEAKER_10]: I've also asked for the trees that need to be cut down that are the responsibilities of public utilities.
[SPEAKER_10]: Just in the news last week, Mr. President, we saw
[SPEAKER_10]: couple down in Abington who were struck by a falling tree branch and killed.
[SPEAKER_10]: And there are many trees in the city that are wrapped up in the electric wires and the city of Medford will not cut them.
[SPEAKER_10]: The public utility is responsible for cutting them.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I'd like a list of those to make sure that we can monitor the work and be sure that it's done, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_08]: Wonderful.
[SPEAKER_08]: Uh, councillor Carrifiello.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_20]: I, I thank council nice for bringing this forward.
[SPEAKER_20]: You know, I drive around and I see, um,
[SPEAKER_20]: All these street dig ups that have been done, and you see the shoddy work that's done after.
[SPEAKER_20]: They've sunk when they're supposed to come back, and we fill them, and the company's never come back.
[SPEAKER_20]: Some of them are two, and three, four years old.
[SPEAKER_20]: And like I asked the gentleman the other night, if he's going to put the road back in the same condition, whether they do it.
[SPEAKER_20]: But there's probably hundreds of trenches that have been dug that just are sinking, and somebody should be held accountable for this.
[SPEAKER_20]: I don't know who inspects this from our city, but when they're done, and I know they sink a little bit after they're done, but there should be a time frame to go back and check it again so the company can come back and refill it and put it back where it belongs, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_20]: So again, I think this is a good motion.
[SPEAKER_20]: I support it.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: So on the motion to approve by Councilor Knight, seconded by Councilor Caraviello, chair recognizes Councilor Scarpello.
[SPEAKER_18]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_18]: I follow along with my fellow Councilors.
[SPEAKER_18]: One of the biggest calls I've been getting and driving around is after the utility work comes in, the sinking of those areas, I think, that are very noticeable now.
[SPEAKER_18]: They're really noticeable when you see the new work on new streets, and then the little patchwork comes in.
[SPEAKER_18]: There was some that are really dangerous out there.
[SPEAKER_18]: So I think that I appreciate Councilor Knight for bringing this forward and I support this wholeheartedly.
[SPEAKER_18]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_18]: Thank you, Councilor.
[SPEAKER_08]: Chair recognizes Councilor Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thank you, President Dello Russo.
[SPEAKER_13]: I too agree with the resolve.
[SPEAKER_13]: I know this has come up many a times and I remember about probably eight years ago we had this issue.
[SPEAKER_13]: with streets not being repaired, and how do we hold them accountable?
[SPEAKER_13]: And it didn't really seem to go anywhere, because obviously you need the administration to get on board, create a plan to enforce our ordinances with regards to utility companies being held accountable.
[SPEAKER_13]: So I think this is a great resolve.
[SPEAKER_13]: I would just ask maybe for a little more clarity, or just if we could be clear with regards to which departments we're sending them to, so that the city administration, the mayor, can send our resolve off to the right places.
[SPEAKER_13]: For instance, number four and five, obviously we'd ask Miss Aggie Tude and our tree warden to, I don't know if she would do like an audit of every tree, or go through the streets and figure out which ones need repair, which ones need to be cut for the safety of the public.
[SPEAKER_13]: And then I'm assuming maybe the city engineer for the top three.
[SPEAKER_13]: I just want to make sure we request the appropriate departments
[SPEAKER_13]: to do this work so that we know who to go to and ask, you know, why haven't you done it?
[SPEAKER_13]: Or when will we be expecting the documents?
[SPEAKER_13]: I think that's important.
[SPEAKER_08]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_08]: So on the motion of approved by Councilor Knight, seconded by Councilor Caraviello, as amended by Vice President Lungo-Koehn, Chair recognizes Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_19]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_19]: And this is a very wise resolution regarding the upkeep of our streets.
[SPEAKER_19]: and to hold the utility companies accountable.
[SPEAKER_19]: I would suggest, as Councilor Lungo-Koehn mentioned, that over the last several years, we've struggled as a city because there's really no oversight on behalf of the city to represent the city, to make sure, as Councilor Caraviello mentioned, that these jobs are being done up to our standards and according to the contract.
[SPEAKER_19]: So I would ask if Councilor Knight doesn't mind
[SPEAKER_19]: to amend his resolution that we put a section in there that puts who the clerk of the work is on behalf of the city.
[SPEAKER_19]: So at least, and there may not be someone, and that's the whole issue that we have, that there is no oversight, the clerk of the work for each job and each utility job, because someone here at City Hall has to sign off anytime a road is being broken into and so forth, excavated.
[SPEAKER_19]: So I would ask that we amend that
[SPEAKER_19]: to put who is the clerk of the work on behalf of the city, for each of the projects.
[SPEAKER_08]: So on the motions, as further amended by Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_08]: On the motion for approval, it's seconded by Councilor Caraviellole, as amended by Vice-President Lungo-Koehn, and Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_08]: All those in favour?
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: Passes.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you, Councilors.
[SPEAKER_08]: 16-405 offered by Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_08]: Be it resolved that the Medford City Council request the purchase of crime wash signs for the West Medford area in light of the current rash of break-ins into the homes and automobiles.
[SPEAKER_20]: Chair recognizes Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_20]: Mr. President, myself and Councilor Marks have attended these meetings with many people from the West Medford area in regards to the rash of breaks both in the cars and in the homes.
[SPEAKER_20]: The neighbors were very diligent there, a lot of them showed up and they've established their own little crime watch there.
[SPEAKER_20]: So hopefully that'll help with some of the break-ins there.
[SPEAKER_20]: But they felt that in the past, there had been crime watch signs up in a lot of those streets.
[SPEAKER_20]: And the neighbors and the committee would like to have in the back.
[SPEAKER_20]: And Chief Sacco is in agreement, he thinks that it shouldn't be that big of a deal.
[SPEAKER_20]: to get them and put them back up, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_20]: So, and I think there's some neighbors here that may want to speak in support of that also.
[SPEAKER_08]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_08]: So on the motion of approval by Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_08]: Chair recognizes the citizen at the podium.
[SPEAKER_08]: Welcome.
[SPEAKER_08]: Good evening, sir.
[SPEAKER_08]: Please state your name and address for the record.
[SPEAKER_15]: My name is Robert Pinter.
[SPEAKER_15]: I live at Zero Summit Road, Medford, Mass., a former member of your August body.
[SPEAKER_15]: I've attended both of those meetings and there is a major concern in the West Medford area as well as throughout the entire city of Medford.
[SPEAKER_15]: But these signs did have, in fact, an impact many years ago as it related to crime taking place, especially in the West Medford area and other parts.
[SPEAKER_15]: I think it's a beginning that needs to take place.
[SPEAKER_15]: There are 100 people strong.
[SPEAKER_15]: They have petitions walking the street.
[SPEAKER_15]: And the real need that needs to take place is this upcoming budget that you folks are going to have to deal with here on the city council.
[SPEAKER_15]: This administration has to step up to the plate.
[SPEAKER_15]: and recognize the fact that in the petition that's running around, they're asking for 10 additional street police officers over the next two years, whether they be bicycle files, fellas, gals, and whether they be motorcycle, walking patrolmen, patrol ladies, or just more people for visibility in the neighborhood.
[SPEAKER_15]: It's a desperate need.
[SPEAKER_15]: They're serious.
[SPEAKER_15]: They don't like their houses broken into.
[SPEAKER_15]: They don't like their cars hijacked.
[SPEAKER_15]: And they don't like to be held hostage in their own community.
[SPEAKER_15]: So when only 72 police officers
[SPEAKER_15]: On the patrol, in our city method right now, we need to increase that.
[SPEAKER_15]: We need to represent ourselves as being a community that is responding to the needs of the community, especially in the areas of public safety.
[SPEAKER_15]: And I believe it's in this city council and prior city councils that's always mandated that public safety was its number one issue.
[SPEAKER_15]: Thank you, sir.
[SPEAKER_08]: Motion approved by Councilor Caraviello, seconded by Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_08]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: 16-406 offered by Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_08]: Be it resolved that the Medford City Council discuss and request a crosswalk be inserted at the corner of Grove Street and Buzzle Road in the interest of public safety.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_20]: As the traffic grows in the West Medford area, as people know, the city's becoming more of a cut-through every day.
[SPEAKER_20]: All these apps on your phones are all giving people
[SPEAKER_20]: cut-throughs, all these little side streets.
[SPEAKER_20]: Grove Street is becoming busier every day, and one of the new areas to cut through is down Bustle Lane, which goes to Placehead Park.
[SPEAKER_20]: There is a mirror up there that helps slow the traffic, but no one seems to be stopping there, and the car's just running right through there.
[SPEAKER_20]: Didn't a famous doctor live there?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes, he did.
[SPEAKER_20]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_20]: If he was here tonight, I'm sure he would be in favor of that.
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_20]: Some of the neighbors are a little concerned.
[SPEAKER_20]: They're walking the children down to the park.
[SPEAKER_20]: And if we could have, I know there's a stop sign there, but if a crosswalk would be helpful, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_08]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_08]: So on the motion approved by Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_08]: Ma'am, you wish to speak on this matter?
[SPEAKER_08]: Welcome.
[SPEAKER_08]: Please state your name and address for the record.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good evening, and thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: My name is Patricia Wheeler.
[SPEAKER_01]: I live at 35 Wellgate Road.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would greatly, as Councilman Caraviello said, together with my neighbors, we would like to see a crosswalk.
[SPEAKER_01]: In addition, children crossing sign, when you cross up from Bustle over to Grove, the curb is so high that it really causes a delay for the children to get their bicycles safely on the sidewalk, moms with strollers, and you literally have to enter into the roadway to look down Grove Street to see oncoming traffic that comes up High Street, and they do come at a high rate of speed, and it has had dramatic increase in traffic because of the apps that Councilman has referred to.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is absolutely a public safety necessity, and these steps would greatly mitigate any potential damage to a pedestrian.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you for your time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: So on the motion for approval by Councilor Caraviello, Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_19]: I agree.
[SPEAKER_19]: In addition to the crosswalk pedestrian crossing signage, neon signage is very important to alert people.
[SPEAKER_19]: There is a crosswalk there.
[SPEAKER_19]: Being familiar with the area, I'm not sure exactly where the councilman wants to put the crosswalk, but I think if you put it close to the bridge, that may be a public safety concern, because coming from High Street down Grove, you're really cut off from visual at a great length.
[SPEAKER_19]: But when you're coming from... They have a mirror there.
[SPEAKER_19]: They have a mirror there, but when you're coming down from Winchester, you have a long strip and you can actually see someone.
[SPEAKER_19]: So my suggestion would be to put the crosswalk
[SPEAKER_19]: further down from the bridge.
[SPEAKER_19]: So if you're coming from Wellgate, you'd have to walk up Grove Street and then cross over.
[SPEAKER_19]: I think it adds a little bit more safety than having it too close to the bridge.
[SPEAKER_19]: It's an odd configuration of streets there.
[SPEAKER_19]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: I agree.
[SPEAKER_01]: So what I've seen be the problem, you know, problematic area is when you come up Bustle and you go looking left down Grove Street,
[SPEAKER_01]: that literally puts you in the line of traffic to have a line of sight.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if you put the crosswalk just to the right of that area, so basically you come up Bustle, and the way the traffic lines are painted, there's an opening that would really lend itself to a visible aid to motorists with the crosswalk right there that people are coming up and crossing.
[SPEAKER_19]: So if you're coming up Bustle, you're saying?
[SPEAKER_01]: As you take that left, there's a wide area to cross over Grove.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's on the Winchester side, if you will, of the train bridge.
[SPEAKER_01]: The cross.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would be basically at the base of where the mirror is, affects to, I think, a telephone pole.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would really benefit the community.
[SPEAKER_01]: That makes sense.
[SPEAKER_19]: That way you have a line of vision both ways.
[SPEAKER_19]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_19]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor.
[SPEAKER_08]: So on the motion for move by Councilor Caraviello, as amended with the country remarks with the, uh, children, protest, cross, cross, all those in favor.
[SPEAKER_08]: All right.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_09]: Can I further amend the paper, Mr. President, to ask for a directed patrol there for the next couple of weeks, just to be sure that we monitor the activity there as well as that it's getting more and more stuck in town.
[SPEAKER_09]: So if you want to go down that route, please.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thanks, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_08]: I ask further amendment by Councilor Knight that there be a directed patrol there to monitor the situation, and perhaps that input that the Traffic Commission would find beneficial to remedy the problem.
[SPEAKER_08]: On the motion for approval, as seconded and amended,
[SPEAKER_08]: Hence, Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_19]: I think it would only be appropriate, whereas this council voted unanimously a couple of weeks ago to prompt the administration to use thermoplastic crosswalks rather than the traditional paint that fades after six months.
[SPEAKER_19]: And thermoplastic, we all know, is highly reflective and slip resistant and lasts up to five years, that this crosswalk be installed with thermoplastic
[SPEAKER_19]: So the residents won't have to come six months from now saying, we can't see the faded crosswalk.
[SPEAKER_08]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_19]: So I would amend if Councilor Caraviello would mind that.
[SPEAKER_08]: That would be fine, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_08]: And shift the whole plastic.
[SPEAKER_08]: An excellent amendment, as further amended by Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_08]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: Motion carries.
[SPEAKER_08]: Offered by Vice President Lungo-Koehn, 16-407.
[SPEAKER_08]: Be it resolved that the Medford City Council request that the city solicitor appear at our next meeting to publicly discuss his findings after his review of the contract the city has with Republic Parking.
[SPEAKER_08]: Madam Vice President.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_13]: President Dello Russo, I believe it was last Monday or Tuesday, we received an email with regards to Republic Parking selling, which we were all pretty in shock by.
[SPEAKER_13]: Nobody knew.
[SPEAKER_13]: I don't believe the administration knew either.
[SPEAKER_13]: and I know that it's in the city solicitor's hands as of today.
[SPEAKER_13]: It's been a week.
[SPEAKER_13]: I was hoping some of his research and obviously review of the contract would give us a better idea of where we go and move forward.
[SPEAKER_13]: I know we all have questions that need to be answered.
[SPEAKER_13]: I know the public has questions and the public has concerns, so I would like to obviously educate us as well as the public, but after getting
[SPEAKER_13]: I did speak to the city solicitor.
[SPEAKER_13]: I know that there could quite possibly be a number of things that could happen and some things that he would like to talk to us in executive session about.
[SPEAKER_13]: I think that's something that he's definitely willing and going to do next week.
[SPEAKER_13]: I'm not sure if you discussed it with him, President, but I think that's something that we at least need to get our questions answered.
[SPEAKER_13]: And if it is a situation where, if you read the contract, I know a lot of people have been bringing it up.
[SPEAKER_13]: And number 23 is the termination clause.
[SPEAKER_13]: So.
[SPEAKER_08]: And he urged us to, if you don't mind me interrupting, Vice President, that we refrain from speculation in an open forum where this matter is so delicate and sensitive.
[SPEAKER_13]: Right.
[SPEAKER_13]: I'm not going to be long-winded and talk about all the problems and whether or not we should get rid of the contract or whether or not we should try to change the contract.
[SPEAKER_13]: I think we just need to sit down and get a better understanding of where our city solicitor believes we're at and where we could possibly be.
[SPEAKER_13]: And then after that, I think we need to try to educate the public as much as we can, as well as when the time comes.
[SPEAKER_13]: possibly hold a public hearing with regards to everybody's concerns and issues with the parking program so that the administration and the city solicitor know what do we need to do, how can we make this better, what do we see as our two-year goals with regards to parking enforcement.
[SPEAKER_13]: I think that's very important and I think the public needs to be educated and
[SPEAKER_13]: It needs to be obviously transparent as much as it can be.
[SPEAKER_13]: So I look forward to the meeting next week, hopefully get some of our questions answered.
[SPEAKER_13]: And then after that meeting, once it's safe to do so, I think we need to obviously educate the public and get some input, public input on how to move forward.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you very much, Madam Vice President.
[SPEAKER_08]: So on that motion, all those in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: Motion carries.
[SPEAKER_08]: 16-408 offered by Councilor Falco.
[SPEAKER_08]: Be it resolved that the city administration
[SPEAKER_08]: provide the Medford City Council with policies and guidelines that are used to operate the
[SPEAKER_08]: Click Fix System.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Felk?
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_04]: I received a number of calls this week regarding the C-Click Fix System.
[SPEAKER_04]: I support the C-Click Fix System 100%.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think it's a great tool.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a great way to monitor issues and actually get things done efficiently.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it seems that
[SPEAKER_04]: We've had a number of issues recently where it's almost becoming more of a populist of some sort, where people, the specific call that I got this week was that someone took a picture of someone else doing something wrong and putting it on CNN.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that is something that's been taken down.
[SPEAKER_04]: But I really think that we should know as a community council, what are the policies
[SPEAKER_04]: But is there a screening process?
[SPEAKER_04]: Are there any policies that you're suggesting behind the system when things actually get recorded and logged on the system?
[SPEAKER_04]: I know, I believe, a few weeks ago, Consular Marks had a resolution regarding it.
[SPEAKER_04]: We need to have that.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think when people talk about issues like this, the policies and guidelines, it's good to get a presentation on how it works.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I know Andrew mentioned weeks ago as well that it'd be nice to see the type of reporting that we can receive as soon as possible.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm really concerned about the policies, the procedures, the guidelines that surround the system.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I think we need to work with them at this point in time.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_08]: All right.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Falco, I wish they changed the name of it, because see, click, fix is difficult to say fast.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_20]: Mr. President, I applaud the administration moving forward with this and finally getting it in.
[SPEAKER_20]: I was able to attend
[SPEAKER_20]: The meeting when they debuted the program, and that was the exact concern that I had that I expressed that evening about that was turning it into a blog.
[SPEAKER_20]: And I think that's what it's become a little bit.
[SPEAKER_20]: And I think Councilor Falco's right.
[SPEAKER_20]: Maybe we should have a meeting with the people or whoever operates it, maybe help fine tune it a little bit.
[SPEAKER_20]: And I think that would be better for everybody.
[SPEAKER_20]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_11]: On Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes, Mr. President, I think we've made a number of resolutions relative to the C-Click-Fix program since the press release came out about its inception.
[SPEAKER_10]: And I think that Councilor Falco, Councilor Luxembourg, the Grand Trafficking Committee, the Board of Governors, and I think that I understand and can kind of grasp
[SPEAKER_10]: as to how this program is going to work, whether or not we have enough personnel and manpower behind it to support the initiatives.
[SPEAKER_10]: The timelines that are being set forward, Mr. President, so with that being said, I owe a lot of your support.
[SPEAKER_10]: So it was a matter of being able to be able to pay this forward.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think it's a great system.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think it works.
[SPEAKER_04]: I support it.
[SPEAKER_04]: If used properly, I think it's a system that can be used to bring neighborhoods together and not be divisive so much.
[SPEAKER_04]: I support this as a monitor, Senator, just to get some more information.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you, Councilors.
[SPEAKER_08]: And so on the motion for approval by Councilor Falco, seconded by Councilor Marx.
[SPEAKER_08]: All those in favour?
[SPEAKER_08]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: Motion carries.
[SPEAKER_08]: 16-415 offered by Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_08]: Be it resolved that the Medford City Council request that the Medford Police increase enforcement of distracted driving infraction in the interest of public safety.
[SPEAKER_20]: Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_20]: Mr. President, I don't know if you've seen in the last few weeks on different stations, different cities, they're doing distracted driving stops around town where they have an office further up the road.
[SPEAKER_20]: And they're reporting people that are texting on the phone and driving, which is, I'm on the road all day and I see it constantly.
[SPEAKER_20]: People just aren't paying attention and it's only a matter of time before
[SPEAKER_20]: And if somebody gets run over, and I'm sure that's a major reason for most of the accidents that are happening now, is people just not paying attention.
[SPEAKER_20]: So I would maybe, if the chief could maybe increase his policy on that.
[SPEAKER_20]: I don't know if we even have a policy on it.
[SPEAKER_20]: But we do speed traps, we do all the kinds of things.
[SPEAKER_20]: I think maybe this is something we should look into,
[SPEAKER_20]: keep people more stable in our city.
[SPEAKER_08]: On the motion approved by Councilor Kerviel, seconded by Councilor Falco.
[SPEAKER_08]: All those in favour?
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: Motion carries.
[SPEAKER_08]: Offered by Councilor Mark, 16-416.
[SPEAKER_08]: Be it resolved that the city's lead service water lines be discussed in the interest of public safety.
[SPEAKER_08]: Very good, Councilor.
[SPEAKER_19]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_19]: I read an article in the Boston Globe back February 11th that talked about lead water pipes and the concern of lead water pipes in the Boston area.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I think the article was a result of Flint, Michigan.
[SPEAKER_19]: And we all know the disaster that took place in Flint.
[SPEAKER_19]: And the article went on to report that there are a number of communities that still have a high percentage of lead lines.
[SPEAKER_19]: And it listed the city of Malden having 47% of their total service lines in the city as lead lines, which is a very high percentage.
[SPEAKER_19]: And then it went on to say the city of Medford has 28%, which was the second highest.
[SPEAKER_19]: And this is in the MWRA district.
[SPEAKER_19]: It's not statewide, but is in the MWRA district.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I found that number to be, in my own opinion, very excessive, knowing that the city went through
[SPEAKER_19]: change back in 2004 when they created a policy to try to address lead service lines in the community.
[SPEAKER_19]: So I did a little research into it, Mr. President, but the reason why I bring this up tonight is to draw awareness to residents that may have a lead line still connected, to report on the fact and not what was reported in the Boston Globe, which listed Method as the second highest.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I don't believe, according to my
[SPEAKER_19]: facts and figures, we are the second highest in the MWRA district of lead lines.
[SPEAKER_19]: And also to let residents know that there may be some solutions to a very costly replacement of a lead line, which could run $3,000 to $5,000 to remove a line.
[SPEAKER_19]: So if your home was built prior to 1940, which many of our homes in this community were built prior, I know I live in a home that was built prior to 1940,
[SPEAKER_19]: your house most likely has a lead service line.
[SPEAKER_19]: And there are standards that were created that allows for a certain percentage of lead to exist within someone's bloodstream.
[SPEAKER_19]: However, for infants and young children, it could be very dangerous, even low, low levels.
[SPEAKER_19]: And what I found out, Mr. President, is that Medford has roughly 14,000
[SPEAKER_19]: water service lines.
[SPEAKER_19]: And according to the MWRA, 28% of those, or 3,920, are made of lead.
[SPEAKER_19]: And after talking to Ron Baker in our water department, who's a very astute person when it comes to water in this community, he mentioned to me that, and he sent me a list, and I can provide that to members of the council,
[SPEAKER_19]: In 2004, the city started with a lead replacement program.
[SPEAKER_19]: And their hope was every year that they would reduce that by 7%.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I don't know if they met the quarter every year.
[SPEAKER_19]: I didn't go through the exact numbers.
[SPEAKER_19]: But from 2005, fiscal year 2005 to 2015, the city has replaced 1,768 lead lines in the community.
[SPEAKER_19]: And when I say they replaced, meaning that when a resident calls up and says, I'd like to, you know, they hire a contractor, get rid of my lead line, the lead line comes out to the curb.
[SPEAKER_19]: And then the city has another portion that leads to the main in the street.
[SPEAKER_19]: So there may be another six or eight feet that the city's responsible for.
[SPEAKER_19]: So the city keeps track of what they've done on their end through these figures, and they have reported 1,768
[SPEAKER_19]: changes in lead lines since 2005.
[SPEAKER_19]: So if you look at the figures now, according to what Ron Baker provided me, and I would assume the Globe that wrote this article on February 11th would have updated information when they're reporting, there currently exist roughly 2,232 lead lines in the community.
[SPEAKER_19]: And this is a rough estimate, but it's a very close estimate.
[SPEAKER_19]: And that is only 16% of the total
[SPEAKER_19]: service lines in the community, not 28 percent.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's almost 1,200 lead lines off in that article.
[SPEAKER_19]: So I wanted to report the facts, at least I've received.
[SPEAKER_19]: And if anyone wants to dispute that, I'd be more than happy to sit down and discuss what I found out on this information, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_19]: And, you know, when you look at what we received from the MWRA, it's virtually lead-free.
[SPEAKER_19]: So our water comes, for the most part, from the Quab and Rez.
[SPEAKER_19]: It's through steel pipes, concrete pipes, iron pipes, comes over to the city of Medford, might travel some 25, 30, 40 miles in piping, and then it comes up to your home, and if you have a lead line, from eight feet into your house, lead can leach into your water.
[SPEAKER_19]: So it travels 30 miles lead-free, it gets up to your home, and guess what?
[SPEAKER_19]: Your eight-foot connection to the main could be putting you at risk for lead poisoning.
[SPEAKER_19]: And it's a major concern, especially, as I mentioned, for young children and infants.
[SPEAKER_19]: However, there is some helpful hints in your cold water, as reported in the paper, which was helpful.
[SPEAKER_19]: I think they were accurate on that.
[SPEAKER_19]: If you run your cold water a few minutes, it takes any of the leaching that
[SPEAKER_19]: If the water's been sitting there a while in your cold lead pipes, it takes any of that and cuts it out in the drain.
[SPEAKER_19]: So you let that run for a little while.
[SPEAKER_19]: And the city of Boston, and I'm not proposing this tonight, but the city of Boston for their residents offers financing.
[SPEAKER_19]: So if you have a hardship and you say, geez, I can't afford this time to spend $3,000 to $5,000 to replace my lead line, although I have three infants in my home.
[SPEAKER_19]: and I'm very concerned, they do offer a financing program.
[SPEAKER_19]: My motion tonight, Mr. President, is to have the water department create a list of lead service lines that they're aware of, they may not be aware of every single one, but they're aware of, and notify residents of a lead connection.
[SPEAKER_19]: So I think it would be a very helpful PR that the city of Medford, we receive so many
[SPEAKER_19]: confirmations and calls.
[SPEAKER_19]: If I was a homeowner, I'd like to know, I may not be astute and realize that I have a lead line coming into my house.
[SPEAKER_19]: I'd like to know if the city of Medford thinks I have a lead line for my own sense of peace and knowledge.
[SPEAKER_19]: And so that would be the first resolution that I offer motion is the city contact those that may have a lead line for notification, nothing else but notification.
[SPEAKER_19]: And also that
[SPEAKER_19]: The MWRA, if we can get a report back from the MWRA, whether or not there's any way that they can assist residents in the replacement of lead lines, if there's any funding available.
[SPEAKER_19]: I know the city takes advantage of roughly a million dollars a year in 0% finance loans through the MWRA.
[SPEAKER_19]: And would any of that apply to residents that may have a concern with lead
[SPEAKER_19]: in their water.
[SPEAKER_19]: There's also lead testing done.
[SPEAKER_19]: The way I understand it, it's done randomly in every city and town in the MWRA district.
[SPEAKER_19]: So they may pick a few homes throughout the community, do lead testing, and report on that particular testing.
[SPEAKER_19]: But if anyone has a concern or believe that they may have, for whatever reason, high quantities of lead, they should be able to contact the Method Water Department.
[SPEAKER_19]: and find out more information on where they can get some lead testing done, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_19]: And this is all  I don't want to alarm people, but I think it's only important that people are aware of some of the concerns, some of the health concerns with lead and ways that they may be able to combat the lead on their own by running the faucet and so forth.
[SPEAKER_19]: And again, the MWRA provides this water to us from 30 miles out.
[SPEAKER_19]: I remember a while back, someone made a presentation when we were talking about water and sewer rates.
[SPEAKER_19]: And it was, I remember at the time, and it's still stuck in my head, to deliver a gallon of water from the Corbin Res to your home of fresh drinking water, it's roughly one penny in cost.
[SPEAKER_19]: Now, the sewer may be a different pot.
[SPEAKER_19]: You know, the sewer may have a different cost.
[SPEAKER_19]: But to deliver, it's one penny.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I just find that amazing, especially with
[SPEAKER_19]: the job that the MWRA is doing to provide clean drinking water to our residents so we don't have a Flint, Michigan in our community, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_19]: So those two offerings of motions I would offer tonight, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_08]: I count to three.
[SPEAKER_08]: So create a list of the city of Medford if they have the data and notify the residents if they have led service.
[SPEAKER_08]: Two, that the MWRA report to the city council
[SPEAKER_08]: regarding any programs they may have or opportunities for citizens to receive assistance in funding the repairs or the mitigation of lead pipes.
[SPEAKER_08]: And third, that the possibility or the resources for testing of a home's water be made available to the public.
[SPEAKER_08]: I recently saw on television, Councilor, that the primary
[SPEAKER_08]: A source still for lead poisoning in the United States, unfortunately, is lead paint in the homes ingested by children, which is a tragedy.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you for this.
[SPEAKER_08]: This was very informative, Councilor.
[SPEAKER_08]: Chair recognizes Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_20]: Councilor Marks is 100% right.
[SPEAKER_20]: There should be some type of program, at least for families that have children, for some type of help.
[SPEAKER_20]: I don't know many people that have $3,000, $4,000, $5,000 sitting around.
[SPEAKER_20]: of extra spending money to get this done.
[SPEAKER_20]: I mean, we have money in our water and soil account that we maybe make available for financing for some of these people.
[SPEAKER_20]: So again, I commend the council for this, and again, it's, especially the people with young families, it really is something they should look into, get done, and the city should provide some help to them.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: So on the motion for approval by Councilor Marks, it's seconded by Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_08]: Vice President Longo.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thank you briefly.
[SPEAKER_13]: I agree with my colleagues How would you know so I think that if the city has a record of that and I
[SPEAKER_13]: you know, feels to do what we're asking with regards to notifying those residents, I think that's really unfortunate.
[SPEAKER_13]: So I think the result's a good one, and I hope that the administration takes it seriously and gets that list together so that we can help notify families.
[SPEAKER_13]: When I got my new water meter is when I got my house, and I had it done then.
[SPEAKER_08]: On the motion for approval by Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_19]: If you happen to go into your basement and see where the water's coming in from outside, the lead line is usually like a brownish, greenish color almost.
[SPEAKER_19]: But you can actually see the line coming in.
[SPEAKER_19]: It may not come in too deep into the house, but you can actually see it.
[SPEAKER_19]: Someone knowing the difference between pipes, copper, lead, should be able to tell you.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I think on your deed itself, or I know when we bought our house, I think it mentioned
[SPEAKER_19]: you know, like it says you have a paid driveway, you have asphalt shingles.
[SPEAKER_19]: I think it also said you have a lead line or copper line or, you know, two 20 electricity.
[SPEAKER_19]: I think it did mention that.
[SPEAKER_19]: So that might be another way of, of also checking.
[SPEAKER_19]: And then hopefully if we can get the city to go through their records, uh, you know, they should be able to give us an accurate assessment.
[SPEAKER_08]: So on the motion for move by Councilor Marks, uh, seconded by councilor Caraviello,
[SPEAKER_08]: Chair recognizes the gentleman at the podium.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you, President Dello Russo.
[SPEAKER_02]: Name is not important.
[SPEAKER_02]: Point of possible information from Councilor Marks and all the people that have water.
[SPEAKER_02]: In order to tell what kind of pipe you have, it would probably be best
[SPEAKER_02]: says it's all dirty and corroded on the top, to scratch it with a piece of metal, and you'd be able to tell if it's a silvery look, that would probably lead, and you may want to get the lead out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Secondly, hopefully you have a reddish copper look, because you prefer copper pipes.
[SPEAKER_02]: As far as I know, these days, unless they change their mind, tomorrow morning.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: On the motion.
[SPEAKER_08]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: Motion carries.
[SPEAKER_08]: 16-417, offered by Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_08]: Be it resolved that the City Administration take the proper steps to notify the Council and the residents of Brewster Road of the construction work being performed on the street, including but not limited to 1.
[SPEAKER_08]: Dates that construction will take place.
2.
[SPEAKER_08]: City point person for the project.
3.
[SPEAKER_08]: Scope and purpose of the construction. 4.
[SPEAKER_08]: Any and all restrictions concerning road closure, detours, parking restrictions, driveway use restrictions.
[SPEAKER_08]: Five, a timeline of what work will be performed and when and where the work will occur.
[SPEAKER_08]: Be it further resolved that the administration make available the point that the point that person for this project to appear before the DPW subcommittee
[SPEAKER_08]: to address residents' concerns arising from this project.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Neill.
[SPEAKER_10]: Mr. President, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_10]: This new resolution was filed.
[SPEAKER_10]: I just wanted to just elect a notice to the residents on the street.
[SPEAKER_10]: A couple of weeks ago, I went up to the engineering division after a simple phone call from a constituent asking about the lines that are located on the street for cutting and excavation.
[SPEAKER_10]: And I went to the engineering division, and they said,
[SPEAKER_10]: Since that time, they have put, what was the construction?
[SPEAKER_10]: residence doors.
[SPEAKER_10]: However, there are still some questions, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I'd ask the administration to provide us with a timeline of construction, at least at this point, versus the scope and purposes for a drainage project that this council actually approved the funding for.
[SPEAKER_10]: There are going to be a significant number of restrictions on the road at this point, as is the number of pedestrians in the absence of residents.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'd just like to talk about communication, the engineering and planning to the residents of the road.
[SPEAKER_10]: First of all, as to what's going to be going on, what constraints are going to be in place, what restrictions are going to be on the expected potential of the road.
[SPEAKER_08]: On the motion for approval, all those in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: Carries 16-409.
[SPEAKER_08]: Offered by Vice President Lungo-Koehn, be it resolved that the Medford High School Drama Club be congratulated on their superb performances of Fiddler on the Roof last weekend.
[SPEAKER_08]: Be it further resolved that the performance director and Andrews Middle School music teacher, Sarah Grant,
[SPEAKER_08]: be thanked for her hard work in preparing and organizing the four plays.
[SPEAKER_08]: Madam Vice President.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thank you, President De La Ruzo.
[SPEAKER_13]: I just want to congratulate the students who were on Fiddler on the Roof, as well as the performance director.
[SPEAKER_13]: The show was amazing, and I just want to congratulate them.
[SPEAKER_13]: I know that
[SPEAKER_13]: This director, she is a music teacher at the Andrews Middle School, is also prepping now for the Andrews Middle School play of Annie, which is going to be coming up on June 10th and 11th.
[SPEAKER_13]: So I wanted to announce that.
[SPEAKER_13]: I'm hoping to take my girls to that play.
[SPEAKER_13]: And it's just really great to have the community involved.
[SPEAKER_13]: And such a great, somebody so great working with the children.
[SPEAKER_13]: Tomorrow?
[SPEAKER_13]: It is June 10th and 11th, the play of Annie at the Andrews, I believe it's at the Andrews Middle School.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: On the motion approved by Vice President London-Kern, all those in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: Opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: Motion carries.
[SPEAKER_08]: 16-410, offered by Councilors Falco and Caraviello, be it resolved that the Medford City Council commend and congratulate Medford Troop 416 on their 100th anniversary.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Falco.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_04]: I just wanted to say congratulations and happy anniversary to Troop 416 down at Otis Street.
[SPEAKER_04]: They run a fabulous program.
[SPEAKER_04]: There are over 100 Cub Scouts and Boy Scouts involved in the program.
[SPEAKER_04]: They produce Eagle Scouts, I think, almost every year.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it's just a great program.
[SPEAKER_04]: They have great leaders down there, Paul McLean, Bob Wright.
[SPEAKER_04]: They do a great job.
[SPEAKER_04]: I know they've always provided us with a lot of service projects, and I just wanted to say happy anniversary.
[SPEAKER_04]: Are you an Eagles fan from that group?
[SPEAKER_20]: I am not an Eagles fan.
[SPEAKER_20]: All right.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_20]: I just want to reiterate what Councilor Falco said.
[SPEAKER_20]: I've been down at Otter Street many times for the Eagle Awards, and I think they're having an event coming up soon in regards to this, if I read correctly.
[SPEAKER_04]: They had one this past weekend.
[SPEAKER_20]: Mr. President, if we could maybe have them come up here and offer them a commendation for their service, it would be appreciated.
[SPEAKER_08]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_08]: So on the motion approved by Councilor Falco.
[SPEAKER_08]: as amended and seconded by Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_08]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: Carries.
[SPEAKER_08]: 16-411 offered by Councilor Falco.
[SPEAKER_08]: Be it resolved that Medford City Council congratulate the Medford Middle Schools String Ensemble under the direction of Sophia Chang for winning the gold medal at the MICCA, Massachusetts Instrumental and Chorus Conductors Association Band and Orchestra Concert Festival.
[SPEAKER_08]: Be it further resolved that they be invited
[SPEAKER_08]: to a future city council meeting to accept accommodations.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor, we want them to come and play.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Marks had them play here last year.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Falco.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, having them come down and play I think is a fabulous idea.
[SPEAKER_04]: I know when I was on the school committee, they would come and play for us each year.
[SPEAKER_04]: And when you hear them play, it's amazing.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's hard to believe it's actually kids playing.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, they do a fabulous job.
[SPEAKER_04]: I just want to congratulate them on winning the gold medal again.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think this is, if not the third, maybe the fourth year in a row.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, there are a lot of great things happening in the Medford Public Schools.
[SPEAKER_04]: This is just a fabulous program that is happening.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sophia Chang does a great job, and the kids are just very, very talented.
[SPEAKER_04]: And congratulations to them again for just a fabulous accomplishment.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor.
[SPEAKER_08]: So on the motion for approval, all those in favor, all those carries 16-four one two offered by councilor Falco be resolved at the Medford city council.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thanks.
[SPEAKER_08]: Susan D a long time member of the board of trustees at Oak Grove cemetery for her 25 years of service.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_04]: Um, I just want to thank Susan D for a long time.
[SPEAKER_04]: I've been a long term, um, time member of the, um, board of trustees up at the Oak Grove cemetery.
[SPEAKER_04]: She gave over 25 years in that position, which is a significant amount of time.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I just wanted to say thank you on behalf of the council.
[SPEAKER_04]: And if I could just amend it to actually, if she could be invited to a future meeting to be recognized.
[SPEAKER_04]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_11]: Do we?
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: And we invited her, but I think it might've been when Councilor Falco was.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, was it the one?
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: I apologize.
[SPEAKER_04]: You weren't available at that meeting.
[SPEAKER_08]: On the motion for approval then.
[SPEAKER_08]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: Motion carries.
[SPEAKER_08]: Motion to suspend.
[SPEAKER_08]: Moved by Councilor, Vice-President Laura Kern for suspension of the rules.
[SPEAKER_08]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_13]: Madam Vice-President.
[SPEAKER_13]: Just briefly, while we're saying thank you and congratulations, I just wanted to mention the vigil that was held over the weekend and
[SPEAKER_13]: I guess congratulate them on a great event, but more so thank Medford's Overcoming Addiction and Janelle Rocco and her strong team for an amazing event.
[SPEAKER_13]: There were five or six strong speakers who were moving.
[SPEAKER_13]: And I know that they filled the auditorium at the high school.
[SPEAKER_13]: There was more people there than last year.
[SPEAKER_13]: I think it was at City Hall last year, and I think I had standing room only in the back, and it was standing room only again this year at a bigger event.
[SPEAKER_13]: So I have to say there's more faces on the wall.
[SPEAKER_13]: slideshow than last year and more names and recognizing half of them myself.
[SPEAKER_13]: It was definitely an emotional event, but it was wonderful at the same time.
[SPEAKER_13]: Trying to break the stigma, which so many people could use some education on the topic.
[SPEAKER_13]: I just want to thank them for doing what they're doing in the city of Medford.
[SPEAKER_13]: And obviously, the council's in support of what they're doing.
[SPEAKER_13]: The mayor was there in support.
[SPEAKER_13]: And it was a great event.
[SPEAKER_08]: So on the motion for approval, all those in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: Motion carries.
[SPEAKER_08]: While we're under suspension, we have papers to clean up here in the hand of the clerk, offered by Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_08]: Be it resolved that the Medford City Council congratulate
[SPEAKER_08]: our residents who participated in the running of the 120th Boston Marathon.
[SPEAKER_18]: Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_18]: Being a superb athlete myself, Mr. President, I want to congratulate our residents who competed in this weekend's historical event, and especially a few people that we know personally.
[SPEAKER_18]: I know that Meg Richard, a personal friend of most of ours, really did a great job.
[SPEAKER_18]: I believe she ran for
[SPEAKER_18]: juvenile diabetes, which is very impressive.
[SPEAKER_18]: And our neighbor, Bella Giambuso, who's a mother of three and a Fulton Street resident.
[SPEAKER_18]: And you realize how important and what this means to the families.
[SPEAKER_18]: I was speaking to her son yesterday, and he said he's so proud of his mother that she really set a tone in what anything they set their mind to, that they can achieve those same goals.
[SPEAKER_18]: So I think that's what the marathon does.
[SPEAKER_18]: And I know that I have a marathon runner at home, and my wife Dina, and this is something that's so important.
[SPEAKER_18]: And they should be commended.
[SPEAKER_18]: So I congratulate them on a job well done.
[SPEAKER_13]: I want to just piggyback on what Councilor Scarpelli said.
[SPEAKER_13]: I unfortunately myself miss Paul Revere because I went into a tear on some of those runners.
[SPEAKER_13]: It took me and my family two hours to get in, two hours to get home on three trains, but we watched the runners at noon and it was just amazing and you saw more faces than I even knew I was going to see.
[SPEAKER_13]: It's such an accomplishment.
[SPEAKER_13]: I want to congratulate.
[SPEAKER_13]: I think we had in bed for 86 runners.
[SPEAKER_20]: I opted for Paul Revere versus the Marathon.
[SPEAKER_20]: I was going to go, but we'd be remiss if we didn't thank myself and Ed Finn's classmate, 72, Dave McGilvery, who had another fine job of managing the Marathon this year.
[SPEAKER_20]: So congratulations to Dave McGilvery, class of 72.
[SPEAKER_20]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_05]: Nice.
[SPEAKER_08]: So congratulations to all those involved in the Boston Marathon.
[SPEAKER_08]: Who have ties to Medford.
[SPEAKER_08]: On that motion, all those in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: Motion carries.
[SPEAKER_08]: 16-419 offered by Councilor Scott Belli.
[SPEAKER_08]: Be resolved that the Mayor's Office report back to the City Council on the status of the trailer of the Medford High School band.
[SPEAKER_18]: Councilor?
[SPEAKER_18]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_18]: I received an email.
[SPEAKER_18]: from the parent president of the board, the band Parent Association.
[SPEAKER_18]: And I know they were asked to send quotes for the, I believe it was the new band trailer, and uniforms that were donated by Mayor McGlynn on his last wish list.
[SPEAKER_18]: So they're curious that when that would come about, because they believe that they were setting up
[SPEAKER_18]: time to drive down to Georgia to pick up that trailer, so if we can get some assistance on that, that'd be greatly appreciated.
[SPEAKER_18]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: On that motion, all those in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: Motion carries.
[SPEAKER_08]: Offered by Councilor Caraviello, be it resolved that the Medford City Council have the two electrical ground boxes at Carr Park be repaired immediately in the effort of public safety to children of Medford.
[SPEAKER_08]: These ground electrical boxes
[SPEAKER_08]: are located in front of the baseball and tennis courts.
[SPEAKER_08]: And the councilor, I think you all saw the photographs that the councilor had attached to this.
[SPEAKER_20]: Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_20]: Mr. President, I was informed of those by a couple of non-neighbors who were at the park with the children, and they brought that to my attention.
[SPEAKER_20]: I'm surprised no one has gotten hurt up there with those two boxes up there.
[SPEAKER_20]: So if that could be something that could be addressed immediately, Mr. President, it would be appreciated.
[SPEAKER_08]: On that motion, all those in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: Motion carries.
[SPEAKER_08]: Petitions, presentations, and similar matters petitioned by Robert L. Capucci, Jr., 71 Evans Street, Medford to address the City Council about TV3.
[SPEAKER_08]: We also have a
[SPEAKER_08]: a redundant motion as well as it is of the same subject matter from another citizen, but the chair will allow both to speak.
[SPEAKER_08]: So we welcome you, citizen Capucci, and ask you to share your name and address for the record.
[SPEAKER_16]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_16]: I'm Rob Capucci of 71 Evans Street.
[SPEAKER_16]: Let me start with the city is being denied a service that we're paying for.
[SPEAKER_16]: The last figure I heard is somewhere around half a million dollars from our Verizon and cable bill is going towards public access that's been shut off since, I believe, 2013.
[SPEAKER_16]: That's years of a disservice to Medford.
[SPEAKER_16]: So on Friday, I actually took a day off from work and I drove around to Melrose Community Public Access Station, SCAT TV in Somerville,
[SPEAKER_16]: and Stoneham.
[SPEAKER_16]: Just to give an idea of what we're being denied here in Medford.
[SPEAKER_16]: First of all, jobs.
[SPEAKER_16]: Somerville employs eight people full-time.
[SPEAKER_16]: Malden, I found out from one of the station managers that I visited, employs nine people full-time.
[SPEAKER_16]: Melrose has three people full-time with three part-timers, and I think it's the same in Stoneham.
[SPEAKER_16]: That's jobs being denied to Medford residents.
[SPEAKER_16]: That's number one.
[SPEAKER_16]: The programming that's on some of these stations is unbelievable.
[SPEAKER_16]: Self-help programs, community awareness programs.
[SPEAKER_16]: I think of some of the organizations here in Medford, like the Medford Community Coalition or Prominent Citizens that were just honored a few weeks ago, Jay Campbell, the fine things these folks do.
[SPEAKER_16]: With a public access TV show,
[SPEAKER_16]: it could be compounded and bring more great services to the city.
[SPEAKER_16]: I mean, you all know I'm a political activist, so my forte is, you know, we're in a big election year here.
[SPEAKER_16]: Candidates, next year's a municipal election year.
[SPEAKER_16]: Candidates could have a forum, another avenue to bring their campaign and talk about different things.
[SPEAKER_16]: You know, I think about in 2015, some 2,500 people blanked
[SPEAKER_16]: the ballot question.
[SPEAKER_16]: It might not have been so many if we had, you know, a public access TV show where we could discuss the pros and cons of the ballot question.
[SPEAKER_16]: Other things, too, that could happen, the Honorable Breanna Lungo-Koehn talked about
[SPEAKER_16]: communications from the police in terms of different things.
[SPEAKER_16]: He could have a show on there.
[SPEAKER_16]: You can talk about different neighborhoods in Medford that might be having problems or might need more attention.
[SPEAKER_16]: Boards and planning meetings that happen in this building could find a show from somebody who wishes to produce a show on things like that and bring more information
[SPEAKER_16]: which is power and knowledge to the taxpayers of this city that deserve public access.
[SPEAKER_16]: Now, in talking with other station managers and the wonderful things that they're doing, at least one of them, the station manager at Somerville, knew a little bit about what we have here in Medford, the equipment, and they offered, you know, they said if I'm successful in bringing a positive message and do get the ball rolling,
[SPEAKER_16]: They're going to reach out, and they're going to help us get us up on our feet and running.
[SPEAKER_16]: I'm sure there's a lot of other residents.
[SPEAKER_16]: The students, they have great teaching going on at Medford High School, but having our own public access, this could be almost like an internship for them to get real world experience to move on to whatever college and future careers they might have.
[SPEAKER_16]: In closing, I just want to say that I
[SPEAKER_16]: I hope that the mayor's office is watching this because I believe ultimately it resides in the mayor's office to get this back up and running or not.
[SPEAKER_16]: But if there's any kind of vote or any influence that you find city councilors can have on the mayor's office to get this going, it would be great.
[SPEAKER_16]: I mean, in terms of helping this city, there's so many things a public access station can do for children, for working families,
[SPEAKER_16]: and for our senior citizens.
[SPEAKER_16]: So I hope you take that into consideration.
[SPEAKER_16]: Thank you for your time.
[SPEAKER_16]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you very much, Mr. Capucci.
[SPEAKER_08]: Do we have a motion to receive and place on file?
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Falco?
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Caraviello?
[SPEAKER_08]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: Madam Vice President.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thank you, President Diller.
[SPEAKER_08]: On a motion of Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_13]: Yes, I don't know if we're going to combine the resolutions.
[SPEAKER_13]: I just think there's a lot of them we're not going to combine.
[SPEAKER_13]: Then on this one specifically, I hear our concerned citizen loud and clear.
[SPEAKER_13]: I think we've asked the question many times, what is going on?
[SPEAKER_13]: I know I had testified in front of Judge Jack Jackson, which seems like maybe
[SPEAKER_13]: and over 10 years ago.
[SPEAKER_13]: And I just, I think it's, I've voiced my opinion with regards to how the process moved along within the last 10 years.
[SPEAKER_13]: It's really unfortunate that the residents of this community are paying for an access station, putting money, money's taken out of their cable bill every single month.
[SPEAKER_13]: And I'm not sure the exact figure, but I think Mr. Cuccio was right.
[SPEAKER_13]: She was right, about half a million dollars is being held.
[SPEAKER_13]: Now, that's taxpayers' money.
[SPEAKER_13]: We've said it before.
[SPEAKER_13]: Are we going to give that back to the taxpayers, or are we going to do something about it, create a new station, something that the residents and the taxpayers, great payers, deserve?
[SPEAKER_13]: I think we need, it's time we get an update from our new mayor.
[SPEAKER_13]: It's been four months.
[SPEAKER_13]: We've had some time.
[SPEAKER_13]: for the administration to settle in.
[SPEAKER_13]: And I think we need to see what we're gonna do moving forward.
[SPEAKER_13]: And I hope that TV3, we did have one meeting with the administration and the mayor, which was a great meeting, but nothing about TV3 was discussed at that meeting.
[SPEAKER_13]: So I'm hoping at our next meeting with the mayor's office that we get some information with regards to how we're gonna move this forward.
[SPEAKER_13]: I think it's extremely important.
[SPEAKER_13]: He nailed it on the head with regards to students and what this can do for students alone, nevermind jobs.
[SPEAKER_13]: what other cities and towns are doing.
[SPEAKER_13]: It's really unfortunate the state that our TV access is in, which is a state, I guess, but we need to move this forward.
[SPEAKER_13]: This should be one of the tough things that need to be done within the next few months, and I hope that comes to fruition.
[SPEAKER_13]: So if we could get a report back from the mayor's office on what we're doing to move forward on this issue, TV3, getting a television station up and running in the city of Medford
[SPEAKER_13]: the entire community, an update would be appreciated.
[SPEAKER_08]: A motion to receive and place on file by Councilor Caraviello, seconded by- If you could withdraw that.
[SPEAKER_13]: Do you mind just move, just to get a report back from the Mayor's Office?
[SPEAKER_13]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: You withdraw that?
[SPEAKER_08]: On the motion of Councilor Lungo-Koehn that the Mayor's Office update the City Council on the efforts towards
[SPEAKER_08]: public access, TV3.
[SPEAKER_08]: Chair recognizes Councilman Max.
[SPEAKER_19]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_19]: I want to thank Mr. Capucci for bringing this topic up.
[SPEAKER_19]: It's a very important topic, and we know the old administration under Mayor McGlynn was anti-public access.
[SPEAKER_19]: I still can't figure out why, but for many years, that administration did everything they could to stop public access in this community, but still maintained
[SPEAKER_19]: the funding through franchise fees that we were all paying for PEG, government, public, and educational access.
[SPEAKER_19]: This current mayor now appointed many committees.
[SPEAKER_19]: I know, Mr. President, you chair the Business and Economic Committee, or co-chair, and I know there were recommendations just made by the Constituent Service Committee after having several public hearings in this community.
[SPEAKER_19]: And after hearing from residents, the main theme of their report was, we need more transparency in this community.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I find it ironic that the one thing that really would bring some great change in this community, and it's not a solve-all by any means, but government access.
[SPEAKER_19]: Community access.
[SPEAKER_19]: Those are the initiatives, I think, that as a government, we're obligated to let people voice their opinion.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I remember the good old days when they used to televise Medford High football games.
[SPEAKER_19]: And they used to televise the parade live.
[SPEAKER_19]: And they used to have talk shows on there.
[SPEAKER_19]: And they used to bring up current events in the community.
[SPEAKER_19]: And they'd have a cooking show, and they'd have other shows.
[SPEAKER_19]: It was just a great way of uniting the community.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I'm hoping this new administration practice what they preach in transparency and brings back local community access, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_19]: We're paying for it.
[SPEAKER_19]: There's a need in this community.
[SPEAKER_19]: People want to have access.
[SPEAKER_19]: I hear it over and over again, and I'm not sure why it takes so many years.
[SPEAKER_19]: to get access after creating committees to advise the administration.
[SPEAKER_19]: We've been there, done that.
[SPEAKER_19]: The Judge Jackson report, we've been there, done that.
[SPEAKER_19]: Now we want access.
[SPEAKER_19]: So I agree with the speaker and I'm hoping this administration, I know Mayor Burke has a lot on her plate, but I too would like to hear more about community access.
[SPEAKER_19]: I read the article in the first 100 days and that's great.
[SPEAKER_19]: There's been some change in the community
[SPEAKER_19]: some initiatives that this administration has offered.
[SPEAKER_19]: But some of the meat and potato issues, I still want to hear about.
[SPEAKER_19]: And this community access has been an albatross around the city's neck for a long time.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I think we need to address it, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_08]: The Vice President and the public are currently with you.
[SPEAKER_08]: The chair recognizes the citizen at the podium.
[SPEAKER_08]: Welcome, Mr. Indy, and Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you, Gene Martin, 10 Cumming Street.
[SPEAKER_12]: And I'm sorry, Indy, that was my bad.
[SPEAKER_12]: I didn't know you were sick.
[SPEAKER_12]: This could be an energizing battery for the city, for the business community, for the schools, for everything.
[SPEAKER_12]: But I wanted to break down some of the money issues involved because not everybody wants to talk about it.
[SPEAKER_12]: For every $100 that I pay in my cable bill, whether it be Verizon or Comcast, $5 gets taken off the top.
[SPEAKER_12]: The deal that the mayor made in 1988 or whatever it was, was that out of that $5, $3 goes to the general fund of the city of Medford.
[SPEAKER_12]: Now, I was hired on the arts community last week
[SPEAKER_12]: But if they were to seek that money from the general fund back into the arts community for AXS TV, then I would be a proponent of that.
[SPEAKER_12]: That's not what the city wants to hear, but I would be a proponent of having that money go back to what it's supposed to go to.
[SPEAKER_12]: Because when you tell me that Somerville hires nine people, they have to be using all 5% of that money.
[SPEAKER_12]: And so we only receive 2% for our peg, which is public, education,
[SPEAKER_12]: and government access.
[SPEAKER_12]: And 1% is used for, only 1% is used for the public access.
[SPEAKER_12]: The other 1% is split in half, the government channel slash high school channel or education channel.
[SPEAKER_12]: And so people need to be aware that there is more money in there.
[SPEAKER_12]: We're paying that out of our cable bills.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's not coming out of the tax base.
[SPEAKER_12]: So it's not the taxpayer's money.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's the rate payers' money, but it goes to the tax base.
[SPEAKER_12]: So there's a little bit of a mix up there.
[SPEAKER_12]: I know it's hard for people at home to figure that out.
[SPEAKER_12]: It took me a while to figure it out myself.
[SPEAKER_12]: So I just wanted to clarify that that's where the money comes from.
[SPEAKER_12]: And I want to know, if I could ask through the chair, is the theater has a cable drop?
[SPEAKER_12]: It has the ability, the theater, our Chevalier Theater currently has the ability
[SPEAKER_12]: to have a station in that building, it's cable ready.
[SPEAKER_12]: So if it's just because of the Boys and Girls Club, if we move the Boys and Girls Club out of the basement, we could automatically, without even renting a new space, just put the station in the basement of the theater.
[SPEAKER_12]: Because otherwise it's a cumbersome process to go through the square, find a spot, and it would take longer to do that.
[SPEAKER_12]: We could do that in the future or whatever, but if you wanted to have it done today, they're cable ready.
[SPEAKER_12]: The man that's in charge over there, he said that they had a cable drop, so it's cable ready.
[SPEAKER_12]: So thank you very much for letting me speak.
[SPEAKER_08]: Good evening.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_16]: Your name and address for the record, please, sir.
[SPEAKER_16]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_16]: Rob Capucci, 71 Evans Street.
[SPEAKER_16]: Really briefly, what these other cities and towns do to offset costs, as I'm sure you probably know, is they charge a membership fee for the year.
[SPEAKER_16]: So that brings in money to the station to help pay for some of the employees that work there.
[SPEAKER_16]: And a couple of other quick points, too, is obviously not everybody has cable in Medford.
[SPEAKER_16]: So what Melrose does is they put all of their shows, you know, if everybody has the internet at home, even without cable, you can still be watching local access in that town.
[SPEAKER_16]: And one final point I want to make, and it's something that I brought up here.
[SPEAKER_16]: that, you know, I don't want to say it was pushback on doing public access, but some of the comments I hear is that nobody will watch it.
[SPEAKER_16]: Well, Comcast actually does internal ratings.
[SPEAKER_16]: And in Melrose, 75% of the Comcast subscribers are watching their community local access TV.
[SPEAKER_16]: So the interest is there.
[SPEAKER_16]: The funding is there.
[SPEAKER_16]: It's just a political will to get it done.
[SPEAKER_16]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_08]: On the motion for approval by Vice President Logan Kern, Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'd like to amend the paper, Mr. President, and ask the administration the question as to whether or not we actually received a qualified, received and accepted a qualified bidder for the running of the community access programs.
[SPEAKER_08]: It's amended by Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_08]: On the motion, all those in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: Motion carries.
[SPEAKER_08]: 16-414 petition by Robert M. Penta, Xero, Summit Road, Medford, Massachusetts, to address the city council about Medford public access.
[SPEAKER_08]: Welcome, citizen.
[SPEAKER_15]: Please state your name and address for the record.
[SPEAKER_15]: Good evening, Mr. President and council members.
[SPEAKER_15]: My name is Robert Penta, Xero, Summit Road, Medford, Mass.
[SPEAKER_15]: I'm a member of this board.
[SPEAKER_15]: I thank Mr. Capucci for coming forward because his flavor on the subject matter is different than mine.
[SPEAKER_15]: Mine basically as history has a way of repeating itself.
[SPEAKER_15]: Regarding public access here in the city of Medford, we are at the repeating stage once again.
[SPEAKER_15]: Since early 2013 to date, we, the Comcast and Verizon cable subscribers, have been charged the monthly public access fee totaling some $500,000.
[SPEAKER_15]: And we, the subscribers, still have no public access station.
[SPEAKER_15]: What we heard from 2013 by the city administration was that the city will be asking for
[SPEAKER_15]: Channel 3 records, bank statements, meeting minutes, and an inventory accounting of the Channel 3 Public Access Corporation, because then at that point in time, Channel 3 Corporation was filing for dissolution of its Chapter 3 Corporation.
[SPEAKER_15]: Records of expenditures of gasoline, restaurants, retail, supermarkets, hardware home suppliers, plumbing and air conditioning materials, building materials, auto supplies,
[SPEAKER_15]: Miscellaneous expenses in bank and ATM withdrawals, along with deposits and credits from the banks in the accounting were examples that were supposed to have been forwarded to the city of Medford pursuant to the dissolution filing.
[SPEAKER_15]: As of this date, no accounting of any records, bank statements, meeting minutes, or accurate inventory accounting has ever been verified from channel three.
[SPEAKER_15]: Regarding the city's lack of providing public access TV,
[SPEAKER_15]: The ever-going question since 2013 has been, why has the city failed to mandate that public access be made available as contractually applied for?
[SPEAKER_15]: Fast forward to today, and putting aside all the comments and issue regarding the forced ascertainment hearing, the former mayor's commission report regarding public cable access, and multiple council resolutions regarding this matter.
[SPEAKER_15]: It seems that this administration feels that to spend some $500,000 for an access studio up in the back of Medford High School will serve in the best interest of a local public access station.
[SPEAKER_15]: I don't believe this to be in the best interest of our subscribers and citizens, and for the following reasons.
[SPEAKER_15]: It's location, location, location that is the primary success staple of any business.
[SPEAKER_15]: The Medford High location will not serve the best interest for our public access.
[SPEAKER_15]: Examples as to why.
[SPEAKER_15]: Its public access is not on a main street that is centrally located.
[SPEAKER_15]: The entranceway is not well lit.
[SPEAKER_15]: It is not easily accessible to walk up and to walk back the hill from the back to and from Medford High School.
[SPEAKER_15]: It presents a winter problem of ice and snow needing to be cleared at all times on the hill and the walkway to the school's back entrance.
[SPEAKER_15]: It presents a safety security problem for after school hours
[SPEAKER_15]: and nighttime lighting is at a minimum.
[SPEAKER_15]: As a major positive contrast to the Medford High location, the Medford Public Library serves as the best location for public access studio.
[SPEAKER_15]: It is centrally located within our city.
[SPEAKER_15]: It has walking convenience within the city's downtown area and bus routes.
[SPEAKER_15]: It is handicap accessible to being easily available for front door entrance for bus and cab transportation.
[SPEAKER_15]: It offers a great additional public educational opportunity for community public access.
[SPEAKER_15]: Medford's $500,000 bank deposits from Comcast and Verizon thus far will definitely produce at the library the space needs necessary for this development.
[SPEAKER_15]: As Councilor Caraviello has indicated by requesting the Massachusetts State Library Commission come to Medford to ascertain what state additional funding can be for the library to Ghana for the library's rehabilitation,
[SPEAKER_15]: That, along with what I proposed last year during the Mayor's campaign to have a complaint present use and future use, along with the $500,000 funds that are readily available right now here in City Hall, could catapult the Medford Public Library to being Medford's premier central educational and social meeting spot that incorporates an entire community of opportunity.
[SPEAKER_15]: This would be the perfect segue for having
[SPEAKER_15]: The Massachusetts State Library Commission realized that we are working to make our library a major focal point in our city, and their additional support position would certainly carry us to that potential.
[SPEAKER_15]: It would be an example of how a city fully realizes the community potential of its public library.
[SPEAKER_15]: To my understanding and education thus far, this would be a first for the Massachusetts State Library Commission to co-invest with a city with matching funds.
[SPEAKER_15]: The Medford Vocational School location, as is presently being entertained, could be a satellite location for students' learning of production and access operations as a school program offering separate and distinct from the public access studio.
[SPEAKER_15]: This opportunity for community public access to be better located and more readily available should not be squandered away because of political posturing.
[SPEAKER_15]: Mayor McGlynn's own committee report of June 2015 specifically stated,
[SPEAKER_15]: We are a committee that feels that the best location will be in one that is conveniently and centrally located with its own entrance and exit and should be handicap accessible.
[SPEAKER_15]: The Method Public Library could serve no better location than the one that has been advised for.
[SPEAKER_15]: Also, with the city owning the property, annual rental payments will not have to be provided.
[SPEAKER_15]: Therefore, providing for more revenue to maintain, upgrade equipment,
[SPEAKER_15]: and conveniently offer to the community programs that showcase our city and the families and subscribers that watch and use public access TV.
[SPEAKER_15]: I respectfully ask that this honorable body of councilors request by a roll call vote that our city administration reconsider its position regarding public access to TV being at Medford High School and entertain the Medford Public Library as the location that will better serve our community in the Comcast and variable cable rate payers
[SPEAKER_15]: for paying for their public access.
[SPEAKER_15]: Well, I have a question that I presented before the council.
[SPEAKER_15]: I was just wondering if anyone would entertain that because I think this is a very important issue.
[SPEAKER_15]: It's a lot of money and I think it offers a great opportunity.
[SPEAKER_10]: I do believe when Barbara Kerr was here recently discussing some of the plans for the library, one of the things that was raised was that there was a deeded restriction on the library because that land was donated to the city of Medford and the only purpose that it could be used for was for a library, if I remember correctly.
[SPEAKER_10]: So maybe we can ask that question to see as to whether or not there's a deeded restriction on the library and as to see as to whether or not there is any other use that would be appropriate there other than a library.
[SPEAKER_08]: On the motion of council night that the Medford City Council requests of the librarian, Ms.
[SPEAKER_08]: Barbara Kerr, to inquire as to deed restrictions on the use of the library.
[SPEAKER_08]: Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_08]: Chair recognizes Councilor Karen Fiala.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_20]: Um, Councilor Penta, I don't want, I don't want the people to be misled to think the library is going to get built, uh, you know, very soon.
[SPEAKER_20]: Um, I was fortunate to be with the mayor, uh, and the library and the library, uh, people when that day they came and, um,
[SPEAKER_20]: speaking with the mayor last week, we do have a lot of work ahead of us just to make the grant round by the end of October when the papers have to be filed for the January meeting.
[SPEAKER_20]: So if that doesn't get done, the next round of funding for the library will be 2022.
[SPEAKER_20]: So I know the mayor and her staff are working to try to get into that date by the end of October so we can get into the final round.
[SPEAKER_20]: Even if we make it to that round, I think it's going to be a couple of years before we see the funding for that to happen.
[SPEAKER_20]: It won't be happening next year, but it'll be probably a couple of years before we actually can get it off the ground.
[SPEAKER_08]: There's a motion on the floor from Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_08]: Madam Vice President.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thank you, President Dello Russo.
[SPEAKER_13]: Councilor Caraviello, can you just better explain or more in detail explain what's due October, November?
[SPEAKER_13]: 2016 full application for funding?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yeah, the application process is quite lengthy.
[SPEAKER_20]: And it also requires us hiring a couple of people before it gets done.
[SPEAKER_20]: And even the library commissioners felt it was a daunting task for us to get done by the end of October.
[SPEAKER_20]: And I applaud the mayor for trying to do this and hopefully get it in by the October deadline.
[SPEAKER_20]: And I have full confidence that we'll be able to get that done.
[SPEAKER_20]: And it'll probably be an expenditure of some money for us for hiring an engineer and a project manager and those type of things.
[SPEAKER_20]: So again, I would hope that would get done soon.
[SPEAKER_20]: But I say, it is, from what I'm saying, I think it was 140 pages of documentation that needed to get done.
[SPEAKER_20]: So again, and when I spoke to the mayor, she was working on it and had the staff on it.
[SPEAKER_20]: So hopefully we'll have it done by the time to get it in for the funding round.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you, Councilor Cavillo.
[SPEAKER_13]: And just on that- And Vice President.
[SPEAKER_13]: Do you know when they would award the grants?
[SPEAKER_20]: I think January was the time when they would discuss who would get the monies that were out there.
[SPEAKER_20]: When I was there, we did walk the property with the commissioner, and they agreed that it wasn't that big of a deal to bump out all the walls and put up a full second floor there.
[SPEAKER_20]: And they also agreed that the library was in
[SPEAKER_20]: In pretty decent shape, it needed a little bit of work here and there, but it wasn't something that was insurmountable with.
[SPEAKER_20]: The building had to be torn down and slapped to scratch.
[SPEAKER_20]: So there was a lot of positive that came out of that meeting.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_13]: Yeah, I was just trying to get a better timeline on when, if by chance, we were able to get the application in, got the grant, build out, so you're still looking at 2019 by the time you have a second floor in the library, best case scenario.
[SPEAKER_20]: Yeah, yes.
[SPEAKER_13]: I think Councilor Penta has agreed, you know, I think a more centrally located TV station somewhere in the square, somewhere.
[SPEAKER_13]: We keep talking about some sort of art center, whether it's at the library or not.
[SPEAKER_13]: We want it centrally located.
[SPEAKER_13]: Obviously, there's no safety issues with the high school.
[SPEAKER_13]: The doors are now locked.
[SPEAKER_13]: Security cameras are working, thankfully.
[SPEAKER_13]: but it is dark, it is not centrally located, it's more in the west.
[SPEAKER_18]: Point of information, Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_18]: So the viewing public knows the lighting has been upgraded along the building, and the building, if I'm not mistaken, is separate entrance when the plan, if they were to put in public access for the rest of the building, so just to inform the public.
[SPEAKER_18]: Thank you, Councilor.
[SPEAKER_08]: Madam Vice President.
[SPEAKER_13]: I think for many reasons, I think more centrally located TV3 station would be the way I would lean.
[SPEAKER_13]: And I think that's how I've been hearing when people do discuss possible television station.
[SPEAKER_13]: I think the general public is leaning more towards a centrally located station, whether it be the library or somewhere else in the square.
[SPEAKER_13]: I understand what you're talking about, and I tend to agree.
[SPEAKER_13]: So maybe what we really need to do, we're asking the mayor for an update on the situation.
[SPEAKER_13]: Councilor Knight asked for what's going on with regards to deed restrictions.
[SPEAKER_13]: Maybe we need to have a committee of the whole meeting and discuss a number of things, the library being one.
[SPEAKER_13]: In general, the roof, as well as TV3, and just get another few things that are
[SPEAKER_13]: really hot topics with the, with the council and have another meeting, invite the mayor to come talk to us about it.
[SPEAKER_13]: I think that might be the best, our best Avenue.
[SPEAKER_13]: So I just amend the paper for a committee, the whole meeting with the mayor to discuss a number of different things that we never weren't able to get to at our last meeting with her.
[SPEAKER_19]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_19]: I thank a council of Penta for,
[SPEAKER_19]: bringing up this important subject.
[SPEAKER_19]: I agree also with the location.
[SPEAKER_19]: I think the high school, although the building is currently underutilized right now and does have the capacity to take on public access and a portion of the building, I think having the building, don't forget the last two community access stations were in the square and they were there for a reason.
[SPEAKER_19]: They were there for a reason because of its location.
[SPEAKER_19]: and it's easy access into the square.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I think the library is one possible item.
[SPEAKER_19]: I think Springstep, you know, we all talk about Springstep and we'd love to have Springstep.
[SPEAKER_19]: It's a stone throw from City Hall.
[SPEAKER_19]: The building itself is made for the performance and the arts.
[SPEAKER_19]: As Councilor Caraviello mentioned about having it an art center slash possibly
[SPEAKER_19]: community cable would be a great suggestion.
[SPEAKER_19]: And, you know, I remember back some 10 years ago, maybe even a little longer, Mr. President, you probably remember, when we were looking at merging the yachts and the community access at the Swan building, the Swan School.
[SPEAKER_19]: And it missed by one vote of this council.
[SPEAKER_19]: We almost had that come to fruition.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I think that's a great marriage.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I think it would have worked out.
[SPEAKER_19]: The Springstep building is ideal for
[SPEAKER_19]: for that situation.
[SPEAKER_19]: It's centrally located.
[SPEAKER_19]: It steps from City Hall.
[SPEAKER_19]: There's ample parking.
[SPEAKER_19]: And really, I don't see why, if I were the mayor, I'd be on the phone with the owner of that property.
[SPEAKER_19]: Mr. President, from what I hear, they're looking to unload that building, and they haven't been too successful because of the setup of the building is conducive to arts and so forth.
[SPEAKER_19]: I think that would be a great addition to this city.
[SPEAKER_19]: So I think what the gentleman at the podium, Councilor Penter, is offering is just another alternative.
[SPEAKER_19]: You know, I, as one member, and I've stated this loud and clear, I don't want to see our high school used for anything else than its intended purpose to educate our children.
[SPEAKER_19]: And in this day and age, with everything that's going on, in my opinion, the least number of people we have up there that aren't students and teachers, the better off and the safer we're going to be, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_19]: And that's a whole other discussion for another time.
[SPEAKER_19]: But I don't want to see that building opened up, even though it may be one separate door and at a certain end.
[SPEAKER_19]: I don't want to see it opened up for anything other than its intended purpose, which is to educate our children, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_19]: So I thank Councilor Penta for offering this.
[SPEAKER_19]: I look forward to hearing back on Councilor Knight's motion to see if the library could be used for any other purpose.
[SPEAKER_19]: I didn't realize there was a
[SPEAKER_19]: a deed restriction on that if there is one.
[SPEAKER_19]: And you know what, several weeks ago, we had the issue of the Hegner Center before us.
[SPEAKER_19]: I mean, here's a small building in the city that could be used for local access.
[SPEAKER_19]: It might not be centrally as located as we like, but that may be a great addition if it comes back in the city coffers.
[SPEAKER_19]: And the one thing Councilor Penta mentioned is when you have a space that you're paying for,
[SPEAKER_19]: when you're paying $1,500 or $2,000 a month.
[SPEAKER_19]: A lion's share of your money goes to housing, community access, and not towards programming and hiring the people to get it up and running.
[SPEAKER_19]: And if it wasn't a city building, I think a lot of that money could be put towards programming and hiring the right people to run the access station, rather than on the physical property itself.
[SPEAKER_19]: So that's a great point that Councilor Penta mentioned.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_13]: Just was updated.
[SPEAKER_13]: It looks like the transcript is due in an article.
[SPEAKER_13]: It will be in tomorrow's online version with regards to the fact that pre-construction work on the new Access TV studio at the high school began last week.
[SPEAKER_13]: So we weren't notified.
[SPEAKER_13]: I wasn't aware.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes, Mr. President, I think it's also very important for us to point out the fact that every time that the library comes up on our agenda, this council chamber has a good number of people here that are speaking in support of it.
[SPEAKER_10]: And if we're going to talk about changing the use of the library, the direction the library is going in, I think it's very important to include these individuals as well.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I'd ask that the friends of the public library be invited to our next committee of the whole meeting when it does take place to discuss this matter.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'd also ask that the city clerk compile a list of all the individuals that have come up to speak in favor of issues going on at the library so that an invitation could be extended to them as well.
[SPEAKER_10]: As amended by Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_20]: On that motion, Councilor Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_20]: I think Councilor Knight, I think we may be a little premature in bringing the library people in to discuss what's going to be going on there because they're a long way away from actually getting anything done in there.
[SPEAKER_20]: In fact, one of the suggestions of the library commission was that we actually had two members
[SPEAKER_20]: Too many books in there, and that was maybe we should scale down our inventory to garner some more space.
[SPEAKER_20]: That was a big thing.
[SPEAKER_20]: But again, Councilor Marks is right, we missed the boat buying the property across the street.
[SPEAKER_20]: I proposed buying it when it was $2 million.
[SPEAKER_20]: Now, from what I understand, it recently sold to somebody.
[SPEAKER_20]: And now it's back on the market for 4 million.
[SPEAKER_20]: But it did, if I'm not mistaken, I was told that it did change hands with another owner.
[SPEAKER_20]: It was back on the market before.
[SPEAKER_20]: But again, that was a spot that we should have taken advantage of some years ago.
[SPEAKER_20]: It was ready to go, needed no work, little wiring for the thing, and it sufficed all the space needs for the whole community that was needed.
[SPEAKER_20]: Again, it was a loss of something that should have been taken advantage of.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you, Councilor.
[SPEAKER_10]: And just to be clear, Mr. President, if we're going to, when I said invite the friends of the library and those people who have come down to speak in favor of the needs at the library, it's if in fact this council is going to deliberate a discussion of changing the use of the library and moving it away from just being a library, whether it's to add a second floor, make that TV three, or whatever it is, whatever direction we're going, I think that they should be involved in at least the conversation to provide their input, because those are the people that have supported the efforts of the library.
[SPEAKER_10]: When the library went through its worst times, they were the ones that held it up.
[SPEAKER_20]: Part of the money that comes from the library association does have provisions on it, on what you can do and what you can't do with it.
[SPEAKER_20]: So again, you are correct on that.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm more concerned about the building and the actual use than I am about the money coming from the state.
[SPEAKER_20]: There are conditions on what you can do with that money if you are awarded it.
[SPEAKER_15]: All set?
[SPEAKER_15]: Mr. President, as just a point of reference, for the last six years, prior to last year, don't forget the city of Medford got waivers from the Mass Department, State Department of Library Commissioners, because the city did not put enough money in there when, in fact, they did have the money.
[SPEAKER_15]: But putting that aside, with all due respect to Councilor Knight, if you look at the Mass Department of Education, cable, public access, and the teaching of public access is an allowable educational product here in the Commonwealth of Massachusetts.
[SPEAKER_15]: It can't be a deed restriction, or even, I don't know what the deed restriction can be, because the library is an educational thing, and the public access is educational.
[SPEAKER_15]: It works hand in hand.
[SPEAKER_15]: And as I indicated earlier, what Councilor Caraviello might have met and talked to those folks from the state, they've never had a co-investing partner like the City of Medford would have.
[SPEAKER_15]: And if we could upgrade not only the building, the roof, the second floor, whatever needs to be done with the $500,000 that the city has at the present time, and moving that forward, having a full public access,
[SPEAKER_15]: here, right here in the city of Medford, centrally located, that would help to expedite.
[SPEAKER_15]: If the administration was serious about the public library, as was a campaign issue during this past year, we wouldn't have to worry about 140 pages being done.
[SPEAKER_15]: You'd go out and hire someone ASAP and make that presentation.
[SPEAKER_15]: And if they knew that the city of Medford was willing to invest its money instead of asking for all of the money from the Commonwealth of Massachusetts, the board of library commissioners, it's the first of its kind.
[SPEAKER_15]: And I think they would be more receptive to that than just the plain grant application.
[SPEAKER_15]: I don't see any what the problem would be.
[SPEAKER_15]: Because if we want to move this thing forward, we have the money.
[SPEAKER_15]: It isn't like we don't have the money.
[SPEAKER_15]: We're not offering the service that's contractually been obligated for through Verizon and Comcast.
[SPEAKER_15]: You do not have public access here in the city of Medford.
[SPEAKER_15]: And we can go back to resolutions from 2013 bringing forward
[SPEAKER_15]: where the votes have been seven to nothing on this council floor to go forward and find out what's going on.
[SPEAKER_15]: You can't even get the records back from the former Cable 3, the Channel 3.
[SPEAKER_15]: We don't even know if they've actually been formally dissolved by the Karma of the Mass.
[SPEAKER_15]: They could still be in operation.
[SPEAKER_15]: Nobody knows nothing.
[SPEAKER_15]: We haven't received anything back.
[SPEAKER_15]: But the onus of responsibility, with all due respect, Mr. President, right now can come from this council, because I think you're all on the same page.
[SPEAKER_15]: you want to see something done.
[SPEAKER_15]: And to find out that they're doing some work now up at that school, and this council not even being notified or entertained about it, that doesn't speak well about transparency.
[SPEAKER_15]: They can do all the restructuring up there they want and do it for another purpose.
[SPEAKER_15]: This is more important.
[SPEAKER_15]: How and where public access is going to go, how the $500,000 is going to go, how it's going to be centrally located, and how it can be immersed into this community
[SPEAKER_15]: as an educational product, ready, willing, and able to go locally, not segued in a certain part of this community that has too many obstacles to make the thing work.
[SPEAKER_15]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: There are a number of other citizens who wish to speak.
[SPEAKER_08]: Ma'am, welcome.
[SPEAKER_08]: Please state your name and address for the record.
[SPEAKER_14]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_14]: My name is Gwendolyn Blackburn, 233 Arlington Street, West Medford.
[SPEAKER_14]: I didn't come to speak really, I just came to support those who were here for the West Medford issues.
[SPEAKER_14]: But I'm really, really concerned about what is
[SPEAKER_14]: going to happen with TV3 and where they're going to put it.
[SPEAKER_14]: And I would hope, and I hate to hear what you just said, that they are starting to dig up and do whatever.
[SPEAKER_14]: And the city council doesn't know that that's going on.
[SPEAKER_14]: You cannot, there's no way they can put TV3
[SPEAKER_14]: up there in the back of that high school.
[SPEAKER_14]: Having been in the high school for 30 years, I know what it's like up there.
[SPEAKER_14]: You cannot, and people are not going to be using it for the same reason, well, not for the same reason.
[SPEAKER_14]: They didn't use it down here or whatever the problem was down here on
[SPEAKER_14]: It wasn't here very long, here on Riverside.
[SPEAKER_14]: So that didn't make any difference.
[SPEAKER_14]: But there's been a problem ever since they moved from Canal Street many years ago, when it really ran quite well and had a lot of programs.
[SPEAKER_14]: All I wanted to say was, please,
[SPEAKER_14]: see that it doesn't go up to behind the high school, the vocational school area, because it's dark up there.
[SPEAKER_14]: Got a lot of senior citizens would like to use TV3.
[SPEAKER_14]: They had programs at one time so that a lot of the seniors could go for different things.
[SPEAKER_14]: And I would hope that you wouldn't deny
[SPEAKER_14]: the senior citizens, which I'm going to be one, I would hope you wouldn't deny the senior citizens by putting it up there behind high school.
[SPEAKER_14]: It's a terrible place.
[SPEAKER_14]: It's dark up there.
[SPEAKER_14]: If they have something up there at night, it's dark.
[SPEAKER_14]: And during the day, it's just not the place for it.
[SPEAKER_14]: So, Councilor, I hope you're wrong, but please, you said it's going to be in the paper tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_13]: Yes, the transcript just contacted me.
[SPEAKER_13]: It's gonna be, that must be why we don't know, because the article's not coming out till Thursday.
[SPEAKER_13]: It's sad that we have to find out from the paper what's going on in the city.
[SPEAKER_13]: I thought that that was to an end.
[SPEAKER_13]: But yes, it's gonna be online tomorrow and in the paper on Thursday is what I was just told when the construction started last week.
[SPEAKER_13]: I was unaware.
[SPEAKER_14]: So, excuse me, but is this something that city council can do something about?
[SPEAKER_14]: No?
[SPEAKER_14]: You're shaking your head no?
[SPEAKER_14]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_14]: Well, I hope you can.
[SPEAKER_14]: That's all I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_14]: As a citizen whose money is going into TV3 or whatever, I would hope that city council do something to stop it.
[SPEAKER_14]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Good evening.
[SPEAKER_08]: Please state your name and address for the record.
[SPEAKER_12]: Hi, Jean Martin, 10 Cummings Street.
[SPEAKER_12]: So much for transparency, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm pretty sure that for quite some time now, a plan's been published that they were going to put the public access station up at the high school.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I don't think that this should be a surprise that it's going up the high school.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's been in the newspaper.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's been in the transcript, right, Alex?
[SPEAKER_10]: It's been in there, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: You put it in the paper that it was going to go up the high school, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: The public access station.
[SPEAKER_10]: Now they start construction, now it's a big surprise.
[SPEAKER_10]: I mean, you know, I'm a little confused about the disconnect there, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_10]: We've all been well aware that that's the location that they've...
[SPEAKER_10]: said that they were going to put it.
[SPEAKER_10]: Whether we like it or not, it's a different story.
[SPEAKER_10]: But, you know, we know that that's what they're going to do it.
[SPEAKER_10]: Now we see progress in them breaking ground, and now we're not happy that they're breaking ground.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm a little confused by this whole thing, Mr. President, to be honest with you.
[SPEAKER_10]: But that's just me.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you, Councilman Knight.
[SPEAKER_08]: The citizen has the floor.
[SPEAKER_08]: Point of information, Madam Vice President.
[SPEAKER_13]: I think the link, like I said before, 10 years going on with trying to dissolve TV3 and then it's going up to high school.
[SPEAKER_13]: I mean, I didn't really think the council had to act fast.
[SPEAKER_13]: I think you'd be notified before any ground was being broken.
[SPEAKER_13]: So a number of rumors that go around with regards to dates and timeframes.
[SPEAKER_13]: I've never heard a timeframe with regards to groundbreaking.
[SPEAKER_13]: So, I mean, I didn't feel that
[SPEAKER_13]: And we haven't had a public hearing on it.
[SPEAKER_13]: And just, you know, the people haven't been able to speak out.
[SPEAKER_13]: So, yeah, I'm a little surprised myself that ground was broken last week and that I was unaware of it.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you for that point of information.
[SPEAKER_08]: Ma'am, please continue.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_12]: To answer Mr. Knight's point through the chair, that was the old administration.
[SPEAKER_12]: And yes, you're absolutely correct that under the old administration, he decided that.
[SPEAKER_12]: But anyway, one of the problems that I see is that the high school
[SPEAKER_12]: There's many, many problems with the high school, public safety being one of them, of having strange adults wandering those halls.
[SPEAKER_12]: Also, senior citizens, and you're absolutely correct, Gwen, I've talked to 75-year-old ladies that say, if I got off the bus, I would never make it up that hill.
[SPEAKER_12]: And then when you make it up that hill, it's very dark, and it's just not a good place.
[SPEAKER_12]: What is, who benefits from having it up there, unfortunately, and this is not going to be popular, is the school system.
[SPEAKER_12]: The school system gets all those fundings.
[SPEAKER_12]: They get that whole bucket of money.
[SPEAKER_12]: to put into their art system.
[SPEAKER_12]: But as far as feeling like it's a community center, it's a ghost town over there.
[SPEAKER_12]: And so it's not going to seem like it's a community center.
[SPEAKER_12]: But I do agree.
[SPEAKER_12]: Somebody pointed it out to me.
[SPEAKER_12]: Handicapped accessibility and shame on me.
[SPEAKER_12]: Shame on me.
[SPEAKER_12]: Because I didn't think about that when I suggested the theater basement.
[SPEAKER_12]: I don't know if it would be wheelchair accessible.
[SPEAKER_12]: So shame on me for not thinking that through before I suggested it.
[SPEAKER_12]: But it needs to go down the Method Square for everybody's benefit, for the community to feel like it's their thing.
[SPEAKER_12]: Because if they don't have kids in the high school, they're not going to feel, it's just not up there.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's just not a good spot for the hype.
[SPEAKER_12]: So I would recommend, oh, and one more point.
[SPEAKER_12]: We have an arts council in this city, right?
[SPEAKER_12]: So they need to be involved in the process.
[SPEAKER_12]: And we have the money right now to hire somebody
[SPEAKER_12]: for $500,000 to direct this process.
[SPEAKER_12]: And it doesn't have to come from the mayor's office.
[SPEAKER_12]: So it doesn't show any bias of who they want to pick.
[SPEAKER_12]: There's an arts council.
[SPEAKER_12]: And that's what they should be doing is focusing on hiring somebody so that they can oversee this process.
[SPEAKER_12]: And they could go to a Malden or Melrose or someplace else.
[SPEAKER_12]: This has been done before.
[SPEAKER_12]: We're not reinventing the wheel.
[SPEAKER_12]: We already had that committee and that commission.
[SPEAKER_12]: And that went nowhere.
[SPEAKER_12]: That went into a drawer someplace.
[SPEAKER_12]: So we need to hire somebody to get it done.
[SPEAKER_12]: And we have plenty of money in that draw now.
[SPEAKER_12]: And the Arts Council needs to be on top of this.
[SPEAKER_12]: Is there or is there not an appointed Arts Council for the City of Medford through the Mayor's office?
[SPEAKER_12]: There is.
[SPEAKER_12]: So why not invoke them and get them to start this process?
[SPEAKER_12]: Because in any city that I see the community access, it's the arts community that does this.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's their ball.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's predominantly their ball.
[SPEAKER_12]: They invite everybody else to sports.
[SPEAKER_12]: In Everett, they have three cameras on every football game.
[SPEAKER_12]: Three cameras.
[SPEAKER_12]: They are wicked into football over there, and they have three cameras over there for every football game.
[SPEAKER_12]: Why don't we have that?
[SPEAKER_12]: And we're missing out on all kinds of stuff.
[SPEAKER_12]: So I just wanted to thank you very much for listening to me rant on.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you, Chief.
[SPEAKER_08]: Chair recognizes Councilor Falco.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_04]: I was just going to make one quick point, and that is I believe someone mentioned earlier that the
[SPEAKER_04]: The studio is going to be located in the back of the high school, and it's really in the front.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you walk in the front door of the high school, it's on your right.
[SPEAKER_04]: So it's in the front end of the location of the school, and there's two classrooms, and then it's set aside for those two people.
[SPEAKER_04]: But I just wanted to clarify that it is in the front of the school, so you're on the same page.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you very much, Carl.
[SPEAKER_08]: Chair recognizes the citizen at the podium.
[SPEAKER_08]: Welcome.
[SPEAKER_08]: Please state your name and address for the record.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_17]: Joe Villione, 59 Garfield Ave.
[SPEAKER_17]: Medford Mass, and board member of Boston Free Radio at Somerville Community Access TV, where, as you probably know, I'm one of the first producers in Somerville dating back to 1979.
[SPEAKER_17]: So I know a little bit about this.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now as for the station being at the high school, Mayor McGlynn decided it would be at the high school.
[SPEAKER_17]: I see a person that said he didn't know about the high school is leaving.
[SPEAKER_17]: It's interesting because at the school committee meeting of March 28th, that's when it was unveiled that the Muccini-Burke administration would have it at the high school.
[SPEAKER_17]: So, and I think the council is sitting here who want to be educated on that.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now as for the radio station, I talked to Stephanie Muccini-Burke about three years ago when she was director of personnel and budget, and I explained to her how a radio station is pivotal.
[SPEAKER_17]: If there's an emergency, imagine Captain Barry Clemente on
[SPEAKER_17]: AM1670 from Medford, which could be a low-power Part 15 FCC station, which you don't need a license for.
[SPEAKER_17]: I ran one of these back in 2000.
[SPEAKER_17]: I was program director.
[SPEAKER_17]: Stephanie Buccini-Burke said to me, Joe, we could get money from Homeland Security, so along with our access TV money.
[SPEAKER_17]: Mrs. Burke told me that we can get money from Homeland Security.
[SPEAKER_17]: Who knew?
[SPEAKER_17]: I didn't know, and I've been in this a long, long time.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now, let's add that money.
[SPEAKER_17]: Let's have a radio station, because we have one running at Somerville, which is now in its sixth year.
[SPEAKER_17]: I've been on the board for a year.
[SPEAKER_17]: It's an incredible station.
[SPEAKER_17]: We now move to the front.
[SPEAKER_17]: So when you go to SCAT in Somerville, which Mr. Capucci did, and I'm so pleased he did, you can see Dan Hurley from Medford doing Somerville Pundits right in the window.
[SPEAKER_17]: You can see Joe Vig doing Joe Vig Pop Explosion tomorrow from one to three.
[SPEAKER_17]: I have two great guests on, musical guests, and you can see people learning on the computers in the third window.
[SPEAKER_17]: So the new program director, he's interim, Rob Zargas, great guy.
[SPEAKER_17]: He put everything in the windows, so when you're in Union Square, you can feel the vibe of the radio station.
[SPEAKER_17]: We're not hidden in the back anymore.
[SPEAKER_17]: That is so important.
[SPEAKER_17]: Councilor Penta, former Councilor Penta, absolutely correct.
[SPEAKER_17]: The high school, and Bob said this to me, could be a good satellite.
[SPEAKER_17]: The high school could be a good satellite like they have in Arlington.
[SPEAKER_17]: Arlington, which airs my program, has two stations, one across the street from the high school, Arlington High,
[SPEAKER_17]: And they have one up in an old library up in the Arlington Heights.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now, this is very, very important.
[SPEAKER_17]: We need it for the elections.
[SPEAKER_17]: We needed it for the last election.
[SPEAKER_17]: And Councilor Marks is right.
[SPEAKER_17]: Mayor McGlynn, as I heard through my grapevine at Public Access TV, McGlynn was talking to someone.
[SPEAKER_17]: He just said, I hate public access.
[SPEAKER_17]: And the guy wanted to work for Mike McGlynn to run the station.
[SPEAKER_08]: But this is allegedly Sir, let's not engage in any hearsay or calumny, please.
[SPEAKER_17]: Fine.
[SPEAKER_17]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_17]: Radio station, public access TV, the synergy is important.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now, Mr. Capucci said that they run
[SPEAKER_17]: the TV in Melrose, on the Internet as well.
[SPEAKER_17]: Trimal casting.
[SPEAKER_17]: We did one of the first trimal casts in 2000 at the old TV3 on Canal Street.
[SPEAKER_17]: So we ran on my AM1670 in Boston.
[SPEAKER_17]: We ran on the Internet, which was a new thing back then, running on the Internet, and we ran a TV3.
[SPEAKER_17]: We did that.
[SPEAKER_17]: That was in the good old days when people actually wanted stuff at TV3.
[SPEAKER_17]: Now, there is a board member here from TV3.
[SPEAKER_17]: I think the council would be
[SPEAKER_17]: prudent to ask him about the financial status.
[SPEAKER_17]: A former board member of TV3IC just entered the room.
[SPEAKER_17]: This is important.
[SPEAKER_17]: I've been writing to the Attorney General month after month, and I get information, but they're still not giving us the information.
[SPEAKER_17]: Solicitor Mark Rumley said that he's waiting for the Attorney General.
[SPEAKER_17]: I implore the city solicitor to understand that the Attorney General's office is running at a snail's pace.
[SPEAKER_17]: Maybe they're overwhelmed.
[SPEAKER_17]: I think it's time our city solicitor went back to
[SPEAKER_17]: The powers that be of TV3, the five board members, and said, come on, give this city the information.
[SPEAKER_17]: Because there's 38 grand that wasn't accounted for in the Medford transcript.
[SPEAKER_17]: We can use that money.
[SPEAKER_17]: I propose a TV station, a radio station, and something like Somerville has.
[SPEAKER_17]: Thank you very much, City Council.
[SPEAKER_08]: Good evening.
[SPEAKER_08]: Welcome.
[SPEAKER_08]: Please state your name and address for the record.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good evening.
[SPEAKER_00]: My name is Matthew Page Lieberman.
[SPEAKER_00]: I live at 15 Canal Street.
[SPEAKER_00]: As everyone may know, I take the archive meetings, these meetings, and then I put them online.
[SPEAKER_00]: This evening, I decided to start live streaming our city council meetings, and I was told by someone that what I'm doing is actually theft.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, while I could put archive meetings online, because there's no copyright issue, apparently all of the television stations belong to the cable company, and that's part of our contract.
[SPEAKER_00]: So what I can do is, I don't imagine I'd have much luck, but I can try to contact Comcast Cable and look at, try to weed through the case law.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I was wondering if there's any way we could query City Solicitor Mark Rumley to get a determination on if what I'm doing by live streaming these meetings is actually legal or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perhaps that could be in a resolution.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Amended by Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_08]: that the city solicitor report back to whether live streaming by a third party constitutes a violation of copyright matter against Comcast and the other cable providers.
[SPEAKER_08]: Welcome, citizen.
[SPEAKER_08]: Please state your name and address for the record.
[SPEAKER_02]: Andrew Castagnetti, Cushing Street.
[SPEAKER_02]: How can I phrase this?
[SPEAKER_02]: In 1970,
[SPEAKER_02]: The new high school was built in the West Method Woods.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I recollect Woolworths and Grants behind you, Candlepen Bowling at Hobbit Vanguard, Method Cinema where the Elephant Store is thereabouts, Pewter Park, Brigham's, Joel's Poolroom below ex-Maki's office.
[SPEAKER_02]: This place was economically viable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Lots of businesses, maybe a bit before your time,
[SPEAKER_02]: However, it seemed shortly thereafter, 1970, the square economically went south.
[SPEAKER_02]: Didn't do very well.
[SPEAKER_02]: A lot of businesses closed down.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I would think if it was a mistake, some of us should learn from our mistakes or other communities can learn from our mistake.
[SPEAKER_02]: As they say in the real estate business,
[SPEAKER_02]: The three words location, location, location.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I would like to see this at a central location, whether it's at city hall here, I don't know about an extra millions of dollars expenditure next door and who's going to pay that nut every month or the gene brought up Chevalier.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe we could figure out how long the leases in the basement.
[SPEAKER_02]: And of course, if it was rent free, we'd be able to use more of our money that's already collected to do a better job and not have to worry about paying the landlord every month.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's been a couple of three years.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nothing's going down.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hopefully this can be done before Christmas and this Christmas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you for listening.
[SPEAKER_08]: April 12, 2016, were passed to Councilor Knight.
[SPEAKER_08]: Mr. Councilor, how do you find those records?
[SPEAKER_10]: One minor correction, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_10]: Councilor Lungo-Koehn and I discussed it earlier.
[SPEAKER_10]: She brought to my attention that the St.
[SPEAKER_10]: Rayfield's 5th and 6th grade boys basketball team
[SPEAKER_10]: were not only the Northeast Regional champions, but they were also the New England CYO champions.
[SPEAKER_08]: Outstanding.
[SPEAKER_08]: So that those records be amended and approved.
[SPEAKER_08]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: Meeting to adjourn by Madam Vice President Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_08]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_08]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_08]: Meeting adjourned.