The following is a presentation of The Day.
The energy picks up in the John T. Conway Gymnasium, the home of the New London High School Whalers, as they play host to the West Haven Blue Devils. A trip to the semifinals of the Division II Boys CIAC semifinal is on the line. The game should be upbeat, and the action is all here live on Game Day. Game Day is brought to you by Waterford Dental Health. Gear up for a winning smile from Waterford Dental Health.
They're your go-to for top-notch dental care in a relaxed, friendly setting. So whether you need a routine checkup, a cosmetic boost, whatever you need, their experienced team has you covered. So you can enjoy the game with confidence and comfort.
Sign up for your appointment. Schedule it today at Waterford Dental Health. Also by Scient Federal Credit Union. Pave the way for your student's financial success with a mySci account from Scient Federal Credit Union. Open a high-yield mySci savings account today and help support a positive financial future for your student. Visit scientscu.org slash mySci to learn more.
also by Mr. G's restaurant and bar located in New London Connecticut it's where the coaches and players go you want to hang out before or after a game and get some great food and some great company go to Mr. G's in New London also want to give a shout out to the New London High School alumni for supporting game day in tonight's game thank you for helping us cover these athletes tonight Casey O'Neill along with
Wait a minute. Back in the driver's seat, Casey. How are you? The sports doctor, Keith O'Brien. We're back in the saddle again, and we are ready for what should be a very entertaining and upbeat game tonight. Yeah, this is March. This is big boy basketball, Casey, as they would say. And you know, West Haven comes in hot off of a win against Glastonbury. New London, hot off of a win against Crosbury. You know, and take a second to talk about this New London team and head coach Dave Cornish and his travels. He's back home here at New London, and he's here to deliver.
another banner on the wall and you know what tonight's the next step to that you know that that goal that New London has had since they brought him back two years ago. I want to thank you sports doctor a that's an excellent point but also I have missed your Sniglet's Crosby of Waterbury Crosbury it makes app it's pert makes perfect sense but I thought but you are spot-on when coach Cornish came back to his alma mater it's returning to a tradition of the state championship banners on the wall his legacy is
is not determined by or dependent upon but would certainly resonate more if he was one of the coaches. I mean you look up there and you see Ralph Ruggiero and you see Chop Parker. If his name could be put up there and he played for and coached for and with Ralph Ruggiero and Chop Parker. So you know those are his role models and his mentors and to put himself into that category would be huge for him.
And listen, we've known Dave for a long time. This man eats and breathes basketball. And I think him personally, Casey, he has that burning desire to deliver that championship. I mean, he got so close that led to a little stint at NFA. But now he's here. And I think it's personal to him to put this banner back on the wall for the Northern Whalers. And he's got the goods to do it this year. He's got a very, very deep team. He's got some good seniors. He's got some great role players. And they're healthy. And they're clicking at the right time.
He's also spot on about the tournament. When I saw him during the ECC tournament and the brackets had come out, I said, who are you going to get in the second round? He goes, we're going to get Crosby. I said, then what, Glassenbury? He goes, no, West Haven's going to be in that game. He's like, and that's the team. He's like, that team can win the state championship. Scared of them a little bit. So he saw that coming. He said, you know, forget. He knew who the teams were going to be. He had every bracket called. He's remarkable. Let's take a moment for the national anthem.
by the dawn's early light, what so proudly we hailed at the twilight's last gleaming, whose broad stripes and bright stars through the perilous fight, o'er the ramparts we watched were so gallantly streaming? And the rocket's red glare,
♪ The bombs bursting in air ♪ ♪ Gave proof through the night ♪ ♪ That our flag was still there ♪ ♪ O say does that star-spangled banner yet wave ♪ ♪ O'er the land of the free ♪
Oh, what fun it is to ride in a one-horse open sleigh
So yeah, I think this new London team has the goods for sure. We said it all the way back at the Classic when they were taking on St. Bernard. We said this is the deepest, most talented roster he's ever had, albeit Ledgerd, NFA. He's had some great rosters at Ledgerd, certainly at NFA. But I don't think he's ever had as deep and talented a roster as this one. And this is going to be a very big challenge for them, because they cannot
have droughts of scoring they cannot get lazy on defense they cannot get into foul trouble this is a game where they're going to have to play all the way through to win. And you talk about situational basketball playing with the lead down the stretch knowing how to hang on to things and you know
When you're so deep like this, who's going to step up off the bench as well? I mean, we've seen it a few different times with, you know, Amir Hall or Gaskin or, you know, Jack Philliston giving you some good minutes, 2KC. You know, the first couple of games, too, they've had a couple of pieces of the puzzle getting to foul trouble early, you know, whether it's Jackson, Bonet. So keeping your guys on the floor.
in the beginning of the game, very important for this Wheeler squad. Absolutely. We saw in the previous game that the whole dynamic changes with Bidet off the floor. New London is not a particularly tall team. They're good sized across. They have length and depth. But Bidet's really the anchor in the middle that gives them both defense and scoring. When Philiston has to come into the game for him, they lose on the offensive end.
and it changes the dynamic and it increases what Savon Warren and Troy McKelvin Jr. have to do so it is definitely a little different for them so they really have to focus on keeping that five as healthy and as you know in shape on the court from a fouls perspective.
One of my old sayings was be productive. And Baudette's one of those kids, especially, you said, from a big man standpoint on the offensive end. When he's out there, he's contributing. He scored 18 points the other night. He got himself a little right end after some foul trouble early. But he's a guy they need. He does a lot of the little things, too, that people don't notice during a basketball game. He plays very hard with a lot of fire. I do think the first four or five minutes of this game very important. See who kind of gets out of the gate and kind of sets the tone early.
Opening tip is sponsored by Kutcher Financial. When you want more than just tips, when you want sound financial planning, go see Lee Kutcher at Kutcher Financial in New London. Lee can help you with financial planning and investment, tax preparation and planning for your business and your personal needs. So feel better about your financial decisions, go to Kutcher Financial.
Starting five for West Haven, Brian Tillman a senior, Aaron Johnson a junior, LaShawn Roman a junior, and a pair of sophomores, Ja'Kai Little and Kanan Morris. So it's a young overall team for West Haven. For New London, Deshawn Phillips and Savon Warren and Jackson Baudette the three seniors, JJ Robinson the junior and Troy McKelvin Jr. the sophomore. Ready to go. Baudette will jump it against LaShawn Roman and we will be underway
here in a moment. Let's have some fun tonight Casey throw the records out the window when you get this deep into tournament play whether to go NCAA or high school level state tournament these teams are all good let's have some fun tonight here at the Mecca as you would call it you did not say that yet tonight. Not tonight I said Madison Square Garden the Mecca the other night but I didn't want to be repetitive just got a little love from the new London alumni that was
Supporting us tonight a former state champion basketball player here at New London High School wanted to wish his whalers luck and say support what game day does. So Roman jumps and the tip won by Westhaven and we're underway. New London come out a little man-to-man early Robinson wreaking havoc. Three-man officials crew Kevin Kobelski, Ben Alamo and Christopher Parker are your three officials.
Very deliberate Westhaven on the first possession. Pull up three is up no good, boxed out by Bidette. Roman, who jumped, stepped out for the three. Robinson all the way to the rack, high and scores over Roman. Gets the Wailers on the board. You know, and Robinson's one of those kids where the coaching staff, I mean, all 12 of them with it for the London, are constantly telling him, attack the rim, attack the rim. That time you saw Robinson doing work at the finish at the glass case, he threw nothing to London. We like the one-to-one coach to player ratio.
There's a lot of guys over there. Hey, they all work well together. It's a great staff.
Brian Tillman, the senior point guard, steps into a three himself, back iron no good, Boo Boo Phillips with a rebound, he'll push, dribbles through traffic, up ahead, Warren again tries to dunk and misses again. He has been trying to get that one to go and his team and the coaching staff are saying would you please just lay it in the basket. But that's one of those, he wanted to get the action up early. He's a half a step away for a little kiss off the glass, little George Girvin finger roll. Take the easy two fella, you know.
It goes off Westhaven so New London will have the possession but that is an easy two. So far the New London speed bothering Westhaven they've been able to get to the rack twice. Robinson up the top of the key now with Tillman on him. Soft defense from Tillman. A lot of teams settle into zone against New London trying to make them shoot from the perimeter.
High screen from Padet, Robinson kicks, Phillips spot up three, no good. And out of bounds it goes, it'll stay Whaler basketball, but only eight seconds now on the shot clock. Yeah, Phillips was one of those kids the other night, first round action, Casey got hot from the three point line, a little cold the other night. Find his touch and find his rhythm early. Robinson to inbound, right in front of the West Haven bench.
Dumps to Baudette, kicked back to Robinson, drives, hangs, floats, no good, and a rebound comes down to Roman, and off to Tillman. Straightaway three is up and good from Kanan Morris, the sophomore.
Cross court pass to Phillips, looking for McKelvin on the block, instead swinging around. They will let New London shoot those threes. See how they attack the zone, whether it's from the side, Casey, or right down the middle. Phillips pulls up, steps up, and buries it. He got bailed out there. He got double teamed. He rose up, knocked down a tough two. A little eight-footer for Phillips on the baseline. He's a senior, and when he gets cooking, man, he is a handful.
Roman double-teamed finds the cutter wild shot no good and Phillips blocked Johnson but they're gonna say you got a piece that's gonna send Johnson to the line and he'll shoot too. And backside boxing out who's assigned to that man Savon Warren's gonna slip in there you know the one and done one and done those are kind of the small things that one will have to do tonight.
It was one thing giving up the cut, but giving up the offensive rebound, that's the problem. So they were covered to defend the cut, but they were not in position to then rebound off of it. That's the, when you get beat like that, it's not only the shot that you have to account for, it's the weak side rebound and they couldn't do both. Especially a team like London who wants to go off of a make. You know, they want to go, they want to leak out, they want to run, secure the ball first, and then get up the court.
But when you're going against a team like this, whether it's Warren or McKelvin or Bourdette, and even Phillips, sometimes it takes four guys on a glass. Looks like West Haven might be setting up a little bit of pressure here as they brought two of their guards up off the make. And they're just going to go with a little 2-1-2. Which gave New London some problems the other night when Crosby ran it. Crosby just ran a simple 2-3. New London should be experiencing how to break it. Look at the trap right there. Robinson.
Norton's got to get somebody into the middle. This is a 2-3 zone. They know it. They've got to get someone in the middle. Robinson floats. No good, but he'll go to the line and shoot a pair. Again, Robinson getting off to an aggressive start. It's his third trip to the 10. He's got a bucket, and he's got a trip to the line for two. And I guess if that's how you're going to beat the zone, you're going to reverse the ball and have him kick in and go.
know Robinson right now hot start here for New London. And certainly when Robinson's playing with a head of steam that's when he's at his best you know yeah he was against the Whalers for you know for two years and they got used to that you know full steam ahead play he was actually a big thorn in their side because he was just relentless constantly going downhill and so now I think they've been waiting all year for him to feel acclimated here enough to
I think it took him, you know, a good at least half the season to get comfortable with the, you know, with the scheme and the style and not look over his shoulders so much to the coaches. But he's come on, you know, very, very well down the stretch this season, especially on a defensive end. Knocks them both down. Pressure here by New London. New London will go into their pressure. And just a step late is Robinson. Here's the danger in the other direction. And out of bounds, it goes as Phillips got a piece. Bidet was trying to draw the charge.
Good job by Panette, protecting the rim. New London comfortable letting West Haven shoot the three as well, so they'll be in that zone as well. Second one goes up, no good from Morris Robinson.
And it was a step in by Tillman. That's a nice move right there, that step in. And fortunately for Robinson, Tillman got a piece of it and went out of bounds. And then Lornen likes to run off of a miss. On the floor right now, the only real shooter here that, you know, Phillips, if he's spotting up, Amir Hall is their real other three-point threat. We're going to get a foul. Salon Warren got hit.
Again, that's the problem with not moving the basketball around the perimeter a little bit. You get sucked into the corner. The double team comes. There's nobody in the middle. Maybe Phillips has got to make his way back to the basketball and ask for it. That's a tough place for Warren actually to pick up his dribble. He's in no man's land out there. Caden Gaskin into the game for New London. We mentioned Amir Hall, who's battling a foot problem. But he's their best shooter, pure shooter.
Phillips can knock it down as well. Instead, he drives the basket, kicks out. KK just into the game for three, no good. Weak side, rebound was tipped and comes to West Haven. Tillman can fly with the basketball, kicks out, and Johnson has it now. Nice look underneath, turn around Jay, no good from Roman. I think he had a little room to go closer. Robinson, tied up on his way to the basket.
Jump ball possession arrow favors New London so they'll keep it here. Robinson shows you that ball just a little bit on his way to the basket. Defenders come on over and they make it a good play. Put that ball on the opposite side of your hip. Keep it ready to roll and keep it ready to shoot. Robinson inbounds. Lob to Deshaun Phillips. Crowd filtering in. Good crowd here for this one.
Phillips tries to drive baseline, picks it up, dumps it down, and stolen as he was trying to go for Bidette. Nice move to the basket by Roman, but he couldn't get it to go. Gaskin with the rebound and an arm bar that he got away with. Now Gaskin, little stutter step. Too much one-on-one from the Whalers, and I think the coaches are going to be saying something in a second.
gets a hand on it knocks it out of bounds it'll stay with West Haven. I mean New London is extremely active on the defensive end disrupting West Haven you know a lot of hands a good job on the defensive glass offensively right now sputtering struggling against that zone. Brandon Bellamy and Tyrone Ogletree check into the game no size lost by West Haven Ogletree is a big as well he's a senior as well all the way back it goes to Bellamy he'll take on the point guard responsibilities with Brian Tillman.
We'll see if Bellamy is a little bit more of a shooter. And New London will have to come out of the zone if he is, or extend the zone if he is. And there it is, corner three, up short. McKelvin gets the rebound. Gaskin, ahead to Robinson. He's tied up, finds McKelvin. McKelvin, left hand, wild shot, no good. Baudette, offensive rebound, misses the bunny.
Four different shots, four different layups tonight right now in the London's Mist. Easy opportunities, they earn them with the offensive rebounds, they can't convert. Badette was in such good position for the offensive rebound, and that's a shot, I mean, he wasn't even challenged, which he's used to being, and ends up missing what is almost a guaranteed make for him. Pull up jumper in the lane, soft touch goes down for Morris.
He's got five of their seven. Friendly rim. Hit three different parts of the rim. Go down to find the bottom of the net. Phillips for three. No good. McKelvin, weak side rebound. Knocked out of bounds. It'll be West Haven ball. And I think McKelvin got bumped, and that's what he's saying, but it was off of him. 22-22 was our score in the first, in the Whalers-Crosby game the other night. It's 7-6 with 147 remaining.
Long pass, three on two here for Westhaven. Pull up three, no good. Phillips high for the rebound. Great job by Nolan again, one and done. Robinson, wild, blocked. Coming in the other direction now is Westhaven. Pull up, jump shot is good from Brian Tillman. And the lead is three. Yep, nice jump shot.
12 feet out, pull up and knock it down. Clean look. And right now New London just struggling to get a good look against the zone. Dump down to McKelvin on the block. Rises up and buries a baseline jump shot. That's a big time shot from the sophomore. The turn, the look, rise up, catch it high, shoot it high. Troy McKelvin Jr. Robinson gets the steal. Phillips heads to the basket.
and finishes at the rim over Bellamy, and just like that the Wailers are on top. And another turnover, that's the lunch pail work the Wailers like to do. Bidette with a smart play. Gaskin, again they hold it up, the shot clock and game clock are effectively even, it's about a half a second difference. So the Wailers can have a lead in the last shot if they choose so.
Gaskin with ready hands in the corner, ready to shoot the three if the ball comes his way. Normally that's Amir Hall's spot. He's their spot up shooter, but we haven't seen him yet. Look for a little clear out here for Robinson. Gets it underneath, loses it, saves it long. Five seconds, West Haven now has a chance to get a shot off. Step back, good if it goes, and in and out. 10-9 at the end of one. We'll be right back with second quarter action. You're watching Game Day Live on the Day.com.
Gameday is brought to you by Waterford Dental Health. Gear up for gameday with a winning smile from Waterford Dental Health. Located in Waterford, where you're go-to for top-notch dental care in a relaxed, friendly setting. Whether you need a routine checkup, a cosmetic boost, or advanced treatment, our experienced team has you covered. Enjoy the game with confidence and comfort. Schedule your appointment today. Waterford Dental Health, where your smile is our top priority. Visit us online or call now to book.
Ladies and gentlemen, the pressure is on. Your financial future awaits. At Kutcher Financial in New London, Connecticut, financial advisor Lee Kutcher offers a path forward. For individuals and businesses, Lee provides steady guidance, aligning your financial goals and investment strategies with your needs. Lee also offers bookkeeping and payroll services for your business. When you're looking to help secure your future, see Lee Kutcher.
One point lead for the Whalers after one and you know Sports Doctor we saw a monumentally poor shooting night from Crosby two nights ago and only a slightly better shooting night by New London. Tonight
West Haven's not shooting the ball particularly well either, but New London has given gift after gift. They've seen this zone defense all year long. It just seems like they're not executing. The ball is not moving. It can't be all about Robinson and dribble penetration. Reverse the basketball, find the cracks in the zone, find the action on the back end, but it just seems like it's extremely stagnant right now for New London. Like you said, without Amir Hall out there with the threat of a three-point shot, they're easy to defend. Right to the rack.
Ja'Kai Little puts Westhaven back on top. And again, no movement, nobody flashing to the center, Bourdette trying to post, but not a real offensive threat, not making himself available. Robinson, pump fakes, kicks out, now Gaskin drives, floater blocked, out of bounds, it'll stay with the Whalers, and Savon Warren's gonna check back into the ballgame.
You know, we've talked about creating a look on the perimeter against the zone. If it's not passing the ball around the perimeter, maybe it's going inside, then back outside. So if Gaskin's got a spot up, if Phillips has got a spot up, create some room that way.
Active hands by West Haven knocks the inbounds pass away. And one thing you notice too, Casey, is any kind of lazy pass tonight is going to be contested. It's going to be tipped. You know, West Haven is too fast, too big, and too talented to get away with lazy passes. McKelvin gets the inbound.
Phillips for three, no good. Baudette, offensive rebound and he can't get it to go, but Warren flies in for the tip and they needed that one. Get on top again by a point. Crash the glass, relentless. Savon Warren at the cup. And again, Baudette normally converts these opportunities. He's given himself easy chances. Knock him in, son.
Robinson on the weak side block that numbers Morris had it instead Warren the other direction and they're gonna call him for the travel. New London can't seem to get out of their own way right now. But they're creating things they're putting themselves in a position to turnovers the block shots the numbers the leak out settle down gather yourself a little bit out there.
Down it goes, they have a double team and another steal as they took it from Roman. Robinson the other direction. High off the glass, no good. McKelvin turns it around and buries the short. Put back from about five feet. The Whalers up three. London back to a man. Tillman.
Now Little. Up on top to Aaron Johnson. He pulls up for three. No good. Contested by Warren. Other direction now. Robinson. Bidet calls for it on the block. Instead, Whalers will go perimeter. They want to give it in to McKelvin. On the baseline, he has it.
Now Bidette comes and sets a screen. Robinson uses the screen, kicks it back to Bidette. Shot clock down to 10. Shot clock down to eight. Phillips tries to create on his own. Wild shot, no good. And Westhaven's gonna run. Up ahead of everybody. Running the floor and missing it was Ja'Kai Little. Robinson and Phillips have done a great job contesting layups. Westhaven extending a little bit.
Bedeck puts it on the floor and gets a foul called against Ja'Kai Little. And in an offensive end, Phillips looks a little bit out of sorts. Casey, he takes one dribble, he picks it up at the top of the key. He kind of kills himself up there. He's going to come out, and I'm sure the coach is going to talk to him. But keep that dribble alive. Be productive. Do something with the basketball. You know, the pounding and the dribbling and then picking it up, it's not creating anything out there for the Whalers. Phillips is a better basketball player than that. Jameer Hall checks into the game for New London.
And so does Jack Philliston, Baudette, and Phillips have a seat. So look for your scoring here to come through Robinson and Warren. And a turnover on the inbound. Into the game, into the lane rather, Tillman.
Tillman handles the ball an awful lot. A lot of responsibility in the young man's hands. The senior. Step back, pull back. Glass is good. Tillman knocks down the shot in a timeout. West Haven, as they've cut it to one.
Well, good ballgame. I mean, you feel like New London, if they could convert on some of these easy opportunities, Casey, they'd be up by a half dozen or so. 14-13 New London. We'll take a quick break. You're watching Game Day Live on theday.com.
Game Day is brought to you by Waterford Dental Health. Gear up for game day with a winning smile from Waterford Dental Health. Located in Waterford, where you're go-to for top-notch dental care in a relaxed, friendly setting. Whether you need a routine checkup, a cosmetic boost, or advanced treatment, our experienced team has you covered. Enjoy the game with confidence and comfort. Schedule your appointment today. Waterford Dental Health, where your smile is our top priority. Visit us online or call now to book.
We're back second quarter 445 remaining in the half 1413 New London if you're interested in the other quarterfinal that this game will match up with NFA with a one-point lead in the basketball with 15 seconds as they take on innovation trying to
create a all ECC semifinal the first half of it is in NFA's hands right now. Boy this league has done extremely well in the state tournament both sides girls and boys and I'm a huge Jeff Brown fan. Griswold has a chance tonight as well talk a little bit about them. Hall brings it up the floor Phillips back in the game and a kick ball. Westhaven back into the zone Casey off the timeout looking to trap
At the top of the key look at the trap when the ball moves and the one who's going to get that thing cooking side to side flash somebody to the middle find the open spots. You know right now in this point of this game with four and a half minutes ago before half and Phillips is going to find himself a little bit on the offensive end. I mean he's got to be the scorer here with Warren McKelvin can work around the block but Hall and Philliston are not much of the offensive threat.
Warren, beautiful look underneath to McKelvin, basket is good, and the foul. And nobody, nobody has seen more banners here than Troy McKelvin, senior and junior would love to add another. Well again, that's the look that time, you know, McKelvin making himself available on the baseline, hanging around, getting ready hands, son, for two at the rim and flexing a little muscle, I like that.
You know, and a good look that time by Warren, you know, recognize him out of the corner of his eye that dished in the delivery. I like the patience, right? We looked around a little bit instead of just blindly flying to the basket, which has been part of their issue. Take a moment, survey. You know, a lot of their misses at the rim, Casey, you feel have been rushed a little bit, you know, by Baudette, by Warren, except great patience that time.
Four minutes, halfway through the second quarter. Three-point Whaler lead. Wild shot by Tillman, no good. And a foul as McKelvin was harassed after the rebound. And that foul will go against West Haven. It's the third of the quarter. Tillman, the guilty party of the region after the miss, the frustration. Brian Tillman to the rim. The timing's a bit of a wild shot, out of control.
No hoop, but to harm. That's correct. Bidette back in the ball game, giving. Looks like Philliston is still in. So Bidette gives McKelvin a breather. And Robinson in as well. Phillips will sit down. Philliston, that's a good idea. That's a great idea. He wanted Bidette to cut and pass it before he's open, to where he's going to be open. That's a smart idea. The quarterback knew what he was doing.
Ball's tipped, no backcourt. 10 seconds on the shot clock. Warren soars, can't get it to go. Rebound. Strong, up high by Morris. Three coming right back the other way by Morris, no good. Hall ahead to Robinson. Robinson turns on the Jets and he's stripped as he heads to the basket. Looks like we're going to get a foul.
And congratulations to Jeff Brown and the NFA Wildcats, who are in the semifinals of Division II after they beat Innovation 56-53. Juice beforehand said, watch the Wildcats. And if the Whalers can do their business tonight, we could have an all-ECC semi, which would be remarkable.
And again, you throw the records out this time of year when you get hot and you get a couple of kids believing in themselves and you get rolling on a bit of a mission, you know, tough, tough, stop. It also helps if you get a couple upsets, you know, you can avoid a certain team, get a matchup to get yourself going. You know, they had to win four games. Innovation was number two, right? No, and it's a tough, tough team. But I think you'd, I think you'd choose innovation over this West Haven team that beat NFL by 30. Yeah, I would think so.
So, you know, it has to be a little bit lucky. And if they get New London, New London's going to beat them, try to beat them for the fourth time. And they've been around it the whole time. So hanging around, hanging around, they got alligator blood. So you've got to love it. Both free throws made by Robinson puts the lead up to five, the biggest lead of the game for New London. I think Coach Cornish has got to be really pleased with the defensive effort of this team right now. Only allowed 13 points. They're hitting the boards, you know, one and done in the offensive end for West Haven.
Nobody's in foul trouble right now for New London. He's kind of finding that right recipe, kind of who to sub in and who to take out. Matthew Morgan into the game for West Haven. First time we've seen him. I'm waiting for that wing shooter. West Haven has it because that's the shot that's available. They haven't had a pure knockdown guy yet. Bellamy passes it off. There's Morgan swinging it around to Morris.
Wide open corner, open look three, up and buried by Aaron Johnson. Johnson the rise up, the catch and shoot, the delivery. Here's your corner ball for the three ball for the corner pocket Casey. Wide open corner three, we love those here on game day. Dump down Bidette, soft touch finish, catch, shoot. Well there you go and Savon Warren throwing the ball up high where his big man can get it and no hesitation. The turn, the look, the delivery for two.
I can tell you already that Morgan's a shooter because he's running the baseline corner to corner. That's where you bring yourself up. That's right. And, you know, they're going to get out here on Johnson. He just shot one. He comes right back again. Oh, Aaron Johnson's on fire already. And it's a one point lead. Like Vinnie Johnson, the microwave. Instant offense.
And by the way, those were rise up contested. Other direction, Savon Warren with a three, no good and it's off West Haven and McKelvin will check back in. So 142-35 on the shot clock.
Boy, how quickly the tides can turn when you've got a seven point lead or a six point lead and the other team starts knocking them down from behind the arc. And those were, I'd give that, you know, I'd give that, that second one was a contested rise up, you know, square up. So you can't do much better than that. A man in his grill, hand in your face. Johnson's got great length though. Yes, he does.
Robinson, to Warren, looking for Baudet on the dump down, back up top. Great job by Bellamy, face guarding Phillips, got number one versus number one, and Dave wants to talk it over in the last minute and a half, and I don't blame him. Phillips right now in the offensive end, even though having a hard time getting himself open, can't a little shake and bake get rid of his guy. Brandon Bellamy, great job on the defensive end right now.
So we've got semifinal action in division one we know that the St. Bernard Saints after a nice win last night against Staples is in a I mean you can't look at the you look at the D1 semis it is the elite of the elite St. Bernard he's Catholic and Notre Dame Notre Dame no BC in any of the semifinals however two Notre Dames so
It's just a shot at my right here. He gets it. Division two. We see NFA first ones to get to the semis. You know, division five. We got that great Grasso tech old line. You know, they're all got Fitch in the semifinal. Fitch has got a great draw. They got McMahon. The ECC has done very well. The locals have done very well. But I go, you know, this one right here, you know, give NFA all the credit. This one right here is going to be contested all the way through, I believe.
Robinson picks the dribble up now for Phillips. Underneath, Bidet, Pumphrey, harassed, no, his own offensive rebound, no, third chance, no, McKelvin, no, Warren, stripped. That's about six chances for a new arm. Four shots, point blank range.
Warren loses it, finds McKelvin, he's harassed. Back to Warren, can't handle it. Rise up jumper, and finally, after about shot seven, the Whalers are up three. Well, there's a term this time of year we call it either win ugly or lose pretty. That's win and ugly right there. Five knocks at the rim. It's also win in advance, right? Yeah, survive in advance. Survive in advance. Right now, three point lead for the Whalers. Eight second difference between the shot clock and the game clock.
Three, up, no good, back iron. Phillips with a high rebound. Whalers can get the last shot of the quarter if they want it. Robinson with a three, no good. Warren finds Bedette, put back, no good. Out of bounds with 6.8. The Whalers will have it with 6.8 seconds. Whalers got a break and they just can't finish around the rim right now.
Robinson will take a break here with the last 6.8 seconds. Hall comes in for him. Hall will inbound. Dumps down to Warren. Warren, pump fake, kicks back. Hall for three, good! Oh boy!
Jameer Hall with a big three at the end of the quarter. Dave Cornish is all kinds of fired up. He is thrilled the Whalers have a six point lead and he is going to talk to the sports doctor in a moment. What a big shot but he goes over first to Jameer Hall and says great job knocking it down. Sports doctors with coach Cornish.
Dave, a big lift on your haul for a corner three. Talk about the defensive end though. You held that good team to 19 points in the first half. Yeah, but we lost Aaron on two corner threes down here. I'm a little disappointed about that. But other than that, we've been playing pretty good. You guys have been giving yourselves second, third, fourth chance scoring opportunities on the offensive end. If you could convert a few more of those tonight, Dave.
Yeah, I mean, we've done that all year. We've hit the offensive glass. So if we can continue to do that, hopefully we don't need to do that. Hopefully we can make the shot and we don't need to hit the offensive side. Good luck in the second half, coach. Well, we're at halftime. The Wailers with a six-point lead. We'll be coming back with the second half after some video action and highlights. You're watching Game Day live on theday.com. It's time for the athletes of the future, grading plays of the week.
At number eight, Carmelo Sylvester. Benny Dover Jackson Middle School against Clark Lane. The long three. Bank it in, Mello. At number seven, Asia Harris. Wind of basketball. Look at the hands, the steel, all the way to the basket and one. Whippets win the ECC D2 Championship.
Harris was a menace with speed all the way to the hoop. At number six, Aria Leonard brought in middle school basketball. The third grader, she wants to be like Harris, steal off to the races and the basket. At number five, congratulations Griswold Basketball's Abby Matheson. A thousand career points. Great job, Abby.
At number four, Fitch Basketball's Luke Wenger. The opening round win over Amistad. A little stutter step, dipsy do, and oh, the English off the side of the glass. At number three, Keon Simillion. Teacher's global magnet middle, with a 360 layup, dare I say, scintillating.
At number two, Maddie Ives, bacon basketball back to the basket, the wild shot. Bobcats win the D1 championship thanks to plays like that from Ives. But at number one, for a week of free training at Athletes of the Future,
Sterling Walsh. Fitch Co-op. 100 free. 9 hundredths of a second. He gets rival Eduardo Marcos. And look at the face. It says it all. Sterling, you won. And you get a free week of training at AOF. That is your Grade 8 Play of the Week. And those are your Grade 8 Plays. Send in your plays and maybe you can make next week's Grade 8.
Long shot up and oh, knocking it down, Henry Lloyd from downtown. Trying to get to the basket, weaving his way through. Jump shot, oh swish, buried by Noah Schaefer. Fast break opportunity, nothing but net. Splash for Bowden. Good pass underneath.
Nice shot by DeVille, high, Archer. Weaving through traffic, Sean Morrison off the glass. Now the rebound back to Redmond, off the glass it's good. Only a sophomore, Damian Redmond. DeFelice all the way to the basket and knocks it down. Sam. That's Wes.
Not bad, good shot by West. This guy inside has been unstoppable. You can't stop Taylor Herbert. And then he's going to sprint back on D, which is the best part of it all. First guy back on defense. And bang, knocking it down from long range is Zab. Great shot.
Reverse layup is good from our guy Jacob Sachs. Nice basket from Colby. Yeah, good left hand. Up ahead to Duda. Duda, bounce pass. Jump shot is knocked down. That was by Jojo Rivera. Fatima.
Swish. Buckets for team Amalo. Warren floats and scores. No one's better at scoring than Warren and Soren. Offensive rebounds. Nice look from Robinson to Bedette underneath for the easy two. Robinson finds McKelvin. Left hand, basket is good and the foul. Troy McKelvin Jr. Nice look underneath.
and a foul on Warren, and that'll be his second foul as Raekwon Anderson, but he gets his offensive rebound on the tip, underneath, beautiful look to Washington. I like the game of Raekwon Anderson. Usually produce long rebounds, the Whalers have to know that. Lazy pass from Hall in the other direction, Washington finishes in the timeout, Dave Cornish, because he knows his team should be up more than five.
Phillips all the way, left hand is good and the foul. He figures it out. Robinson, great look to Baudette. Jackson Baudette is rapidly becoming my favorite player. Baudette with a rebound. Ahead to Warren, finds Robinson, puts it on the floor. Nice patience by J.J. Robinson, the lead is up to nine. Five point second quarter.
JJ, all the way to the basket, and the foul. Robinson draws the foul on Kinsey, he'll go to the line. This game, they have to take care of the ball and get defensive rebounds. Phillips, all the way to the basket. Boo-boo for two. And I think it's a combination of both. Robinson finds Warrant. Easy basket and transition for the Whalers. Yeah, Crosby just fell asleep there. Good job of getting back, setting up the zone.
Three shot and buried by Kinsey. Back to back makes from three for Crosby, has it down to six. And then a turnover on a high pass. Robinson attacks. Wild shot is good and a foul. Hey hey JJ. Consider the way they're shooting the three. Bidet with the block. Warren ahead to Phillips. Phillips all the way to the basket. And Boo Boo scores and gets the lead back up to eight.
And they survive. They advance. Quarterfinals, Friday night here at Conway. It took about two hours for Northwestern Regional to make the bus trip from Winstead to Stonington. But it took Maddie Topa three seconds to score the first points in Thursday's class-M quarterfinal. The 2,000-point score lit it up early for the Highlanders with 14 first-half points, a nice assist to Emma Maltby.
Mackenzie Janko finds Topa on the inbound, Northwestern is up 8. But Sophia Hawinski causing big problems in the paint, she would also score 14 in the first half. Leah DiPeri, the long outlet to Adeline Risley, bears within one. And Kaitlyn Cadness with a steal in the contested layup to give Stonington the lead.
Topa with a dish to Kylie Stapleton, put the Hilltoppers back on top. The Hwinski almost unstoppable in the post. The Bears take a 28-27 lead into halftime. Three-pointer by Cadmus makes the lead four early in the third. Two quick baskets from Topa and the game is tied 33-33.
Stonington though would finish the quarter with 12 straight points. Callie Mansfield to Cadmus for the reverse layup there by nine. And Cadmus gets her own rebound, fights for the putback. Bears lead 50 to 37 after three. Northwestern working to shut down Hawinski with two and three defenders, but she finds Rory Wisley for the easy layup in the fourth. Wisley would finish with 11, Hawinski with 20.
And DiPeri, long pass to Cadmus, 19 points on the night for her and the lead is 15. Topa would pour in 35 points in the game, but it was not enough. DiPeri breaks the late pressure and finds Adeline Risley to make it 61-50. Bears go on to win 67-54. They will face ECC rival Wyndham in the semifinals on Monday.
Gonna start the second half with a six-point Whaler lead, and the second half possession is brought to you by Kuchar Financial. Located in New London, Kuchar Financial will help you keep possession of your money through sound financial planning and investment, tax planning and preparation, whether you're an individual or a small business. Everyone wants to feel better about their finances, so go see Lee Kuchar. At Kuchar Financial, let him make you feel more confident. Whalers with the opening possession of the second half. Yeah, big three by Hall. Casey to give him a six-point lead going into the locker room.
Robinson and McKelvin leading the way with six apiece for the Wailers. Robinson in and out on a spot up three, Baudette lost the rebound and Westhaven's gonna run. Maybe that's gonna be the word coming out of the locker room is for them to push. Phillips with a blocked shot. Again though that three was halfway down. Inside the challenge and the soft roll for Kanan Morris.
We'll keep an eye on Deshaun Phillips here in the second half. He's a senior. Two points in the first half. Check that, four points in the first half. Warren for three, in and out. Right into Baudette's hands though. Jump ball, possession arrow goes to West Ham. So two early threes from New London. I don't know why we've come out of the gates
thinking that they were going to run a different offense but we were we were saying how they had to get it inside work guys two threes. West Haven's made the commitment to get the ball inside you can see it already they're going to challenge New London's bigs. Wild shot no good offensive rebound on the floor West Haven now
challenge but the basket by Ogletree and just like that West Haven's cut the lead to two. 4-0 run all from inside to paint all at the rim for West Haven. Robinson in the corner to Warren that's the shot they will give. They're gonna give it to him too this sag off him.
McKelvin flashes, but nothing there. Bidet pulls up from about 10 feet, no good. Ball tipped on the floor. West Haven's got numbers. And oh, what a block by Boo Boo Phillips. Big time on a defensive end, number one squaring things up, sending it back. Phillips saw that coming the whole way in front of him and timed his jump perfectly. That's an ouchie. Look at this right here, boom, get out of here.
Hall into the game for New London after knocking down that three at the end of the half. We'll see if they're going to run some things through him. It's a small little play like that at defensive end it kind of welcomes Phillips into the game a little bit too. I don't like the second half start for either team. I love what West Haven's trying to do. Miss there in the lane but they've made a commitment to get the ball to the big man down low.
Get to the rim, create some easy scoring opportunities. Phillips gets a step, drives, hangs, and an offensive foul. And saw that coming a mile away. Great job, Kanan Morris. Morris holding his ground. Phillips coming right down the pipe. Good job by Morris on the defensive end. 4-0 run out of the chute. Second foul on Phillips for West Haven.
Tillman has a mismatch with Baudet on him. All the way to the basket. That could take Ty Little, yeah. He took the bump, the finish, the hoop, and just like that, 6-0 run. We're tied at 25. Tillman harassing Robinson.
How quickly your lead evaporates when you're not converting on the offensive end. Westhaven's made some adjustments. Everything right now is close by the rim. Robinson, stutter step, finds McKelvin. McKelvin, short jumper, no good. Phillips with the offensive rebound. He draws the foul.
You know, one thing, too, without Amir Hall available to them, and he hasn't been in the game, which makes me feel like he may not be available. They really don't have a lights-out three-point shoot. They do not. And if he was on the floor, that would extend that zone just enough. And right now, they don't have to come out on anybody. Yeah, whether it's Jameer in the game, and Gaskin showed you some flashes early, but couldn't knock one down. Savon Warren's been a little helter-skelter from the three-point line.
No real offensive threat from behind the arc. I mean, I think Phillips is going to have to be that guy to get things moving. They've knocked down one three. And that was the Hall three at the end of the half. Free throws. One of two. Lead is one. Pressure. Great trap that time by McKelvin and Phillips. And a timeout by Westhaven. Timeout Westhaven, as Ty Sullivan wants to talk it over because this guy was in a dangerous position, trapped in the corner.
30 second timeout, so we'll keep it here. New London's gonna go right into the trap, Casey, after a make or after a free throw. And a great job that time by McKelvin and Phillips, getting West Haven pinned in.
So the second half of this game, though, it seems like West Haven has kind of come out and made some sort of adjustment. On the offensive end, whether it's get the ball to the rack, get yourself some easy opportunities. And the London came out firing a three ball.
Well, I think what Westhaven said, if I could guess, was we're going to up the offensive tempo. We're going to move the ball better offensively and we're going to make a commitment to getting it in the paint towards the bigs. Defensively, Westhaven said, we're going to sag and give them all the three, bait them. And then to their credit, New London missed some threes and that helps Westhaven get out and push, which is what they're trying to do.
Pressure by New London. Sort of the soft 2-3. And they'll drop back in. Turnover as Roman hit the floor. Robinson finds Phillips. Couple of pump fakes and boo-boo for two. Yeah, run on the floor that time and Robinson with a little handoff delivery to Phillips. Phillips converting.
And right into the pressure comes New London. They got Johnson trapped. He finds his man underneath. Bidet's behind. And a soft touch, though, goes down. Kane and Morris keeps getting those nice bounces like he's a New London guy. The home rim. The friendly rim.
Phillips pulls up in the traffic, finds Baudette, and there's a nice look and a nice finish. Well, you know, I like the way Baudette makes himself available. He shows, he seals his man off at the back end and a turnover here for New London, possibly. Can he save it? He does. But who's going to get it? It's like a greased pig. Finally, it comes down and way ahead. And finishing is Aaron Johnson. So a little bit of bad luck there. New London went from turnover
And Baudette! Oh! Jackson Baudette! Is that Cajun for Thunder? Right back on the wheel is the Jims Alive. Other direction. Oh, how did that go down? Shot little. Sha'Kai Little played big. Now we're starting to warm it up a little bit.
Baudette from the free throw line, no good. Tipped by Robinson. Robinson gets the rebound. And we're gonna get a foul, which a good call on Tillman. Right, and Robinson does a great job selling it. You know, we see it in the NBA all the time with the head bob and the arms going up in the air. It could have been a held ball, but Robinson sells that so well. Gaskin into the game from McKelvin. McKelvin is reaching for his calf.
I think maybe a little cramp action, he's gonna see the trainer. Robinson will inbound. Officials get together. Nothing there, so they go high to Gaskin. Phillips.
Drives to the middle. Hall, spot up three. Got it! Jameer Hall, two for two from behind the arc. Big time delivery in the stroke. Phillips with the recognition, kick out to the wing. And here comes London, on the turnover case. Hands from Hall, and Gaskins wisely gave it up. Phillips inside, no good. Gaskins tips it to Baudette, and Baudette's gonna draw the foul.
and Johnson's down on the floor as he landed hard, but a good sequence for the Wailers. Yeah, last couple trips to New London, creating offense off of a second chance scoring opportunity. You saw Robinson get in the mix, this time you see Phillips getting in, keeping the ball alive on the second chance opportunity, and Bourdette, Johnny on the spot once again for New London. That was Ogletree, he's up. I apologize, it was not Aaron Johnson, it was Tyrone Ogletree, but he's up and he's okay, and Baudette will shoot too. You know, in the Crosby game, I said Jameer Hall
was playing like it was just one click he was one click off you know I mean he was a little too fast a little too slow couldn't quite get this game he has been locked in and quite frankly New London would not be where they are right now without the play of Jameer Hall that was his slap away that led to these two free throws for Bidet. You've got to be ready when your number is called when you're coming off the bench to be productive and knock down shots and Jameer Hall calmly has done that.
One more free throw for Jackson, Baudette, the Whaler lead is back to five. Smooth, isn't he? Knocks him both down, lead six, Whaler staying a little bit of pressure.
Tillman the savvy guard though Little into the corner now Ogletree back up top Hall almost had the steal but Little just rose up above him and then we're gonna get a touch foul out on the perimeter. Cheapie out there by Gaskin you know he kind of lets his man turn the corner gets a little too handsy but that's a dangerous pass coming back with Hall challenging it by Westhaven. Inbounding from the far side now will be Tillman
We're gonna get Matthew Morgan back into the ballgame for Westhaven. Ogletree will have a seat. I like this lineup in there right now for New London, giving them a spark. Little mismatch, Tillman had Bidette beat. Bidette recovered though nicely. Now Tillman will spot up for a three, no good, Bidette gets the rebound.
McKelvin trying to walk off a little leg strength. Hall all the way to the basket, finds Baudette and he can't get it to go down because he wasn't ready for the pass. No he was not. Morgan for three, no good. Offensive rebound.
and getting to the basket and causing a foul is Kanan Morris, he'll shoot two, and Morris has been spectacular for West Haven every time they've needed a big play. Yeah, he's been a lunch pail guy, Casey, on the offensive glass, second chance scoring opportunities, the turn and face and a couple of jump shots, but just a guy that's gonna do some dirty work in there and create some opportunities by hustle, you see it here. Morris, again, to lean in that time, drawing the contact from Baudette.
You know and how many times stick to the London coaches are over there saying move your feet. You know if Gaskin picks up a foul on the outside with his hands, move your feet, move your feet son. Two shots for Kane and Morris. First one is no good. This lead is six. That's what it was going into the locker room. So the London's kind of right of the ship here in the third quarter. Watching McKelvin right in front of us trying to run off a little bit of a leg strain. Sure. Little cramp.
Trying to work that out. He'd like to get back on the floor for the fourth quarter, I'm sure. One more for Kane and Morris. That one's pure. And the lead is five. A little bit of pressure again here now from West Haven. Here comes the pressure. Robinson.
Attacks, finds Gaskin, Gaskin blocked, gets his own rebound. Kicks back out, Phillips for three, short. Westhaven's gonna run. Johnson, wild spin and an offensive foul as Phillips took the charge. Johnson was a half beat late on what would have been an exciting spin move. Yeah, Phillips holding his ground, missed a three, came back, played D.
stood his ground, drew the charge, the little things that make big things happen in A.C. A little out of control that time by Johnson. Phillips gets rewarded with a foul called. Full time out for New London, so we'll take a quick... We'll remind you that game day is brought to you by Waterford Dental Health.
Gear up for game day with a winning smile from Waterford Dental Health. Whether you need a routine checkup, a cosmetic boost, or advanced treatment, our experienced team has you covered. So Waterford Dental Health, 177 Boston Post Road, where your smile is our top priority. And Scient Federal Credit Union. Pave the way for your student's financial success with a MySci account from Scient Federal Credit Union. Open a high-yield MySci savings account today. Help support a positive financial future for your student. ScientFCU.org slash MySci to learn more. Talk about balanced scoring. And Mr. G's.
restaurant and bar located in New London Connecticut if you need a good meal or some good company before or after the game go to Mr. G's it's where the coaches it's where the players it's where the fans go and a special shout out to the New London High School alumni for supporting game day tonight and all that we do. Whalers with a five-point lead in the basketball. Well balanced scoring tonight for New London Casey with you know
six players scoring all their points. Obviously, Baudette with eight, JJ with six, you've got Jermier Hall with six, you know, and Deshaun Phillips with seven. So, London sharing the basketball out there.
Pressure again from Westhaven. Last time the Wailers tried to attack it once it got into Robinson's hand. Patience until then. Gaskin finds Robinson, finds Baudette, and that is how you break a press and cause the press to crumble because you get a basket out of it. You attack it with Robinson and in the back end you get Baudette with ready hands this time. Wailers now, they're in pressure. And they've got Little trapped.
Five second, double dribble. Double dribble from Little. Whalers will have the ball. Seven point lead. It's, right now with 54 seconds left, this is a crucial point in the game for West Haven. They're down seven. They just have a turnover. We only got about two or three possessions left in this quarter. This game was tied. And they'll want to find a way to get cooking a little bit. They've extended their lead, believe it or not, here in the third.
What's the problem here? We got a time of official's whistle. Official's time out there. The way that Whalers have attacked this pressure the last two times is they've gotten it to Robinson. And however they did it, either bounce pass to the middle or wing back to the middle. And once it's in Robinson's hand, he attacks the basket. He attacks, he goes, he draws a lot of attention. Then you've got somebody like Bourdette on the backside. And it's an easy pitch and catch for two for Jackson Bourdette. Again, the key here is- Hold on, hold on. That guy right there?
All-time letter winner, most letters of anybody at New London High School, multiple state championship, Trinity High School, he was all everything at Trinity, and you know what? He knows how to use a mop. He's setting up his own defense and a mop at the same time. I don't care if he's an all-time, I don't care if he's an all-time grade, he knows how to use a mop. Gets down to work. Yeah. You know who would never be seen using a mop? Mike DeMauro? No, me. Okay. Me. You know, no Swiffers, no mops, nothing. I mean, you come in for mop-up duty, would you not? If you were called in for mop-up duty. I could go into mop-up duty, that's right.
Teams down 15 to 4 in the ninth inning. That's bringing in Mayday Casey. Not Mayday Malone, Mayday Casey. I tell you though, the favorite quote of all time. We lost in Newington one year. I pitched five innings in an exhibition game. We beat them in the state tournament like 2 to 1. And they said, what's the biggest difference in this team and the team you faced earlier in the season? And their head coach without batting an eyelash goes, O'Neal didn't pitch.
All right, Robinson's been the key to this new London seven-point lead with his ability to attack the pressure, attack the rim, and find open bodies and deliver. Looks like they want to use as much clock as they can, limit West Haven to no more than one possession.
Paul Robinson, Gaskin, Phillips, and Bidette. 13 on the shot clock. Robinson pulls up, zips it underneath to Phillips, but it was a little bit too much of a fastball, and so with 25 on the clock, West Haven can have the last shot of the quarter if they want. Down seven, you would think they would want to limit one shot, no second possession for New London. One and done, no run out with seven seconds to go. Take care of the basketball, get a good look,
That was a good pass by Robinson, it was just a little bit too much of a fastball for Phillips to handle. Pressure by New London. Open look, Johnson, corner three, short. Gaskin, 13 seconds, New London has a chance. Gaskin spins, loses it on the floor. And with eight seconds remaining now, West Haven right back again will have a chance.
all the way to the basket and finishing is Tillman, a big basket. We're at the end of three and a big basket by Westhaven gets him to within five. Fourth quarter action coming. You're watching game day live on the day dot com. Last year, Waterford senior number four on the grade eight, the Olympic go kick. I'm here with Cam Dickinson. I don't think she can pull it off. It looks way too hard. I think it was a fluke. Get it done.
That was just too easy, and that is a grade eight play. Send in your best plays and see if you can beat that and make this year's grade eight Olympico style.
Relive a century of history from the perspective of southeastern Connecticut with the new hardcover book, Front Page News, A Century of Big Stories in the Day, 1881 to 1981. This 136-page limited edition book captures the pulse of a region and a nation, showcasing the day's most iconic front pages from its first 100 years. Order today at theday.frontpagesbook.com.
Ty Sullivan and his West Haven Blue Devils down five as we start the fourth quarter. New London will have the first possession of the fourth quarter. They've got Robinson, Phillips, Baudette, Hall, and McKelvin on the floor as West Haven with a big basket by Tillman right before the end of the third period got them to within five. McKelvin swings, Phillips short, tipped.
Westhaven's gonna run. Little, all the way to the basket. Foul is on the floor on Robinson on the reach. First personal foul on Robinson. They're gonna say it was in the act of shooting though, so. Jakai Little. Continuation? He was on the floor?
Not exactly, you know, Giannis Antetokounmpo going to the basket, but first one in and out. Giannis Antetokounmpo, who gets continuation from half court. Talking NBA tonight, I'm all set with that. No, no, not talking NBA, just referencing the Greek freak, that's all. Little misses them both. The ball don't lie sometimes. Game recognizes game.
And when you watch Phillips too on his release of his jump shot the last few times in London, a lot of legs involved. His shots have been very flat. Robinson blocked as he kind of found himself in the danger zone amongst the bigs. And Ogletree, literally a tree. So he found himself under the, amongst the Ogletrees. Tall kid. Number three. Robinson. And I'm going to kick ball. Do it a third time here.
Trying to get that ball and a bounce pass to Phillips, which they have right there. Swinging it around now. Stagnant here on this trip. They're kind of back to that perimeter swing. Nothing there, nothing there. Back around the perimeter, shot clock to 15.
Now they're gonna run a play with 12 seconds left. This is usually where they find themselves in trouble. Eight seconds, Robinson, crossover, pull up, tipped and stolen by Johnson. Over the top of Phillips, no good. Put back, no good. And Little, working the offensive glass, will go to the line.
And again, you know, when you're in the fourth quarter, the wasted offensive trips, you know, like that one for New London, you know, you didn't get a shot off there. And Robinson turned the corner, decided to kick it out, balls turned over, and an easy opportunity comes down for West Haven. But you've got to find a way to get at least a quality shot in the half court set. Foul was on Padet. Little will shoot two. First one is good.
It's a juncture of the game, Casey, where you work so hard in that third quarter to build that seven point lead. You don't want to let West Haven back in the game. At least hold serve, hold court. Two free throws by Morris are good. Substitutions coming in the game for West Haven. 3-0 run to start the third quarter. Ball from the free throw line.
So the fouls on Baudette, I don't know if that's two or three on Baudette. Robinson. McKelvin now, squares up, looks for a cutter, back to Phillips.
Robinson, harassed, drives baseline, floats, hangs, no. McKelvin gets the offensive rebound and it's knocked out of bounds. Robinson went hard. Only one foul on Baudette, so I thought they had, I thought I was worried about it being three or four and it was only one. So, lots of worry about nothing. Some more mopping on the floor as it's getting a little wet down there.
Whalers caught a break there McKelvin had it knocked out of his hands timeout. That's a good timeout by coach Dave right there the offense is kind of sputtered the last two or three downs down the court talk things over set up an inbound piece you know and go from there right now Robinson seems to be the only the only aggressive piece on the offensive end you know start the fourth quarter for New London. The problem with this with what if
If they get to about 10 seconds on the shot clock, they don't have anything to that they can do other than sort of the reckless drive to the basket. So they really, if they don't get a shot off and a good look by about the 15 second mark, then their offense becomes one dimensional and not something that West Haven really worries about because they've got the size and length. So you watch the Whalers start to move and you can tell at about 25 seconds,
Is this going to be a swing around the perimeter possession or a hero basketball move and that's what so you know they've got to get the ball at the 25 second mark into the paint or to the cutter. If they're just going to go around the perimeter at 25 seconds then they look up and there's 15 and they got they got to start going and then they're at a you know they got nothing. The offense breaks down the quality becomes less than what coach Dave Cornish would want to see. That is correct. So Robinson will inbound.
Kanan Morris who's done a great job for the Blue Devils on him. Bedette flashes, catches it high. And he's harassed and we're gonna get a foul on Ogletree. Ogletree doesn't like it, that's a good call. Grabbing the back of his wrist, holding the ball high. The double team is definitely coming when he touches the basketball.
Inbound McKelvin, stolen. That was good hands from Johnson. They almost turned it over, but Tillman, so quick to the basketball. Tillman with Hall on him. Oh, hanging in the air with a left hand. Jakai Little, and the lead is one. Timeout. Ty Sullivan, because they want to set up pressure. It's a 6-0 run.
to start the fourth quarter for West Haven. And you know, right now, New London is just floundering on the offensive end. And much like the start of the third quarter, KC West Haven kind of comes out, they impose their will on the defensive end, and they get some easy buckets on the other side. They've got four points from the free throw line, and then one made layup. That's their point so far in the fourth quarter. And New London hasn't gotten a reasonable shot in this quarter, because they've been sort of relegated to the perimeter, where New London took off
was when they were breaking pressure and getting layups, or when they had Robinson attack the middle and find his teammates. Right now, New London is out of sync, out of sorts, and out of time here with a one-point lead for them to figure out how to run their offense.
You know, who's gonna step up and be that next player? I mean, you know, Hall hasn't had any good looks. You know, I guess I'm still waiting for Phillips to kind of step up and put his stamp on this game as a senior in the last six minutes. Obviously Robinson, very aggressive. You know, Bourdette's out there. Let's just make things easy for ourselves on the offensive end. Stay aggressive, move the basketball.
We've seen this, though, a few different times in the London team, where they kind of build a little bit of a lead for themselves and fall asleep. Then have to climb back up and take another four or five point lead and kind of hang on a little bit. It's a good West Haven team. Very good West Haven team. They will drop out of pressure off the timeout, which I wouldn't be pressuring New London either, because that's the easy way to give them on offense. Warren back into the game for Hall. Original starting five in the game now for the Whalers. Warren.
dumps down to Baudette. He's doubled and he's tied up and the possession arrow favors West Haven. So that's the one problem. That's what they want. They want to get the dump down so that they can double Baudette. Baudette is telling them I don't I don't need the basketball right there. Put it up high where I can grab it and turn and face the bounce pass is no good. Again they were letting Warren they had said please shoot the three. Spot up wide open three no good.
That was Morris, now Robinson with the basketball. Robinson hangs, finds Padet, soft touch, lead is 3. Yeah, good recognition that time by Robinson, noticing the big man out in front. And Padet with 12 to lead the way for the Whalers. That's when they're at their best. That's a big bucket too. Yeah, when Robinson distributes and Padet finishes, that's when they're at their best.
Around the curl, Johnson, he's been very hot. Not that time, however, as that goes out of bounds, and it'll be Whaler basketball. Boy, you're so right about Robinson. When he gets himself freewheeling, nobody around him, he can survey the floor a little bit, you know, and you've gotta be ready. You've gotta make yourself available, whether you're, you know, McKelvin Jr., or Jackson Bourdette, or even Savon Warren. Just be ready for the basketball, because, you know, if you're open, he's gonna get it to you.
Warren, that ball is tipped. Stolen by Morris. And a laziness, the lazy passes.
Steal the other direction. Phillips goes to the left hand. Tipped out of bounds. Wildly flung in. Robinson gets it. He finds Warren, but it's on the floor. And Warren wisely pulls it out. Instead, floats. No good. Tipped. No good. Who's going to come down with it? It's going to be Johnson. Big defensive rebound for West Haven. Man, if New London could finish around the back. Just make a layup. My goodness.
Bellamy Tillman rather Tillman step back three no good offensive rebound Ogletree and they're going to have a foul. It's like Warren peeking in from the outside region. It is going to be on Warren.
And that's going to put Ogletree at the line to shoot two and Ogletree's length has definitely bothered New London. He has been in for Roman for a while now and Ogletree has been their main guy on the glass. Got to find a body on the bigs. Got to keep him off the glass on the offensive end. One of the knocks on New London, the whispers around the league was
They can't win the close game. If you get them in a close one, they don't know how to finish. That's been Dave's M.O. for a long time, even using the ledger. You know, how do you, how do you close out somebody's close game, situational basketball? They said if they get a lead, they can run away with it. They can, they can bury it. Right. But if you keep yourself in a close one, if you keep yourself in a close one, you know, that Crosby game was close late, but they pulled away. Yeah.
You know, can they win a game when it's a one possession game, you know, under a minute? We're going to find out because I don't think West Haven's going anywhere here in these last four minutes. And they're packing it in West Haven too. Again, challenging the one in the shoot to three. Hall now Robinson looking for a high screen from Bidette gets the mismatch, but we're down to 10 seconds. Robinson.
This is the same thing before, Robinson gets a screen, drives, floats, left hand, it's blocked by Johnson. And we're going to get a foul, I think on McKelvin on the push. Yep, foul's on McKelvin. And that wild circus shot came with two seconds on the shot clock. Again, they cannot run an offense with ten seconds left on the shot clock.
London with only two points this quarter they led 39-32 coming into the fourth. West Haven with a chance to tie or take the lead and that would be interesting if they ever took the lead what does new how does New London respond you know they haven't lost the lead yet. No good tipped keeping it alive.
was little, little, kick out, wide open, three is up, no good, weak side, Phillips, he's ahead, he's got numbers. Blocked by Morris, now Westhaven the other direction. A charge, nice job by Hall. Offensive foul as Jameer Hall stood his ground and took the charge from Morris and that is the second time Hall has done that.
Taking one for the team is a new definition on that one, my friend. Holding your ground, absorbing the blow. And again, Phillips that time with numbers, Casey, and kind of indecisive with the basketball. And what is he going to do with it? I mean, if you're three steps from the rim, drive over to the rim and finish. And they're making a priority. I mean, they're guarding Phillips from the jump. They're making a priority of him.
New London's got to find a way to get an offense going here and not just pass the ball around the perimeter they're just they're playing shot clock basketball right now. Gotta stay aggressive high ball screen here from Burdett the double team comes. And we're gonna get a foul.
foul on Ogletree. On Ogletree, which I think is a break for Robinson because they had him in a dangerous spot as well. He's right on half court. The double team comes a little too greedy that time with the hands by Tyrone Ogletree. It's five on Ogletree, he's fouled out. Ogletree fouls out of the game. Roman coming back into the game is no picnic with Ogletree going away. Roman's been incredibly active. Length comes back with Length.
But the Whalers need to find a way to get I mean I don't like this sitting outside and letting 30 seconds go up the shot I mean that's just that's ridiculous. They got to run an offense. Robinson's kind of fiddling and diddling but doing nothing with the basketball at the top of the circle. I think they were saying it wasn't on Ogletree and they're trying to get Ogletree to fit the foul switched off of Ogletree. You see Kevin Kobelski the outstanding official talking to West Haven.
Look at some fans, security's looking at some fans over there behind the bench. That's what's going on there. Four fouls for New London and three for West Haven. So New London will inbound, Hall far away from us on the far court. Robinson out.
Hall, open three, third one of the game. Oh, Jameer Hall, shooter's gonna shoot. I see you, Jameer Hall. Big time shot from the junior. Step in, jump shot, no good. And Bidet knocks it out of bounds.
I like the way Hall works on the baseline, frees himself up, nails it. Huge shot. A little breathing room for New London with under two to go. Yeah, it's like breathing room on a cold day with asthma. Up top, Tillman. Tillman.
West Haven taking some time they're gonna be methodical they need a basket which means they need a good look.
Open look, three, no good from Morris. Offensive rebound and a foul. Offensive rebound came down to Johnson and that'll put him at the line to shoot two and he's a good shooter. You've got to find a way in these long three point shots if you're in London to find the glass. I mean long shots, long rebounds. Box out on the shooter, all five guys with their faces in the glass. You've got to take care of the basketball on the defensive end.
Two shots for Aaron Johnson. He's been an excellent shooter for them all night long. And he, oh, that one was, that one was in the net and it came out the other way. One more for Johnson.
We said Little, see Little has the friendly rim rolls all night. Johnson, the ugly rim that time. Good basketball game here tonight, huh? One of two, four, now Westhaven's gonna pressure. Now this is where New London has a chance to use this pressure as an opportunity to score. Robinson breaks the pressure, attacks the basket. Off him, great weak side help, and the block.
And it'll be West Haven ball. Get to the rim, maybe a ball fake or something like that if you're Robinson. You're kind of in no man's land a little bit. Bounce pass on the backside, maybe to Bourdette. Easy to say when I'm not out there. When you have a head of steam, you just want to go. This is what we said. Can New London find a way to close out this close game? Time out, West Haven.
The brain trust over there for New London. He's got a great staff Casey. You know whether it's Troy McKelvin or Danny Spellman and it's just a lot of good basketball minds around him. Dave Cornish does. Here's the order of things for the Whalers. Sound defensive effort. Rebound. Yes. Right. Regardless of whether you make or miss you're going to have the lead.
So if it's you have a four point lead with the ball then you know now you got to possess the ball. All right. Be smart with it. They're going to pressure you if you have a two point lead or a one point lead. They're good. They may not pressure you. They may choose to play shot clock. But what New London absolutely has to do first is sound defense and rebound. Take care of the best. No more second chances. West Haven is in a fascinating spot. I think they go for a two.
And then, I don't think they're gonna pressure. I think they're gonna drop back, because they all have a full shot clock. I would make New London try to score. If you play that out, it's still a three possession game. What New London cannot do here is give up an open look three. If West Haven's gonna score, you gotta make them get it in the basket area. Tillman, the senior guard.
swing they'll give that shot he wanted it instead wild shot no good and Warren tipped it. Cornish will call a timeout with 1-12. Part one yes defend the rim rebound take care of the basketball settle things down things a little unrest out there coach Cornish wants to call timeout. Now with a
So Griswold, who has down 10 at the end of three, has cut it to one in the final seconds of their quarterfinal game. That would be their semifinal game coming up. They make the semifinals. It's their quarterfinal game. I'm out of sorts now. You know why? Because I was ready to explain a point to you. No, I got you. I understand. Or the audience. I know the points. Explain to the audience. Four is a huge number. It's a two possession game. Yes, it is.
So I think West Haven is going to try to pressure and trap. And then I think they got a foul, because I don't think they can be down four with 30 seconds left or 40 seconds left in the game. Still one to give. Right. So I think you're going to see pressure, and then the foul. They can't give up the layup. What'll be interesting is if New London gets the layup,
Do they take it, or do they try to run the entire clock? Oh, I would attack it. I would attack it. If it's giving you there, and you've got numbers, and you beat the pressure, I would attack the rim. I mean, New London, Casey, you know, I mean, and Coach Cornish and his teams, I mean, they don't do very well with the game in a cooler. You know, I mean, they're better once you beat that pressure. If you can go get the rim with Phillips, you can go get the rim with Robinson, go get it.
It's always been Dave style of play. Four guards, well three guards McKelvin and Baudette. Hall passes it off to Robinson. Robinson breaks pressure. Here comes the double team. Robinson nifty with the basketball. They haven't fouled them yet. There comes another double and there's the foul.
Good job because that foul resets the shot clock and it's only the fourth. So now New London, now they have to come out and foul New London with 35 seconds on the shot clock. So get it into a free throw shooter's hands here. Which I think they're gonna try to get it to Robinson or Phillips. And a double's coming. Robinson will inbound.
And a timeout, Whalers, as the immediate pass was not there on the inbound. Good ballgame here at New London High School, the way it should be. Four to final action.
Ladies and gentlemen, the Griswold Wolverines have punched their ticket to the semifinals with a buzzer beater. A buzzer beating win for the Griswold Wolverines. The division two champions of the ECC are in the semifinals of division four. Congratulations.
Wow, we've got teams all over the place in the semifinals right now. This league has fared extremely well. I want to put it in perspective, if New London can hold on.
There's St. Bernard's in the Division 1 semis. There would be New London and NFA playing each other in the Division 2 semis, guaranteeing a final spot. There would be Fitch in the Division 3 semis, Grizzled in the Division 4 semis, and Old Lime and Grasso Tech, who are ECC adjacent. They're local teams. They are game day teams. They're in a semifinal already, guaranteeing a final.
And the girls we already said have three or four in class M. The ECC has acquitted itself well, but New London has to hold on here to guarantee that semifinal benefit. Finish the job if you're New London. Good time out by Robinson. A little out of sorts on the inbounds. Talk it over. A little different look this time on the inbounds for New London. They're going to give Bidet available for a lob as well as the bigger screen. The little screen from Hall didn't free anybody up. So there's Bidet with a bigger screen.
And they go long to Hall. Here comes the pressure. Pick the dribble up. And a steal. No man's land. And they're going to get a foul on the perimeter, which will give two shots to West Haven. And if they can make both and pressure, it brings it down to a one point game. And they no longer have to foul. God, I think I want the ball in Robinson's hand on the inbounds or Phillips. Maybe have Hall be the trigger man. Get JJ the rock. Let him do his thing.
Ja'Kai Little, sophomore from West Haven will shoot two. Now, New England's got a rebound too off this second one if West Haven puts anybody in. I think they're going to set up pressure and not try for the offensive rebound. First one no good. Guarantees that it remains the full one possession. Such a huge miss at this juncture of the game, 48 seconds left to go.
Morris has had a, I'm sorry, Littles had a fantastic ball game. Misses them both. McKelvin with the rebound, he's tied up. Possession arrow favors New London. But a big tie up for Westhaven because it flips the script, flips the arrow. Who wants to win the game, that's what it's about right now. 45 seconds for point eight, it is winning time. McKelvin to inbound.
Baudette, long pass, tipped. Swinging it around, three pointer up, no good. Offensive rebound, step in, another three from Little, is good! 44-43 and it's a one point game. London doing everything in their power to give this game away in the last 30 seconds.
Wow. Second, third chance scoring opportunities off the inbounds. Off the turnover. West Haven sticking to it, Casey. The sophomore missed both free throws. No bigger shot in the game than that one. Dramatically alters all of the strategy. And give credit to Tillman for finding the open man. Because now, it is a, not only is it a one possession game, it is a one possession game where you cannot
be put into two possessions if you foul. So, New London will be in the bonus. I mean, it's gonna be interesting what West Haven does. Obviously, they're gonna have to foul if they can't get the turnover. Alright, so they're gonna have to put someone at the line. But New London's gotta break pressure first.
And they have not done that yet. Well, I was going to show you get the ball across half court right now. I mean, it's struggled the last two or three times inbound the basketball twice here on the side. And then once there on the off the miss. But that tried the cross court pass that against nine teams out of 10 is successful. But the length of West Haven is unique that way. And that ball was tipped. It wouldn't have been. There's no other team that would have tipped that ball. That was like you said, Ogletree fouled out. Roman comes in. Roman's got the length. You lose nothing there.
There's a wire job here. And if I were Dave Cornish, my stomach is in Rolaids, Pepsi. I got a little Zantac action. The coach is on the floor, huh? But they put three minutes back on the clock. What happened here?
can't be right. 28.7 seconds should be the time. I don't I hope they I don't know if they know that because the clock says three minutes right now now it's 301. Are they gonna keep the time on the floor what are they gonna do? They're working it's at 30 seconds now they're working it down to the to the way
30 seconds on the clock. Okay 30 seconds is what they put back on the clock. Yeah so they went to three minutes so they could move the decimal over. 30 seconds McKelvin will inbound. I think they're trying to work it out right now. I don't know that they can get it to 29.8 unless they do it manually. 28.7 is what Mike DeMauro had. 28.7 they can't get it to that manually? Come on here now.
That's a whole second and that's 1.3 seconds. They're not going to do it. McKelvin can inbound. He can run the floor and he knows it. He gets it to Phillips. Phillips breaks the pressure. Hooks up his dribble. Finds Bedek. Back to Phillips. New London ball, 16 seconds. They didn't foul or they tried to. Phillips is calling for it. He's showing a ref his arm.
You've got to think right now, as an official, if the kid's getting bumped, there's an effort to foul. Roman back into the game. 16 seconds right now. New London's got to inbound it, and then not just possess it and allow the double to come, because the possession arrow favors West Haven. They've got to inbound it and get it into a place where they can get fouled. So they've got to try to inbound it long here, I think.
They're giving the inbound to Bidette, now they're not. Robinson, inbound. And we got a foul on the floor against Roman. And so that'll put New London at the line to shoot two.
No bigger free throws here because great job by Westhaven no time comes off the clock. It means Westhaven is going to have 16 seconds to tie or win this game depending on the free throws from Troy McKelvin Jr. Big shots for a sophomore. Man my heart is. Yeah it's what a basketball game.
It'll be interesting if New London misses, if they pressure at all, or if they're going to run, you know, get back in the gate. 16 seconds remaining, two for McKelvin. First one is good. This one's big, partner. He makes this one, it guarantees
They can't lose on a regulation shot without something funky happening. Warren checks into the game. If he misses, West Haven can tie or win on a buzzer beat. One more for Troy McKelvin Jr.
It is up, and it is good. Whalers by three. 16 seconds remaining. Tillman with the basketball, Robinson on him. Westhaven needs a three-two tie. No good. Bidet with a foul. So with 1.7 remaining, Westhaven will go to the line to shoot two, but they're gonna have to miss the second one.
Yeah, try to make the first one, miss the second one. Whalers had a chance, if they could've secured that rebound, we'd be done. So back to the line, Ja'Kai Little, who made the big three, but missed two free throws earlier. No two free throws bigger than this one, he's gonna have to make the first one and miss the second.
Little at the line with big free throws. First one rattles home. Philistin into the game, they're gonna put maximum size as they know Little has to try to intentionally miss the free throw. Westhaven down two, 1.7.
Ja'Kai Little, the sophomore, needs the miss. The Blue Devils need the rebound. The miss. And a lane violation, it looks like, against West Haven. No shot, 1.7, Whalers will inbound.
McKelvin will inbound. They can throw it long with 1.7. They have to get this inbounds, however. Here we go. 1.7 away from a semifinal trip to take on conference rival NFA.
And the officials are talking it over. And I don't know what's going on. More problems with the crowd, it looks like. Looks like they're escorting some folks out of the building. McKelvin will inbound with 1.7 remaining.
Here we go, can the Wailers punch their ticket to the semifinal against NFA? And they're sending both teams back to their benches until we can figure this out.
While they figure this out, we're going to take a quick break. We'll be right back. You're watching Game Day live on the Day.com. Game Day is brought to you by Waterford Dental Health. Gear up for Game Day with a winning smile from Waterford Dental Health. Located in Waterford, we're your go-to for top-notch dental care in a relaxed, friendly setting. Whether you need a routine checkup, a cosmetic boost or advanced treatment, our experienced team has you covered. Enjoy the game with confidence and comfort.
Schedule your appointment today. Waterford Dental Health, where your smile is our top priority. Visit us online or call now to book. 1.7 seconds remaining. Whalers have the basketball. They merely need to inbound and maintain possession. Westhaven's gonna have to try to foul.
Mike what was going on that was causing the delay? They're checking the book to see if the kid's foul right there was his fourth or his fifth. Alright so they're working to find out if the foul that occurred on the after the miss was his fourth or his fifth. It appears that they have it all figured out and maybe we can finish this thing here finally.
So McKelvin to inbound. And I guess that was his fifth because coming into the game is Justice Richardson. A lot to go through, a lot of time here to try to get this inbound. McKelvin will do it. He can throw it long and risk the pick off. He does, up in the air it goes. Good if it goes.
but a travel beforehand, and that's gonna be your ballgame. The New London High School Whalers. Barring, if the officials don't put time back on the clock, the travel ends it, and the Whalers have punched their ticket to the semifinals, where they'll take on NFA. Unless, of course, they put time back on the clock. If they do,
New London simply needs to inbound it again. We'll find out here in a moment. We're gonna wait for the official, official, official, but it appears like they're saying time is done.
Or not, because the players haven't left the floor yet. Looks like they're putting time back on the clock. 0.7 being put back on the clock.
So the Whalers simply need to inbound. Technically .7 is not enough to catch, turn and shoot. So all they have to do is inbound it deep enough and this game will be over. How do you turn 1.7 seconds into 25 minutes? This is how.
So 1.7 seconds remaining. As soon as they allow the inbounds to happen, the Whalers simply need to have someone touch it and the clock should run out. So McKelvin will inbound. McKelvin will inbound it right in front of his bench.
Again, shouldn't be enough time for a catch and shoot, so all it needs to be is touched and not shot towards the basket. I have no idea what just happened. Turnover, yes, because McKelvin threw it off his man, off the Blue Devil, but I don't understand why
So now that does allow a lob. We're not done yet. West Haven can get a lob. And if West Haven finds a way to tie this game, this place will literally come undone. Not the building, but the people within it.
So they're gonna put Baudette on the basketball. And everyone else has to guard. It should only be a tap, it should not be able to be a catch and shoot. Bellamy inbounds for Westhaven. Now Tillman will inbound for Westhaven.
This is like the Hail Mary in football. If you're new London, just knock it down. Knock it away. Tillman, inbound. Shot is up, it's no good. The Wailers have held on in an incredibly weird, ugly, and sloppy finish. But 46-44, they are going to the semifinals to take on NFA on Tuesday, which means
St. Bernard's is in the division one semis. New London and NFA are in the division two semis. Fitch is in the division three semis. Griswold is in the division four semis.
Stonington, Windham, and Bacon Academy girls are in the class M semis. And Grasso Tech and Old Lime are in the division five semis. A lot of ECC teams and a lot of locals looking to punch tickets come Monday and Tuesday, but we are guaranteed an ECC team in the division two finals and in the class M finals. An outstanding, outstanding effort from the ECC. The Sports Doctor.
We'll have the Roberto's Log Cabin player of the game day, as well as coach Dave Cornish. Of course, Roberto's our longtime sponsor. They are located in the woods of Lebanon. The Log Cabin, family owned and operated. They got great menu, wings. They got a great bar, great drinks. Go see Rob and his crew. Let them know that game day sent you. You definitely will not go wrong eating at Roberto's Log Cabin. So the sports doctor has our player of the game day and coach Cornish, sports doctor.
He's our Roberto's log cabin player of the game tonight, Jameer Hall. Take this shirt down to Roberto's in Lebanon, free plate of wings for your family and friends. Listen.
Next man up is the mentality of this team. Three big three-pointers and two charges. What was your mindset coming off the bench tonight? Honestly, I know all my seniors, we've been hooping forever. This could have been their last game. I'm not going home like this. I'm not going home. Let's go. Now, these games aren't easy, are they? And it takes a team effort out there.
When things got hard and you had to rise up and hit that big three, was there no thinking involved, just catch and shoot or what? No thinking, you can't think, you gotta just let it go. We practice hard every day, we gotta go in there, we get our reps in. I trust myself, come on. Yeah, great job out there tonight, I don't know if you know or not, but NFA has won on the other side, so you're gonna see them for the fourth time this year.
Altona fan Jeff Brown we on the way, but I said all right coach Coach coach. How did you guys find a way to win this game with always going seven points in the fourth quarter? defense Defense that was it. That's all I can say defense. Oh, you're getting these toughness and defense you're getting these games close games Trusting your kids and trusting the guys out there. I mean, that's what it takes to win a championship. Is it not? Oh
Oh, yeah, you gotta win close games because every team like I said from the quarterfinals on is good So you're gonna get into these kind of games So you got to be ready for you were worried about this West Haven team a little bit you and I had talked and you said you know I throw the records out they beat Glastonbury. This was a tough test for you guys. Oh, yeah, absolutely. It was everything is advertised you saw it We saw every minute of it coach, you know
We'll talk about this league real quick. I mean, you guys are gonna face NFA in the semifinal. They won tonight. You're gonna see NFA for the fourth time. What does that mean, not only for NFA New London, but what does it mean for the ECC? The ECC's done a phenomenal job representing itself in this tournament. I'm happy for them, but one of us is gonna go home, and one of us is going to the championship. But I know my guys are gonna be up for the task. No matter if it's the fourth time, fifth time, sixth time, doesn't matter. My guys are gonna be ready.
Great job tonight, Dave. You're a game away from a state championship. I'm sure one of the goals that you had at the beginning of the season when you first came into London. Oh, absolutely. That was the goal to bring it back to this city. This is my city. I want to represent the right way. Hey, KC, the Whalers tonight in fashion on game day. Thank you very much, Sports Doctor. Well, we'll be with you Monday and Tuesday for semifinal action as long as we are granted permission, and we believe we will be.
We are very excited about whatever we can bring you Monday and Tuesday, but the ECC so well represented as well as Eastern Connecticut in general. So many teams in the semis and heading to the finals will be at least a handful of ECC teams and hey, I said the knock on New London. Yeah, they didn't know how to win the close ones. Yeah, they won this one.
but I would suggest this was not a blueprint for how to close out a basketball team. No, this is a recipe for kind of hang on a little bit. And West Haven's a good team, but up 44 to 40, New London made it way too interesting, made it way harder on themselves with turnovers and some sloppy play than it had to be. And you're going to find some of these other kids who didn't step up tonight are going to have to step up in order for them to deliver a state championship, whether it be the Savon Warren, whether it be
Booboo Phillips, you know, but Jamiro Hall bailed them out with some big threes. They stayed out of foul trouble. Guy stayed on the court. And, you know, here's the other thing, too. You know, Dave told you I came here to win a championship. He was not. He was very candid about that. Well, they are a semifinal victory away from a familiar foe toward heading to the Mohegan Sun with a chance at exactly that. Somebody from the ECC is going to be competing for the Division two championship. I think it's great for the league.
I think all these, Griswold winning tonight, NFA winning tonight, you know, Fitch in the semifinal, obviously St. Bernard's up against a very, very tough East Catholic team who I think beat them this year. St. Bernard beat East Catholic. I'm sorry, St. Bernard beat East Catholic. So, I mean it's, in that division one's loaded. It's gonna be great. It's gonna be a great, great couple of days here. Follow game day Monday, Tuesday. We're gonna be somewhere bringing you all of the action that we can.
For the sports doctor Keith O'Brien and all of the Gameday crew, it's signing off from the John T. Conway Gymnasium. You've been watching Gameday Live on day.com.
you