Hello, everyone, and welcome to your show, Medford Happenings. I am John Petrala, and we're doing a show for and about the city of Medford. The purpose of this program is to give Medford citizens facts and information to help you make informed choices.
First of all, before we start the show, we just want to discuss Veterans Day. And I just want to say, in memory of many, in honor of all, thank you. Your bravery and service will never be forgotten. We thank all veterans.
And now I think we'll move on to some election results from this past election, the local elections in Medford. And I think we're just going to discuss the local elections. We had questions six, seven, and eight. And on question six, which was the fire station, building a new fire station, I think everyone knows that it did not pass.
That was, it's not gonna happen. City of Method, citizens voted it down. Question seven, which was one of the override questions, that passed. The yeses were 14,847, and the noes were 13,304, as you can see on the chart. That was question seven, very close election.
And on question eight, which was another override question, you'll also see the yeses won. It was 14,660. And the noes were 13,518. So both questions were extremely close. I don't want to get into too much about it.
I guess what I'd like to say about it is I don't think the city won either way. I think this question has divided the city. It's kept us divided. There's a lot of people.
I know there was a lot of celebration about, you know, people winning and they're going to get their override and, you know, the schools and everything else. But there's also a lot of people that this is going to affect financially. People are struggling as it is. My personal opinion is this was not the time for the override.
However, it was voted on, a lot of people celebrated, and I just don't really think that anyone wins when you divide the city.
You know, I just think a lot of people are going to really struggle with these new tax increases coming. So that's my opinion. That's all I want to say about it. I just wanted to touch on it briefly. So the fire stations are no. Both overrides passed. And I'm really just hoping, you know, for the people that voted yes, I truly, truly hope
that the new funds that come into the city, I hope that it goes to the schools. I hope that it goes to the roads. Uh, I just want to see the right thing, uh, done with the money. And, um, that's it. That's all we want to talk about as far as the elections go. Um, it's part of method. I think it was something important and, uh, we'll end the discussion right there. And, um,
I think we're going to move on. And the next discussion, time to get on with your show. First of all, we'd like to congratulate all the GBL All-Stars and MVPs from Medford High School. So let's go through the list of names. I apologize if I don't get your name quite right. I'm going to do my best here.
So we have Justin Marino, football MVP. We have some football all-stars. We're going to start with Nathan Brough, Prince Xavier, Darius Weeks, Demi George, Samuel Diarestl, Guy Martins. We're going to go to girls soccer MVP, Josera Cuyate.
A girls soccer all-star, Cecilia Colombo. Boys soccer all-star, Arthur Bragaka. All-star, Michael Park. Cross-country MVP, Emma Beardsley.
Cross-Country All-Star, Isabeli D'Souza-Verrera. Volleyball All-Star, Ella Melchiono. Golf MVP, Emmett Chastain. Golf All-Star, Anthony Madaris. Golf All-Star, Carter Cherone. Golf All-Star, Nathan Tremlett.
and cross-country MVP Adam Lewis. Great job by everyone of these athletes. Congratulations to all of you. We'd also like to take a minute to congratulate Joe Sacco, better known as JoJo in Metfed, on his being named interim head coach of the Boston Bruins.
If anyone can get the Bruins out of their current slump, Joe Sacco is the guy for the job. So best wishes to Joe Joe Sacco and our Boston Bruins. I also want to remind everyone that there's a show on the sideline, Method High School Sports with James Klugisch, and that's on YouTube. And it's a good show, and I highly recommend that you watch it.
And now Method Happenings wants to talk about a lot of great things that are happening in the city of Method. That's the point of the show, so we're going to do some discussions on Method Happenings. The first thing is the Friends of the Method Public Library is holding their holiday book scale on December 7th from 9 to 3 at the Method Public Library.
This is the annual small sale of all holiday themed and giftable items.
All children's books will be available along with puzzles, games, miscellaneous items, and special items like hardcover fiction. Remember, the library also has an eBay store. It is used to sell items that generally do not sell well at their regular sales, but they're still great items. It includes DVD sets, antique books,
and higher priced items. So it'd be nice to check that out as well. A lot of great deals. The next thing happening in Metfid that we'd like to discuss.
is the local arts collaborative, collaborative, sorry, located at 162 Mystic Avenue, Method. We'll be having a holiday shopping event featuring unique gift ideas for family, friends, and this is taking place on Saturday, December 7th from 11 to four. So that's something else, a nice thing to take the family to. A lot of these events we're gonna be talking about
It's great for kids, great for adults. And it's something to do. And there's just a lot of activity going on in Method. Good activity. Also, something that we think is worth it to check out is the books and brews. This is the holiday edition at the Method Brewing Company. That's going to be on Sunday, December 8 at 2 PM.
This is a books and brew pairing with bookends from Winchester, Mass. The tickets for this event or the info is at www.eventbrite.com. That should be a nice time.
And the other thing to keep in mind is the annual Meffitt Police November food drive for non-perishable items is taking place until November 20th. The donation boxes are available at the Meffitt Police Station and our Senior Center. All proceeds go to the Meffitt Senior Center and are handed out Wednesday, November 20th from 11.30 to 1 p.m.
What can I say? What can anyone say? It's a great cause. So, you know, if you can help out, please do so. That is the Medford Food Drive, and you can drop stuff at the Senior Center and the Medford Police Station. And it's non-perishable items. And we appreciate any help you can give them.
The other thing going on at the senior center is what I did was pick up a copy of our place, our time. It's a publication that's put out by the method council on aging. Very informative.
The Method Senior Center, as I think most people are aware, some aren't, is located at 101 Riverside Ave. They also have a calendar of events that they publish every month, and you can find that in the Our Place, Our Time publication. Worth getting. So the annual Thanksgiving dinner is on Thursday, November 21st, from 12 noon to 3 p.m.
And then there's a Letty Paterno holiday party. It's going to take place Friday, December 6th from 12 noon to 3 p.m. And you can enjoy a full-course catered meal by Henry's Catering. You're going to have entertainment provided by the Boston Saxophone Quartet. And also coming up,
at the Senior Center is there's plenty of day trips and getaways, Encore Casinos, one, going to Walmart, the Outback, Townline Bowling and Lunch, some great ones like the North Shore Music Theater or Christmas Carol, the Holiday Pops at the Symphony Hall. And for details on trips and getaways, you can contact the Meffitt Senior Center.
Phone number is 781-396-6010 and you can also visit their website www.methodmask.org slash departments. Just a lot of activity for seniors. Worthwhile to get the publication. The publication is available at plenty of
stores and outlets all throughout the city, local stores, so worth taking a look at. The other thing we really have to mention is because it brings a lot of activity to Meffitt Square.
And that's the upcoming acts for the Chevalier Theater in Meffitt Square. I'm just gonna go through a few of the upcoming shows. And they do bring a lot of activity. Lions Up the Square, and they do a nice job with these shows. So on November 22nd, a drag queen Christmas. December 6th, we have the Indigo Girls.
December 7th is the Jimmy O. Yang show, and that's going to be two shows, one's at 7 and one's at 9.45.
On December 8th, for the kids, the Gazillion Bubble Show, and that's on a Sunday afternoon at 2 p.m. On December 11th, we have the Temptations and the Four Tops, right up my alley. I think I'll be checking that one out. December 12th, Engelbert Humperdinck. December 13th, the Cat and Dave Show.
December 14th is small time murder, I'm sorry, small town murder. December 15th is Macaulay Culkin, Home Alone fame. December 27th, we're gonna have Bob Marley, the comedian. December 31st is Zonagog. Looks like December will bring plenty of activity to Meffitt Square.
And another thing not to forget is Deep Cuts in Method Square. They have a lot of upcoming shows in December. They also have a show the end of November, which is Jackie McKelvey with Justice Cow and Grown Man. December 4, they have a show with Lightheaded, the Ladybug Transistor, and Mark Robinson. December 12 is Christian Death.
December 11th, they have a holiday candle crafting. On December 3rd, they have ceramic stein painting. So that's a few things over at Deep Cuts. There's a lot more shows. I just wanted to mention a few so you're aware of that. Also brings a lot of activity to Method Square.
And now I'd just like to mention a couple of craft fairs that go on every year. These are two local companies. One of them I'm going to mention is Becker Whaling over at Four Good Vibes Gift Shop and Boutique. They have locations in Burlington, Medford, and Kingston. They run virtual craft fairs that specialize in unique handmade gifts. So if you like handmade gifts, Four Good Vibes is for you.
They have a couple of local craft fairs coming up that I wanted to mention. One's at Post 45, the American Legion in Medford. That's the seventh annual craft fair. It's November 17th, 11 a.m. to 3 p.m. And then they have a Four Good Vibes 60 annual holiday craft fair
on Sunday, December 8th, also at the American Legion. And that takes place 11 a.m. to 3 p.m. And great gifts, great holiday gifts, something to check out, another one you can bring the whole family to, and you're going to find a lot of unique stuff there. So please check it out.
And last but not least, as far as small business, I've got to mention Method Soap Company. It's a new company. They were established in 2023. And it's a local success story. What can you say? Their products are made from high-quality ingredients. The packaging is 100% recyclable or biodegradable. They specialize in vegan and all-natural products.
They have cold processed soap.
It's manufactured in small, handmade batches. I want to mention that I use the soap, and I really like it, and I think it's the best. That's all. It's great soap. They do great gift baskets, and they do great gift sets that you can get for the holidays as well. And I'm going to mention it's a lot more than a soap company. I think they have, I don't know, somewhere over 80 products available right now.
event that I want to mention is happening on Saturday, November 23rd from 10 a.m. to 3 p.m. We're going to have the Mary Queen of Peace Christmas stroll. This is at 114 High Street. Everyone knows St. Joseph's Church. It's an event by St. Joseph and St. Francis.
There's no admission fee, and you can just join them for a Christmas stroll. There's two floors of shopping. There's over 30 vendors for holiday shopping. They're going to have door prizes, raffles, crafts, bake sale, games, food.
So please be sure to check it out. It'll be a lot of fun. And once again, a lot of great gifts. You know, Method Happenings, we're going to be promoting a lot of local businesses.
There's a lot of local events that go on in the city. We're just giving you a few today. We'll be doing another show to keep everyone updated on what's going on. There really is a tremendous amount of activities that take place. You know, and most of it is all, it's good stuff, great for the families, a lot of activities, you know, a lot of events.
So, you know, it's good to stay local. A lot of great restaurants in Method now. I don't have to go into that. We will be doing a show on restaurants. That'll be coming up. The other thing I...
I wanted to mention was I want to thank, you know, we're a fairly new show. You know, we're trying to do a lot of different things here. But, you know, we've gotten some good feedback. I want to thank, there's a few people that,
have sent us positive emails. We've been contacted by a few people, quite a few people, actually, that are looking to do shows, to get on the show. And I think we're going to have a lot of fun. We're new at this. I think we're putting on something that's valuable to the city.
So that's about it for the show today. And I just want to thank again everyone that's been watching. And I want to thank the people that have taken the time to write in. We see some nice texts. So thank you all. You will be able to see a replay of this show on Method Community Media.
medfordtv.org, and you can visit us on Facebook and YouTube, Medford Happenings. For more information about our future program, you can visit the Medford Community Network at
MCN02155.com. For Method Happenings, I'm John Petrella. Thank you for watching, and stay informed.