Are we recording and ready to go? Okay. Welcome everybody. Welcome back to Bistro 489. I'm going to read the meeting notice and then we'll call the roll. Please be advised that there will be a full committee meeting of the Medford Building Committee in person at Bistro 489 in Medford being held via
The meeting can be viewed live on Metro Public's YouTube channel through Metro Community Media, on your local cable channel, which is broadcast 98 or 22, and Verizon channel 43.5 or 47. The meeting will be recorded. Participants can log or call in by using the following Zoom link. Meeting ID is 946-5091-2152. I will call the roll.
Jenny grant here as a. Dr. Lucy here, Marta here. Let me brown here. 1st, it doesn't here. Maria Dorsey. Brian Miller here. Tracy team here. Emily Lazaro. Yeah, Nicole. Here.
Joe Cohen. Here. Ken Lord. Here. Bob Dickinson. Here. Fiona Maxwell. Here. Hope Giselli. Here. Chad Mallett. Here. Lori Hodgson. Here. John McLaughlin. Here. Paul Rousseau. Here. Philip Santos. Here.
Lisa Miller here and Dr. Kim Talbot here. So we have 13 present, 2 absent. So we have a quorum and we're here. Thank you all for being here tonight. We have some preliminary business to take care of and then the vast majority of the discussion
But before we do that, the next thing on the agenda is the approval of the August 11th school building committee meeting minutes. Is there a motion to approve? Motion to approve. Motion to approve by Member Okade. Second. Second by Dr. Galussi. Okay, I will call the roll. Jenny Graham. Yes. Mayor Longo. Yes. Dr. Galussi. Yes. Marta Cabral. Yes. Libby Brown. Yes. Marissa Desmond. Yes. Maria Dorsey is absent.
Abstain. Emily Lozaro. Yes. Nicole Morrell, absent. She's on her way. Carol Pottinger. Yes. Chris Prizer. Yes. Joan Bowen. Yes. Ken Lord. 12 in the affirmative, zero in the negative, two
Extension to ask. Oh, no, I'm sorry. 11 in the affirmative 0, the negative 2 extension to absent. It's a lost track. Okay, I remember 3.
We actually are welcoming 2 new members to the building committee. So, as you all know, Dr. Cushing has taken a job in Beverly as the superintendent of schools there. He was a voting member of the committee and he has been replaced by Ken Lord, who has joined MedBird as the chief operating officer. And Dr. Kim Talbot has also joined the team. She is our
introduce yourselves at all, and kind of have like wheels of experience in this space. So it might be nice for everyone to hear. Sure. So this is a little deja vu. So it's been really interesting for me. I'm excited to participate in this project. I've been involved in technology for over 30 years.
Welcome both of you. If there's anything that happens along the way and you're like, what are you all talking about? Please feel free to stop us and ask because we're happy to answer. So welcome and if there's things you need, just let me know. I'll figure out how to get you what you need about anything that's happened so far. Tracy, can you hear me okay?
I can hear jenny okay, but I could not hear can and doctor Talbot at all. So, everyone just use your teacher voice and let's see how it goes Tracy just keep us. Posted if you are having a hard time hearing. Okay, we'll do Thank you. Item number 4 is approval of the August 2025 voice.
So I'm going to turn that over to Matt. You would like to walk us through what's here? Yeah, so this is just our third invoice.
of our OPM services for the month of August. It's our agreed compound sum of $25,000. We don't have any additional sub consultants or other reimbursement costs at this point. It's very straightforward. Any questions for Ken? Hi, is there a motion to approve the invoice?
Motion to approve by Ken, seconded by Luke. I will call the roll. Jenny Graham? Yes. Mayor Longo Kern? Yes. Dr. Galussi? Yes. Marta Cabral? We're absent for now. Libby Brown? Yes. Marissa Desmond? Yes. Maria Dorsey?
Thank you. Brian Hilliard. Yes. Tracy Keene. Yes. Emily Lazaro. Yes. Nicole Morrell. Still on her way. Aaron Olopade. Yes. Luke Pricer. Yes. Joan Bowen. Yes. Ken Lord. Yes. So that is 13 in the affirmative, two absent. Motion passes.
Okay, so we're going to move on to the meat of the meeting and hopefully it will be a meeting by the time we're done here. As you all know, we got 4 proposals from designers and the goal for tonight is for myself, for the mayor and for Dr. Pelosi to really hear from all of you about your impressions. We are not ranking. We cannot rank.
that. All of these four folks are watching us either now or in the future and the MSBA is really explicit about not wanting us to be talking in terms of ranking favorites etc. So what we tried to do was give you all a set of questions to think about
What I would like for us to just go 1 proposal at a time and go through these questions. I think we're really interested in hearing from all of you. We are sensitive to the fact that we are 3 of 13 votes. So we have our work cut out for us when we go to designer selection next week. However. You know, there's a lot of collective experience at this table and we want to hear from.
From all of you from from your lenses, from your impressions of the proposals that were shared and that will help us. Get ready for that for that meeting and there's 2 meetings. 1 is. Where we will talk about all of the proposals and then the 2nd meeting where there will be.
So, the questions that we did want to talk about with all of you, and I'm thinking to just take them one at a time so that we give everybody equal shape.
What did you like about the proposal compared to others? What stuck out as advantageous? What did you dislike about a particular proposal as compared to others? What did you view as being less than advantageous? And then what questions would you have for this applicant about their proposal? So those are the three questions. We can maybe just start. Does anyone have a proposal they want to start with that they feel very strongly about, Luke?
Okay, hold on, hold on. We're going to do one question at a time so that everybody can stick with us. Okay. So let's everyone has DLR's proposal. Okay. So this proposal is from DLR in collaboration
And then, Will, can you keep track of who is raising their hand online? It's a little hard for us to see. I'll leave the questions up. Okay. What did we like about this?
Letty, I like that they have experience working together. I recently had a large project that took it. And I think that Letty shows really strong design skills. So I think that's an example of a successful team. Great. Any else? Paul? I like that they were pretty explicit in their
Any questions online? Well,
Okay. What did you dislike about the DLR proposal as compared to others? Or what did you view as being less advantageous or less than advantageous? Yep.
I'm trying to continue to speak to that. Their experience is spread across the country, and also even to the U.S. territories, which I felt was less advantageous. I also
What's the advantage of playing your team? It's not very high.
I've seen that people are having a hard time hearing us. So Emily, so far, the comments in the less advantageous category are that this group has light on experience with MSBA, that they seem to have a relatively large headcount.
And that there are two firms in the mix with which to coordinate about the design. That's what we've covered so far. Just for those of you trying to listen here. Sure. Yeah.
speak loudly for the crowd. I meant to speak up earlier, but then I got distracted looking at the paper. But I actually think the fact that it's two firms is actually something that could be seen as advantageous. You have a lot of different voices, and you get to take the expertise of each of those firms and leave behind the things that the firms aren't as good at. So I think looking at them as one entity, it's not on us to figure out
There's going to like, who's going to be in charge of this part of design? Who's going to be in charge of that part of the design? Having worked on both sides of projects where I've been either the architect of record or the design architect, all of this would be hammered out between two firms in advance. Skipping ahead a little bit.
Like, how are they going to handle these things? You know, they have extensive experience working together already, which leads me to believe that they already have this process in their minds of how they're going to handle it. And so I think it is actually very advantageous to take a firm that's really rooted in kind of the programming and analysis and then a firm that's really rooted in
really good design and bringing them together to create one super team. Thanks, Marissa. Will, is there anybody online who's got their hand up? All the members of the, oh, oh. Maria Dorsey. Maria? Hi. From an educational angle, I had the feeling that this group, their focus was more on
CTE than on the classrooms, as opposed to the other groups. A lot of them, the others were either on equal footing or had a strong sense of what the needs of the classroom are with CTE combined. This one, I felt that they were, they had a leaning, more leaning towards the shops. So that was just my impression on what I read. Thanks, Maria. Is anybody else online?
Anybody else? Brian? I think one of the things I feel is a little bit advantageous is that there are candidates that maybe we want to get this done. So a little bit of a problem there that we don't know how it turned out and how that can manifest itself. So for those of you online, the comment was that they're like sort of
prime example for us is still a work in progress, and it's not yet complete. So we don't know how it turned out. Luke? When I looked at all the consultants, I didn't find a library consultant. I didn't find a lab consultant. I didn't find a landscape consultant.
Is that typical, Matt and Jen? Can you talk a little bit about what is typical in terms of like how teams get put together? So they need to provide consultants that are listed up in the RFS. We have a very specific set of consultants that we're expecting to see.
or not a pool consultant is required or not. It's not something that the asset was required. They can certainly include one. So I can think of maybe one where the parent pool consultant and the resident pool consultant have. So that's typically, and I can pull up the sub-consultant spreadsheet of where I found everybody just to make sure that they get involved.
I don't think they did. Some of them are maybe a little hard to find because of some of the names. But I'll take a look and see what it would be. Sometimes they have in-house experience, so they look to themselves for those categories. Sometimes that makes it a little less clear.
example. So every question. So it sounds like the teams will not necessarily look at because of how they come together. Other not advantageous things.
Right. Also, a lot of the projects that they're looking at. Questions?
So just so you know, this is the spreadsheet that required to fill up the MSBA. This is all of their consultants, all of the board members. So you can see them here. So yeah, they did have structural landscaping. They did have the CT consultants.
I did have a question. Or maybe for for Lucy and her team. I feel like. What I hear about vocational is that.
What we think of as vocational in Massachusetts is quite different than what vocational looks like in other places in the country. Can you respond to that from a programming perspective?
Yes, and I think that we're in a unique situation where we are a comprehensive high school. We're not a single vocational school, so all of our programs are Chapter 74, which means that there are requirements and regulations pertaining to content that we provide our students, the number of hours that they have in shop, as well as their academics, and then the number of hours that they are doing in the industry fields, whatever that may be, particular to the shop.
And I know that we are to expand our programming and that some of the vocational programming standards have recently been increased. A lot of what I would just say that like from the lens of me reviewing a lot of these proposals would be like looking at that experience that a firm does have with the CTE programming.
that is aligned and parallel to Medford, not a standalone CTE school, but one that's comprehensive, that at this time has full Chapter 74 shops, and one sort of space that is unique and brings with it a lot of flexibility. Do you need more detail? No, I'm good, thank you. I just wanted to
not being in that world understand. Is it the same everywhere or is it different? So thank you. I also would say that maybe also for me, I do not have a lot of MSBA experience coming into this project. So I think for someone like me reading these proposals, I found it very difficult to get a true understanding from the visuals.
on the clarity of the image, the detail or lack of detail. It was really hard for me to get a true understanding as to what the vision was for the proposals.
Okay.
Questions? Libby? I think I'd ask just how frequently do they expect to be physically present in Boston for those who are not local? So are they flying in or doing remote meetings? Just how often are they here in person? That's right, this was the team that was not terribly local, is that right? Yeah, Libby's local. DLR has some of them are local in Boston, but some are not.
What other questions would we have for DLR? Okay. Any last? Brian?
So for those of you at home wanting some more information on their cluster design concept. Other questions for DLR?
I'm going to talk about Perkinsville next. What did we like about Perkinsville? Luke?
I like that they included a estimated
I like that they try to
of central space in between the addition renovating space today, the first kind of slideshow, trying to incorporate the idea that this is an opportunity for the community to be involved. That's as well as outdoor learning spaces. We're learning a lot now that there's a huge benefit to having that available space for students and teachers to kind of get outside the classroom from time to time. So to be able to incorporate that and have that be used as a shared space with the community. Other likes? Paul?
Overall, I think the students are very clear, the graphics are very clear, and this gives me hope for and faith for our team, for how we move forward as a student community. And I just think that there's some very clarity in the fact that
they actually are going to be able to work on our project of splitting wood in Salem. And so some of the work I think is done both, but the team doing the work in the database is our project. Thanks, Lori. I also like the idea that we take into account interdisciplinary learning. That's not just CTE, but
So, for those of you online so far, we, we've heard. The likes include experience working with left field that Salem high school. Is ongoing and ahead of us that they took a stab at a timeline.
That they're prioritizing community space, outdoor learning, geothermal. Messaging was quite clear. They are not splitting their team with other projects like Salem and they are focused on interdisciplinary learning. Just so that you, in case you all were having a hard time hearing. Also. Full consultants.
Yeah, when when we were we were doing the tour, there were lots of questions about those kinds of things. And we really tried to paint a picture for everybody who is here that
There are some interesting spaces in this building that. We should be looking at to say, is this worth preserving or. Is it not for some reason, but that that was 1 of the spaces we talked about wanting explicitly to be able to evaluate. Does it stay does it goes what happens. That also included the gym because it's quite big.
Well, in terms of how they were trying to serve. Hey, what was less advantageous. Answer that question.
Okay. Things that seem.
There aren't a lot of seats. And their team also didn't seem to have lots of vocational experience. Am I remembering that correctly?
Oh, sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry. I'm so sorry.
I mean, not the same things, obviously, but like the same, just like not the same stuff that you don't necessarily need in a regular classroom, like that type of experience. This one, their experience spans beyond public schools and beyond high schools. And while it might, I have a similar question to you,
strictly educational spaces. To me, I would be very curious to see how does that experience match up to what we need here in Medford with a very unique site and the possibilities of being able to do something
Other things we thought were less advantageous. Okay, what questions do you have for this firm? Share questions for all of us.
renovating Jibsville, CTE, or anything else for that matter, to all the ones that experience some sort of solar, whether that's solar, public parking lot, buildings, to the components of whatever project we choose. Other questions?
Um, they, in their, in kind of all their designs, they don't clarify what their expectations are. I know that they kind of discuss interdisciplinarity, collaboration, CT, pre-K, innovation sections on what design plans, but they don't actually clarify if they want that to be built in an adjacent building, in the building, what their thinking is with that. So it's like, it's a clarity on what their vision would be and how that kind of plays into what we're looking for, which is probably the best prospective program. So they clarify everything else.
Other questions? Okay. Two down, two to go. I'm going to do AI3 next. Happens to be one right in front of me.
OK, what did we find advantageous about AI3? Ken? If I count it correctly, it sounded like it had six CTE schools in the last 12 years, having in-house CTE experts. Great. I'd also like to throw in part of the idea that it's taking up a lot of space. I did.
We can dream, right?
I just am really in love with the use of wood inside the building.
So I think that's one of the designs. We're trying to kind of lay it all at the same level. But I think this one, I think it would be an exciting opportunity to use multi-level construction builds, either for the additional, like additional renovations or for the construction. So I think it's a very interesting way to kind of consider what the vision would look like and how we can use multi-level. I don't know. I don't know if the firm decided on 75% of the time. I'm sure it's the majority.
to be a smaller consulting team locally. It's possible that they're going to be a part of the integral project. So I thought that was a good idea. They're task-oriented. You have to work with a complex group. It's important.
So during this fall, a large number of students
Like us, it's a very large plot. It's 40 acres by 270 acres. And if you looked at the pictures of these various high schools, you can see the aesthetics vary quite a lot. So the very key will be executing the stock.
Watertown is almost completed by the beginning of the spring. There are schools in that area that are open to it. I'm sure it's an opportunity to celebrate the high school as a large CTE program.
I would say what I think is very advantageous about AI3 is that, as you mentioned previously, during the tour, I felt like this proposal captured a lot of what we have said in our profile, as well as what's mentioned on the tour. So they were very specific to call out some details about how we want to make sure we have a collaborative space for teachers and staff.
how different options for how the learning environment can be staffed while maintaining some of these spaces and how they can be creative to Aaron's point about using the scope of our land. I just felt like they were listening and really specifically targeting their examples to the specifics of it, right down to even like the community outreach and some of the local
The events going to, I just, I just probably. For those of you online, I'm going to give you a quick rundown of what has been said if you all can hear me. Okay. Thumbs up. Okay. So, here's the list that I've captured. They've done 60 projects. They have an in house CTE expert. They had creative ideas around underground parking.
At a separate aquatic center, they've identified bids that are under budget, which is exciting. Their aesthetic design appeals to more than 1 person in the room. They, they sort of worked with our on the hill. Idea rather than trying to flatten it. As well as the founder being directly involved in the project.
So, hopefully less tension and more cohesion on the team. They have worked with left field before. The Watertown building that's set to open in the spring is a net zero building. And that they were very clearly listening to the tour and the kinds of things that we were talking about that were important. Like an expedited timeline. And the.
overall their, you know, clear commitment to public input. So that's what's been going on here in case you all have been having a hard time hearing us. Are there any likes from the group on the phone that you wanted to share?
I see a comment from Maria. They have a strong focus on integrating CTE in the classroom. Thanks, Maria. Jenny, this is Tracy. I just listed, because you may have already gone through this, but I listed four questions that I think should be asked to each consultant, and I just dropped them in the chat. Okay, great. I will grab those out at the end.
Um, were there things that we saw about this presentation that were. Not advantageous or such. Fairly diverse and diversifying and. The people on the team, I didn't see very much diversity in the group, which is always a concern to me. Obviously.
Other things that were not advantageous.
This is a little bit personal, but I think just compared to other firms, their designs just feel a little bit leaning towards an online-free design. I think it's something that was over-elevated towards, I know, not higher education, but you know, 9 through 12, as opposed to younger children. So that was just to make a sense. Thank you. Flash that out a little bit.
Colors, just materials, chaos. When you get to high school level, it's just a personal opinion. And sometimes things skew a little bit too far. Fun and silly, and that's better for kids. Other, not advantageous.
For those of you on the phone, the two that came up is that the team is not very diverse in its composition, and then that the design leans towards younger children rather than towards young adults and almost adults, nearly adults, which gives me a little bit of a heart attack personally with two kids in this building now. Okay, what questions would we have for AI?
I have a question just to say, maybe the way they structure their team, but they're a person they call project manager, so they have 25% of their time available for the project. Now they have other people that have more, so it might just be that that person isn't doing the same manager job that someone else is, but I just wanted to be very clear about this requirement. If someone's looking at 25%, that means that those tasks are being done by someone else. Okay. Other questions?
Any other questions? As I'm looking at them, so the smaller hill design compared to the other two, the amount of space in there for student learning in general, seems visually smaller than the other two suggestive designs. So I'm trying to understand where the space is going a little bit. It's the first and second design. Oh, it's how it is. OK. I understand.
Thank you, guys. OK, cool. Thank you. I retract my question. Yeah, they have more stories, too.
Yeah, and I do think, you know, whoever works with us,
thing that this other vendor did and tell us about sort of that. So I think that's a good point. Yeah, they might and they might not. I mean, there's, there's many reasons to rule things out on the site, like, you know, in terms of timing, landscape, ledge, and all the other things that could be going on that they just may have some
There are questions for, were we talking about AI3? I had a question that was for everybody. And it was basically, nobody in any of their thoughts thought about addressing the entry, the traffic entry, everybody just making it one driveway. I know that that was like a big thing that we all talked about already. So I'd like a question.
It was like a lot to take all of this in and be like, ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh. Now, which one am I in? Where is it? And all the pieces and parts were hard to keep track of. So. An additional positive thing was that the driveway, all of that, is incredibly long and vast. I think that's a helpful factor.
Yeah, yeah, I mean, they all are being on site. Oh, so just like one way for everybody. Everybody wants to get into the road. But I think the like, road coming. Yeah. Right. The other questions about AI is great.
And number four, SMMA. What did we like? Well, I really like that they had a call on solar and hybrid circuits. Which I didn't see.
It felt like a really cohesive proposal, like all of the parts were cohesive with the other parts.
I hope the choice of agency is smart because that's what our master plan would say. It's a landscape architect, but for what I want. Right. I appreciate the fact that the concepts are still real.
carry a lot of weight with it. So it's just a conversation going on. I like the concept of free and open responses. It's getting things going. It's a lot to work through. Specific and generic at the same time. It's information.
I think the other side of that for someone like me, who doesn't have an architect background, an engineering, design background, I was wanting just a little bit more detail as to where this is headed. So I guess that's a double-edged sword, I would say. Honestly, I think some of it is just a past experience, but you know that it does end up in theory.
It's a long process, so this is what you have to do. Their likes. I like that they had a lot of disabled projects at a wide range of price points.
of discovery, it's like this growing experiential learning opportunity. So the whole, again, they kind of try to incorporate different levels. The building kind of rises as you go from the main entrance, the level going to where the teacher's currently sits. And the whole building's supposed to kind of be this movement throughout the whole. I think it's a really interesting way to kind of incorporate what we want to accomplish as educators. I really like the,
side cut view on the bottom. Because also really like just gave so much information. You know, we have flooding problems. Thank you. You know, the guy. Any more lights?
Okay, on to things that are less advantageous. Well, I'll just tell you my thought on that. Not to disagree with Erin, but when you look at these, this is all pretty flat. Like the top floor at the very beginning is really just
I've walked this place enough times to know that there's much more grain than that. So, what's the plan there? Is it just knock a bunch down, build it up? So, I'm a little bit amused by how flat things actually are. It's a big site.
But I'm just counting the stories Other dislikes
Wakefield High School, which just began construction. And then the car detectives were inside. Certainly, I don't feel like we've let them from the top of the street down to the top of the street. But certainly, there could be negative impacts on the operation of that building.
I saw some evidence of that actually materializing in their estimated schedule. Certainly, if you compare it with the Perkins-Willis, they're not exactly obvious, but you can tell where the design phase has evolved. So I was just looking at that. And it seemed to be maybe six to eight months after UW.
For the folks on the phone, I'll just do a quick recap so that we can make sure you're still with us.
For advantages, they have done 3 CTE programs very recently. They've got whole hog on solar. They have the largest in-house team. Their proposal was cohesive from beginning to end. They do have some sub consultants who were involved in Bedford's comprehensive plan, so they would have a connection to Bedford. Their concept seemed very open-ended. They had a wide range of projects in terms of price points, so that
And then on the dislike side, so far, we have some questions about, like.
that. And then that they are simultaneously doing Wakefield and Lexington at different phases. But there are shared resources in this proposed team that also are working on Lexington. And Lexington is going to be a monster of a project based on what it's a very, very large high school. Lexington. Yes, they do. They did. They did put a visual in their proposal about
I think trying to tell us that the timing, the phasing of our project versus Lexington was different. I think that's what this visual was trying to tell us. I actually had some questions much like Luke about doesn't this sound like it's longer? So I think that visual just probably needs some clarification. Anything from the folks online? I see another hand.
Yeah, just a quick follow up.
creating those big old moves, but sometimes it's harder to get all the people who are programming into those spaces, and it gets, I don't know, too much into constraints. And some of the other projects, some of the other proposals are getting their space to each other. And if you look at the way this
Other dislikes, Will? To me, one of their designs seems like a lot of work for a student.
upstairs. Respectfully. To sort of elaborate on that, it doesn't matter. We don't have a lot of time in class. So this is probably a question
I don't want us to do this. Nobody wants the five minutes. But so that is a concern. And then my question was going to be other questions.
So I'm just wondering, is Left Field allowed to suggest questions for us, having worked with some of them or not worked with some of the others? Are there questions you think we should be asking, or are you allowed to say that? I think a lot of the questions that are coming up are along the lines of what we typically ask. We think those vary from project to project, designer to designer. Some of the questions seem to be varied. From what I've heard here, I think the questions that are being asked
We'll get a chance after this first part of the meeting. We're asked to open for questions.
questions are going to be asked across the board. So it won't be specific to one proposal or one architect, those blank questions in relation to the project. Let me follow up to that. You said, so I know originally, please correct me, the thought was we'd get a bunch
do you think that is so narrow for you to purview or exactly what that means. Right, right, right. It'll be the three voices on the panel. So they will decide if they want to be right, they might go for it. If I want to see it all. But that's the
You have this kind of discussion. Relatively close to today, before.
there will be a ranking with all of the MP numbers. And at that point, if they see there's two better run runners, and the other one starts ranking so far below, they might just pick two, or everybody has the same field ranking. Next question.
It's on page 71. It's on the top right. Oh, it's like a little pie chart.
that it takes to put into the materials. But I think what this is saying, my chart, is the proposed design, body carbon is 20% less than the typical. So it's saying that the body carbon reduction is 20%. So bigger green is good. Bigger green is better, yeah. But that's good. It's through use of sustainable materials, like certified wood. I guess I was confused by the proposed design.
Okay, other questions that we would want to ask? And then I think. Are there other questions that we feel like.
spend a lot of schedule on some of it.
My biggest thing that I do is about storage and places to put supplies and things of that nature.
So are there any questions online about either SMMA or maybe the field overall? Questions you'd want to be asking everybody? Yes. Oh, I'm capturing them right now. I do have a question.
But were there any of the specific things that we were wanting that they did not include?
Sorry, I'm going to miss this, but how is parking heat forecasted? Is there anything in your design that would change the parking heat? The question was from a parking heat perspective, is that a formula or how is that determined and how does that integrate into your design? How does that get determined on these projects?
sessions, they have desire, you know, it's not working that way, they will have a specific number of ED spots that are just a discussion. Yeah.
Other questions for vendors? I was thinking about the concepts. Which concepts would absolutely require plastic?
My bones rattle twice a day, every day for months. Yeah. Other questions? Ready?
Sorry, energy code. It's been something I'll make sure their energy is clear and they're ready for it. So, or if they need an extra consultant to help them navigate that. It's pretty ambitious. I think that's about it. Yes. Anything else?
Um, so the 1st designer selection panel meeting is next week, Thursday. And we will know once the meeting is over what our finalists are. Is that correct? Okay. And so we will let you all know. What the outcome of that meeting is so that you're aware of what's coming next.
6, we will interview and then we will know during that meeting. Okay. Okay.
You do, probably. We can collect a list if there's anybody who would like to participate because they usually ask us in advance. So we'll send out an email. I did have one thing. Sure.
Um, that we had originally scheduled a meeting.
So I don't think you necessarily need to be on 24, but I wanted to just let everybody know that there was a slight schedule change in the MSBA, so that would be on 24.
You want to schedule that or just wait until the October meeting, which I think is quite late in the month, so maybe we can get that up. But just wanted to kind of see what people saw. Maybe we see if we can move that up to the October 7th meeting. Yeah, it's the 27th. It was pretty late. So we'll see if we can get that up.
Is there a motion to adjourn? I move. Okay, I will call the roll. Jenny Graham? Yes. Mayor Lundo Kern? Yes. Dr. Guzzi? Yes. Marta Cabral? Yes. Libby Brown?
Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.