[SPEAKER_01]: Boa tarde everyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: In Portuguese that means good afternoon.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is Mayor Briana Lungo-Koehn and I'm here with the good news video and we're doing something a little different today.
[SPEAKER_01]: I wanted to introduce you to Marilea and Soumya
[SPEAKER_01]: who are our connectors and liaisons.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're two of the nine people that are hired in the community under the Board of Health that help connect our residents that need support.
[SPEAKER_01]: They also are a multilingual team, so they're out in our community building trust and making sure that everybody has what they need throughout our entire community.
[SPEAKER_01]: And especially in the case of an emergency, we want to make sure that
[SPEAKER_01]: all residents feel welcome and supported and know where they can come to if they have any questions or concerns or need any support.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I'm going to turn it over to Maralea and take it away.
[SPEAKER_02]: Good afternoon.
[SPEAKER_02]: My name is Marilea.
[SPEAKER_02]: I am the representative here in the City of Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: I am very, very proud to be here, especially with our mayor here, Brianna, who has a heart of this size.
[SPEAKER_02]: A hug to the whole community here.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you feel a little intimidated to come here to the City of Medford to seek any kind of help, we are here to help you in any department, any of them, any question you have, please
[SPEAKER_02]: I would like to thank you from the bottom of my heart for the great initiative of our mayor, Brianna, for opening the doors for all of us.
[SPEAKER_02]: We are also here with a person who will also help us in this team that Brianna opened this opportunity, Samia.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hello, I'm Samia.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm one of the Connectors.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're here to inform you that we're here to help you.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're the connection between the city and the residents of Medford.
[SPEAKER_00]: So don't feel intimidated, as Marilea said, the city is opening the door for all of us, regardless of the language you speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, we are here to help you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any service, any benefit, any information you need in your language, we are here to help you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, mainly, we have our communication line, not only for Portuguese, but all other languages.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, feel free and welcome to Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: Another thing I want to add to this is, people, today we have here in the City Hall the renewal of the Health Insurance of MassHealth.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can apply, you can renew your insurance.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you don't need to run out of health insurance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Come to us.
[SPEAKER_02]: We welcome you here with a lot of affection to do this service.
[SPEAKER_02]: So don't run out of coverage at home.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is very important for you to know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Talk to your friends.
[SPEAKER_02]: We are also on an initiative to start English as a second language.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you both for joining me and for all your hard work and I thank you for tuning in.
[SPEAKER_02]: We'll be in touch.