Welcome to the McGlynn Elementary School community.
My name is Andy O'Brien and I am your child's principal.
Our staff of over 70 teachers, assistants, paraprofessionals, administrators, and other service providers will work to make your child's educational year productive as well as fun.
The McGlynn offers our 500-plus pre-K through grade 5 students many wonderful opportunities both in and out of our school.
Our learning environment is child-centered and rich with interactive lessons in all curriculum areas.
The McGlynn also services the Access and the Newcomer English Language Learner Program.
Our teachers and staff focus on educating the whole child with meaningful, real-world experiences in a manner that is educational, valuable, and enjoyable.
We are committed to meeting each child's individual needs and ability level, which includes their social and emotional well-being.
We encourage you to get involved and stay involved in your child's education in any way you can.
Please know I will try my best to make your children feel like an individual here at the McGlynn.
Our school and our members are committed to you and your family.
It is important that we work together.
To that end, it is extremely important that you know how to get in touch with us.
The best way to stay informed is to read each monthly newsletter.
These will be emailed to your address on file as well as posted to this website.
The monthly newsletters allow you to stay up to date with everything taking place at the McGlynn and by the active McGlynn PTG.
Also, both the district and school websites include important pieces of information that will enable you to remain in contact and informed all year long.
Be sure to visit these various features often.
Welcome, and I wish you many successes in the years ahead.
Thank you for taking an active interest in your child's learning.
And please remember, all of us at the McGlynn care about your child.