Hello, my name is Michael Mastromoni.
I'm a parent of two, a public servant, and I'm running for the Medford School Committee.
My family and I love Medford because it's a community that values public schools, civic life, and neighbors who look out for one another.
My seven-year-old son, Lincoln, and my four-year-old daughter, Violet, are both Robert's school kids.
My wife and I have built friendships here with families and educators who care deeply about Medford's future, and that's so energizing.
Running for school committee is my way of giving back to a community that's given so much to us.
Professionally, I serve as the budget director for the city of Somerville, where I help develop and manage a $400 million annual budget and lead our long-term financial strategy.
My job is to make sure public dollars serve the public.
That means protecting resources and core programs, connecting spending with community priorities, and keeping services strong no matter what's happening at the state or federal level.
I was also part of the finance team that delivered a new Somerville High School in 2021, from early planning through construction.
I know what it takes to manage a once-in-a-generation investment like that, balancing fiscal responsibility with the real needs of students and educators.
My experience will help Medford as we move forward with our own high school reconstruction, an enormous opportunity to build something lasting and community-driven.
But my 20-year local government career isn't just about numbers.
It's about communication.
In my role, I take complex financial decisions and make them clear and accessible so residents understand not just what we're doing, but why.
It's the kind of honest communication we'll need here in Medford as we make big decisions about budgets, programs, and that high school project.
Leading our school district requires planning, consistency, and follow through.
And that's what I do best.
The school committee is not just a policy group.
It's an executive body.
It hires and evaluates the superintendent, ensures the district's budget reflects our values, and sets measurable goals through strategic planning.
I'm ready to do that work on day one.
I bring experience, leadership, and a steady hand to preserve what works and invest in what needs improvement.
If I'm elected, I'll focus on three things.
First, supporting our school through strong curriculum, special education, athletics, and afterschool programs that give every student a place to belong and a chance to thrive.
Second, budgeting for values and stability.
That means making sure our spending is transparent, sustainable, and focused on what matters most.
Third, delivering a successful Medford High School project, a school we can be proud of that's fiscally responsible and built to meet the needs of today's students, their children, and generations to come.
I believe in collaboration, not confrontation.
I believe in clear communication and honest explanations, especially when decisions get complicated.
I've spent my career helping folks understand how government works and how to make it work better for them.
I'm proud to be a parent and a public servant here in Massachusetts.
Medford deserves a school committee that's focused, informed, and grounded in values.
A team that can plan for the future while protecting what makes our school special today.
I'd be honored to earn your vote on Tuesday, November 4th.
Thank you for listening, and thank you so much for caring about our public schools.