When it says that the stormwater drain drains to a waterway, I had always thought that it meant like it drains to a pipe, and it actually goes straight into the water.
Whatever is on our roads, whatever is on our sidewalk, when there's a heavy rain, those oil spills in the street go into the water.
So low impact development is sort of a tool kit that tries to mimic what that natural state would do.
Low impact development techniques try and slow it down, try and get it into the ground instead of going into our storm drain, instead of going into the river.
I certainly think that there's an aesthetic value to low impact development.
The area we're looking at right now used to be a street and now it's a nice green area
If you're going to develop a piece of land, don't cut all the trees down.
Try and save some of the trees.
Try and minimize paved surfaces.
Try and use paver blocks or porous pavement that allows the water to percolate through.