Are the waiting room people real people? No, they're not. One of them's not. Okay. I knew one of them wasn't. You're good to go, Mayor. Okay, thanks. The 11th regular meeting of the Medford School Committee will come to order on Monday, June 1st, 2026, Executive Session, 5pm.
Thanks, Jerry. 5 o'clock p.m. remote only. And this meeting is being recorded. The meeting can be viewed live on the Medford Public Schools YouTube channel, through Medford Community Media, on your local cable channel, Comcast 9, 8, or 22, and Verizon 43, 45, 47. Participants can log or call in.
to the meeting on June 1st, 2026, Memphis School Committee 11th regular meeting. Zoom link is in the agenda on the city website and school website, and the meeting ID is 923-2618-5567. Member Rossell, if you could please call the roll. Member Graham. Here. Member Mastromoni. Here. Member Olopade. Here. Member Parks.
Here. Member Rheinfeld. Present. Member so present, Mayor Lungo-Kern. Present. Seven present, zero absent. If we could all please rise to salute the flag. I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America and to the republic for which it stands, one nation under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all.
We have executive session upon a motion to enter into executive session pursuant to Mass General Laws, Chapter 30A, Section 21A, executive session to conduct a strategy session on the basis that an open meeting may have a detrimental effect on the bargaining positions of the Medford School Committee. Specifically, the Medford School Committee will convene an executive session to discuss collective bargaining with the Massachusetts Teachers Association, the MTA, regarding a teacher's grievance, and the chair so declares.
an executive session pursuant to General Laws 30A, Section 21A to conduct a strategy session on the basis that an open meeting may have a detrimental effect on the bargaining positions of the Memphis School Committee. Specifically, the Memphis School Committee will convene an executive session to discuss strategy for potential litigation, and the chair so declares. And then lastly, also pursuant to Chapter 30A, Section 21-2,
to conduct strategy in preparation with non-union personnel or contract negotiations with non-union personnel specifically, but not limited to elementary principals, middle school principals, high school principals, executive director of CTE.
the Assistant Superintendent of Academics and Instructions, Chief Operations Officer, Director of Student Services, and the Director of Human Resources. Please refer to the appendix for the complete list. Medford School Committee will not reconvene in public session following the executive session. And our next regular meeting while we are on is June 8th, 2026 in the chambers, Medford City Hall.
motion to enter executive session. I'm not without convening in public after after. Yep. Um, member Reinfeldt, seconded by Second. Member Graham. Roll call, please. Remember Graham? Yes. Remember Master Money? Yes. Remember all
Yes, 70 affirmative, zero in the negative motion to enter executive session and not reconvene in public session has been approved.
Then there were two. Do you want me to add you just in case they go out of order and then you can... No, she'll text when they need to come in. It's fine. What's that? She'll text when they need to come in, right? I would assume so, yeah. Yeah, it's fine. Okay.
Thanks.
Psst.