So the other day, I was talking to someone who had donated to me and some other candidates in 2020 when I was running for a different seat.
But now he said that he doesn't believe in electoral politics anymore.
He had lost faith in our democracy.
And I told him that in 2016, I had a similar crisis where I was really wondering if our democracy was still functioning.
And I've spent a number of years researching what makes democracy tick, creating my own theory about how we can improve it.
So I told him that I had a rough draft of a book on this topic and I sent him the first chapter.
I didn't expect anything because he said he wouldn't donate.
And the next day he actually sent me a very generous donation.
Thank you so much for that.
But I thought in case anyone else out there is worried about our democracy and wondering what you can do.
and also have time to read a 20 page chapter that I wrote.
It is linked down below.
And if you can donate a little bit to my campaign, because I am going to be doing all of the things that I describe in the chapter to reinvigorate our democracy right here in Medford.
Thank you.