to remember what has happened and consider what could happen.
Juneteenth is more than a date on the calendar.
It's a profound reminder of a promise delayed and a call to continue the work of justice.
On June 19, 1865, enslaved African Americans in Galveston, Texas, were finally informed of their freedom, more than two years after the Emancipation Proclamation.
That moment was not simply a matter of legal change, it was the culmination of generations of resistance, of voices raised, of people refusing to accept injustice as permanence.
Today, here in Medford, we honor that spirit not just with a celebration, but with action.
The same moral courage that brought freedom to enslaved people in the 19th century is needed now in our schools, our neighborhoods, and our local government.
Especially now, we need that courage to stand firm in the face of tyranny, fascism, and injustice.
Especially now, we need to protect all of our citizens, no matter what their immigration status, racial, cultural, religious, or economic background.
Especially now.
Thank you.
Yes.
Especially now, we need to be the kind of community that cared for all of her residents.
Our city, like all communities, is still on a journey toward equity, and the power to shape that journey lies with us, the people.
Dorothy Height, one of my inspirations, a towering figure in the civil rights movement, once said, we must always be a strong presence, an unrelenting force working for equality and justice until freedom gates are fully opened.
That message speaks directly with us today, because Juneteenth is not only about what happened in 1865, it's about what happens at every school community meeting, every city council vote, every decision made about housing, health, or education in our cities, and we're a part of that.
The voice of the people still rings loudly, and it must.
In our city, we have the power to ensure our local government reflects the needs and values of our whole community.
So let Juneteenth not only be a day of remembrance, but a renewed commitment to be that strong presence, an unrelenting force, pushing forward until those freedom gates are not just open, but wide enough for everyone to walk through with dignity.
Let us celebrate but also recommit.
Let us remember and also act.
That is the true spirit of Juneteenth.
Thank you.