[SPEAKER_01]: Police officers were hard to miss at Medford High School as students returned to class one day after a stabbing here.
[SPEAKER_01]: All the police up there, it's not creating a nice environment for like students to learn and it's just turning the school into sort of like a prison.
[SPEAKER_01]: By now, nearly everyone at school has seen the cell phone video of two boys fighting in a bathroom.
[SPEAKER_02]: One of them appears to have a knife in his hand as he lunges at the other.
[SPEAKER_02]: That other boy was wounded in the abdomen and went to the hospital.
[SPEAKER_02]: The guy in the video, I know he's in my Spanish class.
[SPEAKER_02]: Students say the bathrooms are where most of the fighting takes place and that the school's efforts to restrict bathroom access haven't changed that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, the schools are more focused on like something called a hall pass.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you have to like request online, you go to the bathroom, but half the bathrooms are broken to begin with.
[SPEAKER_02]: Our kids are afraid my daughter doesn't want to go back to school.
[SPEAKER_02]: Parents and students gave school leaders an earful at a school committee meeting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Some say the schools need to give harsher punishment to troublemakers.
[SPEAKER_02]: What happened to suspensions?
[SPEAKER_02]: What happened to just common sense dignity?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's gone.
[SPEAKER_02]: School committee needs to go.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just not good enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Medford police say the increased security will last at least through the end of this week.
[SPEAKER_00]: Medford's mayor says the district is also working on a culture and climate study that she says should help.