Hi everyone. just trying to pull up the agenda. there's not much on it correct. Okay um so financial status to did we get financial from. The finance office.
I yes I sent you an afternoon email with everything on it. yep. yeah got it. got it.
Hold on a second, guys.
Okay, I'm just taking a look at them. Does anybody have any questions on them? Nope. Nope. Looks good. Kevin, do you have anything to add about these? The meeting minutes that I was absent at the last meeting, I think I just was late.
I'll make that change. Sorry, I made that incorrect. No worries. And that income statement looks correct. I did do another deposit yesterday. I think we're still waiting for Arlington Catholic
D1 soccer owes us the last payment. And I think we're all caught up after that. So almost there. So Kevin, do you know if everything's been rolled forward?
I don't have that answer. I know my other budgets have not rolled forward yet, so I would make the assumption Hormel is the same way. But it is showing that there has been some revenue coming in now. Like you said, the net profit at 35 is definitely more money in than we have in our past previous months. But I don't know if FY22 has also been counted or not.
Okay. Do we have any other business? The only thing I was gonna just let the commissioners know is now that we are seeing that there is a net profit at the end of the fiscal year, we talked about in previous meetings about having the field professionally groomed
So we are looking to do that. John's going to be contacting the company that has already come out and looked at the facility. And we're going to try to get them in somewhere around April or early May before the season really begins. And have that professionally groomed. The lights, I think I already mentioned at the last meeting, are all in place. Yeah, lights are all set now.
Looks like we're getting ready for spring. Kevin, whatever happened with the signage and stuff you guys were working on? No, no, no. What were you looking at working on in the event of an emergency, like extra signage? We do have all the signs now. Yeah. So we have like where the emergency exits are. Yep. Those are posted. We just did update like the facility rules.
Those are all posted out there and stuff. I think we did that during the summertime. We're just taking a lot of the cardboard signs that were made and updating them. Have you gotten a lot of inquiries for rentals for the spring?
I'll defer to John. I haven't received anything yet. I do know Run Medford, David Gilroy did email me about wanting to, in the beginning phases, it's still very early on, but looking for one of the dates in September, having Hormel for either the celebrity run or the children's running. But again, nothing's been confirmed yet, but I just want to see if Hormel is an option.
doing that instead of going into a road race in Method Square like they did last year. But that's all I have really for inquiries right now. John, if you want to speak to that. Yeah, I have the track in there already of the crossing there for Method High and their practices and their games. Boston Glory, the Frisbee team.
I have their game schedule already. I'm probably going to add a few more when they email me. I actually have in my notes for tomorrow to email a few people this round in March of last year, it was Jaguar soccer and Boston glory that were there in the months of March. And we had a mass flag. I think we, we, we had also, we had another middle school flag league, but I think, um,
recreation might actually try to do our own one this year on Friday nights, but me and Kevin have to still discuss that. But as of right now, it's on my radar to email people, but I do have a few people on the schedule already. Is there anyone brand new, do you know? No, no one's brand new. Okay. Any other business?
Phyllis, do you know, did Mr. Karasiewicz respond to that email that was sent out? Yes. He is doing ancestry reviews to see if he can reach out to the family members. He hasn't reached back to me yet. Okay. But I'm sure he has a little bit of work to do and the date hasn't been established. Right. Right.
On another note, I did invite Paul Riggi, the facility director. He did respond that he had a meeting at 4.30. He would try to join us in the meeting as soon as he could. Okay. Anybody else have anything, Kevin or John, has anything come up that you wanted to make us aware of?
Uh, nothing that's come up, but, uh, me and Kevin actually had, um, a meeting yesterday. Uh, we are going to do a few small projects and like try to paint the place a little better and try to do some more upkeep. So actually do like either my staff or maybe someone from the, um, I don't know exactly, um, like the verbiage to call them, but the, like the, uh, um, the people that work with the, uh,
the box department, the ones that come from the department of corrections. I just don't know. They're the ones that help out with the projects. Yeah. Thank you. Sorry. I just didn't want, I just didn't want to say the wrong thing. Um, but yeah, they're going to help out with a few projects. There's a few minor things that we're going to have to do ourselves. Okay. We have to build actually a, uh, a what? Yep.
I can build a shot put cage before the track season. Yeah, sorry. Yeah, you're cutting out. It's a shot put cage, he said. The last one broke on one of the windstorms. So we already have the cage already here. We just decided it didn't make sense to set it up for the wintertime. So in the spring, we'll set that up. What John was saying with the Department of Corrections,
Right now with the facility not being used in the daytime in the locker room area, doing some painting around there, painting the floor and the walls. John is working on maybe having his football team help out with that, but I don't wanna speak for John. John, if you do have a reception, if you wanna kinda talk about your idea that you had yesterday about possibly doing some murals or bringing in the football team to help out with some of that.
Yeah. Can you hand me better now or no? Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Perfect. Yeah. So I actually want to see if my football, I actually talked to my football team. They definitely want to do it to make the locker room look a little better and have some more pride in their locker room when they walk into it. So we want to paint it, but we also want to have someone paint some murals in the, in our walkroom, but also in the business locker room to like have some catchphrase words up there just to make it,
look a little better and just have a team bonding experience to actually do it and paint it together. I think that's a great idea. What about the person that did the murals over at Le Conte? Yes, that's actually the person I was going to contact, Jamie. Yeah, he's definitely on my radar. Once I get the okay, yeah, yeah. He's actually a really good person too, so I think he definitely is a great person and should probably do it for me. But yeah, definitely. Yeah, I think that's a great idea.
And, you know, if there's any issues still, Janine, with lead paint and stuff that we talked about a couple of years ago, scraping the paint in there. I mean, the issue's never been addressed. Right. I don't, from a facility standpoint, the issue's still there. Someone check it out. Yeah, I mean, this facility-
Go ahead, Kevin. I'm sorry. Is there a report or something that you received about it that I could possibly get a copy of, or is this just something that was on discussion? So I think it was part of the RFP that was done on the stadium, if I remember correctly. I don't have a copy of it. Phyllis, I think this is popping in your office, right?
I'm sorry, I did not hear what you said at all. Do you have a copy of the the RFP that was done on the facility? Like five years ago? Yes, the book that was presented with the review of the email? Yes. I can make a copy and send everybody one.
Um, sure, but I mean, it's outdated, Kevin. I don't know exactly. I don't remember what's in there. Um, yeah, there's like, Hey, yeah, I'll be good to go. I don't remember if it was in the locker room or more in that kitchen area. Remember Janine, we were going to put the sink and all that stuff. It's wherever there was a lot of like flaking of paint. Right. I don't know what it looks like now.
possible is the ceiling, the ceiling has a lot of flaky paint. So yeah, I believe that. Yeah, I think that's positive Kevin. Okay. Maybe nothing that just worth mentioning, I think. Yeah. Well, at least that's good. So that we can paint the floor and the walls, right? Right. Certainly won't have anyone touch the ceiling that if that's, that's where it is. Yeah.
That's it for me. Okay. Oh, I have a quick question for John. I imagine either John or Kevin will somewhat be in charge of what's going to be depicted on the walls or how is that managed? Yeah, definitely. Um, I was just thinking like in the, um, the home locker room, obviously you can't really cater to football because lacrosse uses it.
uh, football, I mean, um, soccer, like all the, all the sports you do. So like, I was just thinking about like method Mustangs, maybe like the horse symbol on, on, like in the home locker room, then like the business locker room, like, but like words like pride effort and like other things, it's like keywords that you want to see, like when you play it, when you're playing a sport. But I know that we can't really cater the locker room to football, but I want to do keywords for method and method athletics, if that's okay with everybody.
Yeah, just yeah, if we could just see it before too. Yeah, absolutely. Yep. All I have. OK, I don't have anything else. I haven't been contacted by anybody either for anything. Now, I think at this point, if everyone's OK with that, maybe John, if you want to contact the people from last spring,
If you already have high school already confirmed. It's gonna pull this up real quick. Besides Method High School, is there anything, I know you have track and field, but is there any other sports that are gonna be using as well? I know you said lacrosse, so they're gonna have a couple of games there.
Yeah, that's the lacrosse games that are in there right now. That's all they really going to do. They don't use that much. It's mostly that's a track for my family for the spring. Yeah. Yeah. Boston glory. Those are already in. Yeah. Yeah.
If the school department and the city is all set already scheduled, then I think we are ready then to go out to our outside contract, our outside vendors, and we can start trying to schedule that if that's okay with everyone. Sure. Yep. Whatever makes you guys jobs easier is fine. All right. Sounds good to me. Yeah, me too.
Okay, I don't think we have anything else. Yeah, we can pick a date. 1st, 8th, 15th. I'm fine with any of them, whatever works. Do you want to say the 8th? Sure. February 8th.
Yes, that works. Okay. Okay. All right, everyone. Okay, enjoy.