third regular meeting, Medford City Council, February 6th, 2024. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Callahan. Present. Vice President Collins. Present. Councilor Favara. Present. Councilor Levin. Present. Councilor Scarpelli. Present. Councilor Sanz. Present. President Ferris. Present. Seven present, none absent. The meeting is called to order. Please rise to salute the flag. I pledge allegiance to the flag
Thank you, everyone, for being here. So we have a long agenda, as I just noted prior to the start of the meeting. We are going to be doing our best. I cannot make motions, but I believe the vice president will make a motion to take a number of issues that folks are here to talk about tonight so that we can put those at the front of the agenda. Before that, we are going to go through a number of our standing items, remembrances, condolences, celebrations, and the approval of our records and reports of committees. So with that,
I will start with announcements, accolades, remembrances, reports, and records. 24-027 offered by Vice President Collins, Councilor Lazaro, and Councilor Tseng. Be it resolved that the Medford City Council acknowledge and celebrate Black History Month. Vice President Collins.
Thank you, President Behrs. In February, we celebrate Black History Month. The story of Medford is a story of black achievement and black community, from abolitionist organizing, to local icons like Belinda Sutton, to the historic black community of West Medford. This Black History Month, we celebrate black history in Medford. We endeavor to hold black history and celebrate it every month of the year. And I hope that we can recommit ourselves to policies that will allow Medford to remain a diverse community for people of all backgrounds. Thank you.
I have nothing to add. I thought that was beautiful. Thank you. I'm happy to be part of co-offering this to celebrate this Black History Month, and I'm happy to be part of a town that is historically a community that celebrates that.
Thank you. Councilor say thank you, President bears. Thank you, Councilor about Vice President Collins for your words on this black history, black history is meant for history, and we cherish meant for history we talked about how it's such a blessing to be living in such a historic
a town, a city. And when we think about what has brought us up to this moment, Black Medfordians, and especially the historically Black community in West Medford, has played such a pivotal and integral role to shaping who we are today, the discourse that shapes our politics today, and just the joy, the memories, the happiness of growing up in Medford. I was reminded of this, especially on Martin Luther King's Day.
When I got this book, Place, Race, and Memory, the West Medford Afro-American Remembrance Project, which talks about a bunch of icons that have lived in our city, been a vital part of our West Medford community. And I was really touched reading a lot of these stories and at the same time, a bit sad that I didn't grow up learning about a lot of these folks.
There's such a long way to go when it comes to racial reconciliation in the city, when it comes to making sure that all of our neighbors, our black neighbors included feel welcome and engaged as part of our city. And there's so much more work to do as part of that social justice plan going forward.
little steps first on the on February 19th. It's a Monday from 10 a.m. to 1 p.m. In these chambers, our city will be hosting a celebration on Black History Month. I encourage you all to come join us and celebrate Black History Month. Thank you, Councillor Sang. Any further comment?
On the motion of Councilor Collins, seconded by Councilor Lazaro. All those in favor? Aye. Opposed? Motion passes. 24-029 offered by Councilor Scarpelli. Condolences to the family of Bruno Bruni Bonacorsi. Councilor Scarpelli. Thank you, Mr. President. Again, it seems that we've lost another legend here in Medford.
He didn't have to have a first name. He didn't have to have a last name. He was just known as Bruni and an individual that.
grew up with Down syndrome and was a family who had an amazing family. His sister Carol Carviello, Rick Carviello's former council president, council Rick Carviello's brother-in-law, great nieces and nephews that loved him.
Bruni was a fixture, whether it was on the music site here in Medford, because he loved to dance and he loved to sing. But most people know Bruni and remember Bruni as one of the most committed Medford Mustang supporters in our athletic fields. I remember a story. You don't really make it until Bruno, until Bruni recognizes you.
We were coaching, I was coaching probably my 14th year at Medford High School, and our boys had just finished their sixth straight season without losing a GBL game, and we're going into the state finals. And I wasn't nervous as a coach, I was ready to go, our boys were ready to go. And I remember someone beside me, and I turned to the right, and here's this posing gentleman wearing a Medford jacket. And I said, Bruni, he says, coach,
And I said, that minute, I said, boy, two things. I said, I made it. As a team and as a coach, we made it. Bruni was there. And two, that now I'm nervous.
because Bruni was here. So he left that mark and everybody that crossed his path, he always had a smile on his face. He loved being around him, but individuals with Down syndrome, he lived a full and happy life. He just has had an amazing family that supported him and Mefford will miss him and send his condolences to his family. So thank you.
Thank you, Councillor Scarpelli. I also want to send my condolences to Councillor Carviello and Carol and their whole family. I know that they are in mourning. Any further comment on the motion of Councillor Scarpelli, seconded by Councillor Sang. All those in favour? Aye. All opposed? Motion passes. 24-030 offered by Councillor Scarpelli. Be it resolved.
excuse me, sorry, be it resolved that the Medford City Council congratulate Patrick O'Brien, lifelong resident of our great city and committed volunteer on his recent retirement at UPS. Councilor Scarpelli. Now, Council President, you normally don't put a retiree from UPS on your agenda, but someone like Pat O'Brien, I get more phone calls from residents and owners of small businesses that talked about losing a fixture here in Medford.
You all have, if you live in Medford, if you've been around Medford, you know, Pat O'Brien. Pat's the hardest working individual I've ever seen in your life. Yes, he's in a big brown truck and yes, he's always wearing brown, but he is always running. He's never stopping. He's always giving back to the community, whether it was in his position as a UPS driver and, um,
But I remember Pat as someone that volunteered at the ice rink, that drove the Zamboni to make sure the ice hockey team had the best surface, whether it be coaching baseball or coaching basketball for his children. He was someone that was always a fixture in Metro. And I just want to congratulate him. He's a great role model for any Method resident that lives with the motto of working hard,
to the community. So we wish Pat, uh, happy retirement. I don't know what he's going to do with all that energy he has, but, um, maybe he can come here and, you know, maybe work with the city council. You know, help you with cleaning out the back room again. Council president. So thank you. Thank you, Councilor Scarpelli. Any further comment? I was a classmate of Katie, and so I knew
who was driving the truck when it honked. All right. On the motion of Councillor Scarpelli, seconded by Vice President Collins. All those in favour? Aye. Opposed? Motion passes. I'm just going to read this from the chair if there's no objection.
24-032 offered by President Beers can be resolved by the Medford City Council that we send our deep and sincere condolences to the family of Elizabeth Betsy Schwerer, a longtime Medford Public Schools librarian and beloved member of the Medford community. Folks at Medford High School and across our Medford community probably know Betsy.
either as a librarian in the schools, or as a parent of three Medford Public Schools graduates, or the wife of someone who's provided great assistance to this council, Gary Klein, and her loss is meaningful to many. And I don't want to belabor and speak from the chair, but I just feel it's important to acknowledge and send our condolences to her family. Any further comments?
on my motion, seconded by? Second. Councilor Scarpelli, all those in favor? Aye. Opposed? Motion passes. The records of the meeting of January 23rd, 2024 were passed to Councilor Callahan. Councilor Callahan, how did you find those records? Councilor Callahan has found the records in order and moved approval, seconded by? Councilor Sang. All those in favor? Aye. Opposed? The motion passes.
24-006 committee of the whole report, January 24th, 2024. This was a meeting that we held to discuss the now 30 something page governing agenda. And we referred that out to a number of committees, which did a further deep dive, but I really encourage folks to take a look. We have put out 35 pages of what we plan to do this year and next year. And in my view, it is the most transparent governing plan of any municipality or municipal council in the entire Commonwealth. So I'm very proud of it.
on the motion to approve the committee report, seconded by Vice President Collins. All those in favor? Aye. Opposed? The motion passes. 24-006, Administration and Finance Committee report to follow. We discussed the governing agenda in the Administration and Finance Committee, made several motions, and I look forward to updating the governing agenda with the input of the Administration and Finance Committee.
Councilor Seng. Motion to join the remaining three reports and approve pending the summaries from chairs. On the motion of Councilor Seng to join, seconded by Councilor Kellyanne. All those in favor? Aye. Opposed? Motion passes. The Planning and Permitting Committee report, Vice President Collins. Thank you, President Behrs. The Planning and Permitting Committee had its first standing meeting to go over the projects that have so far been assigned to that committee over the coming term.
and some papers in committee that have also been allocated to be worked on in that committee. And we'll continue to create a draft schedule for working through those ordinances oriented around the zoning project, which will organize much of our work for this term. Thank you. Thank you, Vice President Collins. The Public Works and Facilities Committee report. Councilor Callahan.
public works facilities convened, and we have discussed ways that we can keep up to date on the roads and sidewalks, as well as all of the buildings that the city owns in Medford. We are excited to keep the public informed of how these efforts are moving forward with the administration. Thank you, Councillor Collins. Is there a motion to approve the joint reports? On the motion of Councillor Seng to approve, seconded by...
Vice President Collins, all those in favor? Aye. Opposed? Motion passes. Vice President Collins. I would motion to suspend the rolls and take out of order the scheduled public participation appearing at the end of the agenda. Then paper 24037, paper 24038, the elections papers, followed by 24021, and finally 24035.
on the motion by Councilor Collins to suspend the rules to take Judy Lonergan's public participation position, 24-037, 24-038, 24-021, and 24-035, seconded by? Second. Seconded by Councilor Scarpelli. All those in favor? Aye. Opposed? Motion passes. So we have Judy Lonergan under public participation.
You may come to the podium, Judy, and give your name and address for the record, please. And while you're on your way up, I did want to thank you. We haven't seen you since December. I know that you and many others organized the Jingle Bell Festival, a wonderful event for the city. We look forward to working with you and the committee to make sure it is a successful event once again.
Thank you. My name is Judy Lonergan. I live at 34 Lincoln Road. I'd like to give you a brief history of what happened and why we're here. In 1999, a group of Medford women decided that they wanted to run a function, an event, to recognize the fact that the song Jingle Bells was written in Medford.
We decided that it would be a free event that anyone in the community could attend. We had plans in place, but we had no place to hold it. I went to see Mayor McGlynn, who at the time I was not really that friendly with. I explained our problem to him, and I asked him if he could think of a place. He brought me into the council chamber and said that we could have it here.
That's how it started. This festival started in 1999 when Community Family purchased the historical old railroad station on Washington Street from the city. My husband, John, was on the board at that time and suggested that Community Family become the beneficiary of this event. Community Family is the first licensed adult care facility in the state.
Before they purchased the railroad station, the program was held in the basement of the West Medford Baptist Church for years. This agency provides direct service care to those who have been diagnosed with severe Alzheimer's. They provide medically-based services along with transportation activities and meals. I don't need to tell you that services like this keep our loved ones, friends, and neighbors aging in their homes where they want to be, not institutionalized in a skilled nursing home facility.
There are three community family centers. One is in Everett, one is in Melrose, and the Medford Center. The Medford Center caters to those affected with highest level of Alzheimer's. Clients leave to go either to a nursing home or they die. The festival has grown in size every year, and over these 25 years, we have been able to donate almost $450,000 due to the generosity of sponsors, ads, donors, and chances.
They use the proceeds to assist with the purchase of vans, construct a new kitchen, develop a large outdoor space where the clients can spend time in nice weather, and help to renovate the center. This event is free to any family to attend. If they want to purchase chances, they can buy 20 for $5, and then the prices go up. This year, a mother came in with two children, and she bought chances with four single dollars and four quarters.
But it gave her the opportunity to have her children be involved in an event for Christmas. And this is the biggest event in Medford for this Christmas holidays. And if someone came in and they couldn't even afford $5, they would be included. We would do whatever we could to help them.
Our volunteers decorate City Hall for the month of December, which is still out there, and the city uses our decorations. The festival starts on Wednesday night for the lighting of the tree. Afterwards, everyone is invited inside. These women work for seven solid days on the set, setting up, decorating, and cleaning up on Monday after summer volunteers in City Hall spend 40 hours
having this function be extremely successful. The festival does not cost the city one cent other than the use of this chambers. We have purchased the tablecloth as well as paying for the rental of all the tables and chairs and paying for the janitorial services. It has recently been brought to our attention that some members of this city council do not want us to use City Hall any longer. One feels that it is disruptive and one feels that we are not inclusive enough. We have had
Members, we have been always on display for chances. We have included every church, the Buddhist Center, the Royal House, Chevalier, most recently the new library as part of the tours on Saturday night. This year, Barbara Rothstein, who is an active member of the temple, had her home on the tour. What reason does this council have to desire that the event be discontinued? We hope that you will reconsider and allow this community event to continue. Thank you. Thank you, Judy.
I'm going to recognize Councillor Scarpelli in just a minute. Could you not hear Judy? I got it. Just want to say, you know, I don't think the intent of this council whatsoever is to move or cancel the event. I can't speak for where those rumors have come from, but they have not come from this council or any official statement.
Well, they are not accurate. Councillor Scarpelli. Thank you. So I know that, first of all, I care very deeply for a lot of our members. I respect you. And I will tell you that having deep conversations with my fellow Councillors, that's not the intent of this Council.
we'll do everything that needs to be done to make sure that event comes through every single year. It's too important for our community. In today's society, where we lack a true sense of community at times, that event brings everybody together. So I don't know where where that might have come from. But I will tell you, we will work hard together as a board to make sure that that's not something that's going to ever be forgotten. And and we understand how hard you work.
And I think that comes that evening that happens a lot of miscommunication and a lot of misunderstanding what was coming from the administration, the council, and your organization. So I think all it says is really having an open line of communication. I know that Judy's working really hard with the mayor's office to set up a meeting with different clergy and different churches. I know that the council president would probably love to be involved.
to make sure that we're all together to make sure that this is an all-inclusive and a true celebration the way that you intended for. I think that you know I brought my kids to the event when they were babies and it's something that to this day they still remember the Christmas trees and not for what what
what the symbol of it but what it meant for the city and that was really unifying us. So I think that we so appreciate everything you do and I appreciate that you even had to come up here and share what you had to because there might have been some negative
I'm glad you were here. I'm glad that we got it. We had a chance to speak, get the word out. And really, I think most importantly, is rally around as a council as an organization as a city to do more of these type of functions, because they're so important to what we're doing here. I mean, you want to talk about we have a room full of people that want to that are looking for true inclusion and peace and happiness. And I think that you're you're
You're the originators. You've been doing this before people were looking for where to look, where there's peace and love and happiness. So you are, in my eyes, the cornerstone of what we all should fight for. So again, I'm sorry that there was any negative words that came out in discussions, but rest assured, I've talked to Council President
We're gonna work very hard to make sure this doesn't change. And now, I think that it's out there now. I would love to see so many other of our churches and our synagogues and our different affiliations and partners throughout the community really rally around this event so we can use this as a true teaching moment for everybody and really celebrate that amazing event. I know that still hundreds of kids show up every year
And you didn't mention how much money goes out, Mrs. Lonergan, but I know you're talking to the hundreds of thousands that were raised and that were distributed to so many families that needed it and so many organizations that need it. And I think it's to the point now, we don't have enough room for the people that want to donate Christmas trees so they can. And what's the intent of the tree? People don't realize you can hold what?
more prizes on it. So you get more money and more donations that can come in. So that's one of the intents for it. I think that people didn't realize how important that is. It's really just a mechanism to really stress the importance of gathering funds to support different initiatives throughout the community. So, um,
You know how I feel about all of you personally. I've known all of you probably my whole life, and I think that I'm proud to call you my friend, but I will tell you, as a council, I didn't hear, I haven't heard one negative thing moving forward with anything we're trying to do. I think we're all one team, making sure that we're gonna spread this love. So thank you. Yes, and I know how many gifts. Thank you, Councilor Sanford.
I know how many gifts go out. I know I was a youth volunteer at the Buddy Cohalent Center myself. My family has faced the tragedy of Alzheimer's, so I understand how important it is. If there's any meetings that I can represent the council at, I'd be happy to do so. From here on out, we're gonna keep it to two minutes. Judy had a petition, so she went in advance, but name and address for the record, please. Loretta Tusa, 45 Metcalf Street. Thank you, Councilor Scott Pelli for your words.
and to the council, who I hope is gonna support us wholeheartedly in this effort that's been going on for over 20 years. I have a little speech, won't take long, couple of minutes. I'm a retired 37-year educator of the Medford Public Schools, former board member of Medford Health Matters, and a member of the Jingle Bell Committee. I would like to address the use of City Hall to host the festival.
It is the Medford residents who through their federal taxes, state taxes, sales taxes, excise taxes, local food tax, and community taxes fund the operation of the House of the People City Council.
And on a final note, the festival committee here has, over the last 20 plus years, given their heart, souls, time, and money to raise thousands of dollars to fund the community center to provide a warm and welcoming place for seniors with special needs to spend their time comfortably. Thank you for the opportunity to express my thoughts.
Hello, everybody. Hi, name and address for the record, please. My name is Angela Sperduto, 27 Memorial Way. Okay. Hello, my name is Angela Sperduto. I've been a member of the Jingle Bell Festival for 20 years. My dad, Cosmo Sperduto, was a client at the Community Family Adult Day Health Center for almost a decade. The love I have for my father could not be put into words.
He was the most important person in my life. He had late stage advanced Alzheimer's. He lost his motor skills and ability to speak. Alzheimer's disease is the most common type of dementia that not only affects your loved one, it affects the whole entire family. As the primary caregiver of my dad, the physical and mental demands became very overwhelming.
To see my dad, who was so strong mentally and physically, become a shell of himself was more than most can handle. Not knowing where to turn for help, I was recommended to look into the community family for help and care for my dad.
Having to work every day as well as providing 24-hour care for my dad, this center was my savior. I refused to put my dad into a long-term facility. They educated me on the disease and the progression of its long-term daily effects to the brain. As they provided knowledge on the financial and legal issues that are involved with the Alzheimer's patient.
He needed 100%, 24-hour care, never to be left alone, as he would be a danger to himself, and most importantly, other people. Ms. Peduto, you have 30 seconds. Okay.
Anyway, the staff displayed a genuine concern for my dad. They called me many times with issues regarding my dad's health. Every time they were concerned about his health, they prevented more health issues. I could not have asked for more kindness and professionalism. They truly became a second family to me, showing me love and emotional support until his passing.
I want to thank them from the bottom of my heart, as I will always be a member of this festival, and I want to give back as long as I can. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Name and address for the record, please. You have two minutes.
My name is Val Camilio. I live in 223 Lawrence Road. I'm here in support of the continuation of the Jingle Bell Festival held here every year at Medford City Hall. It's difficult to take care of someone who suffers from dementia or Alzheimer's. It is not an ordinary 24-hour day. It is a 24-hour day of worry, stress, and what's about to come for them and the caregiver.
People who suffer from these disorders require constant supervision, you know preparation personal hygiene care and more families look for any outside support, help and services for their loved ones, much like a child daycare program, but they can be very costly.
My mom was 78 years old when she was diagnosed with Alzheimer's. As much as that family tried to care for her needs, it became impossible and difficult as we had our own families to care for. At the time my dad was 88 years old.
And he did the best he could preparing nutritious meals and trying to keep her occupied and entertained. It soon became too much of a test for him as well. We looked for services in the area, and finally found community family in Medford. It was a relief to find temporary help allowing me and my family members, some comfort during our busy working days.
We took mom to visit community family, and the administrator was welcoming, kind, warm, and attentive to my mom. My apprehensive mother looked at me and whispered, all these people are old. In reality, the people were both young and old, men and women, rich and poor, and of mixed ethnicity.
So you see, Alzheimer's does not discriminate. On her first day, the administrator knew my mom loved to cook. So she took my mom into the kitchen and asked her if she would like to prepare lunch for the guests. My mom was eager to help.
She became a community family member for five years. She started three days a week and eventually went to four. My mom actually thought she was working there. The staff at the facility were kind, patient and caring to everyone. They also had a nurse on staff, and beyond administering medications, she would even give baths for those who needed it.
They had wonderful days planned with activities, games, singing songs, exercise, nutritious lunch and snacks, and they celebrated everyone's birthday. In addition to the wonderful care provided to our community, family provided transportation to and from the facility if it was needed, with a van that was purchased from monies received from the Jingle Bell Festival. Ma'am, thank you. Your time is up, but your message has been heard. I'm sorry? Your time is up. We have a two-minute limit.
I only have another minute. My mom thrived there and my dad and other family members had a safe place for mom to go for daycare. I can show attention to all the people who came there for services. They never got frustrated and was beyond anything I could ever imagine.
The community family always went over and above what they needed to do. It is the type of care that you would never receive anywhere else. They are truly devoted to these people. I am proud to have helped raise money for the community family through the Jingle Bell Festival. I would never be able to repay them for the care they gave my mom in the five years she spent there.
We are so fortunate to have wonderful caring facility in Medford to help our community with respite care and have a safe place to bring our loved ones. Thank you ma'am.
Councilor saying I'll be very brief. I think it's really important to clarify that this council has no plans has had no plans and we'll have no plans to cancel the jingle ball event. I believe that this arises out of a misunderstanding that.
of miscommunication that happened a few months ago, but having spoken to some, at least the councillors I've spoken to, there are no plans to cancel this event. And the council supports the mission of the Jingle Bell event as well. Thank you, Councillor Seng, and I really do ask that everyone please respect the rules of the council and my role as chair.
24-037 call for election presidential preferential primary Tuesday, March 5th, 2024. Be it ordered that the Elections Commission be and is hereby authorized and directed to notify and warn such of the inhabitants of the city of Medford as were qualified by law to vote for candidates at the presidential preferential primary on Tuesday, March 5th, 2024, to assemble at their polling places in their respective wards and precincts, then and there to give in their votes for presidential preference.
District Members of State Committee for each political party for the 2nd Middlesex Senatorial District. Members of the Party Ward Committee for the Democratic Ward Committee and the Republican Ward Committee. And the polls have said Presidential Preferential Primary shall open at 7 a.m. and remain open until 8 p.m.
be it further ordered that the following name polling places be and they are hereby designated for use at the presidential preferential primary on march 5th 2024 the said polling places to be open at 7 a.m to 8 p.m voting precincts ward 1 precinct 1 andrews middle school 3000 mystic valley parkway ward 1 precinct 2 firefighters club 340 salem street
Ward 2, Precinct 1, Roberts Elementary School, 35 Court Street. Ward 2, Precinct 2, Roberts Elementary School, 35 Court Street. Ward 3, Precinct 1, Medford American Legion, 321 Winthrop Street. Ward 3, Precinct 2, Temple Shalom, 475 Winthrop Street. Ward 4, Precinct 1, Tufts University Gantry Center Rear, 161 College Avenue. Ward 4, Precinct 2, and I want to note this will be at Waukland Court and is not being moved yet.
22 Waughlin Court, Auburn and North Street, Fondacaro Center. Ward 5, Precinct 1 and Ward 5, Precinct 2 at the Missittuck Elementary School, 37 Hicks Avenue. Ward 6, Precinct 1 at the West Medford Fire Station, 26 Harvard Avenue. Ward 6, Precinct 2 at the Brooks School, 388 High Street. Ward 7, Precinct 1, Mystic Valley Towers, North Building Entrance. Ward 7, Precinct 2, McGlynn K-8 Public School, 3004 Mystic Valley Parkway.
Ward 8, Precinct 1, Senior Center, 101 Riverside Avenue, and Ward 8, Precinct 2, South Medford Fire Station, 0 Medford Street. Chair Maloran and Member DiBenedetto of the Elections Commission, welcome. If there's anything you'd like to say.
None at all. You did a good job, Mr. President. And I love it. I love it. The only thing we're going to add is in addition to that presentation, we provided the council an election calendar year that will cover the match, that will cover September, that will cover November. The commission will come back again. We love you so much. We'll come back. Because we have to come back to present the warrant and the police
for acceptance after that, nothing else. We'll be, we get our schedule, it's noted on the calendar, which will be posted the next two days after presented to you. We're good to go. Wonderful, thank you, Mr. Chair. Member DiBenedetto, anything?
just happy that we're not moving for two and that we're able to maintain that location at Wakling Court for the primary election coming up. That would be a sin if I don't think personally, through the chair, council saying, you know, he brought blessing to us and he's done a lot of work with us, okay? We get Wakling Court. We don't know how much longer we're gonna have it, but we have it for much.
Fantastic. On the call to election, any comments from members of the council? Councillor Saini. I just wanted to thank you. I'm just happy to see that we were able to get Walkling Court for this election. I'm sure we'll be working a lot more moving forward on future ideas for polling locations and how we can make things work for our senior residents.
Thank you. Thank you, Councilor Sang. On this one, since it's a call for election, I'm going to ask the clerk to call the roll. So on the motion to issue the call for election, to order the election by the, is there a motion to approve by Councilor Sang, seconded by Vice President Collins. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
24-038, which is the election calendar. I'm just going to quickly read it if I get anything wrong. I'm not gonna read the whole thing. You can find it on the city website, but there are three elections this year. There's the presidential primary, March 5th, and there are seven days of early voting before that on the 24th, 25th, 26th, 26th, 27th, 28th. Leap year, 29th, and 1st of March. And then the election is March 5th. There's a state primary on September 3rd.
There's seven days of early voting for that. And then there is the general election on November 5th, 2024. And there's at least two weeks, 14 days of early voting for that. So that's the election calendar. And that can be found at the elections commission at medford-ma.gov. On the motion to receive and place on file, Councilor Scarpelli, seconded by Councilor Callahan. All those in favor? Opposed? The motion passes.
24-021. Resolution to support adult access and education for plant medicine. Offered by Councilor Lemming and Councilor Callahan.
Whereas the so-called war on drugs has led to unnecessary penalization, arrest, and incarceration of vulnerable people, particularly people of color and people of limited financial means, rather than prioritizing harm reduction policies to treat drug abuse as an issue of public health. And whereas ethniogenic plants and fungi such as psilocybin mushrooms, ayahuasca, ibogaine, and mescaline-containing cacti have been shown by peer-reviewed studies and indigenous practice to be beneficial,
for treating spiritual trauma, addiction, PTSD, depression, terminal illness, anxiety, and cluster headaches, among other conditions. And whereas, on average, we lose one of our neighbors in the Commonwealth to opioid overdose every week, as thousands of people we love struggle with addictions that ethniogenic plant medicine has been shown to alleviate,
And whereas seven Massachusetts communities, Somerville, Cambridge, Northampton, Easthampton, Amherst, Salem, and Provincetown, and nearly two dozen cities nationwide have passed measures directing an end to arrests for growing and sharing these plant medicines, embracing their inferred constitutional right to regulate public safety. That is outlined in the U.S. Department of Justice's Cole Memorandum that permitted localities to deprioritize enforcement of cannabis.
Oh boy, be it resolved that the Medford City Council hereby maintains the use and possession of all controlled substances should be understood first and primarily as an issue of public health and by all town entities and that no Medford employees should use any should emanate to city resources, city entities and city resources to assist in enforcement of laws criminalizing personal controlled substance possession.
Is there a motion to waive the remainder of the reading? Motion. Thank you, Councilor Sang, seconded by Councilor Callahan. All those in favor? Aye. Councilor Lemming?
Yes, thank you. So this is, I'd like to thank the council for considering this very long text. Essentially, this is just a resolution to decriminalize plant-based medicine. You know, these are not the same as opioids that cause a public health crisis.
They are non-addictive. They have been shown to be able to treat things like PTSD and addiction. This has already been done, as it said, by seven other Massachusetts communities, so we would be the eighth. This is meant to first encourage local law enforcement to deprioritize this issue. I don't believe that this council has the authority to outright
to decriminalize it, and it is meant to support the state-level initiative to do just that, which is currently being sponsored in the Massachusetts Senate by Senator Jalen. Just to clarify one part of this and offer a little bit of context is in the part of the reading that was waived. This resolution calls that the Bedford City Council, sorry,
to do well so okay so basically there are there's just for a little bit of context there are a couple of different ways to decriminalize this one of them and another avenue that is currently being pursued is a signature collection method which would basically create a an unelected commission that would add its own that if passed in massachusetts would add its own regulation to these plant medicines this has already been passed in
Oregon, and long story short, it's made the price of these plant medicines go between $1,000 and $3,000. So doing things this way through elected representatives would just help to decriminalize it and not create this sort of artificial price. So I think that this is a very important step forward to creating a nuanced and science-backed drug policy in the state of Massachusetts. And I'd like to thank this council for considering it.
Thank you, Councilor Lemming. Councilor Callahan. Councilor Lemming spoke quite well on this. Really, this is a, remember, this is a resolution. This is not an ordinance that we are passing. This is a statement of the views of the council on not prioritizing our law enforcement to spend resources, to arrest and, you know,
you know, sent for incarceration, people who simply have possession of such controlled substances. So given that and what Councillor Lemming said, I believe this resolution is a fairly reasonable state and there are many other cities that have passed something very similar.
Thank you, Councilor Callahan. Councilor Scarpelli? Thank you, Councilor Villescaz. I think any time that we present a resolution or an ordinance that has a level of detail that we talk about law enforcement, I think it'd be prudent for us to maybe send this to subcommittee, invite the chief or someone in his stead to give us their input as our, um,
the city of Medford to make sure that what we're voting on has the best interests of our police department and our safety of our citizens. I think that it would be, um, it would be, um.
a prudent solution to move this forward to get a little bit more information. What I read is, you know, it's information that's gathered, but I'd like to get more information before I would vote on this and really get the input of the chief where it's mentioned a few times that
the ramifications through the police department and getting their input. So I would recommend that we would move this to one of the subcommittees, Mr. President. I said a motion to refer to the public health and community safety. That'd be perfect. And with that ask a representative from the police department there to share their input. Yes. Okay. With the representative from the police department. Seconded by councilor Zaro. Is there further discussion? Councilor Collins.
Thank you, President Behrs. I appreciate my fellow counselors for bringing this forward. I certainly will be comfortable supporting the resolution tonight. I think it's also fine to discuss it more with relevant stakeholders and community members. For me, putting aside the medical and therapeutic uses associated with psychedelic plants, it's certainly not my belief that drug-related arrests and prosecutions should be a law enforcement priority, except when it comes to
some of the things specifically exempted in the resolution, such as unauthorized commercial sale, distribution of minors, driving under the influence. Recent history, I mean, not so recent history has shown us that criminalization of substances does not meaningfully advance public health and public safety. At the same time, this is a holistic issue, so I look forward to future discussion about it. Thank you. Thank you, Councilor Collins.
Was your microphone on? It's on. The light's on. All right. Yeah. Thank you. Shane. Thank you, Shane. Shane said yes. You couldn't hear him either, but I did. Any further comment from members of the council? Sorry, Mr. Cassidy, one moment.
Seeing none, we will take public participation. Two minutes each on the issue. If you'd like to speak on this issue, you may line up at the podium or raise your hand on Zoom. We will alternate between the podium and Zoom. Two minutes.
Name and address for the record, please. Patrick clerkin 50 Princeton Street. I'd like to start off by commending counselors Callahan and lemming for putting this motion forward. I am pretty passionate about history and I have learned about the history of the Cold War and the war on drugs and how they relate to this particular issue of entheogenic and psychedelic substances.
And I started really getting into this when I started noticing the trends and rises in depression and anxiety, chronic depression and anxiety, deaths of despair, the opioid crisis, as mentioned.
PTSD. And I heard about these trials that were being done at John Hopkins University, my curiosity, a lot of the people that suffered from these things saying that this was using some of these substances really psychologically healed them in a way that some of these holistically healed them in a way that some of these more kind of reductionists artificially derived substances like, like,
oxycontin would not do. And so I thought to myself, if I'm going to potentially advocate for these, I want to know more about them directly. Long story short, I myself ended up trying them. I tried ayahuasca several times, I tried 5-MeO-DMT psilocybin, and I come up here not to just drop that in front of everyone, but to say that
I can speak personally to their possibilities and their limitations, and I would put myself forward as someone who would help you to advance this. So, thank you. Thank you, Mr. Clerk.
And I apologize that we, I've been working on an RFP to fix the sound system in this room for several months, and I'm very frustrated that it hasn't been done yet. We do have hearing assistance devices available, and I believe the City Messenger and our videographer can provide those to assist if the sound quality in the room is not sufficient for people who are in attendance. No hands on Zoom, so we'll go to the podium. Name and address for the record, please.
I'll speak loud so everyone can hear me too. My name is James Davis and I live at 9 Cardington Street in Boston in Roxbury. And over the past two years, I've had the pleasure of meeting your neighbors, knocking on their doors, standing outside your lovely supermarkets to discuss psilocybin mushrooms and plant medicines.
They are nurses. They are parents. They are fellow baseball coaches. They are people who have found unbelievable healing from these plant medicines in a way that pharmaceutical drugs have not offered people an alternative.
Psilocybin mushrooms are the most studied pharmacological compound in US history, with thousands of studies published on their benefits and indigenous uses prior to their criminalization in 1970. In fact, they were criminalized because a whole generation that was being sent to Vietnam to die and fight a war that they did not agree with,
The government saw criminalizing cannabis and psychedelics as a way to target certain people politically. And indeed, it has. That's the history of US drug policy. A study of 44,000 Americans found that a single use of psilocybin mushrooms reduces the risk of opiate use disorder by 40%.
We are finding first responders, active military members, who are finding unbelievable relief by taking even microdoses that do not have hallucinogenic effects. You have 30 seconds, Mr. Davis. Thank you. For me, for my brother, for my family, and for Medford families that are struggling with addiction to alcohol, with addiction to food, this is a godsend. And by decriminalizing this,
You're saying to the people who are already growing their mushrooms, who are already talking to their therapist about it, that you don't want them to go to jail, and that this public health issue should not be a criminal one. Thank you very much. Thank you. Any further comment by members of the public or members on Zoom? Seeing no hands on Zoom, I'll go to any member in the room who would like to speak at the podium.
Mr. Castaneda, name and address for the record, please. Andrew Castaneda, Christian on East Medford. You have two minutes. Thank you. I'll make a list. Can you hear me? I am shocked and pleasantly surprised at this government finally catching on to try some other medicines that are totally natural. Of course,
I'm hearing a lot of good stories, especially I believe Matt works for the Mass General. He would know more than me because I'm a layman, although I'm a Woodstock graduate. I am so excited to see there'll be some possible natural remedies to maybe 35% of the population is my guesstimate.
And I'm sure I'm close, especially to my old buddies who are still alive, missing limbs with PTSD from the 1960s Vietnam War. Good luck. Thank you, Mr. Castanetti. Any further comments from members of the public? I see Grace Parker on Zoom, and then I'll come back to the podium. Grace, name and address for the record, please. You have two minutes.
Thank you. Hi, my name is Grace Parker. I live at 112 Bell Ave in Medford. I just wanted to express my support for what everyone has said so far. I am a researcher in the psychedelics space and I just wanted to
share that I'm also really glad to see that this resolution is being put forward. There is so much evidence that these plant medicines are safe and they are so effective. And so it's a huge unmet need, and I just would like to express my wholehearted support. Thank you. Thank you, Grace, and a model of a quick comment. Thank you.
podium. Name and address of the record, please. Sure thing. Nate Merritt, 373 Riverside Avenue, Medford. Councillor Lemming, are you still in the Navy?
Yes. Okay. Um, so some of us are bound based on our jobs, so on and so forth, whether or not we can use controlled substances. Isn't that correct? I mean, you have the UCMJ, which you have to abide by for certain rules. Others like FAA pilots, right? Anyone with a DOT license. And there's a reason for that. And I'm not opposed to this at all. I guess I would just want to caution this council before we start. I'm concerned number one about distribution and what distribution means in your measure.
Because as the parent of a child I can tell you, I can't even give my toddler cough medicine. I wish I could. I can't. So, I think there's some nuances that really need to be addressed which is why I'm glad that y'all are bringing it to committee, because there's always the unintended consequences.
And just to think about that there are reasons that sometimes people don't think of why certain things are controlled and this and that are certain situations. So just before we wholeheartedly say this is great, everyone should have it all the time. I really hope that the council will heed law enforcement and maybe others too, and that there's a time and a place for everything. I'm not opposed to this, but I also don't like blankly saying, sure, it's great for everyone all the time.
because I'm pretty sure nobody would want the pilot of your airplane on a controlled substance at any period of time, especially if it's a psychedelic one. That's all, thank you. Thank you, Mr. Merritt. I will go to Councilor Lemming and then Councilor Kelly.
I just want to clarify that. So the US military is regulated federally. So I am personally subject to urinalysis several times a year. So I haven't personally tried these things. But in my day job, I'm also a neuroscientist. So I don't study plant medicine directly. So my colleagues have. And I've talked with experts who have also
uh specialize in this themselves so I would so I think that if you know if this were to go to committee for further discussion we like um I guess I guess my I guess my
My concern with that is that this is more of a statewide issue. And so it's really trying to support it at that level. I would assume that if seven other Massachusetts towns have also passed similar resolutions, then they're
their law enforcement is not so uniquely different from Medford that Medford has some unique public health considerations specific to this city. So I and you know, if it were all if it were referred to committee, I would also encourage us to speak not only to law enforcement, but to also, um,
public health experts, people who specifically study this, people who specifically study this, and other stakeholders as well. I personally would like it to be voted on tonight, but obviously if that isn't the will of this council, then it would go to committee. Councillor Callahan.
Thank you. As a co sponsor of this, it clearly is important to me that we do consider the spirit of what we're trying to do here. But I also want to mention that this is a fairly long resolution, and it includes a couple of state
recommendations about state policy. And I want to ensure that other counselors have had the time to consider those policies and to consider the entire text. And that I also mentioned this because I am the first in the alphabet, which means that I have to state what I'm going to do first. And that's simply to say to my fellow counselors that I would definitely respect people's desires to have time and committee
to understand the issue more. And I will, as a co-sponsor, make sure that this does move through committee. But I just want to state that I'd love to hear from other counselors in terms of whether sending it to committee is something that you would prefer.
Councilor Sang. Thank you. It's my reading of this resolution that it essentially is a recommendation for the city, for the police department on a policy, but it's not creating policy of our own. And so I'd be fine voting with it tonight, especially seeing that the police chief will still be the final arbiter of what the policy is. I think
We've talked a lot about the science of it, I'm not going to delve into that too deep, but I would be okay with this going either way tonight, either sending it to committee or to are just voting it out tonight, because it is essentially a.
It's a rung above symbolic, but it's not us imposing policy. I think it's to the public comment earlier, I just looked up what the definitions of distribution are in these laws. They don't involve what we were afraid of. They don't involve sale or anything like that. And so
I or I guess I guess Yeah, so I would be happy with this going going forward, but I defer to the sponsors on the motion unless there's further comment. The motion by Councillor Scarpelli, seconded by Councillor Lazaro to send this to committee public health and community safety committee. All those in favor. I think that's for
I'm gonna ask for a roll call. I just, it's right down the middle. Ms. Clerk, please call the roll. To refer to committee. Councilor Kelly. Yes. Vice President Collins. Yes. Councilor Lazaro. Yes. Councilor Lemming.
Councilor Scarpello? Yes. Councilor Sanchez? Yes. President Rivera? No, if I'm in the affirmative, two in the negative, the motion passes and the item is referred to the Public Health and Community Safety Committee. 24-035. Yes, Councilor Strunk? I need to correct something, because I embarrassedly, I just got text with a couple of threats.
Mr. O'Brien did not retire. We received information from a colleague of his saying that he retired. But the truth of the matter is, Mrs. O'Brien sent me a message and said, no, George, Pat was given a circle of honor award for his safe driving in the city of Medford. So please, Pat,
I won't come home tonight. He is not retiring. If someone could reach out to his bosses, he'll be in work tomorrow. So please forgive me. I make one mistake a year and that was it. So thank you. We'll get that amended for the records. And for the public, if you would like to prank this council, email councilor. 24-035 offered by Vice President Collins. Resolution in support. Council Vice President Collins.
Thank you, President Behrs. I've put forward an amended version of the resolution. I would motion to amend the resolution and adopt the revised language. A copy is in front of, sorry, a copy of the amended resolution is in front of all councilors and in the hands of the clerk. I would motion to amend the resolution and adopt the new language and have it read into the record.
On the motion to amend the resolution to the copy before the council and the clerk, after which I will read it and it will be presented. So on the motion to use the amended language for the purposes of discussion of the paper by Vice President Collins, seconded by Councilor Callahan. All those in favor? Aye.
Opposed? Motion passes. 24-035 offered by Vice President Collins, whereas the Medford City Council recognizes and affirms the sanctity, preciousness, and equality of all human life, and whereas on October 7, 2023, the terrorist group Hamas killed over 1,200 Israeli residents, took over 240 hostages, committed a terrific atrocities, displaced families, wreaked untold grief and trauma upon the civilian population of Israel,
and have continued to attack Israeli civilians, injuring hundreds in rocket attacks since October 7th, and whereas since those horrific attacks, the ongoing Israeli military campaign and blockade has created a humanitarian crisis of catastrophic proportions in Gaza, and whereas since October 7th,
The Israeli military has killed over 26,000 Palestinians in Gaza, injured over 62,000, and more than 85% of all Gaza residents have been displaced. And whereas the ongoing military campaign has had a horrific toll on civilians in Gaza, with UNICEF describing the Gaza Strip as the, quote, world's most dangerous place to be a child, and reporting that 40% of all deaths in Gaza have been deaths of children, and whereas the Israeli military has launched more than 22,000 airstrikes at Gaza,
resulting in the destruction of over 70% of all homes and schools, and most of its civilian infrastructure, including electricity, communications, water, sewer, and sanitation systems, with the World Health Organization reporting that all Gazan hospitals have been destroyed or seriously damaged, exacerbated the humanitarian crisis, and
whereas the near total siege on Gaza has prevented the delivery of life-saving humanitarian aid, and whereas the World Food Program has reported that all 2.2 million people in Gaza are facing crisis levels of food insecurity, that one in four Gazans is facing catastrophic hunger, and that without an end to bombardment and resumption of humanitarian aid, famine will spread quickly across the population and
whereas humanitarian organizations report that the Israeli military kills an average of 250 Palestinians each day, almost all civilians, and that these deaths are a direct result of airstrikes, the blockade of basic food and medical aid, and the destruction of hospitals and basic shelter, which are war crimes, and whereas Hamas continues to hold over 100 Israeli civilians hostage and target Israeli civilians, which are war crimes, and whereas Israel continues to detain thousands of Palestinians who have never been charged with or convicted of a crime,
including scores of children. And whereas on October 26, 2023, the United Nations General Assembly adopted a resolution calling for an immediate, durable, and sustained humanitarian truce between Israeli forces and Hamas militants in Gaza, and numerous international humanitarian organizations have similarly called for a sustained ceasefire. And whereas the previous ceasefire from November 24 to November 30, 2023, allowed for the release of some Israeli hostages, some Palestinian detainees,
and allowed emergency aid and fuel to enter Gaza and whereas the history of Israel and Palestine since 1948 includes systemic displacement of Palestinians and occupation of Palestine, the imposition of illegal blockades upon and denial of basic civil and human rights to Palestinian civilians.
ongoing and escalating terrorism and violent attacks by Israeli soldiers and settlers against Palestinian civilians in the occupied West Bank, and extremist violence aimed at Israeli civilians, and whereas many members of the Medford community are suffering from trauma, grief, shock, and fear compounded by recent
increased incidence of anti-Semitism, Islamophobia, and anti-Palestinian racism, both nationally and locally. And whereas members of the Medford community, including Palestinians and Jews, are speaking out for peace in Israel and Palestine, and in support of a permanent bilateral ceasefire and a return of all hostages, innocent detainees, and political prisoners, now, therefore,
Be it resolved by the Medford City Council that we support an enduring bilateral ceasefire in Israel and Gaza and the immediate return of all hostages, innocent detainees, and political prisoners. Be it further resolved by the Medford City Council that we unequivocally condemn all violence against civilians, including the attacks by Hamas on October 7, 2023 against Israeli civilians, the Israeli military campaign against Gaza that continues to unleash disproportionate violence against Palestinian civilians,
attacks by Israeli settlers against Palestinian civilians in the occupied West Bank, and all attacks by all parties against civilians. Be it further resolved by the Medford City Council that we support the lifting of the blockade and the uninhibited provision of life-saving humanitarian aid to Gaza. Be it further resolved by the Medford City Council that we
We affirm the inalienable right of all people to live in peace, free from fear of harm and prejudice, be it further resolved by the Medford City Council that we unequivocally condemn all xenophobic violence, attacks, and rhetoric, and affirm the inalienable right of all people to know safety and acceptance, regardless of their religion, race, ethnicity, nationality, or skin color.
be it further resolved by the Medford City Council that we urge the Biden administration, the United States Senate, and the United States Congress to exert the full extent of their power, influence, and funding to bring about an enduring ceasefire, the uninhibited provision of humanitarian aid, and the release of all hostages and detained innocents,
Be it further resolved that a copy of this resolution be sent to each member of Medford's federal delegation, that's Senator Warren, Senator Markey, and Representative Clark, and to President Biden, urging them to use their power and influence to bring about a sustained and enduring ceasefire so as to protect and honor all human life. Vice President Collins. Thank you, President Behrs. Thank you for reading all of that into the record.
I want to briefly speak to why I'm putting forth an amended resolution from what was submitted to be incorporated in the Council's formal agenda. After I put forward the resolution last week, I was contacted by many constituents who urged me to reconsider the language before us.
With an issue such as this, it is critical to speak with as much clarity and precision as possible, even when and especially when it's uncomfortable. I was called upon to amend this resolution to more authentically and faithfully represent the harms endured on both sides of the Israel and Palestinian border. In addition, while the ultimate ask of this resolution is for an immediate and enduring bilateral ceasefire, I was also called upon to not let the historical context go unsaid and unacknowledged.
I thank everybody who got in touch with me from the original request to put forward a ceasefire resolution to the many people who gave me feedback and worked with me to improve it.
Despite my note about updating the language of this resolution, I also want to put forth a disclaimer that I don't believe I personally have the ability or maybe it's simply not possible to talk about this issue in a way that does not leave one group or another at risk of feeling diminished or blamed or impoverished.
If you are feeling that way, please blame me or blame the insufficiency of language to talk about an issue that is breaking all of our hearts and has been breaking all of our hearts for decades, and most especially many people in this room. And thank you for being here.
I want to speak briefly to why I elected to bring this resolution forward, apart from the fact that I was contacted by constituents to do so, that being the ultimate reason. I am Jewish. My ancestors on both sides came to America in the early 1900s because Eastern Europe wasn't safe for them. My last name is Collins because my great-grandfather couldn't get a job with a Jewish last name. My family knows that anti-Semitism is real and it is dangerous.
I believe that past hardship and trauma and persecution are never valid nor meaningful, but we can seek to make past trauma and hardship, we can seek to get something out of that if we put that experience in service of other people and stand in solidarity with other people who are also facing oppression and persecution.
Now we see a right-wing government using the grief of Jewish people, like me, and the name of Jewish people to justify the destruction of an entire civilian population in Gaza. There are no words that can adequately capture this horror, pain, and injustice. This resolution is long, but the ask is simple. Our US government is deeply entwined with and invested in the Israeli military. Our federal leaders have the influence, the power, and the purse strings to hasten an end to the killing.
This issue is painful and divisive, more for some than for others. But ultimately, this resolution is about safety, and I believe that should unify us. Marginalizing Palestinians, whether legally, physically, or in the media, advances no one's safety. It's simply not right, and I would defy anyone to tell me that the mass murder, displacement, and destruction in Gaza will leave Israeli residents more safe from violent extremism.
Some people would question the validity of city-level resolutions about this issue. To me, this is a Medford issue because Medford residents are invested in the issue. And while the U.S. government condones the killing and sends unrestricted military aid to Israel, communities right here in the U.S. are starved for funding.
If you attend any average city council meeting, what you'll hear us talk about ultimately is how there aren't enough public dollars to pay for resident services, fully funded schools, affordable housing, road safety, and on and on. Meanwhile, our federal leaders authorized billions to help bomb kids in Gaza. I find that
I find it unfathomable on a human level, and I find it infuriating as a counselor. Those dollars should be promoting wellness at home, not destruction abroad.
I hope that we can find unity in the unacceptability of this oppression and this loss of life, and in demanding an immediate and lasting de-escalation and ceasefire in Gaza. I hope that we as a council can join the groundswell of city councils, amplifying their residents' calls for ceasefire, and add Medford's voice to the chorus for peace. I hope we can find unity in diminishing no one's suffering and trauma, and in demanding safety and peace for all. Thank you.
Thank you, Vice President Collins. Councillor Callaghan. Because I work for a 501C3 organization that takes a position on a ceasefire in Israel and Gaza, among other things, I have filed a disclosure form with the city clerk, but I have been advised by the State Ethics Commission that I am able to vote on this issue. Thank you, Councillor Callaghan. Any further discussion by members of the council? Councillor Lemming.
I'd just like to say that many members of this community, people I consider to be very close friends have encouraged me to vote in favor of this resolution. What I will say is that
I'm an officer in the U.S. military. The Hatch Act does technically allow reservists to comment on these sorts of matters when not on active duty. It is my belief, however, that even though I do commend my colleague for writing a
very thorough and very well said resolution that voting on this resolution would adversely impact my ability to do my job. So I just want to put that out there, and I will be abstaining from this. Thank you, Councilor Lemming.
Councilor Scarpelli. Thank you, Councilor Villescaz and thank you, Vice President Collins. I think that I'm going to
bring us back to a few sessions ago, and I made a commitment that for one councilor, I would stand with the policy that I will not vote on any national or international vote that comes to this council. I think we have so many issues right now within our community that I think our focus really needs to be on the measures of Medford right now. I know that, you know,
the information will go out there that Councilor Scott Peli doesn't believe in this, or Councilor Scott Peli's belief is X or Y. The truth of the matter is, everybody is in favor of peace. And I've had the opportunity to talk to so many
great residents of method both from Palestine that are in support of this resolution, that are from that are Jewish that are supporting this resolution, and a Jewish residents that are totally against this resolution. So I found that this one resolution gave me the opportunity to listen to some amazing people that she had some amazing thoughts.
And what I find it more important is that we have an avenue to bring some very, very educated people that have their own thought process to come together and unite them, and then come back with a message that I will personally work with, that we can contact the people that have contacted me, bring my friends together, and then send a message together. Because one thing that I've realized and something Medford doesn't need,
This is another piece dividing our community. So no matter what anybody votes or how they vote tonight, there's going to be a half that's really separated. And that's not from my opinion, my own opinion, my beliefs, but this is my opinion from the multiple phone calls I got.
I did receive messages from people that asked me that if they could, if I could read something into the record or a statement to the record, and I on both sides, I, I recommend a recommended my Palestinian friends to send any messages they wanted me to read on the record. I've asked my friends on who feel that this isn't a resolution that they feel safe on that I would share the information show. So if, if you would allow me I have
I have, if you wouldn't mind, I just have some as well. Could we let councilor speak and then can we come back to the reading into the record piece? Is that okay?
It's uncharacteristic, Councilor Baez, that usually we... I'd just like to treat all public participation the same, if that's all right. This is a public participation. This is the council speaking as part of the record. Are you reading other people's statements in the record? I am. All right, I am. Okay. So if you'd like to do that, I'll... If that's all right. I'll yield to you and then come back. I have some from others. If I could just go to... Let every councilor say their piece, then I'll go right back to you after councilors have spoken to read other statements into the record. You'll be first in line.
Councilor say. Thank you, President bears. Um, my focus as a city councilor in this job as a candidate who ran for city council who first ran for city council, um, just over two years ago, um, who started the campaign almost three years ago. The
biggest issue going up at going in my brain at that time was fighting to make sure that our residents that all of our residents felt safe and not only just safe, but welcome and included and engaged in our city government. I grew up, obviously, my
My skin color makes me look different from other people. I grew up oftentimes as someone who felt excluded, as someone who didn't necessarily feel completely represented in government. And for me, that was a driving factor to get involved in government and to make sure that we built a local government that reflected the desires of its people, that the
push for equity and for justice, and to make sure that that push was reflected in our actions as well. And at the end of the day, to make sure that all of our residents feel safe and welcome here in our city. It's with that spirit that after the horrifying attacks on October 7th, I reached out to Jewish, Arab, and Muslim community leaders to make sure that, at least from my office, that they
felt safe, that they felt welcomed and included, and knowing that there were growing incidents of anti-Semitic and Islamophobic and xenophobic attacks and incidents in this community to make sure that they have the resources they need and needed and still need to feel safe and welcome in our city.
Um, as situations on the ground, um, have developed, uh, more residents of various backgrounds, including a large number of, uh, Jewish, personally very close Jewish friends begged me as a city councilor to vote yes, um, when a ceasefire resolution, if a ceasefire resolution came across my desk. And through those discussions, I realized that not voting, not doing anything is, um, an action in itself.
And so, and for so many of our residents, they need to see that their elected officials align with the values that we espouse as candidates and that we espouse as politicians. When I look at this resolution, I look at the first and last lines.
recognizing and celebrating the sanctity, the preciousness, the equality of human life. Looking at the last line cites the core purpose of this resolution as to reaffirm that we stand with protecting and honoring all human life.
This is undoubtedly a difficult situation, but I really do commend Councillor Collins for keeping the focus in this resolution on the sanctity of life.
for keeping the focus of this resolution through hope on equality, bringing in stakeholders from many, many different parts of this community, hearing opposition to different drafts of this resolution. I know the vice president has worked really, really hard on a product that best captures that inclusive energy and spirit that we want to see in our city.
For me, again, the local aspect of this is that, is just that. It is the quality of letting our residents know that we stand with these values.
when I also think about why this resolution is necessary. I realize that, you know, while this isn't necessarily, you know, obviously, I don't think anyone is under the illusion that we ourselves as Medford City Council is going to stop war in the Middle East, but
I do think that many, many folks, many residents, neighbors, activists have felt disillusioned, disheartened, and in despair after various and numerous attempts to reach out to federal and state level stakeholders on this issue, people with influence. And they're coming to the Medford City Council, they're coming to City Hall tonight, because they recognize that there aren't many avenues left.
We are, in many ways, one of the last stops that people are going to, to ask us, to beg us to help them get their message across to our federal electeds.
I think we really need to try, in any case, be it Gaza, be it a local issue about a park or a street or a sidewalk. We as elected officials, as the Medford City Council, have a responsibility to amplify the community's desires to speak to federal elected officials. That's our job. We do it on different issues. We reach out to Congress people. We reach out to state reps to help us resolve things. This is our job.
I, you know, I think there's a crisis of faith in democracy when people don't feel hurt by their elected officials, and I think we need to work to restore that faith in our country. Thank you, Councilor Sang. Any further comments by members of the Council?
Seeing none, as the president and the chair, I will not be, I will be voting, but I will not be participating in debate as I move us through this resolution. And I hope everyone can appreciate that that is my role. Now we will go to hear from, if anyone would like to read anything into the record, I know we have Councilor Scarpelli has a number of items. I have an item. Are there any other councilors would like to read any statements into the record that they received?
Councilor Scarpelli, and I appreciate your deference to me. No, I completely understand. This is a topic that I respect from all my fellow councilors. I think that anything that you've said, I don't think any of us disagree. I think it's very important that everybody understand this. We have a council that is very cordial and respectful, and this isn't an easy and a simple issue that has a simple outcome. But I will tell you, as Councilor Sagan mentioned,
the communication I received from our constituents that felt the need that were scared to come out tonight, that really wanted to understand that
what is being said so far, they're feeling the opposite. They feel that with this motion moving forward, that it hurts what we have in our community of bringing people together. So again, not my view, I'm explaining what residents have reached out to me and asked that I share. One person that I respect,
A former teacher of mine, who has been living in Israel for many, many years now, reached out with a comment. He said, while nobody here wants to see any more death, people must remember that on October 6, there was a ceasefire agreement in effect that was holding well. However, on October 7, Hamas terrorists violated the ceasefire and attacked
kibbutzim, villages, and a music festival murdering 1,200 Israeli, including not only Jews, but Muslims, Christians, Jews, Americans, Thais, Russians, British, among others. While mutilating many bodies, burning some alive in ovens, and raping countless women, there were people ranging in ages eight to 87 years old.
There was among over 230 kidnapped people that were brought back to Gaza, of which 136 are still being held. If they are alive, we still have questions. Since Hamas has not allowed the IRC to visit the hostages, we have no idea how any of them are doing. A ceasefire resolution only gives confidence to Hamas that they are winning the war in the West and makes it harder to get the hostages, the bodies, back.
Plus, Israel will not accept a ceasefire unless includes a return of all hostages and bodies as well as leadership of Hamas being sent into exile to a country that will accept them. Unless those conditions happen, it doesn't matter how many cities or states or countries vote for a ceasefire. Israel will not accept it. So I think that whether you believe in it or not, these are messages that come from families of Medford. We have another that was sent
that wanted to reach out in the statement. Forgive me that they're longer, but to members of the council and those in attendance, thank you for listening to this statement. The months since 10-7 have been extremely tight trying for the Jewish community. We experienced a predominantly attack on the brothers and sisters solely because they are Jewish.
It brings back haunting memories of when this was commonplace not more than a century ago. We are slaughtered not for the military advantage, not for political maneuvering, but because we're Jewish. The only thing different today is that there is a country and an army that will push back and defend us. In the World War Two during the programs in Russia,
and the inquisitions across Liberia and in ups or uprisings like Farhoud in Middle East, we were defenseless. But today in the first time in 2000 years, we have the ability to stand up and push back against the Jew haters that are attempting to alienate us.
In the latest, we have experienced rapidly rising anti-Semitism, including here at home, with genocide chants down the street at Harvard, and anti-Zionists who, by definition, call the destruction of the Jewish homeland in Israel. We hear louder and louder every day the warning signals that Jews are no longer safe, coupled with the thousands upon thousands who celebrated our deaths on 10-7. We are scared.
We cannot trust our local officials to stand against anti-Semitism, and we cannot trust our fellow citizens when we see them marching in the streets calling for more Jewish deaths. Our concerns are not heard. Our safety is ignored. And this ceasefire resolution before you is a symbol that you are telling Jews to once again not push back, not fight for the survival, but lay down and take it. That is what we hear when there are calls for Israel to call off the war against those who started this in the Battle of 10-7.
During World War II, we did not have a ceasefire for Nazis or Imperial Japan, despite the horrific amount of civilian death in the war and aggression the Axis started. There was no ceasefire against Al Qaeda 9-11, and the worldwide Jewish community will not abide the ceasefire with the Hamas. The common thread here is that there cannot be a ceasefire
with groups whose entire reason for existence is ideological mass murder. The only type of viable, long-term, and durable ceasefire is one where Hamas' war-making ability is destroyed. Only then can Israeli lives and security of the Palestinians can be free from an Islamic dictatorship. A ceasefire that leaves Hamas in place is a banned
band-aid upon a cancer. It may save some lives in the short term, but guarantees more war, death, and destruction down the road. Hamas officials have promised to repeat the genocide of 10-7 again and again. Israel will be forced to continue to defend their citizens. Hamas will continue to try to kill Jews and hide behind their own Gaza subjects. Jews, Arabs, Israelis, Palestinians, all will suffer until Hamas is no longer
poses a threat. And even after this, there is those who are still not swayed by the existential fear of Jewish constituents face. I leave you with this. Why is the council taking such a stand? What is it about
this war that is exceptionally different from all the other conflicts raging in the world, that makes it worth splitting a community further alienated, an already fearful minority, just to issue a statement about a handful of these beliefs.
How does this serve the interests of Medford residents? And what message do you think will be heard for your actions today? Thank you for listening to these concerns. So I will tell you, I've shared some amazing conversations from my Palestinian friends that it was a great understanding, something that I will never understand the,
the feelings that you have. I could never, no one here, unless you're Palestinian or Jewish in Israel and understand the situation we're going through. So to minimize that, to minimize that, to minimize that would be disrespectful. But I will tell you that there is
a ground movement moving forward that I will gladly move forward with, with my friends that I've now worked with, that bringing our Palestinian people and our Jewish residents to find a clear message that we can work together, that could present to this community, that it's more of a unified front. And I think that that's what's important here in Medford today.
So again, whether it's popular or not, that's not my intent here. I have a strong belief in what I believe in when it comes to issues dealing with national, international issues. I'm gonna abstain from any votes. I will not vote for anything on any agenda that comes forth in this council. I've done this in the past, and I'll do this moving forward.
That doesn't mean George Scott Pelley doesn't believe in peace. That doesn't mean that George Scott Pelley doesn't believe that there isn't a way to unify our community. But this is who I am, who my residents have requested their information be spread. And I thank you for the time, Mr. President.
Thank you, Councillor Scarpelli. I'm going to read a statement that we received a call here at City Hall from a resident who has to make a statement in support of 24035 resolution in support of a ceasefire in Israel and Gaza. The caller is a Medford resident of over 15 years, married to an Arab American and mother of two children are also of Arab heritage. She supports the resolution filed by Vice President Collins for a ceasefire in Israel and Gaza. She has friends directly impacted who have lost dozens and dozens of family members
a ceasefire is what's best for all people and would prevent wider escalation of wars and suffering in the region. The caller asked to remain anonymous for the safety of her family. So we've heard a number of opinions tonight. We are going to hear opinions that we disagree with tonight. Votes are going to be taken that we may disagree with tonight. I deeply ask everyone to respect
the rules of the council, my role as chair, and we're gonna try to hear from everyone. We're gonna go, there's no end point. I've been here till 2.30 in the morning before. Maybe we'll be here tonight if everyone in this room wants to speak for two minutes. But when we speak, we're going to listen for two minutes. I'm going to give a 30 second warning.
And I really please ask folks not to interrupt or try to disrupt the speech of anyone. Again, we are going to hear things that we disagree with tonight. I stand here very often and hear things I disagree with. And I do try my very, very best not to react. And I ask just that we hold that level of respect for everyone as they speak tonight.
We'll hear from everyone. A vote on some motion will be taken on this resolution, and that will be how this process goes. So as I said, we can have folks line up here at the podium if they would like to speak. We will alternate also with Zoom. If people are on Zoom, please raise your hand on Zoom, and we will go back and forth between the podium and Zoom as hands are raised. Everyone will have two minutes. I will begin a timer after I ask folks to introduce themselves.
If you would like to just provide the city that you live in versus your street address, you may do so. But I will ask for name and city of residence and address if you are comfortable sharing your address. It looks like we're gonna have a lot of comments. So again, as I did before, and as you all saw the role of this chair, I'm going to ask you to stop at two minutes and I really please ask that you respect that. We cool with that?
All right, thank you very much. And we're gonna start at the podium. Name and address for the record, please. We'll make sure we can hear you. And you will have two minutes once you've said your name. Muneer Germanis. I live at 3 Summit Road in Medford. Thank you, Muneer. I was born in Jerusalem, Palestine, prior to the creation of the State of Israel.
and I'm a survivor of the ethnic cleansing of Palestine in 1948, which has been ongoing for the past 75 years and has drastically increased in the past few months. Apparently, when my ancestors became Christians, we lost our rights to our house and land according to Israeli law.
By training, I'm a physicist with a PhD in physics from Tufts University, and I'm a naturalized citizen that has called Medford home for the past 40 years. I was ordained as an elder at the Presbyterian Church, Clarendon Hill in Somerville, and I served on its ruling session for approximately 30 years.
I was also a member of the Medford Human Rights Commission and served as chair for a few years. I am currently a member of Mass Peace Action, Jewish Voice for Peace, as well as Safe Medford and Medford People Power. I'm here tonight to urge each and every member of this council to support this resolution
which is aimed at ending the nightmare in Gaza and Israel with a huge number of bombs, missiles, and drone attacks that our government is funding from our tax dollars. This is a human rights issue that concerns all of us in this room, in this city, and in this country.
Two months ago, I contacted our human rights commission to discuss issuing a statement about this conflict and its effect on our community, similar to what other human rights commissions in neighboring cities have done. But the commission was not allowed to even discuss this without permission from the city solicitor.
I'm grateful that this Council is not restricted in this manner and thankful for the opportunity to discuss this in a public forum. Thanks again for allowing me to speak tonight and once more I urge and implore you to vote for this resolution. Thank you.
We have some hands raised on Zoom. I'm going to go to Steve Schnapp. Steve, I'm going to unmute you, ask you for your name, and you can provide your address or your city, and then I will give you a 30-second warning and a 10-second warning. My name is Steve Schnapp. I live at 36 Hillside Ave. in Medford Square. I want to address the relevance of this resolution to me as a Medford resident and the concern that Councilor Scarpelli and others have raised about that.
I was born in February 1946, just after World War II ended. I had two uncles in the military, one of whom fought in the Battle of the Bulge, and he was in the advanced forces that liberated several concentration camps. He was featured in Steven Spielberg's documentary of the Holocaust. The Holocaust was very present in my family. My mother gave me the Hebrew name Shalom, which means peace.
And she did that because she wanted to recognize that this atrocity should never happen again. I'd like to read a quote that addresses the relevance of this resolution.
Every gun that is made, every warship launched, every rocket fired signifies, in the final sense, a theft from those who hunger and are not fed, those who are cold and are not clothed.
The world in arms is not spending money alone. It is spending the sweat of its laborers, the genius of its scientists, the hopes of its children, and the hopes of its children. The cost of one modern heavy bomber is this, a modern school in more than 30 cities. It's two electric power plants, each serving towns of 60,000 population.
It is to find fully equipped hospitals. It is some 50 miles of concrete pavement. We pay for a single fighter plane with a half million bushels of wheat. We pay for a single destroyer with new homes that could have housed more than 8,000 people. Steve, thank you very much. That was Dwight David Eisenhower. Thank you, Steve. We're going to go to the podium.
Name and address for the record, and then I'll give you two minutes. Naila Germanis, 3 Summit Road, Medford, Manhattan. Thank you, you have two minutes. I have been a resident of Medford for 40 years. My children went to Medford public schools and graduated from high school there. I was born in Lebanon and came to Tufts University as a graduate student. I have been a U.S. citizen for 40 years.
In 1982, I planned to visit my parents with my infant, but was urged not to travel because within four days of the Israeli invasion of Lebanon, the Israeli army had occupied my village, a Christian village halfway into Lebanon, near Beirut, surrounded by Muslim and Druze villages, where we lived in harmony with our neighbors. The Israelis came to divide and conquer.
Daily, they would bomb the neighboring villages and would tell people in my village to hide, expecting retaliation. My brothers fled with their families, and we were scattered in different parts of the world. My uncle stayed with my parents to take care of them, but he died during one of the Israeli bombings. My parents had to leave home, taking very little with them.
Every home in our village was destroyed. Our home was hit by 18 rockets. My mother died, never saw her home again. My mother-in-law died alone in a nursing home, having been displaced twice. Once in 1948 from her home in Jerusalem, Palestine. And then, they were brutally forced by the Israelis. My children... 30 seconds.
My children grew up yearning for family presence in their lives. Israel destroyed entire neighborhoods, hospitals, schools, and shelters in Gaza. What happened to us cannot be compared to this horrific assault on Gaza. My son-in-law's family was seeking shelter in the church in Gaza City. You have 10 seconds. The Greek Orthodox Church was bombed and nine members of his family died. My son-in-law.
Israel is not allowing food, water, or medications into Gaza. Mothers are malnourished, can't nurse their newborn children. This must stop. Your vote is very important. Thank you very much. I'm going to go to Kate Wall on Zoom. You will have two minutes. Please provide your name and city or address for the record, please.
My name is Kate Wall. I live at 71 Winchester Street. I'll be really brief. I just want to say I completely support this resolution and hope that the council will as well. I think the stories of these people we've heard so far speak for themselves. That's all. Thank you, Kate. Back to the podium, your name and address or city for the record, please.
My name is Suhad Zinda. I live on 5 Essex, Medford Street. I've been a resident of Medford for almost 20 years. My family lives in Gaza. I came to Medford from Gaza City. I came here as an undergrad, I came here as a student, and now I'm an educator on Tufts Medford campus.
I chose Medford to raise my family because of its diverse community and because that's where I felt safe. It was my first time living in a city, experiencing a city without cement walls, without barbed wires or checkpoints.
I saw trophies here after the Israeli government tightened its siege on Gaza in 2001, which revoked my movement permit to return to Gaza and be with my family ever since.
I was living only an hour and 40 minutes away as an undergrad at Birzeit University in the West Bank when they did that. It took me four full years in order to bring my family to the United States and reunite with them on a different continent. It was easier than seeing them and being with my family who live an hour and 40 minutes away from me, only because they were in Gaza, only because of our ethnicity. You have 30 seconds.
Okay, today, the rest of my family members, my extended family members, remain in Gaza. 14 of them are still under, are beneath the rubble of their home. Since October 18th, 127 of my family members, of the Zindah family members, remain missing until today. The last I heard from them was the 10th of December. Sorry, I'm out of breath.
10 seconds of my life. 10 seconds. I have a cousin last week who had to go through an emergency C-section without any medication and with no sutures afterwards. And today she's struggling to keep her premature baby safe because there are no incubators. This carnage must stop now. Enough is enough. I implore you to... I implore you.
Please, I implore you to push this forward. Thank you so much. We're going to go back to Zoom. We're going to go to Lara Germanis on Zoom. I will unmute you. Please provide your name and address for the record. And then I will give you a 30 second warning and a 10 second warning.
um hello and thank you my name is lara germanis and i am a resident of the city of malden but i grew up in medford i'm a physician um and i am also uh have worked in humanitarian crises um i grew up going to the medford public schools and there i experienced anti-arab racism which was scarring at a magnet school with a diversity curriculum anti-arab racism was so normal that it wasn't even considered racism
My father, whom you heard from tonight, didn't even tell me I was Palestinian, to protect me from that. It is this deep anti-Arab, anti-Muslim racism that is being blasted by our nation's most powerful publications and politicians, like the New York Times that just printed a piece calling Arabs insects, that is being used to justify genocide in Gaza right now.
killing over 11,500 children and orphaning 19,000. And we, right now, as American taxpayers, are paying for a second Nakba, like the original Nakba, when the 750,000 Palestinians were forced from their homes and displaced and killed by Zionist militias to create the modern state of Israel in 1948.
This did not start on October 7th. People were living on land. They were killed. Their homes and villages were destroyed. And now we are watching the same live and much faster on social media. And we are paying for it with our tax dollars. During the first Nakba, which means catastrophe in Arabic, my father's family fled to Egypt. They packed up their house in Jerusalem.
yes and we're not allowed to return to my father's house because we are christian this is not a religious issue it's not divisive if you vote against ceasefire you vote for the deaths of the remaining 2.2 palestinians 2.2 million palestinians in gaza
Massachusetts sends over $140 million a year to Israel. We could use that money to pay for subsidizing 75% of treatment for all Massachusetts lung cancer patients. We're fully sponsoring assisted living for 2,000 seniors. Instead, we're using it to rush bunker buster bombs to Israel, the world's fourth most powerful military.
and we must stop it now. We are essential. Our voice is essential. Clark is our representative. She's close to Biden. This is a very, very critical message from this city today. I urge you to vote yes. Thank you. We're going to go to the podium. We're going to go to the podium. Eileen Lerner, name and address record, please.
My name is Eileen Lerner, I live at 9 Adams Circle in Medford. I'm here to represent the group Safe Medford. But before I read the statement of our group, I just would like to say that my family was destroyed by the Nazis.
My great-grandparents, my great-aunts, my great-uncles, my cousins, they're all gone in Auschwitz, but I stand here in solidarity with the Palestinian people.
because I don't want what happened to us to happen to anybody else and it is happening and we need to stand against it. And here's the statement from Safe Medford. Safe Medford works to promote physical and emotional safety for everyone in Medford. We are deeply disturbed by recent incidents of antisemitism and Islamophobia in our city and region.
These incidents, whether swastikas painted on sidewalks in Medford, or the shooting of Palestinian college students in Vermont, reflect growing religious, ethnic, and national animosities that are being fueled by the violence against civilians in Israel and Palestine. Thank you, Eileen. 30 seconds.
This conflict is exacerbated by the supply of sophisticated weaponry funded with our tax dollars. We cannot stand aside as though this conflict does not concern us. We have safe Medford deplore the killing of innocent civilians wherever it takes place.
Safe Medford calls on the Medford City Council to join the growing support for an immediate and lasting ceasefire in Gaza, the release of all houses hostages in Gaza and prisoners in Israel.
urgent deployment of humanitarian aid in the region, and to denounce all acts of antisemitism and Islamophobia here in Medford and beyond our borders. Thank you.
Next, we're going to go to Zoom. I have Devorah Klein. I'm going to ask you to unmute. You can provide your name and address or city, and then you'll have two minutes. I will give a 30-second warning and a 10-second warning.
Thank you so much. As Councillor Scarpelli reminded us, on October 6th, there was a ceasefire in place. That ceasefire was ignored in the horrific attacks on the next day. Calling for a ceasefire without ensuring the return of the hostages and dismantling the terrorist regime of Hamas is just an invitation for Hamas to continue to try to destroy Israel, as they've already said they plan to do,
and for them to continue to abuse the Palestinians as they have done so far, including hijacking aid being sent from Israel. A ceasefire sounds so appealing, isn't it? But without ensuring the safety of all, it is asking for more abuse of the Jews, Arabs, Christians, Muslims, Baha'i, and so many others who form the cohesive Israeli society.
Contrary to popular belief, Jews have been in Israel for millennia up to the present, including my own family. A vote for this resolution says that you don't value those lives and it will make me feel unsafe in this community and that any of you might wish me ill. Thank you. Thank you. I'm going to go to the podium, name and address for the record. Ellen Epstein, I'm a Medford resident. All right, two minutes.
I am an American Jew and no stranger to Israel. I have relatives there and at one point lived there for the better part of a year.
I'm here tonight to urge the Medford City Council to speak out against this brutal conflict. Because I am Jewish, Israel's actions are being done in my name. Because I am American, the conflict is being fueled with my tax money. Therefore, I have not just the right, but the obligation to call for a ceasefire.
I have demonstrated written emails made countless phone calls to our representatives in DC. I've joined with other Jewish members of the fifth congressional district to press Catherine Clark, the Democratic whip in the House of Representatives to call for a ceasefire.
But my most direct line to political power is through you all, my city councilors. And yes, it makes a difference where you stand on this issue. Your voice as a city council is louder than our individual voices can be. Please use your voice to add Medford to the growing number of cities and towns nationwide that are calling for ceasefire.
You'd be taking sides, not with Israel, not with Hamas, but with the children and innocent men and women who continue to be the victims of brutality, day after day, week after week, month after month. Don't wait another minute. You can do this tonight, right here, right now. Please, take a stand for peace, take a stand for life. Ceasefire now.
Thank you. We have a hand on Zoom. I'm going to go to Kate on Zoom. Kate, please provide your name and address for the record. I will give a 30-second warning and a 10-second warning.
Hello, my name is Kate Ryan and I am on Warren Street in Medford and I am not at the city council meeting because as an autistic person, the environment is too hellish. And I am thinking about my brethren in Palestine right now who are suffering so much more. This is a mass disabling event. We should not be supporting
this we need peace we need it now and I would like you to all think about the fact that in the past two hours we have been at this city council meeting approximately 10 children in Gaza have been killed and that is all
to go to the podium, name and address for the record, and I'll give a 30-second warning and a 10-second warning.
Jennifer, I'm sorry, could you press the button on the microphone? You may have tapped it off. Oh, okay. I don't need to start over, do I? No, no, no. Well, we heard you. We'll get it for the record. And we're furious that our tax dollars are being used for this morally reprehensible purpose, especially when there's so much need here at home.
It's heartbreaking to see fellow human beings subjected to so much suffering on a daily and hourly basis. Tens of thousands have been killed and injured, children orphaned, the land destroyed, leaving a scorched earth where starvation and disease are now rampant. Is this what we want to do with our tax dollars? Today we're saying no, not on our watch, not in our name, not with our money.
If our leaders at the federal level don't have the backbone to act, let the cities and towns of our country be the moral voice of the nation. Neighboring cities of Cambridge and Somerville have already taken a stand, and I urge you, let us join them.
The United States has the power to stop this carnage today, simply by cutting off funds and demanding an immediate ceasefire. Please, please be our voice and speak out for an immediate end to this gross misuse of our public resources. Ceasefire now. Thank you. We're going to go back to Zoom.
Grace Parker on Zoom. Grace, I'll unmute you, ask for your name and address, and I'll give you a 30-second warning and a 10-second warning on a two-minute time limit. Go ahead.
Hi, again, Grace Parker, Bell Lab, Medford. I'll try to be quick. I just wanted to say that I definitely agree with supporting this resolution. The atrocities in Gaza are, I mean, so many people have already spoken to this. And I want to say thank you to the people that spoke about their personal experiences and also that I'm just so sorry that you are in this position and that so many people have failed you and failed our communities.
That's really the crux of it. I don't wanna take up too much time just that I support this and I think you should all vote yes. Thank you, Grace. Go to the podium. Name and address for the record, please. And I'll give you a 30-second warning and 10-second warning.
Hi, my name is Beth Basciatelli. I'm a Medford resident. And I would like to present a legal and moral argument for the council's consideration. I'm a scholar of global governance and human security. Under international law, Israel is an occupying force. It's an occupying force. It is bound by the principle of protection.
Under the Geneva Convention, its duty is to protect the population of Gaza, including civilians and civilian infrastructure. It is also bound by the principles of precaution, distinction, proportionality, and necessity. According to any of these principles of international law, Israel is guilty of a whole series of war crimes.
Also based on international law, the United States is guilty of the crime of legal complicity, which is listed in the Geneva Convention. Complicity under the Genocide Convention is a crime. It is legal complicity because it involves active support of a UN member state that is committing war crimes. The United States is providing economic, military, intelligence, and diplomatic support to block a ceasefire in Gaza.
The genocide that is happening in Gaza could not happen without the support of the United States. Apart from the sheer loss of life and property, Israel's continued impunity in committing acts of genocide and the United States' ongoing acts of complicity put multilateralism and the entire international law establishment at risk.
These acts have created a dangerous precedent whereby any authoritarian leader with ethno-nationalist ideologies who comes to power in any country, including the United States, can make a case for committing gross violations of international law.
I recently attended a webinar with Craig Mobaker, who publicly resigned as director of the New York office of the high commissioner for human rights. And he said, do not doubt this. If you don't care about Palestine, you are next. International human rights is the only thing that stands between powerful actors and those of us who care about living, moving and speaking freely. Thank you.
very, very soon. We have Marianne Vidal on zoom. Marianne, I'm going to unmute you. Please provide your name and address or the city you live in. And I will give you a 30 second warning and a 10 second warning. You have two minutes. Hi there, I apologize my light isn't working in my room. Lifelong
uh person i'm medfed i live on central ave i am here today demanding a ceasefire
I refuse to take part in something where we're going to call people collateral damage. What we're seeing is not propaganda from Palestine. We are seeing murder. We are seeing genocide. We are seeing children crying. We are seeing mothers and fathers losing their kids. We are seeing the wipe out of a whole demographic of people and I can't sit by and just swipe up on a social media app for distraction anymore. Ceasefire now.
Thank you. I'm going to go to the podium, name and address for the record, and you will have two minutes. I'll give a 30-second warning and a 10-second warning. Thank you. Elie Strassfeld, West Street in Medford. I came here to commend the city council. I intended to commend the city council on this resolution and to speak out in favor of it. I believe Israel has a right to exist. I believe Israelis should not have to exist in the threat of Hamas, and because of that,
I do not believe that an immediate ceasefire is justified, notwithstanding the heartbreaking stories, and I truly mean the heartbreaking stories I hear from my Medford neighbors. However, I absolutely do not believe that Israel has clean hands here.
And I absolutely believe, as the resolution stated, that an enduring ceasefire is critical and a movement back to a two-state solution is critical. So I was thrilled to see that that's what the resolution said.
I have to say I am appalled that I come here and the resolution now is so dramatically different in tone than what was originally posted on the website. I implore the city council to please move back to the previous resolution that was posted publicly and that people had an opportunity to review. It stands for something this entire city can get behind, I believe,
And that is that we all need to work toward an enduring peace. We don't need to have disputes about definition, about history, the historical context that Councilperson Collins shared was good context, but completely incomplete. And I'd ask that that part be stricken and that this council reverts to the version of this resolution that was previously before the council. Thank you. Thank you.
I'm going to go to Zoom. Yes. Oh, yeah. Sorry, Susan, we can't have a flag. There's a message on there. We don't have flags or signs in the chamber. Pardon? There's a message on your, yes. If you could hand it to Eileen for a minute. But I am going to go to Zoom first. We have Amina Awad on Zoom.
I mean, I'm going to unmute you. You can say your name, address and city or city, and give you a 30 second warning and a 10 second warning on a two minute timer for is yours. Hi, my name is I mean I'm in speaking in favor of this resolution. I'm a resident of Somerville.
And as someone who grew up in the Middle East, the lack of action in this country is unacceptable. I would be surprised at the shocking anti-Arab racism in this country had I not seen the legacy of racism and imperialism that remains. Why are Palestinians always the last in politicians' speeches, including this council, who always mention Palestinians last, even though they're the ones that are victims of genocide?
Palestinians who are dying deserve to be recognized and heard. My grandfather was forcibly displaced from Jerusalem by Zionist militia in 1948. This did not start on October 7th or with Hamas.
The blockades on Gaza have existed for over a decade, and Israel has been killing Palestinians and stealing their land, conducting occupation and suppression for a long time, which is not a ceasefire, by the way. Gaza was living under military occupation. And now, as I'm witnessing millions of Palestinians go through
a second Nakba, which is a part of Israel's genocidal, colonial, and white supremacist regime. This resolution must pass for our collective liberation and for the Palestinians in Medford, Somerville, and beyond to feel safe and supported by this city.
My grandfather, who was born in Jerusalem, died two hours away from Jerusalem in Man Jordan, never being able to return to his home, which is now occupied by settlers. So despite my family growing up for generations two hours outside the border of Jerusalem, not one of us has been able to step back into the city of our ancestors. And I also wanted to share a quote from a friend in Gaza who talks about
One of his daily tasks in the North is burying the dead and decomposed bodies. Israeli forces have killed hundreds in the most horrific ways. Almost daily we find dead bodies that we need to decide where to bury. Never did I think that my life at 21
would be burying others. In order to move forward, I have to convince myself that I do not know the bodies that I am burying, when they in fact could be my neighbors, my friends, or even family members that have been missing under the rubble. I implore you to think as a human being and to stand with justice and what is right and call for a ceasefire. Thank you.
Please go to the podium. And thank you. My name is Susan Girard. I've been living in Medford. I live on Farragut Ave. I've been living in Medford for 40 years. I'm Jewish. I'm a mother and a grandmother. And my message is really simple. As people have stated, out of the 27,000 and growing children that have been killed under these bombs that our tax dollars are supporting,
out of the 27,000 people, over half of them are children. I cannot believe, for anyone who believes that the safety of Israel is important, I cannot believe that you are safe when you kill other people's children. And that's my statement, thank you.
Seeing no more hands on Zoom, we're gonna stick with the podium. Name and address for the record, please. You have two minutes. I'll give you a 30-second warning and a 10-second warning. Okay, thank you. Hi, I'm Rebecca Butorsky. I live on Diane Road in Medford. I'll very briefly introduce myself. I'm a scientist, I'm a mom, I'm a Jew, and I'm a descendant of Holocaust survivors. I'm compelled to speak in favor of the ceasefire resolution brought by Councilor Collins for both political and also personal reasons.
First of all, I join Palestinians and Israelis who are mourning the senseless loss of life and I condemn violence against civilians. I'm urging you to pass this resolution tonight because of the role that the US plays in this current war between Israel and Palestine. Israel is the largest recipient of US foreign aid since World War Two and the US is its major supplier of weapons.
The U.S. therefore has a huge leverage to deescalate this current crisis, and if it doesn't, this catastrophe may escalate into a greater war in the region and causing more civilian deaths. We must urge our representatives to join the growing calls for a ceasefire.
Second, I'm compelled to speak personally on behalf of my grandmother, whose entire family was killed in the Holocaust, except for her and her sister, who were able to escape. She witnessed genocide and she lived to teach her children and grandchildren to speak up and work towards a world where this will never happen again. When I read that entire families in Gaza are being killed and that others are being displaced for the second and third time from their homes, I know that my grandmother would not want this done in her name, and I would not want this done in mine. Thank you.
you.
Thank you, name and address for the record. You have two minutes. Clare Sheridan, 190 High Street, Medford. I support the resolution. Although not Jewish myself, I was an ardent supporter of the state of Israel until about 20 years ago when I began questioning Israel's treatment of its Palestinian neighbors. So I traveled to Israel-Palestine twice over the last 15 years to educate myself.
I had two personal experiences that I want to convey because they are emblematic of what I found. On one trip, I was with a group of American tourists in Hebron in the West Bank.
We were watching a group of little children exiting their school. The street was lined with Israeli soldiers with machine guns. One said to me loudly in English, why are you watching that vermin? I almost reminded him that that was what the Nazis called his forebears. But I held my tongue, he had a gun after all.
On another trip, I was at the airport heading home. I was pulled aside and interrogated. My bags were searched separately and my passport withheld.
Why? I had a stamp in my passport from a previous trip to Bosnia to visit an American friend's relatives. The security guy asked me, so, do you love Muslims? He wanted to know the names of the people I visited in Bosnia and the names of my friend in the US. I responded sweetly that my Bosnian friend's husband was Jewish.
The official became very angry and shouted something I won't repeat. I responded, only in America. He let me catch my plane. You have 10 seconds, Claire. Thank you. Thank you. Seeing no hands on Zoom, we'll go to the podium. Name and address for the record, please. Two minutes.
Hi, my name is Anna Meyer. I live at 6 Douglas Road in Medford, and I'm a member of the Unitarian Universalist Church of Medford. I'm here tonight to urge you to vote for the ceasefire resolutions with the amendments proposed by Councilor Collins. I believe that passing this resolution will have two incredibly important impacts on our community. First, passing this resolution is an affirmation that Medford is a community that values all of its residents.
Ruth Wilson Gilmore tells us that where life is precious, life is precious. What she means by that is that when we intentionally create communities that affirm the life of every person is meaningful, all people have the capacity to thrive. The death count in Gaza has surpassed 27,000 individuals that we can count. At least 10,000 of those deaths are children. Thousands more are displaced without access to food, clean water, or medical care.
Passing a ceasefire resolution affirms that Medford is a community that opposes this needless violence. And it also affirms that Medford is a community that believes that the life of our Muslim and Arab siblings, as well as all of our neighbors that have experienced state sanctioned violence and the harms of colonialism are precious.
Second, passing this resolution puts important pressure on our federal elected officials who can use their power to call for a permanent and immediate ceasefire. This resolution will put pressure on Representatives Clark and Senators Warren and Markey to end the current humanitarian crisis.
We'll also put pressure on them to vote against the legislation that's currently before the Senate that will provide an upwards of $14 billion in military aid to Israel. And this will help ensure that our tax dollars do not go towards intensifying a genocide. So with that, I urge you to pass a ceasefire resolution tonight so that we can affirm the preciousness of the lives of all of our neighbors and to use our voice to call for an end to this violence. Thank you. And I apologize for missing the warning.
name and address for the record, and I'll remember the 30 seconds.
Thanks, Travis Benson, 353 Main Street on Medford. I am aware this is a scarf and not a keffiyeh. I'm doing my best, but I am here to support the resolution as it is currently amended for ceasefire. I don't know what else to say tonight that won't already be said. There'll be many mentions from everyone here of the atrocities and casualties that have been going on with the decades long conflict with Israel and Palestine.
Maybe I'm simplistic and rigid in my thinking, but this conversation becomes really difficult for me whenever it strays away from the overwhelming asymmetric casualty rate that has continued for decades.
as if this is a nuanced issue and that the agitation and cause of the loss of life must be explained or elaborated on further. As more and more towns and cities pass these resolutions, and taking a stance on a ceasefire becomes much safer for everyone's public image and costs less and less political capital, history will look less and less fondly towards votes
not in favor of this resolution, attempts to delay its passage, or suggestions to water the language down. I've witnessed in-person other city meetings that have already taken votes on a ceasefire, and I would just like to note that it is very obvious to everyone watching, and will be even more obvious tomorrow, of the strong dissonance and disconnect that exists between the visible turnout in this room versus the passivity and appeasement that exists in all of tonight's four speeches.
We must always recognize that- 30 seconds, Travis. Gotcha. It should not take this much effort, time, and energy to take a non-watered down stance on a genocide. It does not help us, your constituents, feel confident about your actions and representation on less urgent and less catastrophic issues if you do not take the strongest action on this resolution yesterday. 10 seconds. Thank you. Thank you, Travis.
Name and address the record. I'll give a 30 second warning and a 10 second warning.
My name is Sharon. I live at 14 Winter Hill Road in Medford. And I've lived here for about a year and a half, and I really like it. I'm working with the group Medford for Palestine to organize our city around this resolution. I don't pretend to fully understand the deep complexities of the Israel-Palestine conflict that's been going on for decades. And I'm not personally implicated in it because of my religious or ethnic identity. Therefore, I'm immensely privileged and obligated to educate myself, hold space for others, and stand up for peace.
Nobody in this room is under the illusion that Medford's resolution will put a stop to the violence overnight. However, I believe with every piece of my heart that many small actions can coalesce into something substantial that our federal government might actually listen to. That means we must take seriously our local actions on global matters, not dismiss them as beyond our scope.
These are the stepping stones with which we build a world we truly love and believe in and can trust to hold our future generations. I hope we pass a ceasefire resolution tonight. I hope that our collective actions shake the US government out of the nightmare that it is perpetuating by supplying bombs, weapons, and our tax dollars to fund Israel's militant campaign, which is destroying Palestinian lives under the false pretense of protecting Jewish ones.
We are all watching a genocide unfold on every screen we look at, at all hours of the day, every single day. We cannot do nothing. Palestine deserves peace. Peace requires freedom. Free Palestine. Ceasefire now.
Yes, in one second, I just want to say, if you are on Zoom and you would like to speak, please raise your hand. But I see no hands. Go to the podium. Name and address for the record. Two minutes, and I'll give a 30-second and a 10-second warning.
I'll be brief. I am Simcha Miller. I live on 59 Winchester Street here in Somerville, Medford, my bad, sorry. It's been a long day, came from work. I have not been a resident of Medford for that long, but I grew up four miles away. And I am a proud observant Jew that wakes up every day disgusted that this is done in my name.
And I don't want to say more. There have been other people who have said what I've said from my position. I didn't really prepare in advance. I'm a teacher.
I was raised by a union nurse, local. And I think that I wanna bring it back to you are our voice, our voices aren't being heard otherwise. This is a way for us to amplify our voices. And specifically, I wanna draw back the attention to the personal horrors and anecdotes that were shared earlier by my neighbors here in Medford.
that are Palestinian and have been facing the unknowns of every single day facing this horror. I urge the city council to please put forward this amended resolution. You have 30 seconds. And that's all. Thank you.
Hello, name and address for the record, please. Hello, I'm Esther Alter, I live in Medford. I am a Jew, and I grew up in a very Zionist synagogue, and I'm well aware of the emotional component to this, that the Zionists want security, and they're on a perpetual defensive posture.
I am not a Zionist. We are a minority, and we always will be. And our safety is contingent on being generous and empathetic neighbors.
If the institutions ostensibly representing our interests continue to fail to call for the end of the genocide of our neighbors because they don't want to divide a community or make some people feel unsafe, then we will always be divided, and we will never be safe. Cease fire now. Thank you.
name and address for the record, please, you have two minutes. Deborah Cooper, 112 Lawrence Street, Medford. I stand for the sanctity of human life and culture, and I admire the courage of this council in bringing this motion forward. Beloved American poet Maya Angelou has said that of all the virtues, courage is the most important because without it, no other virtues can be performed consistently.
How do you build the courage to stand up to injustice? You start with something small, like a weightlifter who begins with a few pounds and builds up to 100. You stand up against injustice and it feels good, so you do more. Six years ago, we stood up against injustice and the Muslim immigration ban, and that felt good.
Along with many Medford residents, I ask this council to show your courage by passing the ceasefire resolution. Free Palestine, ceasefire now. Thank you.
name and address for the record. You have two minutes. My name is Nathan Foster. I live at 163 Main Street in Medford. I'm a Medford resident and I'm Jewish. I'm here in support of a ceasefire now. I thank the council for bringing this resolution forward. What is happening in Gaza right now, what the Israeli military is doing in Gaza is morally indefensible. It is horrific and
It's just plain wrong, and that's reason enough to support this resolution. I would like to speak to some things that have been brought up around the issue of the safety of Jewish people. My grandparents were Holocaust survivors. I take this very seriously, and I would just like to state that the war that is being waged by Israel in the name of the safety of Jewish people has nothing to do with that.
Absolutely nothing to do with that. It's a war of revenge. It is, for some, a war of territorial expansion. It's not about safety. One phrase that is used to describe Israel's repeated attacks on Gaza since 2008, which once I heard it, I couldn't unhear, is mowing the grass.
This is used to describe these repeated attacks as something that is inevitable and will just keep happening. It's such a dehumanizing and normalizing phrase, but it also speaks to the futility of these cycles of violence and the fact that
And Israel, which is oppressing the Palestinian people, which is denying basic freedom, basic human rights, will never achieve the kind of safety that is talked about. Safety can only come through peace. It can only come through the freedom and human rights of Palestinians. Thank you very much. Thank you.
for the record. You have two minutes and I'll provide two warnings. Thank you, Benjamin, 76 Marion Street, Medford. I'm a recent new Medford resident. I appreciate the resolution being forward today and I want to speak in support of it. I don't have any personal ties to Palestine or Israel, but like many here, the events unfolding since October 7th have deeply impacted me. The ongoing killing in Gaza and the West Bank, the displacement of an entire people from their homes without a safe place to go, without enough food, water, medicine is horrifying.
And as a resident of this country, I feel the responsibility to speak up today because the U.S. is not just a powerful player in this conflict. It doesn't have just leverage. It is, alongside Israel, the main perpetrator of the suffering of the Palestinian people. It is with U.S. bombs and U.S. fighter jets that the Israeli military has killed more than 27,000 Palestinians.
It is our administration that has and continues to fund this war. It is our administration that stands alone in the world in vetoing one ceasefire resolution after another in the UN Security Council. It is our administration that two weeks ago suspended all funding for the main UN organization providing humanitarian aid to the people in Gaza, the UNRWA. Our elected administration is not just a bystander to this genocide, but an active participant that is able to stop this war tomorrow if it wants to. That's why I think it matters that cities like Medford pass a ceasefire resolution.
It demonstrates to our community, in particular its Muslim, Arab, Palestinian, as well as Jewish and Israeli members, that we care about their lives and that of their relatives, friends, colleagues, that we fully condemn the loss of life, the complete destruction of housing and basic human services and goods in Gaza, that we value all human life, that we want everyone to feel safe here and to feel comfortable to speak up.
And it demonstrates to our government that the city of Medford does not stand behind the support of the ongoing genocide, that we stand for peace and immediate ceasefire now. The more cities that pass resolutions like this, the higher will be the pressure on Biden to stop this war now. Thank you. Thank you. Name and address for the record, please.
the resolution. Brianna Sullivan, 28 Princeton Street. Um many others here have spoken tonight much more eloquently than I ever could on the broader issue, so I will be brief. I'm in favor of the resolution to support a ceasefire in Israel and Gaza, and specifically I am in favor of the city
As the amended version was being read out loud, I was reading the original version along, following line by line, and I noticed every change that was made, and I support them all. I appreciate everything that Councilperson Collins did to put those changes into place, as well as putting forth the original resolution. I urge you all to pass this version and to vote on it tonight. Thank you, cease fire now.
Name and address for the record, please, or the city. Hi, my name is Marie. I live at 31 Gleason Street in Medford. I came here tonight because I'm a Medford parent. I have two children, ages two and six. And my youngest, she goes to a home daycare, and her daycare teacher is a Palestinian.
And every day that I drop her off and pick her up, I see her face just, it's puffy, she's hiding it, but I know that she cries daily while trying to take care of these children. And so I'm here just holding her in my heart, honestly. And I had this whole thing that I was going to read that I read earlier at the rally, but the personal testimonies
from these people back here is more powerful than anything I could ever say. So what I will say is that I'm just going to quote Motaz Azizia, who is one of the heroes of Gaza. He has more followers than the president of the United States as a result of all of this.
And he has truly brought this genocide to our hands. You have 30 seconds, Pri. He's brought awareness to the world. And so I'm just going to quote him on his 107th day when he was finally able to flee Gaza and just say, always remember to say, free Palestine. Thank you. Hello. Name and address for the record, please. You have two minutes.
Hi, my name is Eric Fox. I live at 10 Revere Place. I first of all, foremost want to thank the Councilor Collins for bringing forth this resolution calling for a ceasefire. I personally am Jewish. I have, like many others that have spoken today, have grandparents that were survivors of the Holocaust and other members of my family who I never got to know because they were killed. But
More importantly, I've experienced antisemitism in my life. I have also experienced and seen and witnessed Islamophobia and xenophobia in this community. And so I applaud the council for bringing and talking about this issue and just hearing all of these stories tonight, hearing everyone and hearing how this conflict has been affecting them.
personally makes it clear that this is not purely a national issue that should be ignored by a local city council. It's not something that doesn't qualify as a local Medford issue. This clearly is a Medford issue that is affecting its residents and in a very deep and personal way.
So I encourage you to vote for this ceasefire amendment, the amended version in the resolution, and I hope you do because it clearly is very important to Medford locals. Thank you. Thank you.
Yes, my name is Dina Alemi. I live at 3780 Mystic Valley Parkway. I was not prepared to speak tonight, but I felt that as a Palestinian American, I should share my story and my family's story. My parents both grew up in Jaffa, which is now Israel. They were also forcefully pushed out into Gaza. I have lost a lot of family in Gaza.
Many of my family members in the North do not have food. They are lucky that their house is still standing, but all they're really eating is herbs and contaminated water. This is not a political issue.
This is a humanity issue. We need to support this. We need to be there for the people. And I thank you all for listening. I really hope that you all will vote in support of this. Thank you. Thank you. For the record, you have two minutes. Thank you.
My name is Harlan from Somerville. I grew up in the area. I've been going to day things at Tufts all my life. And my mother and I have lived in Somerville with my brothers for over 50 years. And my mother had to flee when she was a child because of what was going on over there. And every time I go back to Palestine to visit, I get harassed.
I don't care you know my American passport my father being an American army soldier and all my uncles on his side, I still get harassed four or five hours. One time I called my mother up.
and said, mom, they're gonna put me on a plane. My mother was standing on the other side of the wall to get out of the airport. And I was like, mom, they're gonna put me on a plane. That's what I thought they were gonna do to me. And it's so scary to see when you go there to see the tear gas going off and having to run into a store in the neighborhood in Ramallah because somebody did something and I don't know what they did.
Relatives have been arrested and imprisoned for years. But you know what the most important thing is? Even the poorest Palestinian, you go and visit. Like Claire was saying, Claire has come with me several times to Palestine. And they took her in and I thought she was more family than I was. That's how the Palestinians, they may not have water coming out of their faucet.
But you know what, you'll have a nice bed to sleep in, and a male fit for a king and queen. So that's, I just want to say, I hope that you do like Somerville does and Cambridge does, and quick action, which was great, and vote for a resolution to cease fire now, free Palestine. Thank you. Your name and your city or your street address for the record, you have two minutes.
My name is Emma, and I'm a resident of Somerville who went to university and then lived in Medford for eight years. I was a tough student who first majored in mechanical engineering before changing to engineering psychology. I would like to remind you all that in addition to what everybody else has said.
This resolution is relevant and important because there are scientists and engineers in our area, including those who work at Elbit Systems in nearby Cambridge, who work in support of Israel. It is our responsibility as American taxpayers and residents of the greater Boston area to take responsibility for our role in the genocide and call for a ceasefire. Thank you. Thank you.
Seeing no hands on Zoom, we'll go to the podium. Name and address for the record, two minutes. Hi, I'm Karina. I live at 34 William Street, Medford. I just want to make sure that regardless of whether this resolution passes, those that decide to not vote or vote no,
realize what side of history they are standing on, and that is the one that supports genocide. And I hope that your consciences do not forgive you, and that the people of Medford, along with I, do not forgive you. I would just ask you to direct your comments to the chair. OK. The chair, also. Thank you.
That's what I'm here for. Go to the podium, name and address for the record. You have two minutes, and I will dispose this as my campaign treasure.
Yes, thank you for getting to that before I did. Hi, my name is Gregory Zapata and I am, and I live at 16 Emory Street. Good evening Council President Behrs, Vice President Collins, members of the Council, and everyone assembled. My name is Gregory Zapata and I've had the great pleasure of living in Medford's Hillside neighborhood for much of the past 12 years. Two of those years were spent in Somerville, but I ask you to not hold that against me.
I will keep my comments brief, as I know many more wish to speak on this very important matter, and it is a very important matter, even though Palestine is many, many miles away from where we all are. It matters because of the cruel offenses committed, relayed to our radios, phones, televisions, and newspapers on a daily basis, are committed on our tax dime. It matters because these acts of genocide are in violation, not just of international law, but also in violation of the moral codes by which we are taught to abide from when we were very small.
Since the start of this conflict, many in this country and city have been motivated to take to the streets and to speak up for what they feel to be right. Sometimes they speak at the risk of their professional or even physical well-being, but they speak up all the same, and my admiration for them would be tempered by a sense of shame if I did not do likewise.
speaking against the war in Vietnam, Martin Luther King said, there comes a time when silence becomes betrayal. And so I speak in favor of this resolution versus fire and applaud all those who have brought this to this critical moment. But while I support this resolution, those behind it, I also cannot ignore the argument of why we should concern ourselves with this Palestine is so far away. We have so many concerns here. 30 seconds.
But the cause of Palestine is the cause of all those who are oppressed. And if, God forbid, the circumstances were flipped, we would want everyone in the world outside of Medford to speak up for our rights. And that would include the Palestinian people. And so I would ask everyone in this council to vote affirmative for the resolution and to bring a just and lasting peace to this region. Thank you. Thank you.
We do have someone on Zoom. I'm going to go to them, and then I'll come right back to you. On Zoom, I have Sharon Diesso. I will unmute you, Sharon. You'll have two minutes, and I will give you a 30-second warning and a 10-second warning. Sharon? Sharon, I'm going to come back to you. We'll go to the podium. Sharon can, okay, sorry. This hybrid gets a little rough.
Sharon, I just unmuted you. Do you need to accept it? Thanks to everyone for bearing with me. Sharon, I'm going to have to come back to you. We'll go to the podium. Name and address for the record. You have two minutes.
My name is Raviv and I live on Pinkham and Bedford. I'm here as a member of the Medford community and as the grandchild of people who fled violent antisemitism in their home countries. It is not my place to speak of the experiences of living under 75 years of violence and occupation. I urge you to hold those testimonies which have already been shared here today with the weight and compassion they are owed. I'm here because my Jewish values compel me.
To suggest that opposing the genocide being exacted by the State of Israel is anti-Semitism is not only logically inconsistent, it is offensive and dangerous. Months ago, after the death of Massa Amini, Iranians took to the streets to condemn the Iranian government.
as many in the U.S. joined in support of the rallying cries of women, life, freedom, they did so free from accusations of Islamophobia. And yet now, as we stand here calling for a ceasefire, we are met with accusations of anti-Semitism, of implications that ceasefire will jeopardize the safety of Jewish residents. I urge the city council to reconcile with the hypocrisy of these accusations, of accusing a Jewish city councilor and an overwhelming number of Jewish residents here today with anti-Semitism.
To insinuate that supporting an end to violence will create division in our community, I challenge you to consider what version of unity and peace is being disrupted. For the Palestinian members of our community, that peace never existed to begin with.
For non-Jews afraid of accusations of anti-Semitism, I stand before you as a representative of the millions of Jews here in the U.S., in Israel, and around the world who are supporting a ceasefire and an end to occupation. For those who support ceasefire, please know that the Jewish members in this chamber and around the world stand with you.
and an end to occupation. For those who support ceasefire, please know the Jewish members in this chamber and around the world stand with you. Thank you. I see that you're unmuted and I will give you a 30 second warning and a 10 second warning. You have two minutes. Thank you. Council President Behrs and I am speaking from my heart and from my head at this point.
I feel that I have been around a lot longer than many of the council members and some of the people who are in the chamber this evening. I have seen wars, many wars, grand wars. Very luckily for Americans that they were on opposite sides of the world.
My very dear friend, whom I grew up with, married an Israeli. She lives there now. She said it's absolutely horrible scene. She had a peaceful week, but she said, we don't know what will happen tomorrow. This war, internally, you must know, has been going on for centuries. I definitely commiserate.
with anyone who is a victim of war, especially at this time in history, it's 2024. Some of these people are living back in ancient history. I haven't quite decided yet with my age, what is a real good resolution for any war? Israel has had ceasefire before.
and still has been subject to bombings. Thank you. People are getting killed in Palestine, but only one person tonight, may I say, one person in not in exclusive terms mentioned the word Hamas. Israel is not at war with the Palestinian innocence. It is at war with Hamas.
I believe, believe that part of this could be a ceasefire. There are grand talks going on right now, even as we speak. Palestine needs to ask Hamas to leave. Then the rest, I think, can very nicely fall in place. I respect all your wishes. Thank you. Thank you. Palestine needs to ask Hamas
Welcome to the podium. Name and address for the record. You have two minutes. I'll give a 30 second warning and a 10 second warning. My name is Elizabeth Henley. I live at 28 Princeton Street in Medford. Thank you to everyone who has already spoken. Thank you to the council for bringing this resolution forward. The only thing I have not heard explicitly said yet is that Israel has been
indiscriminately bombing Gaza, where the hostages also are, that they are saying that they are worried about. And so I urge the council to not fall for a disingenuous distraction technique to try to delay the vote. Ceasefire and free Palestine. Thank you. Name and address for the record, please.
Hello, everybody. My name is Sarah Halawa, and I live in Somerville at 43 Monroe Street. And I am here to speak to you about what it means to pass a ceasefire resolution to the Muslim community, to the Arab community, and to the Palestinian community in your town.
I'll tell you a little bit about myself. My father was born to a large Jewish family and as a young man fell in love with Islam and converted and I was born and raised Muslim. He built the mosque in my town. He was a very devoted man to his faith.
He has a testament that this is no religious war, and he would tell anybody who he ever met who would listen to him at length about that. My husband, his father was born in Nablus in the West Bank, and he was a teenager when the Israeli occupation began. They invaded the West Bank, Nablus, and the occupation began.
One night, he was awoken at gunpoint as 20 Israeli soldiers stormed his house, burst open the door, knocked down his parents. He was arrested and detained and tortured for three days in all of the ways that we are seeing today on our social media. He was stripped naked. He had dogs put on him. He was physically abused. He was deprived of food.
water, warmth. And then when they were done, they released him under curfew that everybody in his city lives under, which meant that the Israeli soldiers who were patrolling could shoot on sight. When he asked them what he should do about this, they laughed at him and they said, this is your problem. Sorry, you have 30 seconds. He got home and his mother, they took all their money and they sent him to America where
he saw his mother three more times in her life. Every single Palestinian you meet in your community has a direct story of violence from the state of Israel to themselves, their immediate family, of dehumanization, of diaspora, of ethnic cleansing, and apartheid. When we watched this genocide unfold, and we were
we heard silence from the leaders of our immediate community. That felt like a punch in the gut. And the first day we were able to relax was when Somerville passed their ceasefire resolution. It really matters to Muslims. It is a statement that our lives matter. Thank you. Thank you, Sarah. You have two minutes.
Hello, my name is Linnea Strassfeld. I'm a junior at Medford High School. I would just like to say that for these past few months, I have, like many Jews and many Palestinians, I've been caught up in the current conflict and this acute sense of loss that many of our ethnicities have been experiencing. I've seen the suffering of both of our peoples, and I've felt our grief, and I've seen the radical extremism on both sides. And for that,
For the radical extremism that comes from my ethnicity, I would like to say that I abhor this, that they are the vast minority, and that I absolutely condemn it, as do all Jews and all Zionists that I know. If I may speak for my people, I would like to say that this...
What this resolution, I believe, stands for is an ideal that we can all agree on, which is we want recognition of suffering, no matter what ethnicity that is enduring this. And we would like for both of our peoples, Jewish and Palestinian, to be whole again. But I would like the Council to recognize that from the speeches that we have heard today, many of them very heart-wrenching, that this will not be the outcome.
This is not an ideal. This will not be interpreted as an ideal. This is a commitment. People will not read the full text. They will not see the mentions of the hostages. They will only see the word ceasefire. People will not interpret it as an ideal. They will see it as something very flat. And I personally would not like to be the reality of my community. And if I just may speak very briefly to the Jews in the room, I would just like to say that
What is being done is not in any of our names. It's in the names of Nama Levi, and Kfir Bidas, and Elia Cohen, and all of those people that are currently in Gaza, all of the Jews that are being held against their will in Gaza. And that's all I would like to say. Thank you. Thank you, Linnea. I'm going to go to Zoom. Pao Mendez, I'll unmute you. You'll have two minutes, and I will give you a 30-second and a 10-second warning.
Hello everyone, my name is Pao. I live in Somerville and I work as a hospice art therapist. Two of the participants that I work with are Muslim siblings, little, little kids. As much as their parents have tried to protect them, they're having to watch the horror unfold in front of them. In a recent visit, we were playing with toy construction trucks. The seven-year-old said that we were going to pretend to be heroes and use our shovel to dig bodies out of the ground.
I don't want to live in a world where children have to view and live in fear of violence. I wish I could show you all the way that their faces lit up when I showed up to our most recent visit wearing a pin of the Palestinian flag. We can create a better world for the kids in our communities and intervene to prevent as much harm as possible from the collective trauma being inflicted on our youth. You can play a role in that today in Medford by voting in favor of a ceasefire resolution. Thank you.
Thank you. And I also wanna thank you for answering me in the chat and respecting our cybersecurity. Name and address for the record, two minutes. Christine and I live in Medford. I didn't come prepared to say anything. I'm just gonna speak quickly from the heart. I have a bachelor's degree in public health and I currently work in the healthcare field. And I just wanna say that the genocide in Gaza is absolutely a public health issue and concern.
We should pass a ceasefire now so that the folks in Gaza can get the care that they need. I'm tired of seeing videos of people, premature babies being born without an ICU, without incubation, women giving birth and having C-sections without anesthesia, and people having their limbs taken off without anesthesia. Just imagine that for a moment, the pain that the people are feeling in Palestine. Thank you, that's all I had to say. Just ceasefire now and free Palestine.
Thank you. If there's anyone out, I'm just going to say to anyone left on Zoom, if you would like to speak, please raise your hand, and I will go to the podium. Name and address for the record, and you have two minutes. As-salamu alaykum. My name is Fawaz Abu-Shariq for Harrison Road, and I'm here on behalf of the Palestinian House, New England, Boston Coalition for Palestine, and North Shore for Palestine.
I was shocked to hear through you, Mr. President, when the good counselor spoke about his friends, Palestinian, and then he ended up with two Zionist letters. Not Jewish. We have to be careful. Zionist. And it's not Jewish, it's not Judaism. And mentioning all his Palestinian friends,
Excuse me. Personal privilege. My comments that were, like I stated, these were residents that asked me to read things on the record. Okay, this is, don't divert what was said. That's what I wanted to just make sure that that was stated. Thank you. You may continue.
Okay, and I was expecting a letter from a Palestinian or something, but nothing, because we are right. Mr. President, I would really ask that we not engage in direct debate with each other here.
I'm not for every Palestinian that I talked to would have great discussion. I offered the same advice. And I offered the same chance to read. It just wasn't sent. Thank you. Thank you, Councilor. He has to direct you just like I am directing you. Yes, please do not look at me and do not point at me when you speak Mr. Councilor.
You may continue. Thank you, Chair, because we have to go with the rules. Anyways, no Palestinians, and this is why we say white lives matter. A couple of days ago, I saw a sign that said, what would have you done at the Holocaust time in Nazi Germany? And the answer to that is, you are doing it now.
This is exactly what you will be doing if you're going to stop the killing and the murder, or you're just going to try to find excuses. And this is not directed at anybody. 30 seconds. If anybody is coming here thinking he's getting a victory, there isn't one to be had. Nobody is coming back from the tens of thousands injured, destruction. A whole city is sitting on the border.
We are just simply telling them, we feel you, we love you, we want you, we support you. This resolution is not gonna do anything, zero. We're just going to our leaders to tell them, please stop the carnage, stop the killing, cease fire now, free Palestine, and let's work on a solution for today forever. Thank you.
My name is Humayun Morshid. I live in 30 St. Francis Street, Medford. I'm the community organizer and also I represent Islamic Cultural Center of Medford. Just want to say thank you, Councilor Collins, take the resolution to the council. And I hope everybody already spoke, so I think I'll be the last one. I just want to, on behalf of Muslim community in Medford, just want to say thank you and cease fire now. Thank you, appreciate it. Thank you.
Is there anyone else who would like to speak at the podium, or anyone else on Zoom who would like to speak? Are you speaking, Mr. Castanedi? I will allow you as I have allowed us all. Anyone else is welcome as well. There's a lot of people here. I feel like I'm at a ballgame. Hey, you'll have two minutes, Mr. Castanedi, and I will give you a 30-second warning and a 10-second warning.
I canceled most of everything I was gonna say. Hearing these poor people, I feel horrible. As some of you know, I've always been a peaceful person since I went to Woodstock in 1969 and protested the lousy, undeclared war that cost us 60,000 soldiers dead, 10 times that, 600,000 wounded.
Some of my friends in body bags, some are still around with PTSD, missing an arm and a leg, living in Medford right now. War is hell. Actually, it's worse than hell. And we also protested the mandatory draft, which might happen real soon in this neighborhood, again. Just like Israel's had a draft for male and female, or she's, whatever.
They've had it all these years since before I was born. This war is a total mess, and the world is one bomb away from World War III. May I say a God's heavenly prayer for all, please? Really, you'll let me? It's your time, you have 40 seconds.
because before I heard some rebuttal that you didn't like the prayers. Almighty God, creator of heaven, earth, all sentient beings and more, please get me and all of us to be and do the best that we can, now, always, forever and ever, in our quest for eternal, blissful peace. Amen. You have 10 seconds. Some of us might swear there ain't no heaven, but we all better pray there ain't no hell.
Thank you, Mr. Cassinetti. Is there anyone else who would like to speak on this resolution, paper 24-035? We have a hand raised on Zoom. I will go to Matthew Page Lieberman. You will have two minutes, and I will give a 30-second warning and a 10-second warning. Name and address for the record, please.
Yes, I'm Matthew Paige Lieberman I live at 15 Canal Street here in Medford. I just want to start by saying that I extremely appreciate what has been brought before us that we can all really kind of consider about our contribution to this world and what kind of roles we want to play.
I completely appreciate that Councillor Collins also acknowledged the humanity of everyone and did not do any apology whatsoever for any of the sociopathic massacres that we've seen over the past few months. I am a, like many people before me, I am a descendant of the Holocaust survivors. My grandfather made it out. All of his brothers and sisters were killed by the Nazis. There is an expression that
For Jews, all of us are survivors. We're all survivors because the Nazis wanted to take our seed from this planet. And for me, that puts a particular impact with me, in which recently, the International Criminal Court
was not able to determine yet if it is a genocide. But they are kind of taking a little they say it will take them a few years to make that determination completely. However, they have told Israel to take all steps necessary to ensure that it's not committing a genocide. Now Netanyahu's regime has decided to completely ignore that.
completely ignore that. And I want to honor all the people that are suffering from this in Palestine and in Israel, and I especially want to honor the family members of the hostages who have pled with the Israeli regime to care about the hostages, yet Israel, Netanyahu's regime prefers to butcher people.
That's a fact. The family members of hostages, they broke into a commerce meeting, and they said, please take care of our hostages. You have 10 seconds, Matt. I would just end by saying none of us are made safer by thousands of people being massacred constantly. And we need to really cut it out with that nonsense. Thank you. Thank you.
I did. I'm now going back on what I said. I said people could only speak once earlier procedural question. I'm not going to procedural question. Absolutely. I'm wondering if the council would consider us votes on the original resolution and the vote on the amended resolution separately. I will leave that to counselors to make procedural motions as I can't. I do want to say before I turn back to counselors that I want to thank everyone. This is a
This can be, I've run some tough meetings, and this actually wasn't one of them. And I really appreciate everyone, regardless of what they believed and what they felt, for just respecting everyone's time and their chance to tell their stories, because there's some incredibly powerful stories told tonight. I have told folks, I'm supportive of this resolution as amended. That's all I'm gonna say from the chair, because I really probably shouldn't have even have said that, but I really wanna thank
all of you for your time, for your words, and for just, you're creating a respectful space for the people who ask to be heard to be heard. 95-99%. Thank you. I'm gonna go to Councilor Collins, and then Councilor Sang, and then Councilor Callahan. Councilor Collins. Thank you, President Beers.
Thank you to everybody who spoke. I already made the motion to adopt the new language and move forward with that new language. Motion to adopt, yeah, that's what I said. And I'll now motion to amend and adopt the new language. Got it. I hear everybody. I hear all of you.
I don't know if it's possible for everybody to be heard equally, but I hear you. And I motion for approval of the resolution as amended. On the motion of Councilor Khan seconded by second seconded by Councilor Lazaro. I will go to Councilor Sang and then Councilor Kelly and Councilor Sang.
Thank you. I wanted to thank everyone who spoke, no matter what viewpoint of this resolution they have. It really means a lot to our city and our democracy that you're willing to take time out of your evening to do this. In that spirit, we also owe you, at least in my opinion, I owe you your faith, and me as your city councilor, to let you know that I care. I care about the stories.
I know that many of you, as you've said tonight, have family who've been in the area, who are currently still in the area, who are trapped there, who are suffering. And I think this is a moment where people need to know that their local electeds care, that they not only hear them, but they, I think, deeply, deeply, that this deeply matters to them.
I don't think it's wrong at all to say that the context is complex, that there's misinformation, and there's violence and tragedy that civilians take the brunt of. I don't think it's wrong to say that
a lot of the rhetoric in the debate has been challenging for others to hear. But I have to thank you as a councillor that you've kept this conversation, this discourse tonight so cordial, so respectful, that you've followed the rules that the council president has set out.
But you know, even given this, the complex history and context behind this issue, I think the question before us, the heart of this resolution is simple. And I think the big question is, do we affirm the sanctity, the preciousness, and the equality of all human life? And do we
condemn the bloodshed going on. I think it's not wrong to say that war begets war. And I think we should listen to the hostages' pleas to the Israeli government, that their government not do anything that worsens the outcome of people living in Israel and Palestine, of the civilians. And their pleas not to drive more people into extremism.
I was struck by the word precedent earlier in public comment. Because even though we can't, as a city council, we can't stop what's going on from becoming precedent, I think we can stop normalizing it.
And I think we have a moral duty to stop normalizing violence. We have to speak out against it, even if we can't stop it. On the issue of precedence, you know,
thought during the debate about my own family. For those of you who don't know, my family comes from Taiwan. Pretty much everyone in my family lives in Taiwan. And if you've been following the news, we talk about war, the possibility of war every day in Taiwan. And I think about if this were happening over there right now,
Number one, if we set this precedent, what that would mean for my family. I also think about what it would mean to me if I were watching and my community didn't support my family and didn't hear my family. And while Taiwan is a hypothetical for me, it's emotionally close to me, Palestine is now. And Palestine is now for so many of our community.
This resolution I think is measured. I think it's reasonable. I think, yes, it is ideal. I think it is nuanced. I think it speaks to the complexities on the ground. I think it condemns terrorism. I think it condemns Hamas. But I think it supports life. I think it uplifts life. I think
This is a moral duty to say to our residents, no matter if you're Arab, Muslim, Jewish, Israeli-American, right? You belong in our community. You deserve to be heard. And that's why I'll plan to vote yes on this tonight. And I know there are a lot of folks at home watching who
are just getting into activism, there are small steps that we can all take to help. While this is symbolic, donating an eSIM is not. Helping people in Gaza stay connected for just up to $5 a month is not symbolic. These are actions that we can take to help people on the ground, to stay connected to the world, and donations to human rights organizations, relief organizations, will really help people on the ground.
Councilor, go ahead. Thank you. I so appreciate everyone who is involved in this process. And I want to say, just for a moment, about the amended language, that that is actually part of the democratic process. So the original language that was posted was there for people to interact with.
That is why it was there, right? It wasn't there to remain untouched until we arrived here today. It was there so that people could be involved in democracy. Sorry, I'll direct my comments to the chair. Could be involved in democracy and they did, right? They reached out to Councilor Collins and probably to, I certainly had someone reach out to me. People reached out to the councilors and to the sponsor of this particular resolution.
to state what they wanted, their vision of what they wanted this to be. And I know that many, many people did that. And that's where the amended language came from. So I don't want people to think that we are simply looking at amended language that sprung out of one of our minds without input, and that we're voting on it without
you know, thinking about it. But this was something that really was worked on by many people. I appreciate all of their time. I appreciate all of the time of everyone who has been here. It is well worth our staying up late for the things that we do. And I really appreciate that and just wanted to chat for a minute about
how much I appreciate people being involved in our democracy. I do hope that folks will come back and will stay on top of the things that are coming up in the city council and will reach out to us before they're voted on to help us make them better. Thank you. Any further discussion? There's a motion on the floor. Any further motions or discussion?
On the motion of Councilor Collins to approve as amended, seconded by Councilor Lazaro. I could call a voice vote or a roll call, is there a preference? A roll call has been requested. There'll be a roll call vote. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Calderon. Yes. Vice President Collins. Yes. Councilor Lazaro. Yes. Councilor Lemming. No. Councilor Scarpelli. No.
Councilor Sang? Yes. President Paris? Yes, on a vote of five. Motion for a five minute recess. Motion for a five minute recess, seconded by Councilor Sang, all those in favor? All opposed? Motion passes, we're in recess.
I don't have to ask you to vote for it. I'm calling us back into session. On the motion of Councilor Lizardo, revert to the regular order of business, seconded by Councilor Callahan. All those in favor? Opposed? Motion passes. 24-022.
beaten by my own agenda format, be it resolved that the Medford City Council hold biannual trainings refreshers with Medford Director of Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion, Frances Nwaje, or her designee, so that our body may keep these values top of mind in all our work and interactions with the public, Councilor Lazaro. Yes, I had a meeting with Frances Nwaje. Can we make an amendment to this that says designee? Yes. Yeah.
This is Paige. She's lovely. It was a really great conversation. I just think it would be...
an absolute sort of bare minimum, one hour, twice a year, where we have a refresher, just maybe anything that might've come up in our interactions that could be something that we would be thinking about as a body. I'm curious about what it would take for us to meet, to convene. Would we be able to do it with open meeting laws being as they are?
Would we have to do it in an open meeting? Or would we be able to do a training? So we would have to do a training here? We would have to do a training committee of the whole, if we wanted all counselors to be part of it. Or we could do trainings in smaller groups. We could do smaller groups separate. Could we do... There may be exemptions to the open meeting law, we'll have to look into it.
I would be curious to hear about exemptions to open meeting law for that purpose. But either way, I am happy to refer this to the committee on resident services, probably, yeah. City clerk. Ooh, he's a councilor now. Clerk of the council. Councilor, if you'd let me interrupt for a second.
In my previous iteration in state government, we did some training sessions with members of the MassDOT board. We actually had the general counsel in the room. We don't have a city solicitor, but we had the general counsel in the room to make sure that nobody deliberated. There was very specific rules. So let me do a little research on that because there may be a way to do that. Obviously, you're correct because you wanna do it without violating the meeting law, but there may be a way to have the training without violating the meeting law. So if you let me do a little research on it,
find some answers for you. Thank you. I would appreciate that. But I would motion to request that the clerk does that research, but also that we refer this to the resident services subcommittee.
on the motion of Councilor Zara to refer to the Resident Services and Public Engagement Subcommittee. Councilor Sang. Thank you. I'll be brief. I also talked to Director Nwaje about this. Obviously, I think we're all very excited about it. An idea that we had started to talk about before we got pulled away from each other was including boards and commissions in this as well. There's a feeling in the office that perhaps we could do more to align everyone with how DEI works in Medford.
especially given that there are a lot of updates in recent years, and there haven't been many, if any, trainings on this for boards and commissions. And so I would love, if you were amenable, for this to be amended to add exploring doing this for boards and commissions. I'm amenable. Great. On the motion of Councilor Lazaro, seconded by Councilor Sang, as amended by Councilor Sang. Councilor Kalan.
Oh, you were seconding, sorry. All those in favor. Aye. Opposed? Motion passes. Referred to Resident Services and Public Engagement. 24-02. Well, yes. Sorry, Patrick. The chair is tired. Patrick, we'll take your comment. Patrick Clark in 50 Princeton Street.
I want to commend Councilor Lazaro for putting this motion forward. I share conditional enthusiasm for biannual DEI training and encourage City Council's consideration of the following conditions. DEI training could be folded into an overall city employee training, also including nepotism and conflict of interest, where all three together will bring forward the most competent and qualified candidates.
The nepotism section would emphasize prevention of the old boys club of private deals and back-slapping, where family lineage and patronage determine qualification for government service. The DEI section could emphasize variety and integration of broadly cross-sectional experiences and skills across government, in practice and in recruiting, as opposed to simply patronizing box-ticking visual diversity, which can also lead to poor qualifications along a path parallel to nepotism.
Three, the conflict of interest section could emphasize public disclosure of membership in or receipt of resources from state, national, or global organizations, whether they be in the form of a hierarchy or network whose stated goals undermine the fulfillment of responsibilities as an employee of the city of Medford.
These trainings would not only be undergone by city employees during their tenure, but also publicly disclosed and advertised in a place of common access during campaigns or before hirings. This would fulfill both the calls for transparency, competence, and integrity within government and between the public and one fell swoop. If implemented and followed in the true spirit of this proposal, these measures will prevent the kind of mob formation, trials by ordeal, and loyalty tests recently depicted in the film Oppenheimer from being carried out in Medford.
Times of high confusion, stress, and suspicion coupled with low transparency have often congealed into culture wars attempting to rip some bogeyman or folk devil out by the roots. Witches, communists, fascists, Jews, racists, anti-Semites.
We could take a wider lens on what DEI, in union with other measures, could do for Medford's future, or we could see it turn into proving one's diversity credentials in an oppressive, harassing, ultimately counterproductive manner equal and opposite to proving one's patriotism credentials. Let's proceed wisely. Thank you. Thank you for your comment, and Mr. Clerk, please record that as comment on the record for item 24-022, and my apologies for not calling it.
Mr. Castaneda, name and address for the record, please. Castaneda E. Smith. I think it's great that you're going to do this DIA education thing. It's wonderful. But on the other hand, I believe the most qualified job applicants should get hired for the job in the name of public safety and efficiency in our government and private sector, in my opinion. Thank you, Mr. Castaneda.
24-023, be it resolved by the Medford City Council that the City of Medford explore the options, costs, and requirements to open a warming and cooling center for adults experiencing homelessness in December 2024. Be it further resolved that the Medford City Council invite representatives from the administration, including the Board of Health, along with stakeholders in our community and in neighboring communities to attend meetings on this topic. Councilor Lazaro.
I will start by saying that I'm planning to refer this to the committee on public health and community safety. I have been emailing with our board of health folks with a number of stakeholders in the city. And I think the main concern, the main issue I anticipate is space.
Somerville and Revere have both opened warming centers this winter, using a model that is based on the Malden Warming Center, which I help run in Malden, which is a nonprofit, but they use that sort of as a template. And those cities, Somerville and Revere, have opened their centers by contracting with Housing Families, which is another nonprofit.
So the cities use city buildings and they pay housing families to operate the warming centers. So I spoke with
a woman in Somerville who told me it costs them about $200,000 to contract housing families, and they use the armory. I'm trying to sort of figure out what the ballpark would be for Medford to run something like that for next year. But mostly what I want to do is figure out all of that in a committee meeting with all of the people that would be involved in
making something like that happen, but I think the most critical thing for Medford will be space, and if we can find something that is either city-owned or affordable enough for us to make it happen, and if we have any kind of space in the budget, and I'm not sure if we do, or if we would need to do something where we try to just find a nonprofit or a church group that wants to try to run it for us, but
The critical thing that I've observed from my work with unhoused adults in this region is that homelessness isn't a municipal issue, it's a regional issue. So once you lose your housing, you're not considered a resident of anywhere anymore. You just kind of go where the services are. So you're not bound by the lines in a city. And I've had guests at the Malden Warming Center that I knew from Medford because
I knew them from town. So I know that there is need in Medford. And I know that we could help a lot of people. And I know that we could partner with other folks in the region. And we could all do a lot of good. So I look forward to having deeper conversations with people once we can spend more time in committee talking about it.
Thank you. On the motion of Councilor Lazaro to refer to public health and community safety, seconded by Councilor Seng. Any discussion? Councilor Collins. Thank you, President Behrs. I appreciate Councilor Lazaro for bringing this forward. I'm really excited to start a discussion of what we can do to pilot a warming and cooling center of our own here in Medford. As Councilor Lazaro stated, we've known for a long time now that it's not sustainable to keep directing our unhoused neighbors to the resources in other communities to stay safe and warm at night.
communities and other resources are already overburdened. We need to start sometime at figuring out a path towards strengthening our own safety net and supportive services here in Medford. Obviously, this is really complicated and expensive, but it's important, and we all know that Medford has the creativity and the collaboration and the spirit of service to get it done. Thank you, Councillor Collins. Any further discussion by members of the Council? Any discussion by members of the public, either in the chamber or on Zoom?
Seeing none, on the motion of Councilor Zaro to refer to public health and community safety, seconded by Councilor, Vice President Collins. All those in favor? Aye. Opposed? Motion passes. Madam Vice President. Motion to take paper 24028 out of order.
on the motion to take paper 24028 under suspension. Suspend the rules to take paper 24-028. Seconded by? Seconded by Councillor Sang. All those in favour? Opposed? Motion passes. I'm giving the chair to the vice-chair.
What page is it on? Anybody know? The full text? Thank you. Thank you, Councilor Callahan. Thanks. I got it. Um, can you hear me?
24028 offered by President Bayer's resolution calling on U.S. government to end blockade of Cuba. Whereas for 60 years, the United States has imposed an embargo on Cuba, having a devastating economic, social, and political impact on the people of Cuba. And whereas U.S. Senators Warren and Markey, U.S. Representatives McGovern, Presley, Lynch, Moulton, and Tran,
city councils in neighborhood cities, and many state and local officials have called on the Biden administration to restore the policies of the Obama administration, reducing travel restrictions and removing Cuba from the state sponsors of terrorism list that were reversed under the Trump administration. And whereas the continuation of this policy has a detrimental impact on Medford residents and organizations who have family, business and research ties with people and organizations in Cuba. Now, therefore, be it resolved by the Medford city council that we urge the Biden administration
and our congressional delegation to reverse the Trump decision to add Cuba to the state sponsors of terrorism list and restrict travel between the two countries and be it further resolved by the Medford City Council that we urge our congressional delegation to pass legislation to repeal any laws regarding the embargo on Cuba and be it further resolved that the city clerk please submit this resolution to the offices of Senator Warren, Senator Markey and Representative Clark.
President Beers. Thank you, Madam Chair. I appreciate, uh. All of the folks who I've spoken to about putting this resolution forward in the City Council on the City Council agenda. There is a large and vibrant movement to end the embargo and to remove Cuba from the state sponsors of terrorism list and.
There's several, many, many reasons why that's true. One of those reasons is that we already had done some de-escalatory work that was reversed by the Trump administration. It wasn't enough. But to reimpose Cold War, Red Scare rules and thoughts on the millions of people impacted by the embargo and the other restrictions
that the United States places on Cuba for imperialist reasons is just unacceptable. So with that, I have put this forward. I want to add our voice to the chorus. I do have two statements I want to make. I do want to thank folks who reached out and noted that a blockade is different than an embargo. And I'll make sure that the short title matches the long resolution next time. And I'd also like to amend this to include that we submit this resolution to the president as well. Thank you, President Behrs.
Any further comment from Councillors? Councillor Seng. Thank you, President Behrs, for introducing this. I just wanted to lend my support. I talked about the sanctity of life earlier. Giving people food, medicine, water, that very much is in line with the sanctity of life and preserving it. We might not agree with the country for political reasons, but we can't hold its people hostage. Thank you, Councillor Seng. Any further comments from members of the Council?
Any members of the public who would wish to speak? Madam Chair, just if I may also add, I just wanted to add in that it's really important to get this on the desk of Representative Clark. As you noted, Senators Warren and Markey have supported a number of these proposals, as well as Reps. McGovern, Pressley-Lynch, Moulton-Linterhan. Representative Clark has not. So that is something where this is directly providing some advocacy on our federal delegate. Representative Clark, thank you.
Thank you, President Behrs. Feel free to approach the podium. Please give your name and address for the record. Good evening, counselors. My name is Nicholas Shirleo. I live at 40 Robinson Road. I'm a lifetime Medford resident, an attorney, and director of an international relations publication. I'm not speaking on behalf of that publication tonight. I am, though, speaking in opposition personally to the resolution.
Putting aside why the council is spending time crafting legislation on international politics when our city faces plenty of problems on its own, the proposed resolution in effect supports the totalitarian government of Cuba, a socialist dictatorship with a horrendous human rights record.
As Human Rights Watch, one of many organizations, has highlighted, Cuban government human rights abuses have included arbitrary arrests of activists and independent journalists, torture of prisoners, significant repression of free speech, and extrajudicial killings.
Nearly a million people have fled Cuba's communist regime. Imagine some or many have called Medford their home. We should embrace these people, not tout Cuban government propaganda at our city council meetings. Put simply, a vote for this resolution is a vote in favor of the current regime. The United States of America should not be doing business with dictatorships. Why would Medford support the contrary? Thank you.
Thank you very much for your comment. Before we get to you, I'm just going to go to a hand raised on Zoom, then we'll get right along to the folks at the podium. I'm going to ask you to unmute. Please state your name and address for the record. Yes, I'm Matthew Page Lieberman. I live at 15 Canal Street. I very much support this. There's not much I could say that wasn't already covered in the text.
of the resolution. And I think that it's incredibly, just like with the one about Gaza, we have, fortunately, we have Edwards, Markey, and Warren's support, but we have to play our role in order to also nudge.
our representative, Catherine Clark. I think there are a few questions that should be asked. One of them is, what has 60 years of this actually done to improve the situation in Cuba? I don't think anybody here is denying what the Castro regime did, nor the Diaz-Canel one currently. How is that going? How is that democratizing the place? That's one really important question.
to ask. And I think before people speak on supporting the continuation of this embargo, they should be able to answer how this has brought any democracy forward. Just one last thing, though, as far as the distinction between embargo and blockade, it is true that this is an embargo. However, the reason a lot of times that people say it's a blockade is because US government as well puts pressure on additional countries saying, we will not help you financially.
You know, if you go and do any kind of deals with Cuba again, like this has been.
Going on repeatedly, the United Nations, just like with Gaza, continues to ask the US to stop this, to stop this ridiculous economic warfare. And the US and Israel just keeps voting against it. For why? And I think the obvious reason is, I think a lot of us know, is that there are cynical electoral reasons, particularly in Florida. I won't go into any more depth, but on the merits, on the merits, the continuation of this embargo simply cannot be justified. Thank you very much.
Name and address for the record, please. Hey, I'm Claire Blackman. I live on Bristol Road in Medford. I had the honor of going to Cuba with the Democratic Socialist of America delegation this past fall. And it was inspiring to see a country with so much political will to do so much for their people, to see Cuba's massive accomplishments in health care and free education, even under the crippling US embargo.
The embargo is an immoral collective punishment of the Cuban people, which has continued for 60 years to no good end. In Cuba, the embargo means they can't get building materials, they can't take out lines of credit, they can't get vital health care equipment, to the point where they have to reuse pacemakers because they are manufactured in the US.
It is not the Cold War anymore. We can benefit from Cuba's great advances in health care especially. Medford residents could benefit from their lung cancer vaccine, to say nothing of opening trade and tourism. Cuba is no threat to us, and it's offensive propaganda to say it's a dictatorship.
Everywhere I went in Cuba, Cubans expressed solidarity with Palestinians because they know this is all one struggle against imperialism. Let's add our voices to the chorus and tell Congress to remove Cuba from the state sponsors of terrorism list, lift the embargo, and let Cuba live. Cuba si, bloqueo no. Thank you very much. Name and address for the record.
My name is Trent Sandland. I'm a resident of Cambridge. I just wanted to express my commendation to the council for putting this resolution forward. Yeah, the blockade, the embargo, it does no one any good. It doesn't do anything to advance the cause of Cuban freedom. It's only served to immiserate the Cuban population for decades. Thank you. Thank you. All right, Patrick, I think we have your address already.
Yeah, if you need to find me. So my concern with this, not to take away from any of the testimony from the Gaza issue earlier, it was powerful and it was meaningful. My concern is really the precedent that it sends that
If Gaza or if Cuba are local issues, then what isn't? You know, I mean, should we be talking about the Rohingya Muslims? Should we be talking about the Uyghurs in China? Should we be talking about what's going on in Colombia and Argentina and anywhere in the world? I mean, in a sense, yes, but should it be here in these chambers? I think that there's
we have to start to put some structure in place where, you know, there's personal matters, there's local matters, there's state matters, there's national matters, there's global matters, and they're all important, but, and I completely agree that Medford is not this, you know,
completely sealed off entity it were affected by by immigration were affected by by technology changes were affected by inflation. We're not her medically sealed but.
the amount of energy that will go into fighting global issues in these chambers will pull energy away from all of these other things that truly are locally confined issues. And it's like the body needs to continue to function. And if you pump all the blood towards one organ, then all the other organs start to die. I know that's not maybe the best analogy, but it's the best analogy I can think of. So I just wanted to put that on the record. Thank you.
Thank you, Patrick. I think it remains to be seen whether it's a zero-sum equation, but your comments are duly noted and appreciated. Mr. Castagnetti, go ahead. Andrew Castagnetti, Medford. I remember like it was yesterday when JFK put the embargo on Cuba with the cruise ship missiles there. We felt like we were going to get wiped out by nuclear missiles from Russia, I guess.
or the Soviet Union at that time. I think it's great to open up relations with Cuba, personally speaking, providing they don't have any military, especially foreign military installations there. And they don't empty their prisons and their asylums into the continental USA, as they have done in the past.
So saying that, I'm okay with it because Cuban cigars can't be beat.
Name and address again for the record, please. Nate Merritt, 373 Roofside Ave. I guess I'm kind of curious as to why the city of Medford thinks that it knows or should be able to determine whether or not a country should be on the state sponsor of terrorist. This country has a wonderful defense and intelligence apparatus that knows more about the terrorist activities.
than anyone in this community. So I guess I'm just questioning why this city feels like it maybe knows more than the federal government. And if the motivation behind it is because Trump did something, and therefore we need to unwind what Trump did because it's something Trump did, that's a poor decision. Things happen in time. Different people are in different administrations.
But whoever the president is, they're not a dictator in this country. There's a whole bunch of staff that work behind the scenes. So before you pass something where I think you're kind of ill-posed, I'd really question, really, can you make that judgment to say they should be removed without having the data to back it up? Thank you.
It's embarrassing. Thank you. And apologies to my colleagues that I'm sitting here and talking. Usually I'm up there quiet, and I'm sure that some of my colleagues appreciate that.
at least based on past experience, regardless of any affiliation, by the way. I'm sure that's true. I just want to say a couple things. One, there's been a lot of commentary lately. The council's so focused on this, they're not going to be able to focus on the other thing. We put out a 40-page governing agenda.
with dozens of issues. I appreciate the concern that we're going to focus too much on one thing and not be able to do the other. I just don't believe it to be true. The other thing I want to say just on the specifics, the Obama administration, the defense apparatus, whatever we want to say, they removed Cuba from the state's positive terrorism list. The date
that the Trump administration put them back on was January 12, 2021. It was six days after Trump literally tried to be a dictator. And he did it on the way out, out of spite, to try to undermine the legacy of his predecessor. So, you know, I'm making kind of a liberal establishment
you know, defense intelligence agency argument for this, but the fact that there is one kind of underlies why this is something that should just be passed. So I appreciate the support of my colleagues. I hope you vote for it. I move approval. Do I have a second on the motion? Councilor Callahan? Do folks want a roll call vote or is a voice vote fine? All in favor? Would you prefer? All in favor? Aye. All opposed? Aye.
Motion passes with one note of dissent.
On the motion of Council Vice President concert to the regular order of business seconded by Councilor carry and all those in favor of those motion passes 24 dash 025 commercial vacancy tax whereas the city of Medford has many commercial storefronts that are either vacant or
for unacceptably long periods of time, or are rarely and inconsistently open for business. And whereas there exists insufficient incentive for the owners of such property to maintain and rent their storefronts to active businesses. Now, therefore, be it resolved that the Medford City Council discuss the adoption of a commercial vacancy tax, which can be applied to disincentivize these storefront properties from remaining undocupied indefinitely. Be it further resolved that this matter be referred to committee for further discussion with the Chief Assessor, the Finance Director, and the Economic Development Director, Councilor Lemming.
Yes, so is it sorry? So I didn't do this with my last motion is appropriate. Just start by motioning to refer to admin finance motion to refer to admin finance on the motion of Council. Let me to refer to the administration of the Finance Committee seconded by Councilor Callahan.
Is there discussion or yes, Councilor Lemme. So, this is a so basically going going around Medford, I think it's pretty clear that we have a bit of an issue with vacant storefront properties not only storefront properties like in West Medford that have been
unoccupied for a year and a half, going on two years, but also storefront properties that are effective, that are just not open consistently or often. This was a policy proposal that I brought up door-to-door continuously when people kept talking about the fact that stores are just not occupied and generally found
I couldn't find a single person who actually opposed it when I was going door to door. Now, I'm going to be the first to say that this is a nuanced issue. The reason that people choose to create or choose to leave property unoccupied is
there could be a lot of different reasons for that. And so I hope that in committee we're able to craft a policy that can incentivize businesses to open up shop to, or sorry, incentivize landlords to open up shop to good businesses around town and thereby boost the revenue in the city. What we would like to avoid is
you know, businesses just deciding to rent it out to like, you know, a random, a random pawn shop or something so that we just have those springing up left and right around town or just, you know, another another kind of business that I don't want to insult by just bringing up an example. But the point but the point is, like, I don't want to insult pawn shop owners. I shouldn't I shouldn't have said that. You know, but but but yeah, I hope that my point I hope that my never going away.
Yeah, I hope I hope that my my point is heard there. But, uh, you know, uh, in any case, uh, I would just I just think that this is an issue that Medford City Council really needs to, uh, really needs to address and be active about at this point. So I welcome any discussion on motion.
on the motion of Councillor LAMING to proudly insult the business community.
I apologize to any and all. I'm kidding. I appreciate Councilor Lemons, I think appreciation of the nuance of this issue. We definitely have a need to revitalize our squares. There are items later on in the agenda that will help us get at that as well. We have passed as a city council last term, numerous items to help us get there and implementing mechanisms to get there.
It's not wrong to say that we need to do more on the issue, especially of commercial vacancies. We want to be bringing people into the square, into all of our squares, if we don't have populated storefronts.
we disincentivize that. At the same time, the nuances of the questions of turnover and the types of businesses that you'll want to see are extremely relevant in discussing this matter as well, which Councillor Lemming has noted. I've sat down with the city staff on a few occasions before, both this term and last term, to talk about
this idea and there are different views of it, but I think broadly the consensus is we should also as a council consider what carrots we want to accompany the stick. There are some potential state mechanisms that we could look into in terms of giving new starting businesses funding to pay for physical improvements, to pay for
basically capital costs to operate a new business. It will take a lot of talking to the potential business owners, the landlords, to see why things are the way they are. But if we identify the problems as such, there are different mechanisms that we might be able to introduce as carrots going along with this. Councillor Scarapelli. Thank you.
I just, and I think that I understand where the motion's, the resolution's coming from. I think that we just need to be cognizant in the fact that anything that we put forth that companies can look into and say, hey, well, let's take a chance in Medford, but remember if,
it doesn't work, we're going to, you know, it's going to penalize us in a sense that, you know, being taxed and when then that would lead to what we're talking about and seeing unsavory or
other entities entering or being just admitted into each community that would affect us in a negative way. So I understand the frustration because we have three master plans that we spend hundreds of thousands of dollars on for Method Square and nothing's been done. We haven't seen anything. So I know that, as we said, moving forward, I think that
the helping with some of the zoning changes and the understanding of what we're doing moving forward with the planning department to really see what works in Medford. I would tend to hold off on some resolution like this until we see a more of a robust plan that the city is hopefully unveiling relatively soon from what I hear. So, thank you. Thank you, Councilor Scarpelli. Vice President Collins, Councilor Callahan, then Councilor Lueb.
Thank you. I'll be brief. I thank the counselor for bringing this forward often, either in meetings or out in the community. When we're talking about our business districts or squares, residents ask of counselors, you know, why is XYZ business square like this? Why is this vacant? How can we get X type of business in, you know, XYZ square?
There's a pretty obvious limit to what a city can instruct commercial landlords to do with their property. But this is one tool that we could consider and possibly enact to try to incentivize our squares being full and lively and they're always being business tenants and available commercial space and so I'm excited to explore it further. Thank you. Thank you.
I just wanted to mention for anyone watching, listening or in the chambers that this is a resolution that simply sends it to committee. This is an opening of the discussion. So if people are interested in this topic, please come to the committee meetings where this will be discussed. Same with the warming center, same with some of these other resolutions that were passed today and maybe passed later today. This is really the beginning of the discussion, certainly not the end. And we really encourage people to come to those committee meetings because that is where the sort of
you know, meat and potatoes of developing laws for our city comes from.
Thank you, Councilor Callahan. Councilor Lemming. Yes, and I do wish my colleague were still sitting here so that I could respond to some of the points that he brought up, but he seems to have had to step out temporarily. But just to clarify the intent of this, I knocked on someone's door in West Medford, and this person was a business owner, owned some gyms in a couple of other areas, and she told me
that she was trying to open up a gym in West Medford, and she had attempted to contact the landlord several different times, and the landlord wouldn't even return her phone calls. Okay, so speculative squatting, waiting for somebody to give a good price on property, et cetera, is a strategy that landlords do.
this now if the commercial vacancy tax were implemented successfully, it would be applied very rarely. The intention of something like this would be to get landlords to come to the table and work and work with the economic development director, work with different parties. We do need carrots. We also need sticks so that people so that people don't just
own properties and get too complacent with them, but they're incentivized in different ways to own commercial storefront property, not just for their own personal gain, but also to beautify the town. So the intention of this, and I hope that we can hammer out something in committee that works full
that we're trying to do, and I think that's what we're trying to do in both parties is to get something that just gets landlords to the table and understanding that, yes, they do need to rent out something. Suitable in the properties that they own. Thank you. Thank you, Mr Lemming. Any further comment.
Councilor Callahan, are there members of the public who'd like to speak? I see a hand on Zoom and a hand at the podium. I will go to the podium. Name and address for the record, please. Sure thing. Nate Merritt, 373 Riverside Ave. I know it's getting a broken record. So why I'm actually concerned about this, I'm not a business owner. It is a little ambiguous. Does it only apply to storefront properties or would it be all commercial and or industrial businesses?
Sir, I don't think the detail has been worked out yet. So that's why it's being referred to committee for further discussion. I'm actually not sure what the legal mechanisms we have at hand under Massachusetts general law are to implement such a tax, but I think there's an intent behind it, so.
Right. I mean, the intent. I can't ask him. I gotta ask you. Sorry. Yeah. I mean, Councilor Lemming has kind of stated his intent here, I think relatively clearly. If you want to clarify, you're welcome to. I'd just like to, not that I'm responding, but I'm addressing. Yes, tell me, what's the chair? What do you think? In a completely unrelated, completely unrelated. What do you feel? Yeah, just just just totally unrelated to anything happening on this side of the room. I don't.
I don't really understand it. But so the intent of this is to only apply to the commercial storefront property. It's just a thought that came to think. I mean, that's a that's a question that I had. Okay, great. Awesome. Thank you. Thank you, sir.
So and why I was concerned is because right across the street from my house is a vacant commercial property, 400 Riverside Ave, which I was just informed tonight that I guess is not at the moment now being considered for a migrant shelter. However, one of the reasons that they're in that situation
is because it's a vacant commercial building. Now, why it's vacant, I couldn't tell you. Initially, it was supposed to be, I think, a biotech company was the intent, which to me is awesome. I love commercial business. I love private business. Why? Because it's a place for people to potentially work in their community. That's awesome. And a large space like that is great. I caution if we start having
sticks, then people certainly can go out and rent out space. This has been demonstrated where Hey, I've got a space, let's make it a migrant shelter. I mean, there are plenty of other avenues besides business, right to one, they'd want to get income for that building, but then also to avoid on top of that a potential tax.
I really would like to see some sort of plan for the city. For instance, city of Malden, right? When I want to go, Justin, I'm looking at you. Okay, when I want to go and get dim sum with my family, right? There's umpteen, you know, Vietnamese, Chinese restaurants, right? I can go to dim sum in I think three or four places, right? Not Songkran, I went to Songkran last weekend, right? Because the other one I can't, the larger one in Malden Center, right, is full, right?
There was a plan behind that. I don't think it was completely random where a bunch of Asian businesses said, hey, I'm going to go put one next to the other on their own. I think there was some coordination by the city of Malden. And it's a place where young people can actually go and get entertainment. There really isn't a lot of that here in Medford.
So I'd really love to see what a plan for this city is, and including these large industrial and commercial spaces that are vacant. So not just at the state level, I think there's a lot of local incentives that we could do to, you know, populate some of these commercial spaces in Medford. So my caution is be very careful with the sticks. They may have unintended consequences. Thank you. Thank you. I'm going to go to Zoom. Matthew Page Lieberman, name and address for the record, please.
Mayor Mrakas, you're on mute. Yes. Hello, Matthew Page Lieberman 15 Canal Street. I very much support this and I appreciate that Councilor Lemming has brought this forward. I remember when I was looking at this last year, I was trying to come up with some carrots. So I very much appreciate that that discussion is already being had as far as all this alarmism that's just
that's somewhat of a false dichotomy. However, I think if we go into the past, we could see how we could greatly benefit by this. Since pawn shops were brought up, quite a few councils back, this is over a decade ago, I guess, the council had decided
And the mayor's administration had decided to pull all the funding away from the public access station. The station closed. There was a vacancy in Medford Square. And what opened in, what filled, that was a pawn shop, in which the same council would then whine about that there are pawn shops down Medford Square.
I'm not attacking them I don't think you know Councilor Lemus, but I mean, even if that's the case, it didn't start tonight. But as far as this. There was a point in time when we didn't have public access station we did have a spring step building. And one of the counselors is a while back, so why can't we put the public access station in the spring step. And there was this, you know, why can't we why can't we why can't we and there was no innovative thinking.
And I don't know if anybody knows whatever happened in the spring step, but for a few years after it went under, the building was just owned, person was just sitting on it. They're paying very, very little taxes. And then they eventually sold it to a nonprofit that does work in Latin America. And that person who sold it made millions and millions of dollars. They're speculating. They're speculating on property that this council wanted to use for their own community, but the council couldn't figure out how to do it.
That costs a lot of tax money for the community, that costs space that we cannot use. These ideas are incredibly important so that we can address that. And one last thing, I'm just really happy that down at City Hall, we have a new economic development director.
So we could all be happy that I expect a lot of ideas and I'm hoping that City Hall can work with the council and we could have really, really thriving business area for the community. And as well as incentives, perhaps one of those incentives we could eventually talk about is some little bit of tax breaks for companies that decide to view worker cooperatives. Thank you. Thank you, Matthew.
Mr. Castaneda, name and address for the record, please. One minute? You must be psychic, that's all I need. At this hour. I don't have the energy to fight him.
I believe I understand Councilor Matt's idea here, commercial vacancy tax. So the West Bedford Square and other locations can look fuller, like we're all selling on a full apple cart, and it looks better on a retail basis, I presume. And this may be an extra additional real estate tax, commercial real estate tax, on top of the existing, I presume.
as a sort of penalty to push forward someone to rent it out, and make the city look better. Nate brought up 398-400 Riverside Avenue, and I believe it was Life Sciences that bought that building a year or two ago. My son used to work there in the machining department.
And I'm just guessing that I think the life science industry hit the fan. And he paid, or the entity paid $29 million, I believe, for that property. And his last sold, I think, I forget, and previous to that, it was sold for a dollar, probably father to son, I presume. So,
And I believe the entity bought the building behind it, and also the other building behind that, which was Santini Ironworks. They've been in business over 100 years. They build steel beams to build all these bridges in Massachusetts. But anyways, they're all empty. Of course, they're not on street level in the front and center. But what concerns me more than all of this is this.
And I'm generally going to ask if you have an answer and be willing to answer. I'm more concerned if the commercial real estate values are crashing. That is a question. Are they crashing? Commercial real estate values, are they crashing as we speak?
As we speak, I hope not. Right. Big time, I hope not. But because it's pretty late. No, my understanding of the commercial real estate, and again, I don't.
is that it's mainly focused the value issue is in the downtown areas of major cities like Boston. I have not seen, although there is the vacancy at 400 Riverside which is well noted a very large building and office with a warehouse attached but I have not, to my knowledge the assessor has not informed us of any serious devaluation of the commercial properties in the residential is going up. Commercial we just over 5%.
We just finished the tax, not just, but in December, we finished the tax rate and the commercial valuation had increased significantly as well. Yes, I understand. My real estate tax didn't go up prop two and a half style. It went up like four, $500. Again. Yeah. Every year for the last three years, 400, 400, 400. All right. Mr. Cassidy, if there's anything. Yeah, so what I'm concerned about is for,
17,000 real estate taxpayers, if the commercial real estate is going in the dumps, that means the residential real estate is gonna have a huge increase. It's gonna rise dramatically, big time. This happened before, and Mr. McGlynn had this meeting at the McGlynn School.
I said, well, what are you talking about? Prop two and a half, it should only go up like 50 bucks, a hundred dollars. He says, Andrew, you had a full house there, high rate residential owners. And he says, it's gonna go up, I think it was like $700 instead of the a hundred bucks usually. So I said, what about prop two and a half, Mr. McGlynn, Mayor? He says, Andrew, good question. Because when the commercial real estate values go down,
We're gonna get it big time, maybe two, three, four times more increase than normal, which is already $450 for mine last year. That's a scary thought for people with fixed incomes. I don't know if you know about this, if I'm factual, but you might wanna check that out. Thank you for listening. Thank you, Mr. Castaneda. Any further comment?
Hearing none, on the motion of Councilor Lemming to refer to administration and finance, seconded by Councilor Callahan earlier, maybe it was Councilor, somebody. Councilor Callahan, we have Councilor Callahan, I remembered it. The clerk says I was right. All those in favor? Aye. Opposed? Motion passes. 24-026, Transportation Demand Ordinance.
Whereas the city of Medford should address high levels of traffic, whereas developers often need to make exceptions to zoning regulations to feasibly develop new buildings, and the current process of passing those to the Zoning Board of Appeals often adds unwanted uncertainty and delays to these processes, whereas a transportation demand management program automates these exceptions and puts them to the staff level by means of a points-based impacts and credits system, and whereas Everett and Boston have implemented a transportation demand management program
to great success during development of both commercial and affordable residential property, and whereas a transportation demand management program can provide design and programming strategies that developers can employ to reduce car traffic to and from their buildings, therefore be it resolved
that the Medford City Council adopt a transportation demand ordinance. Be it further resolved that this matter be referred to committee for further discussion with the Office of Planning, Development, and Sustainability. Be it further resolved that the members of the Committee on Planning and Permitting submit questions to the Chair, Clerk, and City staff ahead of the committee meeting scheduled for this subject. Be it further resolved that the Medford City Council work with the Office of Planning, Development, and Sustainability to evaluate the suitability of a transportation demand management program, determine the capacity of the city to implement such a program,
and provide specific recommendations for its structure and policies, particularly with respect to the nature of the Medford specific impacts and design of its credit system. And I will go to you in one moment, Councilor Lemming, but I do want to note that this also came up during our planning and permitting committee meeting discussion on
the governing agenda, and we had discussed incorporating this with our larger discussion on the zoning reform. Since some folks and I can't remember what was had talked to planning development sustainability staff, and they felt it would be a good compliment to the zoning to put it in and have our can those consultants work on this as well as part of the comprehensive zoning reform so I just want to let you know that, since we're able to be at the meeting, and the reports just came out recently so. But with that I will turn it over to you Council.
So I was going to motion to refer this to the committee on planning and permitting. Perfect. On the motion of council, I'm going to refer to planning and permitting, seconded by Councillor Scarpelli. Is there further discussion? Seeing none, is there any discussion by members of the public? All those in favor? Aye. Opposed? Motion passes. Referred to planning and permitting.
24-031 offered by Councillor Starpelli.
be it resolved that the Medford City Council ask for representative for BJ's Wholesale Club to meet with the council on construction updates and review neighborhood concerns. Councilor Scarpelli. Thank you, Council President. For our newer members, this is a very contentious situation with the neighbors of the BJ's neighborhood, with the implementation of the new, the building of the new gas station at the corner of Middlesex Street and BJ's entrance.
One thing that we wanted to make sure we cognizant with the neighbors being informed with everything that's happening so they are not left in the dark like they felt the last 25 years. And what's been happening, I guess, is the construction work
they were setting pylons. And as a gym, they were hitting the pylons to set the footings. They shook houses and neighbors were scared to death. Nobody was informed. They let everybody know. I give a lot of credit to our court enforcement officers. They ran to the site at 630 that morning and talked to the
project manager and he showed him some of the seismology equipment that they've had and said that it's not affecting them, but the neighbors want to have
would like to call for meeting with the representative what we did agree with. I believe Council President was that there would be a representative from BJS that would be at our beck and call for our neighbors so if we can reach out to them I don't know where it fell it that it was with the building of the building department, or it was with the mayor's office I don't know who has the.
if we can ask who that connection is and ask him to come to the next meeting, because I think some of the community members really want their voice heard, and especially the fact that they did tell the code enforcement officer they'll be doing this again.
in a few weeks when they set the gas tanks underground. So there'll be more shaking and some other people had some questions with the gas lines that are there. How is that affecting it? And then we had a call that evening
a water main burst in front of one of the residents' homes, and they wanted to see if it's attributed to that type of work that was being done. So I think we need to be super, super delicate with these neighbors, because as one of the members that failed them that night in voting,
in an irresponsible manner, not knowing the laws and the rules of that night, and not having a city solicitor to protect us, it put us in a really, really bad situation. And whatever we can do for those neighbors, we need to follow through with. So thank you, Mr. President. Thank you, Councilor Scrivina. Two questions. When was the incident? I believe it was last Wednesday. Last Wednesday, okay. And last Tuesday. I believe the last day. Got it.
was Thursday was the last day we were doing this. And then they said on Thursday it'll be a couple weeks we're coming back and doing this again. Even if by chance we can get at them, reach out to the neighbors in the immediate vicinity of 4th Street, Middlesex, just letting them know that this is what's happening. One resident said that
they were afraid that the way we're shaping the house, they were afraid it would affect their foundation. So. So the further motion from Councillor Scarpelli to immediately refer this, contact the building department to contact the representative from BJ's and also to request a meeting with us, but also to request immediate notification of the surrounding neighborhood.
All right, that's their daily activities. Great. Mr. Court, do you have that? Appreciate that. Most of it. Great. And we'd like that to go out as soon as possible given the timeline. So maybe before the records. Great. And then I will go to Councilor Callahan, Councilor Sang. Was there anyone over there? All right, Councilor Callahan.
I just wanted to mention that in one of the committees, perhaps you can remind me which one, we were talking about the importance of holding companies accountable for any damages that they do, or for following through on their promises of things that they've committed to. And I see this as part of that ongoing work, but we will be, as a city, we will be doing more to be proactive about these kinds of things. Absolutely, thank you. Thank you.
I wanted to thank Councilor Scarpelli for introducing this resolution. I wanted to second it as well. Councilor Scarpelli and I talked, I think on Wednesday, about how we both called the building department staff over to notify, to talk to them, get some sort of solution out. I think Councilor Scarpelli has really gotten to the root of everything. We were promised a liaison. We don't know who the liaison is. We haven't been, who they report to.
the community members deserve so much more. And while there are a lot of aspects of this project that we were powerless to stop, it just means that we need to do even more diligence on the other parts of this project. Thank you, Councillor Seng. Any further discussion?
on the motion of Councilor Scarpelli, as further amended by Councilor Scarpelli, to refer immediately to the building department for a response, as well as to refer to BJ's for us to have a meeting. Is that to committee of the whole? Councilor Scarpelli. Regular meeting, okay. So we'll send it, there's a motion to send it to building department for immediate response. And then also we will put it on the table.
We'll table it, so we'll take two votes. And if we have it on the table, then we can take it back up in regular session. So on the first motion to refer the question to the building department for an immediate response and to notify abutters of further construction, that was Councilor Scarapelli, seconded by Councilor Collins. All those in favor? All right. Opposed? Motion passes. On the motion to table the paper, so it's on the agenda so we can take it back up at a regular meeting.
by motion by Councillor saying seconded by Councillor Collins all those in favor. I oppose motion passes 2324 dash 033 offered by President bears and Vice President Collins be resolved by the Medford City Council at the planning and permitting committee invite staff from the office of planning and sustainability and associates the Medford City Council zoning consultant to discuss our upcoming comprehensive review and update of the zoning ordinance. Vice President Collins.
Thank you, President bears this is kind of a procedural resolution to formally begin the zoning project which has been in a crescendo for longer than I've been on the council.
Right at the end of the previous term into the start of the new one we officially the city officially brought on the zoning consultant that this council selected. So this is to assign the zoning project a new paper number and formally submit it to the planning and permitting committee so we can begin meeting with relevant staff and our zoning consultant to dive into that work in earnest on a motion for approval.
The motion by Councillor Collins seconded by Councillor Scarpelli to refer the paper to the planning and permitting committee. All those and that's right right. All those in favor. Opposed motion passes.
24-034. This is also offered by me. I'm actually might ask Councilor Callahan to speak very quickly on it. This is just a motion that I put on because we discussed it and public works committee. This was around the facilities management, which I agreed to lead. So I'll just read it real quickly. And then if you, you know, you may be able to provide the context as the committee chair.
24-034 be resolved by the Bedford City Council that the Public Works and Facilities Committee request a report from the Facilities Manager containing the following information. One, complete inventory of city-owned properties and city-managed properties. Two, cost to restore each property on the above inventory to a state of good repair. Three, cost to maintain each property in a state of good repair once restored. Be it further resolved that the Public Works and Facilities Committee invite the Facilities Manager to present and discuss the above report once completed.
Chair Callahan. Thank you. Um, yes, as I mentioned earlier today in this committee, we have discussed getting updates from the administration on roads on sidewalks and on all publicly owned buildings. We also have a new facilities manager. So we feel this is a really nice way for them to get
themselves situated in terms of what all of the city owned buildings are, what state of repair they're in, how much might cost to repair them. So, this is just something that we're, you know, putting forward. And we think that it will both be beneficial to the city and also be beneficial to the facilities manager. The motion to refer the public works and facilities committee by Councilor Cohen second by Councilor saying any further discussion. Members of the public yes Mr Gasconetti.
I think this is great that Councilor Beasley brought this forward because maintenance is key, I've said many times. And furthermore, the McGlynn School, I'm not sure if anyone here knows it, but it's been leaking for years. It's only a 23-year-old building, I think.
That's when I asked for the bike path to be built from those schools to Memphis Square. And finally, it looks like it's getting done. I'm impressed so far. But the point is, there's over 7,000 wood frame homes in this city. I'm guesstimating. And it seems like they're all still standing.
And most of the people back 70, 80, 90, 100 years ago when they were built, most of them were legal immigrants, and they didn't make much cash, salary-wise. But yet, they kept them afloat, and they're still standing. So it hurts me to think, I remember when they built the Method Library in 59, and it seems like 63 years later,
A brick and mortar building is condemned and they had to rebuild it for 30 million plus two from Bloomberg. And if you see the configuration of the two or three roofs, it's like an invitation for snow and leaks to occur, in my humble opinion. I'm not a contractor. So the police station, same thing. I remember being a customer there back in 63 when that was built, I believe.
And I told my friends, it was their fault. They weren't quick on their feet like I was. So they ratted me out. That was five, six years before that. So what I'm trying to say is, if I cut out the Milwaukee,
brick and mortar buildings owned by the city of Method, our most precious assets are not being taken care of. And we don't need no debt overrides, a prop two and a half overrides, debt exclusions. Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Castaneda. Mr. Merritt. I'll make it quick. Just one question. Sorry, I can't ask you. Ask me and I will. Sure thing.
What about considering if the buildings can't be fixed, maybe it's worth selling the property as a revenue generator for the city, if it makes sense, as a possibility, right? Versus if something's really bad and you'd have to tear it down and rebuild it, and you don't know what the city would wanna do with it, maybe it's in a location that's desirable to put something else, be it residential, commercial, industrial, I have no idea, but just as an option four in your list.
Sure, yeah, and I'll go to Councilor Kellyanne in just a second. I think we'd certainly be open to the assessment that it's not worth the existing city capacity to restore it to a state of good repair. So I hear you there, Councilor Kellyanne. This resolution really is all about just getting the information that we need to make decisions like that in the future. Yeah. Personally, I don't think we should sell public land, but maybe a land swap of some kind could be good, but that's neither here nor there until it is.
Any further discussion? On the motion. Second. Councilor Callahan seconded by Councilor Scarpelli. All those in favor? Aye. Opposed? Motion passes. President Pierce? Public Works and Facilities, yes. 24036, Vice President Collins, who has asked to say something. Vice President Collins, yes. Thank you. I have two things. One, I'd like to table 24036 to our next regularly scheduled meeting.
is, why is that funny? I don't know. Okay, here's what, here's something that will not endear me to my fellow counselors.
Sorry, George. I'm going to invoke rule 28, motion to reconsider 24021. That's the plant medicine resolution that we voted on. That's the plant medicine resolution that we voted on. Previously in the evening, we took a vote to send it to committee as a member of the person who voted on the prevailing side. I have the right to ask that the vote be reconsidered. And I'd like to, I don't know if it'll change the outcome, but the vote that I cast differed from
what I plan to support. I just have to take these in order before you continue to explain the motion. On the motion of Councillor Collins to table 24-036 until the next regular meeting, and you'd like it to appear on the regular agenda. So it'll be back on under motions, orders and resolutions at our next regular meeting. On the motion of Councillor Collins, seconded by Councillor Gallihan. All those in favor? Opposed? Motion passes.
Councilor Keohane, you're invoking rule 28 to reconsider paper 24-021? Yes, I am. All right, give me one second. I just wanna double check. I'm sure you're reading exactly what I'm about to read, and it's gonna say exactly the same thing, but I'm gonna look anyway. After vote is taken.
Whereas Councillor Collins was on the prevailing side of the vote, which was to refer paper 24-021 regarding plant medicine to the Public Health and Community Safety Committee. The motion to reconsider. Yeah, you can just do that. So that's back on the table. We're talking about it again. 24-021.
I'm just gonna read it, I'm not gonna read it, sorry. Do we have to vote to reconsider? Hold on a second.
No, I don't have to vote on the motion to reconsider. It's an automatic invocation, it's a motion. So it is under reconsideration, at least that's how I read it, unless someone wants to overrule the chair. 24-021, resolution to support adult access and education for plant medicine. Councilor Collins, if you would like to explain your motion to reconsider.
Thank you, President Behrs. And I do apologize to my fellow counselors for bringing this back to the table, especially at this late hour. But to leave the meeting in good conscience, going into this meeting, having studied the resolution, having talked to advocates for it, I went in planning to support its passage tonight. My vote to send it to committee, I think, was more of my personal vote on that.
was more out of going with the flow than what was really in my plan or what was in my heart for this evening. So I don't know if it will change the outcome, but I personally
would like to retake that vote and have another opportunity to cast my vote for whether we should pass it symbolically tonight as an endorsement of the decriminalization policy, or if it is still the will of the council to send it to committee for further discussion. Is there a motion on the floor? Motion to move the question. Motion to move the... To pass it. Motion for approval by Councilor Lemming, seconded by? Second. Seconded by Councilor Collins.
This is a motion to approve 24-021.
you can make a motion to amend. I'm gonna take the motions in order. Yes, what's the motion? A motion to amend to approve and have the police chief report back. Okay, Councilor Lemming, are you comfortable with amending your motion to approve to also include that the police chief will report back to the council on the recommendation of the resolution? So would the, wait, so to be clear,
we would pass it and then the police chief would come back with his recommendations. His response to the resolution. Sure, that's fine. All right, so seeing that everyone's cool with that, or at least the two motioners, the two petitioners seem to be acceptable on the motion to approve the paper 24-021, a resolution supporting adult access and education for plant medicine as amended by councilor saying to request a response from the chief of police to the resolution.
Is there anything beyond that? Okay. Is there a discussion on the motion? Councilor Kellyanne. I was just gonna say, I worked on this. I'm in support of this. I do, as a general rule, I think councilors should take time to understand everything in everything that we pass. And I know that there's some state laws involved here. And that's why I just wanted to know, but I'm perfectly happy to pass tonight.
Okay, great. Any further discussion? Seeing none, the motion of Councilor Lemming to approve as amended by Councilor Seng, seconded by Councilor Collins. All those in favor? Aye. Opposed? Yes. Motion passes. Do you want to be noted as opposed? Yes. All right. Motion passes, noting Councilor Scarpelli in opposition.
Any further discussion on, oh, well, public participation. Is there, well, we just did Judy, technically. Is there anyone who would like to say anything else? Speak now or forever hold your peace until February 20th.
Larry would like to go home on the motion of counselor Callahan to adjourn seconded by counselor Collins all those in favor. All those opposed motion passes meeting is adjourned.