Welcome everyone to Mr. MHS 2017.
I'm gonna listen to the... I'm gonna listen to the... I'm gonna listen to the... F to the E, R to the G to the I to the E, A to the T to the I to the E, put it down right here. I'm gonna listen to the... I'm gonna listen to the...
You, you, you.
Alright guys, I'm gonna pray tonight. Let's give one more round for the audience before we leave. Alright, I'm just gonna take out my competition now. The only competition I have, David Pagliaro.
Here we go, ready? And... Again! He's out, Sammy wins!
Oh, he has him up. Looks like it's too easy. Oh, he has him up again. Oh, helpful. This is it. This is where they bounce.
The winner of Mr. M.H.S. 2017 is... DEVIN BOMBARDO!
How does it feel to win Mr. NHS? I'm, whoa. Whoa. I did not expect, I honestly, I was expecting Matabella. But, thank you. Thank you everyone.
Good afternoon. Medford is proud to support Team HEMO at Gillette Stadium on Sunday, June 4th. Our community has come together to raise awareness and join in the fight against pediatric cancer. I'm buzzing my hair for kids with cancer. Medford is buzzing off for HEMO. About five years ago, I started hearing commercials on the radio about this great cause.
I think three, four years ago, I had a student who was personally affected, losing a younger sibling, Hemo, and kind of motivated me to do it that year. I decided to buzz in Hemo's honor. I am donating to Team Hemo. Medford is buzzing for Hemo. At Medford, we shave our hair for Hemo. Medford is buzzing for Hemo.
We are so proud of our McGlynn students who are buzzing off of HEMO. And special thanks to Mr. Petrellis and Mr. Kuzmitz who organizes this event every year. Way to go, McGlynn! I donated to Team HEMO. Medford is buzzing for HEMO. Medford is buzzing off for HEMO. Medford is buzzing for HEMO. And I'm donating for HEMO. Medford is buzzing for HEMO. Medford is buzzing for HEMO!
Medford is buzzing for HEMO. Medford is buzzing for HEMO. Medford is buzzing off for HEMO. Medford is buzzing off for HEMO. I'm buzzing my head for kids with cancer. I'm Anthony Petralos. I'm a fifth grade teacher at the McGlynn Elementary School and I'm the team captain of team HEMO this year.
This is our fourth year in the One Mission Buzz Off, which is held at Gillette Stadium, June 4th this year. Four years ago, a third-grade student in our school, Hemal Dufourage, passed away of a real form of spinal cancer. We do it for their family every single year. We get t-shirts, we organize, we get about 15, 20 different people to join the team. Why do we need such luxurious things to prove our worth in this world?
We force ourselves to make sure our phones are our newest models, our clothes are just off the runway, and our homes are of most extreme size and value. We constantly feel the need to compare ourselves to people around us. We are obsessed with the latest of trends, such as what did Kim Kardashian wear to the party?
Why must I know what she wore? Why must I buy the same things she wore? What's so different about me and Kim? Is it because she can wear a dress of ridiculous value? Or because she buys the most expensive things? Last time I checked, me and Kim both need air to breathe, food to survive, and a home for safety. But because I do not own the same overpriced dress Kim wore, I am ignored. The scenario may seem normal, but when you switch the roles to a middle class man and a homeless man, the situation is turned immediately.
Suddenly the lower class person is ignored, but being put down in negative terms, which is lazy, drug addict, slob, trash, and worse. We judge without thinking, before thinking that that person is the same as you and I. They breathe air to live like you, they need food to survive like you, and they need a home for safety like you. But because they are homeless, you choose to place them in a negative way without thinking about them as a person like yourself.
them as a person in the sense of where they came from, who raised them, what are their goals in life, do they have children, do they have a spouse. Most don't ask themselves questions like these when they see a homeless man, because they don't see him as a real person. For example, when a new neighbor moves in, you don't assume they are lazy or a drug addict, you assume they are just like yourself. Yet when you see a man asleep in an alleyway in Boston, you suddenly place negative terms on him such as criminal slob and trash.
Why must us as humans think like this? That person is just like you, whether you like it or not. You must accept this. Once you accept this, you can start seeing them as normal people. People who are mothers, fathers, sons, daughters, uncles, aunts, and even grandparents. These people are exactly like you, just in a difficult situation which is often brought on due to poor economy, lack of affordable housing, lack of education, and medical expenses.
You can help them. You can donate almost anything from food to clothes to furniture to money. Anything will help. You can offer jobs to these people or you can volunteer your time at a kitchen which provides a meal for those in need of one. There are so many endless ways to help people who need to be guided back to their feet. This person we speak of one day could be you. You never know when you'll be thrown in the situation that 564,700 other Americans have found themselves in.
In a recent study, most people had been homeless for more than half a year and had been homeless several times. The study showed most of these people's highlights of their week was being helped in some simple way. These simple ways include a man being offered a job washing dishes at a diner, a pregnant woman getting donated baby clothes and bottles, and a man waking up in the doorway to a sandwich and bag of chips. The simple things you do can change somebody's life. It's taking a few dollars or minutes out of your week that hung.
Now that we've put this all in perspective, do you really need that dress in Kardashian War when there are people around you that can't even afford to eat one meal a day? Do you really need all those luxurious items that will only be put to use when there's a man you cannot even have a warm place to sleep on the coldest of winter nights? You don't. You know you don't. I know I don't. Everybody knows they don't, yet they keep following in these terrible habits.
Make a change in the world. Do it for the people who currently struggle, for those who used to struggle. Do it for yourself, your friends, your family, and most importantly, the future generations. You can make a change, so go out and do it.
Climbing up the top sails, I lost my mind