All right, first special meeting of Medford City Council June 15th, 2023 is called to order.
Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Vice President Behrs.
Still present.
Councilor Kerrio.
Yeah.
Councilor Collins.
Councilor Knight.
Councilor Scarpelli.
Councilor Seng, present.
President Morrell.
Present.
Board, present, three absent.
Meeting is called to order.
Going to communications from the mayor.
23-328, to honorable president and members of the city of Medford City Council regarding food truck permitting.
Dear President Morrell and members of the city council, on behalf of the below entities, I respectfully submit to the Medford City Council the following request for a food truck permit in the city of Medford.
In addition to the city council approval, vendors are required to adhere to health department safety requirements.
We have entity chicken and rice guys food truck 617 12 noon to 8pm Medford Square for circle the square.
We have frozen hoagies 617 12 noon to 8pm Medford Square for circle the square.
And then we have entity frozen hoagies, 624, 10 to 6 p.m.
Duggar Park for West Medford Open Studios.
And entity bond made foods LLC, 624, 10 to 6 p.m.
Thank you for your kind attention to this matter.
Sincerely yours, Brianna Lungo Kern, Mayor.
Do I have a motion?
Or any discussion?
Motion to approve.
Second.
I have a motion from Vice President Behrs to approve, seconded by Councilor Carabiello.
Is there any discussion or questions?
Seeing none, Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Vice President Behrs.
Yes.
Councilor Carabiello.
Councilor Collins is absent.
Councilor Knight is absent.
Councilor Scarpelli is absent.
Councilor Sang.
Yes.
President Morrell.
Four in the affirmative, zero in the negative, three absent.
The motion passes.
Motion to adjourn.
The motion of our student bears to adjourn second by Councillor Caravella.
Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Vice president bears.
Yes.
Council Caravella.
Council Caravella is a yes.
Yes.
Thank you.
Councilor Collins, Councilor Knighton, Councilor Scarpella are absent.
Councilor Seng.
Yes.
President Morrell.
Yes, for me affirmative zero negative three absent motion passes meeting is adjourned.