Hello, happy Monday, and this is Brianna Lungu-Kern, Mayor of Medford, just here with some good news.
First up, if you've been up to Wright's Pond, you will notice that the art mural is pretty much complete.
Our artist, Jamie Chan, has been working on that over the last several weeks.
It looks amazing.
So please go check it out.
And if you haven't got your pass to the to the pond, please do so.
And then Tufts pool is also open for use.
Also, there's a free summer park program put on by recreation from 7-11 to August 15th at Hormel.
It's 9 to 12.
That's in the morning, so go check it out.
And from July 12th to August 16th, it's at Tufts Park from 9 a.m.
to 12 p.m.
Also, Medford Recreation is putting on its movie nights.
There'll be a series of three movies on
was one Friday and our second one is on July 21st.
That's at Tufts Park and the third is on August 18th which is at Wright's Pond.
So you get there around 7 30 you set up and the movie starts right at 8 30.
So please join us.
Also we are doing a lot of work on our streets.
We have almost 50 streets that we're patchworking.
You'll see that work was done recently on Lawrence Road and we have another
30, 40 to go.
We also got bids back for the remaining crack seal projects that we're working on.
That's 94 streets.
So we're doing about 150 streets just with patchwork and crack sealing over the next several months, which is very exciting and well needed.
Also good news on some of our park projects.
We have Gillis Park.
We are breaking ground on that mid to end of July.
We have Car Park that's going to be late July, early August, that will break ground on phase one.
Morrison Park will be done at the end of August.
And then Hickey Park, because we needed time to let the pavement settle, those basketball courts and tennis courts will be done end of August, beginning of September.
And then also great news, a lot of people ask all the time, Riverside Ave is in bad shape.
So we were repaving, milling and paving and doing a lot of the additional work that's needed on that road.
That will be done, hopefully start next week and take several weeks to complete.
And things are a little bit delayed because of the rain.
So just keep an eye out that any projects that we have going on are a bit delayed due to the rain.
But as you can see, a lot in the works, a lot is going on in this city.
And we're super excited and thankful for all the hardworking employees that are making it happen.
Otherwise, have a wonderful, great week and talk soon.