Hello out there. I'm Erica Reinfeld, and I'm running for re-election to the Medford School Committee. I'm the mother of two Medford public school students, an interdisciplinary STEM educator, and a program manager at MIT. I have spent my whole career in and around classrooms and museums, working with educators and students to supplement traditional PK-12 academics with hands-on, experience-based educational opportunities.
My wife and I have lived in Medford Square since 2005, and we're both active volunteers in the community. This is my first re-election, and I am so excited to continue the progress we've made as a district over the last few years, and to move forward some new initiatives as well. But before I talk about those, I'd like to tell you a little bit about some of the work I've done during my first term.
My number one goal has been to support people, and I've done that by bringing community members together to share information, stories, and experiences with people who can truly make change, and by affirming our district's values, particularly around vulnerable and marginalized populations, and in the face of attacks on public education coming from the federal government.
And perhaps on a more practical level, I've pushed the district to address long-standing challenges such as overcrowding in our elementary schools and the expansion of after-school care for families, and to get ahead of the curve on things like artificial intelligence, climate resilience, and disrupted supply chains due to economic uncertainties.
I've also supported initiatives around transparent budgeting, strategic capital planning, proactive curriculum review, and of course, the establishment of a building committee and educational vision for a new Medford High School. The design and funding of that school is going to be a big part of the next term, and I am very excited to bring the broader community into that conversation and build a dynamic, affordable school that supports not just what students and educators need now, but what they'll need in the future.
Public engagement is essential to that work, and that's why I've prioritized communication throughout my first term. Things like regular meeting recaps on social media, you can check out my Facebook page, Erica 02155, which is also my website URL, and joint office hours with my fellow committee members.
Bringing people together is probably the most driving force of my work as an educator and program manager. And you see that reflected both in terms of my actions on the school committee and in the volunteer work I do wearing my parent hat. For the past 16 months, I've been working with caregivers across the city to reestablish the Citywide Elementary Alliance and really ground that work in an equity-focused approach.
I'm also now leading a group of caregivers and educators in the formation of a new Friends of the Arts organization for Medford Public Schools. And of course, I'm still involved with Roberts Elementary School's art and STEM nights. Interdisciplinary education is what I do in my day job, and it's what I've done my whole career.
I don't think answers come from only one place, and I don't think one perspective should ever dominate the conversation. As a school committee member, I'm here to listen, to ask questions, and to advocate for students, teachers, and families, particularly those who are slipping through the cracks.
Medford schools are working well for many students, but not for all of them, and that's why my top priority this term is to look across the spectrum of learners and create mechanisms and opportunities to individualize education for every student while maintaining a consistent standard of achievement and belonging for all.
These next few years are not going to be an easy time for public education, but with strong yet flexible leaders who can stay rooted in their values and work collaboratively towards a shared vision, we can keep things moving in the right direction. Thank you so much for listening, and please reach out if there's anything you think I need to know about your experience with Medford Public Schools, past, present, or future. And don't forget to vote, hopefully for me, by November 4th.