[SPEAKER_02]: Test one, two.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hey guys, I'm on my, I am on my way, but the bus is running late, so I'm joining via Zoom first.
[SPEAKER_04]: I should be there in like 10, within 10 minutes.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'll leave it up to the Councilors who are present to see if they want to start with me in person or on Zoom.
[SPEAKER_05]: Councilor Leming is on.
[SPEAKER_05]: And Vice President Collins just walked in.
[SPEAKER_05]: But we are still waiting for the president.
[SPEAKER_02]: Medford City Council Committee of the whole December 17 2024 is called the order.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mr. Please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_05]: Council Callahan
[SPEAKER_07]: Present
[SPEAKER_05]: Vice President Collins?
[SPEAKER_01]: Present
[SPEAKER_05]: Councilor Lazzaro?
[SPEAKER_00]: Present
[SPEAKER_05]: Councilor Leming?
[SPEAKER_03]: Present
[SPEAKER_05]: Councilor Scarpelli?
[SPEAKER_06]: Present
[SPEAKER_05]: Councilor Tseng?
[SPEAKER_04]: Present
[SPEAKER_05]: President Bears?
[SPEAKER_02]: Present. Seven present, none absent.
[SPEAKER_02]: The meeting is called to order.
[SPEAKER_02]: There'll be a meeting of the Medford city council committee of the whole at 6 30 PM in the city council chamber, second floor, Medford city hall, 85 George B has to drive Medford ma and via zoom.
[SPEAKER_02]: The action and discussion item today is two four five one one, a caucus to designate the 2025 council leadership.
[SPEAKER_02]: Are there any nominations for the office of the vice president of the city council for the year 2025?
[SPEAKER_02]: well, vice president-elect, Councilor Lazzaro.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, sorry, still getting used to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I nominate Councilor Kit Collins for vice president.
[SPEAKER_02]: Councilor Collins has been nominated for vice president, seconded by Councilor Callahan.
[SPEAKER_02]: Are there any further nominations for vice president-elect of the City Council for the year 2025?
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing none, nominations are closed.
[SPEAKER_02]: On the nomination of Vice President Collins as Vice President-Elect for the year 2025, Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, to accept the nomination, I guess I should ask.
[SPEAKER_02]: Vice President Collins accepts the nomination.
[SPEAKER_05]: Would you like me to call the roll?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, please, Mr. Clerk.
[SPEAKER_05]: Councilor Callahan.
[SPEAKER_05]: Vice President Collins.
[SPEAKER_05]: Councilor Lazzaro.
[SPEAKER_05]: Councilor Leming.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that's the next one.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Councilor Tseng.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: president bears.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, six present six in the affirmative one present vice president Collins is the president elect for vice president elect for 2025.
[SPEAKER_02]: Congratulations.
[SPEAKER_02]: Are there any nominations for the office?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, just wait a minute.
[SPEAKER_02]: Great.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you want to take the chair for this one?
[SPEAKER_02]: Thanks.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are there any nominations for the role of president of the city council for the year 2025?
[SPEAKER_01]: Councilor Seheult.
[SPEAKER_04]: I nominate Isaac B. Zach Bears for president.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do I have a second?
[SPEAKER_01]: Seconded by Councilor Callahan.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the nomination of Councilor Zach Bares for the role of President of the City Council for the 2025 term.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mr. Clerk, when you're ready, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, are there any additional nominations?
[SPEAKER_01]: Hearing none, Mr. Clerk, whenever you're ready, you can call the roll.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, this is why you're the president.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you accept the nomination?
[SPEAKER_01]: He says begrudgingly.
[SPEAKER_05]: Councilor Callahan.
[SPEAKER_05]: Councilor Lazzaro.
[SPEAKER_05]: Councilor Leming.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_05]: Councilor Tseng.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: President Bears.
[SPEAKER_05]: Vice President Collins.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Six in favor, one present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Councilor Bears will be the president of the council for the year 2025.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you, everyone.
[SPEAKER_02]: And just a reminder, we will have the formal vote at the beginning of our first regular meeting in January.
[SPEAKER_02]: And right now we are president and vice president elect for the year 2025.
[SPEAKER_02]: Any further comments or discussions by members of the council?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there a motion on the floor?
[SPEAKER_02]: On the motion to adjourn by councilors saying seconded by?
[SPEAKER_02]: Seconded by Vice President Collins.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_05]: Councilor Callahan, Vice President Collins, Councilor Lazzaro, Councilor Leming.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Councilor Scarpelli, Councilor Tseng, President Bears.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, I'm in the affirmative, none the negative.
[SPEAKER_02]: The motion passes and this meeting is adjourned.
[SPEAKER_02]: We'll reconvene at 7pm for our regular meeting.