can it's by Zoom.
You can call in by dialing 1-929-205-6099, enter meeting ID.
You can enter meeting ID 947-377-77381.
I got it.
Roll call, please.
Member Graham.
Here.
Member Hayes.
you're on mute.
I'm member.
He's you're on mute.
She's not, uh, Oh, there you go.
Let's just go.
Member Hayes.
Oh, there you are.
Hi here.
Democrats.
Oh, Kathy's going to be
present, six present, one absent.
If we all may rise to salute the flag.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America, and to the republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all.
Motion to move into executive session?
Yep, I'm just gonna read the,
Number two negotiations and legal matters executive session of the Memphis school committee pursuant to general laws 30 a section 21 a to conduct collective bargaining strategy session.
On the basis that an open meeting may have a detrimental effect in the bargaining positions of the school committee.
Specifically, the medford school committee will discuss ongoing collective bargaining negotiations with this medford teachers association.
This will be conducted by Zoom, will not reconvene in public session following the collusion of the executive session.
Motion by Member McLaughlin to move into executive session, seconded by?
Second.
Member Hayes, roll call, please.
Member Graham?
Yes.
Member Hayes?
Member Kretz?
Not absent.
Member McLaughlin?
Yes.
Member Mustone?
Member Rousseau?
Yes.
Yes, six in the affirmative, one absent.
We will revert to executive session.