This is the City of Medford Conservation Commission meeting, and unfortunately, due to quorum issues, we will not actually be able to have a meeting tonight.
So just for the interest, we have one of the members here, and then we're going to just, the meeting will be continued until August 16th at the same time.
The same zoom information will be used to access the meeting and the meeting will be advertised, you know, put on the city's website and on the city's calendar as this one was so.
I can actually, I'll read the, actually, let me read the open meeting notice first, just to be, make sure everything was Jake.
On March 29th, 2023, Governor Healy signed into law a supplemental budget bill, which among other things, extends the temporary provisions pertaining to the open meeting on March 31st, 2025.
Specifically, this further extension allows public bodies to continue holding meetings remotely without a quorum of the public body physically present at a meeting location to provide adequate alternative access to remote meetings.
The language has not made any substantive changes to the open meeting law other than extending the expiration date of the temporary provisions regarding remote meetings from March 31st, 2023 to March 31st, 2025.
And this is, filing as a notice of intent, DEP file number 215-0233, 4000 Mystified Parkway.
The proposed redevelopment includes construction of two residential buildings, landscaped areas, utility
Um.
Portion of the properties in the 100 100 ft buffer zone to offsite bordering vegetative wetlands and.
So just to reiterate, um, for anybody watching this on, um and for public access, um.
Did a quorum issues will not actually be conducting Conservation Commission hearing tonight for this
I'm sorry.
Apologies to both the applicant and to the residents.
One good thing is that we're just going to be appointing a new member in the next few days, so that will completely alleviate, and we won't have to do this again.
I've been talking to members.
I anticipate we'll have a quorum available on the 16th.
Hi, Dennis, it's Louise.
It's great to see you for everyone.
All good by me.
Do we need to technically open and vote, I believe?
I think a majority of members present.
Yes, that's the one sort of oddball point, but yes, so we, I think just me reading the open meeting law and reading the thing, I think that's kind of opened the meeting.
And so if we can just put vote to continue until the 16th, I guess,
So Dennis, I just, I move and vote on my own.
Okay.
I am making a motion to actually hold on before I do that.
Am I making a motion to open the hearing or just close it?
open and close?
Open and then continue.
Open and continue hearing.
Okay.
I'm going to make a motion to open the hearing on the aforementioned matter before the commission and to continue that matter until the next regularly scheduled hearing of the Medford Conservation Commission.
And I am voting yes for that motion.
That's a yes all in favor.
So
And I'm going, yes, let's have it.
Yes.
So yeah, so folks, if anyone's watching this on the public access again, we apologize.
And if I will just kind of throw it up here on the message thing, if anyone has any questions.
I believe this shows up, so you can email me at dmcdougall at medford-ma.gov.
So that's D-M-A-C as in Mac, D-O-U-G as in Doug, A-L-L as in all at medford-ma.gov.
If anyone has any questions, please don't hesitate to email me.
And I'm gonna actually stay on here for a little bit in case anyone shows up late, but everyone else can,
take off and enjoy your night.
Thank you, Lilies.
Apologies to you and the applicant, of course, but we look forward to seeing you in two weeks.
Absolutely.
We appreciate your time tonight.
I know it's all a bit technical, but I had to check the boxes.
Thank you all very much.
Thank you.
I'm going to hang on just for about 10 minutes to make sure no public comment or anything like that, but otherwise I'll drop.
Thank you all.
Not a problem.
Dennis, is there anything else you need from me?
I don't believe so.
I think, you know, you can.
You can take off, so I think that's appreciated.
I will see you in two weeks.
Yeah, about that, I'll be in touch, but perhaps we could have a conversation about whether or not there will be a sufficient attendance for a quorum.
Do we have a sense on that?
but something to be discussed anyway.
Thank you, Dennis.
Talk to you later.
Have a good evening.
Yes.
You as well.
Bye.