us being here to support us it warms my heart before i get started i want to say happy birthday zach can we get a happy birthday one two three happy birthday zach all right i got one minute so i'm gonna rip it ready you can have three all right all right when i was eight years old i sat in my third grade class and was in awe of what i was seeing on the television
a young man of color walking across the stage being inaugurated as the 44th President of the United States.
Former President Obama became the hope not only for myself, but for generations of those who have been voiceless, for generations of those who have been silenced, for generations of those who have been told, no, you can't.
He looked them, he said boldly, yes, we can.
Three simple words, yes I know, but those three words have informed my life and my purpose.
I made a decision that I'm going to strive for more in this work to represent my neighbors, not because I've been told to or because I was raised to, but because we as a community, we as a city, we as a people have a moral obligation to be of service to causes greater than ourselves.
And that starts locally.
We have to keep telling ourselves, yes, we can, so that the people's platform never falters.
Our commitment to one another never stalls, and that the generations after us can look back and say, yes, we did.
On behalf of all of us, I want to say thank you to each of you for being here, for supporting us, and for continuing to work with us as we embark on the next step of our mission as a progressive movement.
Our Revolution Medford thanks you.
Thanks so much.