This is the Freaking Out on Science podcast. Who needs physics or laws of motion or gravity? In this comedy show, we try the impossible. To deny all scientific facts that have been known for hundreds of years. Join us on a terrific and hilarious journey to deny the laws of physics.
By Adam Peleguin. By Nicholas Camargo. By Daniel Erthel. By Joe Hogan. By Katherine Nguyen.
Episode 1! I'm sorry, was I too loud? I'm just excited. Welcome to Episode 1 of Freaking Out in Science. I'm Joe, and I'm a co-host. I'm Adam, and I'll be answering questions. I'm Dan, and I'm also going to be answering questions.
Today's topic, what would happen if there was no gravity? Without gravity, we would be human birds. I believe I can fly. I believe I can touch the sky. Bro, it's over. I like gravity. It keeps me on the earth. By the way, that's Stan's last name.
We'll give the answers in a few minutes to think. But with podcast magic, we'll be back in just a few seconds. And we're back! With freaking out science. Daniel and I, do you have your suggestions? Yes. To start. Hi, guys. Have we started yet? Hi, Catherine.
I'm Catherine and I am the designer. We were just about to share our suggestions.
Want to join? Sure. While she's thinking, I want to talk about today's sponsor, Spatula City. Spatula City is a warehouse full of name-brand spatulas for everyone. Yesterday, I made an egg with a Spatula City spatula. And I don't like to cook! There's spatulas for birthdays, graduations, weddings, bar mitzvahs, and more. Don't wait. Get yours during the sale.
Buy two, get one free. Act fast, because it's only this weekend at... Statula City! I'm done. Okay guys, let's see those suggestions. According to legend, Isaac Newton invented the law of gravity. Excuse me? I'm pretty sure Nikola Tesla invented it. Tesla is my favorite type of car.
Elon Musk invented Tesla's. No, Frederick Douglass invented it. Frederick Douglass was a balloon. No, Frederick Douglass was an alien. No, he was a ballroom dancer. Wait, he lived on the moon. And the moon has gravity. Wow, a revolving topic. My favorite.
The earth revolves around the sun. We don't need to get into another one of these. Okay, until next time. Bye!