Hey Medford, my name is Aaron Olopade and I'm running for Medford School Committee.
My story is a testament to the transformative power of public education and community connections.
After arriving in Medford in 2013, I found direction, support, and purpose in the classroom, on the river as a member of the rowing team, and through community service.
I was, believe it or not, able to amass over 500 hours worth of time spent in the community before graduating from the high school.
I became driven to lead by example and to work for equity, unity, and progress.
Whether it was as a community liaison for the city of Medford, a team captain at Boston College, a legislative aide in the Massachusetts State House, or serving underrepresented youth with City of Boston, I've been dedicated to these values.
My studies in political science and social justice at BC and my work with the NAACP just intensified my determination to represent the underrepresented and to make a difference through service.
As we stand at the crossroads of tradition and progress,
Mine as a voice understands our past and fearlessly envisions our future.
I'm a product of the Medford schools, an advocate for youth, and a representative who has walked the hallways and felt the community's struggles.
My experience leads me to a platform with these three priorities.
One, a safe and supportive learning environment that produces a quality education.
I envision Medford where students are equipped to handle life's challenges both inside and outside the classroom and can thrive as whole humans.
What will I do to address this?
I will advocate for budgets, buildings, books, and all the tools necessary for students and educators to excel in an environment that promotes safety, security, and sustainability.
Students will be paramount.
I will emphasize the importance of mental health resources, tools for social-emotional growth, and programs that are focused on conflict resolution.
Two, equity inclusion, access, and opportunity.
I see the unequal footing that many students stand on and understand how racism and bigotry hinder young Medford minds.
I'm committed to fostering a learning environment where students feel valued, understood, and free from discrimination.
And I am devoted to ensuring that every student, regardless of their socioeconomic background, has the same opportunities in education.
What will I do to address this?
This means making extracurriculars accessible, paying special attention to the needs of students with disabilities, those from lower income families, and English learners, and advocating for a more diverse teaching staff.
I'll advocate for educational initiatives that create an equitable and inclusive learning environment, such as integrating curriculum that includes contributions from different backgrounds, cultures, and perspectives.
And I will champion an anti-racist, anti-ableist, and inclusive Medford Public Schools ethos.
And three, support of teachers, educators, and families through community collaboration.
Recognizing the backbone of our education system, I will use community collaboration to uplift and empower the educators and staff of Medford schools.
I know from personal experience the power of community, fostering collaboration between our schools, local organizations, and the broader Medford community.
We can tackle broader challenges and impact our students.
A holistic approach to education means ensuring students are nurtured at school, at home, and throughout the community.
What am I going to do to address this?
To solidify a passionate and motivated educational workforce, I'll work to ensure our staff and educators are fairly compensated, have a healthy work environment and the tools that they need
and their voices are central in decision-making.
I will develop a community-wide commitment to achieve these priorities.
I will seek ways to work in our community with parents, students, and local organizations.
I will help to create tools for strengthening these partnerships, such as directories, committees, and an open and safe forum for feedback.
I'm asking for your vote for Medford School Committee to embrace the idea that every student, teacher, and resident of Medford is heard and valued, that dreams and aspirations are elevated
and the vibrant diversity that makes Medford unique is celebrated.
I'm also asking for your financial support because dog running for public office is really, really expensive.
If you are able, please go to my website at electaaronlapate.com and help us with a donation.
Every amount makes a difference.
Help us make sure that everyone is represented and together we create the school system that Medford deserves.
Thank you so much.