We have to live with it, or at least, as Jean said, we have to follow it from a distance.
Or does existence speak for itself?
Jean Lévy, the social group Lévy, the total ecology, the economic situation.
Are we living in a difficult situation?
Are we living in reality X?
And then you have to keep distance between reality Y and reality Y, that's what you're writing for your book.
Do you have to place reality in order to join them, or is distance enough for the product to finish?
Personally, like I said earlier, I'm inspired by everything, but there is a certain reality that I can't talk about with people who are in it.
for the most realistic cases, for the most realistic sensations possible.
When you are a reader, when you read a book, you can either write it sincerely or you can write it because you don't want to read it.
For example, at the moment, there are very few people who are voodooists, and I am not a voodooist.
I didn't raise the voodoo, for example, but I have respect for it.
But for me, writing a book that talks about voodoo is a way of talking to someone who knows voodoo and who is a voodooist.
So, personally, I talked to voodooists, I did research, I read about it.
For me, it was really putting on the feet of characters that seem as real as possible.
And it's true that I wrote all my characters in relation to my personal experience.
Their writers also have the capacity to empathize, because they can put in their place certain rules that allow them to see the writing of the characters, because the reader has taken the label, it reminds me of myself, it reminds me of my friends, it reminds me of the situation I was living.
So all this to tell you what?
It's to tell you that 80% of my novels are fiction, but I'm based on real facts,
Not only my personal experience, but also the experience that I have all around me, the people around me, so that I can talk to them.
And when it comes to topics that I don't want to talk about, I always make sure that I talk to people who have this experience, so that I can talk to them.