Squid Games?
Attorney Wu?
Crash Landing on You?
All of Us Are Dead?
Maybe you've watched some of these, or maybe like a lot of people, you're wondering, what are all these Korean dramas that are all the rage right now?
Laura, what gets people hooked on Korean dramas anyway?
Fashion is amazing, even when I'm wondering where are they storaging all those coats.
Everybody dresses so well, there is true love, the pinkies touching, but when are they gonna kiss?
There is the happily ever after, and drama, and who doesn't like drama?
I mean, how much time do you have in a day?
How much time do I have to invest in something like this?
And then I hear people, they always die at the end.
After you've invested all this time, then they die.
And these extremes, I don't understand what the big deal is.
something less toxic in your life?
Are these realistic standards of beauty okay?
Do kids just think you just have an inordinate amount of money and wardrobe and makeup and skincare regimen?
This is terrifying to young girls.
And why do people get so sucked into these with all these fan vids and fandoms?
Is this a new type of cult?
That's a fair question, Emma.
In the end, what's definitely certain is that K-drama is winning hearts and eyeballs because it has a little bit of something for everybody.
We'll be discussing the tropes of K-drama, the archetypes, what the stock characters are, the plot arcs, and ask what do people get out of watching K-drama and who benefits or loses when we
Tune in and buy in.
Why is the South Korean government trying so hard to get you to watch Korean dramas anyway?
Listen to kdramarama to find out more about these and other questions.
So Serena, if you think kdramas are so toxic, what do you like to watch?
Well, I'm slightly embarrassed, but I watch The Real Housewives, to be honest.
Is it still recording?
Hey Medford Bites listeners, please enjoy some bonus content today from the Medford Public Library Learn to Podcast class.
Today we have trailers for the three podcasts created during that class, K-Dramarama, I Agree, and Disgruntled Tales.
For more information about events at the library, check out today's show notes.
Thanks, please enjoy.
Welcome to I Agree, That Is Stupid, a podcast where we delve into the dumbest parts of our jobs and then cover how to get through them.
We're your hosts, John.
And Calvin.
And we'll journey with you hearing from all types of careers and industries.
From actors to athletes to accountants.
And we'll get practical advice from career coaches to get us on the right path.
So if you're stuck in a bad job or just want to learn more about how people work, this is for you.
You can hear us on Spotify, Apple Podcasts, and anywhere you get your podcasts.
Hello, this is Astoria with the time and date of 1823, the Lord's year in Irmor Kingdom.
I am here interviewing Discrunt Holden to see if he is going to be a productive member of society again.
Yes, yes, there's an agaroon, uh-huh, uh-huh, sure.
Anyway, he is a disgruntled, also known as disgruntled dwarf.
Disgruntled, stop messing with those chains.
I can get out of these.
Don't get out of them.
Freedom!
Okay, can someone put him back in?
But seriously.
Sit down.
Thank you.
So these these are gonna be recorded for the kingdom.
You understand that disgruntled?
Yes Okay, it's going to prove to us if you're going to be a productive member of society again Productive Uh-huh.
Yeah, you got that So it means you're not gonna do the things you did before so we're gonna go over all the your past stuff the good and the bad Okay
Like, all right.
Yeah.
Cause you used to be a hero and now you're in jail.
Yup.
Uh-huh.
You want to say anything for the recording disgruntleden?
I will be free!
Uh-huh.
Whether you like it or not.
That's not how this works.
Guys, what's the name of the podcast?
Never Bites!