Welcome everyone to the meeting.
The other two members of our subcommittee are going to try to come late.
So, but first of all, did you all look over the minutes from our July 29th, I think it was?
Yeah.
Are we good?
Great.
All in favor?
Aye.
Great.
Okay.
So they were brief, and we're really coming to the end here, which is exciting.
So I thought the minutes might be useful.
We could sort of look at them and see if we completed our tasks from the last meeting, and then we can see what else we need to do.
So the first thing was to include survey demographics.
I checked with Danielle.
David is putting together the pie charts, which hopefully he's going to actually also create pie charts for the demographics.
Because last meeting we said we wanted to do that, right?
You gave me- Did he send something today?
He did, yeah.
He did, but- You also gave me a demographic, so they're in the-
I put it in the community engagement.
Oh, that's good.
OK.
Do we care if we have pie charts?
No.
No, I'm with you, Jean.
I don't think it's a make or break.
OK.
I mean, they could be in.
Go ahead.
We're going to have a survey appendix, right?
Yeah.
So do you think we should just put the pie charts in the appendix?
I think so.
The survey report as part of the appendix?
Yeah.
Okay.
I said I was going to add public comments to the issue sheets, which I did.
You did?
Then I should update those numbers because I took it.
Remember I had how many comments we received overall.
Yeah, I definitely added, so what I did was I went through all the survey, well I added whatever public comments that we hadn't added in, which there were a few, and then there were a bunch of comments on the survey.
Okay.
Because remember, in addition to completing the survey, people were invited to comment.
Yeah.
So, and I think that I,
Where is that document?
I think I reflected in the, I'm trying to find it so I can make sure that I did, but in the actual document that they were comments that were gotten from the survey.
Here we go.
Yeah, because I say we received approximately 900 pieces of feedback
Does that include the survey?
No.
OK.
So then the survey is 600.
Oh, no.
It does include the survey.
That includes a survey.
OK.
So on the issue sheet, I thought I had all the code.
I don't know.
I don't know what I did, because it looks weird to me.
But you look at it and see.
Article two, yeah, I put the, okay, yeah, there we go.
It's just the preamble that didn't look right.
So if you look at it, you can see that there's, like on the left where it's got emails, June 8th public hearing emails, form, so the comments we got from the email form.
Yeah, circle to square, right spawn, and then at the end there's survey, and there's quite a lot of comments there.
So I don't know that I'll, because I said that I include this survey in my 900.
Yeah.
Oh, you don't have to change it.
But I don't think I'll change that.
But we're going to include that in our final report, right?
The issue sheets?
Yeah.
I thought we were going to try it so it wouldn't be so big to put a link in there.
We're going to do a link.
Yeah, right.
Exactly.
To the issue sheets.
Yeah.
OK.
Okay, so that piece was done.
What else did we do?
Oh, you were going to revise Article 8 recommendations to separate out recall?
I did that.
Okay.
I'm pretty sure I did.
Let me double check.
I don't think I have finalized all the footnotes.
So that, I was just,
I have to get the footnotes for the award representation, diversity.
Yeah, I have to get a few more footnotes.
And I gave you some suggestions, if it helps.
Yeah.
OK.
So that we need.
So we still need to get footnotes.
And I sent you that Mass General Law on the budget, right?
You did.
It's been a while, so I'm just trying to remember what that related to.
Oh, yeah.
I put it in section six.
Right, right.
Yeah.
Put the link in.
OK.
And there's a bunch of stuff in the appendix.
Maybe we'll add more to it.
Maybe ultimately we'll decide not to include some of it.
I don't know.
But there's a bunch of stuff in the appendix folder.
We need to just put it together.
So we also, the other thing I didn't do was ask, we were going to ask if anybody has photos.
What do you think?
Do we want to try to do?
I mean, it might make a report look nice if we had pictures, but yeah.
A few pictures.
Again, if we have a lot of pictures, maybe set up a link, different events with a bright spawn.
Well, we definitely don't have a lot of pictures.
I know we don't.
Do we have any pictures?
I know.
I don't recall taking.
Stay away from it.
Do we care?
Not really.
Then let's not worry about it.
Because even if we did get pictures from events, we don't necessarily have permission from all the people in the pictures to use them.
One thing we could do is,
We do have a banner that we used at events.
If I could somehow put that into a photo and make it a JPEG, we could maybe put that on the cover of the report.
I mean, I don't know.
It's just an idea.
I'll try to see if I can capture the banner.
So it would be sort of like using it as a logo.
I mean, we'll want to put Medford's logo on there, right?
I think we should put Gene out there as a logo for all the work you've done.
Yeah, and Milva.
OK, well, I don't know if that's going to work, but we'll see.
So Gene, do you have any other thoughts on what else we need to do in terms of actual content?
I mean, there's the appendices like the survey.
Is there going to be like a survey report?
Is David?
I don't know if David is going to do that.
He said he was going to do a survey report.
He's making pie charts.
I don't know if that there's going to be any text in it.
So it might just be here's a bunch of
data.
I mean, I was thinking about that, but in your community engagement, there is information about the survey.
So I think that's probably sufficient.
And that if we just put the graphics in, what do you think?
put the graphics in the appendix.
Yeah, because we're also going to put the questionnaire, right?
We'll put the blank questionnaire we talked about.
For the survey?
Yeah, the survey.
I have to get that from Danielle, see if I can pull that off.
If they would just pull that off the Google survey.
OK, we'll get that.
I think what you put in the community engagement report about the survey is good.
So probably enough in terms of just writing a little text about it.
I mean, if Javid wants to write some sort of analysis, that's fine.
But I don't know that he will.
But I don't know.
We'll see.
And then, you know, I mean, the recommendations have been read through, right?
I added the, I added one to the major recommendations.
I added, because we, I put Institute of Financial Reporting Requirement for elected and other officials.
And I need to see if I need to add to Article 9 too.
Were there any other changes we voted on recently that we need to talk about?
There's the financial reporting.
There's the.
Oh, I put it's okay.
Go ahead.
Sorry.
That's all there was the vote on, you know, replacing a vacant position.
I don't know that's kind of in the weeds with city council school committee.
Yeah, I felt like the only one that was big enough to put in the major recommendations was the financial disclosures.
Okay.
What do you think?
Yeah, I just can't remember all the things.
Yeah, I mean, remember, but I, you have a good memory.
I thought that was really the only one that we should have, like, sort of pulled out.
The other ones are more sort of like, you know, I'm not saying they're minor, but, you know, um,
They're more sort of standard business, you know, standard practice kind of things.
Okay, so that I added.
I don't think there's anything else we need to add since the main thing was the financial disclosures.
In that section nine, right?
So do we have a write up in section nine about that?
Yeah, I mean, it's very short.
It just says requirement for annual financial disclosures.
The committee recommends that elected officials and some city officials be required to submit an annual financial disclosure form to be generated and overseen by an ethics commission.
Okay.
And then, you know, they can read the details in the draft chart.
Okay, so adding the footnotes, other than adding the footnotes, I think we're good.
I mean, I'll probably read it over.
I was just reading over the introductory letter and making a little few changes, you know, changing some wording and stuff.
I'm probably going to do that until the end.
Did the full committee weigh it?
Oh, no, we're going to send it to them once we put it all together.
I mean, I sent them the draft versions, but nobody had anything to say.
I don't think anybody read it.
I think they were too busy working on their draft charter.
So the idea is that the Collins Center is going to get the revised draft charter with the typos fixed and the things that we added since they sent us the draft charter and the changes that we made.
I've asked them to get that to me within the next week to two weeks so that I'm going to proofread it one more time.
Then if we can get this final report part together, we would just put it all in one package and send it to the committee and then we can
at our meeting in October, which would be, which is our final meeting, we will just see if anybody has any, I mean, the same thing we did for the draft charter, I don't expect there to be any big, but you know, any big things that we're gonna, but maybe somebody will say, why didn't we say this in the recommendations or, you know, so we'll see.
Yeah.
Oh, I'm sure someone will say something.
But I don't think it'll take more than one week.
I don't think.
As long as they're not trying to re-vote on the charter.
Yeah.
That part is done.
It's just a question of whether anybody thinks that they don't like the wording in the final report or mostly I think it will be if somebody thinks there should be something else added to the recommendations or we should pull this out and emphasize it.
So because I'm pulling it all together.
Yeah.
So that's what I was going to ask.
And you have whatever your software you're going to use?
I was just going to do Microsoft Word.
Yeah, as long as it looks.
I don't care as long as it looks decent.
They have templates that you can have a title and table of contents and appendices and stuff.
That's awesome.
So do you need any help?
What do you need for that?
It'd be good if everything is done.
So I think you're doing the footnotes.
Yeah.
I'll do that.
Let me give myself a deadline.
Let's see.
Today's the 12th.
Monday is the 17th.
Let me do it by the 18th.
Okay.
And then possibly you could start putting some things together like the, you know, the, the beginning, if, if I can manage to get an image of the banner, otherwise you can probably do something graphic like with Microsoft word.
Um, but there's, um, the members, you know, that little, well, we're going to put all the members at the beginning.
How do you want the, like what's the order that we want?
Well, I put it in there.
What I'm wondering is, yeah, no, I think it's better to put it at the front as opposed to at the end of the introductory letter.
I think that makes more sense.
So there'll be a title page, table of contents.
Yeah, and then we'll show the members.
Members, then introductory letter.
Yeah.
And then I think major recommendations.
What about the appendix is until the end.
Yeah.
So then introductory major recommend, wait a minute.
Introductory letter comes before major recommendations, right?
Yeah.
And then do you think the community engagement summary?
No, maybe the community engagement summary should come before major recommendations.
Okay.
Yeah.
What do you think?
Does that make sense?
Yeah, I think so.
Because then after major recommendations, you want to go into the- Then you go into each article, which we don't have any for Article 1, which hopefully, you know, no one's going to be like, what's going on?
But Article 1 is just definitions.
Right.
I mean, the only major recommendation we have for Article 1 is to include an article
Because we don't have one in our current charter, but I don't think it's worth, yeah, we'll just leave that.
And then after that would be the full charter?
Yes.
OK.
I think, yeah.
And I think the appendix goes at the very end.
Yeah.
So that's the table of contents materials, right?
When we get to the appendix, you know, you can make, you can use your judgment in terms of how to arrange what's in the appendix.
Okay.
The thing, for footnotes, we are, we're just going to
Footnote within the text that we're footnoting right those don't go at the end.
No, I don't.
I think it's easier for the reader, since there aren't any just to have it in the.
Yeah, I agree.
Let's see if I can remember.
Oh, like in the introductory letter, there was reference to, like, we're including a couple of the, we're including the generic modern charter in the appendix that we used as a guide, and we're including the, some memos from the Collins Center, and they're, like, I can change it and take them out, but I made reference to them in the introductory letter,
I put in parentheses appendix number x. But we could take out that if you think it's- No, I can even put a hyperlink so if people want to- Yeah, if you wanted to do that.
That would be awesome.
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
So that's all you need, just the actual content.
Yeah, I think by the time I get into it, I'll probably find questions or something.
And if it would be helpful, I mean, maybe it's just easier for you to do it on your own.
But if it would be helpful for us for me to do anything, or for me to be there and help you just let me know.
Yeah, it's kind of a one person.
Yeah, that's what I figured.
Not really.
Yeah.
But if I
If I need help, I'll let folks know.
OK.
Awesome.
So I don't know.
Can you think of anything else?
I mean, I want to go at least another 15 minutes in case David jumps up.
But I knew this would be quick.
I mean, basically, we have most of it done.
We've just got to wrap up the details and then put it together.
You can reach out you can have a conversation with David about this.
It's not really policy.
No, I that's right.
It's planning at this point.
We're not making any.
So we're not making any decisions.
Any decisions that are made about the final report that we put together will be made at the final public meeting of our committee.
So
So no, I think we're in good shape.
Oh my gosh, that's good.
Easy.
I'll make a motion to adjourn.
You can send them the minutes, Milva.
Not that rush to get on.
Yeah.
Well, we've gone through our list.
We've done our work.
The work that needs to be done now is just work sitting at our desks, right?
Yeah.
I'm waiting until the 18th, so you'll have your stuff done by then and then I'll start working on it.
How long do you think you'll need?
couple of days?
Our next meeting, our committee meeting is, I think, October 3rd.
So ideally, you know, if I could get it to the committee two weeks in advance, that would be nice because I can use them, but I don't even know when I'm going to get the charter from the call-in centers.
I mean, I've tried to emphasize to them that I wanted it soon.
So that's the 19th.
Oh my gosh, that's really soon.
Yeah, I'll try to do the footnotes this weekend.
Okay.
All right, I'll wait for the 19th.
Yeah, we made a deadline at our last meeting, deadline for edited final report August 12th, but I guess, you know, it's summer.
Well, we had it edited and we just didn't have it all in one place.
That's right, yeah.
And this we are because our final meeting is October 3rd.
Okay, awesome.
Maureen, made a motion to adjourn?
I second.
Great.
See you all soon.
Thanks, everybody.