I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America and to the Republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all. We have negotiations and legal matters, executive session at 5.15 PM. I call on a motion to enter into executive session pursuant to General Law 30A, Section 21A.
to conduct a strategy session on the basis that an open meeting may have a detrimental effect on the bargaining and litigating positions of the Memphis School Committee. Specifically, the Memphis School Committee will be discussing ongoing collective bargaining negotiations with multiple bargaining units in a pending litigation matter. The Memphis School Committee will convene in public session immediately following the conclusion of the executive session, expected to be at 6 p.m. Motion to go into executive session.
Motion to go into executive session. Seconded by second member Graham. All those in favor. Aye. All those opposed.
In an executive session, I'm happy to announce that by unanimous vote, we took a major step to pay equity for our kids' corner and paraprofessionals. So that was a 7-0 vote, and those contracts have been ratified, which is great news. We also want to welcome back Domenico Bruno and Melanie Chavez. Yes, thank you for being here, our student reps.
We're going to move on to the consent agenda, bills and payrolls, as well as regular school committee meeting minutes, September 19, 2022. Motion to approve? Motion to approve. Seconded by Member Hayes. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Consent agenda is approved. There are no reports of subcommittees. We have number six, report of the superintendent. Superintendent's updates and comments. Dr. Maurice Edwardson. Turn it over to you.
Thank you, Mayor. Good evening. First, I would like to acknowledge our fellow Floridians who have a long road ahead of them due to the devastation caused by Hurricane Ian. And for the more than 100 plus people who have already passed away as a result of the hurricane, I would like us just to observe a moment of silence
Everybody could rise for a moment of silence. Thank you. Also, since we last met,
At the high school, both on the vocational side. There is a beautiful memorial garden, honoring many members of our staff who have passed away over the past several years, and I want to just thank member
I'm former member vendor code, man, Brianna for supporting that event. Principal Fallon who's here and principal deliver, who also with our CCS our students.
CCS our leaders who coordinated the beautiful ceremony to honor the last members of staff, so I just want to thank them for such a beautiful ceremony, and when you're at the high school complex. When you go into the main entrance.
of the vocational side you can see the beautiful garden. Also, on the West courtyard side of the high school, you can see the continuation of the garden on both sides of our campus.
So I want to just share some updates and remarks. First, we are in the month of October. October is a symphony of permanence and change, said the author, Bernardo Overstreet. The color of the leaves are changing and providing vibrant colors in the Middlesex Fells Woods, which abuts Medford High School, which beautifies our landscape.
I want to open with a very large congratulations to our Mustang marching band and our color guard on hosting the New England Scholastic Band Association competition last Saturday at Hormel.
12 school districts competed and the Mustang band took home second place. Additionally, our color guard took home first place. So we're very proud of them. They will be continuing to compete in many more competitions this season. Great job, keep up the great work Mustangs.
Last week we also had 15 Italian students, accompanied by Dr. Bobo coordinator of world languages, Miss Canada, Michelle for miss over daddy, and former world language director misty color de Carlo.
They attended Puccini's famous opera, La Boheme, at the Emerson Colonial Theater. According to Dr. Bebeau, our students studied this opera in class and later, as in the tradition of the world language department, we brought our students to witness the actual opera. I hope this tradition will always continue at Medford High School.
Also, great community partner Tufts University, not only held an incredible community day event yesterday with over 60 nonprofit tables that had information free food and games. They have also informed us that their School of Medicine hosts the Sherwood Clinic at Cambridge Health Alliance on Canal Street in Malden.
from Saturdays from one to 430 no insurance is necessary and interpretation is available their services include blood pressure and glucose screenings, nutritional counseling, medical management options and school physicals. So if you're out there and trying to get an appointment, please take advantage of that.
I want to remind the community that this Wednesday, October 5, there will be no school. As our Jewish students, staff, and neighbors celebrate Yom Kippur, or the Day of Atonement, may I say to our Jewish friends, Gamar Fatima Tovah, which means, may you be sealed in the book of life.
I really appreciate the quote of the late Rabbi Jonathan Sachs, who once said, the most important lesson of the high holidays is that nothing, nothing is broken beyond repair. It is never too late to change and to be better. Next Wednesday, October 12 Medford CPAC will be hosting
Their meeting by zoom on the agenda is to meet the administrators of the central administration and the special education department, as well as their general meeting. So six to seven is their general meeting and meet the administrators starts at 7pm.
This coming weekend. As you know we are now well into fall. And so during this season there are lots of fairs fundraisers social events, including the following October is breast cancer awareness month, and the Mustang girls volleyball team will be hosting a pink out tournament.
To raise money for breast cancer research, the weekend of October 22 and 23. The team is selling t shirts ahead of the tournament at a cost of $20 track down a volleyball team member to grab a t shirt to support this important cause.
For those of you who may have Columbus Day or Indigenous Peoples Day off, please consider coming out to support the Medford Family Network at the 11th Annual MFN Golf Tournament hosted by Yokey Restaurant. The tournament is held at Sagamore Springs Golf Club in Linfield. The cost is $150 per person. You can sign up on the Yokey website at yokeyrestaurant.com.
The MFN are also actively seeking donations for prizes for the raffle. For further information, please reach out to Ms. Marie Cassidy.
Saturday, October 15 from 12 to three brings the return of the harvest your energy fair behind the McGlynn school. And on Sunday, October 16 from 11am to 4pm, the Brooks PTO will be hosting the annual fall fest. It's a fun time for all. I strongly encourage families to come out to both events on Saturday and Sunday.
It'll be lots of fun, lots of prizes. Also, again, next Monday, there will be no school. It's October 10th for Indigenous Peoples Day, Columbus Day.
October is also Italian American Heritage Month. It is celebrated every year to honor and recognize the centuries of achievements, successes, and valuable contributions of Italian immigrants and Italian Americans. The first Italian American Heritage Month was celebrated in 1989 by a special proclamation of both Congress and President George H.W. Bush,
Over 5 million Italians immigrated to the United States between 1820 and 2000.
Italians are the fifth largest ethnic group in our nation, and one of the many nationalities that have made Medford home. To our Italian-American friends, and forgive me if I botch it a little bit, Feliz Mese del Eredita Italo-Americana. Happy Italian-American Heritage Month. And I close with a poem. It says, it's called Hello, October.
Oh, one of the best things you can do for yourself is taking time to learn and grow. Once you give yourself patience, you become your best friend and the empathy, self-kindness and resilience are what you need to grow. Thank you and have a good evening. Thank you. Thank you, Dr. Edward Vincent. Number two, we have report on chapter 74.
Vocational Programming at Medford High School in the 2022-2023 school year. Dr. Peter J. Cushing, Assistant Superintendent of Enrichment and Innovation. And Mr. Chad Fallon, Principal Director of Medford Vocational Technical High School Programs. Welcome.
Thank you, Madam Mayor and members of the school committee for this opportunity to present the annual presentation on Chapter 74 programming. As Mr. Fallon will detail in his presentation, the vocational school is seeing great expanses and expansion within its programs and is doing a really great job supporting our students with these hands-on, real-world learning applications. Mr. Fallon. Thank you. Good evening. Nice to see everybody.
Gonna give you guys an update on what we've been up to over the past year. Actually, when I was looking at my presentation from last time, I'm not sure that we did this last year because of, I'm not sure, I couldn't find it. I found it two years ago. It was all about remote learning. I was happy to kind of turn the page on that. I wanna introduce some new staff this year that we hired. First off, his name is Andrew Theobald, and he's in the picture to the right, actually. He is our new automotive technology instructor. To the right, actually, he is our new automotive technology instructor.
And then we also hired a metal fabrication instructor, Mr. Curtis Jackson, who's on the left. When I went into the space to take pictures of the teachers, the students were more than happy to jump into the picture with them. So I just let it happen. So that's some of the automotive and some of the metal fab students, two great additions to our team.
We have been doing some renovations. You know, no report is usually complete on my end in case I haven't broken down some walls. So I'm gonna fill you in on what we've done. Cosmetology, as you know, the salon opened a year ago, but we finally moved the grade nine and 10 classroom up to the room next to the salon, which actually already had glass windows installed. So now the freshmen and sophomores can look into the salon. The two teachers are together now.
We renovated our Make Way for Kids and our early childhood education program, the Make Way for Kids program, which is a nursery school for little tykes on three days a week in the morning. We moved them from the cosmetology space downstairs to a ground level floor room. And that's a picture that you see there that's completely redone with new carpet walls, window treatments, and some plumbing. You can go to the next slide. The electrical department,
As you know, there's booths that the students work in. They were splintered and old, so we needed to replace all the booths. So that was a project that the carpentry students took on. They removed all the booths on the left side of the shop and replaced them with brand new booths for the students to work in. The room on the right, on the top, is just a picture of the cosmetology-related room. The teacher did an incredible job getting it to where it is now. You can't really see it, but off in the back are the windows that look into the salon.
And then the bottom right is a picture of graphic design. It was completed last spring. And these are two rooms that have been combined. That's the former cosmetology space, which is now custom desks that were built by the carpentry students and new computers in that space. The Mustang Mall also moved to a new location on our side of the building. And that's where he was.
A quick report on the Skills Capital Grant. If you remember correctly, the Skills Capital Grant is awarded to vocational technical schools, and this was our third time receiving it. This time we saw just under $365,000, and this was directly funded for the Construction Craft Laborers Program, as well as our other construction trade programs, electrical, carpentry, and metal fabrication. That's just one picture on the left of many pieces of equipment that we got
One of my students here to the right, who's in the program, could tell you more. We completely outfitted the shop with the type of materials that students would need out in the workforce. So we have that. We have a couple of pickup trucks. We have a lowboy dump trailer. We have equipment inside that won't even leave the shop. And then we have other stuff that we're using on job sites. So we're really happy about that.
And this was, I just have to do a special thank you to the teachers in that program, Mr. Danny Kelly, Mr. Ralph Taleva, Mr. Larry Brown, and of course to my amazing administrative assistant, Gina Citrano, who kind of pulled it all together for us on the budget end. So thanks to that team. We also were recently awarded a Mass Life Sciences grant that we applied for, just under $120,000. $20,000 will be put towards professional development.
And the remaining is for supplies and materials for our biotechnology program. Can't really see it, but what you can see on the left is kind of a, over the last six or seven years, the enrollment shift in our career and technical education.