Mic check. Test one, two. Test one, two. Good.
I know, I know
th th
I'm not doing nothing without it, right? Learn my lessons well. He's gonna let me know when we're ready to go. I know, yeah. Those are my...
I'm trying to sort out some technical glitch. I know you know. That's a part of it.
You know, you know what it is.
All right, we're good to go.
So good evening, friends and neighbors. My name is Terry E. Carter, and I direct elder services here at our beloved West Medford Community Center. Welcome to another live monthly presentation of Fresh Fridays, Words and Music, Rebranded, Cobbed and Sanded for June, our last show before we break for a few months. We're happy to be back with you tonight.
with a unique conversation that gets us back to our culture-keeping duties here at 111 Arlington Street. Thanks as always to assistance from the Medford Arts Council, a member of the Massachusetts Cultural Council for helping us do this month after month.
So as the emerging summer continues to heat up, we want to remind you that we want you to stay healthy and we're still trying to be mindful of local health requirements and concerns. So masking is welcome but not required.
As always, we're just happy to be sponsoring live programming here at the WMCC and glad to see our neighbors, our friends and supporters coming through the doors. Again, thank you so much for being here. Thanks also to our other principal event sponsor, that's Kevin Harrington of Metro Community Media.
for consistently guiding us as we broadcast you via Medford Community Media Channels 9 for Comcast and 47 for Verizon. Thanks also to super volunteer Mark Davidson. So if you're out there watching on your electronic devices, your television, welcome to the show. So before we get into the main business for the evening, we do want to highlight the fact that this community
anniversary and we want to thank everyone who came out for the two commemorative events we held over Memorial Day weekend to celebrate our legacy and our longevity. Johnny Reed and company did a splendid job on the breakfast and as always Kelly Tucker and her crew made the place look beautiful. More is coming
I encourage you to say, have a good time and clap. So this evening's program is really not a complicated one. At its core, it's about the virtue of friendship, shared experiences, and a home community that's nurtured the minds, bodies, and spirits of a couple of buddies who have been able to then go out and make their own way in the world with a decent measure of it.
So, Calvin A. Lindsey Jr., producer, director, and founder of Centurion Filmworks, began his career at WGBH-TV, Boston's PBS affiliate. He is a seven-time Emmy Award winner.
who served as series producer of Say Brother, one of public television's longest running local community-oriented series. It has been for a number of years called Basic Black. His credits include myriad projects ranging from political coverage to documentary and dramatic treatments
Calvin has received the award-winning documentary, conceived the award-winning documentary series, Reflections. The Reflections series chronicled the lives, seminal moments, and motivations of a number of artists and cultural innovators like Judith Jameson, James Earl Jones, the Nicholas Brothers, and Henry Hampton of Roots.
So another award-winning series featured some of the most notable musicians working in the jazz genre among the performers who
Stanley Turrentine, Ron Cotter, and Roy Haynes. He wrote, co-produced, and directed The Devil's Music, 1920s jazz, a one-hour film for the PBS series Culture Shock, which examined the often controversial relationship between art, morality, and society. The New York Times hailed the project as a documentary that addresses the complex interaction of race and class,
and engages viewers in a conversation as vigorous as the art it chronicles. Lindsay co-produced the PBS nationally broadcast Rebel, a documentary feature about Loretta Janetta Velazquez, one of the approximately 300 women
who fought in the American Civil War disguised as male soldiers. Rebel ultimately received the Organization of American Historians Eric Barnard Award, honorable mention. His work has been recognized by the National Black Programming Consortium, the Association of Massachusetts Broadcasters, the New York Film Festivals, the Roxbury International Film Festival, and the National Association of Television Arts and Sciences, the Denver Jazz on Film Festival Series,
and the International Documentary Association. Folks, I am literally just scratching the surface of Calvin's professional credits and have not even mentioned the extensive work he's done and been doing as a longtime director of the city of Cambridge's municipal television station. Please allow me to introduce to some and reacquaint with others one of the most talented and accomplished brothers I know,
Calvin Lindsey Jr. He hands me the mic a lot. He's had me over at Cambridge doing a bunch of different stuff for him over the years. And he's taught me a lot about the business of television production. So when Patrick Gordon first came over to help us do
Fresh Fridays and now my man Kevin Harrington, I didn't seem quite as ignorant as I might have otherwise Because I had really been schooled quite well by Calvin So as this is my custom in hosting these evenings I'd like to share just a bit, a little bit of verse to help shape the evening.
know by now that I believe that poetry should be, above all things, accessible and inclusive. Sometimes, like the times that we're in right now, it also has to have a little bit of bite to it. But I'm not going to bite anybody tonight. This piece is about family, it's about culture, and you may have heard it before, but I think it's appropriate for the evening. It's called Neighborhood.
Neighborhood is a place where mothers buy extra food for kids that aren't even their own, on the premise that they will eventually show up at the door hungry. Neighborhood is grandmas and grandpas that raise their children's children long after they've raised their own, lovingly, carefully, happily, long after they've raised their own.
Neighborhood is a portable date where that nice Spanish man always gave you 10 cents worth of penny candy when all you ever had was a nickel. Neighborhood is a homeowner that doesn't look down his nose at the
Neighborhood knows everybody's name, but isn't collecting big data on anyone. Keeps tabs on strangers, but doesn't discriminate or judge folk by color or caste or custom. Neighborhood keeps pies and cookies ready to welcome newcomers, and always has something to invite you to, and always has something good to eat when you get there. Neighborhood loves all of its children, watches out for all the babies,
disciplines fairly, drops dimes carefully, and gaps up consistently, marches for justice dutifully. Neighborhood cares for its sick with homemade chicken soup, ginger tea, flowers, cards, and pastoral visits. Never lets you feel lonely, never leaves you alone. Neighborhood laments the loss of its kings and queens reverently, even while it celebrates their lives jubilantly and recollects their ways permanently.
Neighborhood has well-worn welcome mats, four-way stop signs, and a community gathering place as the hub of the wheel, nicknames like the Port, the Coast, and the Ville. Neighborhood says yes more than it says no, chooses love over hate, never cries when it could laugh, and never laughs when it should cry. Neighborhood understands the importance of respect, covers everyone with an umbrella, shovels snow for its elders,
pronounces your name right, and picks up the poop left by its dog, small, medium, and large. And no matter where you go, neighborhood is always the place you call home. Let's get to it. So, Cal,
Give us, to start this conversation, three indelible memories you have of life growing up in West Medford. First, thank you. Hello, everybody. This is, like your poem said, it's home. So certainly one of the big memories is this room, this building, because I grew up here. We all grew up here, running around here.
See, first thing is, I stayed behind the camera. This is like the hardest thing in life for me to do. You sit up here with them, I'm like, oh. So bear with me. I'm sorry, see, I even lost my breath. Oh, good. Three indelible memories. It's the neighborhood. I mean, the center, the neighborhood, the folks, right? And we grew up here. Like, your poem was perfect, right? Like, you grew up here.
We knew that we could go in everywhere. Everybody had, everyone had love for us. They had food for us. They had, you know, a squinting eye for us. They had, like, whatever was required, like, this neighborhood and these folks had it and gave it all the time. And the third, I mean,
You know, I think the third thing I think I go back to are the people. Like, I learned, especially like now when I look back, right? There were business owners here. There were, I mean, there was so much culture and so much entertainment, right? Like, I can, I remember, you know, just as I look out, I can remember as a little kid going down the street, going into the basement,
I can remember being in the driveway and looking up and seeing him sit in the windowsill playing the sax, something like that. I was thinking, I'm remembering today, the jazz instrumentalist, Jack Dyer, and I can remember taking guitar lessons from him. And these were, I was a little kid, right?
their time, their attention, just so freely. Absolutely. Wow, yeah. Those are wonderful, wonderful insights. So, you know, because we toiled in these streets together for many, many years. How significant was basketball
You know, I can kind of, even though when I tell the story now, it's like, the older I get, the faster I was. But, you know, ball, that's all we did. We played ball all the time down here. And, you know, and one of the things, as I'm thinking about it, one of the things that really,
And so, you know, it was interesting, not just, not just in, you know,
I don't know who he was. You know, this man danced on Soul Train, right? So being embraced by you, by the older cats in the neighborhood was important. And then we also had, I won't call names for this one, but there were a number of guys in the neighborhood who were
don't do none of this. We don't want to see you over here every year. You go down to basketball court, that's where you belong. So there were a number of guys who protected us from our suffering. And that's just, that's home, that's neighborhood. We both lost our dads. Yours more recently than mine.
What do you miss about having a real and present father in your life? The talks, the time and the talks, especially as he got older, especially as I got older. And it's interesting, I miss fathers. It irritates me, but I also laugh
And one of my, one of my.
And what they were going to do, they were going to buy the building, and they were going to give the community center, they were going to take the first floor of that whole building, and give the community center a 99-year lease for $1. And I can remember those conversations, and I said, jokingly,
And I'm like, where, like, as I got older, like, where did these dudes, because these were all working, these were working men, right? And I'm like, where did they get an idea about a 99-year lease? And, you know, and one of the things that I remember was they were adamant about putting their money behind this project.
It didn't happen for any number of reasons, which is a conversation for another time. But the fact that as a child, I saw, that's the kind of stuff that I saw. These guys, these men saw a need. Oh, I'm sorry, we talked about the first floor.
I can remember hearing one of their conversations when they were like, let's be clear. If we don't do this, the chances are we won't be able to pay to get in what is our neighborhood. So learning those kinds of lessons took me to go back to your question. So to talk with my father, to hear different stories,
Yeah, it's really very similar. I had the luxury, you know, I view it as a luxury now. I didn't view it as a luxury then. I viewed it as drudgery. The words sounded like, but they're really different. Of going with my father for a lot of the jobs that he was doing in West Bedford and beyond. I mean, there was a time when there were virtually no
houses that you could go into in West Memphis that didn't have a Bonnie Potter ceiling. And a lot of people view that as a real badge of honor, because his ceiling game was top flight. So I want to talk to you a little bit, if I can, about Say Brother, more recently known as Basic Black, and how did that work?
and I remember the very first conversation that I had with Barbara, the very first day that I went in, she said to me, she said, listen, she said, I will open up my head and give you every piece of information that I have. She said, every, she said, I'm going to teach you everything that I know, everything that you need to know. She said, the only thing that I've
that experience, that series, I mean, shaped my entire trajectory, right? There were tons of, you know, just the things that we were involved in, right? I remember the, just some of the big ones, the Charles Stewart murder. And I remember the next morning, at that time, our correspondent, a lot of folks will remember him, Ravel died.
That's right. And probably 90% of the footage that's in that documentary is out of flash. Wow. So we were out there all the time.
the news department, and as the, you know, that morning everybody was like gathering for the verdict, and like you, without, no one did, I mean no one said anything, but like you looked up and
The verdict was read. You heard a collective groan. You heard a collective yeah. And what was so interesting, like the conversations that that sparked, right? Because there was real, there was just real anger and misunderstanding as to, because what was interesting, I can remember, I'm like, listen, we don't care nothing about her.
he didn't do it or that's, it had nothing to do with that at all. But the, you know, it was such an important time because of the conversations. It started to really, you know, pull back some band-aids. We had, we started having some real, some real substantive conversations. And especially, you know, for us like in the,
For those who don't know, in a news space, there's actually somebody who's deciding what is news. They're making a decision to send their news crew to this place and not to that place. And again, I don't want to take up a lot of your time on this,
and there's shootings and there's murders and there's this and there's that. Well, naturally, you're like, that's a bad place, I gotta stay away from that. And when you get to the understanding that somebody is making that decision to make a narrative about this place. So there was just so many lessons. And then I think the big one that I really, I think is important is that we were taught to
unapologetically put it out there. This wasn't at St. Robert's, this was at another, when I was doing the film, the national film on the devil's music. And the executive producer, I remember we were having a conversation with the executive producer, and I wanted to bring, I wanted,
read the phone book today, I love you, right? But I'm like, there have to be other voices that are involved, right? And so, again, that Safe Brother Foundation to learn how to advocate for us. That's right. All right. Fantastic. Fantastic. So quick story.
Calvin is like the single most instrumental brother in my marrying Teresa, my wife. And, you know, trying to do this quickly is he said he was going to do, was doing a program on Phil Hamilton and his group. He had a group called Full Circle at the time. And, you know,
when they would do, you know, these live studio music things, they would bring in a live audience to, you know, sit and enjoy the program. So, you know, he told me about it and said, oh, T, you need to come to this, so and so and so. So I said, man, I'm there. I was working at Leachman at the time in the AV department selling, you know, high-end video stuff.
So I was going into work every day suited and booted, cleaning the Board of Health. I'm just saying. So time for the program comes, and I made my way down to the studio. And Sissy greeted me at the door. And she's looking at me, and I'm looking at her. But we didn't know each other, hadn't met each other.
But Calvin, you know, the wheels are turning in his mind. So after the show, and a couple things happened during the show to kind of get us a little bit together, but after the show, he's talking to both of us and he says, oh, and by the way, she went to Fisk University too. And it was like,
You know, light went off in my head and over the next few weeks, you know, we're getting together and talking and, you know, one thing led to another and we ended up getting married and we'll be married 38 years from now.
on campus at the same time. I graduated the year that she came in as a freshman, and I think I went back for homecoming that year, and she was on campus as a freshman, but I had a girlfriend already that I was going to visit, so there was no half there. But sure enough, you know, I owe Calvin and St. Brother for that opportunity, and I don't know that I'd ever get a chance to repay him back all of what I owe him, right?
or to beat him up for some of the aggravation that I get. Because marriage is hard work. I'm trying to say. Everybody in here who has been there or who is in the institution right now knows that it's not always a bed of roses. OK, good. Really good. So Calvin, I want to ask you about the last project that you
did together, which is, and you'll explain it better than I will, the program about Vidal Igoe. Okay. So interestingly enough, this was, this project, so doing a project on Vidal Igoe, it kind of came up that I was actually co-producing that piece. And so,
and I fire in and save others.
more than us in, was the piece that she brought to me. I knew a little bit, I knew a little bit about it. I was really kind of fascinated with, does everyone know what a good lie was? And so I was really kind of fascinated with, just with everything about it. You know, now, we're in a society, and
And what was interesting, as we started doing some of the early research we found out that
remove the pigment from the stick. For instance, obviously the most famous one, Michael Jackson. Michael Jackson had a lot. So all of the, you know, when folks were, you know, coming in and all that, he really had an end. It's interesting, oftentimes it starts on your hand. So the thinking is that's where the, when you started wearing that single glove, that was to hide the pigment.
like all of this kind of suffering in silence, right? And when we did the research, you know, from every kind of time in mankind, every religion, like when you're reading the Bible and you're talking about the leper colonies, in many of those cases, they're talking about little angel colonies. That's what they would call the lepers. They would, you know, kind of make people, put people on little things all by themselves and this and that.
of women from around the country who all had different stages of Vallejo. And so we decided to tell their story. And also, on a parallel track, we were connected with the medical team that's actually working
who came up with this breakthrough. So now they have a reliable treatment that will re-pigment the skin. So you see a lot of times they have like a molding treatment that a lot of the commercials don't want to do.
And, you know, it was just, it was really, it was especially kind of turning into like what we, what we think of as, you know, just from the TV side, the film side, it was kind of a Valentine's.
And you see here, in some of the stories, it was like two in particular. It was one of the women in the film. She never left her house without being fully made up. Like never, right? She said she wouldn't take the trash can to the curb unless she was
when her husband left for work. She's like two seconds after she leaves, maybe five, 10 minutes after she leaves for work. She had her doorbells ringing.
a major car accident, literally at the end of her street. And she could not go for her house.
and they had to, they had to make use of the job. I cut this man out of college, that serious, and she's watching from her window just broken because she just can't go out. She wasn't ready, right? There was another woman who was in the film who, and she had not, when she was young, she was a swimmer. By the time you were doing swimming, she had not,
gone swimming in, I think it was like over 30 years, just because she actually couldn't, she wouldn't go out in a bathing suit. And so she did during, for the film. So just those kinds of things. Impact. Yeah, impact. And doing a lot of those, a lot of those kinds of films is,
really gratifying. We're going to try at some point in time to have a showing of the film here because I haven't seen the whole film, I've seen bits and pieces of it, but I really think that the work that was done and the stories that were told
will really, really open a lot of eyes to the condition. And for those of you that may have never heard the word before, it's basically a genetic condition where there is an unevenness to the pigmentation that manifests itself in splotches and blotches, in discolorations in the skin tone.
some which can be very disconcerting when you first see them. I just want to add one more thing. One of the other pieces, and we really didn't have a chance to get into this too deeply in the film, but one of the other pieces that was really fascinating to me from the cultural space was now you're actually seeing a couple of major corporations
And so one of the things that I was looking at that was really interesting to me was, kind of given this country's history around culture, was what is the attraction here?
So it was like, so trying to kind of look at like where they were going to see it was really important. And then I asked them, sorry, how did you know? Come on, this is good, this is great. Then to find out also that within the community, there's a big,
wrong way. I don't need to be, quote, fixed, right? And that was a really interesting debate, an interesting discussion. And I remember, like, we first, or maybe, I don't know, one of the times that that really kind of got into my attention was years ago when the cochlear implant came out for the ear. And there was a large debate
Well, I don't need fixing that. I'll be fixing new people. There's a lot of... just a lot of... So stay tuned, because like I said, at some point in time, hopefully, you know, relatively soon, we're gonna try and screen that film here.
I mean, I have so much, and I obviously don't have the luxury of time to do it all. So I'm going to do a little bit of a lightning round with you. And so maybe we'll keep the answers a little bit more brief. But I just want you to reflect on a few things. So a quick reflection on Phil Hamilton. That's my man right there. I know.
So, you know, Phil, and we all refer to ourselves, that's my first friend.
And one of the early kind of musical recollections is, so we were down here at Southern Campus Center. Every Friday, right, the bus would come. You get your permission for this. You have your little, you know, $0.50 in your pocket. And, you know, we were going somewhere. And I remember going to, like, Canyon Lake Park or Whalen Park or something, and Phil
I see him now in terms of percussionists and his vocals. I've seen him in nightclub small venues. I've seen him when he was singing with Patton. I've seen him in that major. All of a sudden I see my boy.
All right, so good friend of both of ours, God rest his gentle soul, Aaron McDaniel. Aaron, just what a great guy.
And so he came up here for a visit when he was a little kid. He was five, six years old. We all got to be friends. And some kind of way, it was like, okay, you know what, Aaron's going to go to school up here.
when I went to college. That was going to be one of my, it was going to be the Middlebury experience. But anyways, for those of you who never met or didn't know Aaron McDaniels, he was a good dude, period. But he was also a remarkable photographer.
His photographic work has been on display in museums and he's really traveling throughout places like Santorini, Greece and just really exotic locations and doing amazing, amazing photographic work. So he has that as a legacy and maybe at some point in time we'll figure out a way to get some of his photography here so that folks can see it.
So I'm going to ask you about one more thing. Monument and Houlton Street. Monument and Houlton Street. Yeah. So we have, we just called the whole area of the building. Yeah. We called it our way, you know, Bunk Hill. Bunk Hill. Bunk Hill. Bunk Hill. Bunk Hill boys up there, which we, which is interesting, you know, made for.
But it was, you know, it was nice, of course, you know, Terry, Hamilton, Peter Phyllis,
It's too funny, too funny. The Braxton's had dogs. And they had Butch and they had Jomo. And these were chasing biting dogs. So we were having a good time, but we always had an I.O.
with Joel and Pesky were on the loose, right? Because that was before leash laws. So dogs basically used to run the street. And when I say run the street, I meant they ran the street. And would keep you from going places that you wanted to go sometimes. I think I want to do one more. Uncles in the Ville.
There were so many. There were so many. You know as well, even just driving in here. I'm here all the time. But it's interesting how this is a place, whenever I drive in, just for habit, I rarely go the same place the same way twice. I just wanted to see something different.
like whenever, like when there were so many folks, just had so much influence, right? So many folks that you had to, that were looking out for you, even when you didn't know they were looking out for us. And, you know, to be, for me, I say constant, constant, right? It's like everybody was here, it's just, you know,
when I'm coming in to go, is again, driving, driving, different way all the time. And I know I'm going to see somebody. And whether, you know, sometimes, you know, I have occasions to stop and talk, sometimes just drive by, but everybody I see, I'm like, oh, there's a connection, there's a story, you know what I'm saying, right? And what happens, like,
It's neighborhoods. Again, I said it before, I'll say it again, we're really, really only scratching the surface of where a conversation like this could go because one, we've known each other since we were both
just little sprites, but two, we've gone through some things together. We've actually had some challenging times, never with our friendship, never with our relationship, but just in terms of family history and family dynamics. We've both gone through some things, so we have a lot in common, and the reason why I wanted to have this conversation
Calvin, maybe more than anyone else that I know, it's because there's always been a remarkable measure of respect between the two of us. We may have had a disagreement, I don't really recall one, but throughout our friendship
respect has never been breached. There's never been a point in time where I felt like, or, you know, or discern that he felt that way about me. So aside from his accomplishment, and again, you know,
really, there's so much more that you don't know about him and that he probably would feel some kind of way about me, you know, trying to talk about all of it. But I just want you to know that this is one of the
the best examples of what can be produced by a community when it looks out for its own. I don't want to put anybody off or anything like that, but the truth of the matter is none of us, I never get to a place where I become
the poet laureate of the city without the folks that looked out for me as I was coming up. And he never gets to be, you know, the former executive producer of St. Bravo or the current director of Municipal Cable at the City of Cambridge without the folks that looked out for him. So in presenting this conversation this evening, I just, you know, hope that
may take a little bit of a measure of pride about who it produced. And credit, yeah. And credit, yeah. All the credit y'all wanna take, you know. It's credit, right? And if you take too much, my mother will probably whisper it in your ear, or your dad will whisper it in your ear. Listen, you didn't do all that. You did some of it, we did most of it, all right? So Calvin, thank you so much. Amen.
Thank you for your broad perspective and great insight to the cultural community and great method. It's always important work that you've been engaged in as you continue to make films and give voice to the voiceless. We'll be watching, we'll definitely be watching to our audience, both here and elsewhere.
discussion and thanks for coming along with us as we continue to refresh for greater flexibility and bring the best stories and entertainment possible. As I always like to say, get ready for something very special on the musical side of the coin right after we take a break to reset our stage and share some WMCC announcements.
All right. Yeah, she's right next to me. Oh, she's a sweetheart.
Okay, so that we can kind of stay on schedule and give our musical guests a full opportunity to display their wares. We feature another performer this evening that has gained a dedicated local following and has made great friends as a singer and a stage performer. Ladies and gentlemen, may I present Anita Wood.
also known as AJ. For like 24 years a Medford native? Okay, 24 years a West Medford native. Okay, press card, okay. She is a versatile vocalist with roots in musical theater and acapella singing. She studied under Laura Serafino for 10 plus years and has more recently dove headfirst into the jazz scene.
She has had the pleasure of being the lead vocalist of the Chelmsford Jazz Ensemble since the summer of 2022, where she rediscovered her love for the American songbook, where singers like Sarah Vaughan and Elephant Gerald and
all got a lot of their most wonderful music from. Since the fall of 2023, she's become active in the local jazz jam circuit. And as the months passed, musical connections were made with talented local players, which led to friendships and the formation of AJ and the Groove. She is thrilled to be part of West Medford's Fresh Friday. She said that, not me. And to share with you her love of jazz,
Welcome back to West Medford, AJ and the Groove featuring Steve Linscott on alto saxophone. And Carolyn Sue Howard, Jessu, Jessu Howard on piano, okay? Alright, alright, alright. And you know, for those of you wonderful seniors out there who come and support us
that we do is a wonderful, amazing member of your own community, that dear of the senior community, on the keys, I think. I think you're going to enjoy her. I had an opportunity to listen to her come in on the door, and she is a wonderful player. So without further ado, AJ and the group.
I want to thank Terry for having me back. I met Terry about a year and a half ago. I came here for a jazz jam. And I had the pleasure of meeting Terry. And he's like, oh, we should connect. And so we finally got this to happen. But Terry, your presentation was wonderful. And you did so many words. So let's start with a little music. So we're going to start with a little instrumental.
do do
♪
do
♪ ♪
do do
do
East of the sun and west of the moon We'll build a dream house of love dear Close to the sun and day
Near to the moon at night We'll live in a lovely way, dear Living on love and a pale night Just you and I Forever and a day Love will not die We'll keep it that way
among the stars we'll find a harmony of life to a lovely tune east of the sun west of the moon dear east of the sun and west of the moon
do do
do do do
East of the sun and west of the moon We'll build a dream house of love dear
Close to the sun of the day Near to the moon at night Livin' in a lovely way, dear Livin' on an island in a pale moonlight Just you and I, forever and a day
Love will not die, we'll be there for thee Among the stars we'll find a harmony in life, too, and a love, too East to the sun, west to the moon, dear East to the sun and west of the moon
East of the sun and west of the moon East of the sun and west of the moon
Next up, we're going to switch it up a little bit with a Latin tune called Fascinating Rochelle.
Besame, besame mucho Como si fuera esta noche la ultima vez Besame, besame mucho
Tengo miedo a perderte y perderte después. Quiero tenerte muy cerca, mirarme en tus ojos, verte junto a mí. Piensa que tal vez mañana yo ya estaré lejos, mil lejos de ti. Bésame.
Besame mucho Como si fuera esta noche la ultima vez Besame Besame mucho Que tengo miedo a perderte, perderte despues
do do
do
♪
Thank you.
do do
Besame, besame mucho
Each time I cling to your kiss, I hear music divine. Besame, besame mucho. Hold me, my darling, and say that you'll always be mine.
This joy is something new, my arms enfolded, you never knew this thrill before. Whoever thought I'd be holding you close to me, it was with you I opened the door. Dearest one, if you should leave,
Mesame, mesame mucho Love me forever and may all my dreams come true Love me forever and may all my dreams come true
come true.
Not the pale moon that sets me, that thrills and delights me alone. It's just the nearness of you. It isn't your swing.
Oh no, it's just a near-death experience.
When you're in my arms And I feel you so close to me All my wildest dreams
I need no soft light to enchant me If you only grant me the right to hold you ever so
And to feel in the night The nearness of you.
♪
I'm going to play it.
so so
It's not the pale moon that sets me That thrills and delights me Oh no It's just the nearness of you
It isn't your sweet conversation that brings this sensation Oh no, it's just the nearness of you
And I feel you so close to me. All my wildest dreams come true. I need no sunlight.
to enchant me if you only grant me the right to hold you ever so tight
the nearness of you. We're going to move on to a couple of instruments.
do do
do
Thank you very much.
♪ ♪
do do
♪
♪ ♪
Ž Ž Ž
do do
you
♪
do do
do
Ž Ž Ž
so so
Next time, we're about a week away from the title of this song.
Summertime and the livin' is easy Fish are jumpin' and the cotton is high One of these mornings you're gonna rise up singin' So hush little baby, don't you cry
One of these mornings, you're gonna rise up singing. Then you spread your wings and you change the sky. But till that morning, there's nothing can harm you. So hush, little baby, don't
to cry.
♪
Music Music Music Music Music Music Music Music Music Music Music
Summertime, and living is easy. Fish are jumping, and the cotton is high. One of these mornings, I'm singing.
So hush, little baby, don't you cry One of these mornings, you're gonna rise up singing And spread your wings and take to the sky
If nothing can harm you So hush, little baby, don't you cry So hush, little baby, don't you cry So hush, little baby, don't you cry
Quiet nights of quiet stars Quiet chords from my guitar Floating on the silence that surrounds us Quiet thoughts and quiet dreams Quiet walks by, quiet screams
And the window looking on the mountains and sea How lovely, this is where I want to be Here with you, so close to me until the final flicker
of my icebergs. I was lost and lonely. Believing life was only a bitter tragic joke to find with you.
Oh my love.
Ž Ž Ž
do do
do
So,
Quiet nights of quiet stars, quiet chords to my guitar. Floating on the silence that surrounds me.
And quiet dreams, quiet walks, quiet streets And the window looking on at the mountains and the sea How lovely, this is where I want to be Here with you, so close to me Until the final flicker
of life's ever burning. I was lost and lonely, believing life was only a bitter, tragic joke. Had fun with you, the meaning of existence, oh my love.
Oh my love Oh my love My love Terry's given me one more song.
It requires a little audience participation. That one was quite a bit by Pia Starr's Corcovado. But this one, you definitely know, and you're required to participate. If you plan to go to West,
Travel my way to take the highway that's the best Get your kicks on Route 66 It winds from Chicago to L.A. More than 2,000 miles all the way
get your kicks on Route 66. Now you've come through St. Louis, Joplin, Missouri, Oklahoma City, look so high up in the sea, Amarillo.
Gallup, New Mexico, Flagstaff, Arizona, Don't forget Winona, Kingman, Moscow, San Bernardino, Won't you get after this time they tear? When you take that California trip, Get your kicks on Route 66,
do
so
If you ever plan to motor west, follow my way, take the highway that's to the west. Get your kicks.
On Route 66 It winds from Chicago to L.A. More than 2,000 miles all the way
Get your kicks on Route 66. Now you call the girls, say Louie, Joplin, Missouri, Oklahoma City look so mighty pretty, you'll see an umbrella.
Get up New Mexico, Paso Verde, Arizona Don't forget Winona, Kingman, Bustel, San Bernardino Won't you get here to this timely tip?
When you take that California trip, get your kicks on Route 66. Get your kicks on Route 66. Get your kicks on Route 66.
Oh, wow. Okay, so A.J. and the group, and Ethan Wood. Stu Howard. Stephen and Scott. All right, all right, thank you so much. You were inspired, so wonderful. That's a wrap. Oops, whoops.
I don't even know if I'm making a difference at this point. But anyways, so this is a wrap for this live edition of WMCC's Words in Music program. Again, we're so happy to have you back at the center.
to be visiting with you in your living rooms and other household places. I want to thank all of our guests for allowing us to invade their spaces, showing their faces, and sharing their graces. Special thanks to West Medford's own Calvin Lindsey, Jr. on the Word side. And once again to AJ and Sue
Air high five to Kevin Harrington and Mark Davidson. Thank you all for spending another evening with us and enjoying what the WMCC has to offer. We'll be back in the fall. We're taking July and August off.
But we'll have a new edition for you of Fresh Friday's Words and Music as we prepare for that familiar chill in the air and begin to loosen our grip on the summer sun. So I just have a few announcements before we end.
The evening, elders join us each week, Tuesday through Thursday for a nutritious lunch and vibrant fellowship. Lunch is served at 12 o'clock or whenever you get there, apparently. Call 781-483-3042 to make a reservation. Juneteenth, flag raising and celebration at City Hall on June 18th.
It's going to be a good affair, don't miss it. And then we'll be back here at the community center on the 19th to celebrate Juneteenth in West Medford where we first got started with the holiday observance. The West Medford Men's Club is having their first annual barbecue on June 21st, Saturday, June 21st.
And Circle in the Square, who's brought to you by Caché, the arts group in Medford, is having their big summer celebration on Riverside Avenue later on that same afternoon, June 21st, featuring artists, vendors, play activities, and more. I'll be down there repping for WMCC and probably sharing some poetry. If you want to know how you can help us, your tax-deductible donations help support the mission
in carrying this mission forward, please consider making a tax-deductible donation to this vital community organization. You can make your donation by phone, online, or by check. Please contact Lisa Crossman at 781-483-3042 for more information or to become a member. We value membership highly.
Thanks, as always, to the great sponsors of WMCC First Fridays, the Medford Arts Council, a member of the Massachusetts Cultural Council, and Medford Community Media. Make sure we have your email address if you want to be included in our regular constant contact connection. You can also, once again, call us at 781-483-3042. That's all I got.
Hope you've had a wonderful evening, and we hope to see you again soon. So we're just going to take a little picture, you know, for the opportunity. So if anybody else wants to take a picture of us, now's the time to get up here and take it.
Thank you.