This isn't a dumpsy thing. This is just bread. It's not a dumpsy, it's a dumpsy thing. It's a recycling bin, not a trash barrel. I have a little bit, yeah. Well that's good, you can make sure you recycle. Yes. Oh Jesus Christ! The latest Mustang report. Oh my goodness. You should probably check it out in case you haven't seen it. Well if you haven't seen it, you should probably check it out. What do you think we're doing right now?
Oh my god, I wish I could have it. How you doing? I'm Anthony. This is... Oh, Jesus. She thinks they might be important? Yes. They don't have gloves on. No. Welcome to the Mustang Report. What's that? Um, you ran out for coffee, watched the gold, peed back in two shakes of Olanto, kept...
Where's the gold? I don't know. I don't see it. Does anyone see the pot? No. Where could it be? There's no gold in this pot. What? Hayley! Alright guys, we all have to run out and go find the gold as quick as we can, okay? Where's the gold?
Has anyone seen the gold? Where's the gold? Has anybody seen the pot of gold?
Has anyone seen the gold? No! Wait, where's Dempsey? Not sure. I haven't seen him today. Wait, guys, what's this? Finish the mission, find the gold. Well, I guess we have to go find the gold. Let's go. Wait, you're going to need this. Thanks, Nick.
Have you guys seen the gold? No. It's locked. Why is it locked? How are we going to get in? Wait, I know the code. We have to say lucky leprechaun three times. Ready? One, two, three. Lucky leprechaun, lucky leprechaun, lucky leprechaun. Oh, there we go.
Mustang? Please, softball. Well, let's go join. Mustang? Do you know where our gold is? Yeah, right here. This is your prize for today. But you can get the real pot of gold on Sunday, March 12th at the American Legion at 10.30 in the morning. See you there.
Let's say you guys are really, you're really short on time because it's getting cold. By the time you guys are done, you're going to be, you're going to be cold. Don't waste your time cutting. Use what is around you that you can get something up quickly because you're going to spend so much energy on something and you don't know what's going to be really useful.
Matt, how are we doing over here? So good. So good. Is there shelter this far? Oh my god. It's made of wood mostly. Paradise. Or just a moss. Yep. Paradise. It's getting there. I don't know about paradise, but. It's close. We're getting there. Oh yeah, the saw's right over there.
All right, so guys let's
Unfortunately, our next inductee, Arantia King, Medford High School, 2007, is also unable to be with us today, but her mother, Brelyn, is here. Arantia is in London right now, and she's finishing up her degree at Georgetown University for going as an attorney. But in high school, she was the New England Gatorade Athlete of the Year three years in a row, 05, 06, 07.
She was the world youth long jump champion. She was a four-time Massachusetts long jump champion, a two-time national long jump champion, and a one-time triple jump champion. At Stanford, her highlights and PRs are 12 100 meters, 24.7 in the 200 meters, 21.6 in three quarters,
in the long jump in a 42-foot, 5.25-inch triple jumper. Her professional highlights include two appearances at the two Olympic Games in 08 and 12, competing for Bermuda. She holds the Bermuda National Indoor and Outdoor long jump records, and her PRs are 11.88, 21.8, 44.6. So let's please welcome Aracha King, represented by her mother, into the athletes hall of fame.
Let's go, Maya! Nice job! Keep it up! Come on, Maya! Let's go, Amber! Come on, Ruben! Come on, Amber! Just an award-winning champion this time.
Do one of those
All I do is win, win, win, no matter what. Got money on my mind, I can never get enough. And every time I step up in the building, everybody's hands go up. And they stay there. And they say yeah.
Deal.
All I do is win, win, win, no matter what Got money on my mind, I can never get enough And every time I step up in the building, everybody's hands go up And they stay there, and they stay there, and they stay there
This is Nick Kenniston with the Mustang Report and I'm here with Haley DiPietro Antonio. And since we couldn't make the Patriots Parade today, we're here to talk a little bit about the Patriots game. Haley, what was your favorite moment from the game?
my favorite moment of the game definitely it was a little bit made that insane catch i think that was a great moment because the pages fans specifically have known uh... to experience i kind of catch before specifically david tyree ins in the super bowl in two thousand four and i'm going to have a super bowl in two thousand seven both against the giants the patriots have been the victim of that sort of thing so many times so it was great for the pages actually be on the other end uh... on the victorious and of of that
Would you want to be at the parade today, even though it's kind of blizzard-like conditions out here? I think it would be cool to be down there, definitely supporting my team and my city, but it's also my duty to be here at school. And we're also here to talk a little bit about the upcoming leprechaun race, which is why we're wearing these two pretty funky hats. Are you planning to be running at all?
I'd like to run it. It seems like a really cool event to be a part of and yeah, so come on down to it at the American Legion on March 12th and show your leprechaun spirit. And lastly, what is your favorite thing to do when it's snowing outside? Do snow angels. How do you feel about the new Mustang jerseys, Haley?
I think they're really cool. I really like them a lot. Would you prefer New Balance or would you prefer another brand like Nike or Adidas? I really like the New Balance ones. I think they're really fitting for us. Watch your step. Did you see Destiny Fitzgerald's game the other night? Yeah, I did see that. She ended up with 41 points and a ridiculous 22 rebounds. That's crazy. Did you happen to attend the boys' senior night? Yeah, I did. It was really emotional.
The boys had their senior night on Sunday, and it was kind of sad to see them play for the last time, because a lot of them are seniors. They have five seniors. Yeah, it's hard to think that the winter sports season is almost over. That means spring sports now. And what spring sport are you most excited for? Definitely softball, by far. Do you think the softball team will be very different from last year, knowing that you've lost a lot of seniors?
Yeah, I think they're still going to be really good though and really pull through.