Good evening, everyone.
My name is Andre LaRue.
I'm the chairperson of the Medford Community Development Board.
Welcome to the board's December 20, 2021 meeting, where we will conduct a meeting via Zoom remote video conferencing.
20.20.2021.
Medford Community Development Board hearing will be conducted via remote means.
Members of the public who wish to access the meeting may do so by accessing the meeting link contained herein.
No in-person attendance of members of the public will be permitted, and public participation in any public hearing during this meeting shall be by remote means only.
They are pretty lengthy and I'm gonna say that I would like to dig into them a little bit more, so I'd like to postpone consideration of these minutes until our next zoning meeting on January 5th, if that's all right.
Yes, David?
Would you entertain a motion along those lines?
Yes, very much.
Okay, I'd like to make a motion to
Oxford Properties Group applied for a special permit for site plan review for a project at this address in July of this year, if you all recall.
When we conducted our site plan review and our conditions of approval, one of the conditions stated that, number five, prior to the issuance of a building permit for its tenant fit-out work, the applicant shall present further design details of the southwest corner facade of the building
We are a global investor.
We are heavily focused on life science in the U.S., as well as in some nascent markets like London and all throughout Canada.
We are approximately $80 billion of assets globally, and we are a wholly owned subsidiary of OMERS, which is the Ontario Municipal Employee Retirement System.
life science market, and we also believe very strongly in the CGMP facilities and manufacturing side, which has become a growing sector in that market.
So this just gives you a quick overview of kind of how we got started through, you know, the biomed portfolio where we were on the debt side, 125 Lincoln and 645 Summer.
645 Summer is part of a 42 acre site we're developing into life science.
The tenant and the client market from really inception all the way through global recognition and manufacturing where it's right at your bedside.
So anyways, it's an exciting sector for us and we believe strongly in Medford and we're very excited to move this forward.
I'll turn it over to Will and John to kind of give updates as to where we are on this project in particular.
Thanks, Matt.
Will Nichols, Oxford Properties.
As Matt said, we're excited to be here.
We're excited to report that we've made a ton of progress since we were last in front of you in August.
Since then, we've buttoned up our design.
We've gotten approval for demo activities to proceed.
We actually just got our building permit approval last week, which is, like I said, really exciting for us.
But yeah, looking at this aerial photograph, I don't know if everyone's familiar with the site, but essentially,
Thanks Will.
John Sullivan with SGA.
We are the architects for the project, also very excited to be here to present before the board.
Will just gave a great update of all of the work that's happening on site, and we figured it would be good to share this image to show the building and describe, kind of remind everyone what is remaining and what is coming down.
Especially when it comes to the site's history, but also very much a progressive statement.
Especially when you look at it from a distance, you can see that there is a lot of space in front of the building.
On this right-hand part of the façade that we focused on, the reason we did that was again because of the relationship between the façade itself and the street.
The loading area again is just kind of tucked back and our goal there was to just kind of calm it down and clean it up.
But on the façade that pulls closer to the street, you can see that there's some signage elements on the top corners.
We think that this will be detailed in a very clean way, be very organized, will have some of that industrial nature and also kind of has a little bit of that techie feel.
So the thought with the screen wall itself was to tie it into the architecture of the building, let it recede behind the planting, and let it visually mitigate some of the tanks that sit behind it.
Thank you, John and the rest of your team.
Let me open it up for comments and questions by members of the board.
Maybe, John, you could stop sharing right now, and if we have to pull something up, we should put that back.
Great, thank you.
Thank you.
Reactions from board members.
Especially the type of asset that it is.
I think it's a nice gesture to try to bring some creativity to that building.
I don't know if it's more than it deserves in this corridor, but I would hope that maybe this sets a little bit of a precedence for an interesting design for any future development that could happen here as well.
Nice job.
This corrugated metal, which is partially perforated, will sit there and the same corrugation is tied into the darker gray material.
There's kind of corrugation throughout in this facade, so that's an extension of that language.
Okay, thank you very much.
I appreciate that.
John, if we could go back to the southwest façade.
Could you show the corner actually?
The southwest corner, yeah.
So just I guess a question.
I don't recall exactly back from July, but I seem to remember that there were along that
Sikkimore Ave, Sikkimore Ave, Sikkimore Ave, Sikkimore Ave, Sikkimore Ave,
Thank you.
Other comments and questions from board members?
No, I see in here none, so I would be open to entertaining a motion from the board to
Thank you so much, everyone.
We hope you have a happy holiday season.
Same to you.
See you in 2022.
All right, take care.
Thank you.
Thank you, bye-bye.
All right, so we have just next on our agenda only some miscellaneous updates.
That being said, we should plan to schedule another meeting.
And Amanda, were you going to get to that part?
Yes, and I don't know if it makes sense to do this offline.
But so, OK, two things.
We have this meeting on the 5th.
There is an anticipated application for site plan review for early December, which
Thanks everybody for doing this.
I think, yeah, shorter meetings, even if they're more frequent are better, so we're trying.
I can definitely get behind this.
Yeah, before 7, talk about a record breaker.
So thanks everybody.
This is our New Year's gift to all of you.
I got to tell you guys the best story about this.
Somebody just offered me Celtics tickets, so I'm going to the Celtics game.
I had said no.
That's pretty awesome.
I was like, no, I'm not going to be able to make it.
All right, so we can put that in our list of outcomes.
Happy New Year.
Motion it in so that Klaes can get to his game.
Is there a sec, guys?