Can you find the giant logs we got from the trees? Are they over there? No! Are they up there? No!
Where are they? Right behind you! There they are! Vamanos! Can you find the Spanish teacher? Is she over there? Or is she over there? Or where did she go?
Here I am! Cha cha cha! Do you find the cafeteria? Is it over there? Is it over there? I need my map! I'm the map! I'm the map! I'm the map! It's over there! Hola! Swiper! Swiper? Where? He's over there! Over there? No, behind you! Swiper, no swiping! Aw man!
We came to the end of our journey, and we found the last Muslim report.
The answer to last week's Mustang report question of the week is 8. Hey, so the last question of the week for the 2015-2016 school year is how many students are graduating in the class of 2016? Tune in next year to find out.
Hi, I'm Lydia Ryan and I'm here with Mr. Skorka and he's here today to explain what's going on at the MHS library today.
Lydia, hi. So this is wonderful. This is called the Bloomberg Fair. All of the groups that are here are somehow connected with Bloomberg or the Bloomberg funds that were given to either run different programs and clubs or activities, or just sponsored by the Bloomberg Center. Hi, I'm Lydia Ryan, and I'm here with Ramon, a senior here at Medford High School. And he's here to tell us today about what he's doing for CCSR.
So my project was about financial literacy and how we can implement that into the high school curriculum. So basically I came up with a bunch of resources that teachers can use. It goes through how they can implement financial literacy in their math classes and their history classes, and it goes from high school to middle school. Basically this docent program, we'd go to the Museum of Fine Arts and students would pick pieces that they do.
and they presented to students that went on this field trip and basically that's it. Hi, I'm Lydia Ryan and I'm here with Katie Russo, Alana Landano, and Jazlyn Merida and they're here to talk to us about what they're going to be doing today.
We started off with the buddy benches, me and Alana here. And they're basically like a way to find a friend outside at the playground or something. Just if you want to sit down, hang out with someone, maybe find some new friends if you really want to. So I just want to say a quick thank you to the media department and to Medford High School for giving me an amazing four years here, for teaching me so much.
and for just giving me laughs and a bunch of joy every single day coming in here. Next year, I will be pursuing my studies at UMass Boston. I'll be studying exercise science and kinesiology. And I'll be playing soccer and softball there. So good luck to everyone else in the class of 2016. I just want to say thank you to the media tech department. I'm going to Rhode Island College for a bio on the pre-med track. And congrats and good luck to the class of 2016. Thank you to Medford Eye and the Mustang Report. Next year, I'll be attending LaSalle College.
pursuing athletic training or exercise arts. I want to thank everyone at Medford High and the media tech department. I'm going to Regis College next year. I'm going to be studying nursing. And I want to wish the class of 2016 good luck in the future. Thank you to MHS and the Mustang report for a great four years. Good luck to the class of 2016. I'll be going to St. Anselm College next year.
I want to thank Medford High School and the Mustang Report for everything that we've been able to accomplish this year, for all the community outreach that we've gotten and all the pretty much like applause and appraisal that we've gotten for the Mustang Report and the popularity that it's gained. Also to thank Mr. Dempsey, Ms. Goldsberry, Mr. Tirada, Mr. Tucci, and Dr. Perlock for making this happen and being great advisors. Next year I'm going to Emerson College to pursue my career in film studies.
which kind of makes sense, but good luck to the class of 2016. I'm Victoria, the editor of the Mustang Report, here with Dr. Pella, the headmaster of the school, to say thank you to the Mustang Report and Medford High for the past year. I thought this past year was phenomenal. It was so exciting to see the Mustang Report on a weekly basis, all the great things going on, and I'd like to let you know I'm very proud of the work you did.
Forever.