Music.
a $31.6 million game. He was coached, came on for the team, coached again and again. That's why I have to make all these great memories. So that being said, I want to say a very, very, very, very, very, very, very, very,
We would like to thank our sponsors for their support and generosity. Today I would like to ask you to please dismiss 5-3. We are going to move on to the next challenge.
Ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen.
Rose.
Can you see by the dawn's early light What so proudly we hailed at the twilight's last gleaming? Whose broad stripes and bright stars
♪ Through the perilous fight ♪ ♪ O'er the ramparts we watched ♪ ♪ Were so gallantly streaming ♪ ♪ And the rockets' red glare ♪ ♪ The bombs bursting in air ♪
Gave proof through the night that our flag was still there. Oh, say does that star-spangled banner yet wave o'er the land of the free
And the home of the brave?
Welcome everybody to Brockton High Basketball. This is Miles Jackson along with my partner Orlando Galveo. And we're here at Brockton High School in Staff Gymnasium playing on Coach Victor Ortiz's court. And Orlando, this is going to be an exciting one. It's going to be an uphill fight for Brockton. They come in here one and four.
Cambridge coming in here, three and one. They've got a seasoned team, Brockton has a young team. What do you expect this evening? Well, like you said, I expect a very challenging game for the Brockton Boxers. But when you talk about Brockton and Cambridge, it's a rival game. And this is Brockton's first home game of the season. So I expect the motivation level to be up and Brockton to be sky high taking the court here tonight. Now, Brockton has a scoring freshman
Phenomenon out here who's starting for this bodge team? Who's that? Yeah, you talk about Clairverne's Patras very good player only a freshman and Sky's the limit for him. All right, we're getting ready to have the tip-off rocking in white Cambridge Ridge Falcons are in black and we're just about ready to start this game Cambridge you got to watch out number 44 for them Paris Moses very good player
We got just about a packed house here at Staff Gymnasium, so a lot of electricity going through this gym this evening. And Brockton wins the tip-off. Three-point shot is no good. Rebound no good by Brockton.
Yeah, nice offensive rebound by the freshman we just talked about. Unable to get the put back, but Brockton retains possession. Yep, that'll be Fonts taking the ball out. Drive to the basket, in the corner. And he's gonna drive to the basket. Out top, in the paint shot is no good, but he's fouled.
That was number one, Christopher Africo. Nice left handed player for Brockton, only a sophomore going to the hoop and able to draw the foul to the line for two. First free throw is missed, Africo a sophomore.
I was talking to you miles before the game, this is one of Brockton's youngest team I've seen in years. Yes, indeed. Second free throw attempt is good. We get our first point on the board. That's Moses with the ball. Drives right to the basket, uncontested, misses the shot, but an offensive rebound, no good by Correa.
Yeah, nice clean up that time by Correa, unable to get the hoop, and he will go to the line for two shots. But you see the explosiveness of Moses going to the hoop that time. Yeah, I think he caught Brockton's defense off guard. Went straight to the hoop, just about uncontested.
And he makes the second free throw attempt, so we got a tie game. That's Lambert with the ball, in the corner. Yeah, right now our Cambridge Band of Men defense are two threes giving Broxson some issues here. Not much room to maneuver.
Nice give and go is good. Yeah, there's the freshman, Brockton stay with it, good defense by Cambridge, but you see the freshman, Petrop to the hoop. Yeah, nice ball movement by Brockton. And here comes Lambert with the steal, lays it, gives a nice little pass, but the rebound is good. Offensive rebound by Africo. Yeah, Petrop got hammered that time, but Africo again with the clean up.
And they're gonna call a blocking foul on number 10. You'll see the replay right here. Yeah, you see Africo all over the cleanup, able to get two for Brockton. Brockton out to a strong start, five to one. Inbound. Moses gets it over to his teammate, Zerman. Takes a long three, and that's gonna be an air ball. And way off. Back on the boxes.
Furman. Fortz. Africo in the corner to number five, and it's gonna. Hit the top. Hit the cables. Yeah, got a good look. Unable to hit the three. Marcus Fortz starting off 0 for 2 so far from distance. And Cambridge looks like they're gonna talk things over here, Miles. Yeah, Marcus Fortz. He was with this boxer team last year.
along with Cody Lambert, again, young boxer team.
and they will be tested this evening. Yeah, during the course of the year, Miles, so far, Brockton has handled the first half pretty, pretty good. Last game, they played Franklin, who's considered by most one of the best teams in the state. And Brockton was only down six at halftime. But it's been a tale of two halves for the Brockton boxers. They've been unable to execute in the third quarter. That's led to their three losses starting the season, one and three.
This is our first home broadcast this year at Staff Gymnasium. And you couldn't ask for a better game. Yeah, look at this crowd. It is completely packed. We also have stands behind us open, which is sometimes not open. I told you the magnitude of this game, Cambridge versus Brockton. Yep, and Cambridge fans have come out this evening also.
to support their team. Again, Cambridge Falcons coming in here at three wins and one loss. Yeah, the only loss is to a really good team, Attaborough, who some think can win that state championship too, so. Wow. Yep. And then you think about Cambridge, right? You got the Patrick Ewins, Ramil Robinson, Brockton, Curtis Bostick. The list goes on with this game between Brockton and Cambridge. Well, Brockton puts a little pressure on the inbounds.
Moses. Great defense by Brock, as you can see. Shot is missed. Good defense by the Boxers. They get it up quickly. Oh, nice pass! Right to the freshman, Lambert! Nice pass by Lambert. Yeah, playing without the ball is Petrop, and he has four to start off in. Long three. Good!
That was Howard. Yeah, Dante Howard saying. From downtown. Give me that. Good shot. Africo at the top of the key. Long shot is good. And Lambert said, whatever you can do, I can do better. He responds with a three of his own.
and that's what they need. It's gonna be a travel, but a great rebound that time by Curry. It's unfortunate he lost his balance. And that's a good sign, Orlando. Box is shooting that long ball and hitting. They're gonna have to hit him tonight to stay with this Cambridge team. You can see the replay of that Lambert three. Very good stroke by Cody.
Stop and pop is no good. Great defense by the Boxers. Rebound, yep, rebound Boxers. Ooh, there's some contact. Nope, no whistle. In the corner, the Lambert, he's gonna take it. Bang! You don't leave that guy open! Cody starting off two for two. You sure do. Back to back threes. Brockton out to an explosive start. Long bomb is no good. And that'll be Boxer Ball.
And you can see Cody once again with his second three-pointer in a row to give Brockton a 13-4 lead. What a beautiful stroke by Lambert. And that's what they need out of the guard. Lambert, a sophomore.
It's gonna be Junior. In and out, tough break for the boxers here. Moses, shaking and baking. Stolen! Here come the boxers. And they're gonna call travel. That's gonna be a travel by the freshmen.
That time he should have just put his head down and go straight to the hoop. Yep, maybe get a foul. Tough defense by the boxers right now. Long bomb, good! Yeah, that's another one by Howard, wow. Who's a senior.
Can't leave that guy open, looks like. This Falcon team is a veteran team. They got two seniors and three juniors starting. Boxers moving around. Inside, back to Forks, and they can call travel again. A lot of times that travel can be caught just by good defense.
by the opponent. I agree. Cambridge's defense intensity is lost. Fox is playing man-to-man defense. Moses back to Desire. No good.
Nice job on the offensive boards by the boxers. Here they come. Shot, no good. Offensive board, puts it back up, no good. Wow, it looked like Africo got followed there, no call. Yeah, no call. But I like what I see Orlando as far as crashing the boards. They have to.
Unlike Cambridge, Brockton stops four underclassmen out there. Very young, including the freshman, who just took a break. That's Howard. Over to 21, he hits it. Cambridge Falcons are showing they can hit that three right now, so Brockton's gonna have to step up their three-point defense.
Drive to the basket, lays it up and in! Cody! Nice job by Cody Lambert. Off to a strong start, that's eight for Cody. Moses drives, passes out. One-handed shot, air ball. And here come the boxes. Nice juggle pass, and it's in!
That's number 10, O'Kerry. Yeah, off a great feed by number 15. Yes. Nazir Pereira. Pereira. Just came in for the boxers and beautiful pass. Got a replay here. Yeah, Nazir Pereira taking it to the hoop. And there you go, O'Kerry ready right there with a nice layup. Great transition offense by Brockton that time.
Oh, kick it out of there. Nice. Great defense by the Boxers. Oh! Looked like a follow through, but will take the hoop. Beautiful play by Forts. He just, two men on him, Orlando. Rocked it out to a blazing start here in the first quarter, 19-10, Boxers. Oh, stolen.
Looks like he got fouled! And he lays it in! And fouled! Pereira out the bench and making it work right now with his passing and you see the hoop and a chance for an and one. Nice job, here's a replay. Wow, Pereira able to hold his balance with the lefty, two off the glass and now a chance for a three point play. Outstanding by Pereira.
Yep, Boxer's playing with a lot of confidence at the moment. Another underclassman for Brockton. And a shot, free throw's good, three point play, 22-10 with 40 seconds to go in this first quarter. Ah, that's gonna be a chance, that's a good call that time. Yeah, that was a good call.
Referee's right there to make the call, easy for him, and he'll go the other way. Yep, that was on Furman. The Falcons. You see the potential of these young boxers. This is a good Cambridge team, make no mistake.
Okay, Box is gonna hold it for the last shot as Coach DeBaros calls out the play. Pereira with the ball. Letting it wind down. Looking firing.
Right, too much dribble in that time. Yeah, he should've took a shot with at least six seconds on the clock. Maybe the boxers could've got the offensive board because they've been doing a great job in this first quarter for offensive boards. Right, but make no mistake, Pereira made his presence felt when he came in the game off the bench. Unable to hit that three-pointer there, but great stop by Brogdon out to a blazing 12-point lead here in the first quarter.
So, Lando, what do you see as far as the boards? How are the boxers you consider as far as defense and offensive boards? Well, obviously, you see the intensity of the defenses. They've had a lot of turnovers, had points off turnovers as well. And then, like you said, Miles, they are crashing the boards. And this is what you got to do to beat a good team like Cambridge. Exactly. So, at the end of this first quarter, you see the score 22 to 10.
boxes gotta figure a way to hold that, hold that lead to at least eight, nine points if they can. It's gonna be tough. Yeah, here's that block, unbelievable. I believe it's occur, pinning it off the glass. Number 10 occur, and then the other way, Brock goes in transition, points off big plays. The Brock to boxes that in the first quarter.
And the Cambridge Falcons, right, Miles, 14 state title, that leads the entire state. This is a rich program, and they're about winning. And this rivalry with Brockton goes back years and years. The home of Patrick Ewing. Yes, sir. This is his high school alma mater, Cambridge Range in Latin.
Brockton, they're in these four games, their first half has been good. Hopefully they can withstand this going forward. Boxing with the ball. Africo has it. Yeah, Cambridge Falcons, they make you work. Almost throws it away. Tough Falcon defense.
And the long bomb is in and out. Offensive board to the spot. And he's good! Nathan! Nathan O'Curry making his presence felt. Miles with another offensive board and put back. Wow. Yeah, he's really hustling. Here's the replay on that. Look at this. Just staying with it, crashing the boards, and just getting points, big points for Brockton here in this first half. See, and that's what they need on them. They need the big man, which is,
Number 10, O'Kerr. O'Kerr, yep. O'Kerr and that's what they need out of the big guy. They need for him to crash the boards every time that he's out there. Offense as well as defense. And he misses the free throw. And number 12.
for the Falcons, gets that one off the boards. Yeah, Burziquin stayed with it with the putback that time. Good position. Yeah, by mistake, but able to get the two. Oh, nice drive by number 15 for the Foxes. That's Pereira again.
That's a nice move. Yeah. Yeah. A little bit too easy. I'm sure. Yeah, Fawkes. Fawkes found the lane. Yep, frowned on that one. Long bomb. Good! Fawkes! Fawkes with the hot hand. And he can do that. Marcus Fawkes. Inside to the big man. Falcon. Oh, what a block. Oh, nice block.
Fiera, and the paint, dishes it out to the corner. Africa, excuse me, Africo. Should've followed his shot. Yes. Yeah, that's gonna be a foul there. Good call by the ref. Yeah, Africo should've followed that shot and came right back to him,
He kind of looked at his shot, it was flat. He followed that, but it had a probably easy layup. But nothing really bad to say here in this first half. Brockton has come out playing. You see the lead 15. Some people looking at the score right now, they're like, wow. And you said it. There you go again. Orlando, they came to play. Nice, nice transition game right there. And you wonder when this coach is going to call a timeout. The lead has ballooned to 17.
for Brockton. Harker's right on him. Long bomb, he's gonna foul Tiki Tack, but it's a foul. I don't know about that, Carl. That's a freebie right there.
You can call that every time. Yeah. Yeah, here's the replay. I don't know about that call. That's just a great defense. Kid misses the shot. Now you can reward him with three shots. Wow. So I question that call, but refs have been good to now, you know? Yeah, they have. That shot had no chance of going in either. Let's go.
So number 12. That's a weird form, but you see right there, it's all net. Oh, that's Amir. How do you pronounce that? Bariziqui. Good enough, Bariziqui. Yep. Bariziqua. Yeah.
You can't lob the ball like that. Bad pass. You can't lob the ball like that. You're making it easier for Cambridge. You're basically giving them possession. Here's the replay right here. Just a simple lob. That's a no-no.
Africa's gonna sit out. Yeah, you can't lobby because this Cambridge team is very fast, very quick. Like ball hawks say, they're gonna go after that ball immediately when you do that. Yep, backcourt. The defense brought some
Amir wasn't paying attention where his feet were. Not too many seniors here in this Brockton team. If you see a senior that just came in, Jaheim Willen, number four. Brockton does not have many seniors that play. Yeah, and as far as Cambridge goes, they've had two seniors come off the bench. Yep. Oh, that's a clean strip right there. And good transition. Oh, nice steal by Carrera. Mark has got to be smarter with that ball. Yeah. He's a better ball handler than that.
All right, Pierre with the ball. Let's go. Let's go. It's gonna be a jump ball.
Brockton looking like a little unraveled here and you can see the steal here, clean swipe. Last couple of minutes they haven't looked like the Brockton in that first quarter. And the coach senses that and he calls timeout. Good timeout by Coach DeBaros. You saw the replay on the clean swipe there by Carrera, able to go to the hoop for two and Marcus gotta be smarter with that ball and they've cut a 17 point lead down to 13. Yeah the big thing now for the Foxes is like you said,
They can't commit turnovers because turnovers.
for the Cambridge Falcons will turn into points. And you make a good point, Miles, because in analyzing Brockton's three straight losses, the turnovers in the second half have played a huge part in teams getting runs on a young team. And sometimes when you get a young team like that, you can go through waves of doing that. Exactly. This is the learning curve that we talk about, right? Exactly. When you're a young team, you're going to make mistakes.
Huge crowd here in Brockton. Not too many much seats open. Front and back stands are open. And right now it's been mostly all Brockton. Brockton is hitting the shots they've had to. They've gotten offensive rebounds, defensive rebounds. They just have to continue doing what they're doing and playing good defense and not having many turnovers. Correct. Especially in their first quarter.
And they've shut this guy down. Their main player, Moses, pretty much the whole game so far. That's a steal. Oh, nice little fake, but he misses it, but he's fouled. Yeah, had a chance for Kent Pereira making his presence felt in this game. And again, you see the replay going to the hoop. Nice fake.
Had a chance for a three point play, didn't make the shot, but able to go to the line for two. Yep, Pierre, a sophomore. Another youngster for Brockton. Yep. Mason's first free throw attempt.
Second free throw attempt is good. Nice form by Pereira. Big guy for a guard. Yeah, and you can see his dribbling skills. There go Marcus, that's a foul. And you know what? I'm surprised they're not going to call that a take foul because there was no one up ahead and he got leveled. Wow.
You see the replay here, there's no one up ahead and Marcus just got clotheslined pretty much. They're just going to call it a simple foul. Surprising that that's not anything bigger than that. And we see Gabe. My man Gabe just checking into the game for the first time for the Brockton Boxers.
There's the freshman. And the paint in the corner. And they're gonna call travel. Nice idea, but too many steps. Another turnover for the Boxers here in this second quarter.
And here come the Falcons. Whoa. That's a Osmosis right there. That's just a strong, that's a big boy. That's a big boy move. That's a big boy move right there. Wow. First points, I believe, of the game. Lambert. The number 22. Back to Ford.
He got smacked, no call, that's a foul. Wow. I heard that all the way over here. I mean, how do you not call that? He traveled, but he got smacked before he traveled. Tough call there, going against the boxers. You heard smack from here, right? I heard it from here.
It's just a nice pass. Nice pass. Correra, again, down below. So far, he's been the main guy for this Falcon team. 11-point lead for the Boxers. Shot. Rebound. No good. Let's go. Rebound, Cambridge. Here they come. Oh, go all the way. All the way. All the way. Stop and pop. No good.
Offensive board, long bomb, no good. Lambert comes out of there and hit him in the boxes. Proctor gotta watch out here. A. Cambridge has stepped up the intensity. Lambert drives in the corner. Turnover.
I brought you gotta watch out Cambridge to step up the intensity of defense and not good look Brock is not getting good looks at Manny Coach the barrels sense that he's gonna call a timeout to put a stop to this surge by the Cambridge Falcons Cambridge creeping back into this game. They only down by nine Yeah, you see the replay again off of Brockton turnover and
able to get two buckets and close this 17 point lead down to just single digits, nine. And this is a big, I would say this is a big two minutes for Brockford here left in this first half. Very big Orlando, very big because they feel the pressure. Right now Cambridge has a little momentum going. Like you said, they brought it down to just one digit which is nine points.
And so they're coming to themselves now. And we're seeing the real Cambridge starting to heat up here. Kind of a slow start, but now they're starting to get into a groove. Starting to make some good defensive moves on the boxers.
I think defensively, Cambridge has been sound. It's the offense, then, that's led to transition points for the Brockton boxers. And Brockton has not been able to run their offense consistently right now. You take away the two Lambert threes, it's been kind of tough sledding for this offense. Brockton's doing it from the defensive boards, offensive rebound and things like that.
So,
Almost a turnover there, not on the same page, Lambert and Forts. Forts gonna take it, and makes it! You talk about a huge shot! That's a huge one. To sense the rush, and wow, what a big shot by Forts right there, because Cambridge was really making a surge, and that stops that there. Long three, in and out.
And that's going to be Cambridge's ball. Yeah, that's the second big three-pointer Fortes has hit for Brockton, and that one was probably the biggest. Moses, good. You see why he's probably their best player, Moses, because guys starting to heat up right now.
Brockton has put the clamps on him for the start of the game, but now he's starting to heat up, and that's a foul. Nice call by the referees there on Moses. Yeah, that's never a good foul when you have to reach like that. Yeah, I mean, that's not a smart move right there by Moses. Unnecessary. Yeah, here's the replay right there of the foul. Clearly hit him. Peltrick with inbound.
Back to Pelcher. And not a good pass stolen by Cambridge. Here they come. Falcons flying in there. Lays it up and in. Nice drop step. Lefty able to kiss it off the glass and again offer Brockton turnover by the freshman. Seven point boxer lead. 53 seconds in the second quarter. Looked like a travel. Perhaps might have missed the call there. Brockton's fortunate.
Off the glass and in! Pereira again! No fear going into that paint going up against the big boy. Sophomore looking good for Brockett off the bench. Oh! Nice block. Even though a foul was called.
Yeah, there's a little bit of talking going on there, the referee. You see the replay, that looked like it was all ball. Yeah, I don't know who the foul was, but they called it on him. And again, I don't know about that call. They called it on Carroll. Wow. I mean, a lot of that's going on in the other end too, so I don't understand that call, but ball don't lie, right? Don't lie. Ball don't lie. First shot in and out. That was a good ball.
Excellent block. Cambridge getting some height in there. Got to box out. Oh, didn't box out. Good defense by the boxers.
That's gonna be on the floor. Unfortunately, it's gonna be a bonus for Cambridge, but again, you have to box out. I tell you, good move by the coach for Cambridge to put them big guys in there. You see the replay here, no boxing out. He's gonna be shooting. That should be a bonus for Cambridge right now. That should be a bonus. Should be going to the line. And he is. A little confusion by the players.
but number four Nazir, a senior, will shoot the free throws. You basically gave him free buckets here. All you had to do was box out, hold the ball for the last shot, and you go into the half with at least a nine point lead for the Proctor, so you gotta box out. Second free throw attempt is good.
20 seconds on the clock, Boxers have the ball. Shot clock is off, Boxers need to hold on to this ball and get the last shot. That would be the smart thing to do. 8 seconds on the shot clock.
And got fouled. Nice job by Forts. Yeah, that time it was all Marcus Forts there in that last. He was not giving up that ball. He knew he was going to shoot it. Isolated this guy, able to go to Hoover. He did get hit in the arm and has a chance to give Brockton a nine point lead to go into the half. Forts a good free throw shooter.
And that's another thing the boxers need, when they get those free throws chances, they need to hit them. Fortuny and Junior, another underclassmen for Brockton. That nearly went in for the Falcons that time.
So we got the first half complete, very exciting first half. Orlando, what'd you see in that first half? That was Brockton's best first half of the season right there. Even the one they won in at Western North, because of the caliber of the team they're playing. 40 points up, considering Brockton has barely cracked a 40 in the previous three games. It was an impressive first half, I would say that. Yeah, that's a good point, Orlando. All right, I'm Miles Jackson along with Orlando Galveo. We'll be right back with exciting
second half action in a moment.
So, for those of you who don't know, last year, last year, we had a chance to have a senior position down here. It was for four or three and a half years, and I started working there, and then after I did, I stopped for a year, before I used to play, I was seven, eight percent.
In the year after that, it was a reason for me to be on set and use the work I was doing to develop a game, to be able to recalibrate on both bodies what blocker basketball is all about. You want to make sure that you give them the knowledge they're looking for. Give them that too.
Ladies and gentlemen, we appreciate the love of our hearts. We thank you for being such a good student athlete and being a very good representative of a lot of rock and roll students, including me. We appreciate the love that's ever been there for you, always been there for us. That's the love of football and everything you do. And so we just want to make sure that we acknowledge you tonight for seeing life as it is and being a special, special gift to everyone who did it.
Hey guys, make sure we're good. Let's go team. Let's go team.
And now just a few, just a few episodes. Thank you, love you guys. Congrats, goodnight.
you
and welcome everybody to Brockton High Basketball. We've got an exciting one in this staff gymnasium. I'm out jacking along with Orlando Galveo. And Orlando, Brockton has risen to the occasion to at least give these Cambridge Falcons a run for their money. Yeah, surprise, surprise. And like I said though earlier, the first half hasn't been the problem for Brockton just off the season. They've done great in the first half. Yeah, that's a good point. It's been the third quarter,
and a lot of people say, okay, they gotta make adjustments, but players gotta step up too, all right? So this is gonna be the telling, the third quarter, in terms of how the season has gone, Miles, this third quarter is gonna be the telling for the Brockton Boxers. Definitely so, as this Falcons defense started to clamp down on the
on Brockton's offense in that second quarter. Yeah, you see Paris Moses. They shut him down early in the game, but you see he's catching his groove now, right? And he's starting to get comfortable. And for Brockton, in that first half, Cody Lambert and Marcus Forts led the way for the Brockton Boxers. And you see the talent of the freshman, Claire Burns-Peltrack.
And he's just, he plays beyond his years. He does not look like a freshman. And we see him out on the court, but at times he do, right? With that lazy pass and things like that, he has to work on it. And in order for this Brockton team to hang with Cambridge, they're going to have to cut down on the turnovers because that's where Cambridge took advantage.
and that second quarter was Brockton's turnover. Yes, and Brockton to Cambridge Defense too, their turnover has led to Brockton transition points as well. So the third quarter, like I said, Miles, that's been the problem for Brockton, so I'm pretty sure Coach Farris is talking about that. How we come out in the third quarter is gonna indicate if we're gonna win this game or not. All right, we're getting ready to start this second half. Third quarter, here at Staff Gymnasium,
This is Brockton Community Access Sports bringing the best in high school basketball. Yeah, Marcus Ford's led Brockton in that first half with 12. And don't forget about Nazir Pereira, who has nine off the bench. And then Cody Lambert followed up with eight. Yeah, Pereira did a nice job coming off the bench, giving the boxers some help on offense. So the boxers will inbound it, begin this third quarter.
sports. Cody off the rim. That was a good look. Good setup. Unable to hit the three. And the paint. No, that is off black. Wow. Again, another missed call by the referees. Yeah, that's a clear miss. If we can get the replay on that, that just went off his leg. He goes to the hoop erratically and gets awarded with the ball again. Unbelievable.
And the referees will have a little meeting. Yeah, they're talking about it. It looked like it went off his leg. It's going to stay here. They talked about it. It still stays here. Shot. No good.
Again, Cambridge scrambling for that ball. Cambridge still with the ball. Long bomb by Moses is good. Yeah, you see he got the shooter's roll. And again, he continues his momentum. And this leads down to six. Nice, Josh Fowler. There's that freshman, Claire Burns. Pelt drop with an and one.
This kid's gonna be a stud. Yeah, nice job by Peltrop. He'll go to the free throw line to shoot one. Here's a replay on the freshman. Nice hoop, nice teardropper to the line for a three point play. Nice answer that time by Brockton off the Moses three. That's Furman with the ball.
In-your-face defense right now by Brockton. They try to get inside, stolen by Cody Lambert. Boyds. Another freshman. Afriko Lambert. Good defense by Cambridge. Yeah. Shot by Lambert, no good.
Freshman's up. Just misses it. And now they come out of there. Nice move by the freshman. Unable to hit it, but good move. Moses. Gets it out top. Stop and pop. No good. Rebound. Brockton, here they come.
Africa just got leveled, no call. It's been one rep, they're just calling it one way right now. Missed that one, that was a lot of body contact, but no call. That's a terrible call, I mean. Falcons with the ball.
Cambridge works it around. That's Furman. Nice defense by the freshman. Back to Moses. Moses spins in the paint, puts it up. No good. And Brockman comes out of there. Oh, nice dish off. Oh.
Again, and number 22 for the Boxers puts it in. Yeah, that was actually a curve with the follow-up off the freshman miss. And again, a curve, stay with it, crashing the boards. Nice job by O'Kerr. Oh, wild shot, no good. Shot missed again by Moses, and he, excuse me, number 15. Carrera, numerous attempts, and the second time he was able to
to get the hoop. Yeah, that was a great hustle by Cambridge. Nine point box to lead, shot from the out, Key misses. Moses comes at it and they push it up. In the corner, no good. Moses, block, and here they come. Not a great pass that time.
And bye-bye Marcus just throws it up there. Brock is getting a little sloppy with the ball right now. Yeah, he should have held on to it and just brought it up. It wasn't like he was by himself. There was a couple guys down there with him. Not a good pass. That's Furman. Clark's not moving. Clark's not moving.
Yeah, another clean-up that time, and Brock is getting... Beat under the boards right now. Handled on the boards right now. Leads down to seven. For it. Off the glass, off the rim, and no good. I didn't mind that shot. Nice pass. And Cambridge starting to heat up underneath.
Both of their baskets in this second half have been underneath the boards. Underneath the rim, excuse me. And watch out here for Brockton. Again, the third quarter has been where Brockton has fell apart early in the season. Another turnover. Man, that's a back court.
So we got some substitutions here by Brockton. And Pereira, the hot guy in the first half of Brockton comes into the game. And the freshman will take a breather. Good anticipation by Marcus, unable to get the steal but.
Nice job. Almost had an easy two going the other way. It definitely would have been an easy two. 25 seconds left on the shot clock for Cambridge Ridge. Drive to the basket, dishes underneath. And it's good, and he's fouled. Nice dish off.
by Furman. Again, Cambridge rolling to the hoop and finding the guy underneath. And you can see the replay, this has happened numerous times tonight for the Cambridge Falcons. Very skilled with the ball, going to the hoop is Furman. Able to find number 33, Aaron Abib, the junior forward for the Falcons and has a chance to complete a three point play.
Number four, Desir just skied up there for the offensive boards. Now the lead is down to one, ladies and gentlemen. We have a new game here. And that's a foul on Desir. Again, almost a turnover and Marcus did get fouled, but again, third quarter rules for Brockton is
Looks like it's happening again. Wow. And a turnover that time. No call and a timeout by Brockton. Good timeout here by Costa Verde. Antoninus to the Falcons. It looked like he just lost the ball out of bounds.
Wanted the foul, but he might have lost the ball just before he was fouled That doesn't count so uh nine-point lead to stop the
The third quarter's been cut down to one. Yeah, it's been, Cambridge has finally come around and started controlling these boards on the offense as well as the defense, and most importantly, the offensive end, because most of their points have been coming underneath the rim on those offensive rebounds. Yeah, you look at Brock, they've been outscored here in the third quarter with three minutes and 12 seconds to go, they've been outscored 13 to five. Yeah, that's not good. And they still hold a one point lead.
but they gotta start producing some points. But again, Cambridge plays some really tough defense in this third quarter. They've been smothering Brock's offense. So let's see what Coach DeBarros draws up here, and it will be going the other way with Cambridge off the turnover.
Cambridge has a chance to take the lead for the first time in a great while. Maybe for the first time tonight. Yeah, that's just unheard of. I never thought that Cambridge, if they take the lead, would be in the third quarter for the first time. Correct. I believe so.
Drive to the basket, and a call travel. Good defense by Brockett. Yeah, that time he spun around and had a guy right in his face in too many steps. Yep, nice job by Cody Lambert. Playing tough defense. Sierra.
Almost lost it. And he is fouled.
Good move by time by Africo, going to who? Brockton stayed patient with it, passing the ball around the perimeter and is able to get rewarded right here maybe with two shots here at the line for Africo. Yeah, here's the replay. And it seemed like it took a little time for them refs to blow that whistle. Yeah, looked like it got hammered, two guys there.
First free throw attempt is good. Let's see how Brockton responds here. Cambridge able to cut the lead down to one. Nice touch at the free throw line for Africo.
You really gotta get in his face. He's a big guy, a junior forward, Aaron Abebe with a three pointer. We are all tied up. Nice strong move, but he missed it.
And Fultz will be called to the foul. And that's a... That's a... See the three here by Abebe. Didn't waste no time. Looked confident in shooting it, nailing it, tying this game. And the other way, Cambridge had a three-on-one break if that foul wasn't committed. So... I like how the boxers go into the paint and attempt the shot, but...
Because of the tough Falcon defense, they're just not making them. You see why you're starting to see here in the third quarter why Cambridge is one of the better teams in this. Yeah, they're going to call a foul. It's going to call a foul in the fourth. Yep.
Nice, nice. Here they come, boxes.
Nice shot, nice touch. That's Pereira who's been excellent off the bench that time with a nice teardropper. He's up to 11. And nice defense by, who's that, Fonts? Yeah, the Cambridge coaches are
Where is the foul? They're screaming, and they might have a point there. Yeah. They might have a point there, Miles. But maybe it's a make-up for that. Yeah, maybe it is. Maybe it is. Box is up by two. Forts. Back to Forts.
Stop and pop, and he's fouled. And he did get hit in that guy forever again.
coming off the bench contributing. Very patient, handles the ball pretty good and that time got hit in the arm and has a chance to go to the line to extend the Brockton lead and most importantly this Cambridge surge and you see the replay here as he gets hit. Again, boxers have
Nothing but juniors, sophomores, and one senior. He's been out on the court. You see the response by this young Brockton team to the Cambridge time again. We're in Cambridge. They're a senior team, veteran team. A lot of seniors, few juniors. Shot is good. Forever giving Brockton a big lift with 13 tonight. Four-point lead for the Broxers.
And... Oh! Offensive foul! Nice call! That is a good call. Yeah, I mean, Furman is arguing about the call, but he clearly throws an elbow, and he's lucky he didn't get hit with a technical that time. Because he clearly threw that elbow. You can see the replay on that. He's arguing, he's frustrated, but you can't just swing your elbows out there, right? No, you can't. No, you can't. He's gonna be taking out the game. Frustrated. Frustrated. Defense. Good defense.
Long bomb is no good. Maybe a little bit too far out for Fonts. Shot in the corner is no good. Moses. Number 33, no good. And here come the boxes.
This'll be a big shot right here. In the corner. Oh, no good. Rebound boxes. And they're going to call travel. Tough call there. That was a tough call, but I believe he did take too many steps, but brought the numerous opportunities that time to extend the lead. Good looks, too, I would say.
15 seconds left in this third quarter. Box is up by four. Box is double teaming Moses. And oh wow, that looked like an elbow by Moses. I don't like the call.
I mean now the game's starting, you see the physicality. It's starting to intensify. The referees are not adjusting to it because. You're right, they're not adjusting to it because that was an aggressive. What's the call? What's the call? Well they called a defensive foul but Moses was quite, quite aggressive with the senior and he got away with one. Stops and pops.
No good. That's going to be a foul. Yeah, he hammered him in the head off the rebound. Tough call. That's probably going to send Cambridge to the line, unfortunately, with one second. Both teams in the bonus here for the right now. But it was a good rebound. I mean, crashing the boards. Even though it's a foul, you want the boxers to fight hard underneath the boards.
You don't want the Falcons just to get an easy rebound and put it back up. You gotta be physical. Second free throw attempts in and out.
They have it into the third quarter boxes still have a lead Orlando and that's a good sign right there that they didn't fold.
They bent a little bit, but they didn't break. Right, they still hold the lead. Cambridge, where they did advantage in that third quarter, outscoring Brockton, 17 to 10. But like you said, Brockton still holds a three-point lead, barely. So we know, we talked about the third quarter, but now you're going to have to continue it.
We talked about the third quarter, excuse me, but now you're going to have to continue into the fourth quarter. Yeah, and you're going to see the physicality on both sides get even tougher in this fourth quarter.
Yes, you see, especially in the Cambridge end, they ramped up in physicality. And Brockton has responded pretty, pretty well. And you see Pereira giving Brockton big minutes off the bench. 13 points for Nysere Pereira. He's been big today. He's probably, let's say, been the savior right now for the Brockton Boxers. And the Boxers really got to concentrate on number 44, the senior, Paris Moses.
good ball handler, good shooter, and he's got a little weight on him where he can get physical. Yeah, and he handles the ball pretty good, very good player. And he's probably going to look to take over right now. Yeah. People in Cambridge know that he's probably their best player, and he's probably going to be the go-to guy. But as you can see, Cambridge is not just one guy, Miles. That's a scary part. They've got multiple guys that's more than capable of scoring and putting the ball in the hoop.
Yes, yes indeed. That's the scary part about this Cambridge team. Cambridge will have possession here in this very big fourth quarter coming up. They should be excited, Miles. This should be a one good fourth quarter coming up. Very excited. Let's go. One thing about Brockton, they didn't make a lot of turnovers there in the third quarter, which was good.
Oh, look at this. Wow. Oh, come on. That is a pocket. He picked his pocket like a thief. Like a thief in the night. That's just a bad call. Big break for Cambridge. You cannot reward. No. You cannot reward. Wow. I mean, you look at the replay. It's just a clean strip by Pereira. And right now, Cambridge clearly getting the advantage of the call. That's a terrible call. Yeah, a terrible call. All ball. All ball.
foul now what do you do I mean you can't play defense they don't want the rest of watching to play defense is there underneath and that's a foul
Good defense by the boxers, but right at the end there. That was a legit foul, but Cambridge shouldn't even have the ball. Let's keep it real. That was a clean pit rip by Pereira at the other end. We're talking about a difference of four points right there. Exactly. In fairness to the ref that made the calls, a very good ref. And he was right there on that pick. I can't believe he didn't.
Well, he had a better angle to it, but as you can see in the replay, it was all ball. It was all ball. Mike, the postman, Simmons, giving us great replay action. Yeah, and then Brock did, most importantly, two early fouls to stop the fourth quarter here. Not good. Two-point boxer lead. Long bomb. In and out. Yeah, Mark has been really cold here in the second half.
Moses takes the long bomb, good. That's Cambridge's first lead of the ball game and Moses. Moses all money. Yep, heating up. They gotta try to get somebody in his face when he shoots that three. Rockton needs a shot here.
Brockton working it around. That got hammered. And I almost thought that was going to call that. That was a late call. Late call. But nice decision by Spahn. You see the three here by Moses, who's heating up. And then at the other end, Forts is able to go to the hoop and draw the foul and has a chance to get Brockton back the lead. Yeah. Again, Orlando, somebody for Brockton has to get in.
Moses' face from way out there, because he can hit those with ease. Especially when the adrenaline is flowing. That's not going to help him. Now Brock needs to take advantage here in the fourth quarter. Every chance they get to go to the free throw line, they need to make these free throws. You see the freshman coming in the game for Lambert. Beltran.
I'm pretty sure Lambert's arrest is going to be very briefly. And he makes his second free throw attempt. Tie game. Stop and park. That's just a good move. That's a sweet move that time. Yeah. Dazeer. Yeah, by the transfer, Dazeer from New Mission. Won a state championship last year for New Mission. Now doing work for the Cambridge Falcons.
and Africo drives to the basket and it's rejected. Now you see the replay there, Desair, Desair with a nice move, all net, that was beauty. Stop and pop. That's gonna be a bad ball. That'll be Cambridge's ball. Nice hustle by the big man, number 10, O'Keir trying to get the offensive boards.
And this young Brockton team with all underclassmen but one out there. And they're gonna call a blocking foul. Yeah, that's okay. He's a senior. He's the only one, only senior that's been playing. And let's see the replay again. That is a suspect foul as well. I mean, he has his position. He just got ran over. Yeah, and his feet was planted. So again, Brockton's not getting the calls in.
I mean, it's almost like they can't play defense, boss. If you get too close, you're going to get called for a foul. Here's Cambridge. Nazir spins. Gets it back to Moses. Moses goes in the paint. Pops. No good. What a rebound that time by the curve. Rebound by the senior. And here come the boxers. In the corner. Cody right back in the game. Shakes, fakes. Can't do that.
That's going to be a foul. Mike's all over him. There's a push right there, and again, he doesn't like that. And again. And Apatow gets in his face. Yeah, and you know what? He didn't like the push. Plain and simple. You're allowing one team. You see the replay here. Right, exactly. You're allowing one team to play one way, but you're not allowing the other team to play. And this is what happened. And this is what's going to happen.
Yeah, basically tackling him. And they're going to call it a double technical, but you're allowing one team to play one way, but you're not allowing the other team to play. And this is what happened. And this is going to happen. This is on the referee. Yes. Yes, indeed. I can agree with you on that. It's like Procter wants to play physical too, you know? Right. You've got suspect calls where they just
running over the Brockton player, a clean strip. And no call. And no call. It's unbelievable. I'm not trying to sound like a homer. I just want you to call it the same way. Call it fair. And the crowd right now is really not liking this referee and crew right now.
There was a Cambridge foul, we have to mention on that, but double technicals, I believe. And the foul was on Correa. I don't like to fight Nadia, but I like... Yeah, it's also a Brock's fault. I like the defense of you coming to your player, but try to keep your calm and try to win this game. Yeah, Africa has got to keep his calm. They need him out there. Yeah, they need him, definitely.
So we got a timeout, 5.47 on the clock. Very intense game. This game is taking another turn here in the fourth quarter here. It's going to be a fight to the finish with 5.47 left. And the referee is going to have to do their job to keep control of this game.
Again, like you said, Orlando, there's been some pretty physical contact by Cambridge, and there's no fouls, but when Brockton
comes and gets physical and met with that steal. There was no physicality there. They're going to call a tap foul. And I'll tell you something right now, and to Brock's defense, that strip of Pereira and the foul call, that has changed this game. We're talking about going the other way and having a five-point lead to possibly giving the other team a chance to tie the game.
Next Brockton foul will put him in the bonus. So Cambridge has three here in the fourth quarter. And the crowd has gotten into this game as well. Well with the way Brockton played in that first half, the crowd has definitely helped them.
and the crowd has backed this boxer team since the tip-off. So let's see how Brockton responds to that fiasco that just happened. They're down by two. All possessions right now are really crucial for both teams. Really crucial. And for Brockton, the free throws would be more crucial for them.
You have to go get to the Fonz. Fonz stops and pops. That's a good look, good pull up. Brock still has it. Ah, threw it away. Wow. That's gonna put Cambridge to the line.
You know, Orlando, I don't like the call. The guard with the ball was throwing his hands out very aggressively, making the contact. Here's a replay. You guys make the call at home. Wow. Another break for Cambridge. As Correa, the junior, will go to the free throw line on the bonus.
Right now Brockton only 12 points so far in the second half. Cambridge gets it back outside on a defense opposite board, excuse me. Oh! Another rebound.
Long bomb is no good. Yeah, that's gonna be an offensive foul that time, but Cambridge just dominating the boards and making their presence felt down there. See, Brockton cannot let them get two and three chances on the board, on the offensive end. I know they got a tough order to fill here, but. I'm telling you, this is a big possession right now for the Boxers. Yes.
Rockman still has a little spin move in the knee, and it's blocked. Transition for Cambridge. And that's a foul. It looked like the freshman got hammered out down there. Again, no call. And we go again the other way. There's a lot of bodies back there. Here's your replay.
Peltrop looked like he was hammered, but no call. This has been a tough second half for these young boxers. In and out. Freshman's gonna take a seat, and Peltrop and Pereira's gonna come in the game, who's been big tonight for Brockton.
That's Howard at the free throw line, makes his second free throw attempt. Cambridge up by four. Brockton hasn't got a field goal in a great while. They need one. Need a shot here. Ooh, contact. And one! No good, he's gonna call it before he's shot it.
Wow. Well, he's still going to go to the line to shoot two, because Cambridge is going to be in the bonus, I believe. Actually, yes, that's the fifth foul. Boxers will be in the bonus. But that was a good call. You don't get continuation in high school. Knee D2. Knee D2. Freak those right here, Miles. Yep, Pierre the Junior. Woo-hoo.
He's been perfect from the line. He's a good free throw shooter. Up to 14 points tonight for the sophomore. Coming off the bench. Should be Brockton ball, and it is. Nice hustle there by number 10, O'Kara.
Missed free throw, Brockton stays with the offensive board and able to get the possession. Timeout. Coach Barrow calls a timeout with 4.15 on the clock here in the fourth quarter. Cambridge up by three, Orlando. Yeah, it's been a struggle here in the second half. Let's keep it real here for Brockton.
with that being said they're only down by three and uh so one possession game so in position to win this game even though the struggles of the second half uh miles yeah brockton these last four minutes they got to make shots and they cannot turn the ball over
And the third thing is, if they get to the free throw line, they gotta make their free throws. That's a must. On this tough Cambridge team. And I think Brockton has gone ice cold here in the second half from three-point range. And they need a big one. They need one from the distance. And they're down by three, so this could be big. This possession, this three-pointer right here could be the calling card here. But been a struggle here in the second half. They've been cold from outside. They really haven't hit that shot like they did in that first half.
but we still got four minutes, 15 seconds left. A lot can happen. Boxer's trying to come out of here with an upset. Yeah, Cambridge has outscored Brockton here in the second half, 25-13 to take this three-point lead. And again, Brockton, early into the season, struggles in the second half has been real. And if they can win this game, this can come a long way to fixing that second half woes.
Okay, here we go. I believe Brock has the ball. Out there to Africa. And they're gonna call travel. He picked up his feet. He got caught in no man's land and nowhere to go now. Going the other way. Another turnover for the Boxers.
That's Howard. DeZear. Goes to the draft, drives, blocked. Yeah, good defense. Looks like a foul, no call. Wow, Howard down for the Cambridge Falcons. And a turnover. And here comes Moses, the senior. And, oh, come on, he had his.
Now, that's a good call. That's a good call. That's a good call. Unfortunately, he did not plant his feet. But however, we saw a foul not get called. And we're going to see the replay here. Didn't look like Pereira planted his feet. We will get a replay on that. But it was planted. So you might have been miles. Yeah, it looked like he was planted. And Moses was coming in full steam.
You called it, Miles, but it looked like, for the replay, it looked like he did play it to his feet, but again, turnovers. It's hurting Brockton, killing Brockton right now. This Paris Moses is a pure shooter. He's been, uh,
Story here in the second half. Paris Moses. Three-throw attempt missed. Rebound, Foxes. Africo. Oh. Africo has been sluggish with the ball of his last few possessions, and he's getting caught in a no-man's land, and it's forcing turnovers. Yeah, you just can't do that. Only a sophomore, but you've got to be smart.
Damon's slowing things down up for him. That's Dazeer with the ball. They're running down the shot clock. Dazeer. In the corner. Good! Wow. Again, set up by Dazeer. With the dribble, kick out.
baseline three point of Falcons extends the lead to seven and Brockton's in trouble.
Yes, just tough break for Brockton. Good pass into the corner, to his teammate in the corner. And he did what Cambridge does. They hit that outside shot. They've been hitting him in this second half, Orlando. Yeah, you saw it. You saw it. He knew what he was going to do the whole time. Waiting for the guy to come up. Had the guy baseline. Nice kick out. And able to make it all net in Cambridge. Wow. Up 7.
Cambridge again, coming in here with three wins, one loss. And your Brockton boxers coming in here with one win and four losses, trying to give the fans a win. And they've really been hustling hard. But a little bit too many turnovers, it's really hurt them. Again, it's a 60-53 game, there's a little bit less than three minutes left, 2.57 to be exact. Brockton can still get into, you know, you gotta do something in the office event.
And if you make a shot here, you're still in the game. It's only a three possession game. Still a lot of time left. Still a lot of time. But now Brockton has to make shots. When they have the ball, come down the court, they gotta make shots. Gotta make shots. Because Cambridge is making their shots. And right now Cambridge feels the momentum. Yeah, this crowd has been greeted by a great game here. Yeah, they've gotten their money's worth this evening.
Cambridge is gonna make Brockton work the ball coming up.
At Cambridge, a very tough defense. Brockton did not find an open shot here. Ports with the ball. Lambe! And that's what you need! Brockton's first three-pointer in the second half, and that was a big one. Wow, I can't believe that first three-pointer in the first, second half, excuse me. But they needed that one. Stop and pop inside. Oh, what a shot.
Howard answers for the Falcons. Six point, Cambridge lead. Going away, here comes Cambridge. Long three, no good. Oh, nice position by number 15 underneath the boards, Correa with the easy two. And again off another Brockton turnover unfortunately.
and they're gonna call a foul on Paris Moses. Yeah, it's been a tale of two halves, Miles, unfortunately. Eight point, Cameron's lead at the moment with one minute, 38 seconds on the clock. Fonts will go to the free throw line, and like I said, in the fourth quarter, you gotta make the free throw. Brock has been outscored 33 to 16 here in the second half.
First one is good. I wonder if Brockton is going to go to a full court press here, down by seven at this point, if Marquez can make this shot and make it a two possession. And second free throw is good. It looks like they're going to do that. Put a little pressure on the Falcons.
almost had to steal it'll be falcons ball surprise procter to go to that earlier
Wow, upright here. Desire gave him an elbow and they're gonna call a defensive foul. Number four initiated the contact. And you can see on the replay, tough break for the Boxers.
And I noticed this Cambridge team, they're all good free throw shooters. Yeah, good shooters, good ball handlers. Very good team, very impressive, Cambridge Falcons. Ah, you chased them off. Gotta make this.
And in a case like that, if you're the offense that's shooting at three and you're down by six, seven points, you gotta follow your shot. You have to. I mean, they're in desperate times right now. All right, Brockton will inbound the ball. That's Fonts. That's a push. Freshman will go to the line. Peltrick will go to the free throw line.
So, the freshman will shoot bonus. So, if he makes the first free throw tip, he'll get another one. A stroke by the freshman.
So it's automatic two at the free throw line for the freshman. And he makes the throw. Beautiful stroke. Brocker gonna come with the full court press here. It's gonna be a foul on Cambridge. And Brocker should go to the line.
beat a freshman again in Brockton. He was hammered underneath. Yeah, see the replay here. Wow. The freshman's gonna go to the other end to cut it to a one possession. These are two big free throws coming up. This game is not over, ladies and gentlemen. You see on that play, uncharacteristically, Moses, I felt like he should've pulled that ball out, up five. Right, right, right. He said he goes to the hoop and take
Reckless shot and Brockton able to get the rebound and as you say, Beltrop gets hammered. Gets a chance to go to line for two big free throws here for the boxers. And they're going to give it to Fonts. So Fonts will shoot the free throws.
actually it was Forts who went to the line, I'm sorry and misses the free throw, that's huge. Yeah, Forts gotta make these free throws. There he goes. So it's a four point lead with about a minute to go in this ball game. Brockton applying pressure in the backcourt.
and the shot is good. Yeah, the problem there, if you're gonna foul him, you gotta foul him. You can't give him the continuation. And now, that's a big hoop right there, and he has a chance to put it to a three possession game. Brockton has his backs really against the wall right now. Again, missed free throws. This is Correa at the free throw line. Who's a solid free throw shooter, by the way. He's been outstanding tonight. Underneath, a lot of boards, Correa.
Big for Cambridge. Yeah, I'm not sure how many shots he made. Oh, you jinxed him. But he's got a number of quiet points. Foxes stop and pop. No good. Moses. Falcons. Foxes got a foul here, they do.
With 28 seconds left. And I don't understand. I didn't know a coach can run out on the court like this. Yeah, why is he out on the court like this? Wow. I did not know a coach can run out on half court in the middle of a play. Right after the whistle was blown, he's out on half court. The rules have changed, I think. But he's not happy with something.
Coach wants to come and sit down where we're at. He's not happy. You know, his adrenaline is up high. I think he's mad at his team. He is. Because they weren't patient. Hold the ball. I think that's what he's referring to. And that's OK, right? Yes. He's mad at his team, but can't run out of court, Coach Rodriguez.
Boxer's gotta get a quick two. Lambert, no good. They need that one to fall. 10 seconds on the clock. Africo will go to the free throw line. And unfortunately it looks like Boxer's gonna come short.
but not without a great effort. And I'll tell you something right now, Miles. Get these young boxers now, because going further, they're going to be a problem. You know? They're a very young team. Yes. Very young. And have fun with them now, because going towards the future, this is going to be a very good group for these young boxers.
The softbore, shoot two. Shoot crowdside to foul out now. And he makes his free throw attempt. First free throw attempt. 10.8 on the clock. Foxes with a gutty effort trying to upset these
Cambridge Ranch Falcons. And Coach Rodriguez will call a time out. He doesn't want to see no mistakes here, no turnovers like a good coach would do. Let's get out of here with a victory. No mistakes here with 10 seconds.
Cambridge is going to walk out of here with a victory, but they know. It was a tough victory. This is a tough one. Very tough. They didn't expect this. Yeah, Brockton really gave them a run for their money. And you look at the Brockton, like I stated earlier, Miles, a lot, a lot of other classmates, freshmen, sophomores.
It's like, it's a young team. Young team going up against a veteran team. This Cambridge Falcon team, veterans, all juniors and seniors. The second half wasn't great for Brockton, but it wasn't that bad either. It was a step in the right direction, considering how the other second halves have gone in the previous three years. They're young. They're going to learn. They're going to get better. And this is a good group for Brockton going forward.
Yeah, man. A lot of these Brockton fans are pretty sure it would be a different game. They're saying it would be a different game if we had different referees as well. The referees kind of let this game get out of control a little bit because of their calls and non-calls. And they almost lost it. But Cambridge benefited from the referees. Yes, sir.
tonight. So it's going to be Cambridge ball. 68-63. Quick foul by Brogdon.
It's about making free throws right about making these free throws for the Cambridge Falcons done an excellent job all all game making their free throws I Think they've only missed a couple Coach Rodriguez a geo they call him coach geo Excellent coach good good staff. He has here for the Falcons in out. They're gonna be a
Good team going forward here in 2025. Ferman, a junior at the free throw line, misses his first free throw attempt. Oh, misses both, gotta go here, gotta go. Cody! Good! Wow! And now!
Wait, the whistle blew. Yeah, hold the brakes here. Hold the brakes here because... Are they going to back that time up or no? They're going to have to back up some time here. That's what I thought. Three seconds. They're going to give him four seconds? They're going to give him four seconds and hold the brakes here because with that shot by Cody, this game is not over, ladies and gentlemen. It's going to be four point seconds and Brock is going to have to foul.
And obviously, if Cambridge hits both free throws, it's probably a wrap, right? But if they miss one, if they're Cambridge, do you foul? Right. Let's see what happens here. Brockton has made it very, very interesting in these last seconds of this ball. Last 10 seconds, boxers have not given up.
And I'm pretty sure Coach DeBaros is saying, okay, look, we're gonna have to foul as quickly as possible. Try to force the turnover off the inbound, maybe a five second call. We get that, we're talking about possibly winning this game, right? And then if you do foul, if they hit one out of two, you gotta have a set play off the possible missed shot or even the inbound. Yeah, great job by Cody Lambert, the junior,
with ice water in his vein. What a big shot, huh? That was a big shot. That was a big boy shot right there. So the inbound right now is very crucial. I do not think, I believe Cambridge might have one timeout left. That's what the scoreboard says. So let's see. This inbound is very crucial here. And Brockton knows that. They sent extra defenders in there. Yep, gonna have to foul right away.
Coach again is on the court. It's a foul and a... They only lose a couple seconds there. Maria throwing elbows out there. Right. He knows he was gonna get smothered.
Big inbound that time by Cambridge. Didn't look good, but they was able to do that. And Carrera going to the line for two big shots. He hits two, it's probably game. All he needs to do is miss one. And the crowd is into it. Boxes have to block out. Ask the box out is correct.
misses it. And Coach Barrow, he doesn't have any more timeouts. Nope. So I hope his players know. So no timeouts for Brockton and I'm pretty sure he explained that during the huddle. So here we go. Gotta get a chance to inbound it here. They're probably gonna foul.
Off the backboard by Florence, nearly setting this game.
If he would have hit that, they would have won that. Actually, they didn't count the extra point, there was 69 to 66. Wow, what an exciting game, Orlando. The boxers gave the Falcons a run for their money. They did a couple of counter punches in that last minute or so to bring this game back to 2 point lead, 3 point lead.
What do you say about it? Again, a young team never giving up, and this is what you want. But again, we have to refer to the second half, because Brock had a nine-point lead going into the second half, and also had a three-point lead to stop the fourth quarter. But I like the fight by the young team. By the young team, they did a good job
They're playing a veteran team and they did the best they could.
Again, hats off to the Boxers this evening for giving Cambridge a run for their money. Your last thoughts? Yeah, I think you basically said it all, man. It's going to be exciting to watch the Boxers going further with this young team. And I feel like this is the team that's going to get better. And hopefully, it's this year. And we make a mark in building towards the future, considering what happened last year, Miles. And while we have, we'd like to thank our cameraman, Curtis Reese, for doing an excellent job
Mike Simmons, our producer, Mike the Postman Simmons. Yes, sir. Giving us great replays. And Orlando, appreciate you, bro. Yes, sir. All right. We'll see you next time. Have a good night. Happy New Year, ladies and gentlemen. Happy New Year, everybody.