Our next speaker is Mike Gammarello.
He lives in the district, he's a teacher, and he and Anna live together in a housing co-op for some time.
He's going to give you some thoughts about Anna and why he's so excited about this campaign.
Thank you everyone for being here.
Congrats Anna.
Alright, the first time we met, instead of a handshake, Anna gave me a comforting hug.
From then on, I knew she was going to be a loving, caring, and compassionate person in my life.
I lived with Anna and her partner for many, many years, and life when he came into this world.
And when you look at someone, you get to see them at their best.
You get to see them at their worst.
And because of that, I would say I'm someone that knows Anna very well.
And I'm here to say that Anna is really good people, and I live for her.
My partner and I live in the district.
I'm a teacher, and when I got my teaching job, Anna sat down with me and helped me with my cover letter and resume.
And I know Anna will fight for me because she already has.
And I know Anna will fight for our district because I can see it in what she does every day.
I can't wait to see the changes she will bring.