We're currently live on YouTube and I'm going to record to the Zoom cloud so that we also have the recording there as well.
I am now going to start to share my screen after I give my introduction.
So my name, for those of you who don't know, is Peter Cushing.
I am the Assistant Superintendent for Secondary Education in Medford.
Right now, just so you know, the PJC Mac Monitor computer is actually a Macintosh computer I have right behind me, where when I share my screen, I wanna make sure that everybody can see what I intend for you to see, which is,
the names of the school and the random number generator, and then you'll be able to see the cut and paste in.
And I want to make sure that that is recorded for posterity.
I also have on the call under the Medford Public Schools, the camera was just turned on, are both Lisa and Susie.
They have co-hosting rights to this, so they will be able to let everybody in as time goes.
While the chat is available and people have the opportunity to unmute, this is not an open public meeting or anything like that.
This is simply a selection.
So there should not be any conversation or anything like that, under my understanding.
I only see myself as a tool to carry this out.
And I guess you could use tool in multiple facets there.
I appreciate all of your patience and your understanding.
And Josie, I hope you're not missing too much class right now.
So you can smile on that one as a former middle school principal.
All right.
So I'm going to share my screen, which will be screen one.
I work on a two screen monitor setup and
All right, good.
It looks like we are seeing what we are we are needing to see.
So I'm going to do a random dot org sequence.
And so the sequence boundaries you'll notice here are the names.
What I did was I simply added an ID number because Microsoft Excel does the row number one.
And so I simply started the numbering
here and carry down through 23.
So Josie Dufour is number 23, Brie Brothers is number one, and we will go with that.
The names are randomly in there, as far as I can tell, based on there's no alphabetization, so these numbers are somewhat random.
So we will pull that down for a second.
And then I will set the parameters, the smallest value of one and the highest value of 23.
I'm going to leave it in one column just because that will be easier for pasting when we start going through this.
So there will be some clicking back and forth because of this.
and I'm going to do the get sequence at this time, and we'll get the first sequence.
I will then copy down five, Control X, and then paste in Control V, right?
So those are the numbers for the Amelia Earhart School.
I'm simply looking at the monitors to see if anyone is flagging me.
For seeing an error, not seeing any, I will go with that.
Wait a second.
So immediately I have to start over.
I apologize.
I must have clicked something there.
So I will just click again and I will copy down those five, Control X. I wanna make sure that that is there so everyone can see.
And then control V. Control X. Control V. My copying does not seem to be working.
These are those embarrassing moments of technology.
So quite frankly, what we're gonna do is, not that, we're gonna simply go,
I appreciate your patience, but we will go 11, 9, 21, 16, 7.
And then we will go to the next.
which will be 18, 10, 18, 10, 14, three, 22.
Then we will go five, 15,
1323 and to go 620 17 or all.
Then we will go 8, 19, 1, 8, 19, 1.
And then we will, again, I love the exclamation point.
Here we go.
And the random number generator has not picked up the two.
So we will simply start at number 18, number seven.
15, five, 10, 15, five, 10, 11, and 16.
We will go eight, 20, three, one.
And six, 23, two, 12.
Hi, you skipped a number.
Oh, I did.
Thank you for picking it up.
Which one did I skip?
I believe it was number 13.
Between 11 and 16, there's a 13.
All right.
Thank you very much.
I apologize.
And that would simply be 13 there.
That's a great pickup.
And thank you.
I don't know who's speaking, but I greatly appreciate it.
No worries.
And I'm going to put a 16 right there and I'm going to move six here.
Six there.
Six, one, two, three, four, five.
All right, there we go.
All right, so 17 was the last number.
So then I go 19.
14.
Sorry, again, I'm sorry.
On row eight now, you have that extra six.
I have the extra six.
All right.
Good pick up.
I love the team support.
If you can't tell, I'm sweating.
I should have worn a degree today.
All right.
We're here for you.
Here we go.
All right.
So I'm going to be 17 and then 19, 19.
I'm not sure why my cut and paste is not working, but you guys saw multiple times.
14, 21, 22, and 4.
All right.
Let's just recheck this sequence real quick with number nine.
So nine, four, 22, 21, 14, 19, 17, 12, two, 23, six, one, three, 20, eight, 16, 13, 11, 10, five,
15, seven, and 18.
So that sequence looks complete.
I will now click the again.
All right.
And 21, five, four, and 20.
And then three,
18, 13, 11, and seven.
As I head to the next line, perhaps it was my Triskaidekaphobia with 13 in the last sequence.
I apologize again.
All right, so numbers six, 22,
17, six, 22, 17, two, 14, and then 10, 23, nine, one, 19,
15, eight, 16, 12.
I'm gonna regenerate.
So number six, and then five, 11, five,
eight, 14, nine, 22, 23, 20, three, and 18, and then 13,
16, seven, 10, and two.
One, 19, four, 15, 21,
12 and 17.
I'll now regenerate.
As I do that, I will say that I wish I'd kept that eye appointment months ago.
16, seven, and 20.
17 to.
Three.
and two.
8 610 1886. 18.
15, boom.
1, 19, 9, 23, and 5.
13, 12, 4, 11, 21.
Again.
So, 22.
Three.
20.
10.
16.
Five.
Six.
17. 21.
13, two, one, 14, 11, 18, 15, 12, four, 19,
9, 7, 8.
I will regenerate.
3, 6, 12,
four, one, 19, one, two, three, four, five, yep, okay.
22, 11, 14, 15, and two, 10, seven,
17, eight, five, 15, 20, one, 16, and nine.
And then we have 18 comma,
Regenerate, we have passed halfway through.
So we have 8, 3, 7, 1.
8, 3, 7, 1.
5, 13, 15, 5.
15, 15.
11, and 22, six, 17, 21, 14.
Regenerate.
All right, so in this sequence, 21 has come up to the top.
So in order to stay with the efficacy of it, I will start at the bottom and work backwards, all right?
That seems to be the most efficient way to do that rather than regenerating again or redrawing.
So as five at the bottom, and then I will work up 16,
18, one, 15, and 11.
And then two, seven, 20, 18, nine,
10, eight, 17, 22, 19, three, 13, three, 13, 23,
six, four, 12, 21.
We'll now regenerate and start back at the top, barring any sequences in the first three numbers that cause an issue.
Seeing none, we'll go 17, seven,
18, 11, sorry, 11, two, eight, six, five, two,
nine, three, and 19, 15, 16, 15, 16, three, 13, 21, 10,
One, four, 14.
Clean break, new line.
And we'll regenerate.
Eight.
Eight, six.
16.
You typed 16 instead of six.
Oh, I did.
Thank you.
Appreciate that.
Good pickup.
8, 6, 14.
13.
16, 17, 9, 22, 16.
Three.
11.
Seven.
20 more.
15.
18.
10. 20.
19, one, 23, five, four, two.
Five, four, two.
Regenerate.
Make sure my cursor is back there this time.
23 and 12.
10, five, two.
22, 22, 21, six, four, 17, three, and one, 20, 15, 13,
Again.
One.
Nine.
16.
Seven.
Sorry, I stopped counting out loud.
15 and 17.
14, 20, 28, and then five.
23, 19, 13.
12, two, three, 10, six and seven.
21, 11, 22, 18, 11, 22.
Hi, I'm sorry, line 60 has six numbers in it.
Ah, perfect, thank you.
What's wonderful is my mess-ups will be caught forever on YouTube.
All right, so 21, 11, 22, and 18.
All right, we will regenerate.
We are almost there.
as the end of the list is now in sight.
So here, we'll start with number 14, number two, 10, seven, 15, and nine.
13 and 20, 13 and 20.
Three, 12, 22.
Four and one, four and one.
And then 21 and eight, 21 and eight.
and one last cycle for regeneration of the numbers.
23, nine, one.
23, nine, and one.
Right, so ladies and gentlemen, there are the numbers as randomly generated.
These will be all shared out with you.
They are probably already shared out with you, but they will be shared out with you momentarily.
And we will make sure that you have them.
We will also send
the numbers yep we're gonna we're gonna work to get the names out to you so that people aren't having to cross reference like and find your names and numbers so we will work on that over the next couple of hours uh for you here.
I really appreciate your patience.
I really appreciate whoever was the voice of a little bit of help um there um and while I see a hand up uh I apologize as this was just the selection.
I really can't take questions or comments.
There's an
I'm sorry, that was my hand.
Okay, I was, I was raising it to make to speak up.
And I didn't realize I could just unmute myself.
So I really appreciate you speaking up.
And I really appreciate you guys being here to observe this process.
And as I said in my email, I can't thank you enough for the support you're giving the Metro public schools in the city of Medford through this process.
With that, I'm going to end this Zoom and we will forward you all the information momentarily and the names themselves we'll have out to you this afternoon.
There are two entries on number 58.
There are two names that cannot stand.
Okay.
So I guess my question is, my question is seeing that, I apologize, Hendrik, for some reason, your volume is very low.
My suggestion would be then that where this is the second name, all right, I can cut and paste this, all right, down below in the line 67,
and simply carry on with the number generation that is still up on this screen where number one was the last number.
So then it would be 15, 16, eight, 11, and five.
Sorry, can Hendricks actually repeat what the problem is?
I couldn't hear it.
So on line 58, there are two names, all right?
It's Sagamore John School or Pawtucket School.
Okay.
And so having not seen that, I did not review the names.
I want you to know like that.
I didn't see that as my purview.
So having now seeing that and having that brought to our attention, my suggestion would be, we simply move the Pawtucket.
There are two ways we could do this.
All right.
One, I could cut line 59 through 66 and bump everything down one.
All right, and then the Pawtucket School would take that, or I simply cut the Pawtucket School.
And what I would say is, since we have assigned the numbers this far, what I think is the best is to take that out there and to put it in on line 67, all right, and to carry forward with the numbers, which are 15, 16, 8, 11, and 5.
I'm OK with that.
So 15.
I'm sorry.
15, 16, sorry.
My eyes are going a little bit on this just because.
15, 16, eight, five, and 14.
Let me just double check that.
15, 16, eight.
I'm sorry, are you still sharing your screen?
No, I stopped.
Sorry, forgot I was sharing.
Forgot I wasn't sharing anymore.
My apologies here.
share screen.
Oh, there it is.
Alright, so the last sequence was here, you'll see that I've cut Pawtucket school, I have not taken out the or up here.
I'll leave that for somebody else to make that decision.
But the number last sequence here is number one.
So 15, 16, eight, 11, and five.
We'll go here, 15, 16, eight, 11, and five.
Okay.
I appreciate that being caught before we closed out this session.
I hope there are no other issues that anybody saw.
But I will stop the screen share at this time, and these will all be shared out with you.
I believe the documents have already been shared as it's linked, but we'll make sure that we start translating these numbers into people's names, members of the committee's names, and so that those are out to you so you can start doing your research before Tuesday's meeting.
Thank you all very much for your time, your patience, and once again, your support for the errors I made along the way that comes along with being human.
I appreciate all your time and thank you.
Have a great day.