[SPEAKER_03]: Good evening, everyone.
[SPEAKER_03]: The 36th regular meeting of the Medford City Council, November 16th, 2021.
[SPEAKER_03]: Madam Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_03]: Council Bix.
[SPEAKER_03]: Present.
[SPEAKER_03]: Council Falco.
[SPEAKER_02]: Vice President Nance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Present.
[SPEAKER_02]: Council Nance.
[SPEAKER_03]: Present.
[SPEAKER_02]: Council Morales.
[SPEAKER_01]: Present.
[SPEAKER_02]: Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_00]: Present.
[SPEAKER_03]: He's on Zoom.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you hear me, Rick?
[SPEAKER_03]: Present.
[SPEAKER_03]: Seven, all present, please stand and salute the flag.
[SPEAKER_02]: I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America, and to the republic for which it stands, one nation under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hearings.
[SPEAKER_03]: 2-1-574-St.
[SPEAKER_03]: Bedford, also a public hearing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Medford City Council will hold a public hearing in the Howard F. Alton Chambers at Medford City Hall, 85 George P. Hester Drive, Bedford via Zoom on Tuesday, November 16th, 2021.
[SPEAKER_03]: A link will be posted no later than Friday, November 12th, 2021, on a petition from Mushari and Grill, Mohammed and Irina Hassanin, 321A Boston Avenue, Medford, Mass., for a special permit
[SPEAKER_03]: to amend its hours of operation in accordance with the Method Zoning Ordinance, Chapter 94, Section 94-145, to operate extended hours at its business at 321A Boston Avenue, Method, said site being located in the commercial C1 Zoning District as follows.
[SPEAKER_03]: Extended hours of operation requested, 11 p.m.
[SPEAKER_03]: to 2 a.m., seven days per week.
[SPEAKER_03]: Petition and plan may be seen at the Office of City Clerk, Room 103, Medford City Hall, Method Mass.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, well, this is a public hearing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Do we have, I see, it would be Irina, Irina?
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, could you, hold on.
[SPEAKER_03]: Could you unmute yourself, please?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, Irina's here, and Mohammed.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, this is a public hearing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is anyone here speaking in favor of that?
[SPEAKER_03]: That would be you, correct, Irina?
[SPEAKER_03]: Are you in favor?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, can we have your name and address of the record, please?
[SPEAKER_05]: Irina Shvets.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mohammad Hassani.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the address, please?
[SPEAKER_05]: 321 Boston Avenue, Medford.
[SPEAKER_05]: OK.
[SPEAKER_03]: All right, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hearing and seeing none, anyone else in favor?
[SPEAKER_03]: We'll close that part of the meeting.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is there anyone here that is opposed to the hours of operation?
[SPEAKER_03]: Hearing and seeing none, we'll close that part of the meeting.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, so, Irina, would you like to give us just a little update on your hours of operation there?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, so we've been open for the last month and we've noticed until 11, we've noticed that on the weekend days, so Thursday through Friday, there's been a demand for late night food and there's not many places open.
[SPEAKER_05]: So we wanna offer our customers a healthy food choice.
[SPEAKER_05]: So most likely we would only be open past 11 on Thursday, Friday and Saturday.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Do any of the councilors have any questions for the owners of the establishments?
[SPEAKER_03]: No questions.
[SPEAKER_03]: The chair awaits a motion.
[SPEAKER_03]: The motion by vice president for approval, seconded by councilor Beers.
[SPEAKER_03]: All those in favor.
[SPEAKER_03]: We got a roll call.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor McLeod.
[SPEAKER_03]: We have to roll call.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry everyone.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Madam Clerk, would you please call the roll?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Seven affirmative.
[SPEAKER_03]: None of the negative motion passes the career.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you very much and good luck on your new hours.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Communications from the mayor.
[SPEAKER_03]: 2, 1, 6, 1, 8, November 11, 2021, to President Caraviello and all members of the Medford City Council.
[SPEAKER_03]: Dear President Carterville and members of the City Council, on behalf of the Community Preservation Committee, I respectfully request and recommend that your Honorable body approve the following recommendation of the Community Preservation Committee.
[SPEAKER_03]: Requesting the appropriation of $120,000 from the CPA General Reserve, the Medford Fire Department for the restoration of Fire Station Engine Roof 4.
[SPEAKER_03]: The project will be tracked in the Community Preservation Fund by Category General Reserve.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you for your consideration.
[SPEAKER_03]: Consideration respectfully submitted.
[SPEAKER_03]: Breanna Lungo-Koehn.
[SPEAKER_03]: Do we have somebody from the CPA here?
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_03]: Name and address of the record please, Nina.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nina Nazarian, Interim Chief of Staff, 85 George P. Hassett Drive, Medford.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm here also with Chief Frank Gilberti and Deputy Chief John Freedman, soon to be Chief Freedman.
[SPEAKER_01]: Happy to go through this matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Community Preservation Committee Representative Chairwoman Cameron was at the Committee of the Whole meeting where we had some opportunity to discuss the
[SPEAKER_01]: project, and I don't know to what extent you, Mr. President, would like us to go through that for this evening.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know it was referred out of committee, so I look to you for further guidance.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Move to approve, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_03]: So on the motion by Vice President Nye for approval, seconded by?
[SPEAKER_03]: Second.
[SPEAKER_03]: Seconded by Councilor Biaz.
[SPEAKER_03]: Madam Clerk.
[SPEAKER_03]: As amended.
[SPEAKER_03]: Madam Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_02]: Councilor Biaz.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Falco.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, 70 affirmative, none negative, motion passes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you very much, Mr. President, members of the council, we appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Chief, and Chief DeBee.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you, Mr. President, and thank you to all the council members, much appreciated, thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you have a good Thanksgiving, Chief.
[SPEAKER_00]: And same to you and everyone in the Council of Chambers.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I echo also.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, sir.
[SPEAKER_03]: Reports of committees, 2-1-6-1-1, November 9th.
[SPEAKER_03]: Committee of the whole report.
[SPEAKER_03]: This was in regards to the CAF classification, which has been tabled for two weeks.
[SPEAKER_03]: Motion to accept.
[SPEAKER_03]: So moved.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the motion by Councilor Bears, seconded by Vice President Knight.
[SPEAKER_03]: Madam Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_02]: Councilor Bears?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Councilor Falco?
[SPEAKER_02]: Vice President Knight?
Yes.
Councilor Matz?
Councilor Morell?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
Vice President Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_03]: 7 in the affirmative.
[SPEAKER_03]: Motion passes.
[SPEAKER_03]: 2-1-6-0-0 and 2-1-6-0-1.
[SPEAKER_03]: This was for the two house visits.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, the two street visits that we did a couple of weeks ago.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is the one we did on Wednesday.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_03]: I apologize.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Motion to accept the committee report.
[SPEAKER_03]: So moved.
[SPEAKER_03]: Motion by council members to accept, seconded by councilor Falco.
[SPEAKER_03]: Madam clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, seven in the affirmative and a negative motion passes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Public participation.
[SPEAKER_03]: Would anyone like to speak in public participation?
[SPEAKER_04]: You wanna speak?
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm gonna take two.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Does anyone have anything else this evening?
[SPEAKER_03]: Records.
[SPEAKER_03]: The records were passed to...
[SPEAKER_03]: One barn burner, John, give us a barn burner.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, we didn't receive them, right.
[SPEAKER_04]: Mr. President, I did not receive the records in my package.
[SPEAKER_04]: I checked with a couple of my colleagues, they didn't either.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, so the records will be tabled for the next meeting.
[SPEAKER_04]: You get tabled for one week until I receive a hard copy, then at that point, I'd be able to- Thank you.
[SPEAKER_04]: We didn't receive a hard or soft copy of the records.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Before we adjourn, anyone have anything else to for this evening?
[SPEAKER_03]: Chair awaits a motion.
[SPEAKER_03]: Second.
[SPEAKER_03]: Motion by Vice President to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_03]: Seconded by Councilor Bears.
[SPEAKER_03]: Madam Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Seven in the affirmative, motion passes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Meeting adjourned.