Good afternoon Medford Mustang community.
So my name is Dr. Cushing and this is Suzanne Galussi.
And we are so excited that we are here today with a lottery because we have such great participation and people looking to volunteer for our reopening task force and the work groups therein.
I just want to say that we were looking for parent and caregiver voices for that to bring that perspective to this working team.
So we value that.
And for the parents and caregivers that don't get selected through this lottery process, we will be reaching out to you to get your feedback through a different means of communication.
And so we are here today.
Filming with us is our superintendent resident, Tom Malachewski.
and is Kim Miles, our District Data Specialist.
Kim does not live in Medford, and she has no stake in the game, except she wants to see the best outcome possible for our students, as does every educator in Medford.
So, Kim is going to run a random number generator to generate our lottery.
The magic will happen at the printer.
You all received an email from Dr. Cushing last night with your lottery number in the subject line.
Once Kim generates, using her platform, the numbers, Dr. Cushing will just read them out loud.
And then we will email them to you later.
We will email you later.
Normally we would have a drum roll, but the band is not in session.
And COVID.
Cue music.
Take one minute, it'll be up.
The hamster inside the computer is working hard.
And here we go.
To generate the numbers.
This is your drum roll.
extra extra sheet all right first we have number 12 number 123 number 104 number 59 number 143 122 135 106
124, 142, 133, 140, 106, 005, so that's just number five, but I want to read the leading zeros to break it up there.
Number 39, number 85, and number 89.
So again, we have 89, 85, 39, five, 106, 104,
59, 12, 123, 143, 122, 135, 124, 142, 133, and 140.
Thank you very much, everybody.
This has been Peter Cushing and Suzanne Galussi, and it's a great day to be a Mustang.
Thank you.