Let's call the meeting to order. It's 104 Wednesday, the 17th. Good afternoon, everyone. Thank you for attending.
I wish we could do this in person, but I get it. It saves on time and travel and gas, and I get it. So we'll continue operating this way. I think our secretary had informed us that it'll go until, did you say 2025, 2025, we can continue operating, or is that just by in the sky?
I believe it was 25, yeah, two years. 2025 that we can still operate this way. Wow. Okay. Well, again, thank you, everyone. Daria, I think we're going to start with the minutes, but I think they're not completed. It's not the end of the world. The May 1st was a bear. I mean, we covered a lot of ground in that hour and a half reviewing all the new ordinances. So no problem. We'll take a look at the
tonight, today's meetings and the other two meetings, and we'll vote on them in the next meeting. So don't beat yourself up, don't go crazy, okay? All right, so let's, as I said, we're gonna stay in order. So the number one on the agenda is the event on June 20th, Brian McCausland. Did I see you, Mr. McCausland? How are you? Oh, you're mute.
Good afternoon. How are you? Thank you. Good afternoon. How are you, Mr. McCrossan? Thank you. Thank you for applying for a one-day license. Your whole concept intrigues me. I looked at the layout
We were talking before and we said, this is kind of a neat concept. So can you give us a good overview of the concept and why you're looking for a one-day liquor license? So, you know, give us the lay of the land, so to speak. Absolutely, absolutely. So once again, yeah, I'm Brian McAusland. I am the owner of Event Them here in Medford.
We originated in Somerville, and we still have some significant presence there, but we really wanted to create this Event Thumb Studios concept that we've been exploring for some time. Basically, we're an event manager. We're a full scope event company. And historically, we've done a lot of events offsite, including at local restaurants, vendors, establishments, community events.
And we've been able to support a lot of nonprofits with those or those events as well. But then we kind of decided, well, you know, a lot of these events need a hub base to be curated, to kind of give people the opportunity to start somewhere. And so we wanted a large space for ourself. And so that's where we found 344 Salem Street here in Medford. And what we've kind of done is we've created multiple
areas where we can help curate local events and lift them to the point where they can be replaced in larger locations throughout the community. So we have a local art gallery, which also serves as a small event space, a middle room, which serves as an extension of that event space, but also as a workable space. So we have a lot of clients that are like, hey, we need a meeting.
where can we go, and we can host those meetings. We've added a full-on podcasting station where people can work on their art, but also be able to promote events, and a rehearsal space in our basement, which allows artists and musicians to be able to prepare for events. We do ticketing, so I've been doing ticketing since 2007, which includes, you know,
do no fees, but we watch markets for secondary market analysis, which allows us to be able to connect buyers and sellers locally without them buying tickets online from companies not even based in the state. So it keeps your taxable income within the community, but also keeps prices down. And we just started an extension of that. We are now doing, as of Eventbrite, we're doing
local ticketing as well for Taste of Somerville and the Boston Pride event on the 10th of June. So we're kind of full scope event company, and we're looking forward to be able to do some small things here. Yeah. Very nice. Like I said, this whole concept intrigued me. So Bobby, Ben, any questions on your mind?
Oh, but Brian, the one day license request, is that, do I see it says local live art show? Again, what exactly is a local live, is it an auction? Like are people? Sorry, sorry, continue. Yeah. So basically, you know, in our small event space, we want to give the opportunity for
people in the community to be able to host small events. We've been approached by some people about, you know, a birthday party, for example, and that's, you know, that's a small little thing. The event on the 20th is a local artist who actually hosts, I can actually send you, send in the chat a link here, but it's basically five local artists which paint live, and they do, every 25 minutes, people get to vote
and categorize kind of the differences in the artwork. And then at the end of it, the artwork is auctioned off. So it allows artists to be able to show their skills, but it also allows people to be able to experience art being created, you know, live. So it's an interesting event, and yeah, he's done very well with it. Good, good. Bobby, Dan, any questions from you guys?
Any thoughts? Um, Brian, yeah, I was looking at your application and just a couple of things. You sort of had a list of questions for us. Um, are these, have you had these answered or these, you know, is this. I haven't. And again, it's something I want to be conscious of the meeting in time. Um, right again. So I don't need them necessarily answered. I just want to make sure that we are clear on how we do things because we've done
doing things with the city of Boston is different than doing it with the city of Somerville. I mean, there are statewide regulations. And I just, we're not trying to be a bar here or anything. We just want to have an offering for certain events if it seems fitting to do so. Because in those cases, we can generate a better audience or not necessarily a better audience, but a better attendance. And that helps us support
the coordinator or whoever's doing the event. So again, doesn't need to be answered now, but I would like to know prior to the 20th if we are able to get the license for that day, just so do it right.
We appreciate that. They're on an event by event basis. A one day license is basically per that one day. So whatever entity you are that is providing for it, we judge it based on what is the event, what is the layout of this event, what is the purpose of it.
And then you also need to have certain things requirements such as insurance. And we I don't see that attached here, has that been given to us. I don't think so we are fully insured. So I think we're prepared up to a million so we cover the 50.
Yep. So yeah, we're fully insured here. Well, we would like a copy of that. So we know for certain for the record. So Brian, send that to Daria. Yeah.
Sorry, Ben, I didn't mean to. No, that's fine. No, that's good. And then just as far as these questions, this would not be the format to kind of get into every single one of those questions. But I think if it's a case, you know, there are reasonable questions. If you want to kind of offline email us, you know, we can, you know, try to or I don't know, Alan, how you want to address some of the questions. I mean, they're all.
Yeah, nothing's wrong with these questions. Just no, no, no. There's just a lot of them. But that's because, Brian, you hit it on the head. Every community, every local license and authority has their own little peccadillo. You know that, right? From Boston to Somerville. Yeah, yeah. So my experience with alcohol awareness is pretty extensive. I bartended for 15 years. I was a bar manager and I actually did
the VIP bar services for Boston calling for two years. And even with that, that event is a much larger event. And just the, the crossover between the VIP bartending or the limitations within that within the event is different than the general public one. So it's like, I just, you know, I just, I need to know my staff needs to know, um, you know, I am, I'm barcode and tip certified and,
yep oh that's okay yeah well I think ben's right what we can do is we can we have your email address we can we can kind of answer your your all your questions so we'll we'll get to you um Bobby any any questions concerns on your end.
Um, yeah, I did go over all of the questions and I agree with. My fellow commission is that it's going to be kind of extensive for answers, but a couple of them just for a short answer before your event is that.
As far as the catering, your last question, if you could use a licensed caterer that caters food and alcohol at any events. The answer to that is yes, you do not need to come before us as long as the caterer is licensed through the ABCC, chapter 138, section 12C.
They can come into our city, handle an event for you, and they just have to give us, the local licensing authority and the police department written notice 48 hours before. If that's the route you're going to go with this event, you don't even need anything from us.
If you're not gonna get a private caterer, then you will need the one-day license from us. As far as all the other questions, like I said, we can answer those. The food thing, that's a border health issue, but the only other thing you may wanna know is that when we issue you this one-day license, that license is to purchase your alcohol through a wholesaler only.
And as far as your cost, your price restrictions on any drinks or anything, the only thing that I can tell you for a fact is you cannot sell any alcohol below your cost.
Okay, so I don't know if there's any other restrictions to be honest with you. Um, you know, I, I would imagine you can price it any way you want, but as long as it's not below your cost, um, it's all good. Um, and yeah, I agree with, like I said, my fellow commissioners, we can, uh, we can get all these answers for you and shoot them out to you in an email. That's great. Thank you.
Right, and just, you know, it's pretty straightforward as long as you send us the insurance so we have it for our records, it'll go in the file and collect us with everybody else. And also, we ask that, it says the event concludes at 10 p.m., we ask that you kind of wean everybody off the beer and wine somewhere around maybe quarter past nine, 9.30, don't go right to 9.59, you know what I'm saying? No, we're an hour before.
So, yeah, that's kind of, we serve up to an hour prior to closing. All right, I just wanna make sure that, you know, even though the event's till 10 o'clock, you're not serving right up to the bell. Okay. Yeah, absolutely. Last thing with me too, last thing is I see the plan for the event that you provided, Brian, and it has, you know, so you're gonna be checking IDs at the front door? We always check IDs if it's,
For if there's alcohol, I've always done that, yeah. And how are you, is it a bracelet or something? We do a bracelet and a marking on the hand, but then if you buy alcohol at the actual station, we do a secondary check, typically. Unless for their first drink.
Got it. And so there's service counter and that we're assuming that that's like along that wall over there. Is that what it's saying? Is that what that means? Exactly. It's our kitchenette area. And so what we have is basically one of those those table, those counters that go down, which allows us to keep any of our offerings separate and in a controlled space. And basically that's where we'll be. You know, people want to buy a drink. That's where they come up to first remarks with a check of an ID.
And then, yeah, and then after that, you know, they don't need to be checked every time, typically, but. Okay, yeah, and that and last thing, so that's something that you'll probably be in front of us again. So that's something that we're always looking for is providing an actual diagram of the event, which you have. But making it just very clear on that diagram where the alcohol is being distributed from, like if it was an outdoor event, you know how it's sort of.
contained and that that's just like what we, you know, we look at and people are good at, you know, good about and this is professionally done or at least for the software so I mean it's, it all looks good to me. But that's something to keep in mind moving forward just kind of noting where the.
like where within that event the alcohol is. Gotcha. Yeah, it's in the kitchenette. I can modify the floor plan. Yeah, for now, I wouldn't need it modified for me. It's pretty clear for me now. But yeah, but just that's a comment.
Yeah, in Brian Ben's right, you'll probably be back for a future one day. And keep in mind that the city has a maximum of 30. So you can do, you can come to the well 30 times and then after that, it'll be no. And I hope you do, I hope you push it right to 30. So, Bobby, Ben, you wanna, if there are no other questions, you wanna make a motion to accept the one day?
Sure. I can make the motion to accept the one day license for the event on June 20th for the local live art show that is located at 344 Salem Street in Medford. With the- Insurance condition. We receive our insurance binder.
Very good. Ben, you want to second? I second that. Very good. Thank you for the motion, Bobby. Ben, all in favor of approving the one-day license for Saturday, June 20th at 344 Salem Street in Medford for the local live art show, say aye. Aye. Very good. Brian, your one-day license has been approved. Thank you for coming before this commission, and I hope it's a great time.
Hey, thank you very much and I've already reached out to our admin about the insurance. So I'll have that over to you. Is there a specific, do you want me to email that to Daria or? Yeah, please. No, send it to Daria and she'll put it in the jacket with the rest of the file. All right, great. Thank you everyone. Thank you. Good luck. Take care.
All right, let's jump to item number two, that's the city. I just wanted to let everyone know, this was a brand new concept to the city, the first one. So we do apologize that we had a number of questions and concerns and he did submit a one page with all questions and we'll get back to him on that.
I do apologize if that took a little longer for, because you might be thinking, geez, it's just a one day license request. But let's jump to the item number two in the agenda. City, Daria, who will be talking to us representing the city? Will it be you, or who will it be? Danny from the art department. Okay. Danny, unmute yourself, we can't hear you.
Can you hear me Daria? Yeah, now I can. Yeah. Hi. All right. Sorry. We're up at the pond doing some painting. So I apologize. This is Kevin from the recreation department as well. I see Kevin in the back. You're at the bath house there. I can see you guys. Yeah. We're painting our snack shack over. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So Dan, tell us about the event. I see one, two, three. I see four outdoor events at the Riverside Plaza summer concert. So give us an idea. Tell us what's going on.
Yeah, definitely. So I think we came before you guys last year for this same permit. We have four bands that are going to be performing down in Method Square. We usually get a port-a-potty set up on one side of the plaza, and then we set up a beer garden on the other side with Method Brewing Company.
I apply for the permit for them and we rope off a small section in that plaza that people are able to buy a beer at the beer tent. And we'll have signs that say like no drinking beyond this point, so on and so forth, and some staff down there.
Dan, refresh my memory, the four dates, any of those rain dates or it will be those four dates? It's four dates, four separate concerts. Okay, okay. We did this last year and it was, it went very well, it was well attended. So I, you know, it's the city. Oh, for license category, that was blank. Is it bear and wine?
Yeah, because that was left out. Okay. Sorry about that. Yeah, no, no, we're good. I don't know. I don't have any other questions. Bobby Ben anything for the city.
No, I basically had the same question Alan had that whole license information section was left blank. You know, just in the future, it asks you if you're a registered nonprofit. And that needs to be checked yes or no, because if you are a nonprofit, you can apply for all alcohol license. If you're just a if you're not a nonprofit, then you can only apply for for beer and wine. Yeah.
just that helps us out. And, uh, you know, but other than that, everything looks great. I don't have a problem with any of it.
Thank you. Yeah, I don't know. And you remember this event, and I don't, you know, I don't believe we need like the diagram, because it's the exact same event that we have had. Yeah. Yeah, it's all within the city. Yeah. Yeah. All right. Let's make a motion. Let's get this off the table. Yeah, so I'll make a motion. One other, you know, one other thing, Alan and Bobby, I was just noticing. So this event, you know, we have all
four events on this one license, and this does cut down on the paperwork. But that is a difference than before, where normally it's four different ones. So I'm going to assume that we're good to accept that as is. Yeah, you know, I think, you know, when it's when it's an
An event or it's an entity that's not the city, then I'm always a little reluctant because then they can say, if something happened unforeseen, then they still go, wow, you've already approved our license for the next one.
I think with this, with it being the city of Tucson, something unforeseen happened, I'm sure the city, the Metro Police, fire, everybody would take the proper precautions and steps to pull back on the other dates if something were to happen. So I guess what I'm saying is I'm a little more comfortable where we have the power of the city to intervene if something happened during any of these events.
Be my thought. I don't know, Bobby, am I just, am I being too Pollyanna? I don't know. No, I agree. You know, I don't have a problem with all four dates on one license. It's run by the city. We're familiar with the event. There were no issues last year. So I don't see any issues with that. Okay. All right. Then let's, like I said, let's make a motion. Yeah. Yeah.
So thanks for that. So I'll make a motion to accept the one day licenses for the dates of June 2nd, June 9th, June 16th, June 23rd for the Medford Rec for the Riverside Plaza Summer Series Concert. I second the motion. Very good. Thank you for the motion, Ben.
All in favor of approving the one-day license for June 2nd, June 9th, June 16th, and June 23rd for the Riverside Plaza summer concert series, say aye. Aye. Very good. Guys, you're all set. Yeah. Keep up the good work. Take care, Dan. See you, Kevin. Bye. Take care. Very good.
Let's see, the next item, we're going to just continue on the agenda, alteration of premises request from Oasis. Ms. Santos, are you there? I don't see you in the lineup. Oh, there you are. How are you, sir? Good, good. You're on mute.
Oh, okay. Sorry about that. It's okay. Good. Good. Um, so I know you did this last year, right? You were out in the sidewalk last year. Tell us, uh, I think I saw, uh, your requests for an additional 900 feet and another 28 chairs outside. Correct. Tell us, tell us a little about, I did Google earth and I was trying to,
Based off of your drawing, I was trying to say, well, okay, where is he? If you could give us a good picture of what you're doing and then we'll see if the other two commissions have questions for you. Okay. Yeah, this is, we've done for the, I think it's the third year. That's right. Right in front of the restaurant and there's two doors going outside. So we put a fence out there.
So it's basically the same thing as last year and the year before. So nothing has changed. So there's a wide sidewalk down over there. So I believe the space we're using is inside of our property, but it's together with the sidewalk, same sidewalk. There's four feet, you know, for pedestrian to walk by. So, and that's about it.
So I did Google Earth, I did the front of your establishment. So I see, will the chairs, they'll start, the 28 chairs will start in between the two doors, right? The two entrances. And then will they go beyond all the way to where, how far does it go? All the way to the kiosk? Or does it end before the kiosk? I think it's right before the kiosk. Okay. Yeah. Okay.
And then the Jersey barriers are still there I right the Jersey barriers are still there, the Samantha ones yeah yeah the four of them yeah yeah. And so, this is the same as it was last year in the year before same exact layout. Sorry on.
Yes, it appears so from the diagram, and I'm looking at Google Earth, the street version, and I can, this all looks familiar. This all looks familiar to me. So I don't know, Bobby, questions? I know we had talked with some of the other establishments when they're requesting outdoor dining. There was some, not confusion, but we were trying to figure out
not to step on other departments toes, you know, because this is really the the licensing commission for for alcohol, you know, and
And so, okay, we can grant you the alteration of premises. We can allow you to step outside, you know, along with ABCC, but then there are other organizations or other departments within the city that kind of oversee other parts of it. Bobby, do you mind speaking to some of that? I know you had looked up some of the rules. Do you mind kind of addressing that?
Sure, not a problem. The change or the alteration of premise form from the ABCC still needs to be filled out as it does if you were to apply for a year round impermanently. But where this is still on the emergency order, it's going to expire April of 24. 24. Yeah, next year if they don't,
Renew the emergency order you won't be able to do it unless you get a permanent alteration promise. But, you know, the city's the city of methods rules, basically the way that this works is you need to follow.
the guidelines of the alteration of premise for outdoor dining. It's listed under the City of Medford Office of Planning, Development and Sustainability. Basically, they're the ones that require
but not require. They're the ones that review all of the applications for this. And they have what they call a review committee. And they impose the conditions on each license. And upon their approval, like after you get our
alteration of premise application and they will go out and they're the ones that'll make sure everything is complete and once it's complete then they're the ones that'll approve it and send it up to the mayor's office and or the office of planning development and sustainability and they will in turn inform you that you've got the approval notice
So, I mean, we can't say, yeah, you're all set. Go ahead. All we can say is, yes, this is what you need to do if you're going to serve alcohol. This is just make sure you comply with those rules. And when the review committee inspects it, just to make sure that you have everything, you're good to go.
But they give you the word, not us. I mean, we only approve a part of it. Right. That's right. And your request is in order. Your paperwork, everything. So we see that. That's as far as we go. But Bobby is correct. It's very similar to this big project coming to Medford in the next couple of years. And the paperwork is fine.
we've approved the paperwork but now it's subject to the the other departments within the city to you know to stamp it okay and that's kind of what we're trying trying to let you know that yes we'll we can take care of that part of it but then it it falls on the other city departments okay yeah thank you so much yeah so yeah i again i you know i don't have any questions it's the third year we
You know, Mr. Santos seems to comply with the city requirements because at no time in the last three years did anybody go back and say, shut this down, so.
But, uh, I don't Bobby, uh, Ben questions. Well, because we're here and we're talking to Mr. Santos, I mean, I just, you know, about the liquor license and everything, you know, being aware of, you know, recent complaints about noise violation. Well, noise. I mean, is that something we want to, you know, bring up here, Mr. Commissioner? I don't know. Um, I know, I don't know. It's a.
If you have a question for for the Mr Santos, you know, go right ahead. I don't. Yeah, I don't object. I do. Yeah. Well, I do. So, Mr Santos, what we've been alerted to recently is Sunday nights that there's been complaints. Are you aware of those?
Yeah, basically, you know, they always say that, you know, it's from me, from my side. I don't see, because we are like on a main street. This is a busy street. There's a train station going right behind us. And Sunday we open until 10 o'clock. So at the end of the night, I have a lot of church around me.
They call for the service finish, I think nine o'clock on Sunday night. A lot of time they call us to reserve to one day, you know, come out of the church, they'll come here and have dinner. And sometimes they celebrate a birthday. It's not every week. And of course, there's a group of people, they walk from here to the parking lot in the back.
And they talk about, you know, I mean, I see now the business right near to me. They're doing the same thing. And this group of people going out there, it's not for me, but I got it. Oh, OK. Well, I mean, yeah. I mean, thanks for addressing it. I mean, yeah. I mean, church groups after, you know, I.
Right. Um, you just, here we are, we're wanting, want to let you know that we've, we've like, it's been brought to our attention. We have no idea about the details. We don't doubt anything that you said, but here we are expanding where you're allowed to serve liquor when we have those complaints. So those complaints, you know, we sort of have, we, we bear some responsibility when we allow business to expand while sort of these sort of things are brought up. So thank you for giving that explanation. I don't actually,
have anything else to even really, you know, discuss on it, but I just to make you aware that that has come before us. And of course, so you're aware that right when you have this expanded this this front area that all you know that you're still conducting your business and you know in the best way and respectful to your neighbors and
we want you to continue to have a good, you know, flourishing business, a lot of business. So we don't want there to be any problems with that. Okay. Yeah. Okay. Thank you. Very good. Bobby, any questions or concerns? Ben, thank you for that. No, I'm, uh, I'm good with it. Um, yeah. All right. So let's, let's make a motion. Um,
and we can get him moving forward and he understands that he's gonna have to work with other departments to get to the final sign off. Sure. Okay. So, yeah, I can make a motion here. Sure. So I'll make a motion to accept the alteration of premises for Oasis Brazilian restaurant at 373 Main Street
Um, as laid out in our application here and as shown on the diagram for the outdoor seating, I second the motion. Very good. Thank you, gentlemen. Um, all in favor of moving the operation of premises, um, application forward subject to, uh, you know, other city departments to sign off, uh, say I
Aye. Aye, very good. Mr. Santos, we're pushing you forward. So best of luck and I hope that you get no rain day. So far it's been really great. No rain. All right. Take care, sir. Thank you very much. Appreciate it. Thank you. Very good. Item four, application of transfer of license. Tappies.
I believe I see most of, I think I see all parties. I think I, I think I even saw the attorney counsel. How are you guys? Yeah. Can you hear me? Okay. Attorney John Meridian to Marcus law. Yeah, no, it's perfect. Perfect. Um, I'm here on behalf of Medford Cappies Inc and we're seeking approval of the transfer of the package store license, um, from Cappy's Liquors Inc over at, uh, 10 Revere beach Parkway in Medford.
This is a transfer of the license at the same location. There'll be no changes to the store footprint in the store. Hours will be 8 a.m. to 11 p.m. Monday through Saturday and 10 a.m. to 11 p.m. on Sundays. Viral Patel will be the manager of record. She is TIP certified. They're going to keep most, if not all, the current employees at the store.
And they do use an ID scanner to help combat, to help prevent underage alcohol sales. So again, this is a transfer of license in the same location in approval of Viral Patel as the manager of record. And like I mentioned, there'll be no change to the business footprint. It will remain Cappy's fine wine spirit, so there won't be no changes to anything like that. So with that, any questions the board may have for me, I'd be happy to take them.
We saw the, you know, I read through the package. I see what the rent will be. Tell me, what's the relationship between Vero Patel and Bhavan Patel? Vero is Bhavan Patel's wife. Ah, so they're spouses. Okay, okay. Yeah, I was just kind of curious because he's the manager of record now.
correct. There was a proposed manager of record. Yeah, yeah. Bob and owns other other other liquor stores and there's experience in alcohol sales. And Vera has worked in his stores too. So that's a family business. It's with with operating. Yeah, no, they, they have quite a
an impressive list of all different enterprises. So they know exactly what they're doing. I can tell. Tell me, do we know what the status of the Malden cappies is? Because I see that one says pending.
We had the transfer hearing two or three weeks ago with the city of Malden and that application is now pending with the ABCC. All the Cappy stores are being sold throughout the state to various Patel groups. And all those applications are still pending with the ABCC at the moment. I see. Okay. My other commission has any questions?
Anything catch your eye or anything you needed to address? Looks all pretty straightforward to me, Mr. Chairman. I should say, this closing won't take place until the ABCC does approve this transfer. So this will be six to eight weeks down the line is my anticipation.
Yeah, we hope that we, you know, like everybody else, oh, we have shortage of staff, you know, all that stuff. So, no, I hear you. Hey, question, how does the inventory get determined? I know I saw 250,000, is that seem to be just the general rule? And then they go, no, no, it's a little more. That's an estimate. What happens in this case is the store continues to operate in the normal course of business.
And then once we get a approval from the ABCC to go ahead and finalize the transfer, the buyer and seller will hire an inventory company to come in and take a final
A physical inventory, right? Yeah, and it's on the price on that. All right, cool. Right. I don't have any other questions. And I had a question. So so the cat currently cappies is it owned by the Patel family already? No, it's this one's owned by blue Scott, Scott Moore. Mr. Moore. Yes.
but the manager is already, it's not Bob and she's going to be the new manager. Bob and Patel is one of the shareholders of, of, uh, Medford Cappies Inc. And Beryl Patel is Bob's wife and she was the proposed manager. Once this transfer, um,
takes effect in, we'll call it two months. Yeah, yeah. Bobbin will be 50% owner. Okay. Yeah. So is that why the sale price is $10? No, the reason why is, as I mentioned, well, actually in the lease, if you look at the lease, the landlord,
currently has a right to terminate it upon a six months notice. I think they might be developing the property. So we anticipate being before the board at some point in the next year or two requesting the transfer of this license if it does go through. So they're taking over the business knowing that they are going to be having to eventually find a new location for this license.
So they're essentially taking over the inventory and running the store as it is now, this location. And then if they do get the notice to terminate the lease, we'll have to find a new spot for it. Right. They'll have to vacate and move to a new location, correct? Yep. Yeah. So because it did seem a little funny, the whole layout of the purchase price and everything. And I thought maybe it was something like that or
changing the manager for some reason, but okay. But you're the lawyer, so you're the one who would know, so. Yeah. Bobby, any questions from you? Any thoughts? No, everything looks in order as far as I can see. Yeah, the Corey reports are in there, and yeah, I'm good with what,
what's in there and, and yeah, nothing risk, nothing gain, you know, right, Attorney Meridian, it's just, we'll say, we'll say they, they, they have a good track record. They know what they're doing. You know, they've been around, I can see from all the locations they own, they've been around the block several times. So I'm sure there'll be a success like, like everything else. Very experienced and very excited to do this. Yeah, yeah.
All right, one of my fellow commissioners, if you wanna, let's push this forward by making a motion. Sure, I can make a motion to accept the application for transfer of license for Medford Cappies Inc., 10 Riviera Beach Parkway, Medford. Okay.
Um, I'll second. Second. Very good. Thank you. Thank you, gentlemen. Um, all in favor of accepting the application for transfer of license, uh, for cappies and on the fells way. Uh, say aye. Aye. Aye. Very good, Ben. Very good. Okay. You're on your way. Thank you very much. Thank you very much. All good. Accepted. Thank you guys. Okay. Good luck.
All right, so I think those were the items on the agenda. Daria, are you still with me? You've been very quiet. Yes, so we have one more one day license that was sent to us last night after hours from West Medford Community Center. And then we'll have Penny from the health department that wanted to speak to us from outreach and prevention.
Okay, so I see, somehow I had printed out two. I see one for Saturday, May 27th, and Friday, May 26th. Are these together or are these two separate ones? They sent us two, yes. That's correct. Okay, so two of them came in late yesterday. Yes. Okay. I guess we'll
We'll review these and we'll act on these today. But Daria, it's been brought to my attention that when we do stuff like that, we kind of defeat the whole public posting.
of an agenda. So I don't know, I don't ever want anyone to say, hey, look, you know, you know, they would never posted 48 hours, you shouldn't have been acting upon them. So, so I think I'm going to administer a little chairman's discretion and say, since we've, we've done these events in the past, and we know exactly where it's going to be. And
And to me, it sounds like exactly what they did the last time. I'm comfortable with that. And if I get my hand slapped because we didn't, they weren't posted 48 hours before today, then, you know, I'll take the admonishment. So I don't know, my other two commissioners, are you okay with that? Or am I, maybe I shouldn't be speaking for the two of you. What are your thoughts on that? I'm okay with that.
I'm okay with it, Mr. Chairman. Okay. All right. So, I guess, Jerry, what we should do is just make sure we don't, you know, everything that we're reviewing and voting on gets vetted for at least, you know, the allotted time. That way, no one can point fingers at us. Is that a challenge we're going to put you, hold you to?
Um, no, that's fine. I'm fine with you guys as long as, um, I'm fine with, um, um, as long as you guys to vote on it. So this way we, I can tell people that it was voted on and you need to do it unfortunately by Friday. Um, and that we cannot do last minute things because we've, you know, because we are kind of circumventing the, uh, the public posting rule. And I know everyone.
goes crazy over that. So, okay. So, Ms. Crossman, I think I see you. You're right there in the middle of the screen. How are you this afternoon? Thank you for attending. Can you give us an overview of the events on Saturday, May 27th and Friday, May 26th, please?
Sure, thank you for giving me the time to speak. I'm sorry my son. So we are doing a fundraising event that we've been planning for some time, and it will be Friday night it's kind of a weekend of events will do Friday night, a meet and greet that will have a tip certified bartender we're requesting beer and wine.
I believe the permit says five to 10 but we plan to not have people in the door until six. And then Saturday will be the same thing. Oh, excuse me Friday evening there will be finger food so there's food being served. Saturday is another evening event. We'll have a DJ will have food.
And we will have a tip certified bartender. Lisa will that also start will Saturday also started six not five. That's correct. Okay, that'll also started six so six to, did you say 10 or 11. I believe it's 10 I'm not, I don't have the paper in front of me. Okay. It says five to 11. Yeah.
Yes, 11 but not drink served until 11. Okay, cut that off. Okay. When would you cut it off? I would do it similar to I guess how maybe a restaurant or bar like 30 minutes before his last call for that last drink and have water have food have all of the things this is just
Um, you know, planning an event and just adding another piece to it. Honestly, I just plan to have the regular event, but this is a little different atmosphere. We're trying something new. Um, I apologize. I wasn't aware of the posting rule. I tried to read every detail online, that one piece. Um, so next time we will be sure to request ahead of time. Please, please.
You know, like I said, we're gonna, we'll make an exception here as long as you're aware for the next one and you'll be having others I know you, I know you, you guys constantly having events which is good. Yes, but yeah as long as we meet the deadline. Yeah, okay. I don't think this helps sway either way but I grew up in a liquor business so I respect everything you all are doing.
So I have the same care and respect for alcohol. We had to have a liquor license. You had to check IDs and all of that. So it's very serious for me as the executive who will be running the event and being here and organizing it. This is very irresponsible event. Thank you. Thanks. OK.
Usually, a couple of things. We always ask for two things. Of course, the insurance. We always want to know, geez, if somebody falls and breaks their leg, make sure they sue the right people. And we always like to see some kind of a diagram as to what the event. And it's going to be within the community center, correct?
Correct. Yeah. Okay, so it's nothing's outside like in parking or the lawn or anything like that. Daria, do we do we have a diagram on record for the West Metro Community Center? Not for these two events, no. Okay. I'm sorry, it's coming from my after school program. I apologize. Okay.
Nope, he's still mute. Cool, sorry. Yeah, you're mute. Lisa, can we ask of you a favor? We would need two more items. We're very comfortable moving forward with the one day license, but could we ask you for two things? One, the insurance liability, so we know that you have adequate insurance.
into some kind of a diagram, give us a, you know, give us a, it doesn't have to be by an architect or, you know, an engineer, but kind of give us a diagram, like a layout of where everything's going to take place. I can see the... Okay, absolutely. Okay. I think Bill has a question.
My only thought is of all the liquor licenses one days that we give, six hours is a long period of time to be serving alcohol. And from five to 11, now, I mean, I understand, so it's a fundraiser? That's correct. I'll concede to the 6 to 10, if that's acceptable.
Well, well six to 10 is really six to nine. Because we want we would like you to pull you know stop serving about at least an hour before you stop. Okay, yeah, because we don't want you serving, you know, alcohol at 959 if you know what I'm saying. Yeah, the doors won't be closed here, but the liquor will be stopped and cleaned up and taken away.
The doors, I want to give people time to use the bathrooms have water, have more time to socialize and downtime before they would get on the road. Many of them would also be walking. So, Mr. Commissioner so few days to say from six to 10. The events five to 11 but from six to 10 is when they would have a bar is that.
Yeah, yeah, time just to have an open bar or a bar going the whole time. I agree with that. Thank you. Well, I I'm all ears. I mean, if you want to do 6 to 10, but last call at 9 o'clock, so it's 3 hours. I mean, I think that may work. Lisa, you know best. I mean, you don't want to be.
you know, holding people, you know, escorting them out the door. I mean, not that you would be, but I'm just looking for the right combination. Bobby, your thoughts on that? Do you think four or five hours is too long? Do you think six to nine with the cutoff of nine o'clock? What are your thoughts? Honestly, I appreciate the feedback because this, again, will be our first foray as an event.
you know, I'm not versed in serving alcohol and having the hours. So I don't mind six to 10 or if like a seven to 10 and keep the doors open till 12 or something in that type of area. I could go earlier. I'm flexible with it, honestly. Okay. My question is, Mr. Chairman, the hours of event, that's just the overall hours of the event, not the hours they're serving liquor, correct?
Um, listen, listen, does that sound right? The original request was for the hours of the bar six to 10. I'm also thinking in line with the event. So I don't
I'll have the doors open at 5 p.m. I don't mind starting to serve till six or seven or whatever they deem, whatever the window is, whether it be three hours or four hours. I think like a six to 10, it'd be perfect. That's when you're going to be actually serving the alcohol. I'm okay with that too.
Yeah, you can open an hour or two earlier and stay open an hour or two later. But as long as the alcohol is only six to ten, that's all I think we should care about. Right, guys? Yeah. You know, it's complicated, too, because it's taking an hour on either end of five to eleven in that. And I mean, I understand if the event is going to go to, you know, eleven is what your goal is, you know, cutting it off at nine might, you know, be not what you want.
But so I'm okay with that period of time. This being your first one, you know, just you guys have all the responsibility and the tips, a tip certified, you know, server has the responsibility, people aren't over served. Correct. Right. Yeah. I appreciate the feedback. Yeah. Okay. Okay. So I think
with the restriction of the hours and then Lisa, you'll send Daria the insurance so we know that if something does happen, there's insurance in place. I'm good. I don't have any other questions. My two fellow commissioners, any more questions or do you want to make a motion? I'm good. I think we can make a motion.
Yeah, well, so do we want to have a diagram? Oh, I'm sorry. Yes, yes, yes, yes. Thank you. Lisa added a diagram to that. Yeah. Yeah, so the insurance and the diagram and then we're good. Now, the diagram we want to see is where it's like what I said, if you were hearing earlier, but it's basically where like what the event looks like. It doesn't have to be
professionally, architecturally done, and then where the alcohol is within that event and how people are carded and sometimes be indicated on that diagram, or you could tell us that, but those are the things that we are looking for.
So it's the insurance in the diagram. It shows where the alcohol is and how it's being securely distributed. Okay. You're muted, but Lisa, shake your head, you can hear us, correct? Sorry, I wanna repeat that. What the event looks like, where the alcohol is being served, how we're checking IDs and how we're preventing people from being over served. Perfect, perfect. And then the insurance and then I think we're good.
and the insurance. All right, so I can make a motion then. Okay. I'll make a motion to accept the one day license for the event on May 26th for the West Medford Community Center for their fundraiser. The event hours are five to 11 p.m., but the serving of alcohol hours we're approving would be from six to 10 p.m.
subject to them providing us a certificate of insurance that complies with our minimum protection, as well as a diagram of the event that details where the alcohol is being served and how it is being, how people are being checked for IDs when it is being served. Very good. I'll second that. Okay, good. So we'll do one at a time.
Thank you gentlemen for that. So all in favor of approving the one day license for the West Bedford Community Center for Friday, May 26, subject to the insurance certificate and a diagram showing us where the alcohol will be served and the tweaking of the hours from six to 10, say aye. All in favor.
All right, very good. Lisa, Friday, May 26 is done. And then I would surmise for Saturday, May 27, the same. Ben, do you want to? So, yeah, I'll make a motion to accept the one day license application for Saturday, May 27, serving hours of 6pm to 10pm for West Medford Community Center.
I'm subject to providing the same things for the same things for the May 26 license, which is insurance and which is diagram. And that's it. And the motion. Very good. Thank you, gentlemen, all in favor of accepting the one day license for Saturday, May 27 for the West Memphis Community Center. Say aye.
Hi. Hi. Very well. Lisa, you're all set. I hope it's a success. I hope you have a great turnout. Thank you. But the two one-day licenses have been approved. Thank you. I appreciate it. Sure. All right. Thank you. Take care. Okay. So we got through those items on the agenda. I see Penelope. How are you, Penelope?
I am so great. I'm so excited to be here. I love everything about what I was just listening to. So cool. Yeah, it's good to see you. We haven't seen you in quite a while. Well, I'm back in for so every I know everyone on the call except for you, Ben. And some of us very well. So
I am Penny Funnelly, Prevention Outreach Manager for the City of Medford. My position has changed over the years, starting with the Underage Drinking Prevention Coordinator. So in the first part of my career here in Medford, I spent most of my time thinking about alcohol access and preventing access to use. And as my career has gone, I am also in charge of outreach for people with chronic substance use disorders.
So the controlling, the over serving is really important to me and I value it and I really appreciate all that you've said so far and just that one day license. So thank you very much for paying close attention to those details. Why I'm here is, so I'm kind of back with a group from the Mystic Valley Public Health Coalition. We are working together, that's Medford, Malden, Melrose, Stoneham, Wakefield and Winchester.
We're all working together to think about how to support our young people. And one of the things that's starting to emerge again is underage drinking is emerging. Specifically, our concerns are major disruption in our teen culture and sort of negative feelings individualized. So we see that kids are starting to use substances to cope.
So we want to really get back on looking at compliance checks and education. So it's, it's sort of a couple different prongs to the approach, I would love to bring someone in to talk with the commissioners about best practices on the national, state and local level for alcohol control.
And then I would like to, alongside my colleagues at the police department, begin compliance checks on a regular cycle. So with this idea here is that ideally we would do three to four per year, and that would be, we will have funding through an opioid settlement funding. We believe that
that this is a prevention measure could be a well-oiled machine over the next 15 years where we're able to pay for the, it's a very low cost activity, but it's still a cost. So we wanna sort of reset that this is something that we wanna do, come back to you with like what our protocols are, how we will conduct these, keep you informed all along the way. In addition to informing you, we'll inform the public
And then just to say, too, that in the next probably month, we will be hosting a regional tips training and we'll be looking at frequent tips trainings for our restaurants and our retailers. And I'm not sure how much you know, but there's two different trainings for the retailer. It's a different format as it is for the restaurants. I, for many, many years, was a tips trainer.
And I am no longer certified to do that. I lost my certification and I actually lost all the time in the world to be able to do that. So I will be outsourcing that to others. But that's the idea is just to keep everybody fresh and on their toes and that we're really looking at reducing access for young people.
Very good, very good. This is a very promising three to four year is the target, the control compliance checks. Nice, nice. Because it's been a while, right? It's maybe too long. Yeah, yeah. I think the great news is that we actually for many, many years saw underage drinking rates decline and declined quite significantly. So the efforts I think that we did many years ago really did have an impact.
as a part of one part of a bigger message, right? So, but I think educating the, you know, I don't love the idea of enforcement always, because that shouldn't be our first try, but sometimes it has to happen in order to get people to really take that, you know, and we do tobacco compliance checks. It is a controlled substance. People are being fined. They are having to follow through with those fines. So why not?
why aren't we doing that with other controlled substances in our city? So let's share that up and let's keep chugging along together. But yeah, so I don't, that's my- Yeah, no, this is great. Bobby, things were going through, you know, when Ralph at the ABCC was asking if
you know, if we wanted to have training, regulating the regulators by the state, which is us, I wonder if there's a way to piggyback what Penelope is talking about and then what Ralph is talking about, or do you think that's two different areas and they might
Penelope's group might not want to hear what Ralph has to say and vice versa or. Yeah, basically, yeah, Penny would what happens is I was talking with Ralph Sacramento a couple of weeks ago and he had.
Brought up that he'd like to have regular regulated training for the commission is basically just to make us aware of certain things. A lot of questions that come up all the time. But not only that.
But after that, he liked to have license compliance training seminars, and he wants in he's the executive director of the ABCC in Massachusetts. Yeah. And he wants us to basically for that second meeting, invite city officials as yourself, the mayor.
police, fire, and as well as make it mandatory for every licensee in the city, because they need to know what's going on, and we're going to have a sign-in sheet there. This is what he's done with other cities. So when a licensee comes in, it's a mandatory meeting, they sign in, they listen to the spiel, they ask questions, do whatever, and then if there's a violation,
then they didn't come to the meeting because they're not on a sign-in sheet. Things may go a little more stringent for them versus somebody that attended the meeting and is aware of what was supposed to be going on and it was overlooked or whatever, which I think is a great idea.
I think we can all learn from it. And, you know, if we tie you in with it and stuff as well, you know, maybe we can merge the two things together or if you'd like to have your things on a separate time. Ralph seems very receptive of anything to do with, you know, compliance training. So I think it's going to be a win-win for everybody.
Yeah, I'm all in. I will follow, I will act as a task rabbit, whatever you need me to do, because we want to be in line with the ABCC. And we want the ABCC to be the authority, right? So we're just really ultimately kind of locally supporting their effort. And
You know, many years ago, we actually did have a retailer training from the ABCC, but then it wasn't mandatory. So I love I do love that. But more importantly, what I love is getting city officials to understand how critical it is to pay attention to this. Right. One of the things that I've started to notice is that there are alcoholic beverages being served at public
City based functions, I want to make sure that that is done with the utmost integrity and and and and carefulness, because that is a huge, that is a thing that we're willing to do that but how are you controlling do you have.
you know, is it controlled to a location? People aren't wandering around the event with alcoholic beverages. How are you carding? Who is getting carded? When they are looking intoxicated, what is the measures that you're taking to do that? So I have a lot of hope that we can really partner and we can get this done. And again, like I have the staff to help us do this. Good. That's great to hear. We've always been concerned about outdoor events because of the optics, especially city events. The optics can
can crucify you, so to speak. So this is great. I'm excited because we're trying to figure out how to, because Ralph has been very good. He's like, you are the regulators. You're a part of ABCC. You're a part of the state. You are our regulator. So he's trying to let us know that we need to understand chapter 138, sections 12, sections 15. So, okay.
And I've always said, you know, we love Jim Flynn. He was great, you know, but there were times when he just led and we followed. And, you know, Jim, okay, you know, you've been around the block hundreds and hundreds of times. So we, you know, we just kind of followed. But now the three of us are all kind of, hey, let's learn. And we're learning so many new things that just were old rules. And we don't understand why we were doing these rules, but we're,
we're slowly modifying and tweaking all the rules. So I'm glad that you're willing to help out and maybe we can, you know, the commission goes on hiatus on July and August. And, you know, I know no one wants to really, you know, take on any huge projects in the summer, but maybe that's the window, you know, maybe for one or two different events or seminars, I guess. Sorry, go ahead.
Oh, no. And just to echo that, I think it's good timing, too, because there's a lot of activity and, you know, new inquiries for one days and for events and for things like that. Some things that have been sort of unprecedented that, yeah, you know, frankly, we do feel like the responsibility sort of lands on us and not always people running
Well, the people running the event and you know that, you know, we want to be certain that they're doing it in a responsible way. Not that we want to like rain on their parade or not or not give them their event approvals, but that this so this is great to hear and it's great that you came on here and told us about this.
Thanks. I mean I would love if it's okay to. So, um, so the other okay so the other added piece about this is that my hope is that you're not alone that will have these other six cities and towns, really also coming up to the level that I think Medford is going to lead.
at right so that'll help that'll help with the messaging that'll help with the hopefully hopefully, but it would be great if I could come and bring my staff, as well as our, our sort of technical assistance provider.
who happened to be a staff member but now moved to the national level. She lives in Wakefield. And so I would love to have them come and just let you know a little bit more, like dig deeper into what I'm talking about. I mean, what basically you need to know from my side is I'm gonna start doing compliance checks and I'm gonna advertise tips training. I think that's the most important thing. The other pieces of like careful policy implementation and regulation,
I want to, I want you to speak to Liz Parsons, she really is on the know nationally what's happening, how people are protecting their communities in these roles. So I would love for her to also be a resource to you and anytime she'd be like, what do you think was should be there for you. So, um, that would be, that would be great if I could come back.
Very good. This is great. This was one of the pieces of the puzzle that we've been struggling with, how to put this all together. This is fantastic, Penelope. This is great. Well, again, I'm very happy to meet you, Ben. I don't know if you know, but Bobby is heart and soul, and I don't know why you're here, Brian, but Brian and I go way back. So it was a great meeting. I was like, oh, I know a lot of people. So anyway.
All right, cool. Daria, anything on the agenda that's not in writing? Anything that we should be concerned over or anything? I think that's it. Okay. All right, well then let's, someone make a motion to adjourn? Yep, I can make a motion to adjourn the licensing meeting, our May 17th meeting at 2.18 p.m.
Very good. I'll second the motion. All right, good. Well then, all in favor of adjourning and saying goodbye? Aye. All right. Good to see you guys. Brian, good luck. Penelope, good to see you as always. And my fellow commissioners, Daria, take care. We'll be talking.