Using the idea of the Mustang Way as a guide, our school aspires to create a functioning community in which all of the students and staff taking part feel productive, cared about, and most importantly, respected. This extremely crucial way of mind is imposed into the minds of each student in the community every day of the school week. The Mustang Way is the perfect way to influence the young minds of the next generation to make the right decisions and help create a new future we'd want to live in. It shows us the importance of respect, citizenship, and perseverance.
The Mustang Way. The Mustang Way. The Mustang Way. The Mustang Way is an entire mindset. The Mustang Way really begins with having respect for oneself and for others. We can apply it to pretty much anything. So be kind to your neighbors, take care of friends and anyone that you see that may be being harmed. Excellence through responsibility and respect. We will be good citizens
Not only in school, but out of school. It's striving to do your best and be your best. Working to our full potential. Just to make yourself better, to improve yourself and get better for yourself. Just being a little more mindful by being empathetic and respectful. Because that will open up doors for you in the course of your life. Doing the right thing, even when it might be the hard thing to do. Take that responsibility and that action to
You know, say, hey, that's not the right thing to do. When you see someone coming down the hallway with a lot of books, open the door for them to make their life easier. Yeah, let them sit with you at lunch. The Mustang Way is empowering everyone around us. Students thinking creatively, and they are very much invigorated and think they believe in. The way to approach life. That allows you to think outside of yourself and see how you're affecting the world around you.
is treating other people the way you would like to be treated. Being kind to other people in our community, other than being people in the school, but all around us.
The Mustang Way is about helping others, friendship, and teamwork. Setting expectations and meeting those expectations, and really allowing students to kind of grow as people, like character-wise. Self-driven, and try to make our community a better place. Like he was talking about, the A's are attitude, concentration, and effort, is what we try and bring all the time to our clubs, everything like that around the school. To be respectful to themselves, to their peers, and of course adults or their boss in the future.
It's not just about studying hard in school. It's hard work worth doing because you're making the world a better place. Key elements that it means to me is to bring your best attitude, concentration, and effort to your studies each and every day and to your life each and every day. Kind, compassionate, and think of other people's feelings. I've always seen that in Lincoln students. That is the core of the Mustang way. Make sure you do your best to be a Mustang all the way on and off the field.
Mustang way. At the Andrews Middle School, we practice it on a daily basis. It's about kindness, understanding, respect, and empathy. Having an understanding for other people who might not look like you or might not be going through the same things as you. For instance, my friend Terry here, he has had a tough life, but you know what?
Sometimes it's all about understanding what's on the inside, because isn't that what life's all about? That's what we think here at the Andrews, and that's why Terry and I always like to show the Mustang way. Hi, my name is Michael Skorka, and I'm the program coordinator for the CCSR. We hope you enjoyed today's assembly, and we want to let you know that CCSR is all about promoting kindness and empathy and building resilience in young people like yourselves.
Today, we hope you learned a little bit more about what the Mustang Way is, specifically, how to incorporate the Mustang Way in your school and in your everyday life. With that, I hope you enjoyed today's assembly, and I hope to see you real soon.