Thank you. OK, we're going to start the Medford Affordable Housing Trust Fund. Today is Wednesday, April 2nd, and I'm going to call the meeting to order for attendance. Kayla? Here. Roberta? Carrie? Carrie informed me that she will not be able to join the meeting.
Penny? Here. Lisa Sun? Here. Madam Mayor? Here. Here. And myself, Lisa, we're here. So if there are no edits to the meetings from February 5th, 2024 meeting minutes, excuse me, from February 24th,
February 5th, 2024, I'd like to request a motion to approve the minutes. I so move the motion to approve the minutes for February 5th, 2025. Second. Okay, we'll do a roll call. Kayla? Aye. Roberta? Here. Penny? Yes. Lisa? Sun? Yes.
Madam Mayor? Yes. Mayor Brianna? Yes, can you hear me? Yes, now we can, thank you. And myself, yes, Lisa. So motion approved to pass the minutes from February 1st.
Okay, we've got the next item on the agenda is funding application guidelines and frameworks. Kayla has an update for the developer's application from form based on the last board meeting. Kayla, would you like to give an update? Of course. Aditi, do you have, maybe we could start with the application package? Yeah, just a minute. Here you go.
Can everybody see my screen? Yep. Yes. Yep. So these are mostly edits that we talked about during the last meeting. Main edits will start on page three. Yes. Here we added a total row at the bottom for sources.
We made some changes of language when we talked about the targeted populations. And then if you look at the next page, the unit composition, we updated this. So now we have a total column, a 30% AMI column and lower, a 60% AMI column and lower,
80, 100, and then we just have the other with the ability for them to fill in, and then a market rate column. And then we did add, I think also I added SRO, which is single room occupancy. Below, we talked about accessible units planned by unit type, and note the affordability which we can type in period proposed.
I think those were the main changes. I think the only other changes I identified in the attachments under number three, under community need, I also included a link to Medford's comprehensive plan in addition to the housing production plan. Thank you for making those edits. I'll move approval.
Okay, and we will do a roll call for approving the funding application. Kayla? Aye. Roberta? Aye. Carrie's not here. No, Carrie's here, right? No, Carrie's not here, sorry. Penny? Yes. Lisa Sun? Yes. Madam Mayor? Yes.
and I approve motion to approve the development application. Great. And then I also put together, and I don't think this has been circulated yet, a very brief notice of funding availability.
Um, again, I tried to keep this very brief and really almost completely exclusively did not include any priorities or how we're really going to rank or decide criteria. Um, so just trying to say, yeah, this is for creation or support or preservation of affordable housing, uh, for 2025.
I also left the amount blank because, you know, we might need to talk internally if we need to hold funds for other reasons. You know, did a very brief overview of what eligible activities are. Reference the housing production plan, the comprehensive plan, and the community preservation plan. Reference the fact that the funds do include Community Preservation Act funds and would be required to comply with those requirements as well.
Didn't know if we were going to plan on having non-CPA funds for this round or if we were just going to be using our CPA funds and kind of not count on any other sources for the 2025 round. So if that's all we're going to use, we could remove that comment.
And then talk about that the affordable units created should have a use restriction that's going to continue in perpetuity. I think that's fairly the norm at this point anymore.
Maybe just stop there if there's any questions up to that point. Yeah. Minor suggestion that where it says requests will be evaluated with respect to the criteria that are consistent, we could add a sentence at the end of that paragraph stating that a affordable housing trust action plan is anticipated in the summer of 2025. Okay. Yeah, that's great. I had a question.
Because I see, and I love seeing rental assistance and direct assistance activities here, but realize we have not set up the framework for evaluating those. So I'm wondering if that is a goal to develop that and approve something like that at the next meeting. If so, I can assist with that, but otherwise I just kind of, within the scope of this, I'm just naming that I see those and we haven't set up
that part of the process yet. No, yeah, that's, that's absolutely true. I thought we should at least, I was wondering whether we should include it, because I thought, you know, depending on what we say in the action plan would probably guide if we're going to try to talk about that. But then again, this application is really just based for a specific kind of project, a specific kind of request.
I think this is a big topic that needs further discussion. Maybe for this NOFA, we want to just focus on development projects and add the potential for affordable housing programs in the future. And among our group, that's a big area for discussion.
Yeah, so then I might make the adjustments on the first paragraph where we specifically say rental assistant requests. Although I think that that could be that can encompass more than just direct assistance, but definitely in the eligible activities. Maybe reduce that to just the first pre development activities, development activities, housing preservation and improvement activities.
And then cut the last sentence, last part of that paragraph. Can we scroll down and see that? Yes, thanks. So just actually, sorry, can you go back up? I was referencing that. Yeah, that first paragraph. Thank you, sorry. Yep, it's okay.
Yeah, I'm just sorry if I could direct response through the chair. I do think it's like, there are a lot of different things like to Roberta's point, like we're learning a lot and we're about to hear a lot of the feedback that we've been getting and ideas that, you know, that we're having to respond to that feedback of what people need. And I think those, yeah, setting the structure to be able to evaluate those when we are setting up, you know, I think it's a slightly different timeline, which needs to align with the
Erika Endrijonas-Nova, COB]: Action plan I, but I speak for myself, I guess, when I say I think it's a foregone conclusion that we would. Erika Endrijonas-Nova, COB]: find help find affordable housing development projects in Medford as part of our action plan right, so I don't that I don't know why, but I feel like comfortable cutting that for this.
I just want to make sure that I heard you correctly, if you don't mind. It sounds like you are comfortable with striking anything with rental assistance, any programmatic, anything referencing programmatic.
funds in this particular NOFA because this NOFA sounds like we're really anticipating developers coming and not agencies coming to ask for funding.
It sounds that is what I am saying, based on what my understanding is, it's like we're releasing this in April with the deadline of like June 30 and just like like for a side or kind of on the topic one idea that needs to come up again. It's like support for.
aging in place, monies and like all the pieces that would need to go into thinking through how that works to get applications. And then I don't know, I feel like we're just not there yet. And so that's why I feel comfortable for this, having that more specific is what I'm saying. Perfect. Thank you. I just want to back that up by saying that the rush to get this application out is because we understand that there are
developers who are anxiously waiting for these funds to become available. And the CPC already funded housing stability programs in FY25. So the funding that's available, like the 250,000 that came to the trust is in addition to 100,000 that went to housing stability funds already this year. So I think like in the future,
It's up for discussion how we're going to arrange the relationship between the CPC and the trust with respect to housing stability programs. But for just this round, this is where we are. Yeah. Lisa would like to make a question. Do we have a date anticipated that we'll be providing a decision on the funds? I wonder if that's helpful for any developers that have
like time sensitive funding needs? Yeah. So, um, right now I don't have a specific date in mind. I did have a pretty tight deadline of saying that we wanted full applications in by June 30th. Um, and then I said just kind of a, generally we're going to review those submissions during the summer of 2025 may request additional information or presentations to the board.
And then funding decisions will be issued thereafter following a majority vote for each application. So, no, I don't. I don't have a date. I think we can certainly discuss here if we're comfortable putting a date on that. I think if memory serves correctly, and I can look back, oh, we don't have.
I think it was discussed at the last last month's meeting and matches me matches meeting. Yeah, we, we did a quick little timetable of what was going to happen. Unfortunately, I don't have my notes from that meeting, but we sketched out a timetable where if the application is coming in June.
We talked about whether or not we were gonna want the developers or the applicants to come and make a presentation to the trustees, and then whether or not we would deliberate at that meeting and then make a decision. So I think we did a timeframe, don't quote me on this, but we're looking more like in August maybe,
in June, July they come in, August probably a vote. But I think we also talked about those two months having to make special meetings because most people have, we take off the summer is my recollection. So we're talking late, talking August, September maybe.
Just to add to Nisa's comment, I think the developer who requested these funds is expecting a decision to be made by late summer, early fall. Yeah. Can I ask a question? It's my first NOFA, so I'm wondering if we need to be more specific
You know, if we think we might have another note in 2025, who knows, right. Do we need to say for like spring 2025 or like say a specific time period in the like at the top and then named in it. I'm just wondering for like that matters or if we can
I don't think it's matters, but it's helpful. That way we can keep track of the NOFRs that we send out. Great. That's helpful. And through you, I think, I mean, it says for fiscal year 2025, which of course, like opening this is reflecting monies we've gotten for fiscal year 2025. So that makes total sense. But yeah, I would love to have that specificity just for our records and quick glance to know.
that would be helpful. Thank you. Yep. Okay. So a specification that this will be our spring NOFA 2025, and then also under the overview, say specifically it'll be for the spring NOFA for fiscal year 2025, a certain amount is what we're going to allocate to this NOFA process, this first NOFA process. Yes. Okay. All right. So I've got removing the direct assistance, kind of making it specifically a,
development specific notice of funding availability, making it clear that it's our first round and that there may be other rounds, but leave that open. Yeah. Okay. Yeah. That sounds great. And then I, last thing is I put in priorities. If we're not ready, I think perfectly fine to just take it out and I'll reference the upcoming action plan as where we would list our priorities.
And just, I want to go back to Lisa's question. Lisa, did you want something in the NOFA that says anticipated decision dates? I was just thinking some developers might have time sensitive requests. So I know this is a very specific push to help one particular developer. So it might not be as
relevant. But I think if we know we're going to have a decision by early fall, maybe that is a good enough time frame to put down just fall 2020 or early fall 2025.
I just, unfortunately, I don't have my notes in front of me, but I recall at the last meeting, we did spell out exactly what the timeline was going to be. So I wonder if that is in the minutes for the last meeting, not the one that we have minutes for today. Because I just want to make sure that we actually schedule the meetings over the timeline that we need to in order to make the decision in the timeline that we
Because we kind of figured out there was exactly, we went through saying the exact same with the action plan. Like everything was like fast forward. I've got some of it. Um, and maybe we'll go through month by month, make sure that that is conforms with everyone's recollection before you move on. So this one is April. Um, it was going to be our goals and the SNOFA. Um, I've got May is talking about guidelines and procedures.
June, a draft of the action plan. And I think this is a present to the council, city council. Developer presentation. Oh, sorry, developers presentation. Yeah. And we're going to have a public meeting. Was that going to be in July? I have a July meeting. Community meeting. And so that was going to be like where we were going to take July off. We'll have a community meeting instead of taking it off. Yeah. And I think I have
July 16th as our draft date for that today. I think maybe post that, there was going to be a report to the city council on the plan plus comments from the public. And in August, it would be approving the draft plan. And I have the only note I have right now is a decision in August, which I think might be. OK, so that's the answer. We'd be making a decision, say, by September 1. Yeah, by September 1.
Okay, and I think we picked in a tentative date of August 6th. To the chair. Okay, great. Yes, can I ask a question? Is there any stuff of like, we're viewing applicants. Or is that a decision meeting? Yeah, I think there's some amount that will be decision meeting. I think that's a good question. If we should do like a subcommittee of like, a really deep dive into the application, it is going to be.
fairly dense, depending on how much of the attachments and things. Yeah, I don't think we did talk about procedures on how the applications were going to be reviewed. And I just took for granted, and maybe this is me, that trust staff would be the one reviewing the application, evaluating the application, going back to the developer if there was any missing applications. So the developer would be,
or developers, let me rephrase that, would be coming to the meeting with a complete application and a presentation that would be made and the material that we get
for that meeting decision would contain the application, it would contain the performers, it would contain a write-up from the trust staff. Sorry, Aditi, if I'm assuming an awful lot. No, no, that's fair. But given the transitions, I'm just trying to see who would be in my place, who would be reviewing these documents. And it's slightly tricky. I don't know how that's going to move forward.
It might be safe to have at least one member of the trust board take that responsibility, hopefully with staff support, but we know that somebody owns it, even if the staff support is not up to speed yet. Yeah. Agreed.
I don't think this throws off any other parts of the timeline. I do think we can clarify more of the same guidelines and procedures, but I do agree that kind of tapping someone who has that role and then, you know, that doesn't have to delay this going out, but that we figure that out in the more detailed timeline over the summer will be a step in the right direction for setting that up.
And then if I may, through the chair, I'd just like Lisa's point that we outline, even if it just says fall, when we will be awarding monies to developers, because it would be nice if we do a press release, either through the city or
and the city can support it, make sure we publicize and are transparent so everybody has, you know, the information and all developers that are gonna help with affordable housing have a shot to apply. Yeah, great, yeah. Do we wanna add for May's meeting to talk about the actual evaluation process and
who is able to assist trust staff with reviewing the application. Do we want to add that to our May's agenda? Yes. Yes. Yes. Can we add some sort of press into one of our June agenda?
I was going to say, I mean, uh, Mary, you reminded me about city support for getting the word out if they're a stick again, my 1st note, but is there a standard places? These are posted. So, just in terms of that outreach to let you know about it.
I think once we're ready to push out the application process, we can do social media, press release. It can be in the Planning, Development and Sustainability's newsletter. It can be in the city newsletter. There's a number of different avenues, depending on how far of a reach we want. Does it get posted in any newspapers?
Does Medford have a regular newspaper, like actual newspaper that would go in a public notice? Because I know that we post. Well, I think that we posted now with the summer goal in Medford. So I think, was that covered? Yeah. I was also going to suggest our stakeholder list that we included in our plan development. We can make a contact list that would include them.
I'll also say I think this is your great idea. We heard from folks who attended that meeting, how they heard from it. And I just want to say like city outreach, it sounds like turned a lot of people out for that meeting. That's where they found out about things. So thank you for that support and getting the word out and let's use them again for more things. Thank you.
Yeah, we put the last one at that meeting in a robocall too. So I'm not sure if we'd do that with this, but we will look at all avenues.
The chair may move on to the application process and schedule. I've got a couple notes in here already, but we could start looking at that. So just says this NOFA and the supporting application was distributed to the public on a certain date.
full applications to be submitted, electronic deferred, blank for the address at which they will be receiving it. And then I just say that they will be reviewing the submissions during the summer of 2025, and they request additional information or presentations. Funding decisions will be issued thereafter following a majority vote. Based on these comments, I will put in here specifically early fall 2025, or do you want to say by September 1st?
I kind of leave it a little open early fall if you don't mind. Yeah, early fall sounds like a good time just to relieve us from a little pressure and make sure we do it right. Yeah.
Um, the next paragraph was something I did see in a bunch of other NOFAs. I'm not sure it's going to be applicable here, but I thought we at least leave ourselves this room. This is to, if we need to vote to retain certain outside consultants that could provide information analysis to assist the trust and that we may, um, request reimbursement from the applicants for such costs. And then the last paragraph on the next page, um,
Again, kind of a form statement, but just talking that they're going to have to execute some sort of grant agreement with the trust. It's going to memorialize the terms and conditions of the trust funding. And I also just say that the funds may also be made available as a deferred payment loan that is secured by a mortgage and a promissory note.
We haven't talked about terms in the past. A deferred payment loan is no payments being made, but if we're doing, I've seen trusts do cashflow payments, monthly interest. Are we going to do a 0% loan? Are we going to do a low interest loan? Yeah, it's sort of, I think, should we just say maybe
may be made available by loans that are secured by, and then we'll leave that open to the next meeting. And if we're going to do the loans and mortgages, I would maybe say a recorded restriction. Yeah. Affordable housing restriction.
I just wanted to suggest that maybe we also need to add to the agenda for one of the next two meetings draft terms and conditions so that we have that ready when we are ready to award a grant. To have it reviewed by whatever
legal body we need. I guess I just was hoping to get some clarity on the turn of phrase. I know you said you saw it in some others about using outside consultants to get information. Is there a situation where we would do that before we ask the applicant for more information? I don't know.
Like without the application involved, because I don't know about like springing a bill on an applicant or something that wasn't part of the, I don't know, I just want a little more clarity on like, when it can be used or like, we want to include it. So the examples I saw, I believe were, you know, like an appraisal. So like a third party appraisal. I'm trying to think the other one. But I agree with you, I think we would always ask.
The developer first to explain any information. Okay, so this is from Wareham Affordable Housing Trust, including but not limited to cost of appraisals and the cost of an outside housing consultant reviewing an applicant's financial statements.
So I think it's just if there's this very specific thing that we as a body don't have a collective expertise in. But I think you're right, it would be a little presumptuous to just hire them without talking to them first and then billing them later for services.
One would assume that that would happen. We would hire consultants after we made the award. I think this was actually supposed to be an app, like a review of the application.
Well, through the chair, it sounds like an example you just gave, like, maybe they didn't have the expertise. So maybe a question for us is, like, do we feel like there are going to be areas in this application that we lack expertise to evaluate and would want that? Maybe I'm just kind of wondering about this turn of phrase, and it's like, it's just in there, and everyone uses it. But I'm just, like, genuinely curious if we are anticipating anything like that now that it's been brought up.
Yeah, I'm trying to think of like an example. We can't just put it in there, just to cover our examples that come up. I mean, because you could do, excuse me, I'm sorry. You could do a conditional, we could have the presentation, blah, blah, blah, do a vote on a conditional approval.
that these items, whatever the ones that we sort of flagged that we may need additional assistance, that these items, let's say a financial audit of the developer's financials, upon review of financial audits, and that way they know that it's gonna happen and it could be reimbursed. I mean, I'm just thinking of
You don't know what you don't know until you see what you have. Does that make sense? How about we could add the trust me vote after consultation with the applicant to retain certain services. So at least we're telling them that we'll give them notice before we actually hire anyone to do anything. Does that make sense? I'm not too sure. I feel like that sounds like that. Thank you.
Oh, and then my last comment here is whether it is. It is going to be required for our funds to also include a monitoring agreements. Monitoring agreements do often come with an annual compliance fee for.
you know, oversight and services that someone would have to provide in order to make sure that the units are being rented to the correct type of tenants. So it did include it. Again, saw it in a couple places. I didn't know if this is maybe something we talk about in the future, and I just maybe say we might also require a monitoring agreement in this NOFA and not say we're going to require an agreement. All right.
Go ahead. I think the regulatory agreements that the developer side will have language on doing annual monitoring process. And I do that for other inclusionary housing units across the city. So I mean, this is an option, but we would still go ahead and do the monitoring for new developments as well.
I just wanted to provide some scenarios that we could imagine. I've seen affordable housing trusts that work primarily with small developers who are not nonprofits, who don't have their, like they don't typically work with income qualified. So they would want to contract out monitoring of their units. Whereas if we're working with nonprofit developers primarily,
they probably are already have a system for managing income qualifying tenants. But if the city wanted to take on the responsibility of that monitoring, do we want that to be reimbursed? Like, should they be contracting with the city to do that, if not themselves?
Great questions. I would also say that I've seen a larger developers doing their own monitoring, but city staff is actually monitoring to make sure that they're doing it correct. Yes, that's what I meant to clarify. Yeah, right. So the way I've seen it in my experience is,
the developer is monitoring and then sending rent rolls, sending leases, or whatever the criteria is to the city, and the city is just checking and making sure that these are in fact there. I have seen language that says that they may be able to charge a fee for their service.
But I don't know what the city of Medford does and their their ability to continue monitoring. I do know from experience that when the city takes something on and as the inclusionary program.
grows and the trust fund, the trust developments, the affordable housing stock grows, then the capacity on the city, so it might, the city may have the capacity now, but they may not have the capacity in the future.
So another question is, I think the monitoring is focused on whether the tenants are qualified. Are we monitoring to ensure that the units are actually being rented out at the affordability level that they are supposed to be? That's why you asked for the rent rules. Because I'm hearing cases of affordable units escalating in rent much higher than what affordable units should be.
In my experience, what I've seen is the developer is sending everything to the staff monitoring, and it also includes a copy of the lease. It includes a copy of the rent rolls. It includes, in some cases, the copy of the rent ledgers because it's just a little bit. But yes, I would,
Aditi, you can speak to what Medford does. Yes, yes, I'm happy to share what Medford does. And like the Chair mentioned, we have a similar process. The developers, they do the initial income verification and eligibility.
And then once a year, I send out forms so that they can fill out the existing rents, lease terms, and share a sample of the lease agreement. And as I monitor, I may request more documents to see if they are income eligible and so on. And once that's done, the HUD area income limits are released, and then we have rent increase request, and I approve based on the previous information they submitted.
So the first round of reviewing is always done by the developers. So that doesn't answer the question on whether or not we want to change.
It doesn't hurt to have it in there. Because in my experience also, once you get a NOCA done, usually take that template and then update it for what you need to do. So if it's already in there, hopefully it stays in there. So city may have the capacity now, but they may not have the capacity in the future. Yes, sounds good. Thank you.
Thank you, that's great. Any addition to the Airbone Snowfire?
Mosey, I'm down to item four, the action plan working group community meetings and draft action plan. Sorry, Chair, if I may. So are we finalizing the total funding allocated for this in the next meeting? That's a good question. The money, the money.
If we're putting it out, when are we publishing this? Because right now, all we have is $250,000. Is there an expectation that there will be more than $250,000 come May?
Through the chair, the only other thing I can think of is the sale of the McCormick Ave lots, which President Behrs has been very helpful moving along. I'm going to triple check and make sure it's on next Tuesday's agenda. But I believe he is on top of that as we've been going back and forth by email. But I just don't know if that would be by May. So, and then anything coming in from Tufts wouldn't be until probably another year or two down the line.
That's all I can think of. CPA is all I can think of. And maybe the chair Cameron of the CPA commission would know if we're getting any more funding from CPA before me. Okay, we got two hands up in the room and I don't know who went first, Roberta. So a quick answer to the mayor's question and suggestion.
There is a tiny bit of funds left in the CPA right now. And at least one, if not two potential off-cycle applications are already in the ether. So there isn't much, but I think there's potentially a small amount, like maybe $50,000 that could be
that we could request if need be. And that is by the end of June. Starting July 1, there could potentially be more funding available. But what I was going to suggest is that for fiscal year 25, a minimum of $250,000 is available to fund eligible requests. Additional funds may be added before the fiscal year
before the funding is awarded in the fall? Does NOFA have to name a specific amount or can it be stated that way? I've always seen a specific amount because then you're not setting up expectations of somebody coming in with a $500,000 ask and we don't have a $500,000 ask.
Or we could say 250,000 is currently available. Additional funds may become available later this year. But if you get additional funds, don't you have to put out another RFP to make it transparent for other developers coming in? With the CPA, what we typically do is state
what the anticipated, what the estimated funding is going to be. And then when the time comes, like eight months later, when we actually award the funds, we look in the bank account and see that there's actually more available. We'll award the projects based on what's actually available, not what was estimated at the beginning of the year.
I mean, the question is, if we put this out, because we need to get it out for them to be able to fulfill it. If we put it out now, and then we get another $100,000, do we say, nope, sorry, we can't give that out because we didn't advertise it? Or can we just put it in this to say that we estimate this amount, but if we have more, we'll share?
That might be a question for legal. I'm seeing a bunch of heads nodding. I'm sorry, I think I know I would support that language if.
If we can make that change, I do think that's probably a legal question. All of the CPA funds are available for this. We don't need any portion of them for anything else. I'm just confirming that before we put all the 250 out there. Is there anything else? Okay. Because we've already made the decision that we're not really doing programmatic stuff because all the programs have really been already funded through the CPC.
I am a Boston sports fan, so I'm nervous about being too optimistic about additional funds for the end of the school year, baking that in. But if we can't have ambiguity, because I also, my father is going to be like, I do think we need to post this this month. So probably at this meeting, we need to sign off on it. So with maybe that caveat of the legal question, it could be big. Go ahead. Through the chair, if I may, so I can ask,
The legal team, if we can include a general language saying that additional funds might be available. And my second question was, in terms of the time frame, are we planning to send this out by end of April or early May?
I mean, if we send it out in May, most developers can get an application in within 30 days. Yeah. So our next meeting would be May 7. We can get the feedback from legal and have another clean version of the NOFA ready to go. And then that would be the NOFA and the application ready to be published after our next meeting.
Sounds good. Thank you. Thanks. Typical response period, like seven, six, seven weeks. In my experience. Okay, so do we need a motion to approve as the approve the NOFA as written now?
HAB-Charlotte Pitts, Moderator, She or Her HAB-Charlotte Pitts, Moderator, She or Her HAB-Charlotte Pitts, Moderator, She or Her HAB-Charlotte Pitts, Moderator, She or Her HAB-Charlotte Pitts, Moderator, She or Her HAB-Charlotte Pitts, Moderator, She or Her HAB-Charlotte Pitts, Moderator, She or Her HAB-Charlotte Pitts, Moderator, She or Her HAB-Charlotte Pitts, Moderator, She or Her HAB-Charlotte Pitts, Moderator, She or Her HAB-Charlotte Pitts, Moderator, She or Her HAB-Charlotte Pitts, Moderator, She or Her HAB-Charlotte Pitts, Moderator, She or Her HAB-Charlotte Pitts, Moderator, She or Her HAB-Charlotte Pitts, Moderator, She or Her HAB-Charlotte Pitts, Moderator, She
Do we want to put a motion on the table to approve the NOFA as written subject to legal opinion for the amount, or do we want to hold off until May? Can I make a friendly amendment that we decide who the completed application goes to? Yes, that would be appreciated. I was going to get home and see that playing and be like, oh no, I didn't ask that question.
Aditi, who at the city should receive applications on June 30th and the 9th? Could we have the general PDS email ID? It's ocd at medford-ma.gov. OK. Do we need an album?
Sorry. No, go ahead. I interrupted you. I'm sorry. And once we have the new housing planner, maybe we can include their email address and name on the application. And then do we need a physical address for the application? Because I'm just seeing this preferred, electronic is preferred. What would be the physical address? Yeah, that's room 308.
Office of Planning, Development and Sustainability, Medford City Hall. I can send those details to Kayla as well as we update the NOFA application.
I had wanted to, so we weren't quite settled on approve the NOFA and application as amended.
tonight and pending legal approval or wait to approve it in May. And the question is, how long do we want to give them to respond? So if we wait until May, then they have a shorter period of time to prepare to respond versus if this is ready to go a couple of weeks earlier,
before our next meeting, then they have a little more time. I'll move approval pending legal's opinion. I'll second. OK, roll call. Sorry. Kayla? Yes. Roberta? Yes. Penny? Yes. Lisa Sun? Yes. Madam Mayor? Yes.
And myself, yes, so motion approved to... Yeah, thank you. Except as amended, waiting for legal opinion. Okay, and now we can move to action item four. Action plan working group updates community meeting and draft action plan.
The trust held a community meeting on March 12th. Would the board like to debrief about the meeting? Would you like to debrief? Sure. I can start us off. I thought it went really well. So we had a community meeting that lasted about two hours, I think, and the great presentation for the action plan team, and then
I would say a pretty candid, like, a conversation Q and a, that kind of the conversation is built into Q and a. So we heard some great and creative ideas for some real problems people are experiencing. Um, and.
I guess I will name we have a tech issue that we want to bring that up in this context. So we did have a Zoom bombing experience of someone explicitly Zooming into the meeting. And so I just want to first off commend the staff that were supporting that meeting that really quickly dealt with it, and then kind of raise it as something to consider having protections in place for future meetings.
Um, that was the same component. I think the hybrid thing kind of work. Well, I, uh, honestly, I'm curious what the experience was and folks were online. Um, but we did get feedback from everybody. So. And a lot of survey results, which you'll hear more about, but I think that was like, in tandem with this meeting was a. A feedback route. Thank you.
Yeah, and I'd like to actually add a little bit about the zoom bomb experience and find out what does the city do when they're having hybrid meetings and, you know, whether or not do all cameras are usually shut off or is it the way that the meetings are set up? Can we get walked through that process?
Yeah, the only way to prevent that is to shut off everybody's camera and you there's also an option to mute everybody unless they're raising their hand. So we do that on the school on the school committee for school committee meetings. We actually same thing had didn't do it during MSBA meeting and we got zoom bombed as well. So I'm sure we'll change all our MSBA meetings to just
blanks, you know, no, no pictures and whether or not you want to choose to have to mute and unmute individuals as they raise their hand is is an option of each chair. So moving forward, I think even even our trust, although our trust meetings have been
All right. Publicly attended. Publicly attended, but maybe that we should do. Would we have to vote on doing something like that, keeping videos off while we are doing our public meetings? No. We can just do it, except for members of the trust. Thank you.
If I may, so Derek and I were exploring our zoom settings to see if we could turn off participants camera prior to sending the meeting invite and we didn't find that option. Our only option was to do that once the meeting has begun. So we're still exploring that option. To change the settings before we even start the meeting.
And can you answer when you're setting up the meetings for the public meetings, do we set up the meetings as a zoom meeting or zoom webinar?
It's a Zoom meeting. It's a Zoom meeting. Because I use Zoom for another public meeting that I do, and we set it up as a Zoom webinar. And then you have panelists that will automatically come on with their cameras on and whatnot. And then the members of the public are then set off on the side and their cameras in use. And you can set it that way to keep the cameras off.
But then they can't participate with the webinar? Yes, they can. Oh, they can? Okay, I thought usually webinars, I can't participate. I just kind of watch. But yeah, you can have it in the in the audience. Well, let me you can have it in the audience. And then when when they have a question, and they put their hands up, you can then call on them. Um,
but we could try it out just in case I'm misremembering. We do currently have the ability to stop people's videos and mute them and boot them if necessary from here. I might have to check this, but I don't know if our Zoom account currently has the webinar option. I'm unsure of that, but I'll look into that.
It just might be an option because if they come on with the TV and this is what happened, like they came on and immediately we had to pull everything out. And it's just, it's disruptive for everybody. And whether we have it on the monitor where the room can see it or just the people that are joining the meeting from the public hybrid.
So whatever we can do to prevent it, it would be greatly appreciated. Thank you. All right, and then for the community survey, we received nearly 70 responses. Aditi, will you share the results of the survey? Yes. Can everybody see my screen? Yes.
As our chair mentioned, we received nearly 70 responses. So this is just an overview of what the results look like. We discussed these responses with the subcommittee working group last week and are just resharing the results with the entire board. So 42.6% of the
responses said that they work in Medford. And most of the responses were from West Medford, followed by Hillside, and then South Medford, and then Wellington. And we have around
60% of the responses who said that they own their current home, and nearly 35% of the responses rent their home. Less than 5% of the responses said that they live in housing that is reserved for low and moderate income households.
Does your housing currently meet your needs? Nearly 22% of the responses said that their housing currently does not meet their needs. And some of the most common reasons were that their current home is too expensive, or their home is overcrowded, not enough bedrooms, or they would prefer to have separate housing from their current members.
Home is unsafe due to its condition, and home is not accessible to persons with disabilities. Most responses we received were from the white population, followed by Asian community, and then African-American community, and then Middle Eastern or North African community.
We received 21 responses from those whose members of their household are above the age of 65. And then we received 14 responses from those whose members of their households are below the age of 18. And then 11 responses from those whose members of their households have some kind of disability or mobility limitations.
I think the most responses that we received were from households that earn $150,000 or more, followed by $100,000 to $149,000. And then the third most responses came from households that earned between $25,000 to $49,000.
What kind of activities would you like the Affordable Housing Trust to focus on? I think the majority of them responded that the trust should be focusing on creating more affordable housing, rental housing, followed by home ownership housing, and then providing housing stability or rental assistance for tenants. And the fourth option, providing home ownership assistance for income eligible households.
Which of the following types of income-restricted affordable housing should be developed in Medford? I think most of them responded that they prefer rental affordable housing followed by accessible housing for persons with disabilities and home ownership housing. Then housing that includes two to four unit buildings.
followed by mixed housing and commercial building, and then larger multifamily buildings, and then accessory apartments or ADUs. Which of the following types of households should the city prioritize in assisting? Most responses said that people at risk of being displaced from Medford.
would be their preference, followed by people experiencing homelessness. And then the third most type of households that require assistance would be families with children in Medford schools. Or did I miss, the fourth one is seniors, yeah.
Do you know of strategies or potential funding sources that could provide financial support to the trust to address housing challenges for low-income households? These are some of the responses that we received. The most common ones were realistic transfer-free, prioritizing tax pilot funds for the Affordable Housing Trust, CPA funds, and then
increasing permitting fees that would go towards the affordable housing trust, linkage fee, condo conversion fee, increased property taxes, and sale of McCormick Avenue parcels, updating linkage fee again, CPA funds, real estate transfer fee,
It looks like real estate transfer fee, linkage fee, and then CPA funds were some of the most common responses. Those were the overall results. Does anybody have any questions or comments?
Some comments that were said in the room, not in the survey per se, were about getting creative with video and properties. I really liked it. Some people got really creative. We heard growing food hydroponically on the river and then using some
Like some other spaces that haven't been on the table in terms of publicly owned spaces that like aren't used that are underutilized and in busy areas that could be considered for housing. So I love that creative thinking. And then there were some other, you know, there was feedback on like,
People wanted to make sure they knew where to go to get the info on things that were happening. I also really liked hearing creative ideas about collaborations, like with voc tech programs, with people changing careers, refugee classes, Habitat for Humanity, Land Trust. These ideas came up to both maximize what we can do with partners. So I just wanted to name those as well. Thank you.
All right, and then we're going to move on to the action plan, unless anybody else has any questions or comments. So Roberta, will you share an updated action plan with the board for input? Sure. Maybe perhaps if Aditi, you can share the action plan. And I'm going to jump straight to page 30.
So I've made since presenting the plan, the data to the whole trust board a few months ago, I have filled in a lot of missing, filled in a lot of gaps since we had them. And so it's a much cleaner looking plan, but,
The body of the plan up until page 30 covers most of what we heard at the public meeting last month, the data presentation. There's also several pages that describe what we learned from the stakeholder workshops and the public meeting and the survey. Starting on page 30 is what I wanted to
go over with the housing trust board to make some choices together about kind of what is the heart of our mission, our goals, that's it. And so everything that I have highlighted in blue in this draft right now is for our discussion as a group.
So last week, the subcommittee met and we ironed out the draft that we see in the plan right now. But I wanted to ask for everyone's input on what is in the draft. So we drafted a mission statement for the Affordable Housing Trust, which is very simple, to create and preserve community housing.
including affordable home ownership and rental opportunities for low and moderate income residents in Medford. Perhaps having a mission statement at all is redundant and we don't need it. Or if we feel like it's helpful to include it, would we modify or add anything to this?
and opinions. We can also come back to it, maybe review more of the plan and come back. I like it, through the chair. The short but sweet one sentence covers what we're trying to do. And it guides us through what we're doing so we don't lose track as the year is going on. Great.
And then we identified some goals. These goals are drawn primarily from the afford the housing production plan.
maybe filtered through the comprehensive plan. And we boiled down what were more goals into the, the, the ones that are most relevant to the housing trust. So number one, to promote a welcoming, diverse, intergenerational and inclusive city with an ideal mix of housing choices that offer diverse options to residents with varying needs and preferences.
Second, to use financial and property resources to address local housing needs and meet production goals established in the housing production plan and to preserve the affordability of existing affordable homes.
Three, foster safe, well-designed, accessible, and sustainable housing. Integrate affordable and diverse housing options throughout the city at a scale that is compatible with the built environment. Four, expand local capacity to implement housing initiatives by building partnership with mission-driven and nonprofit developers.
And five, increase communication about housing resources across the community. Have we missed anything or overstated or have better ways of articulating these goals? We'll offer something.
would like to strike the part that says at a scale that is compatible with the built environment, which I think might have been directly pulled, but to me, I think it is both like, I don't know, I personally
This makes me think of like neighborhood character arguments that I would rather, that I don't think personally are appropriate in the affordable housing conversation. And I also think that like, I think through this new zoning process, we're both expanding our possibilities, but hearing that a lot of things have been built not to code to the state. So then, I don't know, I think maybe I will just offer it seems a little redundant that
And I would, I would hope that we strike that peace, but it's time for our debate. Yeah. Does anybody have any feelings about striking? I am in support of any. I agree. Thank you.
Through the chair, you're thinking it should more say something like integrate affordable and diverse housing options throughout the city, and then mention something about just complying with the current zoning and the new zoning that is being worked through.
I would be afraid to limit ourselves from encouraging friendly 40 bees. Yeah, sure. I think my intention was to like end a sentence that the word city and then hope that that doesn't like build in limitations like that we don't want to open but
Yeah, I mean, I agree with that suggestion. And if there were people who had a concern about the rest of the sentence, maybe it's negotiable to play with the language to make it as flexible as possible. But I would agree with ending the sentence across the city, throughout the city.
Yeah. So maybe we could move to the next, Lisa. Lisa's side. I see something about partnering with developers. Did we want to also mention working with just nonprofit organizations, so not development-driven organizations?
Or did we want to maybe expand that line item to include both developers and nonprofit organizations that work to either advocate for, connect with resources, or organize around affordable housing? Or is that not something we're looking to do as the trust? I'm not sure what.
the full scope of what we want to accomplish there. If it's just to know what others are doing and not encroach on their expertise, then we don't have to mention that in our goals. I think that's a good catch. Maybe the fix is simply to add the word organizations after mission-driven. And that captures the group that you're talking about.
As well as nonprofit developers. Yeah, I think that works. Um, through the chair earlier, Roberta, you mentioned some trust work with developers who aren't nonprofit per se. So, again, kind of in the interest of, like. I don't know if we've officially made that decision or limiting us in that way. I've just named that. Yeah, I, I think.
Mission driven developers is an umbrella. I do think calling out service organizations that we've heard about in stakeholder groups, super good catch, should definitely be baked in as partners. But just want to make sure, again, the language is expansive for our relationships that we're building. Maybe instead of nonprofit developers, we could say developers seeking to build affordable housing.
An example that I've seen before specifically was a developer, a small local developer who came forward to convert a historic house into eight units of housing with a friendly 40B of which two of the units were affordable and two of the units were handicap accessible. So that was a win-win. It wasn't 100% affordable, but it was supported by the trust and so it was
And it used a friendly 40B, so it struck all of those. And it was small in scale and historic preservation, so we would encourage that kind of creativity. One question from what Lisa said, and I think maybe I just also need clarification. The mission statement that you've laid out does seem to gear more towards
development maybe as and not to me on first reading as much to rental assistance, let's say. So I think when I read the mission statement and the goal of that seemed cohesive in that.
But if we are still trying to broaden that focus, maybe we need to broaden the mission statement to then include that in some of our goals. To me, the first mission statement, at first reading, didn't feel like rental assistance, didn't feel like housing stabilization, felt like units in my first read of it. Was that the intent or was that not the intent?
I don't know, I would translate preserve community housing as maybe not community housing, maybe preserve housing. And that way you're preserving tenancy for somebody who may be... I'm also gonna hear what you're saying.
I see preserved rental opportunities as a way of that. But I do also like maybe being explicit about the term phrase that we cut out of the first thing. So it wasn't rental assistance only, it was other forms of assistance or
including affordable home ownership and rental opportunities and other forms of assistance. Other forms of housing assistance. Other forms of housing assistance. Yeah. Thank you. Shall we move to the next?
So potential sources of funding, I added a section on Community Preservation Act funding and a conversation that I think we need to have with the Community Preservation Committee later in the summer, perhaps.
Maybe a subcommittee could meet with the community preservation committee or.
a or we could have a joint meeting of the two boards. So I've laid out a question on the page 31. The Community Preservation Committee currently distributes funds through an annual grant application process. And in FY 25, the Affordable Housing Trust received funds by applying through that process.
Moving forward, there are several options for how the Affordable Housing Trust can coordinate with the Community Preservation Committee to distribute affordable housing funds. So one is that the Affordable Housing Trust could think about what kinds of projects we want to do, how much money do we think we need for those projects, apply for the funding through the Community Preservation Committee.
That's a large output of effort on the Affordable Housing Trust's end and you lose time in the process. The second slightly less onerous method would be for the Affordable Housing Trust to just apply to the CPC like we did this year for a random amount of money and then figure out what we do with that amount of money over the next year.
The third option is that the CPC doesn't require an application from the Affordable Housing Trust, but the CPC decides annually how much money they want to give to the Affordable Housing Trust based on how much money is available in consideration of other projects that are applying for funds.
And the fourth option is that the no application from the trust is required. And the CPC budgets annually how much money they want to give to the trust. And that gives the trust the maximum reliability of a revenue stream, which enables the trust to plan in advance what types of programs we're going to run.
It's really if the CPC is going to be the source of the trust revenue, then the trust needs to collaborate with the CPC to gauge their level as a board, their level of trust in the trust to be the distributor of its affordable housing funds. So that's a conversation to be had.
And so that is something like maybe I can make a proposal to the CPC to consider these as well, just extracting what's written in this section. And besides the CPA potential revenue sources, like we can identify what are potential revenue sources and what are the barriers, what are the actions that might be needed to achieve those revenue sources.
So skip down to the next blue section, other potential sources of priority actions. And what the subcommittee identified for priority actions in this draft.
is first fund housing stability programs. And does the Medford Affordable Housing Trust take over the funding programs that receive funds directly from the CPA currently? And a big question is, do we continue to work with the same recipients who have applied directly to the CPC in the past?
Or do we put out an RFP or a NOFA to invite new organizations to request funding? So I don't know if that's a question we want to bother to try to answer tonight or to save that for a future time, given that we may want to spend more time discussing this.
but just a background of how we got to work with the organizations that are currently working with. The CPC began to have housing stability programs during the pandemic by reaching out to a number of organizations around the region who provide housing stability programs to their communities and asked that they would be willing to apply for Medford CPA funds
to run a similar program in Medford and ABCD and Housing Families were the two organizations that responded to that invitation. So it wasn't formally a NOFA, it wasn't an RFP, it was just a stakeholder invitation to apply for funding similar to how the
other CPA program funds have been applied for. And we did hear feedback during the stakeholder sessions that knowing that Medford already has a relationship working with these programs might inhibit other organizations in the region from applying for funds. So,
I think we need to consider whether we want to spread the program more thinly given our limited amount of funding so that different organizations, because people who are looking for housing aren't necessarily going to know which organization to approach to get funding in Medford. So I think it's a
strategic question of whether it's better off spreading our limited funding over different organizations or directing people to one organization to provide programs.
So that was the number one priority action. The second priority action is to build affordable housing in partnership with nonprofit mission-driven affordable housing developers, as well as Medford Housing Authority. Medford Community Land Trust, if established, would also be a potential partner.
I'd like to make a friendly amendment on that only to just to reflect what we did in our goals and take off nonprofit and put affordable housing in partnership with
mission-driven housing developers and developers with mission-driven organizations and developers seeking to build affordable housing. Third is
to support existing homeowners and first-time home buyers. And options, we could provide some examples of what potential programs could look like or leave it open-ended. Next is to advocate for affordable housing development and policies that maximize the resources available to meet the city's housing needs.
And I gave a couple of examples. We could explore and act upon funding opportunities for the trust and work with, we could strike the word nonprofit. We could work with developers to build support and help navigate the planning and approval process to build affordable housing.
So some of the ideas like real estate transfer fee are things that would require advocacy on like a state level, for example, to get past, which like, you know, advocacy is one of our, our things we can do. So does that fit? Like, does that fit here? Is that a funding opportunity? Because I got like a short list of like funding opportunity suggestions, like, there are ones that need like city council approval, there's some that need state approval. I have a couple others, but I'm just wondering if like,
Is that covered by explore and act upon funding opportunities for the trust? Okay, thank you. And a question is whether we want to expand all of these bullet points to provide more explanation of these things.
If so, maybe we could delegate writing what some of the examples might be. Or do we keep it simple? Or we have the simple version that we could put at the front of the plan, and then the more in-depth explanation can go in this section.
Except before I give my opinion, does anybody have an opinion or a thought? I think simpler at the beginning and more explanation here is my opinion, but through the chair. Thank you. I would say that as well. I feel like this is, we want to try to keep it simple. We don't want to put ourselves in a box.
Yeah, thank you. If you have a couple other bullets, I don't know if you're inviting those at this time, for priority action, something that, and I mean, maybe these are, all the bullets are discussions, I guess, of what we're putting on there, but the ability to age in place or stay in an apartment, stay in a housing situation over the course of a lifetime and funds to
rehab was placed to do that, I don't know if that... That would be a sub-bullet under support existing homeowners and first-time homebuyers. Okay, so maybe that's an example of a potential program is like, yeah, funding for rehabilitation to stay in place for whatever reasons, but like, I think accommodations for aging and access came up, like first floor bathrooms, I think that's something someone, in bedrooms, someone specifically mentioned.
I also had another funding source that I feel like I saw was budget allocations. So that is, does require someone's approval, but less of a, I mean, it is a process, but, you know, that was specifically named, I think some other trust had that as funding. City funds. Correct.
And I think that we can hold off because our timeline said that we would look at guidelines next month. So I did throw some draft guidelines in there, just an example of what it could look like. As with the mission statement,
We could leave it out altogether, or if we want to include it, I just put something down on paper for everyone to respond to, and I would take anyone's feedback. And that's why it's actually in a funny font, is so you can see that what is in that funny font is just for a potential example.
Thank you, Roberta. My vote would be to act to include them. I'm a huge fan of having everything in one place instead of having things scattered in different files. So I would vote to have the guidelines in the action plan. So that's just my opinion. Does anybody else have an opinion? So I would invite everyone to take
some time to look at what I put in as an example and offer suggestions if you have any next month. And then the goal was to be able to finalize this in the May meeting. Yeah, so the homework that I'm seeing
is to expand on the potential funding sources and provide a more expansive explanation under the actions. And then we can create the abbreviated actions as a summary up front. I have some follow up questions if we're going to be
If the goal is to get this approved, voted in May to go to the city council in June.
What it's talking about on page 31 and no, not 31. Yeah, 31. The funding sources for the CPC from the CPC and whether or not we're going to do an application on an annual basis, et cetera, et cetera.
Is that a decision that we need to be able to make before we can finalize this action plan? So there is a five-year estimate, funding estimate, that is in here, right? I think I gave a five, I didn't put it in a table.
So I gave a range of the five-year funding availability of somewhere between $350,000 to $700,000 per year, potentially, of CPA funding, pending
how the CPC wants to so the it's a good question the action plan may say this is what we anticipate for funding but we don't know exactly how much we will have but however much money we have these are our goals and the things we're going to focus on. I think like just like with the NOFA we're not going to know in advance how much we actually have available
So let me rephrase my question, because I didn't say it, Claire. On page 31, the first four steps, we have four choices on how we want to go to the CPC for funding, right? Is that a decision that has to be made on how are we going to go to the board for this action plan?
I think, so remind me, you looked at the timeline earlier, whether the June meeting was, remind me what we said we were going to do at the June meeting. Yeah, I think this was to finalize the draft.
action plan, now including guidelines, procedures, action plan, rules, guidelines, procedures, action plan, and maybe have the developer start presenting as soon as they're ready. That's all I have for June right now. So it may be possible for us to be on the May agenda.
for the CPC to have that conversation. I think that that is doable for that to be on the May. I was thinking June, but I think May might be doable. So the idea was we would go to the May CPC with maybe our preferred 1, 2, 3, 4.
advocate for 1, 2, 3, 4, whatever we've decided, and then see what their response is from CPC. Yes. And so to answer your question more specifically, the, so this meeting, we're just reviewing the draft. Next meeting, we're going to review the other items in the draft. And then the June meeting, we will have a final draft that we will, um, release in June.
for public comment.
I'm just thinking like, there's three, there's four options in the action plan for me and action plan is this is what we're going to do instead of these are our option for funding. So that's why that's where I'm stuck. Like, I'm stuck. Like, do we have to make this decision in order to in order to finalize this or or is there something in right or.
I don't have my glasses, so I can't see what it says in front of me right now, but does it say, like, these are the options that we will pursue over the next few years? These are decisions that we're going to make. Maybe that that will help me with more of an action plan that it's an action plan.
Understood. Yeah, I think that by June we'll have picked which of those four, but we won't know whether where it falls within the 350 to 700,000 range. That's a wild guess because the CPC can't commit in advance. Right. But I did want to note that on the schedule for next time is to look at the guidelines and procedures.
So I wanted to ask whether you're drafting procedures or am I? I was planning to. Good. Perfect. All right. So we'll put those two pieces together at the next. Good. I don't want to duplicate nor have each of us think the other one is going to do it. OK. All right. Thank you.
Does anybody have any other questions or comments? Aditi? Can I clarify if the board is going to vote on the four options right now before the board attends the CPC meeting next month? No, the four options are for the CPC to decide. It's the CPC's choice.
I was a question because then the Claire, I'm going to follow that up with a clarifying question. Does the board have to decide on who in the trust would go to the CPC to make a presentation to say, here's our idea as we're leaning more towards here, but we'll accept. Is that something that we need to decide tonight? It's in order for it to get onto the agenda or in May.
That would be helpful, yes. The CPC meets the second Tuesday of each month. So if we made a decision next month, it would be still in time. But if we, I mean, the question would be, if one of us attends the CPA, CPC meeting, then we don't need to post it as a
as a trust meeting, but if it's the subcommittee attending, then we would need to post the subcommittee. And if it's the full trust, then we would need to post the full trust. OK. Is that the 13th of May? It looks like so. That will factor.
Thank you. Actually, I'm really glad that you asked that question because just earlier this evening, Teresa asked if we could move up the date of that meeting. So I am incorrect that we can't make a decision in May who would attend. We have to make that decision now because the meeting will be on the 6th next month. The first Tuesday? Yeah. Thank you.
There's a school event on the set, so I won't be able to make it. I don't know if we're letting you know if we're available right now. Thank you. I was just going to say, is there anybody pitching to go to the CPC to make a presentation to them? And one, I think we probably have to pick at least one of the four that are up here to make the presentation.
I think what we want to do is give this explanation as it is to the CPC and then say the trust would really appreciate if you would choose option four because that gives the trust the best
basis, but if you have concerns, maybe we could put the options in reverse order so that we put our best foot first. And if there are concerns, then these are some compromise options. All right. So the question remains, is there anybody here who would like to make a presentation to the CPC on
May 6th. Through the chair, may I ask a question? Does it need to be a presentation or could we just write a joint letter from the Affordable Housing Trust Board requesting that, you know, and thank them in advance for considering and determining an annual percentage of revenue to be distributed to the trust?
so that we can plan accordingly. We have a lot of work that's going on, so that would obviously be the best option for us. So that night, I'm willing to deliver our message, however we determine is most appropriate. But also, if anyone else really wants to, I just am available. Madam Chair, if you prefer, defer to you. No, I would welcome.
I agree. I agree with both maybe just one person and go present the letter from the full trust board.
Yeah, well, I'm trying to think what's nimbler than pulling a letter out of this and approving like a letter, right? They've moved to make this argument with the support of the, is that a motion? With the support of the past? Or can you just say like, do you need to use the right tactic? Okay, great. Yeah.
Yeah, I would suggest the content of the letter could be to state, you know, thank the committee for the funds that were given last year. And the trust is in the process of developing an action plan to determine how to spend funds going forward. And what are some additional potential sources of revenue and.
that as part of our plan, we need to identify how we're going to work together with the CPC and offer these options that are described here. And we can also mention that as part of our action plan, we've held, we've received input from stakeholders and from members of the public through our workshop and survey and kind of what are some of the things that we found
And a rough draft mission statement and goals we could mention. And so, I mean, just maybe a two page summary of the whole plan as it is so far. And then the ask, would you be willing to commit funding for us going forward?
I saw you taking diligent notes as Roberta was giving some great feedback on what the letter could be written. I just wanna make sure that whether who's gonna write the letter and whether, Aditi, please feel free to say no, because I know you're on limited hours, but as the trust staff, were you anticipating writing the letter?
I was, yes. But given the limited hours, I'm not very sure. And I don't know what the time frame of my transition is going to be at this point. But if I have a representative from the board, I can probably work with them and then keep them updated. I would be happy to work with you to do it. Just I think we should decide which of us drafts first. So if you want to.
start a volley and then send it back or the reverse, whichever would be honest is easier. As our chair noted, was vigorously writing down these great ideas. And it was like in the room when a lot of this was drafted. So frankly, I'd be happy to throw that in and send that your way and then workshop it together. And then would, am I understanding that you'd be able to circulate it for our approval via email in advance of that meeting, since it is like right before our next meeting? Yes, I can do that.
Thank you. Thank you, Penny. Thank you, Aditi. Thank you, Roberta. All right, and I think, let's see, we have funding, item five is the funding of the trust, the McCormick Avenue parcels.
We updated the city council about the trust approval to support the sale and the transfer of the Warnick Avenue parcels subject to the city council's approval for the purpose of funding the affordable housing trust fund to establish an affordable housing linkage through a nexus study and support affordable housing developments. On March 25th, 2025, the city council discussed the matter
Aditi, would you provide a brief update about the conversation? Sure. I think mayor already updated the board earlier this evening, but yes, I was at the meeting and unfortunately the city council didn't vote on it yet. So they tabled the conversation for an upcoming city council meeting.
But the discussion revolved around selling city-owned parcels. Would that be really necessary for a one-time nexus study? But we did have support from Councillor Lemming, who
recommended that we sell the McCormick Avenue parcels, but there was no decision taken. So hopefully in the next CC meeting, there will be a motion to either approve or not. Thank you, Aditi. You're welcome.
All right. And then, Penny, would you like to lead the discussion you've already planted a seed already on this about exploring other funding sources that the city may be.
Yeah, absolutely. So I'm glad for the opportunity to have space to like brainstorm and talk about some opportunities. So first of all, this was not on my radar before this meeting, but I do think like we want to check in about that remaining CPA money. And if we want to ask for any and get in that ether of people interested in that approximately 50,000, I think that is overall here. I'd love to put that on the table.
I also, it's budget season, so I brought up that someone suggested budget allocations. We've seen some other borough housing trusts that get, for instance, recap allocations or other specific monies to them from the city. So I guess I haven't watched every budget presentation, but I'm just curious about the appetite or mechanics of that advocacy, if that would be a possibility.
that would be great. So just throwing those out and I guess the floor is open if there are other funding opportunities that we would need to make decisions about today or thoughts on those too. Over here.
Would you be willing to draft a paragraph with your ideas and share that with me? And I could incorporate some ideas about potential funding sources into the draft action plan.
I mean, I don't feel like there's any, for the potential 50,000 CPA, I would say that that is like, if there's an emergency, if we really needed 50,000, which I don't think we'd be ready to award that anyway, it's actually maybe better if the CPC holds onto that. And if there's an emergency, a developer can apply directly to the CPC right before the end of this fiscal year.
July 1, the amount of money that's available potentially increases, but then it would be preferable to wait until the application cycle. Then it's, then the question is, what is the method by which the CPC will consider how much money to award? Great. And then maybe just to context, I think this is kind of in general about funding, less than like the action plan bullets of what we're doing. So kind of like, yeah, just, I'm specifically thinking
coming in the next few months that we might need to think about. So I just want to talk about the possibility of going back to the CPC for funding. We anticipate at least one, if not two, developers coming to the table and filling out our NOFAs. $250,000 is not a lot of money when you're looking at trying to fill a gap into creating
Developing affordable housing, you're talking that's not even a unit that's not that that's like a half a unit that we would be able to fund for that. And I would imagine the gaps are pretty they're pretty substantial at the moment.
does it make sense to actually go to the board, go to the CPC now before we put out our NOFA to see if there is a possibility of putting that out? I'm really glad you asked because the CPC meeting next week is when they're going to be deciding on a budget for next year. And unlike Somerville, which usually
free programs, most of its funds to the different program area reserves. Medford has typically promised the minimum to each of the areas. Sometimes they've doubled the minimum for housing.
But doubling the minimum for housing still puts us around the $250,000, $350,000 range. And if we're hoping for more, next month's meeting would actually be an opportunity to advocate for a higher level of funding. Not next month's, next week's meeting. Next week's meeting would be to go into the CPC and say, hey, we're expecting
Yeah, so have we had an idea how much to expect? I mean, so when the CPC allocates the minimum to each program area,
That's leaving the maximum flexibility so that in the fall, should they see a big chunk coming at them for housing, they can dedicate most of their funds to that big chunk. But if they see a big chunk coming at them for another area, they have that available. It's the most flexibility. So that's why they've done it that way in the past. But if we want to advocate for them to
give housing more weight, they can do that. But if we see somebody coming to us, so if we receive multiple responses to the NOFA in September, that just barely aligns with the CPA timeline to apply for funding for next year.
So this is like what I think we need to discuss with the CPC in May is how are we going to request funding from you? No, I understand. I hear what you're saying. Thank you. And that's looking forward. I'm looking at the present and I'm looking at we've got a NOFA coming out. We're expecting something coming in.
In June, end of June, we're going to be reviewing it and come July, giving June, July, August, the possibility of the vote. If we can go in to the city, if we know 250,000.
I'll be flabbergasted if the request is less than $250,000 or their need, maybe not their request, but their need is less than 250. So we can go in like we were talking about earlier, whether or not to put in the dollar amount, would it make sense to go to the CPC now, ask for the additional, because I do recall when we gave the presentation,
around this table to the CPC, a lot of the CPC members were like, we would have funded you more there, you know, $250,000 is not a lot of money for housing. So I'm just trying to figure out like, how can we be able to really fund a development that may be coming to us sooner rather than later. So this is what I see. It's a complication is that
The trust is trying to announce in advance a commitment to how much funding is going to be available, whereas the CPC typically keeps it as flexible as possible. And when they see a large application come in, try to accommodate it. So from the CPC's perspective, why not, if you receive two requests for $250,000 each in September,
why wouldn't you just come to the CPC then and ask, put in an off-cycle application for another $250,000? So the CPC would receive an application and immediately make a decision based on its merits. They don't try to plan in advance who might apply for funding and commit to that application before it comes.
Can I ask a clarifying question? But there is still some CPC funding there. But if we requested it for something like expanding our NOFA,
just kind of spitballing, that we're like, here, we're about to put up this bid, we'd love for it to be a bit higher, like, can we have this money for that purpose? Like, is that advisable, I guess, or even like the way it works? And if so, what do we need to do now to move forward on that? Because when you're getting a developer an application, a developer is going to ask for
whatever it is that they're going to ask for. If we're putting out on our NOFA that we only have $250,000 available, they're only going to, they should only, they know what they do. What they do and what they should do is two different things. But if you're saying we've got $250,000 and they're going to come in with only a $250,000 and because you cannot,
vote to give them more than what they asked for, then we're in a pickle where they're coming in, they're asking for $250,000. We might not get any applications because the gap, like I said, I will be flabbergasted if $250,000 is enough to close that gap to be able to develop units
So if we're going with the knowledge or the assumptions that they're going to need more money, then why not ask? Because I heard there was available, I heard people are going there for there. We're going in with the intention of being able to say, we fully expect a developer to come in and they will be asking for more than we have. So we're requesting, like, is there an appetite for it?
So this is why I would love for the legal advice to say that yes, we can say we estimate that 250,000 is available right now, but we anticipate that there may be more funding available after the fiscal year than
we see what applications come in and then we go to the CPC and request the gap in funding to be able to say yes to those applications. So that would actually, in the four options, that would be option one, is that we have something specific in mind and we go and ask the CPC to fill that gap. So I guess,
I'm just thinking we're not going to get the legal answer before the next meeting. I mean, we're talking in circles. I'm sorry. Can I, as the chair, can I make a motion?
As the vice chair, do I need to recognize anything? I don't know. I'm asking for clarification. Could I get clarification on what? Oh, can you make a motion? Oh, OK. If I wanted to put something up for a vote instead of a discussion, as a chair, can I
make that motion or do I need to ask Penny to take the chair while I make the motion?
I would just to be sure. I would. All right. Penny, will you chair the rest of the meeting for me? Yes, I will. I don't think I need help with the agenda. It might not be up. But I got myself together. Okay, great. And I'm sorry, I just have to run. But thank you, everybody. If you need anything from me, just let me know. Thank you, Mayor. I would like to make a motion.
to petition the CPC for a minimum of $50,000 so we can be able to add $50,000 to our bank account. So I don't think I did that motion very clearly, but I would like to make a motion to
go to the CPC and put an application in and or a request on an additional $50,000 for our anticipated developers applications. I hear a motion from Lisa D. Do I hear a second?
All right, great. Thank you so much. So do I need to roll call? All right. Okay, great. So Kayla? Yes. Roberta? Yes. Myself? Yes. Lisa S.? Yes. Great. The mayor has left the meeting. Oh, I should notice the mayor left the meeting at 8 p.m.
And I don't know if we actually noticed when Roberta came and joined the meeting, which was, you know, at 602. Okay, so moving along with the roll call on Lisa D. Yes. Yes. So, okay. So, 5.
Yes to absent, the motion passes. Perfect, thank you. So we will work together to submit a request to the CPC for $50,000 to add to our bank account for anticipated development. Great, thank you. Thank you.
Can you chair the rest of the meeting? I just wanted to note, and I'm like texting Teresa right now as we speak as the staff person to the CPC, that their meeting is on Tuesday. So if we want to make that request, I'm speaking, I'm making a big ask of Teresa and of Aditi to turn around an application
very quickly to get onto the agenda for the April meeting, if possible. If we wait until the May meeting, then that delays are being able to put an additional amount onto the NOFA DT. Yeah, unfortunately with my limited hours this week, I'm not able to work on the application.
As DT, is there a way that we could get the application that was previously submitted to the CPC and all we have to do is tweak that application, reduce the ask, and then add a little bit of advantage saying that we are actually decreasing what we are going to be doing because we fully anticipate the need for the developer application. Is that something that you can send to us?
Yes, so I believe the CPC application was in a smart sheet format, but I do have the word format of the same and I can share that with the board. Could you do that? Thank you. And because I'm so adamant of going to the CPC, I will.
Tweak the application, I'll send it to you, and if you could send it to the trustees, and then I'll go to the CPC meeting on the 8th. It's the 8th, right? Am I getting my dates right? Yes. And present the ask, if that's okay.
Okay, I'm glad you talked about that funding. And I'm sad the mayor left for this part of the conversation, but I am curious in terms of allocations of something like free cash, if we can get some information on what is available and if that is a request that we as a trust are interested in making.
So is that a request to staff to see what's available, if there is availability of free cash? Will they call it free cash in Medford? Yes, I think some of them. I would love to talk about, yeah, on what's available and what the timeline is, if we know right now and can talk about it, and others will figure out. We'll go from here.
I'm wondering if the board can present this request before the committee of the whole or planning and permitting committee. These are two subcommittees of the city council and have a discussion there. Okay, so you would advise that bringing this issue to one of those bodies is
subcommittees. OK. And that's happening now, right? Like this month, it's getting to be about budget time, or do you know when that decision is made? I don't know yet. I'm thinking if it has to get on one of the committee's agenda, then we'd have to work faster.
have a chance to ask from the mayor? See, this is exactly the mechanic I'm not sure about. Because there have been projects that got a kind of substantial feed funding from a source like this. And just if it is available, and it's our first year, it's exciting. It could be a real, I think,
Show commitment and push us in the right direction really robustly. But again, it's like, for whatever reason, the appetite is not here that we have a lot on our plates, like, politically figuring out where we're at and what our ask is. I totally understand that, but just didn't want to leave it on the table.
Agreed. I think maybe what the path would be and maybe this is an area where you could do some advocacy to talk with the city councilor and the subcommittee and talk with the mayor individually and ask each of them if they would support a request for a substantial
contribution to the trust to capitalize them initially. And I would love a sense from others of what a reasonable ask seems like for that or just like a ballpark. And then I can do some research on what we're looking at, but. Why don't you say a million dollars? Oh my god, you're in my head.
I like it. It's clean. Great. Okay. So, just to affirm this is less an official action and request of this trust than... A sounding. Encouraging individual trust members to check in with members of these and plant that idea and encourage it. Is that what I'm hearing? Yeah.
Great. Does anyone have other funding sources for the trust that we need to discuss at this time?
I don't have, yeah, I don't have timely ideas. For McCormick, I might also, I know we went through that agenda item, but I think the previous advice of just connecting with folks and affirming its importance might be, I just, you know, to get it over that finish line. I'm curious if others have ideas of how to best support this ask, seeing as that will be on the meeting next Tuesday.
Yeah, are they still hung up on the idea that it might be developable? Or is it just they're not sure? So the PDS evaluation was that if the two sites were merged, then they are developable in terms of the zoning approval. And that would change how the land is assessed and if that's in the best interest.
for the city to transfer or convey the city-owned lots. And I think the main concern was that for a one-time nexus study, is the city prepared to sell city-owned lots? Or would there be other funding sources to fund a nexus study? So the city council was not against supporting a nexus study. They still want to do a nexus study, I believe.
But is that the best funding source is what they are wondering? Well, could we ask them for the budget allocation for the next study if they don't want to? I mean, I get their point.
but then we can't use the funds that we have currently for the next study. So without another source, we're kind of, yeah. I'm curious, do you remember what that lot would be zoned for? So how many potential housing units? Cause I do remember a counselor making the argument that like the potential for any housing is more important than like would be, would warrant holding onto it versus, so can you, do you remember? Yes. So based on the proposed zoning,
I think the parcels would be under NR1, which would allow one single family unit and an ADU. Thank you. And then, you know, I think I've heard these arguments and like, I spend a lot of time in other meetings talking about keeping public land in public hands and the importance of that. So I definitely understood those like, concerns from counselors. I think
We personally, I keep thinking about where we're at, 250,000 in the bank, we can't develop that land for affordable housing tomorrow or even in a couple of years. And if it takes significant, I don't know.
That was something turning in my head of making a point around that, of like, this will allow us to do more sooner with other things, but I'm curious of others, like, if you want to think a minute of, like, incurring someone. A question would be if instead of selling those lots for development, if they were donated to Habitat for Humanity, could Habitat for Humanity build two affordable units on that lot? And would that be a better outcome?
I would imagine the city council would be interested to hear that proposal. Yeah. So the question is whether it would be better for the city to place the buildable lot in the trust so that the trust could convey it to a nonprofit developer. Would a nonprofit developer develop one
unit of housing, plus an ADU. It would be two. It would be a single ADU. But they're not separately owned. It could be Habitat for Humanity. It may be entrusted. Again, it goes back to dollars. If you're going to put something to a nonprofit for development,
They may not be able to develop it in a timely manner. Like, it's not going to it's not going to be instant gratification where if you sold, there'll be instant gratification. But I like the, I like the idea of the habitat. I guess. But you just, you just.
Are you yourself kind of a working group and there are a lot of city on parcels that we're looking at that are so much more suited and ready for this sort of development. And so I think, like.
We want the money, right? That's like, we asked for them to approve it for this reason, for the money. And so that's, I'm trying to, I kind of was raising it as like, kind of a temporal outlook of the, like, capacity outlook of, like, practicality, how many actual units would it be. I'm trying to have more, like, raw points, but anyway, I'm just, I don't know if it doesn't get approved for that, then how to continue the conversation, but I do just think we should,
you know, connect where we can to emphasize that this will help us get off the ground to achieve these things. I'm very happy that we have the confidence of the City Council and us pulling it off, but we can't do tomorrow in our current situation. Yeah. All right. Thank you. Does anybody else have any other ideas of other funding sources or advocacy for other funding sources?
On to item number 6, adjournment. Ending the meeting. Do I get a motion to adjourn the meeting? Nobody? I said no. So I said no to end the meeting.
Second. Okay, we'll have a vote to adjourn. Kayla? Aye. Roberta? Aye. Penny? Yes. Lisa Sung? Yes. And the mayor's left, so me, yes. The meeting is adjourned at 8.15. Thank you guys for a fantastic meeting. Great discussion. Thank you.