We fall into
In what year did Medford High football team win their only Super Bowl? I'm Amber Harbisson with the Mustang Report and I'm here with Mr. Nas, the leader of the Stang Gang and the football team. So can you tell us a little bit about the Stang Gang? I know it's a new club this year.
Yeah, so the stand gang is going to be great this year. We're really excited to have it rolling for this season. It's a pep squad, but it's basically like if you ever saw a college student section. And we have organized cheers and chants. And I think one big thing that we need as a school is much more school spirit. But I think if we can really hone in on the entire school population and try to bring everything together, it'll really be an awesome experience for everyone.
And, you know, anyone can join the Stang Gang. You know, as long as you continue to show up, you're officially a part of the club. And we usually try to go to at least one or two, if we can squeeze it in, two big home games a week. So how do you think this is going to promote energy through your football team? And how do you think they're going to feel about the Stang Gang being there supporting them at their home games? I think this is going to bring it to the next level. This thing has the potential to really bring everyone together.
You can tell them that I've been from hell and back When the heat is on, I fire back In this cold world, where your light is at Let's burn it down, I fire back You can tell them that I've been from hell and back
In this cold world, where your lighters at? Let's burn it down, before I buy it back
let's take it to the ground don't too many make it coming through our town looking for a detour nowhere to be found when the pressure's on seems nobody's around uh but i won't let them see me sweat yeah it took a little time but can't really be upset long way to the top i could barely see the steps yeah they sleeping on
At 400 yards, we have the winning structure. It's a little inaccurate, but 800 is good. This is the message to the world. Take the 6.
Hi, I'm Amber, and I'm here with Coach Rugg. They just finished up the GBL meet. How do you guys think your team did? For the first time out, I'd say excellent. Very young. Most of our runners are first-year runners. Most have never run anything like we've ran today, so very pleased with it today. And you guys have run cross-country all four years, and how is this year different from last year or your years before?
Well, last year, we had a couple of really good seniors. And it was sad to see them go. But this year, we also got a lot of new freshmen. So it's nice to see new talent and just people excited for the sport. Yeah, we have a lot of new people this year. So hopefully, we can build the team up for years to come.
You think back to last October when the shovels went into the dirt here, the snowflakes were flying, it was a little chilly, and who would think less than a year later, with the wind blowing just a little bit, that we would be celebrating this beautiful park that has so perfectly achieved its vision on a fall day that is nothing short of perfection.
Oh, say, does that star-spangled banner yet wave? As today we gaze upon this beautiful new garden, let us pray for Crystal and for Martin, Lingzi and Sean,
We pray for all those injured, for all that responded, somehow running towards the scene rather than away from it. And it will mean not just for those who were lucky enough to know Crystal and Martin and Lindsay,
and Sean that they won't be forgotten. But it means those of us who never were lucky enough to know them will also have a place and a way to learn about them, to remember them, to honor not only the manner of their deaths, but the manner of their lives. I asked Patty Campbell the other day if it was really important that the word peace be in the name of the garden.
She said, yes, because it's the reason people move to this country, because they want their families to be safe, and because that's what we believe. This morning, I ran the entire marathon course in memory of Crystal. I had to. I had to reflect. I never met Crystal personally, but I felt she was with me every step of the way this morning.
as were Martin and Lindsay and Shawn. This garden is a fitting tribute to Crystal, Sunflower, Martin, Baseball Glove, Lindsay, Books, and Shawn, Badge. And I don't have a lot to give, but what I do have that I want to give to the Crystal family
is my Boston Marathon medal from 2013. It symbolizes friendship, resolve, and most importantly, peace. On April 15, 2013 was a devastating and tragic day.
but also a time when people came together to support one another with a renewed commitment for a better quality of life for all. That spirit is what this Peace Garden represents.
We celebrate Crystal's life. She was a Medford Mustang class of 2001, an alumnus of UMass Boston. Crystal was a member of the Medford High School band and the girls' softball team. We celebrate her ongoing, fun-loving, deeply passionate and energetic life. Crystal lived life to the fullest.
She touched the hearts and souls of not only family and friends, but hearts and souls throughout the world. When this project began, Bill Campbell, Fiskel's dad, said he could not wait until it was finished, so he could bring his grandson, Billy III, and enjoy his company in the beauty of this park. Bill, the word is out.
You are going to have a lot of company.
As a community, we share in your sorrow. As a community, we share in your healing. And as a community, we are hopeful.
We are hopeful that this special place in our city, a living memorial that countless individuals, entities contributed to, to bring to fruition, is a testament to the longing we all have for a peaceful, reflective space. In the days, weeks, and years following the horrific events, these families, first responders, and survivors have demonstrated pure strength by their actions and words,
seen and heard around the world.