[SPEAKER_00]: Hello, my name is Rick Caraviello.
[SPEAKER_00]: As many of you know, I served 12 years as a city councilor and three of those as council president.
[SPEAKER_00]: Today, I am here before you not only as a candidate, but as someone who holds a strong belief in the strength of community.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am running again because we are in danger of losing the Medford we know and love.
[SPEAKER_00]: Medford is a community.
[SPEAKER_00]: that has always been distinguished by its rich history and vibrant neighborhoods.
[SPEAKER_00]: The most contentious issue in this election is the proposed citywide rezoning and development plan.
[SPEAKER_00]: At its core, the city council's duty is to protect the integrity and stability of our neighborhoods.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, that duty has been cast aside.
[SPEAKER_00]: The current council is pushing a sweeping rezoning proposal that would allow two to six units
[SPEAKER_00]: per residential lot, regardless of neighborhood context, infrastructure capacity, or community input.
[SPEAKER_00]: This approach isn't thoughtful growth.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a density policy, one size fits all, that threatens to fundamentally alter the character of Medford.
[SPEAKER_00]: Instead, I will vote no to destroying our neighborhoods and vote yes to protecting them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Medford's business districts hold tremendous potential, not for unchecked expansion, but for smart, sustainable growth that respects our community's character.
[SPEAKER_00]: I support enhancing these areas with thoughtful planning that boasts tax revenue, creates good jobs, strengthens our local economy without compromising what makes Medford unique.
[SPEAKER_00]: As our city grows, so must our commitment to education for the next generations.
[SPEAKER_00]: Memphis students deserve learning environments that are safe, modern, and built for the challenges of tomorrow, not the limitations of the past.
[SPEAKER_00]: A new high school isn't a luxury, it's a necessity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's invest in our kids, our community, and our future.
[SPEAKER_00]: Police and DPW departments should be fully staffed and deserve the backing of public officials, including the long overdue negotiation of their contracts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fixing our streets and sidewalks is one of the most basic and most powerful things we can do to improve daylight in Medford.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about accessibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about showing every resident that they matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's time to address this important issues.
[SPEAKER_00]: My campaign is about you, the taxpayers, not the politicians.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will listen to your concerns, as I always have, and will represent your voice and restore the trust of the people to City Hall.
[SPEAKER_00]: Together, let's build a fairer, more united Medford than ever before.
[SPEAKER_00]: I respectfully ask for one of your seven votes on Tuesday, November 4th for Rick Caravello for Medford City Council.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.