Okay, please be advised that on July 31st, 2024 at 12pm, there will be a special meeting of the Medford School Committee held remotely via Zoom. This meeting is being recorded. The meeting can be viewed live on Medford Public Schools YouTube channel through Medford Community Media and your local cable, just Comcast 9, 8, or 22 in Verizon 43, 45, or 47.
The meeting will be recorded. Since the meeting will be held remotely, participants can log in by using the following information. The Zoom link is 925-7011-3130. Questions or comments can be submitted by emailing medfordsc at medford.k12.ma.us. Those submitting questions or comments must include the following, your first and last name, your Medford street address, and three, your question or comment.
The agenda is executive session pursuant to Mass General Law, Chapter 30A, Section A3. The Medford School Committee will convene an executive session to discuss negotiations with the Medford Teachers Association for Kids Corner and the Medford Teachers Association for Paraprofessionals because an open meeting will have a detrimental effect on the bargaining position of the committee and the chair so declares.
Thank you, Member Graham. So is there a motion to go into executive? We need to roll call. Roll call for attendance, please. Member Brandling? Absent at the moment. Member Graham? Yes. Member Ntapa? Here. Member Olapode? Yes. Member Reinfeldt? I believe that's Eric. Present. Member Rousseau, present. Mayor Longo, current. Present. Seven present, zero absent.
There. One absent. One absent. Yes, Nicole. One absent. Six present, one absent. Motion to enter executive session. Second. Yes. If I may, through the chair, I just wanted to introduce Mr. Will Pippaselli, who is our new director of communications, who just started on Monday. And I just wanted him to say hello to the committee. That was all. Thank you, Dr. Ellersen. Hi, Will. Welcome. Hi.
Hi, happy to be here. My name is Wilpa Paselli. I just started on Monday and looking forward to working with all of you in the near future. And so thank you. Great. Great to have you. Welcome. We have a motion by member Graham to move into executive sessions, seconded by, I think it was member Reinfeldt. Roll call, please. Member Brandling? Absent. Member Graham? Yes. Member Atapa? Yes. Member Olopade? Yes. Member Reinfeldt?
I don't know if you're trying to unmute. Remember, I don't. Hear you. If you are muted member, Reinfeldt. I don't know if you're trying to unmute. Mark her present. I Yeah, I see her. She did second it after all member Russo. Yes, Maryland. Okay Yes, 60 affirmative one absent emotion to go into
Well, we, I think we will, I think we will return. Okay, we will return and take a public vote. How's that? Thank you. Recording in progress. Memorandum of agreement and one-year contract. By Member Graham, seconded by Member Reinfeld. Roll call vote, Member Russo.
member bradley is absent member graham yes member and have absent member la pate yes yes members say yes maryland okay yes five in the affirmative zero in the negative and the next step is the kids corner contract motion approve the kids corner uh moa which includes um
a one-year contract and a three-year contract for a total of four contract years. Motion for approval by Member Graham, seconded by? Second. Member Reinfeldt, roll call please. Member Graham, absent. Member Graham? Yes. Member Atapa, absent. Member Olopade? Yes. Member Reinfeldt? Yes. Members say yes. Mayor Lungo, current.
Yes, five in the affirmative, two absent, motion passes. Is there a motion to adjourn? Motion to adjourn. By Member Reinfeldt, seconded by? Second. Member Graham, roll call, please. Member Bramley, absent Member Graham? Yes. Member Ntapa, absent Member Olapodite? Yes. Member Reinfeldt? Yes. Members say yes, Mayor Lungo-Kern?
yes filing the affirmative two absent meeting is adjourned have a great wednesday everybody