All right. I think that we're all here. I'll pass the baton. Great. Thanks, Amanda. Good evening. Welcome to tonight's meeting of the Medford Community Development Board. My name is Dave Blumberg. Happy to have you here tonight. Let me call the meeting to order, and as always, begin with some obligatory messages for everyone. This hearing of the Medford Community Development Board is being conducted via remote means. No in-person attendance of members of the public will be permitted.
But every effort will be made to ensure that the public can adequately access the proceedings, as provided for in chapter two of the acts of 2023. A reminder that anyone who would like to listen to or view this meeting while in progress. Maybe do so by accessing the link that was included on the meeting agenda posted on the city of Medford website.
If despite best efforts we're not able to provide real time access, we will post a recording of this meeting on the city's website as soon as possible. A reminder that given the nature of this meeting. That is remote tonight all votes from the board will be made by roll call.
As a reminder, all of our all project materials for projects before the board are available through the city's website, Medford ma.org. If you go to boards and commissions, go to that tab and then find Community Development Board, you'll find what you need. I'll begin with roll call of those in attendance from the board tonight. Vice Chair Jackie McPherson.
Clyson dressing. Preston, Christy down, present. And we haven't present. Peter colors. Present. And Ari Goffman Fishman present. Welcome everyone Amanda if you would do us the honors of just mentioning for the members of the public others in attendance tonight, who amongst our city staff are with us.
Yes, so my name is Amanda Centrella. I'm planning staff in the Office of Planning, Development and Sustainability alongside me, like my colleagues. So Director of Planning, Development and Sustainability, Alicia Hunt, as well as Senior Planner, Danielle Evans, and Building Commissioner Bill Forty is also joining us tonight. Welcome, everyone.
Let's turn to the first item for discussion tonight, and I'll read the public notice on this one.
Our board is to conduct a public hearing tonight, relative to a position by another McLennan and fish representing CPC land acquisition company, LLC, to amend the city's zoning map, as referenced in our zoning ordinance amendment proposes to change the zoning district designation of the area of the property 99 Revere Beach Parkway in Medford from industrial to mixed use.
And the property consists of two parcels. I guess that's pretty much it for the public notice. And at this point, let me introduce and hand the baton over to Attorney Moore.
Thank you, and thank you all for your time this evening. With me tonight is Jack Englert, as well as Eric Van Arum and Liam McDonough from the development team. So with that, I will turn it over to Jack, who will walk you through their vision for the site. Thank you. Welcome. You're on mute, Jack.
Thank you. I'm so adept at dealing with the zoom things you think I'd be able to hit a mute button but I'm jack angler with criterion development company we're also CPC land acquisition company. And we're here tonight just to discuss the amending the map that exists now in the general area and we can start to go through the slides and I'd like to ask Liam McDonough actually to pull up the PowerPoint.
Um, but basically to extend the museum zone from where it is. Over to a piece of at at station landing over to a piece of land that butts the river. So with that, I think if Liam were able to open up. So I'm not having access is, uh, someone able to grant me access so I can share my
All set. Okay. There we go. So yes, this is a zoning map change to mix use zone from what is now an industrial zone piece of land. If you go to the next slide,
just to give a sense, we're calling this the Mystic and Malden River Basin, but it's really the confluence of both the Mystic and the Malden. And you can see the MBTA site that is sort of represented on the point here where those two rivers come together and the big white building that exists on the screen. I don't know, Liam, if you can use your cursor to kind of point out the area, but yes,
a little off, but yeah, there you go. South of Route 16 at the Wellington T stop. You can go to the next step. Slide. This is a little better map, I think, because it kind of explains what's going on with the pathway that's been started and stopped a number of times in this area. You know, it runs along the recreational open space land to the left of McDonnell Park and comes down
across 28 and then goes around the point, if you will, and it sort of stops where the arrow is at the MBTA parking lot there. If you cross over Route 16 to the north, you can see a lighter yellow that extends all the way up to River's Edge, which is a development to the north on River's Edge Drive.
And our site is really the KISS 108 site, which we'll see on the next slide in the corner, just south of Route 16 along the Malden River. This sort of zooms in on the area a little bit better, Wellington T stop. Parking lot, the site that we're talking about is highlighted in purple, and you can see station landing on the left side running parallel with
route 28 on the eastern side of 28. And the Wellington T-stop, which has recently been the subject of an RFI, I think, from the city for some of the air rights that exist over that T-stop and then our piece east of that. Go to the next slide. So this is sort of an excerpt of the zoning map
You can see the MUZ zone highlighted in red and indicated by MUZ, that is basically station landing. And I think it picks up Kelly's as well. And then our site across the industrial area there is right on the river and highlighted also in red, indicated by the word site. Just north of our site is the office zoning. I think there's a residential deal there.
or two, and then you see the recreational open space zoning in green along the Mystic River to the south. You can go to the next slide. This sort of zooms in on that section of that MBTA lot and our lot, just south of Route 16. And to the north, you can see a multifamily development project that was built
probably eight years ago, and then the path along the river that comes underneath Route 16 in that location, and then sort of dies up into a sidewalk that then meanders along Route 16 to the west. We'll go to the next slide.
This is a view of that pathway, and it's kind of about face that coming under 16, and then going back up to 16, and that apartment development in the background. Go to the next slide, please. So after you come under the Route 16 bridge, you're sort of met with the existing situation out there, which hasn't been manicured or kept up very well over the last, who knows how many years,
and you're sort of met by this barbed wire fence and some of the cell towers. And I think on the next few slides, we'll get a better picture of what happens in that area. This is the back of the KISS 108 building, which is just along the river and continue on. It continues quite a ways across the site of the fence and then the cell towers. And then along the river, it's been just, you know, kind of,
not very well maintained at all. And it's just overgrown invasives. And there are a few nice trees actually in there, but most of it is just overgrown invasive species. Go to the next slide. You know, it needs to be cleaned up. It needs to be fixed up. And this kind of unsightliness that exists now is definitely a deterrent from walking along the river. Go to the next slide.
This is an aerial view that kind of zooms in on the site itself, Route 16, on the east side of the picture, the path coming under Route 16, and then sort of turning back up to the sidewalk. And then that area that we were just looking at, those various slides, is that which is along the river, outside the green area. The fence line actually separates the green from sort of the natural.
And the site encompasses both the green, the KISS 108 building, the green area that you see in some parking, and then the adjacent lot is a parking lot to the north, screen north. It's actually west, but that encompasses the entire site. Go to the next slide, please. So, you know, I know we're here just for, you know,
zoning amendment and not really to talk about the actual idea, but I thought it'd be helpful to go through some of the things that we've been thinking about. And the proposal that we have that would be pursuant to the mixed use zone, should it be approved, would be a multifamily structure on the site. It would have some retail on the first floor, probably community space and those sorts of things. And a number of things that we've looked at to kind of engage
the community and engage the walkway and the river. I know it's preliminary, but we have met with the Mystic River Watershed Association. We've met with a couple of bike groups. We've met with some environmentalists and meteorologists, actually, just to talk about the site and what it could be and what needs we could kind of
satisfied by, you know, obviously we're trying to build a project that's a good project, but a good project means not only the project itself, but what we can do to engage the community. This is a very preliminary landscaping plan, but it does show you some of the things that we're thinking about, the continuation of the path, the creation of a pavilion, the creation of some outdoor bike storage, outdoor bike washing stations,
outdoor bike fix it stations and then some kayak potential kayak rental areas. And things like that. If you go to the next slide. No, these are just images that we're starting to look at. Should this be something that we could move forward with? We would love to be able to put some sort of a pavilion. So if you are on that walkway and we can complete the pathway.
across our site and certainly contribute to bringing it across the MBTA site to link it with what is in existence. We think that, you know, having a place where people could get out of the rain or sun would be a nice amenity for the community. You can go to the next slide. Obviously, this isn't exactly what we're talking about, but we are looking south here.
We're at River's Edge, and this is some of the work that John Priato has done up at River's Edge, and we were involved with two projects up there as well, and feel like we were a part of it, even though I give full credit to John for doing all this beautiful work in landscaping and J.P. Shadley. But it's a continuation of this feel is what we're proposing to come across our site and continue to link to the existing path. If you go to the next slide.
And the next. And one more. With some signage, you know, potential and go to the next please. And so what is the building look like you know it is a preliminary stage. This building would be the view if you were, you know, up in the air on top of the river.
and it kind of starts to demonstrate the openness that we're trying to step it down to the river, not be a wall against the river, open up that courtyard to the river. And again, on the preliminary stage, and if we're lucky enough to move forward with this through the zoning and come back to the community board, we would love to be able to get into a detailed discussion of some of the things we're thinking about. But as a starting point, we thought this would be a good,
you know, model to at least attempt to head towards. So this does show some covered bike stations where there could be a bike wash and storage and different tools to be used for people using the path with bikes. And, you know, we've contacted the community rowing group. It's actually a kayak rental. They have a place over in Newton on the Charles River, and we were thinking,
that might be a great amenity for both the project and the community to be able to have a launching point. We know there are a lot of steps to get to in terms of access to the river, but in our discussions to date, everything has seemed to indicate that there's a lot of demand for it. There's a lot of, I think people want to see it happen and we would love to try to make that happen. If you go to the next slide,
I love this because of the sailboat. I don't know the depth of the river. I guess you could sail a boat that size in there, but it just gives you a sense of how it would sit on the river. This is from the southeast of the site, looking up at it. And go to the next slide, please. And this would be from the north, looking back towards the city of Boston. You can see in this picture, I think very well, the MBTA station.
and the parking associated with the MBTA station and the casino in the in the background there. And the next slide. So some of the general project benefits and some of the things that would be allowed should this by special permit should this be rezoned to MUZ you know rehousing at a transit hub which we are very fond of we've built them at Forest Hill station and JFK station and in
Dorchester, and Alewife Station in Cambridge, 15% of housing to be affordable. Extension of that path seems to be something that's been in the works for a long time, and we think that we could put it over the line and get it all to happen. I know there's funding out there right now for some of it, and if we could kind of bridge the gap between the funding and do everything on our side and then bridge the gap on the rest,
We think that would be a nice amenity for the community. Talked about meeting space with some of the different local nonprofit groups. The bike wash and repair station we mentioned as well as the kayak rental. And then the potential public access to the river which we think would be a wonderful thing.
and we're going to do our best to work through that should we have the opportunity. And finally, you know, in terms of the sustainability, we do pride ourselves on a lot of forward thinking on that. We are doing a project right on the Charles River right now in Newton. And one of our houses, one of our buildings happens to be a passive house building. We know we can achieve
full passive house building here, but we know we can put a lot of the sustainability efforts that are going around right now into our buildings with solar on the roof and, you know, stretch code and building envelope and all the things that we've been doing on a number of things. Our project at Forest Hills is gold certified,
lead standard, which was a big win for us. We were excited about that. We've done a number that are silver as well, but that's the future. We're really just talking about the zoning and I thought it might be good to mention some of this stuff. Go to the next, could be the last. I think it is. So with that, I can open it up to questions or whatever the board would like.
Okay, sure. Thanks for the presentation. We can open it up to public comment unless there's more from the presenters. Amanda do we have some folks who are interested in participating tonight.
So we haven't received any comments ahead of the meeting. I'll check now. But while I do that, if there is anyone on the meeting that would like to provide public comment, if you could either use the raise hand feature or put a little note in the chat, we'll call on you. So I'll give folks a second to do that. Just refresh.
Of course, you've got your email address, which is ocd at medford-ma.gov, if someone felt more comfortable for some reason sending an email. Correct. And so we haven't received any new or any comments at this time via email, and I'm not seeing any hands or notes in the chat. Okay.
All right, I guess we'll close that public comment period and open it up to the board. Board members, do we have questions or comments? Yes, Emily. I'm really excited for this development. I live at 5 Cabot, so I'm the development
is just kind of north over Riviera Beach Parkway to this. I think some of the, I know we're not talking about building specifics at this point, we're just talking about zoning, but given the proximity to the T, the area residential, this is really exciting for me and I support it and I don't have any questions. Thank you. Any other comments?
I thought it would be of interest, I'll throw my question out, which is why the MUZ versus some other technique, a planned development district or something along those lines, just out of curiosity. I think we've looked at a few things and the MUZ just struck us as a natural progression from what is existing at station landing, what might be needed at the air rides over the T,
And it sort of fit that whole southern side of 16. I don't think there was any particular reason we didn't want to do the process although you know timing is everything in real estate and, and we happen to have a fund that was very interested in this project and they've been pushing me pretty hard because, and I've been willing to take that push given the, you know, the nature of what's going on right now and.
having someone be interested in a project like this in the market where it's not that easy. I was trying to see what might be the most not only the best path in terms of consistency with the future across the southern part of Route 16 in that area but also expediency I think maybe
And whether we're right or wrong we thought it might be a little easier path in terms of timing, not easier, just perhaps a little faster. That's all. I appreciate your answer. Thanks very much. I could see the benefit of having the same district on the east and the west side of of Wellington makes a lot of sense I think from the community's point of view so thanks for your perspective on that.
Other questions or comments. City officials I didn't invite you to ask questions but I bet I may. Hi. Yeah, sorry. Um, so I provided a memo that should have come in this morning it's very brief.
Our goal is to get these out much earlier, they're just kind of like a nice to have right now. So if you didn't read it, don't worry, I know it's late. But we do I do go into discussion about why the month was chosen, and how we've been working with criterion and the property owner for well over a year, kind of going through different iterations of development proposal at the site.
and how the industrial zone is very limiting and doesn't align with the comprehensive plan or the housing production plan. And this seemed like the easiest lift to just have a simple map change rather than a 40B or a PDD. It just seemed like just a smoother, easier process, even though the Muzz isn't a perfect ordinance, but it's the best that we have right now.
Sure. Thanks for your, your input there. I see Commissioner Forte, you have a hand up. Can we turn to you please sir. Thank you, Mr Chairman. Um, so I guess my questions kind of fall along the same line and I believe that Danielle kind of answered it. Um, but I guess the first question I would have is.
Given the fact that you're not taking the 40B route, I would assume that the future project is not going to entail any additional approvals from Zoning Board of Appeals. Is that correct for you, Jim?
At this time, based on the proposal we showed tonight, we're not anticipating requiring relief from the Zoning Board of Appeals. Those certainly will be subject to site plan review before this board. Thank you. And, and I guess the next question is any portion of the property within a flood zone. And obviously your first floor elevation would be above that but I didn't see any floodplain elevations on the map.
Yes, part of the property is and our first floor would be above it. We've met briefly with conservation just to get a sense of what we're doing because we are removing some impervious soil that is in that second zone from 100 to 200. We are putting something in that as well, but we're putting in less than we're taking out certainly. So we are trying to stay out of that as much as possible. We are gonna keep the first floor above that flood plain
And I don't have the elevations off the top of my head, but I'd be happy to send you an email and kind of lay out where it is at present. Thank you. Yeah. And it might be a bit early for that, but it's just a general question. And then the other general question I had was, would the reason for the zone change, and I'm just thinking future down the road,
If for some reason the residential market for some reason no longer calls for these units. Do you have an alternative plan like a plan B for this property, other than what you see there and I was residential I mean is a laboratory out of the question or is it, you know, what are your thoughts on that, Mr. Chair, again for you.
Because, so the museum zone I don't do think provides a lot of flexibility on that we are residential developers, but the owner of the site. Last parking has a real estate arm that has explored all kinds of uses for the site you know lab was very hot for a while.
And originally when I was talking to the owner of LAS, he said, well, I like you, you know, I've done a couple of deals on his properties in the past and he likes us, but the labs were a lot better looking. And at the time he said, I have no interest in dealing with you. He went out to the lab market and wasn't successful in finding anyone. And, you know, I think labs may come back at some point, I think
If you could deliver a lab today, it would be a pretty successful lab. But the planning and the time that it takes to build, there really hasn't been a lot of interest in lab. I do think having the MUZ zone, though, would allow for flexibility. If something like our project weren't to go forward, I think having this zone in place might be helpful for that possibility of more flexible uses.
Thank you. And again, through you, Mr. Chair, it appears as though this is all surface parking. Is that correct?
The parking that we have is actually under the building at grade but on the first floor, and hidden by, you know, retail and storefront on the front side of the building, and hidden by just fully enclosed in the back as well, you know screen by bike parking or kayaks and things like that. So, in this configuration there is.
parking at that grade and the grade isn't exactly flat out there kind of pitches towards the river. So working through those grades we are determining that we would have one story of parking underneath the building, and then the unit starting on the second floor. Thank you very much. That's all the questions I have at this time. Thank you, Mr. Chair. Thank you, Mr. Commissioner for your questions, much appreciated. Any other comments or questions.
Okay. Hearing none, I wonder amongst the board, will we be okay with a motion? Let me see if I might be able to craft something over here. To recommend to the city council the adoption of the proposed rezoning of 99 Revere Beach Parkway from the current industrial zone to the mixed use MEZ zoning district found at section nine of our zoning ordinance.
I will make that motion. Is there a second? Second. Excellent. Let me go to the roll call. And as always, starting with Vice Chair Jackie McPherson. Aye. Klyce Andresen. Yes. Christy Dowd. Yes. Emily Hedman. Yes. Peter Caldas. Yes. Ari Goffman-Fishman.
All right, have we lost Ari? I don't see Ari. I will vote yes. She's there, but she's- They dropped off and were here twice for a second, and then they came back on. Yeah. So I don't know. I see them twice.
Okay, well we have sufficient votes I think for, for the motion so we'll, we'll leave it at that for this moment and try to get that straight now for our next item. Thank you very much for the presentation tonight and information and it's like a lot of potential community developments forthcoming so we thank you. Thank you for all of you for your time. Appreciate it. Thank you.
Okay. Next item on the agenda is the plan development district at to a mystic have and late breaking news the applicant has asked to withdraw this proposal that was going to be before us tonight. And we're advised that as a result we actually need to take a vote on accepting the withdrawal without prejudice.
If anyone wants to talk about that we could do that or we could just have a motion to accept the withdrawal, without prejudice of the applicants combined properties for the proposal at to any mystic. Are we allowed to have a little more information. I can ask city are we in a position or you.
So I'm not really sure we, but to share, you saw that we had a, you can see the papers we had with them. They gave us a proposed ordinance, right, zoning change. We hired a lawyer, Gareth, who sent them back changes.
And we had a meeting with them and discuss those changes and we thought we had come to resolution on some of them and that they were going to think about some of the others and get back to us. We expected a redlined version today and instead we got a letter basically saying they objected to our changes and they were withdrawing.
Um, I did speak to them further today saying, are you sure you don't want some more time just to ask for a continuance tonight? Um, and their basic concern that they thought was insurmountable was that, um, sorry, I had it in front of me a minute. Um, the plan development district in section 924 has a section lapse.
Um, that basically says that the zoning must be commenced by a tent obtaining a special permit.
as required in section 866 within two years. Until such time as that is permitted and recorded by the property owner, or if it's not obtained within two years the development, the property should be governed by the provisions presently in effect in the zoning district so basically it expires if they don't use it in two years. And they said that was too short that they anticipate meeting a meet the process that that'll take longer than two years.
I conveyed to them that perhaps that they go forward and that at some point when they know that they're not gonna be ready for the special permit in two years, they apply for an extension and they indicated that there wasn't enough certainty in that and that they wanted this changed to be longer than two years. Their lawyer had put into their language and you can see it in the version proposed to you that the,
To that they proposed language sorry I had it open and I closed it that the two years. The good faith, instead of special permit that they would do a filing and ENF or er filing for me, but within the two years and that that would be the execution of it. We didn't think that was defensible because it's very clearly says special permit um.
I suggested to them that they could go forward with their language, but I didn't know how that would stand up, or if anybody would challenge it. And their suggestion is that we change our zoning so that the lapse time is longer than two years, or that for large projects, projects that trigger MIPA, et cetera, they have more than two years.
And that's where it stood. That was today. So I don't really know what to say other than that. Is that clear? Alicia, do you know what the paper trigger was for the lie?
No, actually, I didn't think to ask that until a few minutes ago when I was explaining it. So I was explaining to our lawyer, Gareth, and he said to me, gee, I'm not sure actually what the MIPA trigger is now that we're thinking about it. We discussed it yesterday and he kept saying because it's such a big project, it's going to trigger MIPA. And I realized that I'm I don't know, except I will say it's on Route 38. So it is on a state road.
So there may be some state permits related to the fact that it's on a state road transportation. I'm almost positive. I can't say that I can't say that I'm positive about knowing but I'm just wondering if it's transportation which we discussed in detail.
Right. Right. Thank you. So I did offer them the option to continue tonight rather than withdraw to give us some more time to to work this through and they didn't like that idea. Any follow up that's. Yep.
I will just for your reference they objected to some other articles stuff that we proposed but I but they seem to all be negotiable like they didn't like we had recommended or the lawyer recommended a plan development and cooperation agreement and they didn't like that they wanted to just do special permits with them.
regular conditions. And I said, OK, it was just an idea that the lawyer had proposed. We haven't done anything like that before. If you object, we we don't need this. There's nothing in the zoning that requires that. So in the letter they sent me, they also objected to that. But I'm OK with like, OK. OK, sounds like from your perspective, we could try to work through these issues or they're resolvable.
I just wasn't sure about the two years. They seem to be very concerned about going through all the permit process and then having what if they asked for an extension in two years and whoever's on the board then didn't feel like giving an extension. They thought that was risky. All right. Other questions or we can go to the
Motion again there would be a motion to accept the withdrawal of combined properties for the proposal to a mystic have without prejudice. So, allowing them to come back. I'll make the motion. Excellent. Is there a second to the motion. This Christie I second. And for roll call vice chair Jackie McPherson. Yes.
Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
a proposed drive through bank facility of Bank of America at 3085 mystic Valley Parkway.
As a summary, the existing site currently houses a surface parking lot is bounded by commercial properties to the north London street to the east locus street to the west and the northern access drive to medical and to the south. The proposed project would construct an approximately 5413 square foot bank with one drive through lane and one drive through pass bypass lane, excuse me. So to kick things off, let's.
ask the proponent to present an evening. Wait a minute, excuse me I see Danielle's hand up. Right, if I could provide some context to this. So, this special permit.
There was some confusion about process maybe because of the new ordinance. Even though I do think this is a requirement in the previous ordinance that special permits where city council is a special permit granting authority need to first be referred to the CD board. And then you all have, I think it's 35 days to provide comments. Somehow that didn't happen and Alicia and I
happened to be attending that city council meeting and saw it on the agenda and we're like, huh, we didn't see this. And so it's still the city council opened the hearing and voted on it pending a recommendation from the Community Development Board.
And so now, so it's kind of a process has gone backwards. And so, while this was happening we are trying to wrap our heads around the previous permitting, looking for the previously approved site plan, because 120,000 square foot redevelopment of that
previous Meadow Glen mall. We just assumed this would have required site plan review, but after doing some research, we found out that somehow that was waived back in 2015. So there was not a previous site plan approval, which would have required an amendment with the construction of a new bank with a drive-thru. So it's still a special permit, which is, I'm sorry, I have a sick child, you all said amazing, is subject to a special permit,
still subject to the performance standard in the zoning ordinance, as well as six criteria for approval of a special permit. And so we requested a traffic memo, and we want this to get before different department heads for their review, so that those findings can be made much we requested the traffic memo and we received it on.
Thursday or Friday, but Todd Blake, the Director of Traffic and Transportation, is on vacation and has not had a chance to review it or provide comments. So, PDS's, our recommendation is that you can open this hearing and have the presentation, but to continue it to a date certain until those comments are back.
Okay, Daniel, thanks for the comments and in the background there's quite a bit that you discovered along the way. Is it Mr. Fitz on behalf of the...
Andy is not with us tonight. It's Bill Lucas with Bowler. I'm the consultant for Mr. Lucas. That's, that's great. Sorry, I've got a vacuum going next to me here. Everybody has challenges tonight. Apparently. So, I think, just as a procedural matter would be good, as Daniel suggests to kind of open this up, hear the presentation learn about it.
We do certainly like to hear from this various city departments at their sort of key piece in our evaluation of special permit or site plan review for that matter. So, I think what she's suggesting makes a lot of sense so if you're prepared to present. We can give you our undivided attention and give you feedback and comments and try to do as much as we can short of.
that additional information that we'll have to address with you at the subsequent meeting. Does that make sense for you? That's fine. Awesome. If that's easiest for this group, then I will give a presentation tonight and I'll start by sharing my screen if that works. Thank you. Give that a try.
Hopefully everybody can see that on screen now. It looks good. Opening. So Daniel, thanks for jumping in and kind of given the clunky background that we've kind of gone through to get to this point in time. I've not been integral with all the permitting procedure, but I am here to represent Bank of America as their civil consultant, mainly with the design of the drawings themselves and coordination with the client.
To that end, I will jump in and start to move forward. What you have on screen now is outlined in purple is
the property boundary for the Meadow Glen Mall. And in red in that lower left-hand corner is what our project site is for this development. Just for orientation purposes, as we move through the slides, north will be on the left-hand side of the screen, south on the right-hand side.
So a little bit of a zoomed-in view, again, of the project site itself. It's an existing parking lot that is part of the Meadow Glen Mall. In the upper right-hand corner, which is a little blocked by the North Arrow itself, is the existing marshals, just for your orientation purposes. And along the lower end of the screen, that is Locust Street.
This is an existing survey if we need to get into any of the details of the site. But in general, what this shows is it's a relatively flat parking lot bounded by Locust Street along the bottom of the page. Then what you'll see on the right-hand side is an access drive to Meadow Glen.
most of the utilities to the Meadow Glen Mall run along that access drive and in the future we'll talk about all of our proposed connections. Most of them happen along that access point except for electric and telecom which is along Locust Street. This gives you an overall view of what we're proposing. It is a 5,400 square foot Bank of America
Again, it's a little zoomed in, so Locust Street is along the bottom of your screen. The front door or main entrance to the building is at the lower right-hand corner of that gray box in the middle of the screen. Your drive-through, it's one lane, is located on the left-hand side of the northern end of the building, and again,
As David had spoken to earlier, it does have a bypass lane. That's that second lane on the left-hand side, one way from the top of your screen to the bottom of your screen with stop and do not enter there. As far as traffic around the building itself, it's primarily two-way.
with 90 degree parking stalls all facing all those drive aisles. And we do provide ADA stalls near the main entrance along with accessibility routes from the main entrance over to the shopping center or out to Locust as made available.
A quick snapshot of some of the building elevations, your typical Bank of America look, nothing that should surprise anybody here in terms of the type of colors and materials that you've seen in other locations.
And again, I'm here on a question screen, but I'll just kind of jump in to some other points of interest for the project itself. Again, I talked about utilities, water, sewer, drainage, and our gas services will go out to the right-hand side to that access drive to the Meadow Glen Mall. There's all existing services in that area.
and our electric and telecom will be run underground out to a utility pole on Locust Street.
As far as the drainage is concerned, it will be collected from the roof and several catch basins that we're proposing as part of the development to then pipe, to be piped close to the parking field that is nearest to the main entrance of the building. That is an area where we had performed some exploratory soils investigation.
found the best soils, which is saying a lot for this site because it's primarily urban,
fill condition underlined by some clay soils on the site. So we've had discussions with engineering at Medford to prepare this type of system to try to promote as much infiltration as we can on the site. It is not ideal conditions, but we are moving forward with that type of design on the site. In terms of
Other permits, we don't need anything from the Conservation Commission. We've been in front of them already. We received a negative determination of applicability for this site. There's no... the closest thing was...
I believe it was the floodplain, but that is on the other portion of the Meadow Glen Mall, not near our site. And again, as Michelle spoke to, we had been before the city council and they recommended special permit approval, but pending review by planning staff. So with that said, I can open it up to any questions.
Okay, well, we're gonna invite members of the public, if there are folks out there who are interested in posing questions or sharing feedback, go to that now. And as Amanda mentioned in the last public item, you can use the raise hand feature on Zoom, you can put a message in the chat,
via Zoom. You can also send an email to OCD at Medford-MA.gov. That's the department's email address. Amanda, if you're out there, any visibility on whether we have a member of the public who'd like to speak on this one? So I'm not seeing anyone. Actually, Bill, would you mind stopping your share screen just so I can see all the participants just to make sure? Thank you.
And so yeah see no hands raised, no comments in the chat and I've just refreshed our inbox and see no messages at this time. Okay. Any questions from city staff. Before we go to the board.
Okay, board members. Oh, wait a minute. Mr. Commissioner, you have your hand up. Thank you, Mr. Chair. The one question I do have is that I know that there was some talk about separating this lot. And through you to the petitioner, is there is there going to be a subdivision of this lot? It is not proposed as part of this development at this time. In terms of in the future, that may be considered but
We are not proposing that as part of this application now. Yeah. Okay. And then the other question I had was the proposed number of spaces that are on
the particular leased lot, if you will. We're going to just call it a leased area or a leased lot. Have they been deducted from the parking of the main campus? That would be one concern that I have, you know, for obvious reasons that, you know, we don't want to reduce the amount of parking for the other, you know, for the other project. Although there was no controlling site plan, if I understand correctly from Danielle and Alicia, that it was somehow issued by right
which makes no sense to me, but I guess that's what happened. Was there an analysis done on the existing building and the parking requirements? Yeah. It was counted just in that little screen view of that portion of the lot itself, there's 172 parking spaces existing.
And then what we're proposing now is 117. So there is a reduction of, you know, again, quick math, 55 parking spaces in that area, but we had not performed an analysis on the entire shopping center with respect to the parking. I think it's, you know, maybe that needs to be done and back checked versus zoning just to confirm everything is in compliance.
But I think, you know, based on what we've seen in the field, and as evidenced by the screenshot that I took and displayed earlier tonight, that is just an underutilized parking lot, and there's relatively no cars parked in that area. Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Chair. Thank you. Board members, Jackie did I see your hand up.
Oh, I just can't hear you though. I was on mute, I apologize. So I live right across the street behind 61 Locust, and one of the things, as the point has said, it can be underutilized, but then there's times it's like, when it's bursting, right? And now that there's the Ford Tavern there, the Ford Tavern, I thought had some kind of a, I'm not sure, the city would know this more.
a partnership with that least parking that's right directly across the street from it and then when they're still over during the holidays from the metal glen mall that parking lot is used and if i'm not mistaken there's also a dog park there that is sometimes brings more cars so i'm just trying to figure out um
I'm glad that the commissioner brought up the parking issue because I'm trying to figure out where all of those cars would go, even though it's not pretty much utilized for, I don't know, 70% of the year, 30% is still a lot when you don't have parking. So I'm just trying to, in the absence of department head information from the traffic engineer, I guess I'm just,
It's a fair question, Jackie. And, you know, we can go back and do a little more homework in terms of, you know, we're not going to get a vote tonight, right? But we can do a little more homework on our end just to confirm, you know, what the parking counts are, you know, maybe across the entire shopping center or with respect to the other uses that are in the shopping center to confirm, you know, what is existing out there versus what we're proposing and what is required. I think that's a that's a takeaway for us.
Thank you. Thank you, good takeaway. Other questions from board members? Okay, I had a couple of questions. Can you walk us through how would a pedestrian coming off of Locust, right? That's the main street.
What's, what's the access or are those, do we have, you know, good quality PVA standard sidewalks that will will lead a pedestrian all the way to the bank from the, from the main road.
I know you didn't ask me, but thanks to that development that's on close to 61 Locust, we do. That actually came with a previous development. All right, so this view may be the best. There is an existing sidewalk. I'll start at this bottom lower left-hand corner.
There's existing sidewalk that traverses along the eastern side of Locust Street, across the driveway that exists out there now. Along, it runs up the access aisle, drive aisle, all the way to a point where the sidewalk then jogs across this access drive again, a little bit of a semicircle, and then crosses over to where
Marshalls is located. And at the same time, back at this point, we provide another connection from that same sidewalk system to the building itself. And I can kind of try to highlight that a little bit better for everybody on this. If you don't mind, my quick markups here.
That is your sidewalk system that exists out there today relatively flat and to our knowledge ADA compliant from the door to the street and also to the shopping center itself. Okay, great. Thank you for that. Amanda, your hand is up. I had other questions but
Thanks Mr. Chair, I had received a comment in from a member of the public I believe through our email and wasn't sure if now would be an appropriate time. I'm happy to yield to the member of the public who has something to share with us and I can my questions can wait until after that.
Okay, thank you. So actually, if the member of the public that is watching could perhaps identify themselves, because we will need your name and address for the record. But in the interim, the question was relating to, so there's currently a small dog area in the vicinity, and they were wondering if that area will be removed as a result of this proposal.
the dog area will remain. And just for everybody's reference, it sits up in this area where I just kind of drew a quick circle. And again, I could probably find another slide in this.
set that gives you a better reference point to it. And again, maybe this is a little bit better of a view. It sits up in this area, but that is outside of the limit of work that we're proposing. Okay. More, Amanda, or was that just? That's it. Okay. All right. Fair enough. Good question.
Do you know, Sir Lucas is this. So this, this is not just a drive through but this is going to be, I can walk in and do my banking there'll be a staff there'll be employees at the bank they're available during banking hours. That is correct. Okay. All right. And could you get the traffic engineers, I'm sure we'll be together and be able to talk about these sorts of things at the next meeting.
But can you just give me a flavor for the point where the two-way becomes a one-way? It just strikes me as a bit of a potential conflict there with cars trying to figure out which direction they're allowed to go in that northwest quadrant as we're looking at your screen right now.
sure yeah so i just kind of circled that area again and again let's assume traffic's coming in off of the access drive to the metaglen mall you'll you make a left into the site and you'll be able to traverse your way from the southbound side to the northbound side uh pick up parking along the way and continue along the back of the building where you can then enter the drive-through
or if you can't find a parking space, you'll be able to bypass and then recirculate around the building in a counterclockwise manner. Likewise, if you're coming in from that same area, if you were to make a left, an immediate left to go in front of the building, you would circulate around looking for a parking space and then, you know, would be blocked by the do not enters that sit at that
And you would then circulate around counterclockwise again to get back to that drive through if you had mistakenly not found that area. But really what you need that two way at the rear of this, so that way cars can kind of back out and then head towards the mall or exit back out onto Locust Street.
Sure, so I guess it would just be enlightening I think I won't be with you the next meeting but at the next meeting to have some indication like for instance, at the end of those two drive lanes you have wonderful indicators here for a stop, maybe giving the board a sense of what
what a driver would encounter or see in that corners are going to be some signage or something on the asphalt or some elevated sign or some indication that we're going from from two way to one way, I think would be helpful to see. Okay, I'll make another one. And I noticed while you had that zoomed that there's a, it looks like a fair amount of landscaping that's being added over there to the left of your drive lanes.
That is, that is correct we may have a better slide that gives you a little better indication of some of the landscaping that we're. Again, it's primarily a paved parking lot. So, we'll be decreasing the impervious coverage on the site itself and then introducing some more green, we're showing for trees along that left hand or the northern.
property line, and that as well as for trees in and around the building itself, as well as, you know, numerous shrubs and grasses and mulch beds in and around the parking field. Okay, great. Thank you. Other questions yes class. Hi. Given that this is my last meeting.
I'm gonna bang this drum one more time. I would encourage the proponent here and all future proponents to bring exhibits to these meetings which accurately display what you're trying to show. These are a series of technical drawings that
are, you know, at quick glance, very hard to understand, and they're overweighed with utility information, below grade information, a lot happening on one drawing that's making it very hard for us to really piece together all this information. So I would encourage you, and like I said, everybody going forward to think about that when you're presenting to a group of
people, some of which are lay people. So for next time, again, I think it would be important to have a rendered site plan with a better description of the landscaping that you're proposing here. For David's comment, a better understanding of how pedestrian circulation happens through the site, to the site,
and how traffic moves around the site, including, and definitely an understanding of the loss of parking and how that factors into the overall development or the, I wanna call it the Wegmans lot here. I think it's, I don't think, I personally don't have an issue with the loss of parking. I think it's better to see,
this kind of thing and more activity on the site. But I think just quantifying that will make a better argument for approval in the end. Thank you. Thank you. If I can piggyback on Clay's too, and I agree with all the suggestions, if there's a little bit more in terms of the building rendering than what you've presented here, even if it's a photo of a couple of other
banks that were have been constructed the last few years that are the model for this one. That's, that's all that those can be super helpful as well. All right. I'm not sure I can see everyone but is everyone satisfied in terms of questions for this evening.
Mr. Lucas, thank you for the presentation and answering the questions. Amanda, I presume we should try to find a date.
Yes, that would be I think that would be wise. So we don't it's not this is not a public hearing. So if we can't come to a date certain I'm assuming Bill, you'll probably want to confer with your colleagues and the rest of your applicant team on a date so we can
do this offline, but just for reference, the board meets every first and third Wednesday of the month for the most part. And so, you know, next meeting is July 5th. Agenda is actually wide open for that meeting, if you felt very confident about wanting to be there for that, or we can discuss offline. If you could tentatively put us down for July 5th, that'd be
fantastic and then I would in the meantime confer with Andy. Before we go too far, Danielle I see your hand is raised. Yes, I just also want to note that because planning staff did not see this at all before it was submitted, and we're just, we're basically in a hustle to get this on the agenda to not run afoul of
the process. Um, the land, the landscaping doesn't comply with our ordinance. Um, it doesn't have the requisite amount of interior landscaping. They have more than 20 spaces in a row. They're unbroken, which isn't allowed. They don't have the buffer strips. So we have to work on this and, um, get in touch with
whoever the landscaper or the landscaping designer is. The only communication I've had is with the permitting person. But yeah, we haven't had any pre-submission reviews, so it needs work. So I'm not sure that they will be ready on the 5th. I think that's unlikely. And given that that's the day after holiday, we might not even
have a quorum. Perhaps you'd want to push it out another meeting. Next meeting presumably would be on the 19th. Amanda, your head. Yes, that's correct. Is that an alternative that would be at least a good tentative date for everyone involved.
Mr Lucas that possibility for you. Yeah, it's a possibility for us. Obviously it sounds as if the critical path is, you know, getting the reviews completed by all the technical folks at Medford before we can, you know, see those and address them in a timely manner. The other input otherwise we can look for a motion to continue.
Motion to continue to say July. Okay, so a second for that. I'll second. Okay, thank you and I'll come right back to you on the roll call vice chair Jackie McPherson. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
Are you a Gulfman Fishman? Yes. And I'm a yes as well. Mr. Lucas, thanks very much. Appreciate it. Thank you. Have a good evening everyone. Thank you.
Okay, next item on the agenda, and I think it's just to mention by way of update was going to be the site plan review a continuation of the discussion we started our last meeting with each part at 285 to 95 mils like staff. And it looks like that is continued and will not be on the for us to discuss tonight. Amanda, am I, am I good there. Is that accurate.
Yeah, and I'll just announce that continued to July 5. Are those interested. Excellent. All right, next time you need to vote to continue it to that date. Oh, we do. Okay. All right, fair enough. I'll make a motion to continue to July 5.
And before we do a motion, we may not have a quorum, but we can just continue it in it. There's no quorum and it's just continuous. That's what I'm concerned with. Cause I know we're losing members and I myself will not be here July 5th. You can have one person like log on and vote to continue it. We used to have to do that in some roles sometimes. So we drive to city hall, be there to say I continue all the matters.
I know I will. I'm pretty sure I will be here. So, if we need somebody to log on. I'll be around to Peter. Okay, I second your motion. Right. Okay, so do we have we have a motion and we have a second, and let me start with a roll call again then.
I don't know if I got a second. I motion. I second Emily's and Emily you second Peter's for me. Yeah, I second. That's right. I came right back to Jackie on the roll call basis to ask her if she was a year and a. Okay. And she was a yes okay Clayson Dresen. Yes.
Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. And I'm a yes on the H mark continuance as well. Okay, thank you. Next item are the minutes from the May 3 2023 meeting comments on minutes. Oh.
Mr. Excuse me, sidebar here. Mr. Commissioner was that a wave goodbye. That was a wave goodbye actually I don't think that you are in need of my services any longer so thank you very much for your time and your courage. Thanks for being here we really appreciate it. Thank you. All right. Okay, back back two minutes. May 3 meeting. Any comments. I read them didn't didn't have any suggestions there myself.
But if barring any comments or discussion motion for approval of minutes. I'll vote to approve the minutes from 520 523 5323 5323. You got it. Okay. Is there a second for Jackie's motion.
Okay, thank you. And roll call to approve minutes from a third vice chair Jackie McPherson. Yes, class Andreessen. Yes, Christy down. Yes, Emily had. I'm going to abstain, I was not in attendance. Fair enough. Good point. Peter colors. Yes. All right, got my fishermen. Yes. Okay, and I'm good with the meetings I'm a yes as well.
Okay, miscellaneous items. Let me go back to Amanda, what do we have to share? Yeah, so several of you will be kind of terming out soon. And I wanted to, so I guess a couple of things. Well, first and foremost, thank you. Thank you, thank you, thank you.
And I think if we haven't talked already, it might be helpful to if each of you could reach out and let me know whether or not there's any availability on your end to participate in like a holdover status if needed.
Um, I mentioned it because we do have two candidates that were putting before the mayor for review. Um, but I just think, um, in the interest of being safe, it might be great to have an understanding of who might be available for another meeting. Um, So I lay that out there and I think kind of going off of that, um, I want to say was class had, um, thrown out the idea of having kind of an in person hangout. Um,
you know, before everyone goes different ways. And I think if folks were still, I haven't done any planning on that, I apologize, but if folks are still interested, I'd love to kind of just reanimate that conversation and we can do it offline, but just kind of wanted to temperature check if in the next couple of weeks that might be something of interest to y'all.
Let me, I'll hit you up, I'll hit you up offline, Amanda, on that one. Does that sound good? Sounds good. Okay, awesome. Okay. And yeah, so then other than that, next meeting technically we had, which is the fifth, we had scheduled for elections. If we're worried about quorum,
Maybe we want to rethink that a little bit. So actually, I don't know, temperature check. It sounds like Jackie, we knew you wouldn't be available. Emily and Peter, you said you would be. Ari, do you anticipate that you'll be around that meeting?
Yeah, there's a chance I might be in a car from the Cape, depending on how bad traffic is, but I can tune in by phone if necessary, if running late. Yeah. Okay. Let's...
I feel like we should play that by ear a little bit, especially based on whether we turn around the candidate reviews by the mayor. So I guess we'll be in touch on that as well. That could easily be shifted to a subsequent meeting.
And last, we did get a PDD submission for 243 Mystic Ave, which was Verdant Bio, which if you recall, they've been in front of you guys a couple of times for kind of informal feedback. So they're aiming for the July 19th meeting. So that's something exciting to look forward to as far as discourse goes. And I think that's all I had unless Alicia or Danielle had anything else they wanted to add.
All good. All good. Okay, well, I'll take the last moment of chairpersonship to thank everyone involved, obviously, fellow board members for everything that you do and as hard as you work and you've always been very patient with all of my mistakes and I thank you for that. And to our wonderful city staff, Alicia, for all of your hard work and
care for the city and Danielle. It's been great working with you. And of course, superstar Amanda, who has spent so many, so many hours talking to me offline about various things. So I always appreciate your patience and, and your input as well. So, thank you. With that, I think we can talk about emotion to adjourn.
Would someone like to offer one. Well, I will tell you offline, I'll pick up the conversation offline but I want to thank you for meeting us, Mr. Chair. That's for sure, because I know even in preparation within my seat, it's it's a heavy lift and I can only imagine all that you had to do to keep up so I appreciate all done I think I can't speak for the board, but
It gives me angst to know that we're going to lose you in leading that. Because I'm sure that, like myself, all of us want to see the city pull forward with these planning projects and things like that. But it's kind of hard, the capacity of it, the bandwidth of it, right? So we are very appreciative. I'm very appreciative of all you've done to keep us straight.
You're the best. Thank you very much. I appreciate that. If you didn't mention mistakes, I wouldn't know that they existed. I certainly second that. I started it. Thank you. Thank you very much. All right. Perhaps now a motion to adjourn. I'll give a motion to adjourn. All right, in a second. I will say.
All right, last roll call here we go last time I call it out vice chair Jackie McPherson. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. I'm a yes as well. Thanks again everyone and have a great night. Hope to see all of you very soon.