Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Vice-president Behrs. Present. Councilor Collins. Present. Councilor Knight. I know he's gonna join remotely, but I don't see him yet. Councilor Scarpelli. Present. Councilor Sang. Present. President Morrell. Present. Councilor Kerrio. Yes, six present, one absent. Everyone, please rise and salute the flag.
visible. The motion by Councilor Scott Kelly, you suspend the rules, seconded by Councilor Collins. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Vice President bears. Yes. Council Collins. Yes. Council night. Councilor Scott Kelly. Councilor saying President Morrell. Yes.
Councilor Kerrio? Yes, six in the affirmative, one absent. Motion passes. We'll suspend the papers to take paper 22067, petition for a common fixture license by Ramon Kumar, 38 Lawrence Street, Belmonts, for Omori Pizza and Kitchen, 509A High Street, Medford Mass. I'm referring this over to the chairman of licensing, Councilor Scott Kelly. Thank you, Mr. President. If the petition is here, you can come to the rail.
Welcome. I've reviewed the process, Mr. President. I find everything in order. Do you, your times of opening closing, do you know what they will be? We're looking at around 15th of February, you know, for closing. So as soon as we're done here, you know, I'm gonna start the process. Okay, but then the hours of operations.
It's going to be the same hours. Everything stays the same. I'm going to keep everything the same. The menu, everything's going to be the same. And number of employees? Same. So you're just seamless, just a quick turnover. Yes. So I'm just going to, like I said, change of ownership, basically. I'm going to take over. Well, Mr. President, I see that Mr. Kumar has put everything in order. It's been approved by all the departments. So I move forward favorably. Thank you. Do we have any discussion? Seconded. Seconded by Councilor Baez. Do we have any discussion on this?
Hearing and seeing none, Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Yes, seconded by Councilor Bears.
vice president bears. Yes. Thank you. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Thank you so much. So do I have to pick up any
Okay, thank you. Have a good night. Thank you. Mr. President. While we're under suspension, can we take communications from the mayor? Paper 22068. On the motion by council members to take 22068 out of
Under suspension, dear Madam President and Councilors, I respectfully request and recommend that your Honorable Board approves under Mass General Laws, Chapter 44, Section 53A, donations in the amount of $1,210 to be used for Agent Four funds that were donated by the friends and family of the late Daniel Bates Jr.
In lieu of flowers, we respectfully submitted Brianna Longo Kern, Mayor. And Mr. President, I see Chief Friedman is here on Zoom with us. I move approval, Mr. President. I think we all know what a great man Mr. Bates was. Absolutely. We have the chief online? Yes, I am here, Chief Friedman.
Good evening. I'd like to thank you for putting this on the agenda. This is something that during the transition that, you know, kind of got missed and I'd like to get this donation, you know, to where it needs to be. And that's the purpose I'm before you tonight. I second Councilor Knight's motion to approve. Thank you. Any further discussion on this? On the motion.
by Council Scott Kelly, seconded by Councilor biz. Mr. Clerk, please call the role. Vice President bears. Yes. Council Collins. Yes. Council night. Yes. Councilor Kelly. Yes. Councilor saying yes. Yes.
Councilor Kerrio. Yes. Six, seven affirmative motion passes. I just spent in 20 to zero three seven. While on the suspension by Councilor Scott to take paper two to zero three seven. City of Bedford, notice of a public hearing. The city council will hold a public hearing in the chambers at City Hall, 85 George B. Hassell Drive in Bedford on Tuesday, February 1st, 2022 at seven o'clock on a petition from
Oberlin Abazi of Obie's Auto Service to operate in automotive repair and auto body shop, last floor license at 38 Harbin Avenue, Meffitt, in a commercial one, C1 zone, Zoom link will be provided, no later than January 28, 2022. Petitions and plans may be seen at the office of Meffitt City Clerk, Meffitt Mass. With this public hearing, anyone in favor of this,
please make themselves known. Anyone in favor of this? We may have someone on the line. Thank you. So I got to unmute myself. I don't know why. Hi, good evening, everyone.
Name and address of the record, please. 38 Harvard Ave., Orbelina Bazzi, Obie's Auto Service. Thank you. And you are in favor of this, correct? You are in favor? Yes, I'm sorry. Thank you very much. Anyone else in favor? Seeing and hearing none, we motion to close this part of the meeting. Is there anyone in opposition to this license hearing? Anyone in opposition?
Mr. Clerk, anyone in opposition on the thing? Hearing and seeing none, motion to close this. Mr. Abbasi, if you could give us a little synopsis of what you're doing here. Automotive service and repairs and auto body services. We're going to continue on the steps of Mike Fantasia that was here before. And I'm very happy to work in the city of Memphis.
and we'll make sure that we'll do great work with the neighbors and everybody else. Okay. Does anyone have any questions for Mr. Abbasi? Mr. Abbasi, I have one question for you. I've got a little bit concerned where I think this council just approved
This license, I think, I think it's been maybe less than a year. And now I see there's another one going in here and that gives me a little bit of a red flag for me. And I see where we have a potential brewery going next door and I hate to see changes keep on happening in that neighborhood. What happened is the partnership and didn't work out.
And I had to take this on my own because this is something I've been doing for the last year. That's why I was running the place last year. We're doing great business. I didn't get enough help. So I got to do this for myself where I got to do it for other people. That's all I say doing it just so I have a little bit of a flag when we keep seeing when something changes on this short of a period.
Any other questions for the gentleman? Hearing and seeing none, Chair awaits a motion. Mr. President, I do have a quick question. What is the proposed use that's warranting the council to review for special permit? That was my question. The reason I ask is because if you look at our zoning ordinance, it says if we get an application for certain uses,
uses 12, 22, 23, 24, 27, 30, 31, 33, 34, and 49A, those matters should go to the community development board before the council takes a vote on them. So in terms of just compliance with the law, I was just wondering where we were on that, if this in fact was an application for one of those items.
Do you have an answer for the council? I think that would be more of a question for the building commissioner or the city solicitor than this gentleman. I think he's just an applicant and the use is really not something that he'd be classifying his facility within a table of use chart. That would be a determination that would be made by the building commissioner.
So, Mr. President, I agree with constant I that's my. This didn't come in for the license of petition so I was a little confused with this also, not to say that.
you know, the petitioner, Mr Bazzi that I'm against it. But I think that, like Council night said, I don't know if we should move forward with this until we get again. This is where having legal representation here, um, you know, for the council would help move this along. Now we're looking at
And I'm going to recommend that we table this to next week, date certain till we get the answer from either the building commissioner or the city solicitor, making sure that we're voting on
on something that we're apprised of, because like Councilor Knight says, I don't see a distinguished item that tells us why we need the special permit. So I would look to table for one week and just to get this answer. This could be just a simple question, simple answer. And again, to the petitioner, Mr. Abbasi, this isn't,
Any affirmation of that, I don't wanna support this because if it's just straight what it is, I see it's in order. But again, I don't know what the underlying reason for it hasn't been defined yet to this body. So I would recommend that we table this for one week. Mr. Paziev, do you plan on selling used cars there? At some point, yes, I will apply for that too.
Yeah, just be advised that you will need to get a license for that also. So on the motion, Councilor Scott Pele to table this for one week to get an opinion from the building department. City solicitor, please. And the solicitor. Seconded by Councilor Knight. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Yes. Yes.
Mr. President, I just want to be clear. If we're going to ask the question to the city solicitor, I think we better put it in appropriate terms. The question to the solicitor would be, does this application fall within the scope of section 94-81 subsection B of the Medford zoning ordinance?
Thank you. Motion by Councilor Scott Felder, seconded by Councilor Ntuk and amended by Councilor Ntuk. Yes.
Yes, 70 affirmative, motion passes. Motion to revert back to regular business by- So if we can, Mr. President, just let the petitioner know, I know that before we rush off, I know he's still on, just that we're just asking for the question to be answered, and then we'll bring this up again next week. Okay, thank you. Mr. Abbasi, did you get that? Yes, I did. Thank you, sir, see you next week. Thank you. You guys have a good night.
Motion by Counselor saying we've heard back to regular business second by Counselor is the clerk please call the roll. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
Yes, seven affirmative and a negative motion. Passes. Motions, orders, and resolutions. 22057, offered by Councilor Scott Kelly and Councilor Kerrio, be it resolved that the Memphis City Council send its condolences to the family of Brian Branson on his recent passing. Brian was the true definition of a Metro Mustang, and we have lost a true champion for the blue light. Councilor Scott Kelly. Mr. President, thank you very much.
It's a sad, it's a sad day with the passing of Brian. Brian is what Medford Mustang pride and heart is all about. He fought a courageous battle with cancer, and anybody who
who came across Brian in the middle of his darkest days, you would never know that he was battling this illness. He had a smile on his face. He always, first person to volunteer, donate whenever, especially when it came to kids, he was always there. I still remember it was maybe 94 degrees. We were having a,
a wiffle ball tournament in the name of Jimmy Maturana who passed recently for raising money for his scholarship fund. And then after that, they were going to play the first baseball game at the new Jimmy Maturana Field. And Brian plays in the tournament. It's 97 degrees.
He goes through the whole celebration and then he ducks out and comes back wearing about 40 pounds of umpire equipment because he's now going to umpire for the kids so they can play the baseball game. In the middle of all this, he's battling this horrible disease. And that's exactly who Brian was. I mean, when you talk to people tonight at his wake, when I talked to his family,
He is what makes Medford a great community. He was there to help anybody who needed help. And he always did it with a smile on his face. And to his children, to his sisters, to his friends, we are going to miss his physical being
in our community forever. But I will tell you for one person, Brian's memory will never be forgotten because he left that impression on everybody that crossed his path. So those who didn't know him, talk to me if you see me, we'll talk about a few stories and just a great man. And again, I think in the last couple of years, I've said this too often,
But we're saying goodbye to another Mefford icon, someone who left a mark in this community and never asked for anything in return. So to his family, we send our condolences, our prayers, our memories. If we could dedicate this meeting, Mr. Clerk, in his honor, I would love to do that. And thank you for allowing me to speak. Thanks. Thank you, Councilor Scapi. Would anyone else like to speak?
I'd like to say a few words. I think Councilor Scott Pelley put it quite eloquently. Brian always had a smile on his face, no matter when you see him and everybody knew how he was suffering with that deadly disease. But again, not an old man, but a young man who taken too soon from us. And again, like Councilor Scott Pelley says, this is a man who bled to blue and white all the time.
uh, his family, uh, you know, anything for the community. He was there. And like I said, uh, shame and another icon in our community passes. And unfortunately we don't have people stepping up to fill the shoes of, of, of a Brian Branson.
So I hope people start stepping up and take the place of men like him that did things, that put the volunteers in this community that people like him did. So again, to his family, our condolences. Anyone else wanna speak? So on the motion by Councilor Scott Felly, seconded by Councilor Sang. Moment of silence, Mr. President. Moment of silence. If we could have a moment of silence.
like please call the roll. Vice President bears. Yes. Council calls. Yes. Councilor night. Yes. Councilor Kelly. Yes. Councilor saying yes. President Morrell.
Councilor Kerrio. Yes. 70 affirmative. Another negative motion passes to two zero five nine offered by Councilor Collins. We have resolved that Memphis City Council expresses support the Senate bill one five seven nine and accompanying the house bill two four one eight and act to protect the civil rights and safety of all Massachusetts residents also known as Safe Communities Act. If I first, I'm sorry, I'm gonna do five eight zero five eight.
Oh, I'm reading that. Oh, I'm sorry, I read it wrong. I apologize. I'm sorry. Offered by Vice President Bez and Councilor Collins, being resolved at Memphis City Council that a community control over public surveillance ordinance be considered by Public Health and Community Safety Subcommittee. Vice President Bez. Thank you, Mr. President. The resolution is relatively self-explanatory, but just to
to explain what a community control over public surveillance ordinance is, that ordinance would create a public process where if any part of the city wanted to implement surveillance technologies, that they would just have to be approved through a public process approved by this city council. So the motion is to consider such an ordinance in the public health and community safety subcommittee, and I defer to my co-sponsor, Councilor Collins.
Thank you, and thank you, Vice President bears for introducing this resolution. Just want a second. Thank you. Yes, just a second everything that Vice President bears already said this resolution is to create a public process.
You know, so to create, you know, a routinized way to have a clear routine process for any agency that wishes to deploy a public surveillance technology to outline why they would like to use it, for what purpose, how this information will be collected and used to make sure that we have a very clear and structured process to bring the public into that deliberation and decision process when surveillance technologies are proposed for use in our community.
I think it's a great transparency measure, and I'd like for it to be taken up by the Public Safety and Community Health Subcommittee. Thank you. Any further discussion? Councillor Zang. On this issue, particularly, I think it's important to realize the role that power imbalances play.
in in surveillance and how it affects how you surveillance data, you know, I am a strong believer that whoever has power should should also get some oversight, and that applies to us as as city counselors as well. But in this case, I think, you know, those people with people who are using public surveillance have this access to power and I think it's fair for
members of our community to ask for some transparency, to ask for some oversight as well. Thank you, Councilor. Any further discussion? So on the motion by Vice President Beas, seconded by Councilor Collins. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Refer to the Subcommittee on Public Health and Community Safety.
Vice President bears. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
2418, an act to protect civil rights and safety of all Massachusetts residents, also known as the Safe Communities Act. We are afraid to resolve that the city clerk forwarded a copy of this resolution to the legislative delegation, as well as chairs of the Joint Committee on Public Safety and Homeland Security, Timothy and Gonzales. Councilor Collins.
Thank you, Mr. President. This is a bill that I've heard about from many Medford residents, and I see it as being very in line with our community's values so I'm glad for the opportunity to request my fellow counselors support in endorsing it. For a little bit of background, this act would shore up basic civil rights protections for undocumented people throughout the state, and of course, by inclusion, our community as well.
You know, currently, insecurity about immigration status and the specter of deportation keeps many people from seeking the help and support that they need from police, from medical providers, and in other settings. So this act would restrict the circumstances during which law enforcement is allowed to inquire about a person's immigration status.
Um, you know, essentially the act would make it so people less feel like they have to, uh, you know, avoid calling for help when they're in crisis because of what that call could result in in terms of an arrest or deportation. Um, so I see the measures of this act as being very aligned with our community's existing goals of making sure that our public safety and health resources can actually reach every and any person in Medford who needs it regardless of their background. And I respectfully, uh, ask for my fellow counselors approval.
Thank you. Um, thank you, Mr President. Uh, how's the constant to bring this forward? I think that, um, I've seen how terrible this affects immigrant communities. I think that I've had the privilege of working with a lot of great families and great individuals that, um, just even recently with the elimination of the Dream Act and, um,
these young men and women that came to this country when they were infants, and find themselves now without a home. They're not familiar with their parents' home country, and they're being told that they're not citizens of the country they were raised and grew up with and pay taxes in, and they find themselves left in limbo.
Anything we can do to support that, I would champion that as well. So I appreciate bringing this forward and I would move, second the resolution. Any further discussion? Councilor Sang? No. Okay.
I also support this resolution. I thank my fellow councillor for bringing this forward. You know, I've, like Councillor Scarpelli, I've worked with and grew up with a lot of, you know, friends who are undocumented and I know how difficult it is for them to, you know, just live as normal human beings in our society. And, you know, especially as we've all, as I've kind of
become more of a leader in the community, a lot of people ask me, can I use this resource without being told that I might be deported one day? Can I turn to the police? Can I turn to fire? Can I turn to a medical resource? Can I turn to a state resource? What can I apply for? And it becomes confusing. And a lot of this stuff affects all of us, right? If we're thinking about public health,
We are all healthier if all of us have access to services. We're all safer if all of us feel comfortable reporting, you know, reporting incidents. And so I think it's very important that we support this. Thank you, Councilor. Councilor Biss. Vice President Biss. Thank you, Mr. President. I'll be brief. I just wanted to add that I think it's important to add our voice to this chorus. Anyone familiar with the State House knows that it is
joint rule 10 week, which means it's the last week, unless extensions are requested for bills to be reported out of their committees to be considered this session.
And as everyone has said, all the reasons that this is incredibly important. And there's a really broad coalition of folks from, you know, progressive legislators and I believe all four of our legislative delegation to the police chiefs who would find this to be incredibly valuable as well. So I'm glad we're taking this up. Thank you, Mr. Vice President.
Mr. President, thank you very much. I certainly have no problem supporting this measure this evening. I would like to remind everybody that no piece of legislation comes out the way it goes in. And when we look at what's going on at the State House, we'll see that there are thousands and thousands of bills that are filed every year. And if this council is going to be focused on our goals and priorities, I think our goals and priorities should be that that fall within our purview. However, this is a meritorious resolution that I will have no problem supporting this evening.
However, I do want us to earn the side of caution and to move forward in a fashion where we're not taking up items that we are dealing with the deal with the state legislature when we elected a state legislature to do that for us. I think we have a very capable representation up on Beacon Hill. And if we're going to be taking up state items and state bills every week, it's going to make for very long and unproductive sessions. So with that being said, Mr. President, I certainly will support this this evening.
However, I'd hate to see this become a trend of every week that we're sitting here, voicing support for this piece of legislation and that piece of legislation that's outside of scope and purview of authority. Thank you for the discussion. Okay, on the motion by Council Collins, seconded by second.
Vice President bears. Yes. Council Collins. Yes. That's a night. Yes. Councilor Scarpelli. Yes. Councilor saying, Yes. President Morrell. Yes. That's okay. Yes, I mean the primitive, none of the negative on passes to 2060 offered by Councilor
Be it resolved that the Memphis City Council congratulate Paula Keefe, Linda Pittorino, and Patty Wright on their retirement from the Consumer Advisory Commission. Through their efforts, Memphis consumers have saved hundreds of thousands of dollars over the years through the work of these people. Be it further resolved that the administration provide the council with a plan on how this office will be kept open going forward. So,
I wanna thank the three women who've been there 30 plus years. I think Paul has been there maybe close to 40 for the hard work that they've done that have saved hundreds of thousands of dollars to consumers in our community. I am a little concerned that all three women decided to retire at the same time, which for me sends up a little bit of a red flag. And now the office is closed.
I would hope that the mayor work with the Attorney General's office to get that office open again as soon as possible. So again, I wanna thank the woman for the years of service to our community, but I also wanna ask the mayor to please get that office open. They do great work for the consumers of Medfin and some of the surrounding communities. Any further discussion? Mr. President.
Councilor Morocco. Thank you, Mr. President, I want to thank you for putting this down. You know, this is a lesser known office. And as we've seen the budget, you know, it's funded at a pretty minimum level. But the work they do is very important. I've had residents that I've been able to send their way resident had a really big issue with the contractor, and they were able to get it resolved through this office. So I echo your thanks for the women staffing this office for so long and share your concern and
and push to make sure we get this office staff because the what is offered at the state level doesn't compare to what is offered at the city level and the speed at which they can turn things around and work with local folks for residents in need. So I thank you for bringing this forward. Thank you, Madam President. Any further discussion? Mr. President. Thank you, Mr. President and through you to Linda, Paula and Patty.
who I've been fortunate enough to develop a great friendship with over the years. Thank you for the work that you've done. I've been a strong advocate for the Consumer Office since my election to the City Council, and I've always felt that they were the unsung heroes in City Hall. These individuals are trained by the Attorney General to handle consumer complaints and disputes. They do an excellent job in resolving matters of
anything from scams to the cold cut machine, not being accurate at the supermarket and you overpaying, um, they've done an excellent job. And, um, one thing I know about the three of these women is that they really loved what they did. They really loved their job so much so that, um, when the state grant was cut, um, the ladies worked out a job sharing schedule so that nobody would lose their job.
They were truly a group of people that cared about each other and worked together as a family. This office was created in 1978. It was created as the benefit consumer commission and its first commissioner was the late great Michael Callahan, our governor's counselor. And Michael took great pride in this office. And he was one of his greatest accomplishments in his 50 years of government service. And when you look at what's going on from a human resource standpoint in city hall,
Look it, three individuals with 90 years of combined service don't just walk out the door on the same day because they're happy. All right? I wish them the best of luck in their retirement, but we need to get to the bottom of what's going on in Medford City Hall, because it's getting to be embarrassing. I heard this morning another employee was escorted off the premises and told that they need to submit to a psychological evaluation. I've been told that these three individuals were told that they need to be replaced with younger and more energetic employees, which led
to really a retirement in duress. So while I don't want to rain on the parade of the great work that these three individuals have done in the community, I also think that we as a council owe it to them to investigate as to what's going on and to why the three of them would have left on the same day so abruptly. So with that being said, Mr. President, I rest my case. I thank them for their service and I congratulate them on their retirement, wish them the best and let them know that they always have a friend in me.
Thank you, Councilor. Councilor Scarpelli. Thank you, Mr. President. And again, I echo the sentiments of my colleagues. I think that we had three dedicated people in a very important office. And I think that when you talk about our senior citizens, the most vulnerable members of our community, they were the ones that really needed this office more than anyone, because they are the ones that were being manipulated. And having this office in place really put
someone that they could reach out to at any time to make sure that they're protected. And if I, if I'm not mistaken, I believe the Attorney General has
has acknowledged their office many times on the job well done because of their excellence. So again, it's gonna be sad losing them, but thanking them for everything they've done for our community. And when you can do something, when you walk out the door, knowing that you left a positive mark, I think that you should keep your head high and really applaud what you've done for this community.
As one counselor, I applaud them and thank them for everything they've done. Thank you for the discussion. Oh, on the motion by Councilor Kerrio-Viello, seconded by Councilor Scarpelli. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Vice President Behrs. Yes. Councilor Collins. Yes. Councilor Knight. Yes. Councilor Scarpelli. Yes.
Councilor Hussain. Yes. President Morrell. Yes.
Councilor Kerrio. Yes. Negative. Motion passes to 2061 offered by Councilor saying it comes to call him. We resolve that the Memphis City Council expresses support for House Bill 3559 and actual neck relative to public transit, transit electrification. We have further resolved that city clerk forward copy of this resolution for the method. Let's say of delegation as well as House Speaker Mariano and Senate President Spilka. Councilor saying
Thank you. I wanted to first note my colleagues' concerns about us introducing these resolutions in support of state legislation, but I wanted to say, just in full transparency, that on my end, I had a conversation with Representative Christine Barber about this, and she asked me to come to the council to ask for our support on this specific bill.
And this is a good bill because I think it would, or let me just lay it out very, very clearly. This bill would electrify MBTA and RTA, commuter rail service, and the bus fleet by the year 2035.
Studies have shown that this bill would reduce the CO2 emissions by millions of pounds. And this bill would also create a standardized assessment system to measure air quality in our communities. This bill would benefit Medford because we have, we have bus service in the city, we have a commuter rail station that goes through West Medford.
And air quality is all has always been an issue when it comes to transit when it comes to bus and commuter rail service. And so this is, you know, this aligns with our communities values aligns with addressing our communities concerns and aligns with our communities already stated goals.
Thank you, Mr. President, thank you, counselor saying for putting this forward and just want to echo all of that and also add that I think one of the reasons this is you know important and relevant to our community here in Medford is, as counselor saying mentioned this bill would require that electric bus fleet to be expedited for routes that go through environmental justice communities.
including some of our neighbors in Somerville and Everett, and so adjacent communities close to those cities in Medford or those that share bus routes through those neighborhoods would also reap the benefits of this priority electrification for those transit routes. So respectfully ask for our fellow councilors support for this bill, especially as Vice President Beers mentioned during this final week of pushing bills out of subcommittee. Thank you. Any further discussion? Mr. President?
I saw actually I'll defer to President Morrell. Thank you vice president bears Thank you, Mr. President, I just wanted to know, and add on to what Councillor Collins and Councillor saying said you know, this goes beyond the actual buses traveling and our fleets traveling because we have things like the fellows way bus garage where I've been talking with, you know,
one resident and many residents are impacted by the diesel exhaust that goes on there. So these are residents that are very close to the space. They're affected by the emissions that happen in that space frequently and go right into their homes. So I think the councilors for bringing this forward, I fully support it. And I think this is something that impacts Medford in a number of ways. And I hope it's something that the state actually advances on. Thank you. Thank you, Madam President. Vice President Bizz.
Thank you, Mr President. Um, and that's exactly what I was going to say. I just want to add, um, that while some of the efforts of by the council and our legislators were for a time effective at making sure that idling and bright lights and loud noises were not occurring late night. Over at the Felsway bus yard in Haines Square. That problem has recurred. I have been working with the city clerk to contact representatives at the MBTA
And I also know that Representative Paul Donato and Mayor Lugo-Kern have also been trying to work with the MBTA to make it so that we don't have 75 diesel buses idling at 11pm with bright floodlights. It's creating pretty serious impacts on the surrounding community in Haines Square. So hopefully, obviously this would address it in the long term, also hoping that we can address it in the short term. Thank you.
Does the sponsor of this resolution have any idea if this will impact the MBTA assessment on the city of medicine. I don't know it sounds like it's going to cost about a billion bucks and pretty sure we're going to be caught paying for it.
The city of method is one of the hot one, I think it's number four or five and assessment by the T in the Commonwealth of Massachusetts so we pay a pretty, pretty steep price to have to see running through our community. I'm not aware that it is the assessment for any of the impacted communities at all I think that this is a statewide plan for procuring and implementing in a staggered way the electrification.
of the buses, the bus charging stations. To my knowledge from reading the text of the bill, didn't mention anything about the assessment of the community's fees to the MBTA. That would probably come from the MBTA advisory board if the measure passed and was ever ended up funded. Number one. Number two, the governor's budget has come out. The governor's budget is not that pretty.
Um, again, if we're going to be sending letters up to the state house, I think the letters that we should be sending up to the state house, they give us more chapter 90 money, give us more local aid money, give us more money for our schools. Um, and you know, when you give everybody a, when you ask, when you ask for two slices and you get a half a slice, you can't complain. Um, but if he asked for one slice and you only, you know, you only give them an option to give you one slice, then, um, you gotta, you're in a better position of power from negotiation. Um, so I'd hate to see us be in a situation where we're.
sending letters up to every single chairman up in the state house, asking for this and asking for that. And at the end of the day, we're passing a ceremonious legislation and we're not cashing in on our ability to get the big bucks. Um, you know, it's a great, great idea. You know, something that certainly, uh, uh, sounds like a pie in the sky, um, possibility. Um, but you know, it's going to have to be funded. It's not going to be funded, um, through the forward funding mechanism that they have right now.
through the sales tax because it's going to cost way too much to do that. So it's going to come down to an assessment on our community as well. So there will be a financial impact there. As Councilor Caviello did say, our community is super assessed when it comes to the MBTA and our services are lacking. We've seen service cuts across the board from bus service to commuter rail service to express bus service. So, you know, that's something to think about, you know, are we going to ask for more, pay for more and get less. Is that something we want?
But it also has environmental and economical impacts that will, you know, make a difference here in our community from a public health standpoint. So it's something we need to think about in a way. That's why we have a state legislature. Any further discussion. Just Mr. President, if I may.
Thank you to counselor nice point. You know, I was looking at the fiscal 23 cherry sheet, which is the basically proposed inflows and outflows of state money into the city. And our MBTA assessment was just over $4 million. But we are sending over $9 million a year out of this community to fund private charter schools, you know, and only getting $1 million back.
definitely also agree about the issues with chapter 90 being level funded and local aid being, you know, two and a half percent again. So there's a lot of things that need to be fixed, but certainly I think we can all on this council agree that addressing the charter school funding formula, which is draining, you know, a huge chunk of our city revenue would be a priority as well. Thank you, Mr. Vice presidents. Okay. Any further discussion?
So on the motion by Councilor saying Councilor Collins, seconded by second, seconded by Councilor beers. Mr. Clerk please call the roll. Vice President bears. Yes. Council calls. Yes. Council night.
Councilor Scarpelli. No. Councilor Sang. Yes. President Morrell. Yes. Councilor Kerrio. Well, when you primitive three negative motion passes to 2006 to offer my council saying be resolved that the Memphis City Council so celebrate Black History Month and support episode community city government schools to combat racism and white supremacy and teach black history.
Yeah, um, many members of our community every shot to me over the course of campaign but also as a counselor, asking to see our city, you know, even showed the symbolic steps to toward towards supporting diversity and equity in our city. And so this is one of those.
those pieces, those resolutions that reflect what constituents have been telling me. I think, you know, this aligns with our community's values. You know, we are an anti-racist community. We are a diverse community. And I think our community has been making a lot of steps forward in terms of talking about Black history, addressing racism in our community. And, you know, I think we've made strides
together and talking earnestly and honestly about the two ideologies, racism and white supremacy, whose historical and sociological effects seep into the structures that shape our society. You know, these aren't things that are, you know, these
are targeted at any community in particular, you know, it's not just it's not just you know it's not a white person issue this is something that you know happens in the Asian community as well that I know very well of. And so this is about all of us kind of coming together saying.
telling history as it is because it's important to learn from our past, it's important to celebrate our past as well, because that's where we find unity is in telling the truth about about our city and about our history and, you know, looking positively towards the future to see how we move on. Thank you.
Yes, I'd like to thank Councilor Singh for bringing this forward. You know, I think you said it very well. Black history and Medford's history are inextricably woven. So I'd be proud to see Black History Month be celebrated even more loudly in our community and to have this be a moment for recommitting to investing in black voices, black futures, standing together against bigotry and systemic injustice. And I'd move for approval. Thank you. Vice President Biz. Thank you, Mr. President.
Um, and, uh, in a moment, if my fellow counselor would be so amenable to an amendment, I will propose one. But, um, you know, I think especially at this moment in time, as we're seeing the banning of books, the banning of thought, the banning of debate,
intentionally put forward across this country and in media to constrict and define our history in a way that is untruthful. I think it's important for us, as a place that doesn't do that, to make it very loud and clear why we don't do that. Because that's a very dangerous and corrosive ideology that's
spreading and moving through our society. So just to be more specific in this resolution, I'd like to amend the resolution to put a comma after the phrase to combat racism and then replace the words and white supremacy with the following phrase. Mr. Clerk, let me know when you're ready.
It looks like a ready. And the phrase is to address the growing danger of white supremacy and white supremacist ideology as well publicized by the United States Department of Justice, Southern Poverty Law Center, Anti-Defamation League, and other leading watchdogs, comma. And I put forward that amendment hopefully with the support of the sponsor.
just to be specific about what's happening right now and why it's important for us to speak out about the true reality of what's happened and also where we need to go.
Thank you, Mr. Vice President. So, Councilor Scott-Bell. If I can, thank you very much. I had a nice discussion with Councilor Sangin in support of this resolution, but I will also share some comments that were shared with me from residents that were a little concerned that the understanding of white supremacy
in the inference that there are running rampant of white members of our community in white supremacy. And it really paints a picture
negative tone of unity in that light. I think that I support totally support the celebrating a black history month. I support that the city is city government, the schools, we combat racism and teach black history. I know that in my conversations with different
different educators and as we talk moving this topic forward and not just being just talk like it was mentioned with some members of the community that I had discussions with and putting our money where our mouth is and asking the city to ask the school committee to look at bringing back civics. So everybody understands where we are and a quarter of that civics lesson
Bing!
the focal point to black history in Medford and black history. I think that's something that I've mentioned in the past in moving steps forward. So it's not just talk, it's not just rhetoric, but I know that I asked council's saying to see if we could find other wording when it came to white supremacy, because unfortunately in some people in this community that it doesn't unify, it's really dividing our community in the sense that
people don't look at it the way that it's addressed, because they think that every white person is being dressed as a white supremacist. And I think that's not the message you're trying to send in our conversation. And I like what Councilor Beas, Vice President Beas mentioned that the intent
might be more defined so our residents can understand that this isn't something that you put through to divide or made it so that it's one person against another. It's a unified feeling that we want Medford to be exactly what we've been trying to work for, and that's a community of one.
again if we could in and changing that I would support it if not unfortunately I would just vote present on this because I do other pieces in this this resolution I support a thousand percent and I would I would also make it uh
you know, asked to amend it and to reach out to the school committee and asked to bring back civics and adding a whole block in method black history because we have plenty of it here. And I think that this is how we're going to start the change
at the younger level where people understand where the black history method was I mean that I've talked to one of my closest friends who is educated man of color and said that with the with he would love to be.
given the opportunity to go to the post office when the concern was with the mural, with our slaves being in shackles. And this is what everybody sees when they go to the post office. And he made it a point to me and said, George, you know what? We would love to see that. Leave it there. Let our kids see what this history was about and how devastating it was. And
using that type of philosophy, where you look at the Royal House and the slave wall, and we'll talk about so many benefits and so many educational points we can use in this community, that bringing that class back and use that as a jumping off point to really educate our community, I would support it a thousand percent. Thank you, Councilor Scott. Councilor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much. I think it's important when we look at this,
resolution what it says. It says celebrate and support. Now, when we talk about the debate and discussion that we've had over a resolution that's asked for us to celebrate and support something versus what we did in our first four meetings, I think we spent 3 million bucks in our first four meetings and we've talked less about it than we've talked about this topic right here. Okay, so it's a resolution that's symbolic in nature that says let's celebrate and support this unity. And I certainly don't have a problem with that.
But what I do have a problem with is that the budget has been passed now for quite a bit of time and we still don't have a director of diversity in the school department or on the city side. So, you know, when we talk about things, let's really talk about them. Let's, let's, let's, let's put the issues out there. Let's lay it out there. You know, we still don't have a diversity director. We still don't have a diversity director. It's been three years, no diversity director.
So if we're going to make the commitment, let's really make the commitment. If we're going to talk about it, let's walk about it too. That's where I'm coming from, Mr. President. So I certainly support this resolution. I have no problem with it. Like I said, it's a resolution that asks us to support something. I have no problem doing that. Um, so for that reason, I'll be voting for that this evening. Uh, and if I can make a, um, I agree with council Scott, I think, uh, um, I think the languages, uh, could be, uh,
change a little bit, and I would support it with the white supremacy. I think that might be good, might be taking a little time. Councilor Layton is right. We're three years without a diversity director in the city, and that's something that we've asked for, both in the budget and I think last year that was part of our council priorities was the diversity director. And nothing has happened, we don't have a diversity director.
on the high schools, on the school side either. So again, you know, we, you know, we want to talk, but you know, we can talk all we want, but if we, if we don't have anyone to enact these things, we go nowhere. So again, again, I'm with council Scott Pelley. I, if, you know, if you could change that language a little bit, I would be, I would have, I would support it also. Yeah. On that point, Mr. President, I think, you know, when we look at traditionally this administration's personnel functions and the way that they go about it,
They haven't had any problem bringing back all three employees, retired employees, to perform these functions. We looked at what went on in the treasurer's office. We're looking at what's going on in the CFO's office. I mean, we're bringing back part-time retirees to fill these positions. Why aren't we doing that in the diversity office too? Why is that office less important than these other offices?
I would say that that was something we fought for to make that two separate positions of last year, not one position so constant saying, I'll defer to President Merrill first. Thank you, Mr President, I just want to thank Councilor saying for bringing this forward, and I appreciate the language as well as the amendment by counselor bears I just want to note that the I believe the West better Community Center is putting together a full month of programming.
for Black History Month this month. So if people just wanna keep their eyes out for that, and that is a great way to engage as a community and learn about our history and our future. So I just wanna put that out there. Thank you. Thank you. I just wanted to say that I'm happy to accept the amendments as proposed by Councilor Behrs and the one on civics as proposed by Councilor Spadafore. Okay, any further discussion? Mr. President, if I may just add to Councilor Knight's point,
that there is a job posting for that position. So to anyone here or anyone watching tonight, please spread that job posting for the diversity director far and wide. I do think it is urgent that we get someone hired and I'm hopeful that that will happen quickly. Eight months. Eight months, we're gonna be on the next fiscal year's budget pretty soon.
On the motion by Councilor Sang as amended by Councilor Baez and amended by Councilor Scott Kelly seconded by. If we can just if the city clerk can read Councilor Baez's amendment over. I appreciate Councilor Sang for entertaining that for the other residents that reached out.
Council business amendment inserts a comma after the word to combat racism, and then adds in the words to address the growing danger of white supremacy and white supremacist ideology as well publicized by the US Department of Justice, Southern Poverty Law Center anti defamation league, and other leading watchdogs, and then as a comma and it and then it reverts to, and to teach black history.
Okay, man. I was able to copy down the counselor Scarpelli wants wants to reach out to the school committee to ask them to teach civics, but there was something at the end that I didn't pick up on the microphone to bring to bring civics back to the public schools, again at the high school level, and part of their curriculum
be a quarter that teaches the methods black history and black history. So I think it's important that we see that. So on the motion by councilor saying as amended by councilor bears and amended by councilor Scott Kelly, seconded by seconded by councilor Collins. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Yes. Yes. Yes.
Councilor Kerrio. Yes, I mean affirmative negative motion passes to 2064 offered by council saying we resolve the Memphis City Council celebrate Lunar New Year and reaffirm our solidarity with Asians Americans and method given an increase in anti-Asian hate crimes, bigotry and violence. And given that what may be a difficult holiday season for those unable to visit a relative. And if I could say to our
Councilor Sang, happy new year. And to all the Asian families in the city of Memphis, happy new year. I'm sorry if I said it right. I hope my English is okay. Thank you so much. Again, this is in line with residents who want to see our city more openly embracing our diversity and our different communities here. Lunar New Year is the most important holiday for many Asian communities here in Medford.
And, you know, it's not, not just the Chinese holiday, it's one that's celebrated by many other communities as well by Koreans, by Vietnamese Americans, by Tibetan Americans, by Taiwanese Americans, and the list goes on and on. You know, I wanted to note that this, this New Year's might be
particularly difficult, you know, we're still dealing with the pandemic, and it's traditional, it's kind of like an Asian Thanksgiving where you go into your family. And, you know, for a lot of families are not able to make it back for, you know, be it.
they're sick, it's difficult to, the difficult situations to leave the country or the difficult situations to get into another country. And so, you know, I think it's especially important for us to kind of lift each other up in this moment and to celebrate with each other. A holiday which, you know, a holiday season which might be a little bit tougher for folks now.
Thank you. Thank you counseling bringing this forward and know that I did, I did have some alarming questions. I had a Asian American family reach out to me later earlier today and asked if if method is dealing with recently increase anti a crimes.
as they read the resolution. So I did call, try to reach out to the chiefs and are you familiar, has something happened that we don't know because I think it's important that if it is, we make that public and that's something that we have to reaffirm publicly, so.
I believe that last year there were there were reported incidents of this city council in the last session. We know that. Right. I think you know this is a general rise, that's consistent with that trend that we saw last year, you know.
Medford is a safe community, we are safe for Asian Americans but there are moments where it might be difficult and I think it's important for our city council to, to note that there are definitely, you know, anti Asian incidents that are often gone on reported.
a lot of people don't know about our city's reporting resources, be it with the police or with our city departments. And so I also want to make that clear just for all of our residents here that there are different ways to report hate crimes or hate incidents if that happens to you, God forbid. And yeah, I would say that
My short answer is that there's a general increase in the Boston metro area. And yes, yeah. I appreciate bringing that clarity because I think that, again, this is an Asian family that I'm very close with and said, George, have you heard something? And I was trying to get the answer to that, but reflecting back to last year's resolution, I appreciate that clarity. So they're not alarmed. And again, I support this a thousand percent. I think it's very important that
And again, as we talked to this constituent, that's one of the things they talked about is the Asian community finds it very difficult sometimes to stand up and call someone. And a lot of times it's something that they've taken and we won't take that in this community. So, and that's what I shared with them. So I appreciate it. And again, happy new year. Thank you. Mr. President, if I could.
Again, President. President.
Thank you, Mr. President. I want to thank Councilor Seng for bringing this forward. I don't have all of the history of minutes in front of me, so I don't know if celebrating Chinese New Year has ever been introduced before, but I know it has not been introduced by an Asian American councilor, as Councilor Seng is our first. So I just want to note that it's great to have this celebratory measure on our agenda and that representation matters. And this is the kind of stuff that people can see when they see themselves represented on the council. So thank you, Councilor Seng, for bringing this forward.
Mr. President, what Councilor Morrell, Villes, and Knight don't see is the amazing jacket that Justin's wearing right now. I actually can see it. It took me a little bit. I can't see his necktie, but I can see his jacket.
Next year, the whole council wears it. It may not fit me, but I have one at home. Rick has one, but it's a shoe. I do have one at home. So, thank you again. I want to thank Councilor Tang. I've grown up with the Asian community many, many years, and something that I've gotten very fond of them. And my father and uncle sponsored many Chinese families to come here in the 60s and 70s. And again, I want to thank you for bringing it up.
I will support this. So, on the motion by Councilor saying, seconded by Councilor Scott Kelly. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Vice President bears. Yes. That's our columns. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
Councilor Keohokalole. Yes, seven in the affirmative, none in the negative, motion passes. 2-2-0-6-5, offered by Councilor Zang. Mr. President, I can offer a summary. I'm sorry, Councilor? I can offer a summary. Okay, we have quite a few. I wanna hear this summary. It's quite lengthy, so- Rick, it might be easier if you read it. I'll give it to Councilor Zang.
can give us his description of the 18 paragraphs here in a shorter version.
Well, so essentially this, this resolution is about the practice of data disaggregation. And so I'll give a little bit of history on it, explain the policy, explain the policy and why I've written it this way, and explain why I'm doing it now and then explain why, where where we should go as a city with it with the resolution part. So,
Going about the history, the OMB, the Office of Management and Budget, in 1997 created five racial categories for government agencies to report. Now this is a standard that different government agencies in our country are expected to follow.
But they did allow this guidance, give states and municipalities the prerogative to break our data down even further and to be more specific in the way that we report our data. And so this is something that, particularly in civil rights circles, in Asian American activist circles, and activist circles for different racial groups, this is something that's particularly important because
Racial data informs how we make policy decisions, it informs how we use funds, how we target communities in pandemic outreach and kind of different government city services as well. And I know for certain that our city has been working, has been using racial data to help
help solve the vaccine gap issue to help address disparities in the pandemic response. Now, so basically what this policy is, is that
We would, instead of, for example, take Asian Americans, instead of reporting it as solely Asian Americans, we will break that down into different communities, different racial and ethnic groups that the census has come up with to better help us identify trends within different racial groups.
The way that we currently report data actually covers up and papers over a lot of inequities within communities as well. When you look at the poverty rate for Asian Americans in this country, I don't think you would expect that the poverty rate for Vietnamese Americans is 2.5 times the national average, that the rate of poverty for Hmong Americans is three times the national average.
When you look at English proficiency rates, you'll find that while English proficiency rates for Vietnamese Americans is low, those for Indian Americans are high. And so these are things that just don't come out of the research that our city is doing, that cities generally in our country are doing.
They affect the city services right because if you have, if our city's targeting, you know, we need to provide city services in this language or publish this brochure in another language. We're not thinking about fiscally is it actually does it actually make fiscal sense to spend that money on that translation not on another translation.
Does it, does it, you know, our is our targeting of one community. Does that actually make sense fiscally and in terms of where we're spending our money. And so, this, I'm this resolution calls for city administration to cause for us to ask our city ministrations to disaggregate data.
because I know this will take a while, I know it will take planning and it'll take resources over a few years. That's why I've asked our cities to submit a report looking at long-term, what are the costs? What are the benefits? How else can we kind of affect change in data collection and data analysis? How can we make it fairer and more transparent? And so I think this revolution starts the conversation.
that will help us plan over a long term, what, you know, what, what our city needs to do to what does our city need to do in order to
disaggregate our data? How do we get the community involved in this? How can we get different departments involved in this? This is really about starting that conversation. And, you know, given our conversations about Asian American activism, I think that it is our Asian American issues in town. I think it is a good time to also back that up with some action. And so this is, this is the resolution, essentially. And I'm happy to answer questions.
Any further discussion? Councilor Palacio. Thank you. Thank you, Councilor Sang for putting this forward. This was very interesting to read through and learn about, and I appreciate your rundown of the resolution. This is something I'd very much like to see our administration work towards. I think it's very aligned with our social justice roadmap, our goals of becoming an ever more equitable community. And as you very helpfully described, disaggregating data into more specific
national, racial, ethnic groups. This arms us with better data to act upon through policy, through planning. You know, essentially the point of having all of this demographic information is so we can look beyond the line of best fit and see what's underneath it for really specific populations, you know, and respond appropriately through our governance and our program. So I'd love to see a response from the administration about what it would take to adopt this improved data, improved reporting. Thank you. Thank you.
I should also note, I forgot to mention that the reason why this is worded the way it is, is because this is taking from city council resolutions bits and pieces that apply to us, our community. I've taken from different communities across the country and from the Commonwealth of Massachusetts as well, because there is a piece of legislation in the state legislature that is talking about this issue as well, which will affect
which would help if passed, which would help our city's data collection system. Thank you. So on the motion by Councilor Sang, seconded by Vice President Bez. Happy to second the motion. And just one small amendment, if the city administration could also consider disaggregation of Middle Eastern and North African identities. That's one, basically,
several censuses ago, the census decided that if you're from North Africa or the Middle East, you're white. And that has presented a huge issue in terms of data collection and disaggregation. So just if I could add that small friendly amendment to this. Are you a member? Yes, I'm a member. So on the motion by Councilor Saint, as amended by Councilor Beas, seconded by Councilor Beas.
Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Vice President Farris. Yes. Councillor Collins. Yes. Councillor Knight. Councillor Knight.
I'm gonna come back to Councilor. Councilor Scarpelli? Yes. Councilor Stang? Yes. President Morrell? Yes. Councilor Kerrio? Yes. Six in the affirmative, one absent. Let me just, let me go back to Councilor Naito. I'm going back to Councilor Naito. Councilor Naito, you avail? Okay, so six in the affirmative, one absent. Motion passes. Two, zero.
22066 offered by Council saying be resolved, Memphis City Council expresses its support of House Bill 3155, an act ensuring equitable representation of the commonwealth be approved, resolved, the City Clerk forward a copy of this resolution to Memphis Legislative Delegation as well as chairs of
the Joint Committee on State Administration Regulatory Oversight, Pacheco and Cabral. Councilor Sang. Thank you. This state bill, this state house bill, is very similar to what we just passed. It essentially is also about data desegregation for different communities at the state level. This has been something that people have been fighting for.
As Councilor Behrs did mention before, you know, the deadline week is this week. And I think it's important if we are moving forward as a city, we ask the state to move forward as well, because that will also help us cut down on our resources if we choose to move forward with such a policy. Can't think I'm saying. Any further discussion? So on the motion- Second. Second by Zack.
Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
Councilor Kerrio? Yes, six in the affirmative, one absent, motion passes. Reports of committees, 22046, January 25th. Committee of the whole report regarding the Veterans Affairs Office. Motion to accept the report. It's actually my error, that's the Veterans and Military Affairs. Veterans and Military Affairs. On the motion to accept the report. Motion to accept.
Councilor Scott Peli second by Councilor saying Mr. Clerk please call the roll. Vice President bears. Yes. Council calls. Yes. Council night.
Councilor Sang? Yes. President Morrell? Yes. Councilor Kerrio? Yes, 16 for everyone and one absent, motion passes. 22043, January 26th, media report on council priorities. Motion to accept the report. Motion to accept. By Councilor Scott Kelly, seconded by Councilor Sang. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Vice President Behrs? Yes. Councilor Collins?
Yes. Councilor Knight. Councilor Scarpelli. Yes. Councilor Seng. Yes. President Morrell. Yes. Councilor Kerrio. Yes. Six in the affirmative, one absent, motion passes. Oh, sorry. Not sure if this should go before or after public participation, but motion to take from the table papers 21-631 and 22-023 for third reading.
Council call to take 2-1-6-3-1 off the table and what else? 2-2-0-2-3. And 2-2-0-2-3, which is eligible for a third reading this evening. So on the motion to take 6-2-2 off the table, seconded by? Second. Seconded by Councilor Baez. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Vice President Behrs. Yes. Councilor Collins. Yes. Councilor Knight. No. Councilor Scarpelli, if you can just give me a brief, which one is this? 631. Are you taking both? 631 and 023 to take them off the table.
Six, but 631, I don't see it. It's 21631 on page seven and eight. On page seven and eight. Third reading for the personnel ordinances. And there's two because they were severed. They were voted on separately. Which is the first paper's positions?
The first paper is the positions including the federal funds manager that we approved under the prior council in December. Right. I voted no on that. Correct. So what else was on that? That's right. So Mr. Clerk, we're going to take those off the table first.
Yes. Mr. President, can I request that we keep these on the table for one more week, just so I can have an opportunity to review the paperwork again. I'm a little confused as to what's before us this evening and where we're taking it off the table without the papers in front of us and just like for the professional courtesy to have one more week to take a review. So on the motion by Vice President Mike to table this. It's more of a request, I guess. It's more of a request.
able this to do. We have the paper. The first council calls. I just want to, of course, if any counselors need another week to review it, I don't want to rush the decision. But being as a lot of the positions under these ordinances are related to public health, the public health nurse, food security specialist positions are included in these amendments.
These are positions that I've heard that the community is really clamoring to be filled. I think it's really urgent that we get these processed, be able to hire for them really as quickly as possible. These are some positions that are really addressing urgent needs in Medford. If it's possible even to, you know, maybe review the documents in this meeting and then move forward, you know, I don't want to be ham-fisted about this, but if there's any way to move forward with a measure of urgency, I'd really, you know, appreciate it. Just say no and push the vote. I'll vote against it and you guys can get what you want.
I mean, at the end of the day, when we're talking about urgency, we've had the diversity director's position that's been vacant friggin' for 36 months. So, you know, I think that, you know, when we're gonna sit here and we're gonna worry about urgency, I don't think that that urgency is shared all the time with colleagues in government across the hallway. Mr. President. Vice President Biss. I'm of the opinion that waiting one additional week would not be
the city and moving these forward. So I'm happy to wait one more week and take these off the table at that time. And the only reason I ask is because I voted. Differently on both papers, so I just want to be sure that I can have the opportunity again to review them and be consistent in my efforts as I go forward in the
a motion by Councilor Collins to take these two papers off the table. We have a request by Councilor Knight that was seconded by Councilor Baez to hold these for one week. So Councilor Collins, you wanna rescind your order? Just withdraw the motion and we're done. Yeah. Is there a question? Is there a way to motion for these to put on next week? Just withdraw the motion. Yeah. If you withdraw,
If you just withdraw the motion doesn't go anywhere. So you want to bring it back up next week. Bring it back next week. So Council Collins has withdrawn our motion. So public participation, anybody want to speak on public participation? Mr. Clerk, anybody speaking on public participation? Okay.
Before we leave, before we do the records, I received a bunch of calls today from people at the high school complaining about no heat. If the administration could send us something in the next day or so telling us what's being done to address the heat issues at the high school. Students are being told to wear jackets because there's no heat in certain rooms.
If we can get some kind of report in the next day or so, what the problem is and if it's being addressed. I just wanted to add my voice to the chorus. I know this is a difficult issue. I know it takes resources, but I was just at the high school last week for a meeting and many students and teachers did bring that up to me as well.
So if the administration could get us, send us an email the next day, so it'd be greatly appreciated. So, records of January 25th, 2020, do it, pass the council, Councilor Sang. Councilor Sang, how did you find those records? I find the records in order and I move to approve. On the motion by Councilor- Second. Approval seconded by Councilor Knight. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Vice President Behrs. Yes. Councilor Collins.
Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
Yes, so we can find out why the heat's been diminished in this room. Yeah. I'll take care of it. Clark said he'll make the call. Maybe we can refer that to the Subcommittee on Energy and Environment. That's why Councilor May call him, but he was a little chilly. That would be the Subcommittee on Climate, Sustainability, and Transportation. Yeah, it's still the Office of Community Development to me, whatever they want to call it.
to adjourn seconded by Councilor Scott Kelly. Vice President bears. Yes. Council Collins. Yes. Councilor night. Yes. Councilor Scott Kelly. Yes. Councilor saying yes, President Morrell. Yes. That's trivial. Yes, I'm in the affirmative motion passes tomorrow night subcommittee meeting. I mean the committee the whole meeting at six o'clock.
meeting adjourned.