[SPEAKER_05]: Welcome to the City of Medford Traffic Commission meeting.
[SPEAKER_05]: Today is Tuesday, December 10th, 2024, and the time is 5.08 p.m.
[SPEAKER_05]: This meeting will now come to order.
[SPEAKER_05]: Alba, can we get a roll call of the commissioners, please?
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner McGibbon?
[SPEAKER_05]: Here.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Hunt?
[SPEAKER_07]: Here.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm here.
[SPEAKER_05]: Chief Buckley present and we have one vacancy on the commission.
[SPEAKER_05]: We do have a quorum also present this evening are the Al Erikson secretary to the traffic commission.
[SPEAKER_05]: We have them.
[SPEAKER_05]: Metro Police Department's traffic sergeants, Larry Rogers and Sergeant Canava.
[SPEAKER_05]: Let me see, and the Director of Traffic and Parking, Todd Blake is here, and if I missed anyone, I'm just on a foreign computer, so I'm getting used to this.
[SPEAKER_05]: So the minutes, minutes have been submitted, Alba, to the commissioners.
[SPEAKER_05]: Have they been reviewed?
[SPEAKER_05]: And if they have been reviewed, I will take a motion to accept and approve the minutes from the November 12th, 2024 meeting.
[SPEAKER_05]: Motion to approve.
[SPEAKER_05]: on the motion of Commissioner McGiven.
[SPEAKER_05]: Seconded by?
[SPEAKER_05]: Second.
[SPEAKER_05]: Seconded by Commissioner Hunt to approve the minutes of the November 12th, 2024 meeting.
[SPEAKER_05]: Alba, roll call.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner McGiven?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Hunt?
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_04]: One point of order, since I was not here for that meeting, can I even vote on them?
[SPEAKER_04]: And if not, do we have enough approval votes for them?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, we would have enough if you abstained, which is probably- I just feel bad I wasn't there, so I feel bad voting for them.
[SPEAKER_04]: So as long as we have enough to approve them, I'll abstain.
[SPEAKER_04]: We do, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wait, can I actually- Go ahead.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I was checking the notes against mine and I realized that I, yeah, they look right.
[SPEAKER_01]: I misunderstood something, I saw something.
[SPEAKER_05]: No worries.
[SPEAKER_05]: And the vote is to me, so I am a yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: So in a vote of three to nothing, to one abstain.
[SPEAKER_05]: The motion passes, the minutes have been approved.
[SPEAKER_05]: New business, 2024-68, request from Blue Fuji Restaurant, 38 Salem Street, for 15 minute parking zone.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, let's look and see if the petitioner is present.
[SPEAKER_05]: If they are, can you just wave your hand or indicate?
[SPEAKER_05]: Chief, my question is whether this was already approved or not.
[SPEAKER_06]: I checked that, I couldn't find anything.
[SPEAKER_10]: So Chief, I think Jim Silva was going to be here to speak on this matter and he mentioned he couldn't make it tonight.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, so Sergeant Rogers' comment was that
[SPEAKER_05]: I do believe we have addressed this issue in the past.
[SPEAKER_05]: I mean, I know you looked at it, but we had a discussion as to whether or not we've done this.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, I could not find anything.
[SPEAKER_05]: In what the petitioner, at least my understanding of the petitioner's request is, there was a 15-minute parking that existed, and the city has done, well, there's some private construction, and the city did some reconstruction of Sale Street in that area with a bump out, and at some point during all of that, they lost their 15-minute parking zone.
[SPEAKER_05]: Director Blake's putting it up right here.
[SPEAKER_05]: See the bump out, and it was there, I believe.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Used to be right here.
[SPEAKER_06]: The hydrant's new.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's been 15 minutes.
[SPEAKER_06]: If you go back to our earlier view.
[SPEAKER_10]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: True.
[SPEAKER_08]: Very interesting.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, I'm not seeing a 15-minute sign, but they used to have a parking directly in front.
[SPEAKER_05]: Director Blake, can you go up Ashland?
[SPEAKER_05]: Maybe it was on the corner there.
[SPEAKER_05]: It wasn't up there, was it?
[SPEAKER_10]: This was permit.
[SPEAKER_10]: So it used to be permit.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: I wonder if we gave that.
[SPEAKER_10]: So at one point when this permit went up, as we all know, when permit Parkins approved on the residential side street, it usually does not include next to the business, but the sign didn't have an arrow, so it was unclear.
[SPEAKER_10]: So we had remedied that piece of it in the past.
[SPEAKER_10]: That might be what people are remembering.
[SPEAKER_10]: So we, I'm trying to find the,
[SPEAKER_05]: In a way, that would be a difficult spot, right?
[SPEAKER_05]: Because if you're driving through the square to stop and pick up a meal at Blue Fuji, that's a one-way street, it would be kind of.
[SPEAKER_10]: Oh, here's the old one right there.
[SPEAKER_05]: There we go.
[SPEAKER_05]: So at some point in time, we can make the assumption that the Traffic Commission approved that sign, even though we didn't find it yet.
[SPEAKER_05]: But we have to, logic suggests that we have approved it in the past.
[SPEAKER_05]: And with the petitioner not present, I'm wondering if we should just continue
[SPEAKER_05]: If we should just.
[SPEAKER_10]: So they're asking for it here now is from the pool to the stop sign.
[SPEAKER_09]: They're asking to move it Todd didn't we just move the 15 minute parking when we reconfigure those spaces.
[SPEAKER_09]: We had to move the handicap spot and we had to move the 15 minute parking spot.
[SPEAKER_09]: I thought they just move it further than they wanted.
[SPEAKER_10]: So the petitioner of the restaurant reached out to the mayor's office, and Jim Silva and some others were involved in the conversations back and forth, and it was decided that they would come to the meeting and request 15-minute on Ashland from the telephone pole to the stop sign.
[SPEAKER_10]: But I did point out, yes, that there's a 15-minute, a couple 15-minute spots here,
[SPEAKER_10]: near the modern pastry in the church and then there's a 15-minute spot near at the end near Dunkin Donuts.
[SPEAKER_10]: So there are two other 15-minute areas other than the former Blue Fuji there.
[SPEAKER_09]: I think it's important because we didn't remove any 15-minute spot.
[SPEAKER_09]: I think we moved it as opposed to removed it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, Commissioner McGibbon, you are right.
[SPEAKER_05]: When we talked about moving the hydrant, there was some construction that had to do dealing with moving the hydrant, etc.
[SPEAKER_05]: That was probably the petition where we had agreed to move that 15 minutes on.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's why we're specifically not finding that done.
[SPEAKER_05]: I do believe you're right now that you've said that.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, so these two are 15 minute, this car and this car.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think there's a sign that's missing back here, delineating, but the front is clearly marked out.
[SPEAKER_05]: But that... There are some on the other side of the street also.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: So there's the... So knowing all that, they still wanted to request this 15 minute space on Ashland.
[SPEAKER_01]: They wanted on Ashland?
[SPEAKER_10]: Correct, so so they had reached out to the mayor's office About the loss of the 15 minute in front of the building They got at least one ticket or more on ashland or their customers have So it was already explained to them that these other 15 minute are available on salem and they're available to everyone But they still wanted to request the 15 minute beside blue fuji on ashland Did we have so?
[SPEAKER_01]: I could imagine that if they have some regular Uber Eats type drivers or Dash or whoever, sorry, I sound like a Neanderthal, I don't know if they're all called, that drive at stop there, that they would perhaps know that coming up on Ashland Street would be a great place to stop, grab the 15 minute and run in there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do we know if that spot, as in that photo you were just showing us, it looks occupied.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it frequently used by permit-only permit holders?
[SPEAKER_10]: So the permit piece has already been rectified with an arrow.
[SPEAKER_10]: So from that sign up the street is permit, and from that telephone pole, the stop sign is unrestricted right now.
[SPEAKER_10]: So someone right now could park in those spaces next to Blue Fuji all day long for 12 hours.
[SPEAKER_10]: So there's no turnover.
[SPEAKER_10]: So by asking for the 15 minute in that area during their business hours or maybe replicate what was on the sign before in the front, it keeps it the turnover of that space and someone won't fill it all day long.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I'm very much in favor of our public spots should either be resident permit parking in our business district or should have some sort of turnover, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: This shouldn't be an all day spot.
[SPEAKER_01]: It could be a meter two hour spot, but if the business is asking for a 15 minute pickup spot, like I would strongly prefer that than having it just be something where the one lucky person knows that they can park there and then hop a bus to Boston for the day.
[SPEAKER_10]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_10]: And then if it was ever needed for business employees and there's the business parent parking program with, and they could park in several lots throughout the square if they want that.
[SPEAKER_10]: So this is purely for turnover of, um, customers or like Uber eats or whatnot.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Um, I'm always in favor of additional 15 minutes spots in a place like, uh, Medford square, because I do think it has to turn over and increase business.
[SPEAKER_05]: Um, and that is a,
[SPEAKER_05]: It's a free spot for us to kind of designate if we felt like we should do it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Understanding the petitioner isn't here, do any of the commissioners feel obligated to move forward on this and grant it?
[SPEAKER_05]: We certainly have spoken with the petitioner enough to understand their request.
[SPEAKER_05]: Any other comments from the commissioners?
[SPEAKER_01]: Todd knows a lot about this already and has spoken, or he and Jim has spoken with them.
[SPEAKER_10]: They made a statement for the record too.
[SPEAKER_10]: And Nina has coordinated with them as well.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, Jim apologized that he couldn't make it.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think he was gonna speak for that.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, let me do this because I think it's probably good protocol.
[SPEAKER_05]: Is there anyone in the public here wishing to speak in favor of this?
[SPEAKER_05]: Just on some way, raise your hand or put something in the chat.
[SPEAKER_05]: Seeing none, is anyone here in the public wishing to speak against this petition?
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, also seeing none, I'll go back to the commissioners.
[SPEAKER_05]: I agree, I think we have enough information to act if the commissioner would like to.
[SPEAKER_05]: So I throw it back to either a motion or a discussion.
[SPEAKER_09]: Well, it's pretty short, Chief.
[SPEAKER_09]: If you'll allow, I'll just read the couple of sentences that the petitioner submitted for this, and I think that covers it.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, please.
[SPEAKER_09]: It says, dear Alva, follow the advice of Chief of Staff.
[SPEAKER_09]: See below, I'm writing to request the reinstallation of a 15-minute parking zone along Ashton Street adjacent to Blue Fuji Restaurant at Salem Street.
[SPEAKER_09]: Previously, there was a 15-minute parking zone in front of the restaurant, but its removal has caused significant inconvenience for our customers and staff.
[SPEAKER_09]: This change has led to parking infractions, including tickets issued to deliver drivers and customers while attempting quick pickups.
[SPEAKER_09]: Restoring this parking zone would provide much-needed accessibility for our patrons and staff while reducing these avoidable issues.
[SPEAKER_09]: Please let me know if additional details or steps are required to process this request.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thanks for your time and consideration.
[SPEAKER_09]: Best regards, Julie Blue Fuji.
[SPEAKER_09]: With that, I'll move to approve.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: On the motion of Commissioner McGibbon, do I have a second?
[SPEAKER_04]: I'll second.
[SPEAKER_05]: Seconded by Commissioner Brzezinski.
[SPEAKER_05]: A roll call, please.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_10]: Sorry to interject.
[SPEAKER_10]: You probably, unless you're assuming it's going to be 24, 7, 15 minute, is there any times or days?
[SPEAKER_10]: The former one was 8am to 9pm in front.
[SPEAKER_10]: I would, well, I'll put it back to the... I had suggested to the proponent and to Chief of Staff, but I don't know what they officially are requesting.
[SPEAKER_09]: I was moving on the request to reinstate what was there, just in a different spot.
[SPEAKER_09]: Good, sorry.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's what I understood at all.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, so on the motion of Commissioner McGibbon, seconded by Commissioner Brzezinski to approve 2024-68, 15-minute parking
[SPEAKER_05]: on Ashland Street, but in the same manner and form as had previously been granted.
[SPEAKER_05]: Alvaroco.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner McGibbon.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Hunt.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Brzezinski.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Chief Buckley.
[SPEAKER_05]: On the vote of four to none, the motion approved.
[SPEAKER_05]: Let's make some notes.
[SPEAKER_05]: 2024-69, no parking anytime in the area on Brookside Parkway.
[SPEAKER_05]: Commissioner McGiven and Engineer George Connolly have presented this.
[SPEAKER_05]: Commissioner McGiven, the floor is yours.
[SPEAKER_09]: All right, thanks.
[SPEAKER_09]: So this is an area of the city that receives a lot of dumping and sort of vehicles that just park there for long periods of time.
[SPEAKER_09]: And it's a place that my permit officer is constantly seeing.
[SPEAKER_09]: trash build up there between the vehicles and the fence.
[SPEAKER_09]: On the other side of the fence is MassDOT property and they maintain it maybe twice a year.
[SPEAKER_09]: I think it would be to a benefit to limit parking or just have no parking along the stretch.
[SPEAKER_09]: I don't know if someone's got, I can either pull it up or if someone can help me out and just pull it up and we can look at the stretch.
[SPEAKER_09]: But it's the stretch that is abutting the MassDOT right of way on Brookside Parkway.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, is someone gonna pull it up?
[SPEAKER_05]: I just I am curious as to the length of distances.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah Which which is which plot starting at Westfield?
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm starting.
[SPEAKER_09]: I believe it's Water a Webster.
[SPEAKER_10]: Oh, sorry a Webster.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay, not Valley Okay
[SPEAKER_09]: double checking here too.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, you're looking at from between Webster and water.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: This is the view from Webster looking down.
[SPEAKER_10]: So now it's traveling towards water with my cursor.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, that's the stretch.
[SPEAKER_10]: Then we'll look back from water.
[SPEAKER_10]: There we go.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: So essentially from the Salem Street Rotary to Water Street, is that what we're requesting?
[SPEAKER_09]: If I... It could be.
[SPEAKER_09]: The worst of it is down closer to Webster Street.
[SPEAKER_09]: This area?
[SPEAKER_09]: That area there, yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_04]: Tim, are you looking for both sides of the street or just the left?
[SPEAKER_09]: Just the left side of the street, just the non-stop property.
[SPEAKER_04]: I know the church parks its bus, the church on Salem Street, I think they park their bus down there.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think some of the larger vehicles park there.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, there is a bus there that is just there.
[SPEAKER_05]: My recommendation would be no parking because of the winter.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's extremely tight.
[SPEAKER_05]: OK.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you, Sergeant.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, let me do this, commissioners, if you'll allow me.
[SPEAKER_05]: Is there anyone in the public here wishing to speak in favor of this petition?
[SPEAKER_05]: And anyone here wishing to speak against the petition?
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, seeing none, just want to make sure the public had a right to chime in on this and let's go back to the commissioners.
[SPEAKER_05]: Todd, do you have a question?
[SPEAKER_10]: The lights are shutting off.
[SPEAKER_10]: I was just moving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_01]: I wanted to be positive that I understood what area it was.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I understand it's coming from DPW and its functional needs and stuff, which is great.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just... Was it in the supporting documents that I didn't get to today?
[SPEAKER_01]: My apologies.
[SPEAKER_09]: The extent or the area yeah, just what well, we can, I feel like we can decide that here because we may want to leave some parking between these 2 roads Webster and water.
[SPEAKER_09]: It was going to leave some if you're going to leave some, it should be up closer to the rotary as you're seeing here because that apartment building is sometimes use it.
[SPEAKER_09]: It's really the stretch in between the parking lot.
[SPEAKER_09]: And the parking lot across the street and Webster.
[SPEAKER_09]: That we see the dumping, we see the cars just parked there for weeks at a time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Could we do something about no overnight parking and stuff like that?
[SPEAKER_01]: If people are parking there and commuting to Boston or they're working their jobs in the squares, I'm not okay with dumping vehicles, but would this be better served for the public by just saying no overnight parking?
[SPEAKER_09]: That could work.
[SPEAKER_09]: I just want
[SPEAKER_09]: to minimize the amount of dumping that is happening there.
[SPEAKER_09]: We did something similar.
[SPEAKER_09]: I should actually be hesitant before I say that'll work, because I think we did something similar over on Commercial Street, where we said no overnight parking.
[SPEAKER_09]: I know we're still getting dumping there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by dumping, you mean vehicles are getting dumped?
[SPEAKER_09]: No, just trash.
[SPEAKER_09]: between the cars and the fence or just right over the fence, the cars that make it kind of hidden.
[SPEAKER_09]: So it's a really good opportunity for dumping.
[SPEAKER_09]: Um, and we own up to a certain extent and then mass dot owns the rest, but they don't clean it all that often.
[SPEAKER_09]: So we ended up cleaning it and sending volunteers in there to clean it.
[SPEAKER_09]: And it's a, it makes me nervous to doing, doing that.
[SPEAKER_09]: Um,
[SPEAKER_09]: So ultimately, I mean, ideally, I'd like to just restrict the parking on that end of it from the parking lot across the street to Webster and just say no parking.
[SPEAKER_09]: But I would settle with no overnight parking.
[SPEAKER_09]: I think that would be an improvement.
[SPEAKER_05]: And Tim, for who makes this motion, can you give us, can you try to describe the area you want in words so we can make sure the petition,
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, maybe we can do it in terms of... I'm measuring it for you, Tim, right now.
[SPEAKER_10]: It looks like about 200 feet from Webster to that parking lot.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, then let's make it 200 feet.
[SPEAKER_10]: Is that to... See, Webster's here, the parking lot's here.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's showing us about 200 feet.
[SPEAKER_10]: Is that what you want?
[SPEAKER_05]: Then I see where there's the west side, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: East side.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's what I was looking at right there.
[SPEAKER_10]: This stretch for now and then see how it goes.
[SPEAKER_05]: East side, Webster 200.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_10]: East side from Webster extending 200 feet southward.
[SPEAKER_10]: Sounds about right.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay, you got it.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: All right.
[SPEAKER_05]: So it is the petition of commission of McGivern, so I would look to another commissioner for a proposed motion on this, which would exist.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'd motion for that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And Tim, though, I would be interested, just keep us apprised as to like, if it gets any better.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't know how to, I'm sure it's on your list of things to do, but I like the phased in approach.
[SPEAKER_04]: So a motion, Chief.
[SPEAKER_05]: to approve 2024-69, no parking any time on Brookside Parkway, east side, extending 200 feet southward.
[SPEAKER_05]: Do I have a second?
[SPEAKER_05]: Seconded by Commissioner Hunt.
[SPEAKER_05]: Alba, can you give us a roll call, please?
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner McGibbon?
[SPEAKER_09]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Hunt?
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Chief Buckley?
[SPEAKER_05]: On a vote of four to nothing, the motion is approved and the petition passes.
[SPEAKER_05]: 2024-70, New England Portuguese Seventh-day Adventist Church, 62 Dexter Street, with a petition regarding church parking.
[SPEAKER_05]: Do we have the petitioner present?
[SPEAKER_05]: If you can, we could ask you to unmute yourself.
[SPEAKER_05]: I don't have a name for it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Just wave your hand or something.
[SPEAKER_05]: We could ask you to unmute.
[SPEAKER_05]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_05]: Can you unmute yourself?
[SPEAKER_05]: There you go, Mr. Gouveia.
[SPEAKER_05]: Welcome to the Traffic Commission meeting.
[SPEAKER_05]: We see your petition, but could you present it to us and explain as best you can what you're looking for from the Traffic Commission?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, Chief.
[SPEAKER_03]: First of all, thanks for being here, Chief and all the members.
[SPEAKER_03]: You guys have a good night.
[SPEAKER_03]: We are a small church in Medford.
[SPEAKER_03]: We are at 62 Dexter Street.
[SPEAKER_03]: We bought the building around seven years ago.
[SPEAKER_03]: It was a previous church in there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So the previous church was getting a larger congregation, so they moved away from Medford, and then we bought the building.
[SPEAKER_03]: When we bought the building, there were no permit parkings on the area, so everything was fine.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then the city put a permit parking on Edward, and then I think also on Dexter.
[SPEAKER_03]: We do had a petition that was approved by the parking commission, and we are allowed to park on Baxter using this warnings on our windshields during our church service.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the thing is, like six years back, I mean, not that much, four years back to today, the city has grown.
[SPEAKER_03]: The residents are much more right now, and they have more cars.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the thing is, we can't park on Dexter.
[SPEAKER_03]: We can't find an available spot Saturday morning or other church service hours because all the residents, they are parking on the street.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, there's no problem for us with that.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, they're residents, we're not complaining about that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But just for the commission to know that we are having some struggles to find some spots.
[SPEAKER_03]: during our church service hours.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then what our church members, what they've been doing is they've been parking on Edward Street.
[SPEAKER_03]: The thing is, we can't park there because we're not allowed to park on Edward Street, only on Dexter Street.
[SPEAKER_03]: We've been getting some tickets once in a while.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, it's not every Saturday, but
[SPEAKER_03]: And then because we don't want to break any laws or any rules, we're doing this, moving this petition to you guys so you could analyze and see if it is possible for us to allow us to park on Edward Street.
[SPEAKER_03]: Also on Dexter, there is like a three blocks area.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think I sent a map.
[SPEAKER_03]: That would be between Edward, between Dexter and Henry Street.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think I showed you, I sent that.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know if you have this map.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that would help us a lot.
[SPEAKER_03]: We're not a big, a large church right now.
[SPEAKER_03]: I would say last Saturday, I counted 68 members on Saturday morning, on an average of three members per car.
[SPEAKER_03]: I would say maybe 20 cars on our busiest like Saturday morning service.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, that's the average.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's our story.
[SPEAKER_05]: Can I ask a question, not to interrupt, but can you tell me a little bit about, is Saturday mornings the only day for services or do you, how many days a week do you have services and what's your population?
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, we do have our main service hours on Saturday morning, okay, from 8.30 to
[SPEAKER_03]: We usually stay until 3, 3.30 at church.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not all the members, but we do have some kids activities after sermon.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's on Saturdays morning.
[SPEAKER_03]: And when we do also have what we call like
[SPEAKER_03]: a preach service like a like a prayer service it's on Wednesday night and Sunday's night that would start at 7 30 to 9 and Wednesday night and Sunday nights are like a very few members they go last last Wednesday we had like six or seven at the most and also the same thing on Sundays okay so
[SPEAKER_03]: That would be the three days that we have service in church.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: And the piece of paper you showed me that parking for the Adventist Church, do you know when you got that?
[SPEAKER_05]: No, not the map, the other one that tells you that you're in church.
[SPEAKER_05]: Do you know when you got that from the parking lot?
[SPEAKER_05]: Chief.
[SPEAKER_03]: I've been on the New England Portuguese chart since 2021 earlier, and we also have been doing this since then.
[SPEAKER_03]: When did you have that?
[SPEAKER_03]: No issues at all.
[SPEAKER_03]: Particularly I had one ticket, like back maybe one and a half year ago, because I did park on Edward, but we paid the ticket.
[SPEAKER_03]: I just had one, all right?
[SPEAKER_03]: But I do know that this, we've been doing, the church has been doing that like at least for three years before 2021, okay?
[SPEAKER_03]: So it goes a way back.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know exactly the year.
[SPEAKER_05]: Commissioner, any questions for the petitioner?
[SPEAKER_10]: So Chief, I have some info I could share a screen with.
[SPEAKER_10]: It looks like they used to have, possibly still now, I haven't gone out there, but as of 2022 on Street View, it shows they had some space directly in front, maybe like 70 feet or so, restricted to church use only.
[SPEAKER_10]: which I know is not necessarily exactly what the petition is wanting.
[SPEAKER_10]: He wants, you know, something else, but I just want to highlight that to folks.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: We do have like two spots in front of church.
[SPEAKER_03]: All right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Uh, if you see there's like a, yes.
[SPEAKER_10]: Until there.
[SPEAKER_10]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_10]: Like from this telephone pole to the wheelchair and back here.
[SPEAKER_10]: So it's in front of the church and then like front next to this blue house.
[SPEAKER_10]: So that's maybe, maybe three spaces.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: We usually use like two from this pole.
[SPEAKER_03]: You see the, yeah, this pole, this, the, the pole until the next sign to, there you go.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right here on the beam and trash bins.
[SPEAKER_03]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: And then also, just a point of information in the when people for a completely different matter asked about current park in this area and where they could park.
[SPEAKER_10]: We did point out to others that main street right here is currently unrestricted.
[SPEAKER_10]: So Main Street, which is four or five buildings away, is unrestricted, so that's an option, not knowing what's gonna come out of this meeting, just pointing that out that that's an option.
[SPEAKER_10]: And then the other point was some resident-parent parking streets exclude Sunday and holiday.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm not sure of these individual streets around here, but we could probably get a list.
[SPEAKER_10]: So those are just some things that might help the discussion.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, my traffic size is believed that that is seven days a week up there, so.
[SPEAKER_09]: Do we know when we made it Edward Street permit parking?
[SPEAKER_05]: When we did?
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Probably tell you it's not my office though.
[SPEAKER_09]: Somewhat recent?
[SPEAKER_05]: Probably been a while.
[SPEAKER_01]: Beyond that document that you made, I can take a look.
[SPEAKER_08]: So,
[SPEAKER_05]: Even though, you know, we're looking right now to see if we can tell when it was made.
[SPEAKER_05]: I still think it sort of creates a little problem, right?
[SPEAKER_05]: We got 60 cars on a Saturday morning.
[SPEAKER_05]: We want to be able to extend the area.
[SPEAKER_05]: Pastor, can I ask you a question?
[SPEAKER_05]: Have your members tried to park up on Main Street?
[SPEAKER_05]: I mean, it's probably this equidistance with some of the streets that you're outlining.
[SPEAKER_05]: I know you've got Edwards you've used and
[SPEAKER_05]: You're indicating saying Main Street is unrestricted parking.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: We tried and sometimes we use, but the thing is, Chief, it's really hard to find a spot on Main Street on Saturday morning.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you go there to Main Street and Dexter, let's see, go to the corner of Main Street and Dexter, there you go.
[SPEAKER_03]: You see, oops, you see the mailbox?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right there.
[SPEAKER_03]: You see?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: In front of this house right there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: We can usually find like one or two parking spots.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I've guidance my members to park there on Main Street.
[SPEAKER_03]: But as I've been telling you, it's really hard to find a spot.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've never heard of parking restrictions like the sign that's in front of the church there that says no parking for church only and then you put signs and you're, this is the first I'm actually hearing that that exists anywhere in Medford.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just for the commission to know, we do have two spots in front of church, but it's very common to find residents parking there.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, we never complain about that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Two spots is not going to make any difference to us.
[SPEAKER_03]: We never complain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your members put signs in their cars and then just park on Dexter Street.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't get ticketed.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've never heard of that before.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, yeah, we put this inside the windshield.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: But at some point, we do have like a note on the parking.
[SPEAKER_03]: The parking officers, they knew that we usually do that.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're like members attending church.
[SPEAKER_03]: They never ticket us.
[SPEAKER_03]: They never gave us a ticket.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I do know the commission back then, they approved a note for if there was this sign inside the windshield, the parking officers, they wouldn't give any tickets.
[SPEAKER_10]: So just a point of information, I did look it up.
[SPEAKER_10]: Edward Street was approved for resident parking in 2017.
[SPEAKER_10]: With an exception to Edward place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, and I think that's the same list that you're looking at, but I'm probably looking at that says Dexter street, bow street to Broadway in front of homes only.
[SPEAKER_01]: Permit type resident and that's it because this would be the, this, this, you're looking at the sheet that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That Jim shared to us and correct the spreadsheet.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_10]: And Dexter, that's that's what I know to Dexter is only permit from boat to Broadway.
[SPEAKER_10]: So the rest of Dexter.
[SPEAKER_10]: Is not in the records as permit.
[SPEAKER_10]: Oh, at least in that spreadsheet, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: It just says Bow to Broadway, which is only one block closest to Magoon Square.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else on Dexter.
[SPEAKER_01]: So technically this street isn't permit parking.
[SPEAKER_01]: It does not appear to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why they haven't been getting tickets to Dexter.
[SPEAKER_10]: So Dexter and Maine are not.
[SPEAKER_10]: Dexter and Maine are not, yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: Edwards is.
[SPEAKER_09]: How many spaces short does the petitioner feel like he's short?
[SPEAKER_09]: In other words, how many tickets are happening on Edwards?
[SPEAKER_09]: How many cars are not parking on Dexter or Main?
[SPEAKER_03]: It depends on church attendance.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like some Saturdays we don't have issues at all.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then other days when most of the residents on Dexter Street, they park on the street and then we can't just find a place.
[SPEAKER_03]: We maybe can find like three or four spots on Dexter and then maybe three spots on Main Street.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I've been counting the spots.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, usually I'm the one that's trying to help members to park.
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you have any off-street parking at the church?
[SPEAKER_09]: No, we don't.
[SPEAKER_09]: Any room for off-street parking?
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm sorry?
[SPEAKER_09]: Any room on the parcel for off-street parking?
[SPEAKER_03]: On the lot, we think we can park like three cars if we put like a street access, like right there on the trash bins.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, on our lot, we can use like three spots right there.
[SPEAKER_03]: We'd have to make some changes and some improvements.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, we do.
[SPEAKER_03]: We'd like to change the curb and we'd probably lose one spot, but that's fine.
[SPEAKER_03]: We could use like three more spots there.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, just trying to understand the context of the situation.
[SPEAKER_10]: Not with this fence here, I'm not sure if that would end up being approved.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be a zoning issue.
[SPEAKER_09]: And are those church parking only signs, are those official regulatory signs voted by this commission?
[SPEAKER_10]: I'd have to look it up, unless Alvin knows.
[SPEAKER_01]: I did Google, like I went back in the dates, 2014 it wasn't there, and then I think like 2017 it was.
[SPEAKER_05]: We'd have to do a little bit of research on that to find out.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's like in the same thing, but we can't get it done.
[SPEAKER_01]: if you were just looking to figure out when, and the 2018 image has them, the 2014 image doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that gives you a window of what we're looking at.
[SPEAKER_05]: And I've been here since 2018, and I do not recall us putting them up, so probably right in that timeframe, end of 2018 and 2017.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know how one, so I would actually just sort of play this out, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Say we said, oh, they should be allowed to park on Edward Street and the church members should during church services.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you program that into our parking system, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like you have to have a plate
[SPEAKER_01]: and the plate is in a registration, it has to be registered, and then it has to be in the system, and then we don't have a way to say these plates are allowed on this street during this window of time.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I know I was told in the past that if the street, the car wasn't registered to the street, it was going to be a problem, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Now you need a whole other class of permits.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, this seems like this seems like something Park Medford did to manage the situation with placards.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I did find the parking restriction directly out front was from June 2018.
[SPEAKER_10]: That is real?
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: Well, I think that, you know, the Edward Street petition for permit parking, you know, we require signatures from residents.
[SPEAKER_09]: It's kind of a big deal.
[SPEAKER_09]: They have one permit parking for Edward Street.
[SPEAKER_09]: I feel it's a little bit disingenuous if we were to go back on that.
[SPEAKER_09]: approval and say, you know, well, yeah, we're going to reserve a block, though, during these times for the church.
[SPEAKER_09]: We've already done that on Dexter.
[SPEAKER_09]: Dexter's unrestricted and Main Street's unrestricted.
[SPEAKER_09]: And I think it could be seen as an operational problem for the church that they have more demand than parking available for them, unfortunately.
[SPEAKER_08]: Right.
[SPEAKER_08]: It's a couple of blocks away, but can they park it like the Columbus, the school in Columbus Park, like, Columbus Park has a lot.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know how the walking path is.
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess it's not actually an easy walk because of the grade differential and all.
[SPEAKER_09]: One of the things other organizations do and institutions do will provide shuttle services from remote lots for services.
[SPEAKER_09]: So that's just an option on the table if you can't find any local solutions.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what one of the Medford Square churches do is that they have buses and they bring people over.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: All institutions basically do it.
[SPEAKER_09]: Even Tufts does it if they're going to have a large event.
[SPEAKER_09]: Anybody who's going to have an event that they need to have parking for and maybe can't supply it locally.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not necessarily, I'm not even sure that if we, even if we wanted to do it, I don't think we could pass it tonight, because I think we would need to talk to people in the parking office to find out what literally they're even capable of.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think it would get messy really fast.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has, our system is based on license plates.
[SPEAKER_03]: May I speak?
[SPEAKER_03]: OK, just so the commission know, I do record my pastor saying like the parking commission, they do have like a note on the street on the parking restriction about this.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's a warning.
[SPEAKER_03]: OK, so they do have that.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, they call the book.
[SPEAKER_03]: okay i don't know i'm just saying what i heard so they have like a note on the book saying that if there is this warning on the windshield don't like give tickets okay and i heard i heard that from uh
[SPEAKER_03]: a parking officer too, all right?
[SPEAKER_03]: But I haven't seen the book, so I mean, they called the book of parking.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, so Mr. Gouveia, that's, I don't think anyone's saying that you're incorrect or disingenuous.
[SPEAKER_10]: There was a change though in the time period between 1718 and now, where the parking enforcement used to be by a private entity called Park Medford, which was right at Dexter at Maine.
[SPEAKER_10]: And they might have had that policy, and that's where the placard came from, so it's not discounting that or not believing it.
[SPEAKER_10]: But when the parking department came in-house, that's what Alicia's explaining, that system has reverted to license plates and not done any of the placard system.
[SPEAKER_10]: So it's less about if you had it or not, it's more about that change between the private parking enforcement and the public and how they go about enforcing those.
[SPEAKER_10]: So in the newer system, in the newer department, that hasn't been the practice of the newer department to give placards, even for our city hall employees, unfortunately.
[SPEAKER_10]: So it was a change that occurred that was unrelated to what you all were doing, Mr. Grubea.
[SPEAKER_10]: So it wasn't anything.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I understand that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: I do think if the situation, if the resolution was easy, we probably would all vote it.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's just very tricky with not just the spacing we have up there and the approvals, but the technical aspect of what the parking department can handle and how they can account for this.
[SPEAKER_05]: I do think, well, I'm gonna leave it to the commissioners, but I'm not sure we can vote on this today, and I dislike tabling things, but for whatever time period it does take, I would like you to try Main Street, Dexter Street, the few spots that you have, and see what the impact is, and report back to us.
[SPEAKER_05]: But in the meantime, I think we can,
[SPEAKER_05]: try to find some solutions working with the parking department ourselves to see what they can do.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because we can't pass something that they can't enforce or handle.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's going to just create a problem for them.
[SPEAKER_05]: And so we've been cognizant of that for a while now.
[SPEAKER_05]: Commissioner's thoughts on that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I was just looking at what some of the other streets in the area to see what permit parking, you know what.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I don't find Sanger Street, S-A-N-G-E-R, on our list at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the block.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: Alicia, I found the same.
[SPEAKER_10]: I found that Joseph has permit, Edward Layden, but Sanger doesn't appear to, and Dexter does not, and Maine does not.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I was thinking the same thing, Alicia.
[SPEAKER_10]: In the general vicinity, what is permit, what isn't?
[SPEAKER_01]: I just want to caution that things that are not permit parking in this area, like, I'm expecting more and more streets to want to go permit parking as density and vehicle density increases.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so I do think that it's useful for us to be aware that there's a situation like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's probably not the only one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do most of the church, every church I can think of has a lot, like this church is small.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's one up in Fulton Heights that doesn't have a lot.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just use street parking.
[SPEAKER_10]: For the other streets that don't have any, this part of Bow has permit, the G zone, but this part of Bow does not.
[SPEAKER_10]: which is, you know, not too far away either.
[SPEAKER_10]: If you go by Maine and Dexter and can't find any, you could go over here.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's like less than a quarter mile away, which is a five-minute walk.
[SPEAKER_10]: Just trying to help point out locations if you need to, sir.
[SPEAKER_10]: Oh, yeah, I appreciate that.
[SPEAKER_05]: OK, so for the commissioners, instead of dragging this time, it looks like there's going to be some research done.
[SPEAKER_05]: And we're going to spend some time on this.
[SPEAKER_05]: But certainly, we need to put this on the plate of the parking department to see what they may have a solution for us.
[SPEAKER_05]: They may say, we can do this, this, and this.
[SPEAKER_05]: I don't know what they can do.
[SPEAKER_05]: But we have to find out in order for us to move forward on the petition.
[SPEAKER_05]: It may also beg the question as to, should we look at all the other churches in the city, or whether or not a special permit could be presented?
[SPEAKER_05]: across the city.
[SPEAKER_05]: So is this an issue where we have to table an event or do some research?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, we can approve it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Our choices are to table it and deny it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I don't want the petitioner to think we're just, unless we refer it to somebody else to figure it, try and figure it out.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's my question.
[SPEAKER_04]: Who's going to lead the charge on researching it to help find a solution?
[SPEAKER_03]: I did think in something, I don't know, I'm just going to give an idea.
[SPEAKER_03]: Maybe the commission can think about it, see if it's even doable or not.
[SPEAKER_03]: We don't mind paying like permit parkings for the church members.
[SPEAKER_03]: And maybe if you look at this, all the churching parking in Medford, if you figure out a way, okay, give me all your members license plates and pay a permit for the city.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, that's a great idea.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, we would be really forward to that, too, if there is a thing like that possible, okay?
[SPEAKER_03]: Just an idea, all right?
[SPEAKER_03]: The thing is, we just want to go to church.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you guys find us a way,
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, I'll more than appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I do understand, even if you deny, I know it's not personal.
[SPEAKER_03]: It is like city policy.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I'm just open my heart for you guys to know that we just wanna go to church.
[SPEAKER_03]: And be at peace when we are in service, okay?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because sometimes we do have like some traveling time, like, well, maybe the parking officer is passing that time.
[SPEAKER_03]: Are we gonna get a ticket or not?
[SPEAKER_03]: And anyways, just a thought for the commission, okay?
[SPEAKER_05]: I do appreciate you putting that forward.
[SPEAKER_05]: And in answer to Commissioner Bozinski's question, I think I will take up the charge of this to kind of do the research in defining the term I. But we will take a look.
[SPEAKER_05]: We will take a
[SPEAKER_05]: a good hard look at this.
[SPEAKER_05]: We'll work with Jim Sulver and Todd and see if we can come up with some solutions.
[SPEAKER_05]: But I think the first stop has to be with the parking department to see what technically they're capable of doing.
[SPEAKER_05]: They may have a solution for us, or at least guide us down a path.
[SPEAKER_05]: So with that, I'm
[SPEAKER_05]: Mr. Gilbay, I really appreciate you presenting this tonight, and you did a really good job.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's just, we're stuck in a little place.
[SPEAKER_05]: It has nothing to do with your petition or what you requested.
[SPEAKER_05]: It just puts us in a tough spot, so we have to figure some things out.
[SPEAKER_05]: Would there be a commissioner who wishes to table this, and for what period of time would you give us the research?
[SPEAKER_04]: How much time do you need?
[SPEAKER_04]: This isn't a reference to the people behind you.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, January.
[SPEAKER_05]: My sergeants are confident they can do it by the January meeting.
[SPEAKER_04]: So a motion to table for 30 days while we find a solution.
[SPEAKER_04]: Second.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, on the motion of Commissioner Baczynski to table the petition for 30 days while the Medford Police Department researches with the parking department to come up with a solution, seconded by Commissioner McGibbon.
[SPEAKER_05]: Albert, can we get a roll call vote?
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner McGibbon?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Hunt?
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Chief Buckley?
[SPEAKER_05]: On the vote of four to nothing, the motion is approved.
[SPEAKER_05]: The item has been tabled for the January Traffic Commission meeting.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mr. Gobert?
[SPEAKER_05]: We're going to reach out to you.
[SPEAKER_05]: We have your contact information.
[SPEAKER_05]: My tribe will work with you and kind of keep you up to date and keep you posted.
[SPEAKER_05]: But I really appreciate you coming tonight and presenting this situation.
[SPEAKER_05]: And hopefully we can come to an expeditious solution to this for you.
[SPEAKER_03]: All right.
[SPEAKER_03]: All right, Chief.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_03]: I really appreciate your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you guys have a wonderful night.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you very, very much.
[SPEAKER_05]: 2024-71, request from Justin Gallo, 118 Warren Street, for stop signs on Warren Street at Cooley Road to make it a four-way stop intersection.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mr. Gallo, we're going to ask you to unmute.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you hear me?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, we can hear you.
[SPEAKER_05]: Welcome to the Traffic Commission.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you for your patience, although I think tonight is really short one.
[SPEAKER_05]: There's some lights you would be still sitting out there.
[SPEAKER_05]: But please go ahead and present your petition for us.
[SPEAKER_00]: No problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thanks for having me and Alvo for helping me with the request.
[SPEAKER_00]: I had made a request in the initially CClickFix platform to help make this a safer intersection, which is Warren Street at the intersection with Clulee Road.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a four-way intersection.
[SPEAKER_00]: Currently, there are stop signs on Clulee Road, both sides, west and east-facing.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Clulee Road stop sign that is facing west, which if you're familiar with that area, is facing towards Playstead Park, is not effective.
[SPEAKER_00]: it's obstructed by a tree when approaching it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't see it until you're about maybe 20, possibly less feet away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I initially, last year, made a C-click fix about this concern for safety, and they did add a stop-ahead sign, and the stop-ahead sign is roughly 100 yards.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, right there, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it right there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the tree that obstructs it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So if you are on that side of the road, it is obstructed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there was a stop ahead side and added about 100 yards before that, somewhere in that area that you're going there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was added, I believe, in October of 2023.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even since there remains a safety issue where people are not stopping at all at this intersection, they're just going straight through it, which I believe that is because people don't see it and they're
[SPEAKER_00]: ignoring the stop ahead or ignoring that sign as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even when you are stopped at that West facing sign, the large bush there in your view on the right-hand side, the other stop sign when you're, yeah, not that one, but when you're facing West, the original one that we were looking at.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that Bush makes it pretty tough to actually see cars coming from Warren Street.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's another reason to make this a safer intersection even when cars are stopped stopped at the stop sign.
[SPEAKER_00]: They naturally expect cars on Warren Street to stop as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: seems like it would be a four-way stop, but it's not because cars don't stop on Warren Street.
[SPEAKER_00]: They, of course, have the right-of-way.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are road rage incidents here and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: But major thing is that it's a safety concern here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Chopping down that tree might fix it and make it a more visible stop sign.
[SPEAKER_00]: They did trim the tree a bit when they added that stop ahead sign last year.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't think the city probably doesn't want to chop that tree down either.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yeah, that's the concern is in a way to make this safer, add stop signs to the Warren Street side, so this intersection to slow down traffic entirely.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think you might be muted there.
[SPEAKER_05]: I am getting used to this.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thanks for the presentation.
[SPEAKER_05]: It is pretty clear.
[SPEAKER_05]: We've dealt with this, at least on the police side, in the past.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm interested in Director Blake, your comments.
[SPEAKER_05]: You pretty much have control of stop signs and your thoughts are
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, this one I do support because Cooley acts as a pair with Century Street, which lead to and from Wildwood, which is near the high school, so I think Cooley gets more activity than
[SPEAKER_10]: A typical size street might, so it might be somewhat equivalent to warrant and when it's equivalent or roughly equivalent, then it's unclear which side is right away.
[SPEAKER_10]: So.
[SPEAKER_10]: It does seem like it always stop would improve as well as maybe we could reach out to some of the.
[SPEAKER_10]: Corner houses with build into potentially trim some of the site line issues to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Um, and this is a side street, of course, so it's usually not busy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Um, the weekends, the park is right there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it is busy on Saturday, Sunday mornings, not currently in the winter, of course, but, um, yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: Century street being a one way, clearly access the pair to that, even though it's two way.
[SPEAKER_10]: So it does probably receive more volume than what you would expect typically.
[SPEAKER_10]: I don't know how the traffic sergeants feel about this one, but I'm supportive.
[SPEAKER_06]: The data that we had driven, it doesn't mean that there aren't collisions at this intersection, but it depends how it gets coded into our CAD, but the numbers were... I think there was four noted collisions this year from January 1st.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, and in traffic engineering,
[SPEAKER_06]: That doesn't mean that these numbers are truly accurate.
[SPEAKER_06]: They could be categorized in a different location.
[SPEAKER_06]: And when we're looking at Warren or Cooley, if they're not categorized that way, we may not see other ones.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm not saying that that's the exact number.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm just saying that's the number we found with the data that we had from those locations.
[SPEAKER_05]: As to the petition for the both of you, is there any reason to not support this?
[SPEAKER_06]: I don't see a reason not to support it.
[SPEAKER_06]: I feel that
[SPEAKER_06]: adding the stop sign in this location.
[SPEAKER_06]: I don't see how it could not benefit us.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you, sergeants.
[SPEAKER_05]: Commissioners, any questions for either the petitioner, Director Blake, or the traffic sergeants related to this?
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, just to clarify, Todd, so is the four-way stop warranted here?
[SPEAKER_10]: So, I didn't do official warrants, but.
[SPEAKER_10]: Generally speaking, in comparison, some other requests we've received, we have.
[SPEAKER_10]: In terms of precedence, the traffic commission been approving.
[SPEAKER_10]: Somewhat similar situations where it's.
[SPEAKER_10]: you know, not a collector with a local road, arterial with a local road, it's like two local roads, and it's unclear which one is the major and which one's minor.
[SPEAKER_10]: So one of the warrants is the volume should be roughly equal on the two roads, and that makes it unclear, whereas if it's clearly one road's more volume than the other, then it's not unclear.
[SPEAKER_10]: Crash history's another, volume's another, but I didn't do an official warrant analysis, no.
[SPEAKER_10]: But generally speaking, it seems like it would meet
[SPEAKER_10]: It would likely meet them, but I haven't ran the numbers, no.
[SPEAKER_09]: Would you consider this a recommendation?
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, I would consider recommending approval, yep.
[SPEAKER_09]: I mean, that's good enough for me, fellow commissioners.
[SPEAKER_09]: If our engineering division through Todd is recommending a four-way stop here, then I would motion to approve, and I would motion that included in that motion would be a direction to DPW to trim the tree, make sure the sign is visible.
[SPEAKER_04]: One question, I guess more for Tim.
[SPEAKER_04]: Can you convert the current stop signs to like a stop always?
[SPEAKER_04]: Can we, something like that to let- An always tab?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, we can do an always tab.
[SPEAKER_10]: So yeah, Steve, once this commission, if they approve, if you approve the always stop, that's the requirement now for any always stop that it has the always tab underneath.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: We've been ordering more of those.
[SPEAKER_10]: We're trying to catch up on any that we, if you see any that don't have that, let us know.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just something to let people know that the change is coming.
[SPEAKER_04]: So just something to alert people that the change is coming.
[SPEAKER_09]: And I did notice, too, at this intersection that stop lines are not painted.
[SPEAKER_09]: So or they're faded out.
[SPEAKER_09]: Looks like some older ones that are painted.
[SPEAKER_09]: So anyway, I'm getting mixed results here on Google Earth as far as the paint goes.
[SPEAKER_09]: But if it is faded.
[SPEAKER_08]: take care of the paint.
[SPEAKER_09]: We'll freshen up the paint, we'll trim the tree, and we'll do a forward stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Regarding the tree, I think it might be a tough one to trim because it's like the trunk of it that's blocking the sign, which makes it difficult.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, we might move the sign then.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay, we'll go.
[SPEAKER_05]: All right, on the motion of Commissioner McGibbon to approve 2024-71,
[SPEAKER_05]: for a four-way stop with the caveat DPW will trim the tree and look at the painting of the stop lines.
[SPEAKER_05]: Do I have a second?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll second it.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'll go ahead.
[SPEAKER_05]: Seconded by Commissioner Hunt.
[SPEAKER_05]: Albert, could I get a roll call vote, please?
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner McGibbon?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Hunt?
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: And Chief Buckley?
[SPEAKER_05]: On the vote of four to nothing, the petition is approved.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mr. Gallo, thank you for your concerns and your presentation and your patience to see it.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, thanks for having me.
[SPEAKER_09]: If we can't move the stop sign and we can't trim the tree, the stop line that's painted will help a lot, so just so you know.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, also, Tim, if we have resources, we could consider a flashing stop there, which then would be a little more visible behind the tree.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, that'll help too.
[SPEAKER_09]: All right, thank you.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thanks.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, that concludes real business.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm not saying I want to rush out of anywhere, but this would be like a record time.
[SPEAKER_05]: I have to listen to my traffic side just tell me that the last time I wasn't here, they almost beat a record time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a holiday present, unless we want to talk about any of the things that we need to talk about.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: I will say this, as we enter the new year, we started it a little bit.
[SPEAKER_05]: start working on some of these table defense and kind of clear up, that will be our new year's resolution.
[SPEAKER_10]: Chief, if I may, I just glanced at the old and there's one really easy one, if you do want to feel accomplished to strike one off.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's up to the commissioners, but you would have to point out which one you're referencing.
[SPEAKER_10]: 2021-20 and 2021-19 have already been resolved.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, so it's up to the commissioners.
[SPEAKER_05]: You're killing me because I thought we were going to beat them out of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: But do the commissioners have an interest in this?
[SPEAKER_05]: And I would need a motion to remove 2021-19 and 2021-20 from the table list and then a motion to deny those as having already been resolved.
[SPEAKER_05]: probably shouldn't be too long.
[SPEAKER_10]: The Winthrop Street markings that we did as part of the Eversource already took care of this whole block, so it's already done all the things that we're requesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: So like the right turn only lane exists?
[SPEAKER_10]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_10]: Because this commission approved that plan.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, when we approved the plan, we approved these things.
[SPEAKER_10]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then we didn't think to remove these from the list.
[SPEAKER_01]: So these were actually approved, not even denied.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, they were covered by another item that was already approved.
[SPEAKER_10]: So now that it renders them irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I request that they motion to remove them from the, just remove them from our agenda as no longer relevant?
[SPEAKER_01]: No longer.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, again, my understanding is first we have to remove vote to remove them from the table to take them up and then you can make whatever motion you feel that would be appropriate to remove them from our agenda.
[SPEAKER_05]: So first I would need a motion to take up items 2021-19 and 2021-20 from the table to present for the commission.
[SPEAKER_01]: So motion.
[SPEAKER_05]: So the motion of Commissioner Hunt, seconded by Commissioner McGiven to take up 2021-19 and 2021-20 from tables.
[SPEAKER_05]: Can I get a quick roll call, Alba?
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner McGiven?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Hunt?
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Pozanski?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Chief Buckley?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, I vote for it and that the motion is approved.
[SPEAKER_05]: Item 2021-19 and 2021-20 both relate to Winthrop Street and parking restrictions and long turning lanes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Does the Commissioner have a motion to resolve these issues since they have already been adopted through another petition?
[SPEAKER_09]: Motion to remove them from our agenda.
[SPEAKER_05]: as having been resolved.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, as having been resolved through another petition.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'd like that to be clear.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, on the motion of Commissioner McGiven to remove 2021-19 and 2021-20 from the agenda with the understanding that they have been resolved through another petition.
[SPEAKER_05]: Do I have a second?
[SPEAKER_05]: Seconded by Commissioner Brzezinski.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'll have a roll call, please.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner McGibbon?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Hunt?
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Chief Buckley?
[SPEAKER_05]: On the vote of four to nothing, the motion is approved in 2021-19 and 2021-20 are removed from the agenda.
[SPEAKER_05]: No more time.
[SPEAKER_05]: No, just kidding.
[SPEAKER_05]: So at least that clears up.
[SPEAKER_05]: But we really should look at 2025 as a means of clearing up some of these
[SPEAKER_01]: Some of these things were table to date certain or dates for us to review and I'm wondering if that's something we can ask over the next two months for reviews to be provided.
[SPEAKER_01]: One caught my eyes, like we put in a handicap sign at West Bedford Community Center and we said we'd review in 2022 to see if that made sense and if a change was needed and we never heard anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: I also have a question about 2024-55 from Tim that was tabled.
[SPEAKER_04]: Does that still need to be tabled, Tim?
[SPEAKER_04]: I presume that was in the last meeting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Washington Street parking lot.
[SPEAKER_01]: Amanda was interested in doing outreach and now Tim and I have had a couple of discussions on that offline.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, I think it should stay on the table because yeah, we'll have to rule on something.
[SPEAKER_09]: In the future, I believe, because with the off street parking authority.
[SPEAKER_09]: So, um, there's some, there's some irons in the fire for that lot.
[SPEAKER_04]: I have one on there, 2023-51, which I think Todd was not on that, which was no parking hillside at High Street.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think it was supposed to be referred to Todd.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm okay to remove that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, 2023-51.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were, can you pull it back as the applicant?
[SPEAKER_04]: Whatever's correct and easiest, I will do.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm going to tell you, I don't know the correct answer.
[SPEAKER_05]: I think it would just be safer for us to take a motion, bring it up, and then the motion from Commissioner Brzezinski is remove it as the petitioner.
[SPEAKER_05]: I know this is kind of tedious, but it just makes me feel a little bit better.
[SPEAKER_01]: I move to take it off the table.
[SPEAKER_05]: OK, motion by Commissioner Hunt, seconded by Commissioner McGiven to take up 2023-51, no parking, any time, tow zone on High Street.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'll say it over real quick.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner McGiven?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Hunt?
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Chief Buckley.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, a vote of four to nothing.
[SPEAKER_05]: That motion is approved.
[SPEAKER_05]: Commissioner Brzezinski, you are the petitioner for 2023-51.
[SPEAKER_05]: Are you making a motion to remove that from, we would just list it as removed by petitioner?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, motion to remove by me, the petitioner.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, the motion by Commissioner Brzezinski to remove by petitioner, seconded.
[SPEAKER_05]: Sure, second.
[SPEAKER_05]: Seconded by Commissioner McGibbon.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'll have a roll call vote.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner McGibbon?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Hunt?
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Chief Buckley?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, and we'll afford nothing.
[SPEAKER_05]: That 2023-51 has been removed from the agenda, request of the petitioner.
[SPEAKER_05]: You guys are in the 24 strong.
[SPEAKER_05]: But I think it's a conspiracy because I think they're making you stay later.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's what they do.
[SPEAKER_05]: But I do think like if we spend a little bit of time each week, each month looking at some of these and doing a little bit of research, we probably resolve a lot of them fairly quickly.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know what may be helpful?
[SPEAKER_04]: What may be helpful is to try to get an idea of like who we're expecting to kind of chime in on some of these things because I can't really tell.
[SPEAKER_04]: like why they were tabled, who's supposed to be looking at them.
[SPEAKER_04]: I do note the one that Alicia pointed out about that should have been looked at at the 2022 meeting.
[SPEAKER_04]: But some of these things like referred to engineering, like I don't know who's supposed to be looking in on that.
[SPEAKER_04]: So it'd be helpful to know who we're expecting comments from.
[SPEAKER_05]: I think we have to take a look at the petition, the original full petition should exist and then the notes of those meetings, which we can do.
[SPEAKER_05]: They're all readily available for us.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, and I think we can see anything that's referred to engineering or referred to law department, whatever.
[SPEAKER_09]: I know engineering Todd is here, so we can, I think if chief, the chair wants to, you know, put an email together to say Todd or even Owen, but one of them to say, hey, these are all items in your court.
[SPEAKER_09]: We're expecting the report back.
[SPEAKER_09]: Same with law department and Janice can help with that.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that way we'll know they'll be on the agenda to remove them and then we can put a lot quicker than procedurally we're doing here, so.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, I think that most of the referred engineering are advisements.
[SPEAKER_05]: So I think that'll work.
[SPEAKER_05]: All right.
[SPEAKER_05]: Anything else?
[SPEAKER_09]: Motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_05]: Motion to adjourn, a motion that you all have happy holidays that are coming up.
[SPEAKER_05]: I have to say that as commissioner, but on the motion to adjourn, do I have a second?
[SPEAKER_05]: Second.
[SPEAKER_05]: Seconded by Commissioner Brzezinski.
[SPEAKER_05]: Alma, can we do one more roll call with you?
[SPEAKER_05]: I just like to keep you busy.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner McGibbon?
[SPEAKER_09]: Yes, happy holidays.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Hunt?
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Chief Buckley.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, so the vote of 4-0, we are adjourned.
[SPEAKER_05]: Sergeant, is that the fastest meeting?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_08]: Nope.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then I win.
[SPEAKER_05]: It is 621.
[SPEAKER_05]: I don't think I did beat it.
[SPEAKER_05]: All right, thank you all.
[SPEAKER_05]: Enjoy.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm sure I'll see most of you, but if not, have great holidays and go slow and enjoy it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thanks.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thanks, everybody.