[SPEAKER_09]: Good afternoon, everyone.
[SPEAKER_09]: Good to see you all.
[SPEAKER_09]: Technology is wonderful when it works.
[SPEAKER_09]: I always say this.
[SPEAKER_09]: I had a little trouble getting in.
[SPEAKER_09]: Amory's like, no, no, do this.
[SPEAKER_09]: Try that.
[SPEAKER_09]: But we got it done.
[SPEAKER_09]: We got it done.
[SPEAKER_09]: So I don't know why this time it was different from the other 18 million times I've done Zoom.
[SPEAKER_09]: That's technology.
[SPEAKER_09]: OK, so yeah, crazy, Bobby.
[SPEAKER_09]: It's crazy.
[SPEAKER_09]: OK, so let's start.
[SPEAKER_09]: Let's see 104.
[SPEAKER_09]: We'll start the meeting.
[SPEAKER_09]: We always try to do some housekeeping things before we jump into the actual agenda.
[SPEAKER_09]: The approval of the minutes for the May 15th, 2024.
[SPEAKER_09]: Daria, how are we doing with that?
[SPEAKER_09]: Do we have them or will they be coming to us at a later date?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, they will be coming to you at a later date.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: I know the last one we covered a lot of ground, so I know there was a lot of detailed information.
[SPEAKER_09]: So, and I know you're really great at capturing all the nuances.
[SPEAKER_09]: So, okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: So we'll suspend the approval of the minutes for the May 15th meeting.
[SPEAKER_09]: We'll push that to the next meeting.
[SPEAKER_09]: I guess let's start in the order that's on the agenda.
[SPEAKER_09]: A representative from D1 Soccer League will present two one-day license applications.
[SPEAKER_09]: This one intrigued me.
[SPEAKER_09]: Maybe that's why it was number one.
[SPEAKER_09]: A soccer game and a music performance.
[SPEAKER_09]: Gee, it'd be great if it was somebody really big, you know, like that
[SPEAKER_09]: That woman who's been touring all around the country and Taylor Swift, that would be awesome.
[SPEAKER_09]: Who do we have?
[SPEAKER_09]: Is it George?
[SPEAKER_01]: Paul George is my full name.
[SPEAKER_09]: How are you, sir?
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm well.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you for jumping on.
[SPEAKER_09]: As I said, this one intrigued us.
[SPEAKER_09]: So can you tell us a little more about the D1 Soccer League and what the ultimate goal is to have a music performance on top of a game?
[SPEAKER_09]: So if you don't mind giving us a little background as to who you are, what the league is, and tell us a little more, please.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So like I said, my name is Paul George.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am the vice president of the D1 Soccer League.
[SPEAKER_01]: We've been around for about 10 years.
[SPEAKER_01]: We played prior in the Everett Stadium, McDonnell Stadium, but we've been at the Hall-Miller Stadium for three years now.
[SPEAKER_01]: We are a semi-pro soccer league, a bunch of college kids, retired professional players.
[SPEAKER_01]: We've even had a couple of our young players made it on the professional level.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we try to
[SPEAKER_01]: We try to create an environment where young kids or young players get a chance to have college players, college coaches come out and look at them and watch them play, as well as, like, professional players who have retired and they can't really keep up with the younger kids.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's that type of environment that we try to provide.
[SPEAKER_01]: And trying to promote the league and bring it to the next level, we realized that we needed to bring in some level of entertainment.
[SPEAKER_01]: to be part of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So this is what we're trying to do, bringing a couple of artists from... Well, I'm Haitian, so we bring in a couple of Haitian artists to, like, lure the fans in and try to, like, create this atmosphere for the players.
[SPEAKER_09]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_09]: So... So it would be a game and then some kind of a music performance after the game, or was it before the game?
[SPEAKER_09]: Like, kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: So what we do is, at times, we play music on our phones.
[SPEAKER_01]: Last year, we had some DJs come in and play music for the fans.
[SPEAKER_01]: But we're looking to do a halftime performance and maybe a 30-minute performance after the game.
[SPEAKER_09]: I see.
[SPEAKER_09]: And I do see the one-day applications.
[SPEAKER_09]: Have you submitted any kind of drawings for us to show us where the performance is going to be?
[SPEAKER_09]: Is it midfield?
[SPEAKER_09]: Is it in the end zone?
[SPEAKER_09]: Is it where the stands are?
[SPEAKER_09]: I guess these were all the things that were going through my mind.
[SPEAKER_09]: Ben, Bobby, my other two commissioners, if you have questions also, be my guest, jump in.
[SPEAKER_09]: There is a sketch.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: Which shows the bleachers and where the alcohol would be.
[SPEAKER_10]: Is that right, Paul?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I tried to draw.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not much of an artist.
[SPEAKER_01]: I tried my very best to put a sketch together.
[SPEAKER_01]: where it would be serving the alcohol.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for the performance, it's two ideas that we have.
[SPEAKER_01]: With the permission of the field or the person who's in charge of the stadium, we would bring a stage towards the middle.
[SPEAKER_01]: We can build a stage toward the middle or we can build a stage towards the grass area.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're not, I mean, we're planning on having a few hundred people there at the game, depending on how well the ticket sales are.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have not really put together like a kind of plan where we would have that performance in place.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see.
[SPEAKER_09]: Bobby, any questions or thoughts on your end?
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, same thing.
[SPEAKER_08]: I was kind of wondering where the performance was going to be taking place and, you know, what type of, I mean, Mr. Georges has said that possibly DJ in the past or what type of entertainment they're going to have.
[SPEAKER_08]: One of my concerns is that
[SPEAKER_08]: There's residents all around that area.
[SPEAKER_08]: You've got the three high-rises for the towers.
[SPEAKER_08]: You've got all those new apartment complexes over by Fulcanti Rink.
[SPEAKER_08]: If the entertainment is kept at a decent level for volume and
[SPEAKER_08]: kind of had to point the speakers away from the bleachers toward the river or toward the school, you know, that would be a little better for the residents, I would imagine.
[SPEAKER_08]: But as far as the license application, the one-day license application, I do see an issue with it.
[SPEAKER_08]: One of them is you check the box that you are not a registered nonprofit, and you also check all alcohol.
[SPEAKER_08]: You can't have all alcohol unless you are a registered nonprofit.
[SPEAKER_08]: You can have wine and malt, but not all alcohol.
[SPEAKER_08]: I do see the insurance.
[SPEAKER_08]: I do see the insurances.
[SPEAKER_08]: from April 26, 24 to October 26, 24.
[SPEAKER_08]: So you have it for the dates.
[SPEAKER_08]: Other than that, unless there's somebody else that would like to speak, you know, that might have anything to say on this, this one day license.
[SPEAKER_08]: Other than that, I,
[SPEAKER_08]: I think I'm all set.
[SPEAKER_08]: Like I said, I just wanted to know about what type of performance there is and the volume of the performance.
[SPEAKER_08]: I can see that the hours, they don't go all that late anyways.
[SPEAKER_08]: I think it only goes to eight o'clock.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_08]: So yeah, that's all I have to say.
[SPEAKER_09]: Mr. Thank you.
[SPEAKER_09]: I did see the diagram.
[SPEAKER_09]: I see where where the the adult beverages, where the refreshments were going to be served.
[SPEAKER_09]: So I saw that on the schematic there.
[SPEAKER_09]: And you're right, it's not going into the wee hours, as Nick would say.
[SPEAKER_09]: So I'm kind of satisfied with that.
[SPEAKER_09]: I don't know, because the one day licenses,
[SPEAKER_09]: You know, as Bobby's correct, you can't have all alcohol.
[SPEAKER_09]: It has to be beer and wine.
[SPEAKER_09]: So we get that.
[SPEAKER_09]: That's an easy tweak.
[SPEAKER_09]: Daria, does the city have any concerns with
[SPEAKER_09]: You know, because I remember there were times when if there's, oh, there's going to be 250 people there.
[SPEAKER_09]: We want extra police details.
[SPEAKER_09]: We want, if there's a stage, well, what kind of stage is there?
[SPEAKER_09]: Is there any concerns from the city's point regarding the setup of the musical performance?
[SPEAKER_09]: Like I said, the liquor side.
[SPEAKER_09]: We see that's pretty straightforward.
[SPEAKER_09]: It's just the logistic side for the music performance at Hormel Stadium.
[SPEAKER_09]: Any thoughts or have you heard anything from the city?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Kevin Bailey, who's the Recreation Department Director, he was going to jump on just for informational purposes.
[SPEAKER_02]: he's unable to now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just notified last minute that he's unable to attend because there was an urgent issue at the task pool.
[SPEAKER_02]: Chief of staff asked me to ask you guys to postpone these two-day, one-day licenses requests till we have a special meeting, hopefully in July, so we can discuss it then with Kevin present.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay, that's interesting.
[SPEAKER_09]: Like I said, I was wondering if there was something more, because anytime there's a stage and there's electrical lines, and if it rains, and so it's just all the logistics that go along with that part of it.
[SPEAKER_09]: If that's the city's recommendation, Mr. Georges, we're not saying no.
[SPEAKER_09]: We're going to table the request for the 17th and the 31st until the city can sit and put their heads together and think about it.
[SPEAKER_09]: It's such a unique request.
[SPEAKER_09]: That's why you were first on the agenda.
[SPEAKER_09]: We'll figure it out.
[SPEAKER_09]: Between the licensing commission in the city and all the different departments that will weigh in on this, we'll figure it out and we'll do our best to make this happen for you.
[SPEAKER_09]: I see Ben.
[SPEAKER_09]: Ben, go ahead.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_10]: Just a question I wanted to ask Mr. George.
[SPEAKER_10]: Have you guys done this concept before with the game and with the music somewhere else?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, we have.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we put this together before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Normally, we try to get a halftime show together or that's about like seven minutes long because the players got to get back on the field.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then afterwards, we'll put in another like a 30-minute performance for the fans and then they would leave.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you make a stage?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, we built a small stage.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a large stage per se, and it's towards to the side.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it worked out pretty well.
[SPEAKER_01]: What city?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where was that at?
[SPEAKER_01]: We've done it in Cambridge, and then we've done it in Everett, and also Somerville.
[SPEAKER_10]: OK.
[SPEAKER_10]: All right, thank you.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, that's good to know.
[SPEAKER_08]: The only other thing, too, is you folks do hire police details, correct?
[SPEAKER_01]: So any event where we're serving alcohol, we'll definitely have a police detail.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just for safety purposes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we just think it's just better anyways.
[SPEAKER_08]: Smart.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, especially with this, you know, it's 600 people.
[SPEAKER_01]: When it comes to our games, like I said, we've been doing this for a long time.
[SPEAKER_01]: We've never had any major issues, wherever, like, violence or any fighting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Our biggest concern that we've dealt with is, like, cleanup.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's our issues that we've dealt with in the past, is after we have a large amount of fans and trying to get everybody to go home, and we would have to stay behind or come out the next day to claim.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's our obstacle.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, it's a challenge, sure.
[SPEAKER_09]: Daria, although the commission we take off July and August, that doesn't mean we vanish to Europe for those 60 days.
[SPEAKER_09]: I mean, we're still around.
[SPEAKER_09]: So there's nothing that says we cannot
[SPEAKER_09]: have a quick zoom we posted to make sure the public's aware that we're having a quick zoom so we can resolve this for Mr. Georges.
[SPEAKER_09]: I don't want you know because he's got two targets in August and I would like to get it resolved for him so he can
[SPEAKER_09]: move forward.
[SPEAKER_09]: There's nothing more frustrating than here and we're going to hold this and you got all the logistics.
[SPEAKER_09]: I mean, I plan big events and small events and it's maddening because sometimes things don't come together until like the last five, seven, eight days before the event.
[SPEAKER_09]: So I get it.
[SPEAKER_09]: So Mr. Georges, I'm going to kind of step
[SPEAKER_09]: forward a bit, and I'm going to make a recommendation that we table this until the city can look into the logistics of it.
[SPEAKER_09]: And then if Ben and Bobby don't mind, we can have a quick Zoom meeting in July and just give our opinions on what we hear from the city.
[SPEAKER_09]: And hopefully we can make this happen for Mr. Georges.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm fine with that, Mr. Chairman.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, and I would just say the sooner the better, so he can plan his event.
[SPEAKER_10]: As you said, Alan, I know you agree.
[SPEAKER_10]: And then just because it is going into summer and it's like everybody's got a million things going on and we can't just have these meetings moving all over the place.
[SPEAKER_10]: At least I can't.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I'll do my best to be available.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: So Bobby, you second my motion?
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, I'll second the motion.
[SPEAKER_09]: All right, so all in favor of tabling this until the city can investigate a little more or ask them more questions, and then we'll circle back in July.
[SPEAKER_09]: Say aye.
[SPEAKER_09]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay, so motion carries.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, Mr. Georges.
[SPEAKER_09]: It was intriguing.
[SPEAKER_09]: That's why we put you first.
[SPEAKER_09]: We've never seen something like this.
[SPEAKER_09]: Boy, I wish you could get Taylor Swift.
[SPEAKER_09]: That would be incredible.
[SPEAKER_09]: But we'll get back to you in July and give you a resolution on this request.
[SPEAKER_09]: Awesome.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, guys.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, sir.
[SPEAKER_09]: All right.
[SPEAKER_09]: Ciao.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay, let's see.
[SPEAKER_09]: Method Brewing.
[SPEAKER_09]: Hello, hello.
[SPEAKER_09]: You're requesting two one-day license applications.
[SPEAKER_09]: What do I see?
[SPEAKER_09]: Event September 27th and September 28th.
[SPEAKER_09]: Does that sound right?
[SPEAKER_09]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: So tell us a little about them.
[SPEAKER_06]: uh so we've got two requests uh one is for the uh there's a music i've got to work out which dates which here um it's because we've got there's a music festival and then there's the run medford as well um i think that was the music festival on top of my head uh
[SPEAKER_06]: And that's over the Hatshell.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's been happening the last few years where, again, very similar setup to what we do with the Farmers Market Concerts, where I said it's a one-day music festival.
[SPEAKER_06]: I think Russ Robar organizes.
[SPEAKER_06]: He's got the Hatshell booked.
[SPEAKER_06]: And yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: And the idea is, I think with that one is, if I'm getting the right one, unless I'm confusing myself, which is probably gonna happen.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I think, yeah, so one of them might be, there might be a rain date on that, if it's the right one I'm thinking of.
[SPEAKER_06]: And again, where again, we've obviously put the Nile Colby on these point signs up.
[SPEAKER_06]: I think you've got a map as well, which would be exactly the same spot we do stuff at the farmer's market as well.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yep, yep.
[SPEAKER_09]: No, you're getting good, real good at this, Nick.
[SPEAKER_09]: Real good at this.
[SPEAKER_09]: We had a little bit of practice.
[SPEAKER_09]: I don't have any questions.
[SPEAKER_09]: I mean, we're very familiar with Medford Brewing.
[SPEAKER_09]: You guys do outstanding work, outstanding service.
[SPEAKER_09]: You follow all the rules.
[SPEAKER_09]: No fighting.
[SPEAKER_09]: I think as Mr. George was saying, we've never had an incident of people getting out of hand and fighting.
[SPEAKER_09]: So I don't have any questions.
[SPEAKER_09]: My other two colleagues, anything on your mind?
[SPEAKER_09]: Any questions or concerns with this request for two one-day license applications?
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm okay with it, Mr. Chairman.
[SPEAKER_08]: I just have a quick question.
[SPEAKER_08]: On those September 27th and 28th, those are two different events, correct?
[SPEAKER_02]: Let me hang on my... It's Ron Medford still.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think it just goes for two days.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, OK.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Let me correct.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, because my brain is a little bit addled now.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that one actually is the Ron Medford.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that one where one of the events.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that's that's the David McGillivray event.
[SPEAKER_06]: where we're actually technically the beer sponsor.
[SPEAKER_06]: I think I mentioned last mass meeting where so for the run itself we are not charging for beer that is basically that's included in the admission to the run itself where it sponsors and they've got two events going for that
[SPEAKER_06]: where I think one of them we might potentially be actually selling is more of a make sure we're covered.
[SPEAKER_06]: We did it last year with them, where we had one day where we were actually selling beer.
[SPEAKER_06]: Actually, I think it was at Hormel.
[SPEAKER_06]: But in truth, it was so poorly attended by beer drinkers that we probably wouldn't do it again.
[SPEAKER_06]: But I have to say, we'll do it just to be nice to run Medford.
[SPEAKER_08]: OK.
[SPEAKER_08]: OK, that answered my question.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: But either one of my fellow commissioners want to make a motion, that would be great.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, I'm also good with these, Nick.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I can make a motion, you guys.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I'll make a motion to approve the two one-day licenses, first for the music festivals, September 15th, at the Condon show, and for the Run Medford community events, September 27th,
[SPEAKER_10]: and the 28th at Hormel, and then the 28th at Mentor City Hall for these requests.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'll second that motion.
[SPEAKER_09]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, Bobby.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, Ben.
[SPEAKER_09]: All in favor of moving forward on the two one-day licenses, say aye.
[SPEAKER_09]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_09]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_09]: Nick, you're all set.
[SPEAKER_09]: Best of luck.
[SPEAKER_09]: No rain, right?
[SPEAKER_09]: No rain?
[SPEAKER_09]: No.
[SPEAKER_09]: All right.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, sir.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_09]: Have a great one.
[SPEAKER_09]: See you, sir.
[SPEAKER_09]: All right.
[SPEAKER_09]: Ciao.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thanks.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you, Nick.
[SPEAKER_09]: Good luck.
[SPEAKER_09]: See you, guys.
[SPEAKER_09]: Well, let's take the next one, event them.
[SPEAKER_09]: They're requesting a one-day license application for June 28th.
[SPEAKER_09]: Let's see.
[SPEAKER_11]: Boom, boom.
[SPEAKER_11]: There I am.
[SPEAKER_11]: There he is.
[SPEAKER_11]: How are you, sir?
[SPEAKER_11]: Good afternoon, everybody.
[SPEAKER_11]: Good to see you.
[SPEAKER_09]: Good to see you.
[SPEAKER_09]: Tell us about the event.
[SPEAKER_11]: You're a regular too, so tell us about the event.
[SPEAKER_11]: We actually have two.
[SPEAKER_11]: There's the event, they're both at Eventham Studios.
[SPEAKER_11]: We have the Friday, August, sorry, Friday, June 28th.
[SPEAKER_11]: It's basically a copy and paste of the Sunday gaming events that we've done at the studios.
[SPEAKER_11]: And we're doing one on a Friday night.
[SPEAKER_11]: Just there's been interest on doing
[SPEAKER_11]: them on a night one.
[SPEAKER_11]: So we're going to incorporate the occasional night gaming night there as well with the FIFA tournament as the feature for it.
[SPEAKER_11]: That is the one on Friday the 28th.
[SPEAKER_11]: The 29th is once again a collaboration with JJ Gonson.
[SPEAKER_11]: You should have that application as well.
[SPEAKER_11]: Essentially a copy and paste of the performances that we've done at the studios as well.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, I see both of those.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, Brian.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yep, they both look fine to me.
[SPEAKER_08]: I checked a little earlier.
[SPEAKER_08]: Everything looks good as usual.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, we have the insurance.
[SPEAKER_09]: Daria, we have the insurance on file.
[SPEAKER_09]: I don't know if I saw that in the PDF.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, I do.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: OK, good.
[SPEAKER_09]: All right.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, we have an updated one, actually.
[SPEAKER_11]: So I can send that as well, Daria.
[SPEAKER_11]: OK.
[SPEAKER_11]: We just did a renewal.
[SPEAKER_11]: So I'll send you this one.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_09]: It's just always good to have that on file so we don't have to bug you.
[SPEAKER_09]: All right.
[SPEAKER_09]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_09]: Ben, Bobby, I don't have any questions for Brian.
[SPEAKER_09]: Do you want to make a motion?
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, I can make a motion if you like.
[SPEAKER_08]: Maybe we should do two different motions where it's two different events.
[SPEAKER_08]: Two different days, Sean?
[SPEAKER_08]: Well, two different people, JJ Gonson and Yvette.
[SPEAKER_08]: I guess the first one, we can make a motion to grant the one-day license
[SPEAKER_08]: for June 29th, 6 p.m.
[SPEAKER_08]: to 10 p.m.
[SPEAKER_08]: to J.J.
[SPEAKER_08]: Gonson being held at Event Them on Salem Street.
[SPEAKER_09]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'll second that motion.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, Ben.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, Bobby.
[SPEAKER_09]: All in favor of moving forward with the one-day license request say aye.
[SPEAKER_08]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_09]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_09]: That one's done.
[SPEAKER_08]: If you want, I can make a motion for the second one.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, let's do.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'll make a motion to grant a one-day license to the type of event, FIFA video game event to Brian at Event Them, 344 Salem Street for the hours of 5 to 9.30 PM.
[SPEAKER_09]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_09]: Ben, you want to 2nd that and I will 2nd that.
[SPEAKER_09]: All right.
[SPEAKER_09]: So, all in favor of approving that 1 day license say, I very good.
[SPEAKER_09]: That 1 carries to.
[SPEAKER_09]: Brian, you're, you're all set with both events.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_11]: I have 1 follow up question.
[SPEAKER_11]: Um, I, I, I wasn't, I wasn't aware that you, uh, that the committee takes July and August off for decades.
[SPEAKER_11]: I knew it was August.
[SPEAKER_11]: I wasn't sure about July.
[SPEAKER_11]: Um, so we actually, August 22nd, I hadn't sent that application in, um,
[SPEAKER_11]: Or basically another collaboration with J. J. it's on a Thursday, August, 22nd, and I still submit that application.
[SPEAKER_09]: Submit it and see what happens kind of yeah, I, I would submit it and if we're going to.
[SPEAKER_09]: rule on Mr. George's request that Hormel, maybe we can kill two birds with one stone.
[SPEAKER_09]: Maybe I shouldn't be saying that.
[SPEAKER_09]: That's not nice to say anymore.
[SPEAKER_09]: But Bobby, Ben, what do you think, you know, if we could do two?
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, that's fine with me.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: OK.
[SPEAKER_11]: That was really reasonable.
[SPEAKER_11]: It's the same thing as the event.
[SPEAKER_11]: It's essentially the same thing as the 29th.
[SPEAKER_04]: OK.
[SPEAKER_11]: Same collaboration, same thing with JJ.
[SPEAKER_11]: So just setting forth the expectations.
[SPEAKER_09]: And Brian, it's not that, oh, the commission's a bunch of prima donnas.
[SPEAKER_09]: They don't want to work in the summer.
[SPEAKER_09]: No.
[SPEAKER_09]: But I always try to explain to people that people take vacations.
[SPEAKER_09]: And the fire chief, the police chief, everyone takes vacations in those months.
[SPEAKER_09]: And sometimes it's impossible to get things done because everyone is going to be on holiday, including the commissioners, too.
[SPEAKER_09]: We have to take our vacations, too.
[SPEAKER_09]: So logistically, it was always hard to get anything done in those two months.
[SPEAKER_09]: And that was the impetus as to why, eons ago, the licensing commission started taking off those two months.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, not a problem at all.
[SPEAKER_11]: I just wanted to, I just, I wasn't sure.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, cool.
[SPEAKER_11]: All right.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you, sir.
[SPEAKER_11]: You all have a great afternoon.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_11]: See you, Brian.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: Mr. Sandoval, we're going to skip over you.
[SPEAKER_09]: We're on a roll with the one-day license application.
[SPEAKER_09]: So what I'd like to do is I'd like to jump over to the Riverside Yacht Club, and then we'll circle back to you if you don't mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then we'll have one more from the Frisbee Group.
[SPEAKER_09]: OK.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: So let's address the Riverside Yacht Club, their one-day license application request.
[SPEAKER_07]: How you doing?
[SPEAKER_07]: I'm Michael from Riverside Yacht Club.
[SPEAKER_09]: How are you, Michael?
[SPEAKER_07]: I'm the Vice Commodore.
[SPEAKER_07]: We're just having a little social event on September 7th.
[SPEAKER_07]: It's just basically an end of the year get together, you know.
[SPEAKER_07]: We're not expecting a big crowd or anything, maybe 50 people, and a gentleman offered to bring his band.
[SPEAKER_07]: So I put in for the application.
[SPEAKER_07]: We're looking to put them on the back deck.
[SPEAKER_07]: And that's about it.
[SPEAKER_07]: Like I said, it's nothing really elaborate or anything.
[SPEAKER_07]: It's just a little get together and he offered to play for us.
[SPEAKER_07]: So here I am.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: An application.
[SPEAKER_07]: We do have an entertainment license, but that's for devices only, so.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that doesn't cover the actual deck too.
[SPEAKER_07]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: Right, right.
[SPEAKER_09]: Tell me, how late will the event go?
[SPEAKER_07]: It's only like, I put down five to 11, but it's like six to 10.
[SPEAKER_07]: I put a couple extra hours in for setting up and cleaning up and stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_07]: I mean, I don't see it going much later than 10 o'clock anyways.
[SPEAKER_07]: I mean, we're an older crowd.
[SPEAKER_07]: We have very few young guys down there.
[SPEAKER_07]: So it's pretty low key.
[SPEAKER_07]: And like I said, he off it.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: When the request came in, that was my only concern about how late would it go in the evening and neighbors complaining, that's all.
[SPEAKER_07]: That's also why I put in the application.
[SPEAKER_07]: The neighbors are pretty good.
[SPEAKER_07]: They're nice.
[SPEAKER_07]: We get along very well with them.
[SPEAKER_07]: We try to accommodate them as best we can or exactly as much as we can.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: Bobby, Ben, any questions to Mike?
[SPEAKER_10]: I guess it's a question to the Commissioner.
[SPEAKER_10]: The all alcohol, so it's an all alcohol, is it?
[SPEAKER_10]: That wine and malt?
[SPEAKER_10]: You need to clarify that, Bobby?
[SPEAKER_08]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_08]: If they're a registered non-profit, which Michael checked yes, they can have an all-alcohol one-day license.
[SPEAKER_08]: If they're not a registered non-profit, they can only have wine and malt.
[SPEAKER_08]: Did Mr. Georges, his had non-profit too though.
[SPEAKER_08]: His did not have non-profit, I believe, if we look at it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, no, he's not a non-profit.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_09]: Maybe I'm looking at too many of them next time.
[SPEAKER_09]: No, that was one of the tweaks we will address, because he's not a non-profit.
[SPEAKER_09]: So because he was checked off, he had all alcohol and wine and malt.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, he can't get all alcohol.
[SPEAKER_09]: We'll make that correction in July.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: No, not to go on to that.
[SPEAKER_10]: No, I don't.
[SPEAKER_10]: I mean, whereas this is a fairly contained event, sometimes, Mike, we have like a diagram that shows like where things are happening.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's like, well, we may, you know, I mean, this is, I'm familiar with the club a little bit, so.
[SPEAKER_07]: Oh yeah, it's the clubhouse right off of 52 Ship Out.
[SPEAKER_07]: And then on the back side is a deck.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, right.
[SPEAKER_07]: And you walk down,
[SPEAKER_07]: They can go down the gangplank to the boats.
[SPEAKER_07]: I mean, I could draw a quick sketch on it and show you right now.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: Or, or, you know, you can draw us a sketch because we always want to see a diagram for the file, or you could do Google Earth.
[SPEAKER_09]: and take a snapshot of the location and with a marker, you could do some tweaking in there, whatever it takes.
[SPEAKER_09]: We don't expect it to come from an engineer or an architect, nothing like that.
[SPEAKER_09]: But we do want, because we are asking everybody, so we just want to be consistent with everybody.
[SPEAKER_07]: Like I said, I can draw out a quick sketch and I can leave it with Daria if you like.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, she can share it with us after and we'll say pending that if that if everybody's okay with that.
[SPEAKER_10]: I mean, that's we just do it right on the spot.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: No, I agree, Ben.
[SPEAKER_09]: It's a good point.
[SPEAKER_09]: We've been asking everybody.
[SPEAKER_09]: So let's be consistent.
[SPEAKER_09]: I agree.
[SPEAKER_10]: Do you think the bar would need to stay open until 11 or the bar can just be closed at 10 or?
[SPEAKER_07]: And they said, we're a private club and, uh, I mean, we could close the bar, but a lot of people could just go down to their boats.
[SPEAKER_07]: I mean, they have refrigerators on the boat and get a beer.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: So it doesn't really make it.
[SPEAKER_07]: I have, um, I am tip certified and all that.
[SPEAKER_07]: And I also have another gentleman that, uh, is tip certified that works on the house committee with me.
[SPEAKER_07]: So, um,
[SPEAKER_07]: I mean, we got more retired cops and state troopers down there.
[SPEAKER_07]: We got the fire boaters parked right there at the bottom of the gangplank.
[SPEAKER_07]: They're in and out of the bay.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, that we're not.
[SPEAKER_09]: We know the bigger picture down there, Mike.
[SPEAKER_09]: We agree.
[SPEAKER_09]: I mean, the risk is minimal.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah, no, we get it.
[SPEAKER_09]: OK.
[SPEAKER_09]: I don't have any other questions.
[SPEAKER_09]: Bobby, Ben, if you want to make a motion.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, I can make a motion.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm good as well.
[SPEAKER_10]: That sounds fine.
[SPEAKER_10]: And then we'll just say submitting a diagram of it.
[SPEAKER_10]: And then we'll approve, you know, once you do that, we can approve it.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I'll make a motion to accept the one day license for the Riverside Yacht Club for September 7th, 2024 for the event from 5pm to 11pm.
[SPEAKER_10]: PM as laid out by Mike Silvestro.
[SPEAKER_10]: Is that Mike Silvestro?
[SPEAKER_10]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_10]: And just subject to Mike providing us a diagram of where the alcohol will be served in this event.
[SPEAKER_08]: Great.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'll second that motion.
[SPEAKER_09]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, Ben.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, Bobby.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'll approve of the one day license for the Riverside Yacht Club for September 7th.
[SPEAKER_09]: Say aye.
[SPEAKER_09]: All right.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_09]: Mike, you're good.
[SPEAKER_09]: Lots of fun.
[SPEAKER_09]: I hope it's a successful event.
[SPEAKER_09]: No rain, right?
[SPEAKER_07]: No rain.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_07]: Good to see you.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'll get that drawing to Gary as soon as possible.
[SPEAKER_07]: Please.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_07]: All right.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_07]: Appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_07]: Take care.
[SPEAKER_07]: Bye.
[SPEAKER_09]: Gary, did you say there was one more one-day license?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, from the, oh my God, I can't think.
[SPEAKER_12]: Glory, Boston Glory.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay, cool.
[SPEAKER_12]: There's two of them, yeah?
[SPEAKER_12]: Did I see two?
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: Two, I believe, yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: Can you just grab the AD panel?
[SPEAKER_05]: That's it, thank you.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay, I see them.
[SPEAKER_09]: August 11th, right?
[SPEAKER_09]: Is that one of them?
[SPEAKER_09]: August 11th, July 27th, yep.
[SPEAKER_09]: July 27th.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay, and who do we have?
[SPEAKER_03]: Jay Tallerman.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hello, Jay, how are you?
[SPEAKER_03]: How are you?
[SPEAKER_03]: Nice to see you again.
[SPEAKER_03]: Good to see you again.
[SPEAKER_03]: We're only gonna end up using one of them.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just that we don't know yet which round.
[SPEAKER_03]: We are in first place in the division.
[SPEAKER_03]: We're gonna be hosting a playoff game.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's either going to be on the 27th or the 11th, so we won't be using both, but we thought it would be best just to get both licenses.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: Good.
[SPEAKER_09]: This is exciting that you're in the playoffs, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: We're sitting at seven and two.
[SPEAKER_03]: We've beaten all of our rivals.
[SPEAKER_03]: We're probably ranked number one in the whole league right now.
[SPEAKER_03]: Rankings come out today, so it's a really good season so far.
[SPEAKER_09]: Good, including the evil empire, right?
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, beat them last time.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, that was a big one.
[SPEAKER_09]: There's something in the water around here.
[SPEAKER_09]: I tell ya.
[SPEAKER_09]: Well, we're very familiar with your organization, Jay.
[SPEAKER_09]: You guys run a tight ship, no incidents, no problems.
[SPEAKER_09]: As long as, Jerry, do we have the insurance on file?
[SPEAKER_09]: Do we have, I know we have a schematic, because it's always the same.
[SPEAKER_09]: So are we good with the insurance?
[SPEAKER_03]: There is a certificate of insurance on file that should be fine for the whole season.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was going to say, I do have their insurance just in general.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: Has it expired?
[SPEAKER_09]: No, it shouldn't be.
[SPEAKER_09]: It should be for the whole season.
[SPEAKER_09]: It should be good.
[SPEAKER_09]: Perfect.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: Then Bobby, Ben, any questions or concerns for Jay?
[SPEAKER_09]: No.
[SPEAKER_09]: When will you know what date it is, Jay?
[SPEAKER_03]: So we won't actually know until the last weekend of the season, which is the 20th and 21st.
[SPEAKER_03]: If our two rivals, DC and New York, both lose one more game, then it's definitely going to be the 11th.
[SPEAKER_03]: If they keep winning, then it's gonna come down to the last week of the season when we have a doubleheader in Canada that we have to win both games to lock in the 11th.
[SPEAKER_03]: So we're hoping for the 11th, but we don't know for sure just yet.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: So, yeah, no issues.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think it all sounds good.
[SPEAKER_10]: Daria, is that any problem with the paperwork of like since it's two dates?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I just think as long as they let us know which date they use.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay, yeah, it's very similar.
[SPEAKER_09]: The way I'm looking at it's very similar to when we get rain dates.
[SPEAKER_09]: Look, we have one day and then a rain day.
[SPEAKER_09]: So, yeah, in a way, that's kind of each other.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, then I have no more questions.
[SPEAKER_10]: I have no issues with that.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm fine.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm good with this.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay, cool.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, I'm all set with it.
[SPEAKER_08]: Everything looks good.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm familiar with Jason.
[SPEAKER_08]: I mean, everything's been great the past couple of years, so I'm on board with it.
[SPEAKER_08]: And yeah, we can, I can make a motion if you like.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, please.
[SPEAKER_08]: Okay, I'll make a motion to grant a one day license for either July 27th,
[SPEAKER_08]: or August 11th, depending upon how the playoffs turn out.
[SPEAKER_08]: And that's for the Boston Glory.
[SPEAKER_08]: And it will be from 11 a.m.
[SPEAKER_08]: to 4 p.m.
[SPEAKER_08]: on either date.
[SPEAKER_08]: And the location will be Hormel Stadium.
[SPEAKER_09]: Very good, Bobby.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'll second the motion.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, Ben.
[SPEAKER_09]: All in favor of approving the one-day license request for July 27th and August 11th for Boston Glory, say aye.
[SPEAKER_09]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_09]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_09]: Approved.
[SPEAKER_09]: Jay, good luck.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_09]: Give them hell.
[SPEAKER_09]: We will.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thanks so much.
[SPEAKER_09]: Talk to you soon.
[SPEAKER_09]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, sir.
[SPEAKER_09]: One last item.
[SPEAKER_09]: Novarro, there you are, you're on mute.
[SPEAKER_09]: He's doing his best to try to get off mute.
[SPEAKER_02]: Alan, I'm sorry to interrupt.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think Kevin Bailey jumped on.
[SPEAKER_02]: I see him on here.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think we should probably let him know.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know if he's aware that we were just going to do it in July with him.
[SPEAKER_09]: I do see Kevin Bailey.
[SPEAKER_09]: I don't see him.
[SPEAKER_09]: But Navarre, how are you doing?
[SPEAKER_09]: I still see you on mute.
[SPEAKER_09]: I told you technology is wonderful when it works.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, he just said it.
[SPEAKER_12]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_12]: Back to mute, Alvaro.
[SPEAKER_12]: There we go.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yep, done.
[SPEAKER_12]: Good job.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you all.
[SPEAKER_12]: Good to see you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good to see you again.
[SPEAKER_09]: So it's excited.
[SPEAKER_09]: Look, Alita is finally coming to fruition.
[SPEAKER_09]: We're excited for you.
[SPEAKER_09]: The Square, the community's excited for you.
[SPEAKER_09]: Your El Tecuba is just wonderful.
[SPEAKER_09]: I think you have the Midas touch, sir.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're happy to be on the Square and keep investing, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: in the square, so.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you for choosing MedBit for your businesses and helping the community.
[SPEAKER_09]: Before we dive into the application, can you tell us the concept of what you're putting in, what it consists of, what you'll be serving?
[SPEAKER_09]: Can you paint us a picture of what LocalEat is going to be all about?
[SPEAKER_09]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is a cafe.
[SPEAKER_00]: that we're going to be servicing pastry sandwiches and also small plates.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we want people to be able to get, if they want, a glass of wine or if they want a cocktail.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what we're looking to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, tweak it a little bit in the afternoon, evening, so we can stay open and then have a little bit of
[SPEAKER_00]: of different things on the inside.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know, that's the idea that we want to do, the concept.
[SPEAKER_09]: I see.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, coffees, different types of coffees or... Just one line of coffees, but, you know, not too much of extent, but we're mixing with some...
[SPEAKER_00]: some pastry sandwiches and some salads.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is just the start of.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then also small place in different, not a specific region that needs to be, but we want to have like, you know, good food so you can also have it in the evening, also probably part of the day.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's what we're looking to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So hopefully it works out the idea that we have in mind.
[SPEAKER_09]: Cool.
[SPEAKER_09]: Ben, Bobby, questions?
[SPEAKER_09]: Before we jump into the application, like I said, I wanted an idea of what he's putting in.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm all for Medford Square being a destination.
[SPEAKER_09]: The more the merrier.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm so tired of hearing about Davis Square and Malden Square, and this is what we need.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, I know some, some, I think like last I don't remember if you did this last time people will give the menu.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's why they actually do.
[SPEAKER_10]: They usually do show us the menu.
[SPEAKER_10]: No, really.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: It's kind of like one of the things, because you sort of evaluate it.
[SPEAKER_10]: But, I mean, from what you're explaining, and it's caffeine, it was coughed the Mystic Roaster, right?
[SPEAKER_10]: Right.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_10]: So, I mean, you know, and I looked at the plan, and it's like, whatever, you know, 20 seats or something like that, or less, maybe.
[SPEAKER_10]: And, I mean, it's, you know, I'm not, nothing is,
[SPEAKER_10]: About about this is really, you know, seem like an issue to me.
[SPEAKER_10]: So.
[SPEAKER_10]: So, yeah, why don't we look into the to the actual application and yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: So we're, we're, we're great with the concept, but, but Ben is correct.
[SPEAKER_09]: Usually we do want to see some type of a menu when 1 is drawn up a lot or if you don't mind.
[SPEAKER_09]: submit one to the city so we have one for the file is, you know, what we were saying to the Riverside Yacht Club, we'd like a drawing because we want to be consistent with everybody.
[SPEAKER_09]: We're trying to treat all the entities the same way so no one can say, well, why didn't you ask them?
[SPEAKER_09]: You didn't ask them.
[SPEAKER_09]: So we're just trying to be consistent.
[SPEAKER_09]: So when you do have one, you know, if you could get it over the diary so we can put it in your folder, that would be great.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: So let's take a look at the application.
[SPEAKER_09]: I saw Daria, you had sent us an updated version, correct?
[SPEAKER_09]: Like the last few pages?
[SPEAKER_09]: Bobby, did you see the updated version?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: What was the difference Daria?
[SPEAKER_02]: Sorry, I missed that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was just small things like clicking no and yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: That was just missing basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then the biggest one was three months of,
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, my God, our bank statements.
[SPEAKER_02]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: So.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, we're trying, Laura, we're trying to do our best to help ABCC.
[SPEAKER_09]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_09]: What we don't want is we don't want them going, geez, so what are they still not over there in Medford?
[SPEAKER_09]: So we we try to make sure that a completed packet is heading their way.
[SPEAKER_09]: So yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: You know, so that's that we're not, you know, we're not being a pain.
[SPEAKER_09]: It's just that, you know, kind of reflects on all of us, you and us, you know, if we're sending them an application that's not completed correctly, or their information is omitted, then, you know, they, like I said, they'll scratch their head and start asking questions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, no, and I appreciate the.
[SPEAKER_00]: Daria, that she's been helping me a lot.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all of you, I mean, this is the third one that I'm going to be applying in the city, besides in Somerville, so that I did it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they all have been very helpful.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I understand the process.
[SPEAKER_09]: OK, thank you.
[SPEAKER_10]: I was curious, is that your business partner, Andres?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's my brother.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your brother, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: We both sell the notch and the brand itself, so now we're just trying to grow the business.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, great.
[SPEAKER_10]: How's business?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's doing good, can't complain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything is going well, and having a different, especially in Metford,
[SPEAKER_00]: putting something that we, you know, being in Metford Square for a while now, for more than 12 years, yeah, just to see what the square is shaping, getting the shape and what needs, and the needs.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we think it's just, you know, hopefully it works out.
[SPEAKER_00]: We think that's a need, you know, for the community, not just for the community, for everyone who's passing by and then stopping by and then,
[SPEAKER_00]: The same as the new place that we opened in Tacuba, we thought, you know, that's something that it will be a good fit.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so far, it's been great.
[SPEAKER_00]: So a lot of support.
[SPEAKER_00]: So hopefully this one is going to go that way.
[SPEAKER_09]: Tacuba is cool.
[SPEAKER_09]: How's the outdoor part working out for you?
[SPEAKER_09]: Good?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's good.
[SPEAKER_00]: We just kind of, as a matter of fact, we
[SPEAKER_00]: off, officially open on Sunday, like some people were sitting, my brother just went in and then, seen a few tables, sit down, and then all of a sudden some people were just, you know, passing by and sitting.
[SPEAKER_00]: We probably, by the end of the week, we hope to be like now announcing we open.
[SPEAKER_00]: We want to see how it works with the layout of the inside.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some people change, you know, the reserve, they want to move out, or how we're going to be,
[SPEAKER_00]: you know, working on that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I know.
[SPEAKER_09]: I drove by and it looked completely false.
[SPEAKER_09]: So again, you've got to touch.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: All right.
[SPEAKER_09]: So application.
[SPEAKER_09]: Bobby, I've scanned through the new packet.
[SPEAKER_09]: It kind of closes up the stuff from the first package.
[SPEAKER_09]: Did you see any inconsistencies?
[SPEAKER_08]: No, I went over it myself when we received the update.
[SPEAKER_08]: It looks good.
[SPEAKER_08]: All of the issues seem to have been corrected.
[SPEAKER_08]: The bank statements are on there, but if it's not satisfactory to the ABCC, the inspector will tell you, Alvaro, what you need to do.
[SPEAKER_08]: They like to see that full amount on the statements, but you can deal with that with the ABCC inspector, and I'm sure it'll be taken care of.
[SPEAKER_08]: Everything else, it looked fine to me.
[SPEAKER_08]: You did a nice job on the application.
[SPEAKER_08]: You did pretty well.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: You're welcome.
[SPEAKER_10]: What was your target opening date on this?
[SPEAKER_00]: We're working on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a matter of fact, the Fire Alarm company just called me today.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're pretty much about to wrap up.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think they have to call, obviously, the inspection of services and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's all dependent on that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then myself just going back to the health department to get what they need from us.
[SPEAKER_00]: As soon as we can, I will say.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's hard for me to put a date, because if something happens, I always move forward.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's hard, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we want to open as soon as we can.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's for sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, cool.
[SPEAKER_09]: OK.
[SPEAKER_09]: I don't have any other concerns or questions.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm kind of going through the bank statements too.
[SPEAKER_09]: May 1st, May 31st.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm good with the updated corrections to the application.
[SPEAKER_09]: Daria, I think you did a great job advising through the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: She's great.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to put it on record.
[SPEAKER_00]: She really helped me a lot.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not easy because I know she has a pile of work and then she still find a way to really either send an email, like remind something that is missing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's really appreciated.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know how difficult it is to deal with all those things, especially last minute.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, no, and I'm looking at the, you notified the abutters, I can see all the certified mail receipt.
[SPEAKER_09]: I was on the city council agenda because Ben and I were, our commissions were being renewed.
[SPEAKER_09]: And one of the hot, hot topics was the methadone clinic.
[SPEAKER_09]: And so many of the neighbors got up and said that they were never notified.
[SPEAKER_09]: They never got anything in the mail.
[SPEAKER_09]: And so I was like, you know, what do you mean you didn't get anything in the mail?
[SPEAKER_09]: So I said, do we have the
[SPEAKER_09]: you know, all the verification that the abutters had been notified.
[SPEAKER_09]: And there they all are here.
[SPEAKER_09]: So only, you know, like I said, I'm just, it's just going through my head.
[SPEAKER_09]: So I'm good.
[SPEAKER_09]: Bobby, Ben, you want to make a motion so we can help Elvaro move forward with Localita?
[SPEAKER_09]: Would be great.
[SPEAKER_09]: I can't help you at Cuban Coffee, but I'm sure you'll figure something out, so.
[SPEAKER_10]: I can make a motion on that if you guys are okay with that.
[SPEAKER_10]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_10]: All right, so I will make a motion to grant the sorry.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm just sorry I just was clicking between this, this is the all, it's a beer and wine, or spirit wine and wine cordials and cordials yeah so the beer and wine and cordials.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay, there we go.
[SPEAKER_10]: New license for Localito LLC at 30 Riverside Ave.
[SPEAKER_10]: When Alvaro has a menu available, please send it to the commission.
[SPEAKER_10]: I will.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'll keep that on the record.
[SPEAKER_10]: Daria's great.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's on the record already.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think that's it.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's my motion.
[SPEAKER_10]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, Ben.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'll second the motion.
[SPEAKER_09]: OK.
[SPEAKER_09]: All in favor of moving forward with this new application, say aye.
[SPEAKER_09]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_09]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_09]: Navarre, you're good.
[SPEAKER_09]: I was just looking to see how many licenses we have requests for beer, wine, and cordials.
[SPEAKER_09]: If I'm reading the quota breakdown, it looks like there's four.
[SPEAKER_09]: So you're going to snag one of the four.
[SPEAKER_09]: So we'll have three left.
[SPEAKER_09]: Good.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, sir.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you for coming.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_09]: Best of luck.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: All right.
[SPEAKER_00]: I see you.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of you in the place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: When it's open.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, sir.
[SPEAKER_00]: Appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bye.
[SPEAKER_09]: Bye.
[SPEAKER_09]: I see Kevin.
[SPEAKER_09]: Kevin, you're on mute.
[SPEAKER_09]: Hi, how are you?
[SPEAKER_09]: Good, good.
[SPEAKER_09]: Kevin, what we decided to do with the soccer D, with the game and the musical performance, what we decided to do was put it on hold and let the city look into the logistics of the combined events.
[SPEAKER_09]: And what we told Mr. Georges is that we would get back to him in July.
[SPEAKER_09]: Even though this commission takes off July and August, we don't have an issue with that.
[SPEAKER_09]: We need to get together for 15 minutes and do a public Zoom or something like that.
[SPEAKER_09]: So that was our thought.
[SPEAKER_09]: So we'll give you guys ample time.
[SPEAKER_09]: But he wants to do a couple of events in
[SPEAKER_09]: August.
[SPEAKER_09]: So we need to get an opinion to them.
[SPEAKER_09]: I was saying I've done these big events and little events and there's nothing more frustrating where you don't know whether things are going to come together until a week before.
[SPEAKER_09]: So if you can help us out, that would be great.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, I'll, I'll reach out to the organizer and also have our facility manager who oversees home out will probably set up a meeting with him and what his plans are for the alcohol permit and stuff and hopefully we can.
[SPEAKER_05]: expedite that later on in July.
[SPEAKER_05]: So I appreciate that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, cool.
[SPEAKER_09]: And you know, on the surface, you know, it looks fine to us the you know, the one the one day requests.
[SPEAKER_09]: So that looks fine.
[SPEAKER_09]: But it's just I am concerned about the other part of it, and how they all they meld together.
[SPEAKER_09]: So so we'll resolve this farm in July.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: Cool.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you so much commissioners.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you for having me.
[SPEAKER_09]: All right.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_09]: Gary, I think we, we have everybody if I'm looking at the agenda, I think we've.
[SPEAKER_09]: Taking care of all the requests.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_09]: Cool.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: So, um.
[SPEAKER_09]: Before we talk about any other business that may arise, I think you had some questions you wanted us to discuss the new proposed layout for the 1 day license application.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: So tell us how do you see it?
[SPEAKER_09]: It's going to be all interactive and they can just type right into it.
[SPEAKER_09]: Tell me more about what your vision is of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I actually was Bobby's.
[SPEAKER_02]: Bobby, remember he sent it to us after the last meeting, which I liked that he included payment because that was going to be easier to
[SPEAKER_02]: Even though we have a lot of nonprofits, we still have some for profits.
[SPEAKER_02]: Some of them are really good about paying, some of them are not.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we want to keep that on there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So if they haven't paid and we know that's not checked off, I can follow up and say, you know, we can issue you, we cannot, for example, review this application until you pay us the fee first.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it also has rain dates on there and it also has,
[SPEAKER_02]: avoiding where it says, if you're not having the one day license event, let the commission know.
[SPEAKER_02]: But this way we can void it or whatever, you know?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because a lot of people do do that where they tell me, oh, I didn't have this event, but we didn't know because we weren't notified, you know, till the moment when this person is like, oh yeah, I didn't have an event on that day.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I think that's important.
[SPEAKER_02]: Bobby, what else did you?
[SPEAKER_08]: The application must be filled out completely.
[SPEAKER_08]: Not applicable.
[SPEAKER_08]: But other than that, yeah, it's not really one of those fill-in-your-own-forms.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm not that talented, Alan.
[SPEAKER_08]: Maybe you'll be able to take it.
[SPEAKER_09]: No, I love those interactive forms.
[SPEAKER_09]: Those interactive PDFs are great.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's what I was going to say.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can turn it into PDF.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just Word right now, just to have it at least drafted somewhat.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then if we like what we see, I can turn it into PDF.
[SPEAKER_09]: I, I think that would be great.
[SPEAKER_09]: You know, we, you know, I'm constantly reminded by all my nieces and nephews uncle Alan.
[SPEAKER_09]: It's 2024.
[SPEAKER_09]: So this is what I get from them all the time.
[SPEAKER_09]: So let's let's get the the word document together.
[SPEAKER_09]: I Bobby I'd like to your recommendations and
[SPEAKER_09]: I think let's adopt it, let's vote to adopt it and then when Daria has time, if she can convert it to a PDF so it can be interactive for the kids, that would be great.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, that works.
[SPEAKER_08]: That way they could fill it out online and just submit it.
[SPEAKER_08]: And, you know, even if they, it's like the ABCC, they have them fill it out online, print it, and then submit it to Daria.
[SPEAKER_08]: They can do the same thing with this and submit their check with it at the same time, because there's a box at the bottom, fee with the line payable to City of Medford, payment to one day of application.
[SPEAKER_08]: So when they submit the application, there's a check for $60.
[SPEAKER_08]: We don't have to chase, Daria doesn't have to chase people for money all the time and just make life a little easier, you know?
[SPEAKER_09]: No, it's smart.
[SPEAKER_09]: It's smart.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm good.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm in favor as well.
[SPEAKER_10]: No, no, that sounds making, you know, let's get up to, to the modern, you know, way of doing these things.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, no, definitely in favor of it.
[SPEAKER_10]: Cool.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_08]: I was thinking of tying in something else with that, but I think it's better off in a separate form for caterers licenses, because they're required to notify us in the police department 48 hours in advance if they're going to have an event in the city.
[SPEAKER_08]: I mean, we don't have to approve it.
[SPEAKER_08]: We have jurisdiction there, but they're required to notify us.
[SPEAKER_08]: So maybe we can just have a small one pager
[SPEAKER_08]: that if somebody calls the area or the police saying, well, look, we're notifying you, we're having an event that event them, like, you know, whatever.
[SPEAKER_08]: And it's sure there's a form you got to fill out, just email it back to us.
[SPEAKER_08]: You're all set.
[SPEAKER_08]: I mean, we don't have we don't have to sit.
[SPEAKER_08]: It doesn't have to come before us or anything as long as the area gets notification.
[SPEAKER_08]: That's all we could get.
[SPEAKER_09]: Could that be done?
[SPEAKER_09]: You know, I'm thinking of
[SPEAKER_09]: When I used to work, could that be done through the city website?
[SPEAKER_09]: Could we put language on the license commission in that section?
[SPEAKER_09]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: Do something there?
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: just let me know what you want and then I will have Lisa added, Lisa from our office to add it to the website.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: So that's not- Bobby, I was just thinking, you know, in residential lending, we, you know, we, oh, let's have that.
[SPEAKER_09]: No, let's just put it on the website.
[SPEAKER_09]: So when they're looking at rates, they can see all the, you know, all the narrative that associated with the programs and rates.
[SPEAKER_09]: So we'll come up with something for you.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: So, okay, so do we need to make a motion to approve the.
[SPEAKER_09]: The application, I think so.
[SPEAKER_09]: Right.
[SPEAKER_09]: I motion just revised application.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, I make a motion to revise the, the, the, the 1 day license application.
[SPEAKER_09]: That's my motion.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'll second it.
[SPEAKER_09]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_09]: All in favor, say aye.
[SPEAKER_09]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_09]: So let's get that into print, and let's see if we can get it in a PDF, and let's start using it as soon as we can.
[SPEAKER_09]: Cool.
[SPEAKER_10]: Mr. Commissioner, can I ask you a quick question about just the last thing?
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: When Brian Bailey came on, he came on, but he was coming on to talk about the soccer event or give some insight.
[SPEAKER_10]: But we just didn't want to hear.
[SPEAKER_10]: I was just curious why we didn't want to hear from him now.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think because the other party has to be here to
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever the issues are, probably you want the other part to explain, you know what I mean?
[SPEAKER_09]: And I think, Ben, it's a good observation.
[SPEAKER_09]: I think by tabling the requests, now the pressure is off, so now they can kind of
[SPEAKER_09]: look at it differently rather than under the gun in the last half hour.
[SPEAKER_09]: I think that's why we took the wind out of his sails by saying, look, we're going to hold this until July when you guys can all study it.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm guessing that's what happened.
[SPEAKER_08]: They've never been in the city before, correct?
[SPEAKER_08]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_02]: For the past three years.
[SPEAKER_02]: They have?
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, yeah, I have not done the not the music event, but no, no, no, not the music event.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_10]: So my only comment on that, which was like a little, I don't know, disappointing or whatever you want to call it, but was that we have to have a special meeting now.
[SPEAKER_10]: For for a reason we are not aware of yet, I guess, and so it's sort of like I know it's all Brian was trying to get on the call, but it was it's.
[SPEAKER_10]: For the last three years, we really never end up taking any break from this and we have a lot of special meetings to sort of accommodate different things.
[SPEAKER_10]: So, you know, I always try to avoid that if we have to, because it's like a whole other thing to schedule.
[SPEAKER_09]: No.
[SPEAKER_10]: So that's my, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_10]: That's my comment.
[SPEAKER_09]: I get, I get it.
[SPEAKER_09]: But rather than making, trying to make a decision today on that, when we didn't have all the pieces of the puzzle, I, I don't think that would be prudent for the, for us in the city.
[SPEAKER_09]: So, and I agree, Ben, I don't like the idea that, you know, okay, July, August, but you know, we'll make it painless in July.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, well, and also the guy needs to plan his event.
[SPEAKER_10]: I mean, do you have to plan your event without it?
[SPEAKER_02]: I guess you do, but... The village was truly an emergency at the Tufts pool that happened that involved a child, so that's why Kevin couldn't come on time.
[SPEAKER_10]: I don't doubt that he had a legitimate reason.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_10]: All right, that's my only thing.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'll think about that.
[SPEAKER_10]: I get it.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay, two last things.
[SPEAKER_09]: Dari, anything on your mind before I jump in?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I don't think so.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, I have a lot on my mind.
[SPEAKER_09]: This year is my 12th year on the commission.
[SPEAKER_09]: I enjoy what we do in helping the city and I enjoy my other two commissioners, but what I'd like to do is I wish to stay on the commission, but I want to
[SPEAKER_09]: put up the chair, either to Bobby or Ben, and see which one of you would like to take over with the new fiscal year after this month.
[SPEAKER_09]: So I'm staying on, but I'd like to turn the chair over
[SPEAKER_09]: to either my two fellow commissioners.
[SPEAKER_09]: And there's some logic there.
[SPEAKER_09]: As you know, I retired after 42 years as a banker, and we've been doing retirement stuff, and we've been going back and forth to Florida, and I don't ever want to
[SPEAKER_09]: um, jeopardize the city or this commission by, you know, being somewhere traveling is something enjoying my retirement and, and you go, geez, the chair is not even going to make this meeting.
[SPEAKER_09]: So I don't think, again, I don't think it's fair to the commission into the city.
[SPEAKER_09]: So, uh, Ben, Bobby, I, uh, I make a motion that either one of you, you're both very smart and talented and, and you're up on, uh, one 38 and you're out and you ask it very,
[SPEAKER_09]: insightful questions, but I would like to offer either one of you the chair.
[SPEAKER_09]: So, Ben, Bobby, any thoughts or comments?
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, I may, you know, as the second ranking time person here, you know, just a second, you know, I think, you know, when I appreciate you being the chair, Alan, big shoes to fill with Jim leaving.
[SPEAKER_10]: You've done a great job and been committed.
[SPEAKER_10]: So do appreciate that.
[SPEAKER_10]: I think, you know, and I also was sworn in last night for another six years.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I'm here.
[SPEAKER_10]: I do think with my current life of three little kids and running my business that I wouldn't be the best fit for the chair.
[SPEAKER_10]: I was thinking about arm wrestling Bobby for it, but he may win on that one.
[SPEAKER_10]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_10]: Also, so but in real reality, I think, you know, you know, and Bob, Bobby is newer, but has just become such an expert and is so diligent with
[SPEAKER_10]: with really a lot of things, and we all know that.
[SPEAKER_10]: And so I would like to weigh in that I would definitely feel very confident in Commissioner Delfano being the new chair as you are stepping down.
[SPEAKER_10]: So that's my just opinion on the matter.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, Ben.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_09]: You're, you're, you're spot on with all your points.
[SPEAKER_09]: Um, Commissioner Delifano, the, uh, what say you, are you, are you up for, uh, the chair position?
[SPEAKER_08]: Well, um, I don't know when Ben had them sunglasses on a minute ago, he looked like he should have been in the movies.
[SPEAKER_08]: It was just like, wow, where's he been all these years?
[SPEAKER_08]: But you always go back.
[SPEAKER_08]: Look at that, that's awesome.
[SPEAKER_08]: And I don't know about the arm wrestling, Ben.
[SPEAKER_08]: I think you got it all over me in that department at this stage of the game.
[SPEAKER_08]: But I would be honored to accept the chair.
[SPEAKER_08]: I have the time.
[SPEAKER_08]: You two gentlemen, like Ben said, Alan, you stepped up when Jim retired.
[SPEAKER_08]: It wasn't an easy position.
[SPEAKER_08]: I just filled in one week when you weren't here and it isn't quite as easy as it looks.
[SPEAKER_08]: And Ben had done it a couple of times and he did a great job.
[SPEAKER_08]: But I do have the time.
[SPEAKER_08]: I am somewhat familiar with 138 where I was in the liquor business many years ago, the sales rep.
[SPEAKER_08]: So, um, that's kind of how, like, I understand it a little, but we all bring something to the table.
[SPEAKER_08]: Um, you know, Ben, you've got the, the, uh, construction, uh, knowledge, uh, and, and Alan, you've got the, uh, financial financing and stuff.
[SPEAKER_08]: And, you know, I've got a little bit of the ABCC stuff.
[SPEAKER_08]: So I think we're a great team.
[SPEAKER_08]: And of course, Daria, she just holds it all together.
[SPEAKER_08]: She makes us all look really good.
[SPEAKER_08]: So, I mean, um, I really enjoyed talking with Daria and
[SPEAKER_08]: working with Daria, we seem to work fine together.
[SPEAKER_08]: I think it would be a good fit for the commission and I'd be honored to accept the chair.
[SPEAKER_09]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_09]: Ben, I'll make a motion to
[SPEAKER_09]: uh, appoint, uh, Commissioner Bobby Delafano as the- the new chair of the Licensing Commission, um, starting September, right?
[SPEAKER_09]: Because, uh, oh, no, at the end of this- the end of this month, right, Darren?
[SPEAKER_09]: It's the- the fiscal year ends in June, right?
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: June 30th, yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: So the beginning of the next city fiscal year.
[SPEAKER_09]: Ben, you wanna second?
[SPEAKER_10]: I- I'll- I'll second that motion.
[SPEAKER_09]: Gladly.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_09]: All right.
[SPEAKER_09]: So all in favor say aye.
[SPEAKER_09]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_11]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_09]: Congratulations, Bobby.
[SPEAKER_09]: You've been great to work with and I'm just in awe at your knowledge and it's gonna be a lot of fun, a lot of fun.
[SPEAKER_09]: So congratulations, sir.
[SPEAKER_09]: And then one last item.
[SPEAKER_09]: I understand that control compliance checks were done throughout the city.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'm hoping that everybody passed and we don't have any incidents.
[SPEAKER_09]: I know in the past we've always had at least one, which isn't bad when you think about how many package stores and restaurants and
[SPEAKER_09]: you know, how many vendors or entities are out there.
[SPEAKER_09]: But I think, and this will be, Bobby will be the chair, but in the past we've had separate hearings for if a violate, if we've come across a violation.
[SPEAKER_09]: And I remember that some of them used to go 30 minutes, 40 minutes, 50 minutes.
[SPEAKER_09]: And it depended on the severity and depended on
[SPEAKER_09]: who it was that committed the infraction.
[SPEAKER_09]: But I guess what I'm driving at is we'll find out if anyone failed the control compliance checks, and that's something that we have to think about in September when we come back and we're up and running again, and how we want to handle them, whether we want to
[SPEAKER_09]: have a separate hearing for them, or do we ask Daria that we'll do one at a time, or I'm hoping it's none at a time, but sometimes we get-
[SPEAKER_09]: Well, we're not fully sure how many in total.
[SPEAKER_09]: We have an idea of how many have not passed, but we're not completely sure.
[SPEAKER_09]: So we'll just kind of hang on until September when we see the final number, and then we can figure out how we want to address them, whether we want to do them on a Wednesday with a regular meeting, or we want to have a separate.
[SPEAKER_09]: Again, the three of us will come up with
[SPEAKER_09]: something that will work for the city, for the commission, and for any of the entities that committed the infractions.
[SPEAKER_09]: Sound like a plan or no?
[SPEAKER_08]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, that sounds good.
[SPEAKER_08]: And I think if even if we need to discuss this, we can legally as long as if there are any issues, we don't mention who the issues are, what licenses they were.
[SPEAKER_08]: We can just talk in general that
[SPEAKER_08]: okay the city had several infractions and and this is how we're going to handle it uh why don't we start in September and we can set up this this and this we'll meet with Lieutenant Lockowitz and they and the other two officers and uh and and not discuss any names of any businesses but just what the best course of action is because I I've never
[SPEAKER_08]: been involved.
[SPEAKER_08]: Alan and Ben, both in the area, have all been involved with it before.
[SPEAKER_08]: But since I've been on the commission, I haven't been involved.
[SPEAKER_08]: So I really don't know the procedure, you know, to a T. I wouldn't feel comfortable even, you know, fining somebody or suspending somebody unless I really felt good about knowing what to do, you know.
[SPEAKER_08]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_08]: And I think, like I said, it's OK that we talk about it as long as we don't mention any names.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: No decisions.
[SPEAKER_09]: No rulings.
[SPEAKER_09]: Just table it for now then.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_09]: Just until we see the full report.
[SPEAKER_09]: And like I said, we'll come back.
[SPEAKER_09]: We'll be back up and running in September.
[SPEAKER_09]: So that's it for me.
[SPEAKER_09]: Dari, anything from you?
[SPEAKER_09]: Any trips coming up?
[SPEAKER_09]: Anything you want to share with us?
[SPEAKER_09]: No, no, nothing fun.
[SPEAKER_12]: All right, cool.
[SPEAKER_10]: All right, so we have a motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm going to make a motion to adjourn our meeting, our June meeting to 12 p.m.
[SPEAKER_10]: or to 18 p.m.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, very good.
[SPEAKER_09]: I second.
[SPEAKER_09]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_09]: All right.
[SPEAKER_09]: So motion to adjourn to 18.
[SPEAKER_09]: I know there was a lot to cover.
[SPEAKER_09]: And thank you for taking the notes.
[SPEAKER_09]: And we'll be talking to you in July.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_09]: Sounds good.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you guys.
[SPEAKER_09]: Cool.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thanks, everybody.
[SPEAKER_09]: Good to see you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Congrats, Bobby.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Congrats.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.