Hey listeners, this is Danielle. And Shelley. Shelley is a radical Dravidian and racial equity activist. And Danielle is a community mobilizer and changemaker. And this is the Medford Bites podcast. Every two weeks, we chew on the issues facing Medford and deliver bites of information about the city by lifting the expertise of our guests. Join us in discussion about what you hope for the future of Medford. And as always, tell us where you like to eat.
Thank you so much for joining us today. If you don't mind just introducing yourself to us with your name, pronouns, and just a bit about who you are. All right, well, thank you for having me. I am Kate Quinn. My pronouns are she, her, hers, and I am the program manager here for Medford Recreation. I help structure programs, create programs, and even coach some of the programs myself.
Thank you. And we'll get into more of that. I think there's some certain programs that we're excited to hear about today. But we're going to start with just the question that we ask everybody on the podcast, which is, what is your favorite place to eat in Medford? And what do you like to eat there? Okay, so I couldn't pick one place. So I have a top three. I really enjoy Chili Garden. And their pineapple fried rice is one of my favorite dishes there. Or
The pork belly is also another really good one. Yes. I also really enjoy a chicken salad sandwich from Lakasha's. OK. And my last would be buttermilk chicken from Snappy Patty's. OK. Doing it right. I love all of those answers. Yes. I definitely enjoy the food in Medford. And it was hard for me to decide which three.
I could talk about. Sometimes it's the hardest question. And I think it can change depending on your mood and the day and what meal you're thinking about. But I don't think lakashas has come up, so I'm glad that you brought that one up. So we're really interested to hear anything that you want to share about Medford Rec, especially I think we were kind of put in touch with you to talk about the adaptive programs that Medford Rec offers. So I'm wondering if you could tell us a little bit about any of those.
Yeah, so Medford Recreation, we strive to be like an inclusive department, like no matter what program we're trying to be accommodating for all, right? So to make that happen, we started offering an inclusion request form. This is something that anybody can go online and fill out to ask for any type of accommodations for all of our programs.
We also have an intake form that can help me and the rest of my staff get to know the participant, maybe what works best, what doesn't really work for them, and or the best way to reach their goals, right? So, and so once we started doing all that, adding in our adaptive program, so we decided, you know, sometimes not everybody's ready for a certain program, and
All our participants, you know, who may have special needs or physical or cognitive disabilities, we decided to add in one adaptive program per session to help meet the needs of people who may not be ready to participate in, you know, Medford youth sports or even just, you know, our non-adaptive programs, right? And what I've noticed from a few of our participants is this, this adaptive program has kind of transitioned
these patrons or participants into feeling comfortable, into feeling ready to participate in our non-adaptive programs. And it's really kind of a great feeling just to see, you know, the families and the participant just to feel comfortable and excited to start a program. And maybe they didn't need a one-to-one in the adaptive program, but maybe adding a one-to-one for the beginning of
non-adaptive program was the way to get them to transition and the way to get them in and using that inclusion request form really helps us figure out what that child needs to be successful. So I want to make sure I'm understanding. So if you, it works like if you had a child who
needed an accommodation to be able to participate in sort of like a non-adaptive program, you could fill out this request form, or is it also to request a specific program for a child who might not be ready for those non-adaptive programs? So it's not to request a program, it is to request accommodations to help assist with the program.
Okay. And you said you gave an example of like a one-on-one. So like, can you explain more about what some of those accommodations might look like or what are sort of reasonable requests? Yeah. So like a one-on-one, right. Might be just a volunteer partnered up with the participant to help them stay focused or repeat the instructions, you know, possibly go hand over hand if necessary. We have.
visual cues, I can make communication boards that I've used in the past. We did also just work with Merge Consulting and had a really good training this summer. So I've gotten a few more tools that I can access as well.
There's also accommodations if you need large writing and, you know, if you have sight issues, if you need an interpreter, you can request that. We do ask, you know, that you give us at least two weeks notice so we can try to make our best at getting those accommodations for you.
I wonder, have there been any barriers to like expanding this program or like initiating? So honestly, for me, the biggest barrier has been finding volunteers, right? We've gotten some really, really great, passionate and driven volunteers, but in order to
bring enrollment up, I need more staff and volunteers. And to keep the price down, we try not to use as much staff as we do volunteers.
I haven't even occurred to me, like how, yeah, the, the idea of like, where are you getting these people to help out with these accommodations? So it's, it is like a volunteer program. Like, how do you like recruit people? Is it just kind of like, if you know about it, you show up, like what's the. Yes. For the volunteering, we have had a range of, you know, people we've had high school students, we've had local parents we've had, you know, retired OT and PT or.
a special ed teacher, things like that. We, for the adaptive program, that is when I'm really looking for backup with volunteers. And we send out flyers in our newsletter, reach out to some of the teachers and guidance counselors at the high school. Cause I know a lot of the students, you know, they also need hours to graduate. So it's a nice way to come down, help, help out, get the,
the participants to really have fun with not just like me or like these moms, like peers their age, you know, which is also really nice. But we also had, when we had the merge consulting, we also had a few of our volunteers who came and did the whole training with us, which was nice also.
I feel like there's a benefit to both participants, like, you know, the person who's participating and then also the volunteer like that, especially when we're talking about youth and other teens. I think that's a really, that could be, I think, a really beneficial experience for them as well. Yeah, yeah, absolutely, absolutely.
I'm wondering, once you are able to recruit volunteers, is there some sort of a training or like a space where folks are learning about what potential needs participants might have and how to create the best sort of experience possible?
Yeah, this past summer was the first time we had, you know, a professional training. Having more of those in the future is definitely something that I'm looking forward to, because it's a volunteer based thing it's mostly if they can't come to the training.
It's mostly me explaining things we've done in the past, things I've learned, you know, through Merge Consulting, things I've learned from my experience from working in a special needs school, you know, just trying to make sure that everyone is
understanding of what I'm expecting and comfortable with, with what I'm requesting them to do. Since we've started, I'd have to say with a lot of our volunteers, the consistency with our participants, like these guys are just looking forward to seeing these volunteers coming in, you know, and remember your name. If we're at Tufts pool, they see you. No, everybody's so excited. So it's.
I thought that crosses my mind, given the work that you're doing, what are your thoughts on sort of the built environment for something like the adaptive program? And you mentioned Tufts Pool. There are so many parks in Medford. Just wondering like what your sense of access and equity and how is the city sort of responding to like various needs as far as like mobility and etc.
Yeah, the adaptive programs, you know, have definitely helped contribute to equity by allowing participants to access programs, right? Like I said before, maybe they've never tried before or hoping to transition from non-adaptive to non-adaptive or youth athletics within our community. But also like how I've mentioned, you know, Tufts pool, we have, because we have that facility.
like allowing to teach swim lessons, not only adaptive, right, but non-adaptive swim lessons at a very affordable price has definitely, has definitely contributed to the equity. I mean, that's definitely one of our most affluent programs that we offer for $35 when, you know, it's usually up to $200. And when I started working here, when
My boss Kevin mentioned swim lessons and then said $35, my jaw dropped. I thought it was like the most amazing thing like I've ever heard. Allowing people to access just to get in the pool and, you know, learn basic skills and safety about the pool. It sounds like what you're saying is like, because some of these programs are
like, housed by in-city programs, it makes them more accessible to folks, like, because of cost, and just, like, being able to use city equipment and city facilities. I have heard, though, that some of the parks, maybe this is what Shelly was saying, like, could be better set up for people that maybe have, like, physical limitations or, like, use a wheelchair, like, couldn't get, can't get, like, in and out of the parks, like, somebody who doesn't have those needs might have.
Yeah, I think, you know, there are definitely, definitely some parks that are better than others, you know, getting Medford does have a lot of parks. So getting around and making them all accessible is definitely going to take a little while, but we, you know, we have been.
Getting there with other facilities, like, you know, we've recently added the handicap accessible doors and the pool, you know, having the elevator for our rec center has really helped out for some of these things, even, even not even, you know, just for wheelchairs for parents with children and strollers, you know, at Lakhani rink, we just, we got some,
Ice sleds, as well as skate walkers that are also able to be accessible. If anybody goes and asks for them, they can, you know, use them while they're at the ice rink, which is pretty cool. I got to test out in one of the sleds, which was really a fun experience. I mean, we've even used those.
walkers for our little skaters program. And I really think, you know, we are, we are taking strides to get, you know, as inclusive as we possibly, as we possibly can, you know, it's just, there's a lot in there, you know, there, there's a lot of parks, there's a lot of facilities. But I think, you know, I think we're doing, I think we're doing a great job. And we're, we're really working hard to get to get there. Yeah.
I so you've talked a little bit about what it's like for like sort of this connection between volunteers and participants. And like, I can hear that that's that sounds like a pretty like, lovely thing to be able to witness and be a part of. I wonder, is there like, so two questions? Is there like a most popular program within the adaptive programs? And is there one that maybe needs the most in terms of support and volunteers and like awareness? So most popular, or
My participants are most popular for my volunteers. I was thinking participants, but maybe the answer is participants. Okay. I just wanted to make sure I was clear on that. So it's probably a tough one, right? I have had a lot of the participants, parents, guardians, caregivers, really, really love the swim lesson.
right and that's a big one you know it's hard to find some lessons getting you know getting a one a one-to-one or somebody who's willing to go in the water with you you know every every class you know sometimes rain or shine can can be tough but
We had eight last summer and this summer I had 14 in my adaptive swim lesson program. So I'm saying that's the most popular for parents, caregivers, guardians, but I think my kickball program ended up being one of the most popular for the participants themselves. I started a kickball program last spring up at Carr Park.
And it ended up not only just the people who registered, but some local kids at the park noticed we were playing and ended up coming in and playing with us, who may have been in some of our participants' classes in school and didn't hear about it.
You know, I think that ended up being one of the most fun and parents wanted to get involved so we were able to like really, you know, teach the game itself of kickball but then also at the end kind of have like a fun.
parent, volunteers, staff, participants game, you know, and it really definitely, I think everybody had a great time. The only downfall to that class was we had to cancel for a couple of thunderstorms, you know, it was outside. But yeah, I think that was probably, probably one of the most, most popular, but we also run for hockey.
basketball and soccer. And they know soccer was a big one that everybody loved to do. Yeah, the imagery of that kickball class, though, it seems like, I think like, there can be this goal when you're thinking about like, adaptive sports and making things more accessible, of like, I think sometimes that can be mis- misused to sort of create this separate space for people who like, you know, aren't able to, to like participate in the more like,
typical ability sports, right? And like, I think that that can get, you know, it can seem like these two separate things, but that image of that kickball game, it sounds like it both created awareness for these other students that like, these are things that everybody can participate in and sort of worked up to this more like inclusive, like this is a game we can all play together and like create that space. I think that sounds beautiful. Yeah.
Yeah, absolutely. And that's really the goal, not only for, like you said, people who are participating in the adaptive program, but people who are participating in non-adaptive programs and just not thinking anything when everybody's playing together, just being one and having fun and enjoying themselves and learning something new.
you
While you're speaking, and I love this sort of notion of like one people, I too appreciate the Tufts pool and love that like swimming is like a program that feels like everyone's clamoring to get a spot. I voyeuristically saw on Facebook that the pool is getting some sort of maybe much needed renovation. Do you know if there was space for like Medford Rec and maybe other sort of stakeholders or community members to comment on what
whatever new look was coming. So we needed the deck redone. Yeah. So it's not necessarily like a re... Okay. So it's not as much of a revamp. Yeah. It's not really like the pool will be the same. We just will have a nicer, safer deck and fencing around the pool. We may have, you know,
Like a special feature that's coming, you know, into the waiting pool for the children. Sounds like that. You're all putting a lot of thought in it and into this, into this program and that there's like some careful planning going on there. Anything that like any like hopes that you have for like expansion of the program or like, if you think about like where it's going, anything that you are hoping for? Yeah. I mean, I would hope to not have to.
Like limit my I mean I limit my intake know obviously there's always going to be a capacity of people I can bring into my programs, but I usually start off with about eight or 10 participants.
In hopes that I can find volunteers and staff, but I could end up with eight or 10 or more on my waitlist and, you know, having to turn people away because I don't have, or we don't have the access to volunteers or staff.
can be a little disheartening. So, you know, I'm hoping, you know, as we progress and as, you know, people hear more about these programs that we can continue to increase enrollment for our adaptive programs. And so what's the best way both for participants to like to, you know, kind of navigate the system of like making this request? And what's also what's the best way for folks that might want to volunteer to become involved? So there's
There's two ways you can go about it. You can one, reach out to me personally at my Medford rec email, or if you go onto our website itself, you can register yourself as a volunteer. We have two links. We have like a special event volunteer link that you can register for that, or you can register for like adaptive program.
programming and then I can, each session, I can reach out via email to the people who have registered for these volunteer positions online and see if they're interested or available during that time. And participants, the same thing, the inclusion request form is also on our website. It's a PDF that can get filled out and emailed directly to me. When you register for our programs,
Before you can pay, you get asked a question that you need to fill out. Does the participant require any accommodations? And if so, please go and fill out the inclusion request form. Yeah, it's pretty straightforward. Anything else that you were hoping to be able to share about your work or the program before you wrap up?
I mean, honestly, all of the programs that we've run in Medford, I have just had a great experience. Seeing children in any of our programs go from, you know, sitting in the back corner, possibly not comfortable, to the third class, you know, running in, grabbing their soccer ball and showing, you know, showing their parents
what they can do or, you know, being at the hockey rink and seeing somebody who's never ice skated before, right? Get out on the ice during our open skate times or our, you know, our half day free skate for the kids. You know, it's really just,
Very nice to come to work and see a lot of happy people and people transitioning out of their comfort zone. It's, it's been, it's been a great experience so far. Sounds great. And it's really nice to know about all these programs. I don't think I did know so much about them before this. So thank you for, thank you for doing it. And thank you for sharing with us.
Well, our, our programs actually begin September 19. There's a few that are in fact sold out but we definitely still have a few more available from adult.
basketball to puddle stompers and inclusion sports, which is another great vendor that we bring in. So if anybody is still trying to register for programs, you've got till September 19th. Sounds good. Yeah.
Okay, thank you so much and I look forward to seeing some of this stuff in action. I would also like to thank all of my participants, volunteers, and staff that have also helped make our program so successful. Great, well thanks so much. Yeah, thank you.
Thanks so much for listening to today's episode. The Medford Bytes podcast is produced and moderated by Danielle Balacca and Shelly Kisherman. Music is made by Hendrik Irenys. We'd love to hear what you think about the podcast. You can reach out to us by email at medfordpod at gmail.com, or you can rate and review the podcast on Apple Podcasts. Thanks so much for listening.
Guys, what's the name of the podcast? Never Bites!