Meeting of the Benford School Committee will now come to order. Please rise to salute the flag. I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America, and to the republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all. Mr. Secretary, would you please call the roll? Mrs. Cuno. Present. Mr. Benedetto. Present. Mrs. Falco. Present. Mrs. Schiapelli. Present. Mrs. Gary. Present. Mrs. Vanderkloof. Present.
Mr. Chairman, you have six present, one absent. Do you have a quorum to conduct business? Thank you, Mr. Secretary. Approval of the minutes of April 2013. Move approval. Mr. Skerry moves approval. All those in favor? Aye. Opposed? Minutes are approved. Approval of bills and transfers. Move approval. Motion Mr. Skerry. All those in favor? Actually, roll call vote please. Mrs. Cuneo.
Yes. Mr. Benedetto? Yes. Mr. Falco? Yes. Mr. Scarpelli? Yes. Mr. Scarry, yes. Mrs. Vanderclue? Yes. Six in the affirmative, one absent. Bills are approved. Approval of payrolls. Bill of approval, Mr. Chairman. On the motion of Mr. Scarry, that the payrolls be approved. Mr. Secretary, would you please call the roll? Ms. Cuno? Yes. Mr. Benedetto? Yes. Mr. Falco? Yes. Mr. Scarpelli? Yes. Mr. Scarry, yes. Mrs. Vanderclue? Yes. Six in the affirmative, one absent. Payrolls are approved.
Report of Secretary. There's none, sir. Report of Committee of the Whole, April 30th, 2015. Those minutes are going to be addressed at a subsequent meeting. Community participation? None. Report of Superintendent. Mr. Superintendent. The report on high school accreditation.
Mr. Chairman and members of the committee, I believe Dr. Perrella is here, as well as Mr. Tucci, our assistant principal, and Candy Margulies here, member of the steering committee, co-chair of the steering committee. Let me begin by saying before we call them up, we're pleased to report that the New England Association of Schools and Colleges, NEASC,
acting on behalf of the Commission on Secondary Schools, has awarded Medford High School, Medford Vocational Technical High School, full reaccreditation for a 10-year period. This is the best possible rating under the NESC system. A round of applause for that. A lot of credit to a lot of people.
The high school accreditation process, as you know, is a major undertaking. Congratulations and credit for the preparation of our self-study and evidentiary submission, as well as the confidence on the on-site visit belongs to the leadership of both the high school and the vocational school, and Heidi's here also, the steering committee, faculty, staff, and students. There are many significant findings, but I'm gonna cite a few of them here before we call up our leadership.
The school board, that's you, superintendent and principal are collaborative, reflective, and constructive in achieving the school's 21st century learning expectations. In talking to the various people who come in, they don't always find that to be true, that people talk to each other. I'm surprised. The school is a safe and respectful environment that responds to the diversity of the school community.
The school has made significant capital improvements and technology investments. There is a strong collaboration between the principal of Medford High School and the director of the vocational school. Teachers who personalize instruction help meet the needs of a majority of students. The use of formative and summative assessments in the classroom for the purpose of informing instruction. The teacher's practice of giving timely feedback to students. The students who feel supported and cared for by their teachers.
All powerful statements. The personalized care and attention that is given to the various wellness needs of the school community, the topic that we addressed the other evening. The active and effective site council and parent-teacher organization, and the cultivation of many productive partnerships. These above commendations that I'm reading are only a sampling of the findings by the visiting committee and the commission. Naturally, there are recommendations for improvement as well.
However, when taken in context, the overall picture of our high school and vocational school is excellent. The report is in front of you. I'm going to give you time to read it and digest it, and then we will schedule a committee in the hall to go over any aspect of it in detail.
But I think, you know, we take a little time to reflect on it. That will give us a better opportunity to pick those areas that we want to concentrate on, especially as we go into budget. So, Mr. Chairman, without further ado, I'd like to bring up the leadership of the high school, Dr. John Corrella, Assistant Principal Nick Tucci, Director of the Vocational School, Heidi Riccio, and Steering Committee Co-Chair, Andy Margulies,
accept your congratulations and at the same time answer any questions you may have and to make whatever statements they want to make. Mrs. Vanderkloof. Well, first congratulations. Um, it was, and is always a lot of work, but we are so appreciative, um, for that work. And I think that as I read through this report, um, that the things that really struck me was when we got to that part about school culture. And that just made me feel so proud.
That what, you know, when we say, you know, we have the best students and that we appreciate all of them and we celebrate their diversity and that they feel cared for. Those were just golden nuggets to hear that somebody else walking in who's never been to our school before so quickly picked it up. Because that's certainly what we as school committee members and I for all these years, that's what we want. And we are so appreciative. And it's great that notice,
The collaboration now between the two schools have so much added to that. We want each of our students to be recognized for their individuality, celebrated for their diversity, felt that they are cared for and that there are people who care for them every day. And that's, as I was looking through this, and I know there's many recommendations and other things that we could talk about or whatever, but that's what came through so strongly and I really appreciate that.
Thank you. If I could say a few words. You know, the four of us are standing up here tonight receiving this. Congratulations. But really, this is a full package of celebration for everyone in the community. From the superintendent, to the school committee, to all the teachers, and to the students themselves. So we are very proud of the collaboration that we all have and of the successes that the students have brought to shine in this report.
So, again, we're very happy and proud to be up here, but obviously this is something that should be spread to everyone in the school community. But thank you very much. Thank you. Mrs. Cunha. Basically, everything that my colleague has said. I just want to congratulate everyone I do know.
Dr. Perrella, as you mentioned, there's a lot of people behind you, and it could only be as successful as the hard work that everybody put in. And I do know that there were a lot of people involved in this. And as a parent, we're always trying to push and bring the level of the bar always higher. But one thing as a parent I really feel good about is knowing that my children will go to a school.
and really have that atmosphere of, you know, they could go speak to someone and it's a great atmosphere to be in. And so I thank all of you for all your work and for everyone else who was involved. Thank you.
Mrs. D. Benedetto. Good evening. Thank you for coming. So I know that I hold you accountable when things don't go well, and I also want to hold you accountable for when things are going well. This is a very big achievement for our school system. I read through what the recommendations are, and there are a few building things which will get budgeted for and fixed now because they were in black and white from the department.
There's a couple collaboration things that we still need to work on throughout the thing, but we're doing wonderful work. You're doing wonderful work. This is years of work. This is a moment in time of how the school is on the day that they came, but it's a year in prepping and a year after. So you're at the midpoint now. Take a breath, enjoy your victory. You did a great job.
I'm proud of all of you, and I'm proud to be part of this community. Thank you for all the work.
Mr. Scarpelli. Again, I echo my colleagues. Pat's on the back so y'all deserve it. The one thing that we need is as you walk the streets and you talk to people and it's coming down to picking their high schools and parents are talking to us, geez, you know what? I wish the high school was, was newer. I wish it was, um, you know, I wish, I wish we had a different color for the front or something silly. When I tell them that, that it's not the,
the exterior, that's the heartbeat. And what you do every day just reinforces what we're trying to do by showing everybody that this is a great place to learn. And, um, again, I commend you and that's, that's, that's impressive. So thank you very much. You make us look great. So Mr. Scarecrow, I've read a few, a few of these reports during my brief tenure here in the board, but it's my goal is again, thank you for your help. And Nick, John, Heidi,
It was great to see that the teachers came forth. As in years past, trying to get any information on them was like pulling nails. But with the leadership that we have in place, I hope you will go back to your faculty and let them know that, hey, they did really a super job. It just reflects on what we have in Medford and our leadership team. And I, as one person and a taxpayer, thank you very much and just wish that we can keep up the good work and carry on.
So I'm wondering, this has not yet been announced to the students, correct? No, it has not. So I'm wondering, and maybe there's a few dollars that could go towards this, whether we could do something fun to celebrate it at the high school with all the teachers and administrators and the kids. I don't have anything off the top of my head, but it seems like this would be worthy to
I would request that the superintendent be find some perhaps there's a few extra dollars here or there that might go for having some sort of recognition at the high school that everybody can share in.
I was just going to say, I mean, the day, I know it already happened, but I don't know if there's another day that's coming up, but usually the kids will have like a spirit day or a fun day or something like that.
While all the students are in that atmosphere, maybe we could have something a little bit special for them. Just to throw it out there. But I also want to say, I just want to piggyback on what George mentioned. And I have to say that this year it's been really a lot of fun already. Going out and listening to parents.
that usually I'll have parents say to me, what are you going to do with that vocational school? You know all these students are going here, and we're going to lose them here, and why don't you try this program? And I can honestly tell you, I was out a lot this weekend. And it was really nice to hear parents say, you know, my son's going to the Volk, or my daughter's going to the Volk, and they're freshmen this year. And I had no idea how wonderful it is and how things are moving, because you have all these rumors out there of,
You know, we're trying to destroy the vocational, or we're trying to get rid of the vocational, and they're finally, everyone is finally understanding. We're not trying to get rid of anything, but really to make it better, and to give the students the best opportunity possible. So, when I throw in now that, you know, our vocational students are taking languages, rather than taking night courses at night, because a lot of them go off to colleges, people are like,
standing back now saying, really? I didn't know that. So again, this is all the hard work that, as my colleague Erin had said, it's years of building, but it's finally coming together, and I couldn't be prouder, so thank you.
Mr. Falco. I was also just wanted to mention that we're supposed to have a meeting of the public relations subcommittee. And I think that because this is a piece of it, this is a piece of that. We want to make sure that the whole community understands some of the things that have been said in here. I think we have a tentative date of May 14th. Is that true? May 14th? No.
Oh, so what's, you know, we've got a lot going on, but I've got some suggested dates as we move into the evening tonight. Okay. Go over a whole list of dates and you can pick. I want to make sure we get better. Yeah. Yeah. We'll get better. We have a couple of dates a month in May that are open that hopefully everyone can.
I could add a few things to it. I love the idea of celebrating with the students. Primarily because the students are really what make this report. And when you get a chance to really dig deep into it, what you'll find is that the students really make us what we are. It's kind of a cliche in many ways.
Again, when you get deep into that report, you'll find that they were raving about how the students perceived what we did, how they reacted to the teachers, and how they interacted with each other. So the cultural pieces to that, that's because we have some of the greatest students, probably, I think we have the greatest students in the state. And I also agree that we have the greatest teachers in the state. And I think this school committee really embraced us and made this all possible. So again, it's a full collaboration.
Thank you. In fact, as a reward for all of you, you're invited to the junior prom. All you have to do is get a date. I'll let you get it at 12 to six. If I may add really quick, congratulations to all of you and to the whole team that was involved. Great job, fabulous. There are a lot of great things happening in the Memphis Public Schools, and this is one of them. So great job, fabulous. I agree with what all my colleagues said, so just fabulous job.
Heidi's getting tired of all this. Okay, on the motion of Mrs. DiBenedetto that the report be accepted and placed on file. All those in favor? All those opposed? The report is accepted and placed on file.
Next item is the recommendation to accept gift to Medford High School from Silvio Sella Foundation. Mr. Superintendent. Mr. Chairman, our football coach is here, Jason Nascimento. Up here, Jason, come on up and let everybody see you. Promising an undefeated season next year, by the way. This is the chairperson of the football associates, okay? So the other day,
received a check from the Sylvia Occella Foundation in the amount of $3,000 to enhance our football program. Sylvia Occella was an outstanding educator and athletic director and coach at Revere for many, many years. And his family has put together this foundation in his honor and memory. And Medford was the recipient this year. He was a 49-year veteran.
as a football coach, athletic director of Revere High School. And so I'm going to let Jason and Chris talk a little bit about what they're going to do with the money, and then we can take a vote to receive it, and we'll send a thank you note to the Chavo Foundation.
Yeah, first off, I'd like to thank everyone for having us here. This is an amazing opportunity for us. I originally didn't even know this specific opportunity existed. And when an email came across my desk and Mr. Maloney's desk, I was thrilled. We went down to Gillette to accept the award.
And it's fantastic for this opportunity to give back to the kids that work so hard. Even now, in the off season weight training and attending camps and clinics and stuff, they really do a fantastic job. And even in times when the season doesn't go the way that you'd love it to go, and it pains me and the other coaches to see it that way. But just to have this in the budget now, and it's gonna go towards, we talked about,
getting some new uniforms, attend some more clinics and camps for the kids to go to that can get super expensive, and some equipment that we'll need during the season as well, which is super exciting. And Silvio Cello Family Foundation does a great job year in and year out with this grant. They give it out to four different teams who are in need and who can apply to it. And it's just a great way to continue on his legacy to give back to young people, which is what we're all here for. So thank you, Chris.
I just want to piggyback on what he said. I've been part of the booster board for about six years now. I just took over as the president this year. I know most of you have kids and you fundraise for your kids' sports teams and activities. You know how hard it is to get donations and to get a grant of this size. It really is going to really help us.
We've had uniforms we've had, we've had them for six years now. The booster clubs bought those. The average life of a uniform is like four to five years. So it's going to be good to make a dent in that. It's also, you know, get some things to help, you know,
take our program to the next level. So we're really excited as a board to receive this. It was great news when I got the email from Bobby saying that we received this great honor. So thank you. And I hope you guys will approve it. Oh, we'll approve it. We'll approve it. This is Cuno. The way she dealt in the room, though. Chairman, will you accept the donation? OK. This is Cuno.
I just want to say thank you, and also if we could send a letter. Okay, a letter of thanking. And there was one more thing I was going to say. To Mr. Nascimento, not only do I want to say thank you to you for being the high school football coach, and the team has done a great job, and I don't think I'll forget the last Thanksgiving game ever, but I also want to commend you on
the academic side of what you're doing. You've done a terrific job and I hear the students all the time speaking about coming down. So I just wanted to say thank you to you on that. Thank you.
I just also want to say, great job, and it's wonderful to hear part of the previous report when our students also are being recognized for being good athletes. And we're going to do our part, too, because we're going to make sure that your line item is not cut in any way, shape, or form because of this excellent donation. So we'll make sure that it is a plus, as it's meant to be.
Thank you. Mrs. DiBenedetta. So did you apply for this grant? Yeah, Mr. Maloney applied for it. And I wasn't aware of it. And all of a sudden, it came across. So it was a surprise to you that he had done that? It was a surprise. It was amazing, yeah. And today, with how tight our budget has been, and the program has really run well,
And we all appreciate that. But these type of situations, when teachers and administrators go out and go above and beyond to bring money back into the community and to our students, I just want to say thank you to you and to Ms. Maloney for taking these opportunities and to be proactive.
and on our students' behalf. So I hope you tell Mr. Maloney, and I'm telling you directly, that I love to see this in the teachers and the care and the effort that you put forth for our students. It's appreciated. Thank you. Thank you. Mr. Murphy, you're next. While I have you all here, I just want to invite you all. June 18, we're going to have our big fundraiser we do every year. It's 12th year we've done it, the Push-Up-A-Thon.
It's going to be at 3 o'clock at the high school. You guys are all more than welcome to come down, time some push-ups that the kids do. It's one of our biggest fundraisers, and the kids have a lot of fun. I can do two. Are we doing push-ups? You guys, if you want to. I know George can do like five push-ups. I can do two. No, no, no. Two. So what time is this? On the 18th? It's at 3 o'clock, June 18th, at the gymnasium. OK. Thank you.
Coach Nassimather, good luck in the upcoming season. Thank you for being here tonight. Chris Murphy, congratulations on being named president of the Football Associates. Thank you to Athletic Director Ms. Maloney for obtaining the grant. Any other questions? Okay, on the motion, Mr. Skerry to approve. Mr. Skerry, could you please call the roll?
On the motion to accept the $3,000 grant. Ms. Cuno, Mr. Benedetto, Mr. Falco, Mr. Scarpelli, Ms. Vanderbilt. Yes. Six in favor, one absent. The grant is accepted. Thank you.
Just like Belichick, we won our version of the Super Bowl against Malden last year. We're ready. Next item is the recommendation to approve extended year, day, and evening programs at Medford Vocational Technical High School. Mr. Superintendent. Chairman and members of the committee, our director of vocational school, Heidi Riggio, is here. And she's going to begin by telling you a little bit about this program to extend the day and also to recognize one of our outstanding students who
really came up with something special along with his teacher. So I'm going to turn it over to our director, Heidi Richie. Thank you, Superintendent Belson and school committee. I appreciate you having me come here.
I would like I don't know if that was true or not, but it is so true. So true, I promise. It's all good stuff. So in your packets today, you have a couple points of interest. The first point of interest is
extending or reconnecting with our evening school program at the vocational school. As you know, in the past, we have had a very successful evening program, and I'm not sure when it ended, but it did end at some point, and we believe that our students deserve continuing education at a value price. So instead of going to a proprietary school, there should be no reason why our students are not continuing
their education at Medford Vocational School in the evening. In addition to that, that serves the community at large as well, because there are plenty of tradesmen out there within the Medford community that would benefit from continuing education units, which is required in order for them to maintain their license. So there are a variety of classes that we're starting with for next year. We are keeping it limited.
so that we can grow the program. As you know, whenever you start programs, you need to slow and steady and make sure you get all of the bugs out. We have had a successful electrical program using Gould Institute last year, but they removed the contract and is using another vocational school.
down north, and so we would like to have our own electrical school at Medford Vocational School, as well as cosmetology, which would be a full 1,000-hour cosmetology licensure course, as well as a 100-hour nail technician course.
There are also a variety of other classes that we are investigating, including welding and metal fabrication. As we know, sheet metal is a requirement for all industries within the construction industry that they are certified in sheet metal and have so many hours towards that license. So we'd like to continue that as well. So that's for the evening school. And I don't know if you have any questions related to evening school. Yes.
Well done. Ms. Riccio, I think this is something that I've been talking about when a friend of mine who was working at Lawrence Vocational Tech and now who's at neighboring community talked about how schools would open up their vocational school and offer programs like this to our eighth grade students to see and get interested in vocational education.
And also, just for the novice to explore some of programming, getting more involved. The nominal cost is something that will cover the teacher's pay, the equipment that's needed, and any upkeep for the building, correct?
Correct. Typically when you re-engage in an evening school program, there may be a small incremental loss in the first three years, but it's really an investment that you're making for a long-term commitment for evening school. So there may be an incremental loss, which obviously would be recorded, but the intention is for it to be self-sustaining.
Well, if you look at the top notch vocational schools in the region, I think they are, not only do they have a great high school program, but then an evening school too. So I applaud you and congratulate you again on moving us forward. So thank you. Mrs. Cuno. Just basically, thank you. Thank you.
And thank you. This has been something that we've been pushing for for a very long time. I am totally excited about this. It's been a long time coming. And the way it's presented, the way it's set up, I can't really express how happy I am about this. I will ask, I know that this is for after school, more at night.
Just again, I know we've had the discussion of maybe something in the summer for maybe students that might be interested, or even something during the school year, like after school, if that's possible. Totally understandable that this was never, I know that when we brought it up in the past, it was never to make money.
It was really to get a foundation started up to bring more eyes and ears to the vocational side of our school, to give all students the opportunity to see what we were offering. And I really commend you all and all the teachers that were involved in this because this is a long time coming and I can't be more happier than this. Thank you so much.
This is D Benedetto. Just to clarify, this is just the evening classes for children that have graduated from Most Method Vocational High School and other graduated high school people that want to continue their
their licensure or complete a program. Am I correct? Correct. So it's for recent vocational high school students in Medford and beyond, but also for the existing workforce who have to continue their education or often what we will hear from students that maybe they graduated two years ago and to go to a proprietary school, they don't actually get financial aid. They get loans, but they don't get financial aid because a degree isn't offered.
So because of that, it becomes very expensive for them to be able to support and to be able to pay for this coursework. So typically, when a vocational school offers that evening program, it is anywhere from 50 to 75% of the cost compared to a proprietary school. So this is actually twofold. So we have that evening school program for the continuing ed.
which we are hoping to get off the ground so that in January we're able to offer those enrichment type courses for whether they're existing high school students or even just the community at large. Kind of like the fun classes, you know, maybe a knitting class and, but it's really getting this, the focus is to get the training that these students need at a reasonable cost. The second part of this program is a summer exploration program for incoming eighth grade students.
And you have been given the registration form for that. And we've selected 30 students at each of the two middle schools in Medford. And we've already received multiple phone calls. They wanted to take credit cards, so I said, not yet. But any help on that would be greatly appreciated. Because I know everybody uses credit cards now. But we are offering five to six different programs.
for incoming eighth graders to explore the vocational school, knowing that we are collaborating with the high school and their academic coursework would actually be already integrated with the high school, but yet they can opt and select. And we're using this as a promotional means for our programs. If I may add really quick, um, I know that, uh, Pat is working on the piece.
Hopefully that will be coming soon. So it is in the works. Yes. And we've been working on it, so that should be coming soon. Thank you. Mrs. Van de Kloot, you had a question? Yes. Heidi, could you explain that a little bit more? You said we selected 30 students from each school, which is to say they were sent this information specifically?
I actually did not select only because I do not obviously know these students, and we didn't necessarily hand select the students. What we did was to keep it equitable between the two middle schools is that there are 30 slots from each of the two middle schools. So was it sent out to the entire student body?
I would, I know that it was posted, I know Paul DeLeva had posted it on his Facebook page and Twitter account, so I know that it was posted publicly. And then the interest would actually go to the guidance counselor directly at that middle school. Parents would need to sign off on it because there is a cost to this. In addition to that, they cannot have, I mean there's a disciplinary and attendance piece to it.
because we would want to make sure that that child is obviously safe working with equipment. OK. Thank you for explaining that a little bit more. Sure. So 60 is the maximum number of students you expect to be able to take? For this year, yes. For this year. And these courses, and I'm speaking specifically about one-grade graders, they will be taught by our current staff.
We would post it, much like we would post any other positions, and the hope is that our existing staff would apply. If not, we would obviously reach out to the existing staff within Medford Public Schools. OK. And that was my same question with the evening offerings. Would you anticipate that that would be our staff, or are you thinking that it would be a staff that we hire specifically to run the evening program?
It's a combination of both because when you are a Chapter 74 teacher's license is not equivalent to an adult education license.
So they would need to be dual certified in that particular piece. So if they are, we would certainly want to employ our existing workforce because we know them and they know the community, but we would have to post making sure that they meet the requirements. Now, it seems when I've been up at the vocational school in the evening, I see many cars.
And so, I'm somewhat surprised that Gould has pulled out. Was that because of a lack of students or, well, can you give us any better understanding of that? They were using another vocational school for three other programs, so it made sense for them from a business perspective.
to have one contract under one house. So there wasn't necessarily any reason other than them streamlining into one location. And it's at a greater distance so that us offering it here will have enough potential. Correct. We definitely have enough existing workforce within this community in order to sustain, we believe, the program. That's great. Thank you. Mrs. DiBenedetta.
A lot of my questions were about staffing, who's going to staff the evening program.
And my other question is, how do you figure out the cost? And I just want to make sure that the maintenance of our equipment for our students is upgraded a little bit because of those costs and because of the usage. I just want to see some of that money go back if there is any profit. I know there might not be profit in the beginning, but when there is profit, that we reinvest those dollars into the vocational school to keep
things up to date and if they're being used more, we need to make sure that they're maintained more. That's a concern I have.
Thank you, that's a legitimate concern, actually. Most other vocational schools that have a Gould will actually enforce that they have an employee of that program on site at all times because of that very thing. If there is a maintenance issue or a maintenance concern. At my former district, that was the case. Where we are operating it under our own and not having an outside vendor come in to teach it, we do definitely have more control.
over who's teaching it, as well as the maintenance of the equipment. And obviously, we would want any funds to be rolled back into the program to support the day students. I mean, that's the intention, is that our students during the day certainly come first, because that's our main purpose. But for the equipment to sit idle isn't good either. I mean, a lot of this equipment, they want it to be operable more frequently than it currently is.
So through you to the superintendent, when we figure out this funding piece in the income from these programs, can we please set aside a good maintenance, a good amount of this money to go back into our vocational school, not only the maintenance of the programs that it is existing, but the advancement of other programs through this. The vocational school has revolving accounts.
It's already been set up. The goal will be to take any tuition in and put it back into those accounts, and when there are surpluses in there, to reinvest it. In addition to our own budgetary allocations that we may make, or capital improvements that we may make, that may be beyond the ability of this particular type of fundraising. Thank you. Mrs. Cunha, did you have a question? No, I'm all set, thank you.
Mr. Riccio, thank you very much. This is a great initiative. I know it's something we've been looking at for a while. So it's good to see that it's here. So thank you very much. On the motion of Mrs. Scarapelli to approve extended year day and evening programs at Meffitt Vocational Technical High School. All those in favor? Aye. Motion passes. Next item is the report on robotics project at Meffitt Vocational Technical High School. Mrs. Riccio.
Thank you. I would also like to call up Rich Cormio, our electrical instructor, and Hunter Raymond, a senior in the electrical program. I'm just actually going to read the script, because it's pretty important that I'm going to let them talk, because they know more about it than I am, because they've lived it. So Hunter Raymond was recently included in the April edition of Tech Directions magazine, which I believe you all received a copy of.
This is a national publication. Hunter is a senior in the electrical program at Medford Vocational Technical High School, who began taking an elective coding class with volunteer software engineers in the fall. As a result, he began to seek better ways to communicate to Rich Cormier, an instructor in the electrical program who was on medical leave from a rare form of cancer.
Hunter, working with the software engineers and our new engineering instructor, Mr. Sam Christie, learned how to code and develop a software application that can control an Android tablet remotely from MVTHS to Rich Cormier's computer at his house.
He then built a device with the assistance of the metal fabrication program that moves and is able to navigate through rows of desks so that Mr. Cormio could teach his electrical students from home. Since then, Hunter has competed at SkillsUSA state competition, was on boston.com, and will be visiting iRobot in May. Hunter will also be seen in the near future on Channel 7 News.
Because of the partnership with the TEALS organization, a Microsoft company whose purpose is to teach computer science to students in the new engineering program, Hunter is interested in majoring in robotics next year. His knowledge of electricity will assist him greatly in his future educational purposes.
And then I have attached the article so far that he has. He was also contacted by the Donahue Institute, which is a research institute that organizes the STEM Summit. It's an annual national conference of STEM professionals. And they were so impressed with the work of Rich Cormier and Hunter Raymond that they asked if they could be
the keynote speaker, and so they will be speaking in November, their story, sharing their story in front of 1,300 people this coming November. So I'm going to let them speak. Hunter.
I would just like to thank you guys all for letting me speak here tonight, and also, we've all had a great afternoon so far. So, at the beginning of the year, I learned about the new program that they just added to the vocational school, Robotics Engineering, and I've always had a thing for technology.
But before this year, the only thing I've really done with building technology was I worked on my own computer, and I built it. And when I did that, I knew that this is kind of what I wanted to do in life. And so seeing the new shop come into the vocational school, I knew that I had to work with the teachers somehow and feed my love and passion. So with Mr. Cormier being out for the past year and a half,
and his love for teaching, I knew that he wanted to be back in the classroom. So the idea was brought up to me about basically holding a webcam and controlling it somehow. We didn't really know how yet, but at the time, just controlling it so he could look left and right and see the classroom from his home, so he could teach us and still feel like he was a part of the classroom.
So, at the time, I really did not think that much of it. I loved the idea, I was very intrigued by it, but I didn't really know if I could do it, to be honest.
So I went down to the robotics shop, I asked the teacher for help, and he assured me that this project could be done. So over the next eight weeks, I tested it and built this RichBot 3000. It took a lot of trial and error.
And if I needed any other help from any of the shops in the vocational school, for instance, this robot, as you can see in the picture on the front of the magazine, the right picture, that pole that raised it up to eye-level height wasn't there at the beginning. So he was driving around looking at people's shins, and it really wasn't very productive. So I went over to the HVAC shop and asked them,
It's like a weld me some sort of pole or at the time. I really didn't know what we could use to raise it up but a few days passed they came back to me with this this pole and
It just goes to show that I can go to any other shops that I need help from, and within the next day or two, they'll have exactly what I need. And it was so helpful trying to build this thing. So I definitely could not have done this without the robotics and engineering shop. It was the first year here, and that was the first major thing that we did in that shop.
I couldn't have done it without the robotics shop, without the help of the teacher Sam Christie.
Definitely my parents, they kept pushing me. Every day, they would tell me to just, you know. I would come home, I was so excited to tell them what I added on to the robot. And every day, they would just keep telling me to keep trying. So like I said before, it just goes to show what can be accomplished in the vocational school. And I think Rich has some words to say.
Good evening and thanks for having us here tonight. I would first like to start by thanking the school department for keeping my job for me while I was out. I originally thought that I'd be back in September and then I had a little setback and I was able to come back the first of January. It's been an incredible experience.
When I first went out, I spoke to Mr. Nelson, and I said, I'd like to try something different. Let's try teaching from home. And his words to me were, just go home and get better. And I appreciate that very much, because that first part of the year before June last year, I couldn't have done what I did afterwards. In September, I did have a setback back in August, which kept me out of school again.
So I spoke to Adam Burns, the other electrical teacher, and I asked him if it would be OK with him if I taught via Skype. And we cleared it with Ms. Riggio, and we did that. We did that for a little while. But it was difficult, like they said. If somebody asked a question, I'd say, Adam, can you turn the iPad, and we'd look around and see where everybody was.
And then one night I got a call from Hunter saying that, you know, we're going to try this new thing out. And it was. It was down low and I'm driving it around. There was nobody around. It was wonderful. And by the time we got it perfected, I really screwed up. I came back to school. So we only really used it a couple of times. But it was great to use it. It was a phenomenal thing for Hunter to even think about doing.
And I have to thank him because it really helped my recovery. As soon as I started teaching from home, my wife mentioned how my attitude and everything had changed. Because I was getting a little dry at home. It's not that easy to do. Some people say, oh hey, you had a year and a half off. That's great. You don't really want it, and that's not the way you want to do it.
So I do want to thank you all for your support throughout my illness. And I feel like I'm back 100%. I teach every day. And I thank God every day that I'm back doing what I love to do. And thank you. Thank you very much. Thank you. Mrs. Van. So first, Mr. Cormier, I have to say it's delightful to see you here again. Thank you. And we're very happy that you're back. In fact, now, if you take a day off,
or two, there's no safe place, there's no hiding. And this gives us sort of a new perspective to, you know, they say, so teachers somehow know it's like they have eyes behind their head. And now you've got them all over. So a great project. Hunter, thank you for taking the initiative. And because I actually think, you know, I mean, if you think about it, we've talked about, you know, students being home and I've read some articles, but this is now
when a teacher has to be out, what a great potential here. So thank you so much and it's great to see you.
Thank God that you're with us and I appreciate everything that you're fighting to be back in the classroom, so thank you. But Hunter, you are an unbelievable role model. I want to make sure that your presence here today, it just again, again with the vocational school when you talk about greatness in Medford.
So I want to commend you, because this is something that should be screamed from the rooftops. To have that incentive and have that dream and drive not to stop in what you believe in. This is a story that I'm going to go home and talk to my 12 year old son about, because that's very impressive. So I congratulate you, nice job. Thank you so much. Mrs. Cunha. I echo what everyone else has said tonight. First of all, Mr. Cormier.
Thank God that you are here. I know when you had told us a year and a half ago, it was devastating, you know, and the way it was. But you're here, and sometimes, you know, who knows? I mean, this was such a wonderful thing that Hunter has done. Hunter, like Mr. Scarpelli, you know, and everybody else, he is a clean cut, articulate,
Nice kid in front of us. He's a vocational high school student. I can't be any prouder. And your parents must be beaming, because you have no idea how you have changed the stereotypical vocational student tonight. And you've made us extremely proud. And as I said, and I know we've talked about it so many times, there are so many wonderful stories.
And yours tonight is just the topper. And these are the stories that need to go out. These are the stories that our community and everyone else around us have to hear. Because I am so tired of hearing about the bad kid or the bad person or something horrible happening. And we have so many jewels in this city that put us to shame. And you guys are the ones that are really the ones that are shining. So we really need to make these kids shine. And we really need to promote that.
Mrs. DiBenedetto. Hi. I'm glad to see you here. Thank you. And I also want to take this moment to commend our administration and our superintendent. Because not only have I seen him support you and the need that you had, I've seen him do it repeatedly throughout a district to many of our teachers. And a lot of people don't realize how much of a big heart that administrative team have for all employees within our district.
And I see it not only in the superintendent, but his whole administrative team, repeatedly. And the community needs to know that. Secondly, I wanted to talk more about this. I was speaking to my sister about this before I came tonight, as I was reviewing the paperwork. And the bond that MedFit teachers have with their students, and the students, and the commitment that the students have to our teachers as well.
Now your teacher was gone for a year and a half, so you must have had a strong bond with him for you to not give up when things got tough.
and keep trying until you got it right. Yeah, he was the first electrical teacher that I had at the vocational school. And I had him for, I'd say around a year and a half before he had to leave. So throughout that year and a half, obviously, we've built a very strong relationship. And seeing him not be able to teach and knowing how much he's taught me,
I love having him teaching me, so it just kept driving me to get him back in the classroom. So this is a dream of every teacher? To motivate children to
to figure out problems, to be self-driven, to figure things out, to work really hard, and to inspire them in a love for learning. And you have that, and you represented that, and you gave it back to him. So that, to me, is commendable throughout this. And I just want to comment, and I'd like mom and dad to stand up.
is talking about the struggles and how he came home and spoke to you. Dad's over there shaking his head, like how he didn't give up and how you guys encouraged him. So it takes a community to raise our children. And I'm seeing that tonight. We have parents, we have teachers, and we have students that really care. And I'm really feeling very happy to be here. And I'm looking forward to see what you do in your future. Yeah, me too. Thank you very much.
I'm amazed at his presence. Mr. Skerry. Mr. Cormier, I'm glad to have you back, and thank you for your tutelage. Hunter, you took the bull by the horns, and you've done possibly what no other student has done at Medford by
doing your thing with the robotics, getting that program off the ground. So you're not only a student, but you're an innovator. My next question to both of you is, I hope you've seen a patent attorney. Thank you for your hard work, and Hunter, keep up the good work.
We're kind of afraid that that's what our robot wants. I just want to say that Hunter definitely embraces the vocational spirit. We have a saying around the school that we don't really see problems, we see solutions. And that's exactly what we do, what we try to teach them day in and day out. It's nice to know somebody was listening.
Mr. Cormier, great to see you tonight after a fabulous job. I remember actually you showing me this during the vocational school open house in the fall, and I was amazed then. This is just a fabulous story. This is another great story that's happening in the Memphis Public Schools, and it continues to happen more and more. We love to see it. I know myself, I'm so proud of you.
It's great to see the initiative. It's great to see that you wanted to do this. It's great to have the support from your parents. Great job. This is just a great story. Thank you so much.
I'm just collecting my papers, but I think that this is a really great story to kick off our week-long festivities of Teacher Appreciation Week. So I just want you to know that it is a wonderful story, because it's really about what the teachers do every day that's part of their daily world that changes these kids' lives. So we appreciate all of the teachers. Thank you.
I just wanted to spell one false rumor that seems to be making its way around the city. Hunter is not working on a robot that will be running the school district. On the motion of Mrs. Van de Kloet to accept the report and place on file. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Report is accepted and placed on file. Thank you.
Next item, recommendation to approve school lunch price increase for school year 2015-2016. Mr. Superintendent. Chairman and members of the committee, I'm going to call upon our Director of Finance and Administration, Pat Feely, to come up and deliver this report and tell you a little bit about why this is necessary at this time. Good evening, school committee. Jewel Bradley was going to be here with me, but she is not feeling well.
The Medford Public Schools Breakfast and Lunch Program serves a large portion of the school population and is currently at a financial break-even point. We're serving in the 40s, probably mid-point 40s on an average daily basis. However, the food service program must ask at this time that a price increase be approved for both the breakfast and lunch services due to federal regulations and inherent cost increases.
The requested price increases are federally and financially necessary. At the federal level, the price increase assists the district in meeting a regulation requiring school food authorities participating in the National School Lunch Program to ensure sufficient funds are provided to the non-profit school food service account for meals served to students who are not eligible for free or reduced price meals.
The whole logic behind that is that free and reduced cannot support the lunch program. They want to make sure that it's an equal amount of money coming from all avenues.
Currently, the FBS lunch prices average $2.65 per lunch, which is a combined calculation of current pricing weighted by free, reduced, and paid meals. To meet the USDA regulation, meals should have been $2.70 for the current FY15 fiscal year. So we are a nickel behind as of this time.
Financially, the food service program is breaking even with the current revenue stream and the current expenses. Food costs have been increasing and reducing any reserves for maintenance and replacement of aging equipment. Additional increased costs can be expected due to undetermined collective bargaining.
The current price of breakfast is $1. The food service program is asking for an increase of $0.50, resulting in a breakfast price of $1.50. The request for the lunch increase is $0.25 per lunch. The current price of lunch is $2.50 at the elementary and $2.85 at the middle school and high school, resulting in $2.75 for elementary level and $3.10 at the middle school and high school, making our average weighted meal $2.90 a meal.
The requested price increase should align the food service program with the USDA regulations for the next three years, barring any extreme food or labor cost increases. The last food service price increase occurred about a decade ago, according to what records that we could locate. The school committee is asked to approve the price increase at this time in order to provide ample notification for our families who will be using this essential program next year.
So, Pat, what I'm understanding is that this is basically the federal government is moving this and saying we need to change our price. I have to tell you, when I got to this paper, I was shocked at $1 to $1.50.
And so they don't, they don't, you know, they don't, you know, they don't, you know,
They don't qualify. And that just seemed like a lot. So I was surprised at that. When I got to the second part, I thought, 310, what an odd number. Couldn't we just do $3? Do we really need to do that dime? I have to tell you, it is a long time, because I was thinking about it. It has been a long time. But it sure did.
I laughed at where it was, because we had all this good news. And sometimes, you know, the superintendent mentioned something to us that's coming up or whatever. He didn't mention this thing at all. And so all of a sudden, we got to this paper, and she was like, whoa, shocker here, trying to slide it in, thinking we wouldn't notice. Well, we noticed. I have to let you know that we did do a survey of all the surrounding communities in preparation for this. Yeah, because you knew we'd ask. Well, we knew you would ask. We knew you cared. And we knew that it would be, you know,
It's something to think about, quite hardly. And so we did a survey, and we surveyed all the local communities. And we tried to survey hitting the demographically similar districts to ours. And breakfast in most communities is $2. Point of information, Mr. Chairman. Point of information, Mr. Chairman. Ms. Selle, would you make a copy of the
communities that were researched and get that to us, please. I think that'll make the decision a lot easier. Compare and contrast. What was lunch? Lunch can be anywhere up to $4, depending on where you are. So we are actually still one of the lowest ones. And it is kind of an odd dollar amount, as you said, but the goal was not to reach a round number. The goal was to do only what was necessary to get us through the next three years so that we didn't have to come back the next three years.
Mr. Scarpone. Can I? Oh, I'm sorry, Mrs. Vandenbroucke. Is this going to improve lunch options at all? I can't say that for sure. You know, I walk through the building every morning, and I go through when the kids are eating breakfast, and they seem very happy with what's being offered. I do know that Juul does an excellent job of using our commodity options, and that has helped keep our food costs down.
I don't know, you walk around the building and I don't hear a lot of complaining. I see kids eating lunch, so I'm not sure. Okay. Mr. Scott. If I can, I, I don't, I don't, I'd like to table this, move this along because I think there's some information.
We haven't seen the actual breakdown with the food services. You know, a breakdown has been for the last couple of years. I think we as a school community, before we raise it a nickel, have to look at that, those options. I think that maybe looking at other increases. I know that at some of the schools, the PTG run their, you know, their little, the little snack bar that kids,
come in and invest a lot of money that can afford to go in and buy the extra cookies and buy the extra ice cream and do all that and so forth and so on. If we're at a point where we're looking to raise, because I didn't take this as this is the federal government. The federal government numbers are one way. This isn't pushed by the federal government. This is us. This is our initiative. We're a nickel behind right now.
Right. But this isn't coming from the federal government telling us we need to push anything. Yes. Okay. So what I'd like to do is maybe look at some other, you know, look at our numbers first before we do anything and then look at what we're doing in that other piece where I know the high school has the different, um, different areas to purchase different types of foods that maybe we can capture funding that way instead of, um,
instead of doing this, because again, the free and reduced lunch, those kids are going to eat. We know that. It's the kids that are right in the middle. And again, that might be the difference. Fifty cents a day might be the difference of not having a meal one of those days and whatnot.
I'd like to look at it, and I make a motion that we table this until we get some more information. Okay, on the motion to table by Mr. Skarapelli, seconded by Mr. Skerry. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? This agenda item is tabled. I just have one other point of information. Point of information, Mr. Skerry? Ms. Folley, could you have the lunch director put together a
An explanation of the USDA's program where to see what we're entitled to receive commodities and to what extent we really use what is offered. Maybe we can increase our participation to sort of stabilize the lunch prices. My information is to-. One of the information is to Scott Kelly.
If we have Jules presenting part of the budget, we wrap that with that, I think that would be very helpful. We can set up being redundant of what we're doing with them. Okay, and if we could have the cost from the surrounding district before we vote on this, that'd be great. There's a few more, I believe Mrs. Cunha had a question, and Mrs. DiBenedetto, Mrs. Cunha.
I just wanted to ask, I know that there are also students that will come and they've got their money or they don't have their money. By law, we still need to feed these children. And I know that in the past, cafeteria workers have taken their name down and they kind of keep a tally.
of how much they owe. Some children come back to school with the money, some children don't come back to school with the money. I'd like to find out if possible, like, if they're children that really should be on the free and reduced, but maybe because we haven't caught, you know, we haven't received an application, or we're not sure. And we have those students that are repeating themselves daily, but belong on the free and reduced lunch plan.
maybe that's also a different way of seeing some money come back in because if they're not applying and they really are supposed to be on that, we're losing some money there. And because I remember like when I was in the cafeterias and stuff in the past, as I said, you know, students would forget or they wouldn't have the money on them and some would come back and some wouldn't, but I always used to wonder like, how much money are we not getting back? So, and is it, you know, is it from a student who can't afford it or is it from a student who
the application number went through. So if there's some way of trying to figure that out too. Right, and I think that Jill Bradley would have the answers for that. Okay, thank you. Mrs. DiBenedetto. I too was going to ask for a budget for the last few years to go over what we've done, how much money's come in, because I know we've put a new program in how parents pay in the last few years. And I wanted to know, I know now that you can track things a little.
easier electronically, and we can see where the money's gone in and where the money's gone out, and if there are any surplus funds, and what equipment needs to be updated as well. If we knew that, you know, as well, and what other big expenditures for this program we need to pay for in the near future, that would also be helpful. So any information and all information would be helpful. Thank you so much.
And I'm not saying, the price of food has gone up, and I understand that we may need to do this at some point, but we just want to make sure we do our due diligence as a committee. Thank you. Mr. Scarry. Also, just to follow up with Mr. Benedetto said, would it be possible to get a report on what machinery or things that have been misplaced or unaccounted for?
I know years past we were always short of meat slicer, or pots and pans, or what have you. We could get a report what's not been accounted for in the last couple of years.
Mr. Falco, I think they're pretty strict about that now. You know, one day I had to take home a bowl, and I think that was like on Saturday. And by Monday I had a call saying, Paulette, remember to bring the bowl back. Which I did, of course. But I think they've got it down. Thank you for your report. So we've tabled this report here. We'll take it up during our budget sessions.
Okay, next item is a recommendation to reject the school choice program for school year 2015-2016. Mr. Superintendent. Move approval. Chair and members of the committee, this is a standard thing we do every year. I have to report to the Department of Elementary and Secondary Education by June 1st. I'm asking that you take the vote this evening.
The choice program is a program in which if we were to participate, we would have to take students from anywhere that wanted to come to Medford for available seats at approximately $5,000. It really doesn't work for us, so we recommend the school committee take the vote to reject school choice for the school year 2015-2016.
We have a motion of Mr. Scarpelli, seconded by Mrs. Van de Kloet. Mr. Secretary, would you please call the roll? Ms. Cuno? Yes. Mr. Benedetto? Mr. Falco? Yes. Mr. Scarpelli? Yes. Mr. Scariot? Yes. Mrs. Van de Kloet? Yes. Okay, six in the affirmative, one absent. School choice has been rejected.
Next item, uh, pre-budget report mathematics. Mr. Superintendent. Mr. Chairman, members of the committee, I call upon our deputy superintendent to begin the process of introducing the departments. We'll be presenting pre-budget reports in this evening. Good evening. Uh, tonight we continue with our pre-budget reports. We have three departments that are going to present tonight. Mathematics, English language learners, and the health and physical education department.
And the individuals who oversee those departments have prepared their reports, and they'll be giving highlights from those reports, as well as answering your questions. And so Carolyn Joy, our Director of Mathematics, is here tonight. Leslie Trotter, our Coordinator for English Language Learner Department. And Ms. Rachel Perry, who's our lead teacher for Health Phys Ed.
With Dr. Riccadeli, we'll be presenting our reports tonight. We've organized all our reports into different categories, which you have. And again, each report has the previous year's budget.
There is one correction on the bottom of this report. We have changed our meeting of the whole for the principals and school improvement plans from the 11th to the 13th. So Wednesday the 13th we will have a meeting of the whole at Medford high school at which time the principals will be there to answer questions. I believe you received those school improvement plans this evening.
We ask that you do read them over so that we can use our time efficiently that evening. So again, having a lot of questions for principals rather than a lengthy presentation. So that will be on the 13th. We will also have two other departments. We hope to have another meeting of the whole to discuss technology as well as special education. But I don't believe we have a definite date for that at this particular point. So with that, I think we'll start with Mrs. Joy in mathematics.
Good evening, everyone. I'd like to start today by giving you a little bit of a description of the program and for those people outside watching. The mathematics program in the district supports teaching and learning of mathematics in grades kindergarten through grade 12.
The support includes supervision and evaluation of instruction across grade levels, analysis of student data, and review of the effectiveness of program materials. The curriculum document is aligned to the 2011 Massachusetts Mathematics Curriculum Framework that is based on the Common Core State Standards. The mathematics curriculum is standards-based.
with a shared emphasis on mathematical practice and content. The new K-5 curriculum materials and revised report cards reflect the shift.
The middle school program has an accelerated option with a compacted grade 7 pre-algebra, followed by algebra 1 in grade 8. And the high school program offers 11 five-credit courses at the standard college preparatory and honors levels, three advanced placement courses, and five two-credit courses.
Mathematics electives include three five-credit courses in computer programming and five two-credit support and test prep courses. Mathematics courses for special populations are aligned to the district's curriculum. High school students are required to take and pass four years of mathematics to include a course beyond Algebra II.
Students can choose from six senior year mathematics courses to meet this new requirement. And a proficiency score of 240 or better, as determined by the MCAS testing, is required for the attainment of a diploma.
Our primary instructional materials is the new EnVision program at the elementary schools, Connected Math Project and Big Ideas Math is in the middle schools, and Prentice Hall's program, Tools for a Changing World, and a variety of other texts for all our courses post-Algebra II.
Teachers are encouraged to use supplemental resources for curriculum alignment, remediation, and enrichment. So over the past year, we've had a lot going on, especially at the
K-5 level with the adoption of the new Envision Mathematics program. The elementary teachers, specialists, and administrators, we all participated in year-long professional development with Pearson trainers and consultants. The teachers are now in the process of benchmarking student learning using the Envision Math program materials.
Families gain insights to the mathematic offerings and engaged in conversation at the presentation Middle School Mathematics Programs and Pathways to High School Mathematics, which we held recently.
It was a great night that we had. There was a lot of clarification and we even had fifth grade parents wanting to know more about what's happening at the high school. So as was said earlier, people are looking ahead to high school programs.
We'll be celebrating the final cohort of middle and high school teachers. We'll be graduating from the NSF grant-funded research project offered by the Poincar Institute at Tufts University, and preliminary data shows a positive impact on student learning. When this report comes out, I'll be able to share it with you. I've just received pieces of it, and they are showing positive trends
with students who have been taught by teachers who have gone through the program and also those schools where it exists as compared to other schools across the state because the teachers do collaborate with non-institute teachers.
Our department meetings this year focused on district and departmental goals to include social-emotional learning, student assessment, curriculum, and instruction. Our collaboration among the mathematics, special education, and English language learning faculties is strong and includes development of common assessments at the secondary level, sharing of resources and teaching strategies.
We had common midterms developed and end-of-year assessments that are constantly in revision. New assessments have been developed and piloted to meet the DESE's requirement for district-determined measures.
And Kathy McDaglio presents her report to the committee. She's going to talk a little bit more about how there was a great collaboration. We had the National Council of Teachers of Mathematics, their conference.
just came to Boston, it comes every six or seven years, and she was able to find a group of teachers to go out, gen ed and special ed math teachers, and they're in the process now of putting together a presentation to share with the rest of the faculty.
Our teachers are participating in training for SEI endorsement, and they implement best practices for teaching and learning. Our Algebra I class is integrated with the vocational, technical, and high school students. So this was a first this year where the teachers shared students from both schools, and it's working well. And the plan is to continue next year with the geometry classes.
It didn't, kids got there on time and did what they needed to do and it worked well both ways. So two new courses, Advanced Placement Computer Science and Mathematics Decision Making were launched at the high school.
We're growing that computer pathway, and it's going to be slow, but we see the excitement starting at the younger grades, so we hope to increase the participation there. And the mathematical decision-making course
has met with rave reviews. We've got positive feedback from the students about this course. The pedagogy is a little bit different. It's a senior level course where the students do come in, facilitated by a teacher, and work together to solve problems. So it's been a great program to have, and we hope that will be expanded for next year.
The high school robotics teams received continuous support from E-Day of Medford and takes the second place in the New England vault ball robotics competition. The department collaborates with the district technology department, the vocational tech school,
community and university partners on grant-funded initiatives in coding and robotics for the middle and high school students, and courses and activities are in place to create that pipeline to the AP Computer Science.
Tufts University's new STEM Ambassadors Program comes to Medford High School. We've already done some preliminary planning to extend that program for next year. It's worked really well. And that was led by one of our former Medford High School graduates, which was nice.
We also had a group that participated at the university's annual presidential summit, and here we made some more connections and collaborated with university and community leaders. So you'll be hearing more next year that will be growing out of that. We've applied for some grants together.
17 new high school science labs open with the oversight of the physical space, the furnishings and equipment, planning for transition into the new space, professional development for safety, technology and systems, and relocating mathematics teachers back to their previous classrooms.
And our current staffing, we have 28 and a half positions in mathematics for grades six through 12. And of the 29 teachers, 23 teachers have professional status in district and six are pre-professional teachers. And you have the breakdown of the faculty there.
And again, these positions at the high school and vocational technical high school, they're shared. So like we said, we have the students going back and forth between the two buildings. And for next year, the department will make staffing projections when the enrollment figures are available. And we will make all efforts to utilize the existing level of staffing at the high school.
The four-year mathematics graduation requirement, that began with this current graduating class. And as we go on, we might see a need for more increased staffing as a result. Re-instituting mathematics coaches at the elementary and middle school levels is recommended as the district implements new standards and programs.
The programs that are coming into the schools are quite different from what we had before. And any extra training or support that we can have for the elementary teachers is welcome.
The funding that was given this past year went to textbooks, instructional supplies, and office supplies. As you can see, as you read through, we did need to fund the new AB computer science and more mathematics courses to meet that four-year requirement.
And what becomes a continued expense is purchase of calculators and batteries every year. And it's just that now we're looking at generations and what the life is of these calculators.
And we're looking at like 15 year marks, so now we're starting to replace, as well as we're making sure that everybody at the secondary level, especially grades eight on up, have graphing calculators, whether they're in gen ed, special ed, and ELL.
So that we continue to purchase those supplies, and with that comes the need for the batteries. So for next year, our non-salary funding needs for the textbooks, what I would like to do is be able to purchase one classroom set of the new Envision program for each grade level. Because the numbers of students at each grade, it fluctuates.
And we don't have any spare kits. So that would be like outfitting a classroom for 20 to 25 students and one teacher at each grade level. That would come to approximately $6,000 or $1,000 per grade.
And then funded as last year would be reminding of books. We do have old textbooks, especially at the high school level. We're not ready to do a purchase just yet. And again, we might need to because of the fluctuations in enrollments.
and the kinds of programs that we're offering outside of the general ed population and also for the vocational school, we want to be able to support any of their programming needs. Instructional supplies, again, level funded as funded this year for those typical supplies as the calculators and also the teaching supplies. But of us that we purchase,
some document cameras for the classrooms. Some teachers have gone out and purchased them on their own for their classroom because it's such a useful tool. At Andrews Middle School,
Principal DeLava, he has purchased them for a good number of the mathematics classrooms. They're very, very useful, not for just only the teacher, but for the students. So it's a way for them to project student work. It's invaluable for special educators when you want a model in 3D, you can actually put a 3D model under the camera.
and use the projection system that we have in place. So this will not be the quality as those that we purchased for the science labs, but it should be something that we would be able to maintain for years to come. So we'd like you to consider that change and then the office supplies funded as in prior years.
So the vision for the department is that all students be college and career ready through the implementation of a well-articulated mathematics curriculum and for the community to provide support for the tools and the professional development necessary to fulfill that vision.
So, some of the examples of long-term activities. Again, our curriculum committee will be working to develop model curriculum units. They've already started that. It's been many teachers' goals to do that.
as part of the evaluation process. They did piloting of district-determined measures that they developed this year, and that will be ongoing. And we're beginning to develop a new scope and sequence based on the Common Core curriculum, which is our new framework.
We're looking for support restructuring at the elementary level to strengthen mathematics instruction. And that support could come from outside programs, after school, summer, and also in school with the coaching piece. A commitment by the school committee, I look to you for a new program in grade six through algebra two.
And this will come at a substantial cost. Right now we have a segment of the middle school using new materials, piloting programs. We have textbook committees now developing again, where rather than piloting, publishers have sent me some examination copies.
and we're actually going to go through them starting in June and through the summer and hopefully by February we'll have some titles for you to look at and consider for purchase.
Again, mathematics coaches at the elementary and middle schools to provide ongoing professional development in implementing these new standards and participate in developing a K through 12 science and technology engineering curriculum that aligns to the mathematics program.
The new standards have not been adopted yet, but once they are, we will be seeing the connections between the two, because the preliminary documents do articulate what students need to know in mathematics to be able to do science. And here is a list of some of the goals. Again, go along with those long-term plans for the department.
I have two questions. One, the document camera, I don't exactly understand what that is. Okay. It's a freestanding device that can be put on a table that hooks up to the computer.
And also your LCD projector. So you can put an item underneath and it will project. So the students could actually, if they're working together in group work, and they have something that they want to present to the class, they can just put a piece of paper underneath this camera.
And it will project the student work. So we find that it works well with those students who are not confident to go up to a board and write, that they might feel more comfortable bringing a piece of paper up. And then also, it helps with the modeling. And the teachers find that it saves a lot of time. So a lot of these programs, you really need
an hour to implement that. But if you have the right tools, it's going to help you cut corners in time. So that piece of technology and seeing the teachers use it at the Andrews Middle School and a couple of teachers who bought their own at the high school, I think would be a worthwhile investment.
And are they, how many of them, how much do they cost? They're about $300 a piece. Okay. And so, but I would work with the vendor to see how many we could get so that I would start with the higher grades first because the elementary program have a lot of pieces right now that are online.
So through their program, it's a little bit different from what the middle and the high school have. Do many different companies make them? Yes. Okay. The second just comment I wanted to make, and this is totally about my places right now, okay, but down in your goals, one of your goals is increase MCAS performance by three percentage points. I would be much more comfortable if you identified
increase the geometry strand or pick out two or three different strands and say further students' knowledge of these particular stands rather than saying increase it overall by three points. And it is about my feeling about the testing and if we change, whatever. I just don't want people looking at our paperwork and saying, well, you know, we're driven by the test. I want to be driven by the subject. Right. What happens is every year after the data is released,
We meet as a department and we go over the data. The elementary principals go over their data for their school, I go over with the middle, and the high school teachers, we actually go through the item analysis. Not just for their building or grade, but they all walk away with the item analysis for the students they teach.
So they drill down what they need to focus on. So I understand that this is a shorthand. Yeah, absolutely. But unfortunately, it's an uncomfortable shorthand. That's the overall piece of it, sure. Thank you very much. Motion to approve. Any other questions? If I may. Motion to accept the paper, please, on file. Second. OK, on the motion of Mrs. Carey to accept the paper, please, on file. Seconded by Mrs. D. Benedetto. I have a couple of quick questions. Two. In Visions. Yes.
Has every teacher been trained that's in the K-5? Right. Everybody who's in the K-5 have received the training along with a lot of the principals participated in the training, assistant principals. I know our assistant superintendent, Diane Caldwell, attended many of the trainings as I did so that we're all pretty well versed in it. So this is the first year of implementation.
So it will take teachers a little while getting used to how to use the materials to the best, but they had three separate trainings during the school year. They had one during the summer that was optional for teachers who wanted to come in, but those other three had different focuses. One was on seeing lessons modeled for the grade level, but all the way down to how to use the technology that goes with the program.
And that's my next question. The technology that goes with the program, from what I remember, there was an online component that you could use at home. Am I correct? Yes. So do the parents or have the students been given all of their login information to use that? All the students should have their login. And that was done, and it was centralized here at the high school with the data team. They were able to work with Pearson so that this
The passwords that they have, they can use year after year. So it'll just move with them as they move up through the grade. So once they're in the system, they're there. If a parent needs login information, do they contact the classroom teacher? Yes.
Last but not least, you had mentioned under textbooks about funding one classroom, set up K-5 divisions. Is that for a particular school or is that spread? That's spread out just so that as the enrollments change,
you know, some year you might need an extra third grade because they've moved up and we have that second grade set sitting there because maybe the second grade is smaller. Diane might speak a little bit more to the enrollment piece. So currently over at the Roberts, excuse me, elementary school, we have
5 grade 1s who will be going into 5 grade 2s. If we look at the Columbus, we are looking at a possible extra 3rd or 5th grade. The Brooks, a 4th. And at the McGlynn, we have 5 Ks that will go into 5 1s. So we don't yet have all the materials yet, so that's what Carolyn is referring to. Okay, perfect. Thank you. Any other questions?
Mrs. Cuno. Thank you. Just to go back to the goals of raising 3%, are we going to
provide maybe more tutoring after school next year for students? I mean, not only stay after their particular teacher, but actual programs after school that students could take, not necessarily just students that are not doing well in math, but in general? Right now, the funding that we have, it's grant funded. And students have to meet certain criteria.
for that program, and it's at the high school where it's the high stakes testing for grade 10. We offer other programs during the year. Some of them are after school programs. Some are almost like a camp-like atmosphere. We had one teacher who's, she's currently now teaching
some MCAS review on Saturdays for students, but those are students who are identified and meet the criteria of the grant. So we try to do as much as we can through the classroom teachers. I did have a parent inquiry and asked, is there a teacher who was doing anything?
That name will be passed on to the parents of the student if they want to go there. But a lot of the teachers use the questions as openers every day that you'll see the MCAS or MCAS-like questions being posed. So there are no definite plans of having anything structured because the funding isn't there for it.
What about if, I mean, I haven't gotten a statistic or anything, but I do hear parents say that sometimes they've taken their middle school students to a private tutor. So I was just thinking, is it possible maybe to do something in the middle school, target middle school students that parents are willing to pay, but instead of going all over the place, dropping off, picking up. I know we utilize the students at Tufts University, and we have a great program there.
But I also do know that parents are willing to pay for tutors, but I don't know if we ever offer those types of services. Well, we want to avoid any conflict of interest where the teachers are getting paid for what they're contracted to do anyway, with the extra classes.
meetings that they have with students contractually for the extra support after school. It's not unusual for a teacher to take on students that are not their own and that just come in and want to sit in on a test prep situation. We also have at the middle school, again built into the program,
We have, at the Andrews, we have a math lab set up, and all the students go through there, and it's more intense for those students who have been identified with the testing piece that Mr. DeLaver has put in place. And then at the high school, we offer mini courses in MCAS prep.
So we do have quite a bit out there, but sometimes the students overschedule themselves, and it's just not the right time or the right place for it. But I would be happy to investigate further if that's something we could do. And it's just for the students. Well, like I said, it's not necessarily just for always targeting the MCAS. Right. It's just to get more information on the mathematics itself. But you brought up a point.
I mean, I know that, I'm not just saying Medford teachers, but I know teachers in general, no matter what city you work, some teachers have part-time jobs. So are you saying that if a teacher in Medford has a Medford, not necessarily their student, but has a Medford student, and they're tutoring like after school or something, that's conflict of interest? Well, I would just be careful. I would be careful. If it's for a paid position.
I've never encouraged teachers to do something like that for pay. But it's OK for them to do it, let's say, for a student that's outside of the city. That would be better? Yeah, because then I'd pull the check. I was just curious in the conflict of interest thing. I hadn't heard that one before. All right, thank you. Any other questions?
Okay. And the motion was too scary. Seconded by Mrs D Benedetto that the pre-budget report on mathematics be accepted in place on file. All those in favor. All those opposed. The report is accepted in place on file. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Next item is the health. I'm sorry. The pre-budget report on health and physical education. Mr. Superintendent bring up Rachel Berry to make that motion.
I just want to say before Rachel speaks that she's just been doing a tremendous job as our lead teacher, also teaching full time. So she has a lot on her plate and she's just stepped right up and done a wonderful job. So Rachel. Good evening, Superintendent Belson, members of the school committee.
The goal of the Physical Education and Health Department of Method Public Schools is to enhance the well-being of the school community by creating a culture that integrates and balances the six dimensions of wellness. Social, physical, intellectual, occupational, emotional, and spiritual. The department strives to encourage an active, healthy lifestyle, healthy decision-making, and lifelong commitment to wellness.
Now the department is in really two parts. It's the physical education and the health education. Starting with physical education in elementary schools, our goal is to teach basic skills and concepts that will enable students to participate in a wide variety of physical activities with success and enjoyment.
Basic skills are learned and then applied to a wide variety of games, dance, gymnastics, and fitness activities. Moving on from elementary physical education, our students move on to middle school physical education.
In the middle school physical education program, built upon the knowledge and skills that they learned in elementary school, we make it a little bit more advanced so they're learning more advanced skills and concepts. Moving from middle school to high school, the high school program continues to build on these concepts and knowledge and skills. In freshman and sophomore physical education,
is fitness-based and allows students to learn about the five components of fitness, fitness testing, how to improve our fitness, and how to set up their own fitness routines. As juniors and seniors, the physical education program is a choice-based program, and our students choose their classes based on their interests. Some of the classes that we have for our juniors and seniors are first aid and CPR class, and that is for certification in both.
net games, dance, team sports, fitness, wellness activities, and yoga. Moving on to the health education, at our elementaries, we have a second step health curriculum at the elementary level, and that is taught by classroom teachers. We don't have dedicated health teachers at that level. At the middle school, for many years we used second step.
as our health curriculum. And many teachers and administrators thought that second step is developmentally appropriate, but that it's not addressing the health issues that we're seeing today for our students. So what we did is we started to pilot the Michigan model at the middle schools at both the McGlynn and at the Andrews. The Michigan model is its second year of use at the high school. Having it at the middle school will help add continuity to the health education program.
In the middle school, the guidance counselors and the physical education health teachers are covering the curriculum there. At the high school level, we are also using the Michigan model for 9th through 12th grade students. They have health for half the year and they have physical education for half the year. The Michigan model is the skills-based curriculum. It's student-centered and it gives students skills needed to help make healthy decisions.
And we have two teachers teaching health at the high school right now. Moving on to the highlights for this year. I've collaborated with the guidance department in the alignment of the guidance and health curriculum to the Michigan model, because the guidance councils and the health or physical education teachers will be teaching the Michigan model. We've piloted the Michigan model at the middle schools. We received the Department of Conservation and Recreation grant at Medford High School.
And Matt Galussi actually received that grant, where they're going into the woods and setting up paths in the woods, and they're marking the paths so that we can use them for hiking during our physical education classes. And there are also a number of classroom teachers that are going out and using those paths as well.
We have successfully integrated vocational freshman students into our high school physical education classes. In the past, they have been separated. This year, we integrated the freshmen. Next year, we will be integrating the sophomores. We have collaborated with the guidance department in scheduling the 2015-2016 junior and senior choice classes via I-PASS. In the past, I've had to do it by hand.
So we would have our juniors and seniors choose what classes they wanted when they were in their health classes, and then I'd have to go through them and place them based on what they chose. So this year we were actually able to do that via I-PASS when they were choosing their classes. We collaborated with Tufts University students in presenting health and wellness workshops to our high school students. Some of those workshops included nutrition, fitness, and stress management.
Collaborated with Team Medfit in ordering drug and alcohol educational videos for the middle school and the high school that will actually help complement the Michigan model materials. Some of those videos also include some of the things that we're seeing coming up. For instance, the vaping issue that we're seeing, we did get a video on that. We also got a really good video, educational video on the teen brain and what happens when they are using drugs and alcohol.
Two members of the physical education and health department attended the MIAA drug and alcohol education workshop in March. We were able to take away some really good information that will help us and add to our program.
And I actually participated in the design and delivery of the workshop related to the social emotional initiative for the November professional development day for teachers. Two of our health teachers did as well. Ashley McDonald and Dan Georgette actually did some team building activities with the teachers to help them learn about problem solving, things like that, things that they could actually bring back to their students. I presented yoga, where we did some breathing exercises. I presented with Liz Dineu.
We did a few yoga poses and we did a progressive muscle relaxation and a visualization. So that actually, we brought the teachers in in three different portions and they were able to experience that.
Another thing that we did is we did a yoga video, and that was myself, Liz Dineu, and Lisa Dunphy. And we shot the video, and then we were able to actually show it in advisory for all of our junior students. So they were able to participate in yoga. It was relaxation breathing and another relaxation portion at the end with some more poses. And it was about 10 minutes long, and a lot of students did that before school.
And there were so many students that came back to us and said, I had the best day after we did that. So it was really successful. In 2014 and 15 expenditures in physical education, we purchased office supplies, we maintained equipment, and purchased instructional supplies. The health expenditures, we purchased office supplies, we purchased the Michigan model curriculum for middle schools, and we did professional development conferences.
of fitness center expenditures included the after school fitness center supervision. We presently have 16.5 positions in the department.
For next year anticipated staffing needs, we are in need of a 1.0 adaptive physical education teacher to meet the needs of the special education students across the district. I've met with Kathy Medaglio, and she advised me that there are students in need of special adaptive physical education. We do have some students that can go into the general education, physical education classes, but we do have a number that need adaptive
classes and that number is growing.
We also need a 0.5 middle school physical education health teacher at the Andrews Middle School to help align the physical education and health schedules of both middle schools. We piloted the Michigan model this year. And what we saw is the McGlynn had 2.5 teachers and the Andrews only two. So what was happening is the McGlynn was able to cover more of the Michigan model where the Andrews could not. So we'd like to add another 0.5 there so that we have really both middle schools
on the same ground. The last one there is 1.0 health education teacher to assist the teachers with implementation of the health curriculum at the elementary level. They're presently teaching second step, but we're seeing a lot of anxiety and emotional issues at the elementary school. We're looking to add one teacher that could possibly help our classroom teachers with presenting the health curriculum
maybe model some lessons and help them out on that. Long-term development needs and direction. Continue to add electives to the junior and senior physical education choice program. That will include swimming, so we can utilize the beautiful swimming pool that just recently opened this year. I would also like to add a yoga two. We have yoga one, and kids really do enjoy it, so really build on that to make it a little bit more advanced.
I also would like to add some courses like Introduction to Teaching Physical Education, where our students can actually come in, learn how to teach, learn how to write lessons, and then use that and teach to our preschool children at the high school.
I would also like to incorporate introduction to coaching, introduction to athletic training, and introduction to fitness. I think that would give our students a really good basis. They might be thinking of going to college for one of those things and they can get some of that experience at the high school level and move on from there. I'd like to increase the
Health education staffing by 2.5 to incorporate the Michigan model at each elementary school, increase instruction at the middle school, and provide support for our special education students. Provide professional development in physical education and health content for K-12 physical education and health teachers. One of the things I'd like to incorporate is professional development for adaptive physical education. That's one thing when we're in our
degree programs, you might have a class, but that's all you get. You don't get anything in between. I really think that for all of our teachers, we need to really take a look at that adaptive physical education and take some more courses on that. We're going to complete piloting of the Michigan model at the middle school and explore its use at the elementary level.
Continue to update physical education instructional equipment, purchasing basketballs, footballs, different things that we need to be able to teach our classes. Those things do wear out yearly, so we do need to continue to replace those. Continue to keep up to date on physical education and health education standards to keep up with what's going on in the field.
Continue to collaborate the guidance department on the Michigan model health curriculum to make any changes that we need to make sure that we're working together and we're covering all aspects of the Michigan model. And the last one, improve the middle school schedule to afford all students the same amount of time in physical education and health. We really want to make sure that both middle schools are getting equal amount of time and I'd like to work with both principals on doing that.
Goals and objectives for 2015 and 16. By June 2016, the Medford Public Schools Physical Education and Health website pages will be updated to include curriculum and teacher information so that our parents know exactly what's being taught in physical education and in the health courses.
Starting in September of 2015, the Michigan model health curriculum will be reviewed for use at all elementary schools during the 2016-2017 school year by putting a committee together of administrators and teachers so that we can review that and talk about the best way to roll that new model out if possible. By January 2016, the high school physical education program will include swimming courses as electives for juniors and seniors in the course selection handbook.
Looking at the non-salary funding needs for maintenance of equipment, that does stay the same. We continue to maintain our equipment. Travel stays the same at 500 so that we can go out to professional development opportunities. Office supplies stays the same as well. Under textbooks, you'll see an increase there from 3,000. It does go to 23,000. That includes the purchase of the Michigan model curriculum for the elementary schools.
Educational supplies, again, stays the same at 6,000. And the last one, the fitness center supervision. I would just like a line item added. We didn't have anything allocated for it, but it was coming out of our budget. So it's $6,000 to actually staff the fitness center after school for our students. Mr. Scarpella. Nice job. Thank you very much for your report. Thank you.
As a former phys ed teacher, I have a few questions. How are the numbers in the health class at the high school? I know in the past, they've been pretty astronomical. Right now, our health students go from health to phys ed and then phys ed to health for half the year. So we have them capped at 30.
And sometimes students do get put in, and we've really done a great job with the guidance department to make sure that's not happening, or trying to figure out a way to place that student somewhere else so that the classes aren't really over 30. Does that fill all their requirements? If they move to still everybody's safe place? We'll move to another health class, I mean, so that they're used. All right.
Now I know that you're working a full teaching schedule and now this role, who's doing the evaluations of the teachers for? Administrators are doing the evaluations. Okay, so are you doing those? No. No, so you're not yet. Okay. But who is, do you know? I think it's different evaluators for different teachers. I don't know exactly. We've actually distributed them among the principals, assistant principals and others, but
It would be at the high school level, the assistant principals. I know Bernadette, you picked up some of the department too. I did. So I do one middle school teacher. So it was split. We took, we took the Phys Ed teachers and we split them between principals and myself, director. So Rachel is not, she is in the teachers association.
I'm just saying, as a former phys ed teacher, it'd be nice to have an administrator with a background in physical education doing those evaluations. Not to disrespect anybody here, I think it's a great job, but I think it's important. Well, if we make her an administrator tonight, she can pick right up tomorrow. We'd have to evaluate that, but I don't disagree.
The equipment, I know the equipment, we keep talking about the equipment at the high school. It's being used for school, uh, for classes and for afterschool. We see, we see different groups in there on the weekends, um, through community schools and it is $6,000 enough or are you talking about fitness center maintenance equipment? Excuse me? $5,000 that yes. Um,
Now, equipment for the other schools, how is it broken down for their budget for equipment? I usually break it down between all the schools, so it's about $500 to $600 per school that they're allowed to purchase each year. OK. And with the addition of the adaptive physical education teacher, is that needed under
that we fall compliant to special education, or is that just? So it's a must. Yes, when I met with Captain McDougall, yes. When she does come to speak on her pre-budget, she's going to speak a little bit more about that as well. That's going to be interesting to hear, the breakdown of how many children. Because that might be something you can use hiring a split and adapted physical education teacher, and then looking to fill some of the other gaps that you have. So that might be something that we need to do.
Then the other number, obviously, that sticks out is the $23,000 for the textbooks. As we move down, has it been, it's been piloted at the high school level? We're in the second year at the high school level. This year it was piloted at the middle schools. And we're moving down to the pilot, this is what's going to be used to pilot the elementary level? Yes, at all four elementary schools. Okay, thank you. Thank you. Mrs. DiBenedetto.
I thank you for your report, it was very thorough, and I appreciate how you worked everything out. I just have a question. You asked for another health education teacher to assist teachers.
to help them implement the curriculum due to the social emotional issues of children in the classroom and I want to address that but I want to address that as a whole district and we talked about possibly having a meeting because we have many departments requesting staff to help this both
A few people have come through, the guidance department has come through to help us with this, to make requests for additional staff members to help with this. Other department heads have come through. And we did talk about a few weeks ago or a few meetings ago,
having a meeting to discuss this and how we were going to address this, rather than each department coming and asking the committee for additional supports, but in this manner, as to which is the best way to support our educators in this realm and where those positions should be placed, whether they should be more nurses or more guidance people or more, you know, rather than each department.
If I could I just take for a second because we obviously know there's a need and we know there's a need for more personnel. And so as people are doing their pre-budget, we've asked them to put it in because obviously we can't get an extra person in each department. We're hoping that we get one or two extra people, whether it's a health dedicated person or a person guidance dedicated.
because they all work together, but we know there's a need for more. So they're putting it in their budgets independently, knowing that we're not going to get the full complement of what we're asking, but we're hoping to get more. With the case of the health, the classroom, elementary classroom teachers have a tremendous burden already teaching all the subjects, and they're the dedicated health teachers. So they're really with the phys ed, but it's not the high school and the middle school have more people dedicated to the teaching.
The elementary teachers, some of them really, especially the new ones can need some, need some assistance with this. So again, between the guidance, the health, the nursing, we're hoping to emphasize the need for more people to work on the same topic. And it doesn't have to be multiple people, but hoping at least one or two.
Well, that that's my point. We keep discussing this as it keeps coming forward. And I think it's great that each department is bringing that, but we did discuss meeting to see which is the best way to move forward to supporting our students needs as well as our staffing needs. So we talked about that. I don't know if you've set up a time for that, Mr. Nelson. Well, first of all, as you know, we have, and I'm going to talk about more meetings coming up.
You know, we have multiple meetings and, you know, we're already in May. And so one of the things we're going to be doing is we're going to be, you've got to look at this as a two or three year plan. People come up and say, I want this, I want that, I want that.
You know, and we're going to triage it for you and give you some recommendations, and then we can discuss it. It'll be part of our, an active, you know, discussion that we have. And we'll set up a time to do it. But obviously, this is, when people come up and they tell you they need this and they need that, in probably over two, three years, we can probably do it. Just as we replaced assistant principals, just as we put other things in place, you're going to see this move over two, three years. And now, if the revenue is good, you move a little faster.
But the reality is, is that we're asking people to tell you what they really would like to have, so you see that. But from our standpoint, we're going to have to triage it over two, three years. My concern is that we don't just put bodies in certain departments, that we as a committee determine where that need can be best.
Well, we'll certainly go over it with you. I think we've got to look at it from a holistic standpoint because the other thing, too, is that certain departments have people who can do more than one thing. Some departments don't have that possibility. We know of certain possible retirements. That opens the door for replacing people in certain ways. So, for example, a senior person retires.
You might be able to get two positions for that senior person because of their salary level. All these things factor in, so we're just going to have to look at it intelligently. But first thing, we'll get it together, and then we'll have that good discussion that you're looking for. Thank you. Thank you. Mrs. Cunha.
Oh. Thank you, Rachel, for your report. It's really thorough. Just a couple of questions, actually. When you said you capped your classes at 30, I was just curious in knowing, is the contractual, are we going against any contractual numbers? Because I know at the high school level for teachers, it's no more than 23 to 25. That's for the core content. So the physical education, we're within the contractual. OK. And Rachel, how many classes are you teaching during the day?
I have three to four a day, depending on the day. Three to four? And they're all at the high school? Yes. And you had mentioned, you know, that one of the goals is 2016, hopefully we could use the pool. I was wondering if we could look into maybe some type of intro to lifeguard certification or, I know that's a long
but some type of like introduction as you were mentioning before. I love your idea about having students maybe come and help out and introduce them to like sports medicine and things like that.
looking at colleges lately, not for one, but for two. And sports medicine has increased. I mean, I can't get over the amount of students now that are looking for sports medicine or, oh my gosh, I just went blank and that's all I've been doing. Sports medicine, what was the other one? Sports management and things like that. So I love that idea. And also, the Michigan Model Health.
When parents have like open house, has anybody explained the Michigan model health to them? Is there any presentation to parents of what it actually encompasses? I mean, I know you've spoke about it here, you spoke about it the other night when we had the meeting of the whole, but I was just curious in knowing when we have open houses, do any of the principals speak about it? Does anybody talk about what we're offering?
Sure. When we had the 8th grade night at the high school, I was there and I spoke to parents about the Michigan model. And that's one of the reasons I really want to redo our website so that parents can go on and see exactly what we're offering for health and for physical education. I love the ideas. I love the idea of the website. I just love the inspiration of new eyes, new ears, and new programs. So thank you. Thank you for this. Thank you.
Mr. Scaramucci. Mr. Scaramucci. Mr. Scaramucci.
see if we can put together a professional day, some type of training, adaptive phys ed for our phys ed teachers. So we can probably begin that beginning in the next school year. On the Michigan model? No, no, on adaptive phys ed for the kids. Adaptive, okay. She needed a need, and I think that's probably one of the first things that we should attend to. And we get that going, and at least they'll be able to plan for September.
This is very good. Rachel, thanks for your report. There were so many interesting things that you touched upon. One of them, though, I just want to ask you, you mentioned making a 10-minute video that the kids could watch. Is it posted someplace? It is not, but I can get you a copy of it. I just was thinking that it could also be a nice introduction for other teachers at the elementary level and whatever, because I'm thinking so much that we're going to need to incorporate this somehow into our curriculum.
ways to help kids relax and teachers relax, but I'm thinking about the anxiety that we talked about. So, yeah, if it's possible, I'd love to see it. We could also probably put it on the Memphis Public Schools website. That would be a great option. Mr. Scariot. How about giving Mr. Dempsey to put it on the high school channel? Yes, we could do that as well. A couple of mornings a week. Okay.
and Mrs. Cuno. I had one more question, and that was, you have down here that you'd like to improve the middle school schedule to afford all students the same amount of time in physical education and health. Could you elaborate a little bit more on that? Yes, what's happening is, like I said, at the McGlynn, we have 2.5 teachers, and at the Anders, we only have two. So they're not covering as much of the curriculum as the McGlynn is.
So adding another 0.5 would actually help afford and make that a little bit more even on both sides. Okay, so it's not necessarily then, because I've heard in the past, you know, well, if you're selecting an instrument, then you lose out on the Phys Ed, but you're not saying that. You're saying that it's more because of a 0.5 teacher. That's what we're saying for health and Phys Ed, yes. Okay, thank you.
All right, thank you for your report, very thorough. I just had a quick question, well, statement. First of all, I'm really happy to see that in your goals and objectives that you're incorporating the pool. It's fabulous, I mean, it's a great facility. Not all cities and towns have a facility like this, and it's great to see that we're using it. One of the things I was wondering is, have we ever done any type of poll, got to the high school students, and how many kids know how to swim?
Because we actually haven't had a pool in a while, so I'm thinking, you know, there could be a group of people out there that just don't know how to swim. I think it's something that should look into just a swimming class in general, how to swim, especially because you hear each year how so many kids...
Right, that's definitely a great idea. One of the things I was looking at doing is when we do have the swimming electives for juniors and seniors, that we would do one introduction to swimming for those students that cannot swim, and one more of water games for the students that can swim, where they can learn different water games. Mr. Scott probably touched on it earlier, the maintenance of equipment. So with regard to that budget line item, is that
Is that inclusive of the fitness center or is that just equipment outside of the fitness center? It's both. It's both. And with regard to that.
The fitness center in general, is the equipment in kind of shape? Are we in pretty good shape still? It is. We have a maintenance company that's coming in to look at the equipment. There's a few things that do need to be tightened, things like that. We haven't had anything major break down. One of the things when we did order the equipment, I used to manage fitness centers, so one of the things that I advised not to get was treadmills, because that's where you're really putting a lot of money in flipping the decks and putting on new belts and things like that.
So the equipment we have is in really good shape and just little things that need to be repaired. I just thought about the pool again. The pool. If students are taking swimming, is there a proper bathing suit that we're asking students to be wearing? Those are some things that we do need to go over as a staff. That is definitely going to be incorporated. That's definitely something we need to do. Absolutely.
Okay, on the motion of Mr. Skerry to approve the pre-budget report on health and PE in place on file, all those in favor? All right, opposed? The report is accepted. Thank you very much. Thank you. Next item is the pre-budget report on ELL, Mr. Superintendent. Last but not, certainly not least. I don't know, by the time I get to this time in NIDA, it probably least. This report will be delivered in five languages.
So on the pool discussion, I just want you to all know that one of the high school teachers is actually sending out an email to see if there will be a faculty interest in having a swim club for faculty in the mornings. So that's kind of cool. Brian Murnoff, one of the chemistry teachers.
Okay, well first I would like to thank you all and the superintendent and central office for your continued support of the very important work we do in the ELL department. And I also really want to publicly thank my dedicated and talented ELL staff for all that they do each and every day. They're really amazing.
As you can see from the breakdown of ELLs in each school and the languages represented by our current ELL population, we service an extremely diverse group of students. So I did include a sheet with all the languages and the numbers at each school. It's really pretty remarkable. Medford is unusual in the number of languages that we have for, you know, we don't have a gigantic program like a Boston or whatever.
But we have a very, very diverse program. So in addition to the many countries of origin and languages spoken, this year we have registered a number of incoming students with disrupted schooling. This has posed an additional challenge for my staff in terms of course needs, curriculum, materials, and differentiation.
We have registered approximately 85 students over the course of the 2014-15 school year, and more continue to come. My assessment specialist and lead teacher, Loretta Tusa, has been very, very busy.
So with the funding we received this year, we were able to purchase much needed science textbooks for the middle school, National Geographic ELL language arts textbooks for MHS, and ELL world history textbooks for MHS. We also got two computers per newcomers class, a huge help. Now that we have the computers, it is critical to fund software.
One of my teachers last summer did a research project on best software for ELLs, and the chosen program was BrainPOP, which is actually a great program for the entire system, not just ELLs.
And my wonderful secretary, Gislaine Pinto, was able to get a one month free trial for it. In your packets you have testimonials written by the students and one of the teachers. I wasn't able to get a chance to poll everybody, but some of them did send out some. So there are some testimonials from the newcomer students and teachers at the Roberts.
The software program was highly regarded across the city in ELL classrooms. It really made a big difference. And it would be a tremendous tool, not only for us, but for mainstream teachers as well.
We also need some science books for the Newcomers Elementary Program and updated assessment tests for the placement of entering ELLs. That would be in order to be aligned with the WIDA standards. Finally, one more teacher for the Elementary Newcomers Program would go a long way in meeting the needs of the ELL students. Sorry to ask for another staff member.
Currently our grade four or five class is overflowing over at the Roberts. More details on funding are in the ELL pre-budget report, should you have any questions. So already, having already presented many of the highlights from this year in March, I'll only touch upon new information.
And there are many things that went on this year that were great. So members of the ELL staff, including Xia Lin, Melissa McIntyre, Lisa Bolio, Emily Polini, Ami Sanye, Tanya Bogaty, Matt McKenna, Teresa Castagnetti, Sarah Dion, and Katie Rockwell.
are working on ELL curriculum K through 12, and then that includes math and science as well. This is a long-term project projected to be mostly completed by July 2016. DESE originally said they wanted it done by then. Then they offered to do some, a framework themselves and realized how difficult it was, so my guess is we'll probably have an extension.
As far as retail news, my survey monkeys kept failing when I tried to figure out exactly how many people had taken the courses, what was still needed. Really only DESE has that exact information because I don't have anything to do with teachers who take courses outside of Medford. So I would guess that probably close to 300 of our teachers have gotten their endorsement.
That leaves approximately 100 who still need to. I gave all that information to DESE so they are aware of the courses that we need and what numbers we still have for each kind of course. Almost all of the administrators have completed the SEI endorsement requirements.
Many of us, most of us, took a course this spring. Diane Guarino and I audited it just so that we would know what was going on, because anyone who has ESL certification does not have to take those courses.
We provided professional development within my department for the interface between ELLs and special education, which keeps coming up over and over again. And this coming summer, we're going to offer a workshop for my teachers targeting the WIDA standards, which is a very, very involved piece for them.
Two of our ELL teachers, Lisa Bolio and Melissa McIntyre, have also offered to provide training for our staff in regard to the retail initiative. This will give the ELL staff an understanding of the expectations for mainstream teachers in these courses. And Miss Bolio is actually a DESE trained retail instructor and taught a course this spring.
We provided language enrichment programs at every school where there is an ELL program this year after school, mostly taught by my teachers. A few other staff members who are ESL certified also taught them.
And then some very exciting news that we just found out about. Our ELL summer program will get free lunches this summer, sponsored by Project Bread and the Food Services Department. So we're really thrilled about that. Tanya Bogaty, an ELL teacher at the McGlynn Middle School, provided professional development for mainstream teachers to prepare for the SEIM TEL.
At the McGlynn Middle, Matt McKenna, Tanya Bogarty, and Elaine Oggett presented the world of ESL and ELL's PowerPoint presentation to the McGlynn Middle School staff, and I think I included a copy of that for you.
Melissa McIntyre, an ELL teacher at Medford High, organized and ran a multicultural night at Medford High in March. And Emily Polini, also an ELL teacher at the high school, presented at the symposium on Chapter 22 Discipline and Best Practices this past Saturday.
So my teachers are really, I'm not just saying that they're great, they truly are. They're very involved. Ami Sanye and Tanya Bogaty have administered and taught adult ELL evening classes this year, a very important component for the families in Medford.
Another very interesting thing that happened this year, a young woman named, I hope I get this right, Hawasata Dombuya, who is a Medford High graduate and former ELL student, currently a PhD candidate in molecular pharmacology and physiology at Brown University.
really amazing. She's implemented the science career program. And so she was written up in a Brown University publication about our
She's presented at Medford High over the course of the year, which I gave you a copy of. And we would like to invite any of you who would like to attend to the next panel discussion, which is at the high school on Monday, May 11th at approximately 1230. She'll be having former Medford High ELL students present and talk about what they're currently doing. So she's been wonderful. She's a great role model.
And another really great thing that just recently happened, Teresa Castagnetti, one of our ELL teachers at the McGlynn Elementary School, won Teacher of the Year award from MatSol. And she was nominated by Sarah Dionne, a second year ELL teacher whom she mentored last year. She will be recognized at the MatSol conference this Thursday evening, so that's really exciting.
And finally, I would like to publicly thank Nelida Lepore, the high school Spanish teacher extraordinaire, for organizing the educational tour to Cuba that many of us were able to experience during April vacation. It was a remarkable trip, and she did a tremendous job.
So thank you all for your attention. Our work with the English language learners is an extremely important piece in the scope of the many functions of our schools and I'd be happy to try to answer any of your questions.
I just want to comment on one of our teachers becoming the Matisol Teacher of the Year award. I know Teresa very well and she's been a long standing, dedicated teacher throughout our community for a very long time. And I personally want to congratulate her as well as a member of the school committee. This is the type of thing that we hope all of our teachers,
become and I look at her as a master teacher. Absolutely. She's incredible. And this is a huge, this is throughout all of the United States. Massachusetts. Yeah. That's outstanding work. She's wonderful. And all the other teachers look to Teresa for answers. I mean, she's really terrific. Yeah.
Following up on that is I thought that we should at least invite her to school. Thank you. I think that's in the plans. Yeah, perfect.
Mr. Felton. Mr. Scott Felton. If I can, as a former colleague of Ms. Castaneda, she was a great role model, not only for just the ELL teachers, but all of our teachers. So we applaud her and thank her. One question I just had to have, I know in the past, it's a question we've always asked. We're in compliance with the Department of Education with all of our numbers and teaching teachers.
across the board. For retail are you referring to? For all of our coverages that we have. There are no issues, no additions. Class sizes. There's a problem at the Roberts. The newcomers grade four or five classes. Right, so the Roberts is, this is,
This is the one we're asking for the increased consent. Yeah, it's so hard to judge with ESL because the kids come and go. So like I said, we've registered close to 85 kids this year who entered. We've also had some exit. I know that's a tough part, especially as years end in different countries and they move. Right. They might be done in their countries, then move here. Right. And they're right in the middle of ours, so I know how difficult it is. Yeah, so currently,
The Roberts Newcomers Grade 4-5 class has been a very large class all year long. Thank you.
So I see what your wish list is for 2016, and I see a large increase in software. What type of software would that be? So that's for BrainPOP across the city, and hopefully RAS Kids, although a lot of the elementary teachers have collected a little bit of money from each student for RAS Kids.
But the BrainPop, I believe, is close to a little over $14,000 if we bought it system-wide.
Okay, and my other question is about your assessment tools. Yes. Are those to keep up with regulations that have come forth? So, we've used the same assessment tools for placement of incoming students for many, many years, and Loretta is in the process of going to different cities and calling different places to see what people use.
The state allows us to use a free test from WIDA, which isn't necessarily the best test, but we have used it. And so we're looking to try to come up with the very best thing we can do so that we do place kids accurately. Okay. Mrs. Cuno. Thank you, Leslie, for the report. I'm looking at your pie chart, the one from Massachusetts and the one from Medford.
Because English is not on these pies at all, I'm assuming that these pies are just based on ELL students, correct? Yes. That's the PowerPoint that Matt McKenna put together for the middle school teachers, yes. Thank you.
I just want to comment, I mean, I sort of got lost in some of the handouts you gave us. They're great, very much like the PowerPoint that you'd mentioned. And reading the kids bring up very cute. Aren't they cute? Yeah, I know. Yeah, I definitely, it would be very, very nice to be able to provide that because clearly that's something that they enjoy. Yeah.
Okay, on the motion of Mr. Secretary and seconded by Mrs. DiBenedetto to accept the pre-budget report on ELL and place on file. All those in favor? Aye. Opposed? The report is accepted and placed on file. Thank you very much. Thank you. Thank you. Next item, report on summer programs. Mr. Superintendent. Mr. Chairman and members of the committee, we call upon our curriculum director, Dr. Bernadette Riccobelli, to tell us about what's going to happen this summer quite a bit.
Good evening. So I'm here tonight to tell you about our summer 2015 programs for students. I understand you have read this report, so I'll try to keep it brief and leave plenty of time for questions. So this year, there are seven programs, two of which are new. So I'll spend most time talking about those two new programs.
So we have our regular summer school program, and as you know, this program is designed to meet the needs of students in grades 6 to 12 who have failed one to two of their major courses. This year, summer school takes place at Medford High School between July 1st and August 11th. The cost is $250 for Medford students and $300 for students outside of Medford.
We also have an English Language Learner Summer Program. So this program is intended to help ELL students master the important skills so that they can be successful when they come back to school in the fall and then beyond. So there's an elementary and a middle school program. That program runs from July 6 to July 30. And then there is a high school program, and it is a short program. It's just a few days. It's June 30 to Friday, July 3.
The reason for that short time frame is because many of the ELL students work. So under the advisement of the ELL director, that program was created to be just for a few days. As Leslie mentioned, breakfast will be included in the cost, and the cost of the program is free to the students. It is supported by the grant.
The third program is the Summer Fun Program. It's a recreational program offered through Medford Community Schools that will take place this year at the high school and not the Columbus, and that's due to the availability of the high school pool. So that will run from July 6th to August 21st for students in grades K through 6.
Students will have an opportunity to participate in a number of activities and sports and swimming and many more activities. So parents can sign up on a weekly basis for their child, children. The cost is $145 per week and includes breakfast every day and pizza Friday.
The next program is a new program, and it was organized by Molly Leighton. It's the Middle School Computer Science Camp. So this is, I think, an innovative program that's going to provide middle school students with the opportunity to explore the field of computer science. And they'll be developing a working mobile app. So they'll develop a community-focused app. So there's really a social justice
slant to this, and they will collaborate with other students to further their problem solving and programming skills. So it's available to our district through the Middle School Pathways and Computer Science Grant, which is through the National Science Foundation. Lunch is provided daily, and the dates for this camp, again, it's a short one, it is one week, it's July 6th to July 10th from 8.30 to 3.30 p.m.
The next camp is also a new one. The next program, I should say, is also a new program. It's at the Vocational Technical High School. So this is an idea from Heidi Riccio. This program has been developed to provide grade seven students with an opportunity to explore the various offerings at the vocational school.
And some of these programs include culinary arts, cosmetology, robotics and engineering, metal fabrication, babysitting certification, biotechnology and environmental science. Each one of these programs will also include one hour swimming at the Medford High School pool.
The course runs Monday to Thursday from July 13th to July 30th from 8 a.m. to 12 noon. The cost is $150 and that price includes a snack.
We anticipate that we're going to have a number of students apply for this program. It is limited. This is our first year. We're trying it out. Perhaps in the future it will grow. So students will be enrolled on a first-come, first-served basis, and seats will be divided equally between the two middle schools.
Our next program is the High School 101 program, which has been running for a number of, I'd say three or four years now, and from all accounts has been enormously successful in providing our incoming ninth grade students with an orientation, a physical orientation of Medford High School campus, and an academic orientation. The teachers prepare them for their summer reading assignments. They go over what they need to be successful in their first days in their algebra class.
So that program will run in late August, and it runs for a week. In previous years, it had been funded through the academic support grant. Since the allocation for this grant has been significantly reduced recently, we are now funding it through our regular budget.
And lastly, for summer programs, we have our special ed programs. These programs are designed to meet the various needs of our special ed students. Many of the students have IEPs that specify that they need to have 11-month services. So we've designed these programs with this in mind. So there are six-week programs that run from July 6 to the 14th.
and four-week programs that run from July 13th to August 7th. And then there are also some tutoring and related service programs depending on the individual needs of students. So we're in the process right now of
creating job descriptions for our instructors for these various programs, and we will be recruiting students very soon. I'm seeing now that we're at the beginning of May. Thank you Bernadette. How many students can be included in the middle school computer science camp?
That is Molly's program. Actually, I don't have a number on that. Originally, that program was designed to take students who were already in the middle school computer science program. When I talked to Molly last, she anticipated there probably would be about 15 students. About 15, 1-5, about 15 students. That's her anticipated number.
I just note, because it's free, that parents looking... Right, it's free. And when we talked about it, I guess the one drawback is that when parents are looking to place their students in a program, they're looking for a longer duration. This is just one week.
It's a great program. I don't want to take away from it. It's wonderful. There's some concern about our parents going to want to place their students in camp for just one week. We hope they do. But they do that for one week and then go to the camp. I'm just saying that because it's free, it definitely stands out. Anyway, thank you for providing us with all this information. You're welcome. Mrs. DiBenedetto.
So I noticed that you're moving the summer fund program from the Columbus School to the high school. Yes. Is that going to affect the program in any way?
So the reason behind that is accessibility to the pool. So it's the only school with a pool. And now that we have a pool, we want to use it. And it's the summer. And we thought that would be the best place. So we've talked about the summer programs. We don't see any drawbacks. There are going to be a lot of people at Medford High School. But we've coordinated these programs so that they don't interfere with each other.
We see an upside to this. Of course, we'll evaluate it and if there is a downside and we determine that it doesn't work at Medford High School, then next year it would be at another location. Well, I know that the students have walked in the past from the Columbus to Tufts pool.
So for safety reasons, that's always great. As long as the children still get enough outside time, because I know the tough school, it was weather related because it was an outside pool. So they might get more exercise and more swim time, but as long as they get outside and use the fields and stuff like that, that's really important as well. Thank you. Point of information. Point of information, Mrs. Cuno. They will still have the same type of curriculum because they'll be using the field.
I guess my concern was also just the change because I really kind of like the idea of being on the Tufts pool outside. I guess there's always pros and cons to everything. And also, you know, at the elementary school there was a playground and stuff like that. So it changes the nature, again, whether it's a positive or negative, I'm not quite sure.
So we will, we will evaluate that and we will see how it goes and get feedback from the parents. Anthony Petrellis. I've talked to Mr. Mr. Petrellis, the director of the program, and you know, he, he, he reached out to me with my background in recreation. And when we founded it years ago, his, his philosophies using what's there, even if we have the playground apparatus, if there were younger kids at the, um,
at the high school, but he didn't think that was an issue. He says having them in a safer area, not doing the walk, having the pool open, the fields accessible to them, the gym space being larger, I think it all falls into
to what we're looking for, for a safe environment for our kids. And also, if I could just mention really quick too, it gives, I think, by moving up to the high school, it also gives the Columbus the opportunity to be properly maintained during the summer. Because if it's not, I mean, if you have the program at the Columbus, you really, there's minimal time to get that school back in shape before it's online again for the school year. And I believe in the promotion of the pool, having over 150 kids there.
We're using that pool with no limitations in the sense that now they can see what we have and more kids will go to that area. So. Yeah. Very curious. Yeah, no, I just, I appreciate the conversation. That's exactly what I wanted to hear. Yeah, and.
Just a point of information again, I know that in the past years because the, you know, our summers have had a lot of days that it's been raining, students do lose out on actually taking advantage of going out because they can't go out in the rain. So, sorry, but they can't not only go out in the rain,
to the park but they can't get to the pool either because it is, you know, it is out there. Whereas we have the indoor pool and it's better so that way they're not getting sunburned if we, you know, if it's really hot and they're not losing out on the activity because of the weather.
Thank you. Mrs. DiBenedetto. I just wanted, well, first thing I was going to talk about is the maintenance at the Columbus. So I'm glad that school is getting a little bit of a break. I know there are other programs being run out of that, out of that school, the special education programs are still going to be, I'm assuming in that program. So, but it does deserve a break. It's, it's been used, you know, quite often in,
quite a bit, and this does give it the chance it needs. And also, I just wanted to comment on the Summer Fund program in general. I think it's an excellent program. It's priced extremely affordable, and I think it has a really important need within our community that really helps our parents that have to go to work to have a safe place for their children.
and that they're really, they're learning swimming, they're outside, they're well cared for, and it's $145 a week, which is well below what other camps cost our families. So I'm really grateful to have this for our families in our community.
Thank you. If I could just, um, just clarify something. The special ed cam program this year is taking place at the Roberts elementary school. Oh, it's being moved as well. So the Roberts is getting a big break. So, yes. So I, so I just wanted to clarify that.
Mr. Scott Pellett. No, just again, just clarification. Are there any special ed programs that are working together with the summer program? I know we did a lot of that and it really helped financially for both outside placement offering that type of program. How does that look? You mean through the community schools program? Through the summertime program. I know we had a lot of the special needs programs, uh, working conjunction with the summertime to, to offset any of the, um, you know,
Not to my knowledge, but I certainly will follow up on that. So my understanding is that the special ed students are, that they're in that special ed program. I mean, that's not to say that special ed students, that special ed program is for students whose IEP specifies that they need to have that 11 month placement. So you're going to have special ed students that are in the regular summer program.
So maybe that's where the disconnect is. So yes, there will be special ed students in the summer fund program. They will automatically be enrolled in that program. If they choose. If they need to, right? Yes. OK. I think the other piece of this is you don't say it enough, because I know my colleague, Mr. Benedetto, has talked about the promotion of who we have. When you're talking about the teacher of the year, Anthony Petrellis,
I had the opportunity to mentor him years ago. And we often talk now with recreational interactions with what we're doing with my full-time position. And I will tell you, he is a jewel. I think that sometimes you overlook
What he does in the classroom is amazing. What he does for that program is one of the reasons why we get the numbers. Because I think people, myself included as a parent, who had Mr. Petrellis, the comfort level is so high.
It's such a high level that it's easy just to bring him in no matter what the price was. So again, people have to know the people that are running these programs are who they are. They're pretty amazing, as well as our special ed programs. I know our other summer programs, our vocational programs, this is amazing. So I think this is
Well done. So Anthony Petrella's name is not in the report, and it probably should be. However, his name is on the website, so that the flyer that is posted does identify him as the director of the summer program for him. So we have to champion this. And I'd like to get, if we can, to the superintendent having a conversation. I know he's not too... He's very...
I'm embarrassed if I brought this up, but the change in his life and what he's being asked across the state and what they're asking him to do because of this award, I think has to be championed from this committee, because that just shows one of our teachers, where he's being asked to teach at the collegiate level now in higher education and where he's going for different conferences, and again, that's
He didn't just win the Teacher of the Year and get a check and then go to a basketball game. He's doing so much more in education because of that award. I think we need to get more information so people can know what he's doing. So, thank you. Mrs. Cuno. What my colleagues have said is absolutely, I mean, true.
The summertime program was something that, it was like a baby when I first started, and I know myself and Brianna Longo and George, but no matter what programs we bring,
forward, if it's not for the people that are actually working in those programs, they would never be as successful as they are. And it is very important to know, you know, when you have Teacher of the Year or you have different opportunities, it's just wonderful to know that when they have those opportunities and they are going to the conferences,
you bring Medford to the table. And there's a difference of just talking about it than rather than just sitting at the table and representing your city. And again, to Anthony and to everyone for that particular program, it was near and dear to my heart. So not that the other ones aren't, but this one here, I rolled up my sleeves and walked.
it's been very, very successful. And again, like talking about the programs that Heidi was talking about tonight, those were the piggyback programs that we were talking about because we had seen how successful these were. We have seen what the community is asking for and what we really need. And I'm hoping that these programs that we have, we've added a couple this year, and I'm hoping that by next year we'll add even more because it is something that our community is looking for. And again,
Our community is not asking for everything to be free, but affordable. And if we could provide those programs, especially in the summertime, and we have a place for our students to go, there's nothing better than that. Thank you. I think a lot of credit, I had a conversation with Mr. Belson about eight years ago.
And Mr. Belson said, one of the things he said to me was that he's done, in our eyes, he's done so much in this field. And he said, really looking at the community school piece and getting education, bringing it out, and making that a success is a big piece of his plan. I just want to commend you, Roy, because you know what?
Unfortunately, our city doesn't have a full time recreation program. And the work that you put in this and the opportunity that you've given to our coaches, our teachers, our vocational school to do what we're doing now is for our children. I think it's something that I've heard over and over next door, but now they're coming back. So it's a lot to do with that. So I just want to commend you as what you do completely is impressive, so thank you.
I just wanted to, actually, I can tell you it's a fine program. My kids actually go to the summertime fun program. They have a great time every year. They really enjoy it. Can't beat the cost. And they have a lot of fun. And they've met a lot of friends through it as well. As far as, so at the end of the summer, do we do any type of,
Do you do any type of communication with parents just to get their evaluation of how they felt the camp was? I think that would be interesting to see if there's anything that we can add, anything we can do differently. I don't know that we do, but it certainly can be done.
I think it'd be nice to reach out to the parents to actually see if there are ways to improve.
It's already a great program, but it's good to see. And actually, would it be possible at the end of the summer, actually probably in September, just to get like a follow-up report on each of these programs, just to see, just update us on the good things or if there's anything that needs to be addressed? Okay, we'll do it. Thank you very much. Any other questions from the committee?
Thank you so much. You're welcome. Thank you. You're welcome. Seconded by Mr. Scarpelli that the report on summer programs be accepted and placed on file. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? The report is accepted and placed on file. Thank you. Negotiations on legal matters, done. All business, done. Communications, done. Under new business.
We resolve that the Memphis School Committee express its sincere condolences to the family of Robert Delfino. Mr. Delfino was a former city assessor.
Be it resolved that the Medford School Committee express its sincere condolences to the family of Gerald Eisenhower. Mr. Eisenhower was the father of bed supervisor Joan Bowen. Be it resolved that the Medford School Committee express its sincere condolences to the family of Anne DiBenedetto. Mrs. DiBenedetto is a sister-in-law of school committee member Erin DiBenedetto.
Be it resolved that the Methodist School Committee express its sincere condolences to the family of John Jack Regan. Mr. Regan was a former teacher, coach, and athletic director. He was the father of Teacher Joan Cavalier. We all please rise for a moment of silence.
Mr. Superintendent, I believe you have a few announcements? There are a few items that I just want to cover with you, just so we're aware of them. I've given you some papers, just for your information, on the hot water heater at Columbus. We have it basically.
We did do some repairs on that, but the repairs are not holding. And we're going to have to work with the procurement officer to replace that as soon as possible. But in the next few days, there may be some need to use sanitizer and other things of that type until we can get it actually done. You have a paper in hand with regard to an investigation that we're underway. I'm not going to talk about it, but you've got the paper there.
The indicated minutes from the other night will be forthcoming very quickly, but we wanted to make sure I get back to each of you so that you can be properly recorded as to what your positions were. There was so much going on that evening that I took notes, but I'm not sure I got everybody's.
position clearly, so I want to make sure that you have an opportunity to comment to me so I can record them properly. A couple of other things on Friday, May 8th at 9 o'clock in the morning, the Family Network is having a legislative breakfast in the Family Network area. Mary Cassidy's group always invites our legislators to talk to them about some of the issues that they would like to see happening.
On Monday, May 11th at 6 p.m., the National Honor Society has its induction. It's Thursday, May 8th.
That's what the invitation says. May 7th, do you have it? No, May 8th. May 8th at 7. Thursday night at 7 PM. That's what was in our packet the last time. So it was changed. All right, it's changed again? Yeah. Well, no, no, Roy, that's what was in our packet when you gave it to us at our last school committee meeting. We each had a letter, and it said Thursday, May 8th.
And the 11th. I will check that out and get back to you. Right. May 7th. May 7th. Thursday. Thursday. 7th. 7th. May 7th is National Honor Society. Yes. That's what we're saying. I will check that out and be sure.
Right. So Roy, in terms of dates, you had the school council reports on the 11th. I'm going to clarify that now. Okay. Okay. Um, so I get to get the national on site because I have a different date in my book. So I'm going to get that out. Okay. May 13th school council reports. We have a meeting. I can't schedule. There's no dates. But you changed it from the 11th, which was fine. Let's continue. I had other conflicts. Let's continue.
May 20th, we're looking at before school programs. We're going to be talking about our initiative of before school programs. Diane's been working on that. I'm looking at May 25th and May 26th for meetings, committee of the halls. One to deal with tech and SPED. May 25th you said? May 25th. That's right.
Isn't that what? Isn't that Memorial Day? I'm sorry, not May 26th. May 26th and 27th, I'm sorry. We're working fast. So, 26th and 27th? 26th and 27th, yeah. What are you thinking of doing? One, having a committee of the whole on technology and sped together, you know, different things like that. So, instead of being in here, because those things are a little bit more complicated and a little more give and take.
And then maybe that week also having one on the public relations issue that you want to talk about. It doesn't work. That's why I'm putting dates out and I want to get feedback. So what do you have for the 27th? Yeah. No, is there a meeting on the 27th? Did you say the 27th also? Yes. So what are we doing on the 27th?
If I may really quick, so with regard to technology and spending, is that one meeting or two? That's one meeting. On the 26th. 26th, I think. You know, it could flip either way, whatever works. Public relations would be on the other day if we can do it. Now, again, I'm asking you about data because I've got to try and work it all in because there's a million things going on that we're
involved in as well. If I can. Could you send us those? Yeah. I mean, and just, and just then we can get back to you. Those should be actually stolen, what I'm just saying. Just send us those and then that's it. The Curtis Tufts graduation is coming in here. I'm not sure what the date on that yet. I'll get you that date as well. High school graduation is June 4th.
We got that, okay? Our next meeting is May 18th, the next formal meeting in here. And at that time, or next week, I'll be sending you materials on my evaluation and contract negotiations. So you'll have a chance to look at that and you'll be able to respond to that. Because of that evening, I would think we have some discussion on that. Are we meeting, all the meetings as a whole, are we all starting that at 7 o'clock? Most of them start at 7 unless you want to change the time. No, I'm just double checking.
Okay, you may know the state budget. It's being heard at the state house by different groups now. There's a lot of committee meetings and testimonies and hearing going on. The house has passed a budget. It's a little bit better for us than the governor's budget. The senate will be producing one in the next couple weeks. We'll be watching that to see how those things play out.
There were park forums all over the place, you know, there was four of those statewide. We're tracking those.
This week there's also a GBL meeting with the athletic directors talking about possible new league configurations. So there's a lot of things going on. I mean, that's why I'm saying every day we settle something, there's something else happening. And of course, we're negotiating with our teachers and all our bargaining units, and they're clamoring for dates to be available to talk. We had a meeting with the teachers today. So all those things will be in front of us, but
Some bad dates here, you're going to let me know. I'll put them out tomorrow again and just let me know. Our schedule is pretty tight. And I would think that sometime in June before budget, before the full budget, again, I'm waiting on the mayor to give me some guidance on when he's going to be prepared to go forward with the budget.
But I would think that we would then have a meeting in the US with regard to priorities sometime in early June. Plus, there's any number of retirement parties and things like that that are going on that are hard. So, Mr. Belson, can I just clarify that there's no possibility to hold any meeting on Monday?
It was that because you thought it was the National Honor Society? Well, it conflicts with some other things that are going on. So I just, I thought it was possible that we would conflict it. Right. I'm just wondering if we could have this subcommittee at PR on Monday. Subcommittee on Monday? Yeah. On the 11th? What? On the 11th you said? On the 11th. The only reason I asked-
Yeah. The only reason I'm asking is we had that date set aside and now, and I asked for that meeting months ago and now it would be thrown into a week where we already would have multiple meetings. It would make more sense if there is no other conflict to do it on Monday. I'll be happy to do it if you're prepared to do it. That works for me.
We'll schedule a subcommittee meeting of PR on the 11th, okay? Right now there's nothing on the 27th. Well, we can hold it in reserve just to be sure there's something else you want to do. I mean, there's so many things you want to do, as you can see from all the good things going on.
When do we schedule it? I mean, we certainly want to schedule a night sometime down the road to talk about the high school and the accreditation. I mean, you may have other things you want to talk about, too. So, you know, I'm just trying to work it all in, but I want to be respectful of your calendars because you've got a lot of things, too. But every day there's a bump on something, you know. Now, the other thing I was going to talk about, we talked about it briefly, Beverly mentioned it briefly, which was the issue with regard to the council reports, okay? School council reports.
We're going to try a format. I'd like to cooperate to try a format. The format is that you read these reports carefully.
list whatever questions you want to list instead of having a principal come in and read you everything that you can read yourself. And then, you know, we'll go around the room and we'll take 10, 15 minutes on the report, but you ask the questions and we'll get it. And then at the end of those reports or those questions, we'll then take like 15, 20 minutes to go over any kind of common threads or half an hour to go over common threads. That way we'll get through the meeting in a couple of hours.
rather than be there for four hours, as people read you everything you could read yourself. So that's the idea behind it, to try it as a format. If it works, that's a good way to go. If you find something that's really pressing, that you really feel you have to talk about, well, that's a different matter. Okay? That work? Sounds good. Thank you. Motion to adjourn, Mr. Chairman. On the motion of Mr. Skerry to adjourn, seconded by Mrs. Di Benedetto. All those in favor? Aye. Opposed? Meeting adjourned.