[SPEAKER_00]: Right now, teachers in Medford are rallying at City Hall after working a year and a half without a contract.
[SPEAKER_00]: WBC's Paul Burton is live in Medford, and Paul, I understand they have some new demands.
[SPEAKER_02]: I tell you what, Lisa, they were decked in red for education.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dozens of school teachers just marched right in here to Medford City Hall to deliver a letter of a vote of no confidence, both to the mayor and the school committee.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, Mayor Cohen was not actually here to receive that letter, so they taped it to her door and continued with the rally, letting their voices be heard.
[SPEAKER_02]: More than 100 teachers rallied at Medford City Hall late this afternoon.
[SPEAKER_02]: Today they marched right into the building to hand Medford Mayor Brianna Lungo-Cohen and the school committee their vote of no confidence.
[SPEAKER_00]: 94% of our members have no confidence in the mayor and the school committee to get this contract ratified.
[SPEAKER_02]: The teachers union has been without a contract for a year and a half.
[SPEAKER_02]: Negotiations are ongoing.
[SPEAKER_02]: The city says they've reached a signed tentative agreement with the union, but it's not yet been ratified.
[SPEAKER_02]: The rest of them are all here because we just want something fair.
[SPEAKER_02]: Listen, the city's, whatever situation they're in, they're in, but we didn't cause that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we just want what is rightfully ours.
[SPEAKER_02]: Teachers are looking for a 3% increase in compensation and better benefits.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where's our contract?
[SPEAKER_02]: Katie Perez is a fourth grade elementary teacher who says she's actually had to buy most of the supplies for her classroom.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I purchased all tables for my classroom rather than desks.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have a lot of students that come from underprivileged families, so that's buying their school supplies.
[SPEAKER_02]: Today the city released a statement saying, we always aim to do the right thing, especially for our hardworking teachers, which is how we have been able to reach a signed tentative agreement with the leadership of the Teachers Union.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are less and less teachers going in, less and less people going into the field of education, and we want to attract the best here in Medford.
[SPEAKER_00]: So in order to do that, we want a compensation package that is better than surrounding communities.
[SPEAKER_02]: Both bargaining teams will meet back here on Wednesday at 3.30 to go over that contract and hopefully reach an agreement.
[SPEAKER_02]: No talks of any strike.
[SPEAKER_02]: Today was all about delivering that letter of a vote of no confidence.
[SPEAKER_02]: Live in Medford, I'm Paul Burton, WBZ News.