Hello, everyone.
Thank you all for coming out tonight.
Right now, we're in the middle of feasibility study, so getting to know a new phase of the project and getting to know the site, the community, and really putting a plan in place for the rest of this feasibility study.
Our next submission is coming up in the end of June.
Very important during this phase, during the preferred schematics work phase, to get as much community feedback as we can on all these options, and that really, really starts here tonight in a very significant way.
So everyone will be facilitating a conversation in some way, shape, or form.
We have structural engineers, we have HVAC engineers, some folks are more familiar with different parts of the project.
So we had several visioning meetings for us as educators, administrators, to walk in the shoes of students through the halls and through their classes.
Some of the most impactful moments of this work that we did together in teams were from our students.
Really the purpose of this evening is to get some hands-on activity with the larger parts and pieces to understand what those relationships are.
Everyone should also have a voice and vision card.
It's like a postcard-sized document that if you don't have currently, we do have some around.
We also have a couple of non-English translations as well.
We have a priorities pom-pom table.
At that table, what we have is a series of glass jars with some of the major priorities that we've heard to date from the community.
And everyone, I think, has access to like three pom-poms when you visit the table.
You can start to just get a sense of where the community preference for the different priorities are.
A total of nine of those tables themselves grouped into the three alternatives.
We've done this with the building committee already.
We did it with the full high school staff on Tuesday of this week.
So we're trying to generate just heat maps of interest from the whole cross-section of the Medford community, just to understand where interests are, right?
It's not more or less scientific than that, but it is valuable to us to hear your feedback in terms of the different options.
We're looking to open the building in fall 2030.
The exact date is somewhat going to depend on which one of those 29 different options or what version of that we end up with.
Some of them are going to be able to be completed more quickly.
Some of them are going to take longer in terms of duration.
And then by June, we will go from grid five to one.
So sort of two sets of decisions where we are narrowing in.
The building committee meetings are open to everybody and you're all welcome to join us at those meetings.