So motion to start the meeting. We don't need a motion to start the meeting. We just have enough people that we have a board so you can get the meeting started. Meeting started guys. Okay, first order is administrative review of the minutes from June.
It's. I don't know why the previous one's not coming out on my email. Was it the last one? The last one should be on here. It's working for me. Did you have edits to it, Lisa? No. Oh, okay. You're just filling it out for reference. I also wanted to fill it out just in case. Does anybody have edits on it?
She's talking, but I can open mine over here for one. Yeah, did you have any edits to it? Although I didn't add anything now. OK. Great, do you want me to share? I don't think we need to. If nobody does, do it to the second one.
So we would just need a motion to approve the minutes. Yes. The motion guys to approve the minutes. I second the motion. All in favor? Aye. Aye.
Okay, so the 2nd. Order is the method connection. Yeah, well, we're administrative. Can we talk about next month's meeting? I was hoping, could we move it from it would be the 16th that we kept to our new schedule. And we move it to either the 9th or the 23rd. We're going to have family visiting that weekend.
9 to the 23rd. I think the 23rd is fine. What about guys? 9 to the 23rd. That works. Are those Mondays or Fridays? It's Fridays. Well, we have options for Zoom, just in case. OK. Yeah, it can work. But maybe it's not. Yeah.
So does the 23rd works for everybody? Yes. Okay. Awesome. Thank you very much for being flexible. And then one more administrative sort of announcement. I just, just for my office, we had four new interns start this month, all of them from Tufts. There are two undergrads and two grad students in the UEP program, urban and environment,
policy and planning, which is what I did. And one of them is really interested in the sustainability work that we're doing. So he's really digging into some of the projects that we've, that I've got going. So I'm excited about that because it means we'll be able to move forward with some projects that I've done on the back burner for a while now. Yeah. Like they've already started working on
doing a greenhouse gas inventory for us for this year, updating that, and the Harvest Your Energy Festival, the planning for that for October. All right, so that's all I have for administrative. The owl does make you self-conscious, doesn't it?
Yeah, the eyes.
The national night out and the Brazilian event. When is the Brazilian event? The 17th of August. And is that at Andrews? No, it's here. Changing the venue. It's outside. It's outside. Yeah. That's exciting. It's a wonderful weather.
just like today. It should be. What sorts of things are happening at the Brazilian event? So we're going to have the vendors, you know, we're going to encourage the Brazilian business to participate in local organizations and office. You know, of course, we count on you to be there, you know, with your table and teaching people.
And we can support you with whatever you need, you know, and our capacity, you know that day. But like it's more like to get everybody together to know a little bit of the culture of Brazil, and get to.
let the residents know that the population of Brazilians in Medford has grown, you know, and just like the Hispanic, you know, and Arabic, Haitian. So just want to make sure everybody's welcome and, you know, and you don't need to be Brazilian to be part of the event. It's a city event, so everybody's welcome. That's great. Are we going to have dancing there, too? I think that's been my favorite part. Yeah, isn't it cool you learn different, like, dancing?
Are there any other Medford Connects events coming up? We haven't gotten the lists yet. I know that they're working on it, Sophie and Catherine. I have a list of potential events for Medford. Let me share the screen here.
Can you all see that? Yes. Oh, now it's back. Okay. Yeah, so coming up in August, there's the Mystic River Family Fun Day is August 3rd.
What's that? This is the way that it's like set up. We should have something like that. I like. Yeah, I should. Let's see. Oh, and it's starting earlier than that. We were doing the Electrify Medford kickoff event July 31st, and it's actually happening this time. A press release has gone out. It's booked on the Mayors calendar. We're holding that at the library. It's a Wednesday from five to seven.
but I'm very excited we're finally doing that. I would love it if maybe you guys could come. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, that's a Wednesday, right? So then we'd have to like let them, let Sophie and Catherine come. So it could be there. So Brenda, you can update the date for the Brazilian day now. You put it early September. Yes. It's gonna be August 17th. Wonderful. It's city hall.
And you said it was, what time is it? 1-4. Awesome. Let's see what else we're doing. Oh, August 1st, we're going to have an Electrify Medford table at the farmers market.
Yeah, we are there every Thursday too, so with the Medford Family Network. Okay, that's great. I've only tabled there once before, and that was in June, so. Really? Yeah.
Yeah, so maybe we can be all together over there, you know, and take advantage of the kids and the parents right there with Medford Family Network, you know? Yeah, where is there, do they, wait, do they have a table every week or is it just on certain weeks? They have the space, they don't have a table, they have the whole space in front of where the band plays, you know? Oh, where the kids are playing. On the grass, yeah. Yeah, that makes sense. I didn't venture over there when I was table last time.
Um, yeah, we have the community table, which is up closer towards the street. Yeah, I don't know what mystic river family fun day is. I just, I just somebody told me that that was happening at my opportunity. I don't know if we have anybody who will be able to go there, but. I added it here just so we can keep track of it. Um.
And then in September, there's the Missing Rivers celebration on September 21st. You're not going to, you're not going to be at the night out? That should light up the. Oh, so I don't have a table for there. I signed up to wait for that. Um, but if you guys have a table there, can I, can I bring my stuff to your table?
I don't see why not. I mean, you're forgetting that we asked. YMCA, everybody come on board. Yeah, so maybe. Ask Sophie maybe. Yeah. No, because last year was just our office and the health department. No, but it's the YMCA Food Justice Council and we asked in person yesterday when we were here. Oh, okay. Sophie and Catherine, if they could have like share a table or have their like table next to us.
And they said, yeah, so maybe if anything, we can just ask if you guys can both share a table or depending on how it works, we can add on to it.
I mean, at the very least, we can just, I can just bring flyers instead of the whole big setup that I do. The setup's nice. Yeah, they love their house. The kids love their house. It's an attraction. That'd be good because that way people go there.
I liked your other games that you rented the other day. Yeah, I know. But the house is a great idea because people start recognizing, well, it's the table with the house, you know, where the lady talks about climate change. I'm serious. My kids always say that. That's great. The lady with the house. That's so funny. We'll be at the farmer's market again September 26.
There's Run Medford on the 27th and the 28th. I don't know if I'll be able to be there or if the coaches will be able to be there, but maybe. And then there's Tufts Community Day on September 29th. So I'm hoping to be there to talk to Tufts students who are generally renters about
Energy, I should say, and stuff. And then, sorry, going up through October 5th is Oktoberfest in Medford Square. And our Harvesty Energy Festival is on the 19th. Which is our big event.
Um, we do things like we do, we open up the inside of the wind turbine, so you can look up into the wind turbine. We did that last time, no? Yeah. Yeah. It was in October. Yeah. Last October. Yeah. Who was behind the raw at Loma Glen? Yeah. I was at Loma Glen. Yep. Exactly. I saw that. Yeah. It was really epic. It's always scary to go up there. So I like, I've never climbed up there. They're like insurance. Do they let you? Yeah. Okay, good. Yeah. I was going to say. Yep. Yep.
Oh, and one more thing I don't have on here is I'm trying to schedule a electric vehicle showcase here at City Hall. It looks like either September 7th or the 14th. Can I test drive? So what we're going to do is we're going to have people who work in City Hall and we're like energy coaches bring their cars.
if they hadn't been. And that way you'll get to talk to people about their own experience rather than talking to a car dealer who's trying to sell something to you. That's very true. Yeah. Cause they'll be like, Oh, that's the best thing in the world. Cause you have no idea. No, you need to be real. Like I, I, I panic every time I see like the energy down and I have to go find someone, a place to get, you know, charged. I have a hard time. We're also going to have e-bikes there too.
And I think we're going to have Blue Bikes to talk about their like options. Yeah. That's cool. I remember, didn't we have, it wasn't there before Blue Bikes. What's that line? It was line something. I didn't know you had those in Medford. I've seen those before. We have them. And that like, they don't be left around in my house or on my house. That's why I know, like, I don't need it. Yeah. But I think- They're in the docking stations, right? Yeah. Yeah, but people would live everywhere.
Yeah, that was the problem, you know. So did that company take over? I think they just pulled out.
Well, I think the idea that you have a timer for that, and if you don't return them, you keep being charged. I think that was the way they found for people to return the bikes to their, you know, whatever location they have their, you know, section. And I think that was helpful for the residents, because sometimes I will find in my street, you know, a bike is just sitting there, you know, on my sidewalk. I mean, what's going on over here? So I think they come up with a bad idea and took the business.
Yeah, I think they found some of those bikes thrown into the harbor. Really? What was going on there? Brenda, about the events, are your flyers multilingual? Do you need any help with translations with any of the new ones that are coming up?
Like the Brazilian event is coming up, do you have them in Portuguese that can provide those information in Portuguese? Do you need help with that? So we have the flyer, all of our Electrify Medford flyers in the different languages, in the four languages. And then in terms of like advertising for like the Electrify Medford kickoff event,
Like, I have a little flyer for that that is not translated, but it's also not going to be in a lot of different places. There aren't a lot of things happening for them. Yeah, so just keep in mind, if you have anything like that, just send it away, you know, like, so we can get that done. Oh, yeah. Let me jump into the... Sorry. Let me jump into the ElectroFanMet for updates if we don't have...
Any more events that we want to talk about? Okay. Let's see. Yeah, I think that's it for now. We're into our coming weeks. And you guys all have access to this document, right? I thought I sent it out, but let me...
So, I'm tossing it into the chat right now for the folks who are online. And then I can email it out to everybody. This is just an events calendar that I put together. Okay, um. For the elected by my from stuff, because the online city events calendar doesn't seem to be immediately quickly enough. Yeah. We have to plan ahead more than that. Um.
I don't know, but for me, I feel like it's so like, it's awesome to have like that in our calendar. You know what I mean? How we did it not for like the meetings or like, you see, go Climate Equity Council. These would be really nice to have like too. It might be a good thing for you to like take a look at these and see which ones you guys actually want to be at and add them to your calendars. Yeah. Yeah.
Okay, so for electrifying Medford. I am, so we have the intro flyers translated into the four languages. And the way we're doing it is, so we have one flyer that's in English on one side, and then on the back, it's each of the four languages just in a quick blurb.
directing people to the website. And then we have separate flyers with the whole thing in English on one side and then the whole thing in each of the languages, one of the languages. And we have four different versions for that. Do you want me to give you copies of those flyers? And would you like me to email them to you or give you printed copies? What would be better? I still have to edit mine and make some changes. Oh, you do? Yeah. Okay. Yeah.
on there about me. I think it would be nice for us to have, you know, if you could email us because let's say if we are in an event, you know, and you're not able to come and maybe you can bring to some and bring with us, you know. Yeah. Natasha and I are going to be next week. Sort of.
uh making like boxes for each of us so like for events we're gonna have good flyers and everything from all the stuff that we need so that way we're able to like go so that'd be good for you know any event that we need we have that there so it's great to be able to put it on and if you ever want printed versions and you can't do it here for some reason like let me know and i can get them for you
I'm also getting, we have that decarbonization roadmap, which is like the, all of the information and for each person that we speak to, we pull out the relevant parts for them into a document for them. We're getting that translated into the four languages.
And I got a quote back from Francis about it this week. More expensive than I thought. For all four languages, it's like $1,800. Because it's a long document. It's all of the information that people are going to be pulling from for the residents. But it's important that we have it in the languages, so I'm definitely going to do it. But I was surprised that it was that expensive.
And then we're also going to, I figured out how to translate the forms in Smartsheet, the online forms where people can sign up. I haven't done that yet, but I figured out how to do it. Basically, you just have separate forms that are all pointing back to the same document, and there's a way for you to have them going into the same fields, but there's a descriptor
thing there that you can change for each one. So the name of the field is the same, but the descriptor that people actually see on the front end is from a different language. Yeah. So that'll be good. Once we have this, that was the one thing that I was really worried about. I couldn't figure that out. So that's going to work. Oh, we've had 16 residents sign up so far.
which I'm excited about. I'm following up with them myself right now. And just for this first group of people to work out some of the kinks in the coaching process. But then after this batch, I'll start assigning them to coaches. And there have been people who I've talked to so far who are looking for help immediately. Either want to switch to a different electricity rate or find a way,
funding to help them with past year bills, um, or they're installing solar in their home and they want someone to help them like look at quotes that they got from installers. Um, and we have 12 coaches who finished their training. Um, and there are others that are still finishing it up online.
So I'm excited that we have so many who are trained up now. That's really exciting. Yeah. But we don't, I'd still like to get Spanish and Portuguese speaking coaches. We do have one Spanish speaking coach, but she's not, that's not her. She's not a native speaker. So I'd really love to get a native speaker of Spanish as well as a Portuguese. So she learned it. Yes. Yeah. And she's a social worker. So she uses it every day.
Um, but I would still like to get a native speaker. Yeah. So, if, you know, anybody who might be interested to speak Spanish or speaks Portuguese, please let me know. We still like, onboarding coaches as we go on. Do you have a. Where, like, we can send it to someone like the info.
Oh, yes, there's a sign up form for coaches. You're all set with Haitians. Yeah, yeah, yeah. I don't have it in front of me right now, but I will email you the sign up for just that. I don't know if you know, but we're. Chairman, I mean.
We're creating our own, like, Facebook page. So that way, like, we can, like. That's great. When do you think that will be on Wednesday? We have a meeting, so we'll see how that goes. Oh, a couple of things I noted down here.
Thank you for the recommendation to bring more to events in addition to the forms for people to sign up later. That was definitely more helpful. We're not collecting all of the information that we need to with the online form, but we are having more people sign up for it, so that's awesome. And we are in process of getting an Electrify Medford banner for events.
Moving on from Electrify Medford, curbside composting, we've had over 4,000 people sign up for the program. I have a question on that. Yeah. Is it too late to register people? No. Because I have a homeowner that I was explaining, so I didn't know anything about that. I'm not even going to read. Yeah. OK. That would be great. Right now, it is only for people in one- to four-unit homes, so sometimes people
might not have heard about it because they're in a larger apartment building or something but like a two-family oh no two families great yeah yeah two families don't work for this yeah in eight like five units or above the city considers that a commercial building and so the city doesn't do a waste services for commercial buildings um i have some door knockers like door hangers upstairs if you guys want to take some of the door hangers and
and distribute them, that would be really helpful. And there's actually, although I think if you're actually going to go door to door to put door hangers up, they would want you to sign up for like a street or something, but yeah. They have an online form if you wanted to sign up your street or something. You'd like to do door hangers on your street. Imagine you just go down the entire map.
take it out of there. I mean, that's what they're doing. Yeah. Well, I personally don't like people knocking on my door. So well, you don't have to knock on their door that you can just leave the door hanger. It's okay.
Yeah. Oh yeah. You don't have to knock on the door. That's what I'm afraid of. She's even afraid of my smooch. So after the meeting, like we can go upstairs and I can grab this for you. And people can sign up anytime. This is an ongoing thing.
Can you grab some extra so we can give it to us on Wednesday when it's here at the meeting, if you don't mind? Do you want the door hangers or do you just want flyers? I think the door hangers, I can give some.
Moving on to EV charging stations. So the police station charging stations are online. Those aren't public. Those are just for the police vehicles. But I'm really excited to do that. And the police are now looking, we're looking at grants to purchase electric vehicles for them. Not for the cruisers themselves, because those aren't really available right now.
But for, like, the detectives' vehicles, just because they drive so much that it's a really great opportunity to reduce the emissions from those cars. And we're also getting recommendations from National Grid for our entire fleet of vehicles. So basically, we send them our inventory of all of our vehicles, and they'll say, here are electric vehicles that we think will
Be a good replacement for this, so we're going to replace this. We can say, okay, this might be a good way to replace it. We don't have any right now. Like, if we promote it, we need to.
Yeah, I mean, staff have a lot of staff like, to be personally, but like, see, yeah, we do have that electric street sweeper. So that's good. That was our 1st.
Those things are terrifying. Stop it. I went in one time and then I was like, you know, he was like nine. And then I turned like I was getting salad and then I turned and he was like, mom, mom, turn around. Like, what's going on? I turned around and he was right behind me, you know, joking. I was like, I ran. I was like, bye. Look at the environment. It's just scary.
I don't know if the robots in the stores are not for the environment. They put faces on them. No, thank you. The last thing for charging stations. We're still waiting on National Grid to connect the West Medford parking lot station. So that has been installed for six months now or more.
just waiting for electricity to be connected to it. Then I think my last update is the school's HVAC project, the McGlynn and the Andrews replacements and then the repairs to the smaller schools.
We're still finalizing the contract with the designer for that. We just did a walkthrough of the schools today with the designer for an existing conditions assessment. And yeah, it's bad. There are lots of systems that have broken down and we're at least trying to get them repaired so that when students come back to school, they'll have some cooling in place. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
There's one time they didn't, they don't have a CVS, so they had to keep the windows. Oh, and it was horrible. My son would come up. I feel like they should invest in. I know there are affordable things you can bring in, but those are very expensive. So.
Um, there's a, there was a debate of, of, of, you know, if something does break down and we can't, you know, we can't fix it in time or something, are we going to bring in these portable things or what are we going to for those few days? But it's that hot when schools in session just have a, just cancel school. Yeah. Um, because they can have a personal, like AC. Like van.
No, like for the window, like, you know, the window that you see. Well, that was another discussion that we had to, again, very expensive and a very temporary solution. Yeah. Yeah. That's that's always the trade off. Something I was like, no, I was pointing at my hand. You know, we didn't get one. Yeah. I mean, they should and they should have it there for like, you know, when they need it. Like is this come on, Brenda.
Can you imagine having like 30 of those in a room? All you would hear was the buzzing. I know, right? That's true. I mean, yeah, I guess. I heard, so I thought it was in my head. I didn't think that. Because I wear it all the time, I don't notice it. But we're very close to getting that contract signed, so.
We should be starting the design very soon. And then starting, we could start some pre-construction probably next spring, and then do the bulk of the construction in the summer so that by next fall, not this fall, next fall, there'll be new systems in place at the end. There's a new one. I can't even read it anymore. I know. Yeah, well, we're trying to repair the systems right now, so you can laugh at that one.
Is it just for like these schools here or high school as well? Not, the high school hasn't been part of that project so far. Are there issues in the high school? For heating? I don't remember. I mean, for cooling? Yeah, I don't remember that. It would die. And it's bad up there. Like, it's right, like, you know, like tip of like a mountain, you get like the full effect of the sun. Oh, really? Yeah, like trees would be cool.
Well, the high school is going to be either renovated or completely replaced. So we're not replacing the heating and cooling systems now. Is there an update on that? Not that I have heard. They are going through the process to apply for the MSBA grant, but there's a sort of a
design process that happens before that point. So you're submitting what the design and the cost is for the data firms. So there's a committee that's working on that. And on the Medford events calendar, the meetings of those committee, that committee should show up on there. But I'm not part of it. And I haven't gotten any major updates.
I mean, I will be involved in the project once we get to that point in the process, but it's not at that point yet. They're talking about funding and the MSU grant and stuff. I think that's it for the city updates. Any comments, questions, anything on those?
Do you guys online? Coach Palmer, same question? No, ma'am. It looks like the Energy and Environment Committee update, isn't it? Yes. So yeah, so for our July meeting, we met at one of the members' homes.
And he did a tour for everybody of his solar panels and his heat pumps. And we got to talk with him about that whole process with installing those, in addition to our regular meeting. So that was fun. And the Energy and Environment Committee, one of the members, or some of the members, I don't know how many are involved, they're considering applying for Community Preservation Act funding.
to do a study of invasive plants in city parks. And the reason I think they're doing that is it kind of goes hand in hand with the pollinator garden project that they're interested in doing. So yeah, removing invasive plants and then replacing them with native plants that are good for pollinators.
And there was a rain garden planting project this morning, actually at Wright's pond where there used to be a rain garden there. And then I think somebody didn't realize that it was intentional. They thought it was weeds and they mowed it multiple times and destroyed it. Yeah. Well, cause if they're native plants, they like maybe, you know, that's intentional.
So they were replanting that this morning and putting signs up to say this is a problem. Can you imagine getting a knock on your door and being like, lady, be a lawn mower. I see it outside. You messed up. This happens more often than you think. There was somebody down along the river who was just weed whacking a bunch of stuff, which to be fair, he was weed whacking invasive plants there. Yeah.
But that wasn't, that's not the way that you get rid of those. Right. Yeah. Yeah. And he, the way he was doing it was going to cause erosion into the river. Yeah. Well meaning, but yeah. Yeah. They need to get educated. So that's it for the energy and environment committee.
So we want to discuss this year's priorities. Let me share this. Can everybody see that? Beautiful. Yeah. Wait, wait. There we go.
Sharpa, you went into it already. That's great. Yeah, I added those two things at the bottom. I don't know if they're relevant. But were they extreme heat zones? Talk about areas in Medford that experience increased vulnerability during extreme heat waves.
sea level rise and coastal flooding. You talked about flooding in areas of America that are susceptible to heavy precipitation events. I think we've looked at the maps of those before, but I remember we haven't really talked about what options can be shared with people. So is that what you're thinking, Sherva? Yeah, just thinking more about like, you know,
building social resilience and like offering people resources. If in case these like disasters were to hit, like what can people do? What options do they have? I know that there's the resilience hubs, but I'm just wondering if there's like other things too. Well, I mean, we're working towards the resilience hubs, but also in the meantime, what can be done? Yes.
Oh, one thing that I learned this week actually about sea level rise is that even if we're not impacted by actual coastal flooding because we have the dam protecting us from that.
We could be impacted by groundwater rising because when the sea level rises, it will come in underneath the freshwater and the groundwater because it's denser than the groundwater. So it'll be like seawater underneath, freshwater on top, and then it'll raise it up. So it'll go into like people's basements, it creates sinkholes, like they're seeing this in places like
Salem. I saw one on the news. Yeah, like House of Seven Gables, for instance. Yeah. Yeah. They're having serious issues with that. Screaming. Yeah. And I hadn't considered that before as a as an impact of sea level rising. So. Yes, I think it's one thing. It's another thing. So, yeah, so the priorities that we have in here right now, electrify Medford,
composting, stormwater education for residents. That might be, Charbel, that might be sort of the same thing as the sea level rise and coastal flooding. Just water issues related to climate change. I'm sorry, I didn't catch that. Can you repeat it? Yeah, so number four here,
And the fourth one here, stormwater education. It would be similar outreach work, I think, to sea level rise and coastal flooding. Right, right. I think those could be combined. Yeah, I didn't see that, sorry. We have school outreach, city policy, statewide policy, state, federal policy.
City building upgrades, city transportation projects, EV charging stations, blue bike stations, and then the extreme lead zones and the sea level rise and coastal flooding. So is there anything else that people want as priorities that's not on this list that we should add?
Let's see. Temperature. I'm saying let's see temperature. I mean, maybe I can't like see like the thing that's like so loud.
But, um, do they have anything for like, like thunder? Like, you know, like, you have like a horrible, like, thunderstorm. Oh, like power outages. Yeah.
Well, we have the big heat right now, you know, and another day I was going to the city hall, and I walked from the theater to the city hall, and I noticed that Medford needs desperately some more trees, more shade. You know, it's something that, you know, we're looking at because, man, it was horrible.
it will stop to find a shade at all over the area. I think one of the ways that you can get people involved in that, well, so there's Trees Medford that does a lot of work about preserving trees. And they also give out trees, I don't think, at least once a year, they actually give out saplings for free to anybody who wants them. So publicizing that, I think could be really helpful. And then
There's also things like the adopt a tree program where you can sign up to make sure that they, that a tree gets watered during the summer, like a new sapling that was, that was planted in the, in the sidewalk. You just reminded me of something. This is crazy. So next to my house, we had a tree and I don't know if it was my dad in the public city. Can you get it to talk about?
Is that okay? Well, I mean, obviously it's okay that we did it, but I'm saying like, you know, it kind of sucks. I liked having the tree there, but it blocked the house, obviously. Was it in bad shape? Like it was going to fall on it or? I don't know. I don't think there's a tree that would be in the way. But we still have one that's right in front of the house that still blocks the view. But we need to ask permission to cut a tree, right?
Yeah, that hasn't been passed yet though. Well, the tree ordinance I was, I looked in that into that after the last meeting. And there's an updated version that's going to be sent to city council. That's what trees Medford told me that they didn't have it ready yet. So they're going to send it to me when they do have it ready and I can share with everybody. Yeah, I know that you guys, I think it was you guys.
Like, you know how the sidewalks have like the little square that you, that they, that like, yeah. Okay. So that's the city thing, right? Yeah. So like on my street of the other, like a little further, there's like in the summer and like in the spring, there's like beautiful, like cherry kind of like cherry blossom trees are like white, pink, like, you know, are those like, or do you're saying tree trees, like green trees?
Oh, no, those are great. I think the city's policy is to try to have as diverse a group of trees that they're planting around the city as possible. Because in the past, I think there were issues, I don't know about in Medford, but in other cities at least,
issues where they planted one kind of tree, and then there was like a disease or a pest or something, and they lost a whole bunch of trees all at once. So I've tried many different kinds of trees as I can, but I just always wondered. I think Sonia dropped a lobster. Yeah, I don't know. I just thought that was like funny, right? Because like, well, you see normal trees, and then I saw like those trees, and I'm like, what? Why are they planted not the same ones, you know?
But it makes the, what's it called? The street look nice. Do you know what I mean? Yeah. So that is another plus that we should help. The aesthetic part of it. People are all about that, yes or no.
It's a tree that looks aesthetically nice. There's one tree that my uncle's trying to take off. I'm like, don't do that. It is blocking kind of like the second line. Yeah, you know that tree? Yeah, yeah. I was down in Georgia earlier this year. And there's a city, City of Savannah.
yeah the entire city is like full of trees beautiful yeah and you know you know it gets hot down there like hotter than here but it's like you don't really feel the the heat because the trees the trees everywhere and they like like the branches like uh they're like um i forget what they call the trees that's that's that's true there's not a lot of looking for like mystery
There's not a lot of like shade. Like, yeah. Yeah. And definitely in certain areas of Medford. Yeah. Yeah. Plus it would, it would be better if it would be good for like the, the pavement, you know, it cools the pavement. So, so that there's not as much like, uh, I guess, uh, what's the word.
Um, you're just like, you're walking on like just the heat island effect there. Right. Yeah. Yeah. Um, are you interested in talking to the tree warden about how the city makes decisions about where trees are planted and things like that? Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, I'll talk to her and see if she can make it to one of our meetings. The tree warden, that's a that's an awesome title. I know, right? The tree warden. You've been to the house. The whole, like, building is flowers, right? And it's like a ward. And, like, they use pollen for psychiatric stuff. It's a little crazy in there.
All right, anything else people want to add to the list? Where are we to make it bigger?
Maybe if I stop sharing it, just a second, I'll try to make it bigger and then stop sharing and then share it again. Just because my brain is on the last, you know.
It's kind of creepy being here in City Hall. It was so dark. It was like lights off. Yeah, I turned on the lights. Maybe the maybe the motion detector turned off again. I went in the elevator. I was like, I threw my flashlight. And then I ran into the hallway. I only turned the lights on in the stairs. Okay. Yeah, no. I was like, run!
Yep. Okay. Oh, my sister has a little compost like thing outside her house. It's crazy. I'm trying to get one of the neighbors. Okay, so if there's nothing else to add to the list right now, we can always change it in the future if you want to. But what is a lot of stuff.
What areas in particular would you like to focus on? With the composing, right? So they put food in it, right? Yeah, food waste. So what do they do with that? The process of composting is like basically it decomposes in a hot environment, like in a big pile, basically.
And then it turns it into into dirt, essentially. Yeah. So, like, one of the things with Garbage to Garden, which is what we're using, is you can order compost from them. They get a reduced rate from what they would normally be selling it.
use it in your garden. So is, because I just, I know he's going to ask me all these questions. Is there a specific type, like are they doing just veggies and roots and meat? So if you were doing it in your backyard, you could only do like fruits and veggies and stuff like that. But because they're doing it in a commercial composting facility where the temperatures get hotter, you can do meat, bones, everything. Yeah. Yeah.
No human bodies or anything like that. No, for real. How do you know, Brenda? So with the meat, can they put it in a plastic? Because they'll be like magnets. No, it has to be all like raw. Yeah, they'll do magnets and stuff like that. There are biodegradable bags. And so that's what I use to like line the inside of my compost bin.
So then they just take the bag out and the bin itself stays cleaner. My question is though, really, how do they know?
Like for real. I know, but it's crazy. Yeah. I've never been to a commercial composting facility. I don't know. Like how do they like value what they get? You know what I mean? Food waste, not human waste. You know, that would be weird. I know it's cycling. So Natasha, I mean, not here. I hope.
Okay, so sure, you put your name. With areas that you're particularly interested put my name on the trees. Yeah, and the trees. Yeah, me too for the trees.
Sorry, what did you say? The same one. Okay, with this city transportation, maybe I need to put my name on it because I don't like really what's going on here in Massachusetts. What, in particular, is it the train? I think that's always going to be an issue. Unfortunately, it's sad to say. It's hard.
It's affecting people's work schedule. Cause when you're, especially when you're working in the city, it's like, there's always an issue. You're being late to work. But that's like, but this is how I, cause I, I commuted literally all my life since 2018, 19 around there. So for me, like, I know that at the end of the day, it's all like, you're dealing with like people.
or, you know, maybe link to work or not even link to work, just like things like come up, you know what I mean? It's a human error. So yeah, it's human error, unless like a lot of it's underfunding, but well, that too, you know, so that that plays a part, you know what I mean? So it's like, every time there was a delay or something, I didn't stress about it because I'm like, at the end of the day, thus,
It happens. My boyfriend just started a job at South station a couple of weeks, near South station a couple of weeks ago. And his commute is either has been 45 minutes one day and an hour and a half another day. So he was like, how do I plan on this? Yeah. No, I know that happened to me too. It's wild. I think a lot of it is also just how like just the overall infrastructure of like Boston and how they handle like the traffic.
It's like very inefficient in some areas. Like in Cambridge, for example, like they make the streets so tight because they're adding like, they added the bike lanes. And that literally leaves like no room for the cars to like, like, let's say, let's say a fire truck was coming through or police car was coming through. There's nowhere the cars can go to let them through, which just causes more traffic.
i like the places where they have like the combo bus bike lane so it's a lane that's just for buses and bicycles basically and then the buses are able to move through the city faster yeah but i mean that only leaves one other lane for the other cars so
Yeah, there's pros and cons for public transportation. So I think the city is involved in boards and advocacy groups that try to advocate with the state to try to get better service for the T. For this, this would probably be more
related to city road projects. Yeah, exactly. Or, you know, bus stops, bus routes and things. So the city doesn't run the buses. They can't, they can't, they can't control the MBTA buses, but we do, the city does advocate for those too. And so that's something that's probably more
Specific that we can give feedback on is like, particular routes and things like that because recently I was talking to the transportation director here and he was saying that. Years ago, a couple of couple of years ago, I think they. Change the bus routes in in Medford as part of an overall, like. System wide restructuring of the bus routes.
And I think the city was promised like an express route or something like that as part of that. And like some things were cut back and everyone was upset about it, but then their city was also promised like an express route or something. And it doesn't, I don't think that's here. So that's part of life that the city advocates for, but the state is trying to get those sorts of routes. So that's fine. I don't think it's ever going to be as perfect.
than it should be. It's frustrating. When I first came to the city, I'm not going to say how many years ago, it was what? It's so much better than it is now. Yeah. Yes. And cleaner, I'm sure.
I don't know about that, but it definitely worked for me. I used to take it when I used to go to high school and that was many years ago. So anything else that people want to sort of highlight as areas that you want to focus on? I think the extreme beat films too.
Yeah. Oops. So besides the cooling station, what's there? I like the storm.
I think also city extreme heat zones as well. City policy. It's crazy because with climate change, you have to think of things that are immediate and then bigger picture.
You know what I mean? Yeah. Yeah. Like with the school HVAC upgrades, like we need these to be working. We need the AC to be working and the students come back this year. Yeah. But then we also have to do the bigger fix. So this is a bigger replacement assistance. You said the C-level res, what was the C-level res for? Yeah. I would probably combine those. I think that people would think of them together.
So. All right, does this look, does this look, the ones where people have actually put down their names, do these look like good high-level priorities? I'll still give you updates about Electrify Metro, but it sounds like we don't really want to be
involved in that. What do you mean? I didn't even see that there. What about school outreach? Yeah, we should try to get the youth into this.
Oh, only me? She just didn't put tab. So city building upgrades, I'll keep you updated on that and it sounds like you don't want to be actively involved in that. Same with EV charging stations and blue bikes, keep you updated, but not.
Unless I get one of those cars. Cool. And power outages. Oh, yeah. No, that one, yes. Yeah. I almost feel like that could be kind of combined with, you know, it's like extreme heat. Yeah, that's very, very similar. Power outages with heat, but it's also like when it's like
That's why you put it down with severe weather. Yeah. Yeah. Like the thunder, everything. Yeah. I think that that kind of goes hand in hand with extreme heat because the more, the hotter the air is, the more moisture it can contain. And so then you're more likely to have thunderstorms and things like that, hurricanes. Yeah. Okay. So I'll probably, what I'll,
do, I'll combine a couple of them that we talked about, and then the ones where, you know, more people have expressed interest and then we'll put them sort of at the top and then, yeah. Do y'all care about the transportation projects? Chabelle? I do. I mean, honestly, you could put my name for all of these. I mean, same. It just seemed like, it seemed like a bit redundant. It's a lot though. Yeah.
I'm saying more like, I'm just talking recency, recency bias, because of the heat, you know, so that's the first thing on my mind. Yeah, that's true. Can we can we talk about that a little bit, actually, because so I feel like the Office of Outreach and Prevention did some communication about heat, like cooling centers. I haven't been involved in those conversations. So
I would love to learn more about what is going on with pooling centers and what people can do. Verna, you have that list of events. Which one's the one? I don't know if you went to one that we did this year. That was for health. Do you remember the one that you couldn't go? I keep talking about it. That I couldn't go? Yeah. Charbel, do you remember the one?
where you met Jessica at the library. Remember when you met my cousin from Ecuador when she came? Yeah. Okay, do you remember in the library, what event was that? It had like everything about kids, health, us, like,
also like physical activities. There's some kind of a job fair, resource fair. But I have to do it. It's rather like counseling. Yeah. I know exactly what you're talking about, but I don't remember the name. Maybe if I check my calendar.
I was gonna say, if we had that, that would be perfect for it. We weren't there. Those resources. Yeah, you weren't there. This was like, when did my cousin come home? No, no, but remember my cousin, health and wellness fair. That was, it was March 30th. I don't know. And like what resources did you share around like,
So we didn't have that at the time, but that's what I'm saying. We had traction there, so that's a good, like, you know, people came in and we had like the passport, like a cage, where like they had to go to each like table and stamp it. So that way like they get like something or like, I don't know.
or like they're able to win something but point is like a lot of people kept going to all of the stations so that way you know you get your information yeah so that's like a good we should be doing that to be honest i know and like our event and stuff yeah because that way you're you're like the kids forcefully like take their kids their parents and stuff around the block and say like okay like we can give them like even like
You know, we're ordering like the stress balls, the pens and all that stuff. Yeah, anything like that. So I saw that there were three pooling centers right now, right? And there's the library, there's the police station, and there's... Where's the third one? Here. Is here one of them?
City Hall is not one of them. The library, the police station, the Western Community Center maybe? Oh, the senior center. The senior center, so yeah. But those are... How crazy is it that I just Googled this and it went up the city webpage, but
I don't know what it is that like, like residents ask us stuff. And I'm like, didn't go on the website. Yeah. Point blank. I mean, some people do, but the people who are asking. Yeah. Yeah. But like, sometimes like things are like, can't even open the tabs, like things, cause there's so much information. You know what I mean? Yeah. Yeah.
But none of those are open overnight, are they? No, so this one, the police one, is available 24 hours a day. The Medford Senior Center is from 8 a.m. to 6 p.m., and then the Medford Public Library is from 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. on July 26th, 27th, and then there's just certain times and certain days. In addition to visiting police centers, residents are encouraged to follow
other extreme hot weather safety tips. That's what they tell us. And then we actually have... People don't really use the cooling centers that we have set up. Or maybe because people don't know about it. Because I bet you a thousand bucks I go to my mom and my sister, they don't even know how we've lived here. And then some of them probably can't get there. Yeah. They're seniors. Yeah. People who don't have transportation.
Yeah. Sorry, we dove into a topic there rather than just doing the priorities. Sorry about that. All right, so did these, this is a lot of priorities, but we'll have it as a reference and we can kind of prioritize based on the number of people who are interested in something. Yeah. So you can do maybe like the ones that have three and then the ones that have two and then, yeah.
Cool. Okay. Anything else on the priorities? No, but can you share them with us in an email just in case we think of anything else? Yeah, I shared it with the agenda, but I can share the minutes and stuff too. Okay.
I think the only thing we have left is new business. Um, it says future meeting topic. Okay. Yeah. So. 1 thing that I think you've got someone had asked about it a previous meeting was doing like a condensed, like, electrify Medford coach training. Just to, like, learn about the technologies that. That we're talking about.
That would take up a meeting by itself though. Are you guys interested in doing that? Okay. I mean, it's one meeting. It's not like, yeah, a recurring thing. So I think it's worth it. Didn't we come up with ideas for the table too? Or are we coming up with ideas to like, get more traction? So like, people remember? Because we talked about the dollhouse.
And then like we were talking, remember I said something about the thunder? Yeah, yeah. Okay. Yeah. Oh yeah. I'm just saying where you're at with that. Yeah. I'm not very far with that. I'm getting the banner. That's as far as I am with that right now. No, I'm saying like, you know, sometimes there's weeks where we need more like hours, even though like right now for me, I have a lot.
That could be something that we can help with. Oh, yeah. That would be awesome. We should talk outside of this then. Yeah. And it sounds like you came up here asking the tree warden to come to a future meeting.
I don't know if the transportation director is going to have time to come to a meeting himself. It's sort of a one-man office. Yeah, that's crazy. But maybe I can get updates from him and bring them to future meetings and then bring questions back to him. Yeah.
Maybe give them an option to zoom in for at least. There's a lot of evening meetings too, so I think this thing might be like an evening meeting. Yeah. Anything else that we want to have to queue up for a future meeting?
Would you say that you might want to look at the school? About the school? About the school average? The HVAC upgrades? The heating and cooling system? Yeah, yeah. Are we getting updates from that from you? Oh, yeah. That would just be my opinion. Okay. Yeah. Yeah.
I'm working with the assistant superintendent on that. And the facilities director for the schools. Actually, and the city facilities director, because it's a big project, so he's getting involved, too. Yeah. Do you have a question? No. Charbel? I'm all set. Thank you. Cool.
Thank you. All right, so we need a motion to adjourn, if there's nothing else. Motion for the meeting to adjourn. Everybody? Motion granted. Yes, so Chair Beall, you're seconding? Third. Yes, that's unanimous. There are only three right now, so. Great, perfect. All right, thanks everybody. Thanks for Zooming in, Chair Beall.
Thank you. See you at the whatever the next event meeting. Oh, by the way, I was thinking I was speaking with my mom and we were thinking of doing like a like a potluck maybe in August on like a random weekend still talking about it, but
You, you all would would in theory be invited so nice to keep that in mind. I know we spoke about it last time. So, so like, would this be a committee or would it be a.
like just like you know amongst like you know co-workers we have at our house we you know be a nice barbecue everybody can bring some food it'll be nice you know and we can still do a potluck at your house too brenda
No, I was just wondering if this is going to be like an official meeting or- No, no, not official. Not official. We just thought it'd be nice to have it amongst like the co-workers and the, you know- That'd be great. I gotta say, I would be nervous bringing food to your parents. Oh, no, no. Their food is so good. Don't worry, don't worry. I'm sure you make delicious food too.
I think we're all planning to order. I know. So, yeah. Well, we'll see if it's going to be going on, but we, we, we would like to do it in August. Okay, that would be great. Yeah, let us know. Let us know.
Okay. Bye, everybody. Thanks, everyone.