So Deb, I know you don't have a vote, and I don't have a vote. Alex, do you have a vote? No. No? OK. The only thing I can do if we don't have a quorum, because it's been officially posted in the three cities, I need to read the notice of the meeting, which I'll do, and call the roll, and then see where we're at at that point. But we'll give it another minute not to hold people up.
I know a couple of members couldn't make it.
Well, in the hopes that people will join us, I'll at least read into the record the notice of the meeting to move that portion along, and then we'll see where we're at once I read this paragraph. So notice of the meeting. Notice is hereby given in accordance with Section 23A, Chapter 39 of the Massachusetts General Laws, that a virtual meeting of the Mystic Valley Commission will be held on Wednesday, July 23, 2025, at 2 p.m. On March 28, 2025, Governor Mara
Healy signed legislation extending certain COVID-19 relief measures, including extending remote meetings for public bodies. The same provisions which permitted multi-member bodies to meet remotely or convene in a hybrid manner have been extended through June 30, 2027. This extension allows public bodies to continue to meet remotely or to meet in a hybrid manner without a quorum of the public body physically present at a meeting location
as long as the public body provides adequate alternative means of access to remote meetings. This meeting will be conducted via remote participation. This meeting will not include in-person attendance by members of the public, but all effort will be made to permit public attendance in the manner specified below via remote access by internet and telephone.
Public access will also be provided by posting draft minutes and or transcript recording or record of the meeting on the City of Malden website at CityofMalden.org as soon as practicable after the meeting. Additional information and guidelines for the public can be found and it provides a team's link to the meeting. This notice, by the way, was also posted in the City of Medford and the City of Everett.
So there are five members of the Mystic Valley Development Commission, including an additional, here comes somebody else. I did just hear that there are, I think Jared and I think perhaps Jeff was also on another team's link. So let me figure that out. You know what to do, Alex, is the issue is that
Well you need to click on the link itself that's in the email that Deb sent and not on the Microsoft Teams link. She sent the URL. I had to. I didn't know how to deal with it. That's what I did. So that's what I had done and there's a few people on that call. I'm going to leave that call. I'll jump over there, Deb, and just let people know. I'll jump back in a minute.
Yeah, thanks. Hey, Tom. Hey, Jeff. We also have a guest, the Medford Community Media here. So what's been done so far, Jeff, is I've read the notice of the meeting, just to move that part along. And then we're waiting to see if members joined. Very good. Thank you.
Hi, Jared. Hello, how are you? Hi, Cheryl. Hi, Tim. Hello. Hi, Tom, how are you? Good, yourself? Good, thank you. Sorry about that. We all follow the same join the meeting now link evidently.
Alex, did you see Kevin Foley on there at 1.2? I saw that he was trying to- I guess it was when that calendar event got sent out, it automatically added its own one, so that's probably where- Yeah, Kevin was on the meeting with us. He was, and I forwarded him that link, so he should be arriving shortly. What would be the method up top, that method community media link? We've already asked that question. It's method community media. They're probably going to be
taping this. We told them if they are, they have to disclose it. But other than we started, we didn't start the meeting, but I read the notice. I guess we did. I read the notice of the meeting into the record to move that piece along. Hi Kevin. Sorry for any confusion on the link.
Um, so I've read the notice of the meeting into the record, which talks about the ability to do remote meetings under, you know, legislation with Governor Maura Haley. So, um, at this point I want to call the roll, um, because this has been advertised in all three meetings. And as you know, we need, um, five members of the commission present in order to carry out business. So I will start with Brianna Lungo Kern.
We'll note her as absent. Carlo DeMaria, mayor of Everett. We'll note him as absent. Justin Quinn, member representing the city of Malden. We'll note him absent. Colleen Mejia, representing the city of Everett. We'll note him, her, excuse me, absent as well. And Jared, yeah, I'm going to do this one. Is it Yajian? You got it. That's good.
Great, okay. You're here. I am here. All right. And Mara Haley's representative is in absence too. So not having a sufficient number of members on hand to conduct business, I think we need to, I don't know if we just table the meeting or adjourn the meeting. We're going to have to reschedule this meeting at some point, but I don't, maybe we table it until
The chair calls another meeting of the commission. I think that's appropriate. Okay. All right. So that's what we'll do it, you know, whatever time it is, uh, two 11, we're going to, um, you know, table the meeting because there wasn't a sufficient quorum until the chair calls the next meeting. Okay. Thank you very much. Thank you. All right. Thank you everybody. Thank you.