So this is the meeting of the Medford Historical Commission, Monday night, November 13th, 2023. I'll call the meeting to order at 7.05 p.m., just gonna read the governor's statement. On March 29th, Governor Healey signed into law a supplemental budget bill, which among other things, extended the temporary provisions pertaining to the open meeting law to March 31st, 2025.
Specifically, this further extension allows public bodies to continue holding meetings remotely without a quorum of the public body physically present at a meeting location and to provide adequate alternative access to remote meetings. Language does not make any substantive change to the open meeting laws other than extending the expiration date of the temporary provisions regarding remote meetings from March 31st, 2023 to March 31st, 2025.
So for folks who want to join us in the future, you can log into the city's website. Our agendas are posted there. Thank you, Dennis, for posting that. We usually post the Wednesday before. So we get all of our business in. Okay.
On the agenda tonight, new business, 56 Wareham Street. We're gonna receive the demolition application that we received two days after the previous meeting and make a determination of significance. Commissioners, I sent around the link, it's on the Google Drive. If I could have your acceptance of the demo application and then we'll go from there. Motion to accept the demolition application. Thank you. And a second. Second. Second.
seconded. I'll go around the room. Roll call vote. Jen? Yes. Peter? Yes. Kit? Yes. Doug? Yes. Jess? Yes. And that's it. That's everybody. So it's approved. Five to zero. I'll take a motion to kick off discussion of determination of significance. Motion to find 56 Wareham historically significant.
And a second. I'll second. All right, Jen, you've got the floor. OK, thank you. In reading the form B for me, I actually wasn't
I wasn't overly enthralled with the description of the house itself, or the narrative in terms of it being overly interesting and in either section, and I did look at the Google map.
I really wanted to just take a look at the streetscape to see how the property fit in. Certainly, I think Wareham, we could probably all agree is a little bit of a mishmash of two families, single families, triple deckers, it's a little bit all over the place.
However, I do think it is significant based on the age alone of the property and we have such diminishing resources of pre-1900 buildings that I am going to vote for significance on this one. And I will leave it at that. Thank you. Great. Kit, do you want to continue the conversation?
Well, I think Jen just said exactly what I was going to say, which is, you know, especially this, the stock of, well, two things. First of all, sort of the landscape from the street, the streetscape.
And I recognize Wareham is a mishmash, but it's going to become an increasing mishmash if we actually don't take some steps to limit that. And then the second thing is, I think there is such a diminishing stock of houses of this nature in the city. I mean, we can't just be tasked with preserving only the largest and most
sort of elegant homes. I think that there is, you know, these are like the starter homes for the next generation. Great. Peter? Well, I just walked down the street on Google Maps and I think I agree it is a mishmash. It's one of the smaller homes on the street, I believe.
I think it's kind of a charming house. So I think, and it does have some excellent detail, although not in great repair. Seems to have pretty early siding, if maybe not the original siding, and it has some nice detail on the columns, on the front porch and stuff. So I think it's worth a pause to consider.
Peter, how was the condition from the exterior since you walked by it? I'm curious. Well, I only walked by it on Google Maps. Oh, sorry. You said you didn't say that. I apologize. No worries. But yeah, I mean, I'm just zooming in on this front porch here, and it does look like there's rot and stuff, but, you know, on the base of the columns and stuff. But I mean, all in all, it's not in bad shape for
how old it is, has nice brick foundation and stuff. So I think it's worth a pause. Um, I think there are quite a few of these end houses around, maybe not on this street, but I don't know. Um, I thought, and I, I kind of agree with the other two commissioners that I felt like it was, it was a pretty interesting story and design, but not like, um,
outstanding in its architectural or historic interest. Kind of like a common house, I felt. Anyway, that's all for me. Great, thanks. Doug? Yeah, this one's a little tough. I'm actually on the other side of this one. I understand that I wouldn't, mishmash is a little negative term. I guess I view eclectic because it's just, it seems like
Every decade of the last 15 is represented somewhere on that street, you know, which is not uncommon in South Medford, I think. It's a lot of change. But I couldn't, you know, I know this one's looking for a full tear now. They're not looking to make it bigger, build on the foundations. I think they're looking to tear it completely down and build two townhomes, which is, I haven't seen any drawings, so I can't judge on that, obviously, but I'm not a big fan of that.
This building is awful small, and I struggle to see how it rises to the level of being perfectly preserved. I understand the pause is probably not a bad thing, so I'm not unhappy that the other commissioners are looking to kind of pause the process here. But right now, I'm on the other side of this. Thanks. Jess?
Yeah, the form B says that, you know, the house retains original or early building fabric. But it also doesn't recommend for listing in the National Register, or really seem to, I think, put forth an argument for preservation. So I think I'm with Doug on this one.
I just wanted to say that I looked online to see if there were any interior photos and I didn't find any, not that that really matters, but I was more curious. And that I think if just personally, if we were voting for preferably preserved status, I don't think I would vote to preserve it. I do think it's worthy of significance.
But I also think that density in this neighborhood with the T nearby and whatnot might make more sense for the lot. But I do think from a significant standpoint and it's pre-1900, for me, for right now, that's what I'm looking at. I would be curious to hear if it goes to preferably preserved status and the public comes out, what would they think?
Right, I think I think that's the goal right so our job is to determine whether or not it's significant and then let the let the public decide with us whether it's in the interest of the city of Medford to save, you know, if all of a sudden, you know, somebody said oh we have a proposal to do to townhouses and they're going to be affordable or something like that that might be different than just simply maximizing the number of units that you can put on this lot.
This house reminds me of the little one on Cotting that we lost however many years ago. Was it 15? I don't think it was that long ago. It might have been less than five years ago. It was before COVID, which feels like 100 years ago. Fifteen years or 15 street address? No, I think it was 15 was the number.
Remember that little one, the worker's cottage? It just reminded me of that. Different neighborhood, though. You raise a good point, Shannon, that it's the small in-houses that have the set kind of half-floor framing, that don't have a lot of headroom.
Unless it's an architectural gem, we tend to let those go. And you're basically saying, we should think about that because then we'll have none left eventually. And I don't know, Ryan, you seem to have these kind of factoids at your fingertips all the time. I mean, if you had to guess, do you think we have 10 of these houses, 50? What are you thinking we have left of this type of building?
Yeah, well let's let's start with the numbers right so there's less than 2000 3000 pre 1900 buildings of the city.
maybe let's just say on the safe side, like two dozen, three dozen, maybe good stick, this is a stick style house. So it employs a number of architectural elements. So it employs the knee wall construction that was popular from the 1850s onward. But unlike the knee wall houses, this actually has a wider base. And so as a result, it actually has a full third, like somewhat
full third floor under the gables, which is cool and unique. That's the Victorian era pushing the limits of architectural construction because they literally have a floor that's being supported by the roof trusses that run down. Then they incorporate all these different mishmashes of things attached to it. They have a rear L, they have a front and side bay, off-center projections.
The other thing I noticed about this house is the dormers break the E lane line, which is, I don't see that much in Medford. No, and you often find with these littler buildings that because they're smaller, they can get more ambitious in their architectural detail. So the bigger the building is, the more that person has to spend on money. So in this case, they had tiny areas. So they put the details in like the front porch. And maybe this had,
more detail. It looks like it's probably been recited once in its lifetime probably, but, you know, it still resonates in terms of its massing and detail. You know, you might actually find that the original detail is probably still intact and they may have just gone over it, which was the case of 17 Edwards where they just applied a siding over the original. So,
You know, they're rare and diminishing. I think this one's actually in a really good state of preservation. I don't know what the inside looks like, but I would like to probably, you know, maybe we should do a site visit, right? I don't know if the building's occupied, but if it's not occupied and it's just sitting there, maybe it's time we do a site visit again, you know?
There are some interior shots, but I think they're from like 2005. They're like 11 on maybe Zillow. Yeah, I looked for a recent sale and I didn't see anything. I don't think there was one. I think a site visit's a great idea, Ryan.
Yeah, I mean, I might feel differently about this one if we actually had a plan of what they're proposing to do, because it sort of seems like if what they're thinking of is something that actually kind of maintains the character of what's there and sort of builds off of it, like, I totally agree with Jen about the density of that particular neighborhood.
It would be great if if whatever those townhouses look like we're actually in keeping with with what's already there. I can so usually what they'll do kit is they'll take existing plans of something they've already done and just redo it. So I would look at.
Probably not clearly, but look at Jerome, look at Washington Street. They just did something interesting on Washington Street. 69 Jerome is their project. They're doing two side-by-side townhouses on High Street. Again, I don't know what the width is here, but I would bet what they did, I would bet their project on Washington Street or Jerome.
they might replicate. I mean, we can ask Sid, he would probably just tell us, but they usually don't stress too far from something they've already done. Nobody's here from the proponent, the owner or the developer.
Looking at the interior photos even though they're dated if they haven't got at the house which judging by the condition of these photos I seem to be in okay condition there are things present from the outside, also present on the inside the door casings moldings the banister the bath dual posts, all the typical things, some radiators.
window casings, all those seem to be intact. So I think you'll find that this building is probably in good condition inside and out. They're just simply, it has problems with the roof line and things like that, that they would have to completely demolish. So at that point, you just down to a roof and at that point, you might as well just go all the way, which is why we're facing full demolition at this point.
We can certainly ask, well, we can certainly look at the building and see what we think, whether we, you know, think in advance of the next meeting, whether we, you know, what we want to say. So, okay, anything else to add on this one? Only other thing I would add is that I don't think there's anything remarkable about the sheds or the garage.
I think it's a cinder block, right? Although it has siding on or sheds kind of siding on the front of that. I don't think it was like a carriage house or anything like that. No, they look like there was an extensive carriage house out in the back of this building at one time, but I think that's all been torn down. Yeah. So great.
If nothing further, we have a motion on the table to find for significance made by Jen, seconded by Kit Nichols. I'll go around the room, take a roll call vote. Jen? Yes. And Peter? Yes. And Kit? Yes. And Doug? No. And Jess?
Yes. You convinced me, Ryan. I'm malleable. Ah, nice. Thank you. Great. So building's been found significant. So next month, we will have a public hearing provided that the owners meet the sign requirement posting and the legal ad posting. So we'll send that out to the owner. So, Jen, I would appreciate some help getting that together for
said we can reach out to him for a site visit. Is there a day people can do site visits over the weekend? What do people want to do? I'm flexible. I know in the past we've done early Saturday morning, but I'm flexible. Yeah. If I schedule it for early Saturday morning, the Saturday or something like that, maybe I can take a bunch of photos, upload them afterwards and point out some things. Yeah.
Jen we can include that with our. Yeah, we can ask let's ask if there's a lockbox there or something and if we can just they might just say go at your leisure and we can plan time. Okay, great also to see if there's lights and power there too that will make a difference. I would yeah. Okay, great.
So next up on the agenda, I have here noted that 69 Court Street, the demo delay public hearing is tabled because they did not meet their sign requirement as listed in the demo application. So we just want to make sure we can update the legal language and make sure we get that to the owner and re-send the sign information over so that they can get going on that and post that so that we can get a picture of it, get them going.
Discussion pertaining to Peter headland, and the next meeting regarding Thomas Brooks Park so Peter asked were under contract to begin the work on the archaeological cap that will sit on top of the Thomas Brooks house site. Once the.
next archaeological dig, which hopefully will be funded by CBC, is complete. So Peter had a question on whether it made sense to meet with the whole commission to start to get a direction for what that might look like, what things people want to see for direction, and he wanted to see if we wanted him to come to the next commission meeting in December. I know we have two public hearings, so we could take care of him first before the demo hearings.
if that makes sense. Ryan, can we talk about what the range of possibilities is? Because it's not like we're starting from zero here. You guys spent a lot of time really thinking about that park, and there were multiple phases, multiple options, multiple designs. What do you think the purpose of this conversation would be exactly?
This is to get like more ideas of the type of thing, it's a little bit more zoomed in right so we have a general understanding of what we want to happen with the park.
know what does it look like what is its function other than just simply protect the the site what sort of elements would you want to create uh i guess and almost in a like an amenity or an attraction to bring people to that site right that's one of the goals of cpc is to create things or that celebrate medford's um
you know, unique place in American history. So this is this is a perfect example. And Peter's looking for maybe I gave Peter some loose ideas, you know, starting with what's already been done. But, you know, you guys may have other ideas, like I guess we'll start with.
Like going out and finding parks and places that you guys find appealing that celebrate history or celebrate something and and bring a picture or something that or a tidbit or an idea that Peter can use to kind of
bring into Thomas Brooks Park? And Peter's going to start with the park itself and all the elements in there, right? So there's things on the site, field stone, brick for materials. There's the trees. But then, you know, what else do we want to bring in there? You could bring in granite from the Middlesex Fells, you know, and then how does that celebrate the person's events that happened there, that sort of thing.
So that's really what this is. This is really the defining feature that will tell people what this park was and what it's protecting and why it's important to Medford history. Okay. I think after hearing that, and I agree with you, there's a lot of different directions that park can go and having a conversation with him makes a lot of sense to me. So it's going to be the first of
I think several conversations beyond the MHC obviously to have that be effective.
Yeah. And this is just a start to the conversation. And then there'll be a public meeting with feedback. And I'm sure there'll be, I told Peter, the commission will take his design and we'll take the feedback back and forth with all the persons, stakeholders, et cetera. So there'll be some meetings where we're, you know, presenting the design, defending the design, incorporating feedback, that sort of thing, you know, and then.
uh he'll take it back and make final revisions and come up with like a final solid concept for ideally something that can a contractor can use to price out so that we can look at pricing grants etc in the future is there anything that it cannot be
So the only restriction is that, what did Roberta say? It can't be sort of a designated memorial, but a memorial meaning, I think like, like statue maybe kind of, you know, like that it could incorporate like interpretive panels and a plaza, but, you know,
It could have some kind of signage or something. Yeah, yeah. Or a fence or something. It can't formally be called a memorial. Its function is an archaeological cap. So for example, if you go down to Charlestown and look at the Governor Winthrop House site that's there, that is a low-key, flat memorial that
even though it was destroyed by the big dig, it replicates the archeological site that was there. So, and if it were still there, it would protect it because it's capped, so. Can he bring like photo examples of what others have done or? Yeah, well, I think, I think, yes, and I will bring, yeah, I'll bring some things so we can share and kind of give a direction, that sort of thing.
So I would say maybe one of two ideas, A, maybe have him come at eight o'clock so that we can get the public ones out of the way. The other option is, does it make sense for him to come in January instead when we won't have any preferably preserved hearings at night? Well, I guess I can't say that for sure unless something comes in next month.
Um, yeah, I could ask him, we're not going to formally start the project until January anyways, because of his scheduling. So that might actually work out better for him. Now give us a month to kind of get our ideas together, put them on the table. So and then say in January, come to the meeting, we have some ideas. Here's some, here's a bullet point list of everything that we've thought of. Yeah. Um,
just then we can keep next month's meeting focus on the demo hearings. And then if we get something new in and we have to determine significance, it could end up being a busy evening. Yeah, Jess, you're still allowed to participate. Thank you. You're welcome. You're welcome.
Okay, great. While we have- Speaking of. Yeah, while we have a pause between all this, we're being shadowed by a potential commissioner candidate. Jen and I met with Aline Glicas, who is down in the lower corner on my screen. She is a Medford resident. She is the Director of the Historic Preservation Program at the Boston Architectural College, still, right?
Yeah, so she's interested in joining us for the new year, and we'll fill the vacancy left by Jess, who will be leaving us at the end of this year. It's her last term, sad. Bad days. I'll miss you guys, but I'm sure we'll be in touch. I hope to work with you. Yes. And in many other capacities. Are you gonna be picking up some things in Malden?
Maybe. I'm thinking about, I want to find out when the Library Board of Trustees is, like, how to get on to that. I think I want to do some library work in Malden. Yeah. Nice. Oh, exciting. Dora St. Martin is awesome. I believe she's the library director. So, yeah, she's, I've worked with her for a number of years, and she's good friends with an associate of mine, so.
Well, good, that's a good endorsement then. I'll be excited to dig in a little bit more in Malden. But yeah, I am planning to use the time that I get back from this meeting to put in the Malden. Great. Yeah, so. Yeah, we had a great meeting with Eleni and we wanted to invite her here to meet everybody and she is,
willing to step into Jess's place, assuming that everybody approves her and the mayor appoints her. But we thought we'd have her come and introduce herself. And if anybody had questions for her, we had a great call, not call, meeting last week. It seems like it was two weeks ago. It was only Thursday. All right, so hi, everyone. My name is Oleni Glegas.
I am a newish resident to Medford. I moved here about two years ago. And yeah, I was excited to get the email from Ryan and Jen about the spot opening on the Historical Commission here. I have been working at the BAC for a little over eight years. I've been Director of Historic Preservation, Director of the Historic Preservation Program, which is a graduate program the whole time.
I haven't really had a chance to get much involved with local preservation work. Now that I moved out of Boston and moved here to Medford, I'm excited for the opportunity to contribute in my local community. I just love living here and I just think that Medford has just a wonderful urban fabric between the older buildings, the different types of neighborhoods, the street grid, and a lot of the historic sites. I really enjoy it.
I loved hearing the discussion about Wareham Street. Just from looking at the exterior photo, it's hard for me to tell, but if you don't mind, if I can join on the site visit, I think it would be interesting for me especially to see the interior of a 1880s home built in this era. Does anyone have any questions for me?
How are things at the BAC? It's been a while since I've been. We're doing okay, you know. Yeah. So yeah, the architectures program is growing quite a bit. Um, but, uh, and Ryan was one of our first historic preservation program graduates. I think he was in the first graduating class, which is pretty amazing. Um, so yeah, it's nice to have another representative from the BAC here.
But yeah, everything's going great down on Newberry Street. That's good. What neighborhood do you live in Medford? I live on Stearns Avenue, south Medford, close to Tufts. Got it. I think we're pretty close to accomplishing a diverse range of Medford neighborhoods. We might actually be a good cross-section of Medford. Oh, yeah.
I know it's so rare. Yeah, yeah, it is. And we all have, you know, diverse range of backgrounds. And, you know, I think the Commissioner, this is a good group of people. So not to toot our own horns, but it is. So any questions for us on processes so far? No, I think Ryan, you and Jen covered everything pretty thoroughly last meeting.
And, you know, again, it was interesting. I know the agenda was a little light this time, but it was interesting for me to see kind of like how the discussion works. And, you know, it doesn't sound like anyone from the owner, property owner, architect or developer were present at the meeting, but... To be fair, they usually do come. Yeah. So...
maybe they were, they just got busy, but you know, and also I'm not sure if they, did they realize we changed our process a little bit to do application and significance the same night? Well, I, I had the form, I had the form B, so because I knew it was coming and they told, they gave me the courtesy of telling me it came. So they benefited from the fact that they said we're submitting our paperwork early.
So so that worked. So as long as I'm told ahead of time or Jen's told ahead of time in the email that something's coming, we can get the form B and just have it there on site. So.
But it's not going to work every time, but most of the time. Yeah, just to give Eleni some context. So typically it would be like application comes in and 30 days and we have significance and 30 days demo delay, but we're trying to help expedite the process to some degree. So if we have a heads up that something's coming in or we already have a Form B, we can kind of
accept an application and make a determination the same night we've come under fire or the past few years of like our process takes too long. And so we're trying to, you know, we hear people and trying to make some changes on that front, which I think, you know, are working. So, yeah. So I think in Sid's defense that they are usually here and they typically participate.
Yeah, they've been good to work with this particular developer. They've worked well with us on other projects. Nice not to have people scream at us. It's been a while since that happened.
Great. Well, welcome. Do we need some vote, Ryan? Let's wait until the end of the meeting to see how she feels about the rest of this. We might do something to scare her away, but I doubt it. And then once we have that, we can make a recommendation. Ryan, we should have started to do the end of year composite of all the votes we took. There's a nice
Oh yeah, newbie gets that job. And she can have a nice summary of, she'll have to read all of Peter's minutes, which are greatly compiled and very helpful. And then she can just compile everything and be caught up to date. A year's worth of information in about 10 minutes. I was kind of joking, but that's fine. No, no, I think that's a good idea too. Plus I, you know, I have all the things. Jess, did you mark up or want to keep your copy of the commissioner handbook?
I did not mark it up. I guess I don't really need it. I know where to find that stuff on the drive. I still have access to that probably.
Yeah, I could give you digitally. So maybe we can swap that out just to save me printing it all out again. Yeah, it was such a nice binder. I was so impressed. I'll definitely pass it along. We're the only board in the city that has a how to run the board book. So I told the mayor, I highly advise you to advise all your boards to have it, but it hasn't happened yet, but it should. I mean, I don't know, Doug, do you guys have a CPC book on like, if Roberta got hit by a bus, people know how to run the board?
Oh, that's Teresa. She's the one who's in charge of that. I suppose. Having the paid help helps. Yeah. Yeah, I mean, you know, and this one just, what's nice about this is that it has all the how we determine significance, how you determine preferably preserve, that sort of thing, so. So the mayor is going to set it up. I'm sorry, Doug, I missed that.
the mayor to sign off on it is we can make this vote. We need we have to give. Yeah, we need to recommend her to and we'll send her a letter with her. And ask ask the mayor to appoint her. And the mayor ultimately has just final decision. Yeah.
Ryan, before I forget, I was thinking before we started tonight, you and I need to make sure we update like our slate of officers, the terms, like our meeting dates for 2024, like just that end of year stuff that we normally do. Yep. We should know better. If anybody's thinking of running as a board officer, chair, vice chair, secretary, et cetera, wants to keep their existing roles, just reach out to Jen or I.
And we should put that on the agenda for next, I know it's either December or January, we usually do it but at least run through our meeting dates for next year so we can get those on the website and in the calendar. Yep, can do.
And also I feel like we need to look at all the terms because the records that you and I have in terms of term ending dates doesn't match what's on the city website. Yeah, we got it. It's a hot mess. Yeah, city website doesn't always track. City website is a hot mess. I always tell people that whatever I tell them to appoint it to do it because I know how to stagger the board. Right. Required.
So anyway, we have to figure that out with whoever at City Hall.
Yeah, okay, we'll work on that. I haven't technically been appointed from last year and I'm not following up because I asked and they don't do their jobs, so I can't be held responsible. And I was told back in the day that if you're not replaced, then you just keep going in perpetuity. So if nobody had, if Jess didn't resign, she could have kept going in perpetuity.
We all know that she's running to Malden, so. No, I want to keep my speed and then kick you off, Ryan. Oh, might need an election. Okay, that's fine. It's a coup. That's right. Okay, that's fine. Are you a rogue commissioner? I'm a rogue commissioner? I don't know. Yeah, I guess so. She's following in the Malden-Medford rivalry tradition, yeah.
I don't know, I already have a cool nickname, Preservation Man, so I don't know if you can defeat a superhero. Was that your Halloween costume, Ryan? I want to see that. Yes, I just ran around saying I'm Preservation Man. I have one of those silly little memes like, what people think I do and what I actually do.
All right, great. We'll move it along. Okay, moving on. We'll circle back to final appointment at the end of the meeting. So, real quick, any other new business before I move on? Okay, hearing none, moving on. Properties currently under demo delay. The only thing is the barn, haven't heard anything from 91 Waychester. So, not sure if we're going to hear anything on that one.
Yeah, that was it. I forgot to remove permanent subcommittee report. We don't really have anything at this point, right? We're just waiting for some new people to be hired, like a new building commissioner. Yeah, in fact, I was thinking today I should just touch base with Bill. I know he's there like internally and just, we can check with the, now that the election's over, maybe ping the mayor and see if they're making any progress on a building commissioner. Yep. Okay, great.
Um, CLG report, haven't made any progress on it. I'm working on it, but that's before, not before I close out the, uh, survey and planning grant, which is, um, we're just waiting on product, but I have to get some paperwork into MHC for some stuff that's time sensitive before December. So that's going to get done tomorrow. Um, Cross Street Cemetery, uh, I pinged MassDOT today for my public records request. That's two months overdue. Um, I reached out to the,
appeals person for them because if they don't respond within 10 days I gave them 60 because of how extensive the request was that they're supposed to answer that person and they did and they responded to me they don't have anything on the cross street cemetery in terms of what happened and what they did back in the day I think there are records but they're probably no longer in their custody so I just I'll
push the Alicia's office now and the mayor's office to fund the PAL report because PAL will chase down where those those files are. So the goal is to have PAL prepare an archaeological summary for the existing Cross Street Cemetery parcel so that before any development happens there they do some legwork to determine if there's anything there, period.
and go from there just to avert a potential PR disaster. We want that project to be good. Same thing with the headstones. I haven't done anything. Thanks, Jess. I appreciate it.
I haven't done anything yet, but we're waiting to see if we can get some good weather so that they can test whether or not there's a, they think what they did was they poured the headstones into a cement base and didn't put them into a normal slotted concrete base. And if they did that, it will make the stones virtually impossible to repair. If they didn't do that though,
work is infinitely easier and it's a completely different proposal. So the consultants are still back and forth with that. We're hoping to wrap that up by next month. CPA, I hear you guys are going to be meeting with proposers. So we're going to be invited to one of the meetings, right?
Ryan have you. I mean one of the knees is tomorrow night which I think we've gotten a formal invitation so I the second one is 2 weeks from tomorrow at 28 so that's probably it I think the first one is mostly. City departments which I don't think we can if you haven't gotten the invite that we I guess we're not in that one but. It should be in the 28th year you should you don't have anything for that.
I haven't, but I can go tomorrow. So maybe I'll reach out to Teresa and just say, did you just forget to invite me? Because I'm happy to, I mean, even if you guys kind of finished early, I'm happy to sit there and listen and just tuck in quickly. But if it's not on the agenda, it's not on the agenda. Let me text her right now and see what the deal is. Okay, great.
So survey and planning grant, just real quick, I said, we're trying to wrap that up. I'm just working on final paperwork at this point, and then the consultants will submit their final forms. And that's it for old business. Does anybody else have anything that I missed? Okay, hearing none. It's not something you missed, Ryan, but I had a question. Yeah, go for it. We were just looking at that roster on the
I just want to make sure that I'm not missing anything. I know that there is a historic commission site on the website sorry on the Medford city website. I know that some of that information was wrong. It said that my term ends on December 1st so. And I expected that the December 11th meeting or were you that this was my last meeting being there for December 11th, but I just saw that I
Yeah, I don't know why they made it December 1st. It's such a weird date, like December 31st, maybe towards the end of the month. I don't know, it's weird. But yes, no, please come, even though you'll be expiring as a term. You're still good as long, you know, up until when you're replaced is what the mayor said. That's better than expiring in what, 2022, I think? Yeah.
So, just circling back, if the commissioners feel comfortable, I need a recommendation to recommend Aleni to the mayor's office to be appointed to the historic commissioner starting in 2024. I move that we vote to recommend Aleni, sorry if I mispronounced this, Gleckas,
for our new historical commissioner. Second. Okay, go around a roll call vote, Chen? Yes. Peter? Yes. Kit? Yes. Doug? Yes. Jess? Yes. And Ryan's a yes, so six to zero.
So we'll send a communication to the mayor, Elainey, and then we'll keep you posted. Okay, sounds good. And if you want me to sort of like lurk in the next meeting, I'm happy to do so.
Oh, yeah, we'll send you the agenda and you get to see the the determinations of preferably status. So that'll be the other half of the demo delay process. December 11. And yeah, because it'll depend if the mayor gets the appointment letter out before then or not as well. So she won't be she won't be a member, but she'll be until 2024. Right? Because Jess will still have her seat. Right? Yeah. So I'll just be there sort of like, yeah. Yeah. Perfect. Happy to be there. Thank you.
Okay, meeting minutes. Peter sent out meeting minutes. Any questions, comments, concerns? Hearing none, I'll take a motion to approve. Motion to approve meeting minutes. Is that a second? October. Second. And roll call, Jen? Yes. Peter?
Yes. I will abstain because I wasn't at that meeting. Okay, understood. Doug? Yes. Jess? Yes. Okay, 4-0-1 approved. Anything else? Otherwise, I'll take a motion to dissolve the meeting. Motion to adjourn 7-50. Oh, I made it under an hour. It's a Christmas miracle. Second.
You can have a chance. And roll call Jen yes here. Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yeah right yes 6, 0, approved. Well, thank you all. It's nice to get done with that 4048 minutes this meeting was.
Ryan's social event, is that... Oh, yeah. On the... The 28th, if you're not at CPC. 28th, I will not be at CPC, I will yell at them. So, I mean, I guess I could go. Yeah, the 28th, I guess I could go. You guys meet in person? It's actually starting to be hybrid, starting tomorrow night, but I'm not gonna be in room 201, I'm gonna be online. Oh, okay.
Yeah, 28th, seven o'clock, Alta Cuba. Alta Cuba. Yeah, I will call them maybe tomorrow. Their website says they all take reservations. I don't believe it. I'll call them and try to book a room. I did invite Teresa and Dennis and Lenny can join us as well. And I think we'll also be joining us. That's the date that works for him. So maybe everybody except for Ryan and Doug.
But, you know, we'll just join you guys later. Yeah, Teresa will obviously be running the CPC meeting until it's done, which who knows how long that is. They vary wildly. Yeah. Great. All right. We'll see you guys. Thank you, everyone. Night all.