I'll say everything.
♪ Don't let them sorrow till he's gone ♪ ♪ Just think about tomorrow ♪ ♪ With the way that's always been ♪ ♪ Sorrow till it's gone ♪ ♪ When it's not the day that's gray and lonely ♪
Tomorrow, tomorrow, I love ya.
Tomorrow, you're always a day away.
Thank you.
you
It is December 1933, and America is in the middle of the Great Depression.
On the lower east side of New York, an orphanage has been the draft home of 11-year-old Annie for all but the first two months of her life.
Annie!
Go back to sleep, Molly.
Shut up.
Now leave her alone.
Bonnie, sit down.
Oh my goodness, they're fighting again.
How are we ever going to get any sleep?
Everyone, be quiet.
It's all right, Molly.
Annie's here.
Annie, read me the note again, please.
Oh no, not the note again.
Please take care of our little doll.
Her name is Annie.
We have left half a silver locket around her neck so that when we come back for her, she will know that she's our baby.
Baby far away, oh baby.
made me in a house over by a hill.
She took my Indiana into the pale of hill.
Back to the young, back to the smart, back to the cool and things like that and that and that.
Why shouldn't they be?
They'll all mistake what's given of me.
So maybe now it's time.
And maybe when I wake, they'll be there for me.
Baby, baby.
♪ Maybe she's making a plot that looks ♪ ♪ Maybe there's a trick that's written on the line ♪ ♪ Don't really care as long as they're mine ♪ ♪ So maybe now it's red, the last one of its kind ♪
Oh my goodness, she's running away.
Shhh, Tessie, I have to see you going, you little brat.
I love you, Ms.
Hannigan.
Hannigan
It's four o'clock in the morning.
I know it's four o'clock in the morning, but you get going.
That kitten never misses.
♪ On a night for us dedicated ♪ ♪ We get tricks and kisses ♪ ♪ We get kicked in the heart of life ♪ ♪ But I hope to speak up so we are not wrong ♪ ♪ We all got to like it ♪ ♪ Step a foot and we believe ♪ ♪ Step a foot in the heart of life ♪
And what we never see, and what we'll say, we'll see.
Don't care for you, a bitch, when you're even more a bitch.
It's a hard-knock life.
Yes, it is.
♪ For us it's hard not to fight ♪ ♪ For us can't we get through ♪ ♪ We can't take stand and sit ♪ ♪ We can't take it hard not fight ♪ ♪ We're supposed to speak up though ♪ ♪ It's hard not to go ♪ ♪ We have time to let it get through ♪ ♪ Set our goals and do at least ♪ ♪ Set our goals it's hard not to fight ♪
What do you have to say?
I love you, Ms.
Hannigan.
Be cute once a month, whether you like it or not.
Boy, this is a heavy load.
We'll miss you.
Where is that little brat?
In New York, St.
Mark's plays city dog jackets for a few stray dogs, but they miss one exactly this month that is immediately adopted by Annie, who has been wandering along through the wintry streets of the city.
Stop.
Would you like to donate an apple for your constipation?
Why not?
They're not selling anymore.
Hi, little fella.
Things I don't love for you either.
Apple sale.
Hi, little fella.
Things I don't love for you either.
I'm looking for an apple.
If I don't find one today, then maybe...
♪ The sun will come out tomorrow ♪ ♪ Bet your heart and soul and then tomorrow ♪ ♪ There'll be sunshine shining above ♪ ♪ Tomorrow clears away the cobwebs and then tomorrow ♪ ♪ There'll be sunshine shining above ♪
But it's such a day that's gray and lonely I wish there was light in and green and day But it's time to move on tomorrow So you gotta hang on tomorrow
Tomorrow, tomorrow, I love ya.
Tomorrow, you're always a day away.
But tomorrow, tomorrow, there's a lot of other days.
♪ Tomorrow there'll be a sun ♪ ♪ Just think about tomorrow ♪ ♪ Live the way that I planned ♪ ♪ Tomorrow still there's time ♪ ♪ One step in that day ♪ ♪ That's great and cool only ♪ ♪ I stick my chin in the sand ♪
Tomorrow, tomorrow, I love ya Tomorrow, you're always a day away Tomorrow, tomorrow, I love ya Tomorrow, you're always a day away
Hi, little girl.
Yes, officer?
That dog bit Henry, I see him in the neighborhood.
Ain't it strange?
Oh, no, officer.
That's my dog.
Oh, yeah?
Your dog?
What's his name?
His name?
Um, I call him Sandy.
You see, he's here.
Call him.
What's Sandy Institute's new name?
Well, he's not a note, and sometimes he doesn't answer.
Call him.
Sandy, Sandy, good boy, good boy.
Underneath the 59th Street Bridge is a Depression-style shantytown that is home to some of the unemployed New Yorkers who are living like hobos.
Hey kid, you hungry?
Want some grub?
No grub for me, just a bit to sing and dance.
Even the dog doesn't like it.
So, what are you doing here, kid?
I'm looking for my parents.
Your parents are looking for their kids.
Well, what are you doing here?
Well, kid, you know with this depression, things are really bad.
I used to enjoy the traffic.
I spent my summers at the shore.
I used to throw away the papers.
I don't anymore.
Thank you very much.
Thank
♪ We'd like to thank you for everything you've done ♪ ♪ Today is what we are today ♪ They all put on a show, Mr. Hoover.
We paid attention and we chose.
Not only did we pay attention, we paid through the nose.
♪ We'd like to thank you for everything you've done ♪ ♪ For really showing us the way ♪ ♪ We'd like to thank you for everything you've done ♪
♪ Please trust the arts today ♪ In every party setting, chicken.
But in our review we forgot, not only do we have the chicken, we ain't got the pot.
♪ Please trust the arts today ♪ ♪ Please trust the arts today ♪
So whoever has, off to you.
We're off to you with admiration.
Come down to Herb and Mrs. Toot.
So let us thank you, Herb and Mrs. Toot, for really showing us the way.
We'd like to thank you, Herb and Mrs. Toot, for being what we are today.
Come down here to Christmas then.
Be sure to bring your Mrs. Toot.
We ain't got any chicken for our stuffing.
Why don't we just stomp you?
If you're ever in a mood for a party, we'll show you just the way.
You've already had you.
You're a friend, you've made us what we are, too.
Come on, move on, let's get out of here, run!
Little girls, little girls, everywhere I turn I can see them.
Little girls, little girls, night and day I mean they can't bring them.
Look what a beautiful winter it is.
Come on, come on and drift with her.
Lucky me, lucky me.
Look at what a friend I've been to.
Someday I'll step on that crackle.
One night I'll scrape that curl.
You don't want to say no to anything that I know you can do to the little girl.
If that girl doesn't come back here real soon, I'll be in real trouble.
Annie's back!
This better not happen again or I'll report you.
I'm here on behalf of all of the world.
All of the warlocks, the millionaires?
No, the billionaires.
Eight, nine,
Dad?
We have lots of little girls around that age.
And someone smart?
M-I-S-S-I-S-S-I-P-P-I.
What about her?
Annie?
No, you can't have her.
I'm what you give up for having Dad.
Annie, get your coat.
Annie doesn't have a coat.
We'll have to get a nice new one.
These are my things.
There goes Annie, we'll miss you.
Annie and Grace arrive at Mr. Warbeck's mansion where all the servants are busy cleaning.
Annie is delighted to learn that as a guest she won't have to do any cleaning.
Good evening, miss.
Wow, what a place!
May I take your coat?
Will I, Captain Man?
It's okay.
It's okay, Danny.
We'll give it back.
Okay, what would you want?
What do you want to do first?
Well, I'll start with the windows, and then get to the floor.
You don't have to do any work.
You can go on vacation.
In the field we'll lay out all your clothes.
Blue?
No, red I think.
We'll balance on my Mrs. Rear.
Gloves?
No, I won't let you.
Then come sit you in your bed.
Bill?
No, bag machine.
I think I'm gonna like it here.
The pool is to the left.
Inside the house?
Uh-huh.
The trash is put in the rear.
I'm gonna pick up a racket.
The instructor's here at you.
I think I'm gonna like it here.
I used to grow in a tomb where I sit and read.
Get me that holy cow.
Could someone pinch me, please?
You've never had a little girl.
I'm very glad you're all here.
We hope you understand.
Your wishes are command.
I know what's gonna get here.
Hello, everyone.
Good to be home as this business trip was very demanding.
Dismissed.
Not you.
Not you?
Who is this?
This is the orphan you want.
I was expecting a boy.
Why, I've already purchased balls and a bat.
You just say what kind of orphan.
I'll throw them out.
Oh, well, we'll have to make the best of it.
What do you want to do?
Want to go to the movies?
I've never been to the movies before.
Oh, good.
Great.
You take her.
Thank you.
What's the matter?
I thought you were going to take me.
Oh, all right.
We'll all go together.
Drake, get our coats.
Shall I have a car paged for you?
No, we'll walk.
It's only 45 blocks to Times Square.
I'll be playing your Grace Brown Returns to the Orphanage.
Oh, it's you again.
What do you want?
Mr. Robux is a very famous man who would like to adopt her.
Would you excuse me for a minute?
Ah!
Anne is getting adopted by a millionaire!
Hi, gorgeous.
Rooster?
Who's that?
This is Lily St.
Regis.
Boy, isn't he daft to move to you?
Shut up, you dumb old cow.
Can you owe me 500 bucks?
Last time I owned you any money, I never started.
Well, I'll spring for some money this time, but never again.
We pass through the way of hate and monster.
Who's in, who's out, who's full of the mind?
Chasing in and out of places like no other.
You gotta get there.
before you die.
You don't get to ever play it from the floor, but I gently ace it a load of times.
Mother dear, oh, I know you're down there listening.
You've got a problem with me and I.
Is this real?
Where has winter been?
Can you see the leaves?
Is this real?
How can this be?
I'm a proud black Korean champion.
Andy, sit down.
I want to tell you something.
But first, you'd better sit down.
I can't sit here.
Well, maybe I had better sit down.
Here, I want to give you this.
It's a locket.
I always noticed that old one you wear.
No, the only thing I have to remember my parents had is this locket.
The only thing I want more than anything else in the whole world is to find my parents.
I promise.
I promise you, Amy, that we will do everything possible to find your parents.
If I should need the FBI Then I will have the FBI
With all the favors that I've done J.F.R.
Hoover owes me one And then the midnight oil gets burned Till not a stone is left unturned I will search everywhere And I'll find them, I swear Oh, you won't be an orphan for long
If I should need U.S.
Marines, then I could have U.S.
Marines, without the order of the Lord.
They'll be included in my throne, and other men would call it quits.
Annie, do you have anything else that will help us find your parents?
Can you use my note too?
Okay Annie, go work on it.
A Rockefeller Center-on-the-radio program called the Oxygen Hour is found very daily.
Warbucks offers a reward for anyone who can prove that they are any parent.
Maybe far away, or maybe we're nearby.
Maybe.
Maybe in a house, or in my eyes.
She may be me, and I'll be her.
Vegetative, why shouldn't we be?
We're both the same, what's giving up me?
So maybe now is time, and maybe when I leave,
Ladies and gentlemen, we have another special treat for you.
all of the reward bucks himself.
Yes, even I lost those two things.
Now I'd like to announce that I am offering a certified check for $50,000 to anyone who can prove they are any fair.
And now we present the Boiler Sisters.
Hey ho!
♪ You never did what you supposed to do just now ♪ ♪ But rather you're never fully dressed without a smile ♪ ♪ Your clothes may be woefully made and somehow mild ♪ ♪ But rather you're never fully dressed without a smile ♪
They're wearing army jeans and pillows.
It's what you wear for me each year.
And I promise you, don't laugh at me.
So sad and slow, she enters the wonderful world.
♪ With a smile ♪ ♪ Hey, old man, hey, young man ♪ ♪ You could be a child, but probably you're never ♪ ♪ Fully dressed with a smile ♪ ♪ You're close to me, oh, probably a kid a mile ♪ ♪ But probably you're never fully dressed with a smile ♪
Guess what they're wearing on Main Street's Elm Hill Road.
It's what you wear every year.
And I promise you, so that matters no, matters no, matters no.
Long for a while, remember you're never fully dressed, through you may wear
♪ You'll never believe it without a smile ♪ Wow, eating on the radio!
I would just love to be on the radio!
What's so good about that?
Now, with our smiles, this bird here will sing.
Ladies and gentlemen, Ms.
Hannigan has a pair of collars at the orchard.
Ralph and Shirley and Bunch, a couple from Canada, claim to be Annie's parents.
Who are you?
We're Ralph and Sheryl Mudge.
We understand you are our aunt.
Your aunt, Karen?
We have been barred and we must take her home with us.
We have cows, pigs, and goats.
and Roosters.
Roosters!
Okay, but it's got to be at a quest.
Hey, don't forget me.
You should have a Rooster out to give you any information.
Okay, okay, lady, but I don't know why you're being so tough.
You're simple, and I don't believe this is happening.
Now don't forget, he doesn't have the locket.
What locket?
They didn't mention anything about a locket or anything.
I didn't tell you.
When Edie left her padlock, they left her with a hat so she could lock it around her neck.
Edie snapped at both.
Okay, I know a guy who can make the other half of a cheap boat.
Okay guys, I'll leave this in your hands.
But what are we going to do with that little brat we get?
I'll handle that.
When you're chasing after good things, ask for a lullaby.
Keep the kids in a place like no other.
You've got to get there before you die.
You don't get there by playing how your rules work.
You're scared of the exits.
You're bold to die.
You want to be your own.
I know you can't be elicited.
You're gonna wobble if you see that my tears bleed.
It's free.
It's free to live.
May the coming of days bring peace and strength, better and dearer.
In Washington, D.C., at the White House, President Roosevelt and his cabinet reflect the national gloom as they listen to a radio broadcast against FDR.
Well, gentlemen, we have high time
and we are in a deep depression.
Maybe we can create some new jobs.
Yes, things are really tough and we have lots of work to do.
Mr. President and everyone, I would like you to meet my newest addition, Annie.
She's been outside while we have been doing business together.
She can stay in here.
Can I say something?
I know things are bad, but maybe... The sun will come out tomorrow.
Sit down, little girl.
♪ Tomorrow, well you gotta hang on till you come home ♪ ♪ There'll be some time ♪ ♪ Just thinking about tomorrow ♪ ♪ Gives away the hard work and the sorrow ♪ ♪ Till that time ♪ ♪ When the dark of the day gets gray and lonely ♪ ♪ I just think of my kid and grin and say ♪
Tomorrow, tomorrow, I love you.
Tomorrow, you're always mine.
Tomorrow, tomorrow, I love ya.
Tomorrow, you're always a day away.
Sorry to interrupt you, Mr. President, but a telegram from New York has just arrived from Mr. Wood.
Come for me.
Hundreds of couples are here claiming to be Annie's parents.
You'll have to excuse us.
Annie, we'll have to get back to New York as soon as possible.
Okay.
Where is everyone?
I'm sorry, Annie.
No one knows about the locket.
None of them were really your parents.
Don't worry, Annie.
We'll keep trying.
But in the meantime, we'll look after you.
In fact, I would like to adopt you as my very own little girl.
Together in the blast Together forever We're time-alike They never can sever And I don't need sunshine now to turn my skies to blue I don't need anything from you You wrap me around
That cute little finger.
You played us a song.
You made me the singer.
And once the bells went to you, always bubblegum.
I don't need anything but you.
Catacombs in the rain, dear, they won't be long.
Towers in the plain, dear, with you, I've got it all.
You're far from someone else.
I'm richer than goddess, but nothing on earth.
could ever define us.
And if tomorrow I'm an apple seller too, I don't need anything.
I don't need anything.
I don't need anything but you.
at a party of the nature to celebrate the adoption.
The happy servants feel as though it's Christmas every day since Annie has come along.
♪ Annie, Annie, Annie ♪ ♪ Everything's all right now, Annie ♪
♪ Annie, Annie, good times are running out ♪ ♪ Since she came our way ♪ ♪ It's Christmas, Christmas every day ♪ ♪ We've missed this bad times, sad times ♪ ♪ Now we're on a straight and loose ♪ ♪ Since Annie kicked out the loose ♪
Annie, Annie, look what you've done for us.
Annie, Annie, Annie, turn on the fun for us.
Family says that she is never very angry.
Never very, Annie, Annie.
♪ Music and a message of love ♪ ♪ It's raining, it's happening, come on ♪
Mr. and Mrs. Mudge, do you see them?
They claim to be his parents.
Oh, my baby!
Mr. and Mrs. Mudge, do you have any proof that you are really in his parents?
Here, Mr. Wilberforce, is the birth certificate.
That's not enough.
Here, then, is the silver locket with the 3D of the orphanage.
Oh, the silver locket?
Let me see it.
Oh, you really must be Annie's parents.
Come back tomorrow as we are having a party for Annie here tonight.
Would you like to stay?
No, we really must be going, but we'll be back to figure out tomorrow.
I know I've seen that place before.
I think I saw them at the orphanage.
Mr. Wolbach, there's something phony about the lighting.
President Roosevelt, I have helped you out many times before.
Can you please do me a favor?
Get me a phone.
It's Christmas morning, 1933, in the Warbuck's Mansion.
Warbuck's police and FDR have been up all night in constant telephone contact with the FDR, and they now have unhappy news for Annie.
Maybe in a house all hidden by a hill She's sitting playing piano
He didn't make a bill.
Betcha they're young, betcha they're smart.
Bet they collect things like asteroids and ice.
Betcha they're good, why shouldn't they be?
Their poor mistake was giving up me.
So maybe now is time.
When I wake, there'll be them calling me baby, baby.
Annie, we have sad news.
We have found out that your mother and father have died many years ago.
Well, then who knew about the locket?
Kids!
Annie!
Miss Hannigan, this is President Roosevelt.
Kids, we have presents for everyone!
Yay!
Oh, my baby!
We've missed you so very much.
Hi, Mom.
Hi, Dad.
I suppose you would like the reward money?
We didn't know anything about the reward money, but that would be enough to bring up tomorrow evening.
Shall I make the check out to you?
Yeah.
Just sign it and we'll be on our way.
You guys are imposters.
You're under arrest for posing as Annie's parents.
I never liked you anyway, Annie, you little brat.
From now on, no more money, yes?
Yay!
No more hard knock life.
We'll all go to school.
Yay?
Annie, what do you have a surprise for me?
A car.
We hope you enjoyed our performance of Annie.
Grade two and grade four.
Grade three, I promoted myself.
Grade two and grade three were very hot under some very warm conditions this week, and they were excellent.
We're about ready now to get everybody up for the applause.
Our hobos, police, and laundry men,
Our servants, the Boylan sisters, our cabinet ministers, and President Roosevelt himself.
Lily, Brewster, and Grace.
Our two Oliver Wolbachs.
Our Miss Hannigan's.
And our Annie's.
in our second grade chorus.
When it's not a birthday, that's great and lonely.
Tomorrow, tomorrow, I love ya.
Tomorrow, you're always a day away.
We're gonna, like, give out flowers now to the, uh, mothers.
First, Mrs. Wallman.
Mrs. Swanson.
Mrs. Yeager.
And Denise Dobson.
And the second grade class.
And thank you for coming.
Please join us for refreshments at the foyer.
Maybe in a house over by a hill, she'd sit and play in the air now, instead of paying the bill.
Back to day now, back to last night,
Back to their good, why shouldn't they be?
Their one mistake was givin' up me.
So maybe now it's time, for maybe when I wake, they'll be there callin' me baby.
Maybe that's what love looks.
Maybe they're strict and strict on time.
Don't really care as long as they're mine.
So maybe now he's friends, the last one of his kind.
Won't you please come and join them?