A bird knows you're true Then a little voice inside you whispers Kid, don't sell your dreams so soon
Everywhere you look, everywhere you go There's a heart, there's a heart, a hand to hold on to Everywhere you look, everywhere you face Somebody who needs you Everywhere you look When you're lost out there and you're all alone Life is waiting to carry you home Everywhere you look
you
Here at the 8th grade open house and I'm here with Erica, the captain of the girls gymnastics team. Erica, how did last season go? Last season went well. We were able to win the GBL title and we worked together great as a team. How do you feel about this upcoming season? I'm excited. We have the freshmen coming in who haven't done the gymnastics before so we're excited about that. Hi, I'm Hallie Farrell and I'm here with Mike McLaughlin. What contributions do you make to Medford High School?
Well, I'm the main office secretary and every day me and Lisa Bowler help run the high school alongside Dr. Prella and make sure that everything goes effortlessly and flawlessly for all our lovely students. We're back again with the Mustang Report and I'm here with Abby McCarthy, Rhiannon Arnold, and Destiny Fitzgerald, three juniors who participate in the Medford High School varsity basketball team. Abby, what are you doing specifically to train your body and your mind for the upcoming season?
Well currently right now we have our fall ball going on and in like a little bit closer to the season we'll be starting up open gyms so that kind of thing so yeah. Now you guys are some of the kind of like the major contributors to the Varsity basketball team you know what you know what made you again kind of see basketball as something that you could do you know further on in your high school career?
Well, we all really love the sport a lot, which I think helps. We have a really passionate team. So yeah, it's really just nice to be in a group of people who all love what you love to do, and it's a lot of fun. Basically, to the incoming freshmen, what is the voice of Medford High? So the voice of Medford High, we get the opportunity to do the announcements every morning. So I go one day, George goes the next, and yeah, it's super fun.
Yeah, so basically what we do is every other day we flip off and we just have a set of announcements and we let people know what clubs are going on, any big activities that are going on in MHS, and anything else interesting. Maybe fun facts, who knows? We just let the people know what they want to hear. Hi, I'm Hallie Farrell and I'm here with freshman Carmen Diorio. What sports are you planning on playing for the high school? Right now I play soccer and I'm planning on playing basketball and softball. What's any piece of advice that you have for the 8th graders that are coming to high school next year?
One thing I've learned is that the school's not as confusing to get around as you think it is. The eighth graders don't know what school to go to. What would Tucci do? What would Tucci do is a no-brainer. You go to Medford High School. I look forward to seeing you in September.
I'll help you with that.
Out of here, we're out of here Out of heart, we're long within They're going to fear again They're going to fear
And gods betray us, out of fear And life goes past, to kill some evil dead ghost
I'm here with the Mustang Report, and I'm here with the four captains of the varsity soccer team. Can you guys give us a little bit of reflection on how the season has been going so far? We've been doing really great. We've only lost one game so far, and I think we're going to do great in the future. I'll move over here. What are you guys doing each week in practices to prepare your body and your mind for upcoming games?
Well, we obviously do a lot of conditioning because it's soccer, so we do a lot of running, we do a lot of game situations, offense versus defense, and we just practice free kicks, corner kicks, everything. We're back with the Mustang Report, and I'm here with Mike Senner, who's one of the captains of the Medford High School varsity baseball team, and I'm also here with Mike Nestor, who's the coach of that varsity baseball team. Mike, what are you doing to prepare your body for the upcoming season?
So two or three times a week we actually have workouts in the workout room where we basically lift and then on the weekends we do conditioning for running. Mr. Mike Nestor, what have you been preaching to the players about getting their bodies ready and getting their minds ready for the upcoming season?
Just that the season never ends. It's a 12-month season that you can't just show up in March and start swinging a baseball bat and throwing a baseball. You know, we work out year-long just to get ready for the season, especially up here in the Northeast. Well, I certainly wish you guys luck on your upcoming season. And this has been Nick Hennison, again, from the Mustang Report. Back to you.
Hello, this is Nick Canniston from the Mustang Report with some insight on the Medford High School football season. And I'm here with Mustang Report staff member Eric Rapucci, who is also the Medford High football team manager. What are some of your responsibilities as team manager?
So my responsibilities as team manager is to, at practice, I'm there with a schedule, a time clock, and anything they really need me to do. So if someone's gear goes haywire, I'm the one to fix it. And when I'm at games, I'm always on the sideline trying to keep them back, keep them in order. If anyone needs help, I'm always there to help them.
I think, indeed, that is a very important responsibility. There have been some pretty close and hard-fought games, specifically the home opener against Beaumont, with the team lost on the final play. What do you think you have seen and what do you think the team can do better to preserve leads late in the game?
Definitely one of our biggest issues is we don't stay focused when we come out of the second half. We keep the fire in the first half. We're all amped up. We're getting ready. Then we come out in the second half, and everyone just loses it. No focus. That was a really tough game. It definitely hit us straight to the heart. Definitely another issue we have is tackling. That's our big thing. We are on tackle and missing tackles. And that's what's definitely one of our biggest issues.
No.
How long have you two kind of known each other and what like created this kind of interesting relationship that you guys have? Well, you know, I've known the gentleman next to me for a few years now. Once I found out that he went to Bowdoin College, the rivalry just immediately started right there. I mean, you know, Bowdoin College is, it's enough said. I don't even know where to go with that. But that's when it started pretty much.
For those of you who don't know, Nassim Eto'o is an alumni of the Tufts University Jumbo, so that's why voting in Tufts is kind of a little bit of a rivalry. What is your role with these guys, getting them prepared, not only just for the games, but also for basically life?
Well, first I would like to say that up until last year's faculty flag football game, I never lost to Mr. Nassimano. We played in college and I beat him twice, so I would just like to make sure everyone understands that. Last year was really humiliating for me, but he bent the rules and found a way to cheat as much as possible.
We won't go into any more detail about that. But in terms of the football players and just the youth of Medford, I think it's very important that we as a community, as a school, find ways to help every kid reach their full potential and teach them the work ethic that I think myself and Coach Nascimento have tried to display for them as much as possible with football and education as part of it.
uh... if you guys just kind of share a little bit of inside on the upcoming flag football teams on you know kind of what the format is like how what are the words of the rules because you know five football with faculty it's kind of a bunch of adults who don't really know a bunch of a lot of them don't really know football so what are some of the things that you guys should do that to kind of facilitate you know a better an easier environment nick it's a great question uh...
There were lots of complaints about the rules. Figure it out. Figure it out. We had meetings. We announced it before the games. There's no legal practices. There's no legal practices. Just listen. Blue team, figure it out. That's all. Just know the rules. That's all. But hey, it's going to be an exciting game as it was last year. I think it's going to be a lot of fun for everyone. And I'm looking forward to it. Team Gray all the way.
I would just like to reiterate that there needs to be a play clock this year so he can't sit in the huddle and wind down the whole clock. I would also like to reiterate the fact that his team had practices while you know my team was full of coaches who were actually doing other things in the building so his team was just kind of hanging out finding ways
to sneak around. He actually skipped football practice multiple times to attend those practices. So I would like to say while he was finding ways to beat me in flag football, I was worrying about the actual football team.
false these are all false accusations I mean it's it's such it's so ridiculous but uh you know I'm not here to make excuses okay I'm not gonna talk about the last year last year's game anymore I'm on to this year and and we're gonna focus on what we need to do it's that simple
uh... you know if i if i were to say something to any of the eighties or even high school is watching this if you don't like football fine you know personally i love football so this is only that i enjoy doing even for those of you don't like football i was still recommend coming to this is a great event you know you know that that benefits eric rizali who was a former graduate of medford high school was in a tragic accident
You know, so it funds, you know, a scholarship in his name. So it's definitely a great cause and it's a lot of fun seeing, you know, a lot of the teachers kind of go at it. This has been Nick Hennison with Mr. Nacimento and Mr. Jaworski from the Mustang Report. Back to you.