[SPEAKER_03]: So why don't we call the meeting to order?
[SPEAKER_03]: We have me, Chris Banner, Chair, Sean Scuderi, Vice Chair, Fred Sewell, a member, and Joe, a member.
[SPEAKER_03]: And hopefully we'll have Melanie in a minute.
[SPEAKER_03]: And we have Ryan.
[SPEAKER_05]: And Ryan.
[SPEAKER_05]: Welcome, Ryan.
[SPEAKER_05]: Ryan, are you there?
[SPEAKER_05]: You're muted, Ryan.
[SPEAKER_06]: His name is showing up, but he's not responding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's right.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I just let Melanie in.
[SPEAKER_02]: She should be joining us any minute now.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, terrific.
[SPEAKER_05]: Good boy, good boy, good boy.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is there a good boy?
[SPEAKER_03]: around here?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, you know, I'm not talking to Frank.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's the dog.
[SPEAKER_06]: He's talking to the dog.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's being a good boy.
[SPEAKER_06]: We just had the trainer here.
[SPEAKER_06]: We're working with him to train him to be a good dog.
[SPEAKER_03]: Good.
[SPEAKER_03]: Excellent.
[SPEAKER_03]: All dogs.
[SPEAKER_03]: All dogs should be good dogs.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is Melanie in, Fred?
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't see.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't see her.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I did come up that she was in the waiting room and I admitted, but hopefully she'll
[SPEAKER_02]: Drop back in here.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm gonna wait a few minutes or you just want to proceed to the discussion and vote?
[SPEAKER_02]: We might as well just get started, Chris, we're already.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah, I meant for this to be like a 10 minute meeting.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_03]: So has anyone, has everyone who is interested had a chance to look at the report?
[SPEAKER_03]: It hasn't changed much.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, I looked at it.
[SPEAKER_05]: It looks great.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: How about you, Charlotte?
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm all set.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Fred?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I looked at it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It looked very nice.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Melanie?
[SPEAKER_02]: Hey, Melanie.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm all set.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, I looked at it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sorry for the fiasco here.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Did you have a chance to look at the preliminary?
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: So this we're on a very tight schedule, unfortunately, and that's, that's my fault.
[SPEAKER_03]: But ideally, we should vote tonight and submit it tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_03]: So can I have a vote to approve the report and submit it to I'm sorry, a motion to
[SPEAKER_03]: approve the report and submit it to the mass historical commission.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hi, Chris.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is Fred.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll, I'll make a motion to approve the preliminary report prepared by Chris Skelly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Uh, recently submitted to us.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't have the date in front of me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Um, but approve that, uh, for submission to the mass historic commission.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Second.
[SPEAKER_06]: I second it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you, Charlotte.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, so let's, this is a Zoom meeting obviously, so we need to call the roll.
[SPEAKER_03]: Charlotte?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Fred?
[SPEAKER_03]: Melanie?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Joe?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I also vote yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I will make a note of that.
[SPEAKER_03]: and submit the report.
[SPEAKER_03]: I will submit the report tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_03]: So let's talk briefly about, anybody who needs to drop can, and I will send out comments.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'll send out what I'm about to say later, but briefly,
[SPEAKER_03]: We need to make some, we'll come up with final version of the, we need to send out notices to all residents.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I would also like to send out notices to anyone who lives within 300 feet of any house in the district.
[SPEAKER_03]: And Dennis has told me that it's not a big deal to put together a mailing list like this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Does that sound like a reasonable plan?
[SPEAKER_06]: I think so.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'll be more than happy to help out.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Charlotte.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't think we're going to need help.
[SPEAKER_03]: But Deb and I did this.
[SPEAKER_06]: Do we have all the names and addresses?
[SPEAKER_03]: I believe Dennis can put them together using a program that they have at City Hall.
[SPEAKER_03]: OK.
[SPEAKER_03]: Does everyone agree?
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you disagree with.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sending them to the butters within 300 feet as well as the residents.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no, I don't.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Great.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so what we would, what I'd like to do.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is have a mailing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which consists of the letter, which consists of a letter.
[SPEAKER_03]: and closing a trifold brochure, the same trifold brochure that we've been working on, and mail that to all residents and all abutters within 300 feet.
[SPEAKER_03]: Does that sound reasonable?
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Chris, are we sending them to owners who do not live presently in the district?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Um, so we will add our next meeting, which will be in August.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if people can't make it to a regular meeting, we can, we can, uh, well, let's just, let's just, uh, talk about that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Uh, can people make it to our regular August meeting, which is August 10th.
[SPEAKER_05]: As of now, I think I can.
[SPEAKER_04]: I may be visiting colleges with my daughter, but as of now, I can.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Charlotte, can you make it to August 10th?
[SPEAKER_03]: The regular meeting?
[SPEAKER_06]: Hold on a second.
[SPEAKER_06]: At the same time, so it'll be right at 6 o'clock.
[SPEAKER_03]: Regular time.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's my daughter's birthday.
[SPEAKER_06]: We're taking her out to dinner afterwards.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, well, well.
[SPEAKER_03]: Fred, are you going to be able to make it to our regular August meeting?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I should be able to attend that.
[SPEAKER_03]: How about you, Joe?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't see why not.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think so.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I have to check.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't have my calendar in front of me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think I might be at a Boy Scout camp.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is your son in the Boy Scouts?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is your son in the Boy Scout?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, he is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, good for him.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, he is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was a Boy Scout myself long ago.
[SPEAKER_01]: He loves it, he's super excited.
[SPEAKER_03]: I loved it too.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, so what I will do is I will send out, preferably before more than a day's notice, the text of the letter and a version of the trifold.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, um, uh, we can approve that on, uh, on August 10th and I will mail it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Uh, or rather to be precise, Dennis and Teresa will mail it, uh, either the following day or, you know, maybe the following Monday, something like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: That sounds good.
[SPEAKER_03]: Good plan.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Um, and then, um,
[SPEAKER_03]: In September at our regular meeting, we will have the public hearing for which I booked City Hall, the big City Hall chamber months ago.
[SPEAKER_05]: So we will be meeting at six o'clock in person at City Hall.
[SPEAKER_05]: And- And what's the date?
[SPEAKER_05]: That is, what is it?
[SPEAKER_03]: September 14th.
[SPEAKER_04]: I will not be here.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'll be in Paris.
[SPEAKER_03]: Paris, well, well.
[SPEAKER_03]: Tough life.
[SPEAKER_06]: I think we should all be with you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, maybe we just have the meeting in Paris instead of here.
[SPEAKER_05]: That sounds good to me.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can you, well, technically we don't need a quorum at all.
[SPEAKER_03]: We're just- It's a public hearing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you can make it by Zoom or even just calling in, that would be probably helpful.
[SPEAKER_04]: I will try, it'll probably be 12 o'clock midnight in Paris at that time.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_04]: There's six to eight hours ahead of us, I believe.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, yes, it's six hours that morning.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, so that meeting is September 14th.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, 6 p.m.
[SPEAKER_06]: at City Hall.
[SPEAKER_03]: 6 p.m.
[SPEAKER_03]: at City Hall.
[SPEAKER_03]: In the big council chamber.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, that's the plan.
[SPEAKER_03]: Too bad that Chris Donovan's been MIA for a couple of months.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm not sure what's going on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, he got COVID and seemed to have a really bad case of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I haven't talked to him in a month, but last month he was pretty sick.
[SPEAKER_02]: So he'll be having the effects of that, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_03]: Anyway, so, but we have everybody else here, everybody approved.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, does anybody else wanna talk about anything else?
Nope.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I know if we have Ryan Hayward's here and I know Ryan- Oh yeah, Ryan.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just can I jump in?
[SPEAKER_00]: Chris, I do have to jump off to start my other meeting, but I'm- Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hopefully, as long as none of you all log off again.
[SPEAKER_00]: If someone is logging off, make that other person another person to host.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if the meeting ended right now, it'd be fine, Dennis.
[SPEAKER_03]: But not to worry.
[SPEAKER_03]: All right.
[SPEAKER_03]: OK.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ryan, are you there?
[SPEAKER_03]: Ryan?
[SPEAKER_03]: OK, well, I will ask Ryan.
[SPEAKER_03]: I will ask Ryan for any comments.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know if Ryan was able to hear what just transpired, but in any case, I will ping Ryan right after this meeting by email and ask him if he has any comments or questions.
[SPEAKER_06]: He sent me something that says, bad audio connection, Zoom issues all around tonight.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was regarding the
[SPEAKER_02]: It wasn't regarding the South Street Historic District.
[SPEAKER_03]: It was the... Oh, the community, something or other.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, what are we?
[SPEAKER_03]: We're a... Yeah, I need to work on that.
[SPEAKER_03]: All right.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, I need to jump off right now.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, thanks, Charlotte.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why don't we adjourn?
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_03]: I second it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, okay, see you all next month.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you everybody for attending.