So why don't we call the meeting to order? We have me, Chris Banner, Chair, Sean Scuderi, Vice Chair, Fred Sewell, a member, and Joe, a member. And hopefully we'll have Melanie in a minute. And we have Ryan. And Ryan. Welcome, Ryan. Ryan, are you there? You're muted, Ryan.
His name is showing up, but he's not responding. Yeah, that's right. So I just let Melanie in. She should be joining us any minute now. Okay, terrific. Good boy, good boy, good boy. Is there a good boy?
around here? Yeah, you know, I'm not talking to Frank. It's the dog. He's talking to the dog. It's being a good boy. We just had the trainer here. We're working with him to train him to be a good dog. Good. Good. Excellent. All dogs. All dogs should be good dogs. Is Melanie in, Fred? I don't see. I don't see her. No, I did come up that she was in the waiting room and I admitted, but hopefully she'll
Drop back in here. I'm gonna wait a few minutes or you just want to proceed to the discussion and vote? We might as well just get started, Chris, we're already. Okay, sure. Yeah, yeah, I meant for this to be like a 10 minute meeting. Sorry. So has anyone, has everyone who is interested had a chance to look at the report? It hasn't changed much.
Yes, I looked at it. It looks great. Okay. How about you, Charlotte? I'm all set. Okay. Fred? Yeah, I looked at it. It looked very nice. Okay. Melanie? Hey, Melanie. I'm all set. Hi. Yeah, I looked at it. Sorry for the fiasco here. That's okay. Did you have a chance to look at the preliminary?
Okay. So this we're on a very tight schedule, unfortunately, and that's, that's my fault. But ideally, we should vote tonight and submit it tomorrow. So can I have a vote to approve the report and submit it to I'm sorry, a motion to
approve the report and submit it to the mass historical commission. Hi, Chris. This is Fred. I'll, I'll make a motion to approve the preliminary report prepared by Chris Skelly. Uh, recently submitted to us. I don't have the date in front of me. Um, but approve that, uh, for submission to the mass historic commission. Okay. Second. I second it. Thank you, Charlotte.
Okay, so let's, this is a Zoom meeting obviously, so we need to call the roll. Charlotte? Yes. Fred? Yes. Melanie? Yes. Joe? Yes. And I also vote yes. So I will make a note of that.
and submit the report. I will submit the report tomorrow. So let's talk briefly about, anybody who needs to drop can, and I will send out comments. I'll send out what I'm about to say later, but briefly,
We need to make some, we'll come up with final version of the, we need to send out notices to all residents. And I would also like to send out notices to anyone who lives within 300 feet of any house in the district. And Dennis has told me that it's not a big deal to put together a mailing list like this.
Does that sound like a reasonable plan? I think so. I'll be more than happy to help out. Thank you, Charlotte. I don't think we're going to need help. But Deb and I did this. Do we have all the names and addresses? I believe Dennis can put them together using a program that they have at City Hall. OK. Does everyone agree?
Okay. Do you disagree with. Sending them to the butters within 300 feet as well as the residents. No, no, I don't. Okay. Great. Great. Yeah. And so what we would, what I'd like to do. Is have a mailing. Which consists of the letter, which consists of a letter.
and closing a trifold brochure, the same trifold brochure that we've been working on, and mail that to all residents and all abutters within 300 feet. Does that sound reasonable? Okay. Yes. Chris, are we sending them to owners who do not live presently in the district? Yes.
Um, so we will add our next meeting, which will be in August. And if people can't make it to a regular meeting, we can, we can, uh, well, let's just, let's just, uh, talk about that. Uh, can people make it to our regular August meeting, which is August 10th.
As of now, I think I can. I may be visiting colleges with my daughter, but as of now, I can. Okay. Charlotte, can you make it to August 10th? The regular meeting? Hold on a second. At the same time, so it'll be right at 6 o'clock. Regular time. Yeah. Okay. It's my daughter's birthday. We're taking her out to dinner afterwards. Oh, well, well.
Fred, are you going to be able to make it to our regular August meeting? Yeah, I should be able to attend that. How about you, Joe? I don't see why not. I think so. But I have to check. I don't have my calendar in front of me. I think I might be at a Boy Scout camp. Is your son in the Boy Scouts?
Is your son in the Boy Scout? Yes, he is. Oh, good for him. Yes, he is, yeah. I was a Boy Scout myself long ago. He loves it, he's super excited. I loved it too. Okay, so what I will do is I will send out, preferably before more than a day's notice, the text of the letter and a version of the trifold.
And, um, uh, we can approve that on, uh, on August 10th and I will mail it. Uh, or rather to be precise, Dennis and Teresa will mail it, uh, either the following day or, you know, maybe the following Monday, something like that. That sounds good. Good plan. Okay. Um, and then, um,
In September at our regular meeting, we will have the public hearing for which I booked City Hall, the big City Hall chamber months ago. So we will be meeting at six o'clock in person at City Hall. And- And what's the date? That is, what is it? September 14th.
I will not be here. I'll be in Paris. Paris, well, well. Tough life. I think we should all be with you. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, maybe we just have the meeting in Paris instead of here. That sounds good to me.
Can you, well, technically we don't need a quorum at all. We're just- It's a public hearing. Yeah, yeah. But if you can make it by Zoom or even just calling in, that would be probably helpful.
I will try, it'll probably be 12 o'clock midnight in Paris at that time. Oh, right, right, right. There's six to eight hours ahead of us, I believe. Yes, yes, it's six hours that morning. Yeah, yeah. Okay, so that meeting is September 14th. Yes, 6 p.m. at City Hall. 6 p.m. at City Hall. In the big council chamber. Okay. Okay, that's the plan.
Too bad that Chris Donovan's been MIA for a couple of months. I'm not sure what's going on. Yeah, he got COVID and seemed to have a really bad case of it. I haven't talked to him in a month, but last month he was pretty sick. So he'll be having the effects of that, I don't know.
Anyway, so, but we have everybody else here, everybody approved. So, does anybody else wanna talk about anything else? Nope. Well, I know if we have Ryan Hayward's here and I know Ryan- Oh yeah, Ryan. Just can I jump in? Chris, I do have to jump off to start my other meeting, but I'm- Yes.
Hopefully, as long as none of you all log off again. If someone is logging off, make that other person another person to host. Even if the meeting ended right now, it'd be fine, Dennis. But not to worry. All right. OK. Ryan, are you there? Ryan? OK, well, I will ask Ryan.
I will ask Ryan for any comments. I don't know if Ryan was able to hear what just transpired, but in any case, I will ping Ryan right after this meeting by email and ask him if he has any comments or questions. He sent me something that says, bad audio connection, Zoom issues all around tonight. It was regarding the
It wasn't regarding the South Street Historic District. It was the... Oh, the community, something or other. Yeah, what are we? We're a... Yeah, I need to work on that. All right. Okay, I need to jump off right now. Okay, thanks, Charlotte. Why don't we adjourn? Okay. Motion to adjourn. Okay. I second it.
Okay, okay, see you all next month. Thank you everybody for attending.