[SPEAKER_08]: Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_06]: Vice President Collins, present.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Lozaro, present.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Lemming, present.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Scarpelli, present.
[SPEAKER_06]: Councilor Singh, present.
[SPEAKER_08]: President Behrs, present.
[SPEAKER_08]: 24475 offered by Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_08]: be it resolved that the Medford City Council hold a question and answer session to discuss the definitions and terminology regarding the proposed Proposition 2.5 overrides and the proposed debt exclusion measure.
[SPEAKER_08]: To that resolution, the following amendments were added.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Scarpelli asked that the administration and Council on Aging do outreach to seniors about this meeting.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Callahan requested outreach to parents of school-aged children, not just teachers, and specifically requested outreach to the PTOs.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Sang requested general outreach and specifically requested that the community liaisons translate into other languages the information that is on the city website about the overrides and the debt exclusion.
[SPEAKER_08]: To ensure that the council is able to answer questions in a timely manner and that decorum is maintained, the council president, myself, will be enforcing the following rules.
[SPEAKER_08]: One, members of the public will have one minute to ask one question.
[SPEAKER_08]: Members of the public will not be able to ask a second question until all who seek to ask a question have had the chance to ask their first question.
[SPEAKER_08]: The president will verbally request that residents not ask duplicative or largely similar questions to questions that have already been answered.
[SPEAKER_08]: and may move to the next question if a duplicative or similar question is asked.
[SPEAKER_08]: Each counselor will have up to two minutes to answer per question.
[SPEAKER_08]: The president will verbally request the counselors not answer if a duplicative or largely similar answer has been given by another counselor and may move to the next question if a duplicative or similar answer is given.
[SPEAKER_08]: After members of the public have had the chance to ask their first question, the president will open the floor to either a second question or a short public comment by members of the public in attendance.
[SPEAKER_08]: And before we start, I just want to say
[SPEAKER_08]: that the council itself is in mourning today.
[SPEAKER_08]: Last night, we lost our city messenger, Larry Lepore, who has served us for many years.
[SPEAKER_08]: We will be having some condolence remarks made at our regular meeting that will begin after our committee of the whole meeting.
[SPEAKER_08]: So I hope that folks will stick around if you knew Larry or otherwise to say a kind word or story that you may have shared with him during his many years serving the city behind this rail.
[SPEAKER_08]: With that, I do want to invite our city assessor, Ted Costigan.
[SPEAKER_08]: The council had requested some answers and updates from him, and I know that he's here to share some information that his office has been working on.
[SPEAKER_08]: So with that, I will go to our assessor, Ted Costigan.
[SPEAKER_03]: Before we go on, can I just address my original question?
[SPEAKER_03]: resolution?
[SPEAKER_03]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_08]: And then we'll go to Ted.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pete, there are questions.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know that there were some questions about council rules, about limitations when it comes to meetings, minutes, and how long we could speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if there are follow-up questions, and if there's one question, I believe Councilor Villes explained the process that we're using.
[SPEAKER_03]: And as Council President, I think he wants to move this meeting along, but I just, there were some senior citizens that mentioned
[SPEAKER_03]: if there's some confusion, I hope we have a little leeway when it comes to maybe asking the same question twice because of maybe not understanding it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I hope we would do that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Uh, the other question that, uh, council bears did read this speak about is that, uh, we all asked for information to be sent out to the community.
[SPEAKER_03]: Uh, the mayor's response, I believe, um,
[SPEAKER_03]: The chief of staff did respond that legally the city couldn't inform or give an, I'll just read if I can just so people understand, cause it's a little confusing to people.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sending this information request, so it's, we sent this email to legal on today to guide us on what we can do, should avoid doing before we can assist given the OCPF guidelines.
[SPEAKER_03]: One specific question in mind is whether we can intentionally direct notification advertisement to subset of residents.
[SPEAKER_03]: So the following is up on my email below, per council, we can't send unsolicited information
[SPEAKER_03]: to all voters or a portion of voters of the city, whether by mail or by email.
[SPEAKER_03]: We got that, that response was today, correct, Council Beers?
[SPEAKER_03]: It was 10 a.m.
[SPEAKER_03]: today.
[SPEAKER_03]: If we knew that and we needed to change wording, I think sending out an all call that we were having a meeting that would, it's open to the public, that just read the resolution, I think that that wouldn't have been an issue.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I just wanted to share that with you.
[SPEAKER_03]: So thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Sure, and per council, you mean legal council?
[SPEAKER_08]: I don't know that I was on that email.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, you are.
[SPEAKER_08]: Was I on that?
[SPEAKER_08]: I believe it was.
[SPEAKER_03]: Council, Adam, did you forward this to everybody?
[SPEAKER_05]: You know what?
[SPEAKER_05]: I don't think I did.
[SPEAKER_05]: I apologize.
[SPEAKER_05]: I don't think I did forward that to everybody.
[SPEAKER_05]: I thought it was, I thought it went to everybody.
[SPEAKER_05]: I think it only went to the, to the three who had amendments.
[SPEAKER_05]: I don't think I did for that area.
[SPEAKER_05]: I apologize.
[SPEAKER_08]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: She means legal counsel, right?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_08]: All right.
[SPEAKER_08]: Good.
[SPEAKER_08]: I didn't want her to think about this council.
[SPEAKER_08]: All right.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: With that, I'll go to our city assessor and let me know when you want me to put slides up.
[SPEAKER_08]: The new mics are coming on Thursday.
[SPEAKER_08]: Shane's going to come out.
[SPEAKER_08]: He's going to fix it.
[SPEAKER_08]: I hear the chair moving.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thanks, Shane.
[SPEAKER_02]: testing.
[SPEAKER_07]: Great.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thank you, Shane.
[SPEAKER_02]: pretty big guy, so sorry about that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but if we could go to the slides.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just out of a point of information, the Department of Revenue received our valuations for fiscal year 25.
[SPEAKER_02]: They approved it actually this morning.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I'm able to share with you our evaluation changes for fiscal year 25.
[SPEAKER_02]: As a reminder to everyone, on a yearly basis, the Department of Revenue and the state mandates that
[SPEAKER_02]: We the assessing office update valuations to full and fair cash value again on that fiscal year basis.
[SPEAKER_02]: We share those valuations in January, but we worked really hard in the office this year to get them done.
[SPEAKER_02]: And as of this morning they were approved so just sharing this information, because it will apply to the override.
[SPEAKER_02]: in those override options.
[SPEAKER_02]: So residential valuations went up approximately 4% this year and the commercial industrial personal property which is our commercial base went up about 3% in value this year.
[SPEAKER_02]: Our new growth which is when you think of like new single family homes
[SPEAKER_02]: new condo conversions, any exempt property that goes to taxable, that's a $2.5 million in new growth, which adds to our levy.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then I just wanted to point out that, you know, absent any override vote, the average tax bill would go up approximately $175 on our median single family this year.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's sort of the effects of Prop 2.5.
[SPEAKER_02]: Next page, so we obviously have our override votes just as a reminder to people, questions, just as a note, question six, whether it passes or not will not have an effect on fiscal year 25 tax bills.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's because the debt service payment would have to be paid in fiscal year 25, which would not be possible given the time it takes to issue the debt and obviously the six month period before the first debt payment would be due.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we're looking at questions seven and eight tonight which would have an effect were they to pass on the fiscal year 25 tax bills.
[SPEAKER_02]: And just next slide.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't want to
[SPEAKER_02]: four people to death, so I just took one example, which is our median single family tax bill.
[SPEAKER_02]: I know the numbers might be a little small, but again, the way we arrive at your tax bill is multiplying your valuation by the tax rate.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what, you know, our tax rate is in a lot of ways, determined by how much we can levy on taxpayers.
[SPEAKER_02]: So the levy the last year was about 139.9 million.
[SPEAKER_02]: We have Prop 2.5, which pushed up the levy by 3.5 million.
[SPEAKER_02]: The new growth, which is 2.5, which gives us our fiscal year 25 levy at $146 million.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the amount of money that the city can collect in real estate, personal property taxation from its residents, taxpayers.
[SPEAKER_02]: Our estimated tax rate, given all this, and we do have a split rate between the commercial and the residential, we'll focus on the residential is $8.37.
[SPEAKER_02]: On the median single-family home, that would mean a tax bill of $6,519 for the year.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, that's a year-on-year difference from last year of $195.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now the next two columns contemplate the passage of question seven and eight respectively.
[SPEAKER_02]: As you can see, the year-on-year differences, and then I'll just go move on to the last column.
[SPEAKER_02]: If they were both passed, instead of a median single family home in Medford having $195 a year-on-year increase, the increase would be $529, giving us a net effect if both questions were passed of approximately $334 to the, again, median single family in Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: I did a,
[SPEAKER_02]: run the calculations for the median condo, which would be a year-on-year change of $345, and the two families would be $873.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's again the median.
[SPEAKER_02]: What I will pledge to do, and I'm working with the mayor's communications office to get this done on our website, now that as of this morning I have the approval from the Department of Revenue, I will publish all our addresses and values of residential properties on our website.
[SPEAKER_02]: with these contemplated tax rates which could change slightly and I'll get that in the next slide so that every resident in Medford that would like to can go on to our website as they can normally you could go right now and find your 24 value but in advance get their fiscal year 25 value and the contemplated tax bill that would be associated with that value.
[SPEAKER_02]: So just go real quick to the next slide.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just a caveat that we, those tax rates are dependent on councils tax rate hearing.
[SPEAKER_02]: They are dependent on the department of revenue, uh, approving our tax rate recap.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there is a rounding issue that comes in because we split the rate.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I can't go all the way past the levy.
[SPEAKER_02]: So occasionally the tax rate will be, you know, off by a penny that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's to say, um,
[SPEAKER_02]: We're done with evaluation.
[SPEAKER_02]: We want to be as transparent as possible as people are starting early voting on this issue.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I believe this weekend.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we will commit this week to as long as the mayor's office communications team can help me do it, get all the values and the impact of these overrides on our website.
[SPEAKER_02]: Any questions from the council?
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, sure, and just thanks, Ted, I wanna appreciate your hard work getting this done.
[SPEAKER_08]: In October, it usually gets done in January, so it's appreciated.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Scarbelli.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I know that the word transparent gets thrown around, Ted, and I hate for you to get dragged into this, but you weren't part of any financial task force for the override, correct?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, I was not.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Normally, when communities put this into place,
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm told from different communities, different assessors, finance directors, that they usually line this up prior to any budget meetings, so we can help our most vulnerable people in our community understand what any impact it would make.
[SPEAKER_03]: So having this calculation that you're doing for us, and thank you so much for doing it, because I know there were so many questions with the calculations that have been public on the side that you had nothing to do with.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know it came out of a state website, but it didn't truly,
[SPEAKER_03]: calculate the newer assessment.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's correct, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yep, right.
[SPEAKER_03]: So when we look at this and now we're doing it on the 11th hour, the question was normally in your experience, other professionals in your field, this is done usually during budget season.
[SPEAKER_03]: So we can prepare our residents that if there was an increase of 373 median price,
[SPEAKER_03]: They're prepared.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know it sounds minimal to some people because it's only, that's all we keep hearing, it's only.
[SPEAKER_03]: But is it odd that we're doing this so late?
[SPEAKER_02]: Councilor, I think you described the typical circumstance where the vote, you know, as we know, we look at the votes online are done in April or May.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_07]: Appreciate that.
[SPEAKER_07]: Any other questions?
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Collins.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you, President Barras.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you so much for being with us here tonight and for all the legwork that you've been doing to get the FY 25 estimated valuations online months earlier than you otherwise would.
[SPEAKER_11]: Really appreciate that, and I appreciate that it helps folks get a clearer picture of what precisely their bills might look like in the future based on various
[SPEAKER_11]: how the votes go in various directions.
[SPEAKER_11]: So just to make sure that I understand the information that's available, and it would be, is it on the Assessor's Department page or the Finance Department page on the city website?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so I just got the values done today.
[SPEAKER_02]: I just prepared the PowerPoint.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm working with the, going to have to work with the Mayoral Communications Office to get it onto our assessing page.
[SPEAKER_02]: We will also have anyone who doesn't
[SPEAKER_02]: you know, they can call the assessing office and we can look it up very quickly for them.
[SPEAKER_02]: So they want to call in, or if they want to access our website, either way.
[SPEAKER_11]: Great.
[SPEAKER_11]: So up until today, people can call your office or look on the assessor's department website webpage and find the webpage is going to be dependent on like, I'm going to try to get it up this week, but like, it's just however fast we can do it.
[SPEAKER_16]: So probably let's say by Friday.
[SPEAKER_16]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_11]: But
[SPEAKER_11]: We have the FY 24 based calculations and now you're expediting getting the FY 25 based valuations so that people can have even more clarity.
[SPEAKER_11]: Great.
[SPEAKER_11]: Well, thank you so much for updating that ahead of schedule.
[SPEAKER_11]: Appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thanks, Ted.
[SPEAKER_08]: Just two more questions.
[SPEAKER_08]: One, given your estimates, if neither of the overrides pass, based on your estimates, the tax rate would once again be going down.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's correct.
[SPEAKER_08]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_08]: And before today, when you had the approved fiscal 25 values, would it have been possible for anyone to provide an update using anything other than the fiscal 24 values or an estimate?
[SPEAKER_08]: Anyone from the public, not from your office.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, you know, it's possible they might have gotten close, but it's kind of hard to, you know, drill down and get it accurately presented.
[SPEAKER_02]: So yeah, I would say no.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: All right.
[SPEAKER_08]: Any further questions from members of the council?
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Say.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_13]: I understand, you know, one of the council's main priorities going in before
[SPEAKER_13]: Knowing that this might be an option in the coming years was to maximize this senior circuit breaker for the tax deferrals and to push for the senior work-off program to get more of that done.
[SPEAKER_13]: It's my understanding that folks can find out more about the senior tax deferral from the assessor's office, is that correct?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, so there's, as you mentioned, our senior work-off program is staffed, I believe over at least 20 senior work-off participants this year across the city.
[SPEAKER_02]: The senior deferral applications are available as well as the personal exemptions for low-income seniors.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it's kind of two different programs.
[SPEAKER_02]: They have both asset and income limits.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Scarpelli.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: With just a couple more questions, I know that you mentioned that this doesn't have any impact on question six, correct?
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not in fiscal year 25.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it's not enough time to put everything in, correct?
[SPEAKER_03]: We don't know the actual numbers, correct?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I haven't calculated that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, interest rates could change drastically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, but we still don't know how much for question six.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's an open-ended, as it said in the question, there's nothing there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's I, you know, I can't really tell you what the market's going to do right on the on the bond market.
[SPEAKER_03]: All right.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I realize the exemptions are great.
[SPEAKER_03]: but I know that there are options when you do this ahead of time, is to really prepare your seniors.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know the exemptions sound good, but when you read them and you talk to actual people, there are a lot of senior citizens that really don't fit in that category.
[SPEAKER_03]: So there are no other options.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I know the buzzwords easy to say, we do have exemptions, but when you put it apples to apples and you sit with the senior citizen and you go through their situation, I'm sure you know,
[SPEAKER_03]: Mrs. Jones bought her house with her husband 55 years ago for 50,000.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now the house is appraised at $100 million.
[SPEAKER_03]: It really doesn't help what we're offering.
[SPEAKER_03]: So it's a funny number and there could be something done more if we had time for an exemption.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's all I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know that if we had time, this is something we could petition to see if we can really, truly
[SPEAKER_03]: support our senior citizens.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think that must be said.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I think the, the last piece to this, I think that when they look at this and because one question I have Ted is that a lot of people have asked, not just seniors, um, that the, this is like a one time tax.
[SPEAKER_03]: This isn't.
[SPEAKER_03]: So when you see that 4% above your two and a half percent increase, that's going to be compounded year after year after year.
[SPEAKER_03]: This isn't something that's going to go away like debt exclusion, correct?
[SPEAKER_02]: Correct, the levy is set at the new limit and the two and a half is on that new levy.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right, so that'll grow forever.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I think the other piece that people have to understand too, and it's a tough office.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I just, when you hear the misconceptions, I just need your input to educate our residents in understanding that, again, I believe the mayor said her house is only $13.
[SPEAKER_03]: Some others here said their house is $40 a month or whatever, and we can handle that.
[SPEAKER_03]: That might be the first year, but again, we were told, I think someone from your office emailed us and said that we'll be reassessing again in 2025 for 2026 using the data for 2023, correct?
[SPEAKER_02]: Um, so the 25 values used calendar year, 23 sales.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's correct.
[SPEAKER_02]: So next year we're going to see a 26 using calendar year, 24 sales.
[SPEAKER_08]: So we're going to say that happens every year.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's a every year.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's good.
[SPEAKER_03]: So it happens.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you for helping with that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So it increases.
[SPEAKER_03]: So
[SPEAKER_03]: Again, when this tax goes in, it's now assessed again, the homes will be assessed again.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so I can't predict what the final 24 numbers are going to be, but it could go up, could go down, depends on the market, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: Right, but we're seeing that most assessments, because I could tell you, I'm dealing with my own family members that are looking at a $400 increase per month for his new assessment.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's real.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I think that what people also have to understand is that it's not just the home tax.
[SPEAKER_03]: You've seen their cars.
[SPEAKER_03]: Motor vehicle excise.
[SPEAKER_03]: Vehicle excise tax is going to go up.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're going to see the CPA tax because your homes are going to be assessed higher now, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: So now the CPA tax will also be taxed higher.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're going to see that a little bit higher, correct?
[SPEAKER_03]: OK, that's yeah, that's generally correct.
[SPEAKER_08]: Generally, the CPA was included in the calculations presented.
[SPEAKER_03]: OK, so thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: So what you're seeing is it's not just it's not just an override tax.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's an override tax.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's compounded year after year.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a tax that increases in the CPA as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the excise tax that increases as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's so much more than just 13.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's my point I'm trying to say.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know it's easy to look at a site that wasn't put forth by our office because we know that although it's correct, the numbers that my colleagues did put out there on a page, it does give the numbers that are true and factual, but
[SPEAKER_03]: That didn't include the assessments that residents had, and I'll use my brother's example, because his house was appraised at, on the calculations, at $800,000.
[SPEAKER_03]: His house is now appraised at $1.2 million.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's why we're seeing that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's not odd.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is family-owned homes that
[SPEAKER_03]: that we passed on to generation to generation, just like most people in this room.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, but thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know I'm monopolizing the time because I think it's important, because these are the questions the people that are sitting in this room right now and their friends have contacted me and said, we're very confused, Mr. Scappelli.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because even something simple as, Mr. Scott Pelley, why are we fighting for $7.5 million for a new high school?
[SPEAKER_03]: And I'm like, no, no, this has nothing to do with the new high school.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's down the line.
[SPEAKER_03]: And people understanding that, well, this is a fight between schools and kids and senior citizens.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's not true at all.
[SPEAKER_03]: We just want to make sure all the information's out so every resident understands the impact.
[SPEAKER_03]: that, and we could talk about solutions as we go, because there are solutions.
[SPEAKER_03]: There were solutions back in April, but thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thanks, Ted.
[SPEAKER_08]: Really appreciate the hard work of your office.
[SPEAKER_08]: Just want to note, certainly this council, and you've shared some recently, has taken several votes to maximize the exemptions allowed by state law.
[SPEAKER_08]: If you see anything more that we could do on that front, I believe in 2022, we voted to tie it to the law so that we wouldn't have to constantly be updating it as the state did.
[SPEAKER_08]: If you see anything, please let us know.
[SPEAKER_08]: Certainly our intent is to be maximizing everything, and I believe we have.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, just the HEROES Act that just was passed allows us to tie the veteran personal exemption to cost of living.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that just passed, so it would be a new action by council.
[SPEAKER_08]: Awesome.
[SPEAKER_08]: We will do that.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_08]: All right.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm going to read off the rules one more time.
[SPEAKER_08]: We're going to move to question and answer.
[SPEAKER_08]: All right, so we're gonna follow the following rules for this part of the meeting.
[SPEAKER_08]: Members of the public will have one minute to ask one question.
[SPEAKER_08]: Members of the public will not be able to ask a second question until everyone has had a chance to ask their first.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm gonna verbally request that we not ask duplicative or largely similar questions and may move on to the next question.
[SPEAKER_08]: If a duplicative or similar question is asked, counselors will have up to two minutes per counselor to answer each question.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm requesting that counselors not provide duplicative or largely similar answers to answers that have been already provided by other counselors and may move on to the next counselor for an answer if that happens.
[SPEAKER_08]: And after members of the public have had the chance to ask their first question, we'll open the floor to a second question or a short public comment.
[SPEAKER_08]: And I'm going to be alternating between the chamber and Zoom.
[SPEAKER_08]: So we will start at the podium.
[SPEAKER_08]: Mr. Castanetti, you'll have one minute to ask a question and then we'll go to Zoom after answers from counselors.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you, Councilor Beers, Andrew Castagnetti, Cushing Street, East Medford, Massachusetts.
[SPEAKER_12]: I'm very devastated that we lost Larry Lepore.
[SPEAKER_12]: He's a wonderful man.
[SPEAKER_12]: He's a good friend.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is the microphone on?
[SPEAKER_03]: Andrew, is the mic, turn the mic down.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, there you go.
[SPEAKER_12]: I'm sorry we lost Larry Lepore.
[SPEAKER_12]: The minutes, thank you.
[SPEAKER_12]: I hope you all had a good Columbus Day yesterday, because he is the greatest world naval explorer in history.
[SPEAKER_12]: He said the world is round, not flat.
[SPEAKER_12]: He had more courage than all of us combined.
[SPEAKER_12]: He is also a hero to me and others.
[SPEAKER_12]: Also hope you had a good Indigenous People's Day.
[SPEAKER_12]: I also hope the same for the Jews.
[SPEAKER_12]: in the Mideast, because they've been there more than 2,000 years.
[SPEAKER_12]: Now let's talk Prop 2.5 overrides.
[SPEAKER_12]: As I told you all before, Method never had a Prop 2.5 override.
[SPEAKER_12]: We're not Winchester.
[SPEAKER_12]: We are all Method here, a working class town city.
[SPEAKER_12]: Our problem is fiscal management and lack of building maintenance, period, full stop.
[SPEAKER_12]: My ask is for you honorable city councils to stop this real estate tax assault on we the homeowners and leave the people alone.
[SPEAKER_12]: Stop the bleeding.
[SPEAKER_12]: We're already having trouble with all this Biden inflation.
[SPEAKER_08]: Andy, thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: That's a minute.
[SPEAKER_12]: Um, does it have one sentence?
[SPEAKER_08]: Go ahead and say the sentence minutes up.
[SPEAKER_12]: I mean, it's up.
[SPEAKER_12]: You can say the sentence.
[SPEAKER_12]: Andy is a minute up.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yes, sir.
[SPEAKER_12]: It is up.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: All right.
[SPEAKER_12]: My motto was this.
[SPEAKER_12]: No, no further taxation.
[SPEAKER_12]: He's allowing me to speak.
[SPEAKER_12]: Do you want to interrupt me?
[SPEAKER_08]: Let's just hold on here, guys.
[SPEAKER_08]: Like, I can't believe we're doing this on the first question.
[SPEAKER_12]: This is crazy.
[SPEAKER_12]: Stop it.
[SPEAKER_12]: My motto was this, no more further taxation without proper representation.
[SPEAKER_12]: The end.
[SPEAKER_12]: Andrew said that dark call.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you, Andy.
[SPEAKER_08]: Does anyone have a response?
[SPEAKER_08]: Your time.
[SPEAKER_08]: Anyone want to answer the question?
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Lemke, you have two minutes.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm going to try to respond to one thing there.
[SPEAKER_04]: I didn't hear a specific question, but you did say that Medford's not like our surrounding towns.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, I said Winchester.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, we're not like Winchester.
[SPEAKER_04]: 90% of cities in the state of Massachusetts have had an override.
[SPEAKER_04]: Medford has one of the low, has
[SPEAKER_04]: one of the lowest operating budgets per capita of any mid-sized city in the state of Massachusetts.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that is in large part because we are one of the 10% of cities that has never had an override.
[SPEAKER_04]: So you're right, we are not like our neighbors that have had overrides and we have less money for it.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: We'll move on to the next question, unless anyone else has an answer.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you, Andy.
[SPEAKER_08]: We'll go to Michelle B on Zoom.
[SPEAKER_08]: Name and address for the record, please.
[SPEAKER_08]: And you'll have one minute to ask your question.
[SPEAKER_10]: Hi, my name is Michelle Barkson.
[SPEAKER_10]: I live at 23 Diane Road in Medford.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you everyone for your work with this important progress.
[SPEAKER_10]: My question is, can you please speak to the ramifications of what will happen if questions seven and eight do not pass specifically to the school budget and how that will affect our students
[SPEAKER_10]: learning environment.
[SPEAKER_10]: I just want to remind everyone listening that teacher working conditions are student learning conditions, and those two things cannot be separated.
[SPEAKER_10]: As a public school teacher in another town, I can speak to that being very true.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I would love to hear, or I would not love to hear, but I want to hear what might happen if these don't pass so we can highlight the importance of them passing.
[SPEAKER_10]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'll go to Vice President Collins, then
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you, President Behrs.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you for the question.
[SPEAKER_11]: I wanna add a disclaimer that I obviously sitting behind this rail on this date, I'm not a school committee member.
[SPEAKER_11]: I don't have that level of granular knowledge of the school department and the school department makes its own budget.
[SPEAKER_11]: The city council does not.
[SPEAKER_11]: That being said, I have discussed this matter extensively with people in the community, with people involved in the schools, with school committee members.
[SPEAKER_11]: I understand that
[SPEAKER_11]: you know, what we stand to lose if these questions do not pass includes, you know, some of the stuff that people involved in the schools may remember from when we had to cut the school's budget during the pandemic.
[SPEAKER_11]: And that includes eliminating positions, including teachers, nurses, behavioral specialists, literary coaches.
[SPEAKER_11]: We lose the opportunity to add programming within the schools that supplement the curriculum that is state mandated.
[SPEAKER_11]: So, some programming that is really beloved by students and their families, such as arts and musical curricula.
[SPEAKER_11]: We lose the opportunity to augment the student experience with those types of classes.
[SPEAKER_11]: We lose the opportunity to augment the student experience with more people in supportive roles.
[SPEAKER_11]: such as therapists, nurses, people outside of the classroom who are nevertheless there to make sure that students can thrive in our schools and achieve the best learning that they can?
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_11]: These two questions combined also limit our ability to offer competitive and living wages to the many, many people who work in our schools and offer
[SPEAKER_11]: students the experience that they really deserve.
[SPEAKER_11]: We know that we need to be offering living wages to our teachers and paras and all school staff because it's the right thing to do.
[SPEAKER_11]: We also know that we need to be able to do that in order to keep these people in our school system so that our students are served in the way that they deserve.
[SPEAKER_11]: This will also have impacts on building maintenance.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thank you, Councilor Collins.
[SPEAKER_13]: Sorry, Councilor Sang.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_13]: Councilor Collins, I think, touched on a list of positions that, subject to the school committee talks, might be at stake.
[SPEAKER_13]: Literacy specialists, school nurses, guidance, mental health specialists, increased class sizes.
[SPEAKER_13]: You know, it's not fear-mongering when a lot of this stuff has already happened.
[SPEAKER_13]: happening in our school districts.
[SPEAKER_13]: We've already had to make a lot of these cuts.
[SPEAKER_13]: We've already found it hard to retain our long-term teachers.
[SPEAKER_13]: We also need to take a step back and look at this big picture-wise.
[SPEAKER_13]: We know when we invest in our schools, your investment and your value of your property goes up as well, that your public safety around you, crime goes down and public safety goes up.
[SPEAKER_13]: And so we, I think there are longer, bigger picture benefits to everyone, even if you don't have kids in the schools.
[SPEAKER_13]: Touching on the roads real quick, because that's also a part of question seven.
[SPEAKER_13]: I think we need to look at the opportunity we lose.
[SPEAKER_13]: Now, the basic role of government, of local government is to fix your potholes and to send your kids to school.
[SPEAKER_13]: And if we're not, if we can't do either of those, then we're not, you know,
[SPEAKER_13]: we're not doing our jobs, but we were asking the voters to give us the tools to do our jobs.
[SPEAKER_13]: And something about question seven with the roads and sidewalks is that it would give us a crew that would work full time on fixing our potholes and sidewalks in the city.
[SPEAKER_13]: That's something that we don't have right now because our resources are too constrained.
[SPEAKER_13]: And that's something that I believe if passed, will show, will give our residents a real benefit, a real benefit that you can see and live in our city.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thank you for the question.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let me start off by first saying that, unfortunately, this administration has divided this community for the children in the schools and the seniors or the homeowners or renters.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I say shame on this administration, shame on this council, shame on the financial task force, because the bottom line is this.
[SPEAKER_03]: this group knew that we were heading in some tough waters back in June 20th of 2023.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you could see that in a city council budget meeting when council beers met with the mayor behind closed doors to set up some sort of deal.
[SPEAKER_03]: We didn't know what that deal was, but they created a financial task force and that financial task force put together a plan of an override without anybody's knowledge, anybody's input or any,
[SPEAKER_03]: or any community participation.
[SPEAKER_03]: There are no issues with our school department.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is a fair tactic and fair tactic only for the fact that we should remember this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Back in April, back in May, back in June, when the city had $25 million in free cash, it was my responsibility to bring forth that we take that $5 million
[SPEAKER_03]: levy that budget, make sure there were no cuts, understand the process, and then move forward to see if we truly need an override, which I never said that should never be an option.
[SPEAKER_03]: But to hear parents and teachers and friends and family say, George, explain this to me.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Villes knew that this was going to be a devastating situation, but it could have been solved and still could be solved with free cash.
[SPEAKER_03]: We have plenty of free cash in the system not to turn the city upside down or divide the city.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, remember, I'll leave you with this.
[SPEAKER_03]: What we're asking for in the budget
[SPEAKER_03]: in this override doesn't mean you'll get exactly what you think you're gonna get.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because all these cuts were made to set up this override as a fair tactic.
[SPEAKER_03]: So please, Dr. Scarpelli is not against the children.
[SPEAKER_03]: We just hope that people understand that this could be solved.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Council President.
[SPEAKER_03]: Appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Just gonna say a few things really quick.
[SPEAKER_08]: the council.
[SPEAKER_08]: Oh, I'll go to, okay.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'll wait.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilors are councilor.
[SPEAKER_08]: Let me two minutes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Um, one thing that I want to mention about to answer the
[SPEAKER_01]: Zoom residents question, Michelle.
[SPEAKER_01]: One thing that we would lose if this question, question seven in particular, does not pass, it's a very specific, I believe it's question seven, it's a very specific thing about the high school schedule, which right now does not allow
[SPEAKER_01]: some of the students who are taking specific classes, I believe it's in the vocational school, to take certain art classes, theater classes, visual arts.
[SPEAKER_01]: It limits our students in being the fully well-rounded students that we want them to be able to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you're in high school, you want to be able to explore
[SPEAKER_01]: figure out who you are, what you're interested in.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we want to give all of our students the best opportunity to be everything that they can be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we don't want to limit them because we haven't had the opportunity to expand the schedule to really experiment with what that can be.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will also say that in 2019, I worked for the school district and I knew then that we were underfunded.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I started thinking about running for city council to make something like this happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: This has been happening for a long time.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have had underfunded
[SPEAKER_01]: schools for a long time.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this has been in the works for a long time.
[SPEAKER_01]: This has needed to happen for quite a long time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Councilor Lemming, two minutes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Saying that we can address the budgetary problems of the Medford public school system with free cash is like me saying the government gave me a $1,200 check from COVID.
[SPEAKER_04]: So I don't have to look for a job right now because that check is going to last me another
[SPEAKER_04]: another two weeks.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: The government gave us, the government gave the city of Medford some money.
[SPEAKER_04]: It was a one-time thing from COVID and the proposal that we can plug ongoing costs from free cash.
[SPEAKER_04]: All that would do is drain our reserves and we'd be back at square one in five years.
[SPEAKER_04]: If these overrides don't pass straight up, there will be layoffs in the school system and the roads will continue to be in disrepair.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you, nope, one time, sorry.
[SPEAKER_08]: It's question eight, yeah.
[SPEAKER_08]: And any other councilors wanna go?
[SPEAKER_08]: I'll be quick, give myself two minutes.
[SPEAKER_08]: Just want to list it out.
[SPEAKER_08]: Two literacy interventionists, two behavior specialists, one nurse, four teachers, and four department heads.
[SPEAKER_08]: Those were cuts that were postponed because we used one-time funds this year to plug the hole.
[SPEAKER_08]: There's another 25 positions, two school counselors, four classroom teachers, two security monitors.
[SPEAKER_08]: one attendance and re-engagement officer, five paraprofessionals, and 12.2 additional staff members that are on one-time federal funds this year.
[SPEAKER_08]: So it's about 35 to 45 staff in the schools.
[SPEAKER_08]: We would not have a
[SPEAKER_08]: permanent dedicated street and sidewalk crew to use the machines that we already own.
[SPEAKER_08]: We don't have enough staff in the DPW to actually run those machines four times a week.
[SPEAKER_08]: And there would not be significant room for looking at additional compensation for educators, paraprofessionals, and staff in our schools, whether that's just to raise their pay, because it's a contract year, or whether that is when we're talking about extending potentially 10 to 15 minutes to school day to align vocational with the comprehensive high school schedule.
[SPEAKER_08]: or just to address any issues on time on learning.
[SPEAKER_08]: So thanks.
[SPEAKER_08]: That's what we would lose.
[SPEAKER_08]: We will go to the podium.
[SPEAKER_08]: Name and address for the record, please.
[SPEAKER_08]: And you have one minute to ask one question.
[SPEAKER_15]: John McGonigal, 20 Ross Street, Medford.
[SPEAKER_15]: Question is the residential
[SPEAKER_15]: Override not override the assessments on each house that are going around now.
[SPEAKER_15]: They're roughly around $60,000 for each house for the last three years So if you take the $60,000 and you multiply it by your nine dollars a thousand You're coming up to five hundred forty dollars a house every single year so Multiply that by your twenty six thousand seven hundred houses that are in Medford which is
[SPEAKER_15]: $13,857,000.
[SPEAKER_15]: My question is, where does that go?
[SPEAKER_08]: So that's not actually how the tax rates calculated.
[SPEAKER_08]: The assessor just presented the information.
[SPEAKER_08]: The levy changes based on the two and a half and new growth.
[SPEAKER_08]: So it's only about 6 million this year, not 13 million.
[SPEAKER_08]: And generally that amount is only going towards fixed costs.
[SPEAKER_08]: So we have union contracts, increasing health insurance costs, increasing retirement pension costs, increased costs of materials and pavement.
[SPEAKER_08]: So that's generally what the normal two and a half new growth increase goes towards.
[SPEAKER_15]: And with that assessment, one thing you didn't put in as a cost increase to the citizens of Medford is your homeowner's insurance.
[SPEAKER_15]: Your homeowner's insurance, if your residential area goes up 160,000 over three years, that's going to be probably another three, $400 a year that I don't think anyone's talked about yet.
[SPEAKER_08]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_15]: So that was my question.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Does anyone else want to answer that question?
[SPEAKER_03]: I think if I can.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think I heard some similar situations with, I know what the assessor came up, he gave us medium price homes, but we're seeing real people have told me that this is what we're seeing.
[SPEAKER_03]: We're seeing the increase close to $60,000, most homes that you're seeing an increase at a higher percentage rate.
[SPEAKER_03]: And again, on top of all of what we talked about,
[SPEAKER_03]: with this, so it's not the $13 a month, the $40 a month.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the pieces that this gentleman just said is the understanding that I never thought that our home insurance now will now increase.
[SPEAKER_03]: So again, this isn't them against us.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is understanding that we have viable options right now to fix this.
[SPEAKER_03]: with free cash and then work together to see how we can have an open process to really include all the stakeholders to make sure that, uh, that no one is hurt.
[SPEAKER_03]: So thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Any other questions from answers from members of the council?
[SPEAKER_08]: Seeing none, we'll go to the next question on zoom.
[SPEAKER_08]: We'll go to Lizzie Charbonneau.
[SPEAKER_08]: Lizzie, you have one minute to ask one question.
[SPEAKER_08]: Please provide your name and address for the record.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, my name is Lizzy Sharpener.
[SPEAKER_00]: I live at 18 Stickney Road.
[SPEAKER_00]: So my question is, why do we need to do the override now?
[SPEAKER_00]: And in particular, I'm curious to hear you speak to the rising inflation the last few years that has exceeded the rate that the levee limit has been able to increase as well as which costs increase even faster than inflation.
[SPEAKER_00]: My understanding is that insurance and pensions and other fixed costs that the city has to
[SPEAKER_00]: for our rising faster than inflation and faster than those levy increases.
[SPEAKER_00]: I would also like to hear you speak to the increased costs in schools that are exceeding inflation rates and our inability as a city to provide some basic infrastructure like maintenance of roads due to our low budget.
[SPEAKER_00]: So if you could speak to why we need this override now, especially in relation to those items, I would like to hear that.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Go to Councilor Callahan.
[SPEAKER_14]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_14]: So, I think this is a basic question why do we need these overrides.
[SPEAKER_14]: And as Councilor Lemming stated, we, we actually I will say we rank 320th out of 351 Massachusetts cities and towns.
[SPEAKER_14]: in the amount of budget we have per person.
[SPEAKER_14]: So, we have less budget per person than every other city in Massachusetts and we have less budget per person than 90% of towns.
[SPEAKER_14]: All of the others that spend less per person than we do are much smaller than we are.
[SPEAKER_14]: Our budget is too small to provide the services that we need.
[SPEAKER_14]: I want to go ahead, I don't know, this is probably gonna be too small for people to see, but this is a chart of our budget.
[SPEAKER_14]: And this large blue area here is the schools.
[SPEAKER_14]: That is what we are looking for more money for, so we cannot cut that.
[SPEAKER_14]: The next one is insurance.
[SPEAKER_14]: Insurance is something that we are required to have by law.
[SPEAKER_14]: We cannot cut that.
[SPEAKER_14]: The next one is pensions.
[SPEAKER_14]: Those are contractual.
[SPEAKER_14]: We cannot cut pensions.
[SPEAKER_14]: The next two are our fire department and our police department.
[SPEAKER_14]: My feeling is that no one on either side of the Prop 2.5 debate wants to drastically cut our police and fire departments.
[SPEAKER_14]: The next one after police and fire is our roads.
[SPEAKER_14]: And I appreciate your question about the roads, because underfunding of our roads has caused us to have $67 million in essentially road debt.
[SPEAKER_14]: It's called the road backlog.
[SPEAKER_08]: 30 seconds.
[SPEAKER_14]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_14]: After that, our bonds, which we are also required to pay, and then we get down to smaller things, the library facilities, many other small departments.
[SPEAKER_14]: None of these, if we even cut the entire department, could possibly fix the $3 million to $5 million that we need for the school budget.
[SPEAKER_14]: Our budget is simply too small.
[SPEAKER_14]: I'll let someone else talk about which of these increases more than inflation.
[SPEAKER_14]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Go to Councilor Lemming, two minutes.
[SPEAKER_04]: So adding on to what Councilor Callahan said, partially this is due to the lingering costs of COVID, which resulted in both decreased funding going to the school system, partially that was just because you have fewer students going into public schools, and partially because
[SPEAKER_04]: there was a lot of activity in the healthcare system from COVID.
[SPEAKER_04]: So there is a sort of a, so the cost of health insurance, which we have to pay ended up rising.
[SPEAKER_04]: Those are some of the more short term reasons why we need this now.
[SPEAKER_04]: Longer term,
[SPEAKER_04]: The way that Prop 2 NAP is designed is the total amount of money that the city can take in basically can't go up by more than 2.5% every year.
[SPEAKER_04]: While inflation has averaged for the past 44 years at 3.1% over time, that compounds.
[SPEAKER_04]: So the budget today
[SPEAKER_04]: is only a fraction, well, it's only about 78% as valuable today as it was back in 1980.
[SPEAKER_04]: So Prop 2.5 has this effect long-term on municipal budget where it squeezes resources.
[SPEAKER_04]: Most cities in Massachusetts have addressed this with the intended mechanism for overcoming this, which is periodic elections.
[SPEAKER_04]: This is just the first time we're doing that, and that's part of the reason.
[SPEAKER_04]: the fact that we're so late to the game there is part of the reason that again we are 320 out of 351 cities in terms of our per capita budget and that is the reason why our schools could definitely be doing
[SPEAKER_04]: better.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is the reason why you see so many potholes.
[SPEAKER_04]: This is one step in addressing that situation.
[SPEAKER_04]: Once again, free cash, one time funding is not an actual longer term solution.
[SPEAKER_04]: If we just went with free cash, that would be drained in a couple of years, even shorter than the four to five year span I put, I said earlier, and then that's time.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Go to Councilor Scarpelli you have two minutes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I think my council is not understanding the free cash should be used now to fix a problem now, which we have, and I appreciate the clarification it's only $3 million to Councilor Kelly I just said to fix the school budget, but the key issue isn't
[SPEAKER_03]: isn't the process of getting this fixed now.
[SPEAKER_03]: The problem that we've had, and we could use the pandemic and use the pandemic over and over again, but what neighboring communities are doing during the pandemic with the infrastructure money that was given through ARPA, that wasn't intended for, for the roads and sidewalks that you're asking for right now.
[SPEAKER_03]: Our mayor didn't do that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Our mayor had to balance our budget through ESSER and ARPA funding.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the easy way out.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's like paying your mortgage with a credit card.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I'll tell you why.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is the difference.
[SPEAKER_03]: Everybody hasn't said it, but the difference between why we're here and we're in trouble is because of new growth.
[SPEAKER_03]: New growth is what pushes
[SPEAKER_03]: our value, our income up.
[SPEAKER_03]: It gives us more tax base.
[SPEAKER_03]: It brings more money so we can do all the things we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_03]: This mayor has done nothing.
[SPEAKER_03]: We haven't had shovel in the ground in five and a half years.
[SPEAKER_03]: We're talking about, I know my council friends have gone out and told people that Massachusetts is the number one, Medford is the number one community new growth in permitting.
[SPEAKER_03]: Wrong, I sat with the commissioner.
[SPEAKER_03]: Permitting their fine, the biggest concerns we're having, look at the process that she lost fighting 40B projects.
[SPEAKER_03]: One project alone was $3 to $5 million in permits.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then an additional $7 to $9 million that would have come in as new growth.
[SPEAKER_03]: And one job that she fought in court, lost, and appealed it, and this group had to leave.
[SPEAKER_03]: The problem isn't our tax base, because our assessments are up.
[SPEAKER_03]: And we're paying more than anybody else in neighboring communities because our assessments are so high.
[SPEAKER_03]: I will share my last point.
[SPEAKER_03]: Neighbor communities per child, Malden, Arlington, Winchester, between 15 and 17,000.
[SPEAKER_03]: Medford, we pay $22,000 per student.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it a management issue or is it really we don't have enough money?
[SPEAKER_03]: Think about it because it's public.
$22,000.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Go to Councilor Seng.
[SPEAKER_13]: Councilor Seng, and then Councilor Collins.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_13]: Councilor Seng, two minutes.
[SPEAKER_13]: Touching very quickly on the topic of new growth, I think our council is very aware that new growth is the priority for Medford.
[SPEAKER_13]: And so when we look at the last three years of new growth, so the last two years plus the estimates that we have right in front of us presented by the assessor,
[SPEAKER_13]: It actually shows that our first round of zoning reform, which was the first round in almost 50 years of zoning reform, actually has led to the most new growth our city has seen in decades.
[SPEAKER_13]: We are currently working on round two of zoning reform and we are very, very optimistic that that new growth will help us achieve more financial stability going into the future as long as these questions pass.
[SPEAKER_13]: I think
[SPEAKER_13]: I also have this chart right here.
[SPEAKER_13]: I'll do what Councilor Callahan does.
[SPEAKER_13]: It's not really easy to see, but you can see that the new growth is growing, is growing throughout the last few years with the reforms that we've instituted.
[SPEAKER_13]: We are permitting more units as Councilor- Could you put that chart back up?
[SPEAKER_08]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_13]: We're also permitting more new,
[SPEAKER_13]: New units than ever before, as Councilor Scarpoli states.
[SPEAKER_13]: Here's the thing, because on the topic of new growth, we're getting a little bit away from the why now question.
[SPEAKER_13]: We have a plan, that plan is being implemented, and the results are already bearing fruit.
[SPEAKER_13]: We fell behind decades.
[SPEAKER_13]: I mean, that's just the truth.
[SPEAKER_13]: And I don't agree with every decision that the mayors previous have taken, but we are in a situation now where we need
[SPEAKER_13]: to face the facts as they are now.
[SPEAKER_13]: High inflation, lack of new growth over the last few decades means that we need to do a short-term plan, which is these three questions, and then a long-term plan, which is investing in new growth, which is what our zoning efforts are.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_13]: Councillor Collins.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you, President Behrs.
[SPEAKER_11]: I appreciate the discussion from my fellow councilors on this topic.
[SPEAKER_11]: I won't go into the topic of new growth.
[SPEAKER_11]: My fellow councilors have covered that.
[SPEAKER_11]: We are very optimistic about how the council's current work on zoning and permitting, which we've been keeping up for two terms, will continue to accelerate new growth and augment the city's operating budget to the greatest extent possible.
[SPEAKER_11]: I do just want to note that on the issue of free cash, just to, I think,
[SPEAKER_11]: Different ways of framing the issue are helpful for me, maybe for other people.
[SPEAKER_11]: It's no secret that we accrued free cash over several years, and that was not dispersed into savings accounts where it could be used and spent on capital expenditures because our city, unlike almost every other city and town in Massachusetts, before this year did not have any stabilization accounts.
[SPEAKER_11]: Now we do.
[SPEAKER_11]: That means that that money can go to the purposes that I think
[SPEAKER_11]: City staff and many residents really wanted it to be going to expected it to be going to all along.
[SPEAKER_11]: Things like capital expenses and also repairing our infrastructure.
[SPEAKER_11]: Putting aside some of that money that's already been allocated to things that people can see out on the street, helping our DPW and other departments improve life and do basic maintenance in the city.
[SPEAKER_11]: Even if you say, okay, let's forget some of those capital expenditures.
[SPEAKER_11]: Let's pretend that we still have $25 million in free cash just using an easy number.
[SPEAKER_11]: That's one-eighth of the city's annual operating budget, which means, you know, if it's one-eighth, you can understand how quickly we would run through that if we were using that as things to plug the hole in the budget.
[SPEAKER_11]: And I do want to emphasize that doesn't include any capital expenses whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_11]: Going back to the resident's question on why now, I think it comes down to we know that free cash is not sustainable.
[SPEAKER_11]: We know that we're already full steam on new growth, but we need more and better funding and services for our residents now.
[SPEAKER_11]: And I think the question is, do we want to punish residents and students for past shortcomings by failing to invest now?
[SPEAKER_11]: Or do we want to take this opportunity to start making Medford better for all residents and students in the public schools?
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you, Councilor Collins.
[SPEAKER_08]: I think everybody went on that.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'd like to avoid everybody answering every question if we can at all possible, but everyone did give a different answer, which is appreciated context.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm just going to be brief myself to ignore my own advice and say, light poles are falling down.
[SPEAKER_08]: We had a meeting two weeks ago where a light pole fell on a public way, and luckily it happened at night, so it didn't hit a car or a person and hurt them.
[SPEAKER_08]: I mean, that's the situation that we're in.
[SPEAKER_08]: We have finally,
[SPEAKER_08]: appropriated some funds to a capital stabilization fund.
[SPEAKER_08]: We have a paper on the meeting at seven o'clock to look at that.
[SPEAKER_08]: We are in a historic multi-decade deficit where we have massive needs.
[SPEAKER_08]: The free cash that is being spoken of is spoken for.
[SPEAKER_08]: It is spoken for, it needs to go to our roads, it needs to go to our schools, it needs to go to fix things that are already broken.
[SPEAKER_08]: And thank you, please stop, thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: And that's just reality.
[SPEAKER_08]: If we use that to plug operating budget holes, we'll have to plug those holes with new revenue in the future.
[SPEAKER_08]: We can't wait for the new growth from our new zoning, which will take five to 10 years to propagate.
[SPEAKER_08]: And I don't think any of us want more light posts falling in the sink, we certainly
[SPEAKER_08]: should be grateful that so far they've only been falling at night.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: We'll go to the podium for the next question.
[SPEAKER_08]: You have one minute to ask one question.
[SPEAKER_08]: Name and address for the record, please.
[SPEAKER_09]: My name is Maureen Tardelli, 11 Chester Avenue, Medford.
[SPEAKER_09]: And this is my question.
[SPEAKER_09]: where financial professionals, business owners, residents, firefighters, school administrators, teachers, parents, the chief assessor, and the DPW commissioner, part of the financial task force.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you for your question.
[SPEAKER_08]: Would anyone like to answer the question?
[SPEAKER_08]: Vice President Collins.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_11]: The financial task force was a group explicitly made up of elected to consider the question of what we would put before our elected bodies to deal with solutions around this problem.
[SPEAKER_11]: However, I feel really comfortable in saying that all of the.
[SPEAKER_11]: above types of people, city staff, members of the community, were consulted in various ways, formally and informally, throughout this process.
[SPEAKER_11]: Some that people talked to, some that members of the financial task force talked to while we were considering these matters that were discussed in our meetings.
[SPEAKER_11]: Some of that were explicitly consulted.
[SPEAKER_11]: And others that have just been part of this greater conversation around what should we do with about what should we do about chronic underfunding in Medford over the course of months and months and years and years of challenges that have led up to this year in which we are.
[SPEAKER_11]: Working together to try to solve these issues once and for all, instead of having budget season after budget season, where the school budget is essentially held hostage by our inability to raise enough money to add to provide the services that residents.
[SPEAKER_11]: students and teachers expect and deserve.
[SPEAKER_11]: And I also just want to underline, again, that these ballot questions, every single resident, every single voter in Medford, whether you're a parent, a teacher, a union member, somebody who works for the city, who also lives in the city, you get to use your voice.
[SPEAKER_11]: You get to cast your vote.
[SPEAKER_11]: You can vote yes on all three.
[SPEAKER_11]: You can vote no on all three.
[SPEAKER_11]: You can choose which ones you feel comfortable voting yes and voting no on.
[SPEAKER_11]: You are a part of this conversation because every single person who votes gets a vote.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: Any other one?
[SPEAKER_08]: No, that's all I have.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I can, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_03]: Two minutes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: So again, this financial task force was put together without any individual involved in that comment that a young lady put forth.
[SPEAKER_03]: This was done in a bubble.
[SPEAKER_03]: This was done behind closed doors.
[SPEAKER_03]: It wasn't planned to educate our seniors, educate our residents, educate our renters, educate our landlords so they could prepare themselves for what's being asked for.
[SPEAKER_03]: within a vote that was presented, a discussion was presented on a Thursday, voted on a Tuesday.
[SPEAKER_03]: not one community meeting.
[SPEAKER_03]: And as a matter of fact, I will share this with everybody.
[SPEAKER_03]: There was a FOIA request put out by a resident that asked a simple question.
[SPEAKER_03]: They asked for all of the information, minutes for the meetings, any information, letters, any emails, any text messages, with this financial task force, with any building or any entity within the city to figure out if this is needed or how it will be used and how it can work.
[SPEAKER_03]: 150 pages later, all the information that was in that FOIA request were information about when we