Welcome everyone to the meeting of the Medford Charter Study Article 7 subcommittee meeting. Since we don't, this is our first meeting of the subcommittee, so we don't have any minutes to approve or anything like that. So we'll just get started.
So, Maury and Anthony, I don't know, did you have a chance to look over the Google Doc I sent, which, you know, why don't you share it on screen? Which is basically- I had an opportunity to go through it. Okay, great. I did as well. Okay. So, I don't know. I mean, what's the best way to go about this? Should we share screen and go through it that way or just talk through each section? Do you guys find the visual helpful?
doesn't help me, but if it helps Maury, go ahead. Right, right, of course. Okay, so as you can see, Article 7 basically doesn't exist in Medford's charter, so this is going to be a new thing that, I mean, obviously we follow certain
procedures, state laws regarding elections and things like that. But we have the opportunity here to put this in the charter so that residents can actually sort of have an easy way to see how things work and maybe add some details particular to Medford that we would like to include.
The first section was the preliminary elections. I mean, if we're looking at our example charter language, it's all similar, right? Any thoughts on that? Just a thought in general, you know, a lot of the things we may be looking at is, especially when, you know, other committees are looking at three year terms, you know, how this section
would have to kind of cooperate with any changes if we were to do something in regards to three-year terms rather than the two or four. So that's one thing. And the language is
Pretty similar it seems in all the other cities that haven't that you used as an example in the chatter, except for I want to say the, the dates of. Of what on the preliminary election, the dates are always the 3rd. The 3rd week of the preceding month. Yep, and.
That really can't change either, is that correct? I mean, I think it's, I don't know what reason we would change it. And the reason it says odd-numbered year, and as, it's a good point that you make about the three-year terms, Anthony. But, you know, realistically speaking, municipalities in Massachusetts, cities in Massachusetts don't have elections on even-numbered years because of the,
complication with the state elections and the federal elections and they're needing to be two ballots, et cetera. That's why it says odd numbered year and each of the three communities that we're looking at says that.
And I'm guessing most other city charters in the state say it as well. So you do make a good point, but I feel like maybe we should just, I mean, all these sections interact. So if we just sort of make our recommendations and if they have to be revisited because of a decision that the whole committee makes, I think that's okay. Do you agree? Okay. Yeah. Okay. I know in Medford, we've always been the second Tuesday in September.
for our primary or preliminary elections. Instead of the first Tuesday. This says third Tuesday. The first Tuesday following the first Monday. Yeah, right. Well, because Labor Day is always the first Monday. So it's never on the holiday week. So it's always the second Tuesday. However, they want to word it as it's just a matter of that.
So keep second to, I mean, and, you know, keeping, that might be a good idea to keep that, unless we can think of a compelling reason to change it, just because these other cities do it this way. It might be better to keep it the way Medford has done it, because that's what people are familiar with.
we wouldn't want the preliminary election to go by, and people say, oh, wait, it's the first Tuesday now, not the second? I think the top section is dealing with the general election in November. There isn't much here. The preliminary reschedule, the preliminary action to the fourth Tuesday in September. See, we always, Denver's always on the second Tuesday in September.
And then general. Oh, that's the regular election. Thank you. Yes. Thank you, Mark. I was confused because this section is preliminary. So I was, I was. That's general first and then it dovetails into the preliminary. So they have it as the third Tuesday in September. And you're saying we have it in the second. We always have the second Tuesday. Okay. So, um, and does each of these have it on the third? They vary. Yeah.
I think my, you know, so third Tuesday. So let's say we would, do you agree, Anthony, that we could keep second Tuesday for preliminary elections because that's what people are used to? Yes. I think it's fine. The only one thing that I'm a little confused or concerned about is now with, you know, with mail-in voting and stuff with
Those new rules, which I believe are out of the state, we have to follow them regardless. What's in the charter? The charter can't kind of conflict
with the state. I don't think there's anything in the charter regarding mail-in voting because the charter is so old that there was no mail-in voting back then. Right. And I think what we've done here in the city, we can confirm it with the clerk's office, is kind of based up, picked up what the state kind of guidelines are. Like everybody started
early voting last Saturday, and it goes until, I think, this Friday. That's statewide. I think those are the way it goes throughout the entire state. And these are newer charters, and they also don't mention. None of them mention mail-in or early.
I think that, yeah, Anthony, I think we would just continue to follow the state laws on that. This would just, these charters anyway, just set the dates for the actual preliminary election and the general election. Not set the dates, but you know what I mean, just say when they are. So I don't know if it would be a good idea to add things about mail-in or early voting.
We've had a preliminary election where there was mail-in voting. No, not from municipal, you're right. Right, so... Yeah, I think we probably, I think the elections department probably would have to handle that. And the question of whether we could even have that for a municipal election, I don't know.
Well, we did have, you know, mail-in and early voting for, you know, this past election, but we didn't have a preliminary election, which is like super local, you know, so. We didn't even have it for mayor this past time, I don't remember. We did. Yeah, we did. Yeah, we did have early voting. But you're saying we didn't have the mail-in.
But we didn't have a preliminary election. There was only two candidates. So there was- Oh, that's what I mean. Yeah, I didn't remember that we only had two candidates for mayor this time. Well, I don't know. I think- We did have a primary for city council, I believe. This last time? In school committee. No. No. No, we didn't. No.
No, I don't think we did either. I didn't have enough candidates, you know that that you know that because you have to have uh, you have to have over 14 or over 12 on city council. You're right. You're right. I think we only had 13 or 14 candidates. That's right Okay, so the question is do we want to look into whether adding information about early voting or mail-in voting makes sense or do we think that um
Well, I think it would just be if it isn't necessary. If it's not, if it isn't necessary, let's keep it out. Let's not bother. But I don't know if, you know, just it being new in the state and new one that people haven't, you know, people already
Did that piece of their charter, you know? Yep. We can put a disclaimer in, you know, all mail-in and early voting practices will conform to the state regulations or something like that. I will ask the Collins Center if municipalities are starting to add information about early and mail-in voting to their charters.
How's that? Okay. Okay. So that will be good. And as far as what I thought we could do, hang on, I just got to write this down, is kind of create a draft article seven. So these are all very similar. Is there one that anybody liked better than another?
piece of, I think it's in two of them, which isn't necessarily about dates, but about, you know, names on the ballot. Yeah, we have to take out city clerk. Sorry, go ahead. Sorry, go ahead.
just with the, you know, Medford has the incumbents at the top of the ballot, and I saw that many of the newer charters have, you know, drawn by lot for ballot positions. And I read up a little bit on it, and there's some studies out of MIT where it does give the people at the top of the ballot, you know,
an advantage. So I think it'd be wise to kind of move away from that. I know the previous and back in the day the city council just came up several times and they wanted to you know but the way it the way it was where the incumbents are first on the ballot and and you know but I
Thinking of something to look at. So you're suggesting that positioning on the ballot would be done by a lottery process, right? Right. Like, well, I think it's a couple of those there have it that the the clerk, the city clerk. Draws lots or, you know, picks names out of a hat or whatever.
I think we definitely are going to, that is definitely something we're going to talk about. I just want to get through this part first. Okay. I took city clerk out because we don't elect our city clerk and we have not made any decisions that we should and we have not heard from anybody that we should, so I'm taking city clerk out.
And did we want to keep, did we want us to keep second Tuesday? I would keep the second Tuesday. Yes. And... So, candidates for Mayor, Ward Alderman, and Alderman-at-Large? Yep. Councilor-at-Large, Mayor, Councilor-at-Large, Ward City Councilor, and School Committee members. Okay, great. Okay, on the second Tuesday. So, I think that's it, right? I think so.
Okay, so and then there's the details about the special elections for vacancies. Yeah, so I think these are pretty standard. Do we have any? I think it was set up now that if there's a
Let's say the mayor vacancy opens up. If it's within six months of the end of the term, council president now becomes the acting mayor. And that is what's, yeah, that's what we've discussed. Right, and then prior to that, like in the term, I think we have an interim mayor with a special election. What are we doing, within 90 days?
to be held? Yes. But this just says if a special election is to be held, which could theoretically happen. So maybe we could just leave this the way it is, or 28 days before the date established for the special election, a preliminary election. OK, yeah. What they're saying is if there's more than two candidates on the preliminary election, that within 28 days before the
The special election did be a primary. Right. OK. OK. So we're good with this text. And obviously, we can review all this later. But so the next section is preliminary election procedures.
So this establishes number of certified. Okay, so this is an interesting question. Establishing the number of certified signatures required for each office. It looked to me like these other charters make people get more signatures than that. I found this interesting when I was saying it. I thought it was the way we did it, you know. So what do you think about it, Marty?
My feeling is, you know, maybe for mayor, you require more signatures, either 150, 200 signatures, or whatever we determine. I think the Ward-Alderman School Committee and Alderman-at-Large, I think you're okay at the 50. Maybe the Alderman-at-Large, you go to 100, because they're running citywide.
But I think individual districts, I think 50 is a good safe number that someone should be able to get if they want to appear on the ballot relatively easy that we give them an opportunity to be on the ballot. Anthony, what do you think?
I really don't have an opinion. I don't know what it's like to go out and try to get signatures. So I'd really like to just ask a few. I'd like to ask a few of the elected folks, is it a difficult thing to do to get 200 signatures?
Having been a person who has collected signatures for various things, right now it's 50 for everyone in Medford, correct, Maury? I think that's right. I think so. So 50 is pretty easy. What some of these charters had, which I believe was 300 for mayor. I mean, it's not like that would be terribly hard, but I feel like it's probably too many.
just because this is just for getting your name on the ballot, right? Remember, that's all it is. So let's see, I think- 50 for school committee, 50 for ward counselor, 100 for citywide, and 150 for mayor.
I mean, I think that sounds reasonable. That's still an increase for at-large counselors and mayor. But what do you think, Maury? Well, I kind of like it. Just, you know, I mean, you want to make sure that a person that's going to run for mayor or citywide office as an ultimate at-large, that they can at least get to 150 or whatever the amount of signatures we have that would allow them to be a viable candidate.
Yeah, and you could make that argument for 300, right? I guess my concern would be, you know, especially for like, look, we didn't even have enough candidates to have a preliminary election last time. Yeah, I mean, we just we don't, I don't know, I think we didn't want to like, change things too terribly much in terms in regards. So that makes sense. 150 million or 100.
at-large counselors, 50 ward and 50 school committee. Okay, was there anything? Okay, now we have also ballot position. So, right, so right now, just, I have it up here. Right now, Medford is following this mass general law, this right here, section 42 of chapter, what section we are, 54.
So this is just describes what we do and it says except unless the charter otherwise provides, right? But since our charter doesn't otherwise provide, this is what we do and it just describes what we do, which is alphabetical or incumbents first in alphabetical order and then challengers in alphabetical order.
Anthony, I would love to see the study that you mentioned. It comes right up on Google. If you go to ballot position Massachusetts, it'll pop right up.
I like what Anthony is saying. I think it gives everybody a better shot for positioning instead of, you know, if you're an incumbent and your last name begins with A and you're the first one on the ballot year in and year out. There is a distinction. If I were to run, I would be at the top of the list.
It just seems that it's fair. And if you look at the study from the MIT study, they crunched the numbers. And mathematically, it's significant enough for them to be able to kind of draw conclusions. And there's a reason the other town, the other new charters have gone to it.
And what are we using for a time frame that this ballot position will be done a week after it's closed out with sending in to have your signature certified? I don't know. Is it spelled out in any of the other? Well, it's funny. This one doesn't. But yeah, the I think it was does. Right. It says at least 40 days before. And this is for preliminary election. Yeah. At least 40 days before the preliminary. I mean,
And then I was just looking for where they talk about the general election. Hmm, okay. I think that would be down here, ballot position for regular city election. 30 days, yeah, right there, 30 days before the date of the election. That's Melrose. That's Melrose, right. And then let's see, Pittsburgh, Pittsfield, not Pittsburgh.
This drawing shall be conducted on the 4th, Tuesday, and September prior to the regular city election. So that's comparable to 30 days. And then Weymouth just doesn't give that. It just says it will be a drawing. So. I know. They don't have time for him in there.
I know it's for the towns. It's also an opportunity for people that want to make sure people can find them on the ballot. They'll say in their advertisements or in their campaign materials, number seven on the ballot. Or if somebody's down, they'll say, you know, make sure to go down to number 14.
Right now, it's, you know, we're talking about trying to level the playing field in Medford and trying to get people to run in wards and, you know, get people who may not have access to a lot of campaign funds to, you know, have a fair shot. And I think this is one way that we can actually do that. I'm in full agreement.
I think we all are, so that's great. Do we want, and do we think, you know, putting the, you know, at least X number of days before the election, or? I would, myself. I think that's it. Do you think 40 days? It's the simplest.
I mean, as opposed to I'm thinking a lot of these candidates, they have to get all their printed materials. And what Anthony just said is very true that, you know, I'm number 11 on the on your preliminary ballot or something like that.
Trying to think when we close out the primary. If the primary is the second Tuesday in September, I think what we should do is contact the clerk's office to find out when all candidates' signatures have to be in by to be certified. Then we can go from there, I think. Wait, do they have to re-certify? They don't have to re-certify after the preliminary. No, no.
So you're saying ask the clerk. I mean, that's something I, is that, did we see that in the charter? I feel like, you know, also if you look at Pittsfield's is way more comprehensive. Actually, Weymouth's is a little longer, but Melrose's section here is very short, right? So, you know, do we want to go with something more like
more comprehensive. I mean, there's pluses and minuses to putting more detail in, you know, in the charter, right? This gives the date of when they have to have their signatures in, right? So we can put that in the charter.
And you're saying, Roy, we should just keep it the same as it is now and kind of earn the city clerk. I would check with the city clerk to see what he's saying. And also ask him how long it would, you know, he would need to kind of draw these lots. You know what I mean? You know, if he's saying, well, you know, give us a week to do that.
process or two weeks. So we know whether it needs to be 30 days, 40 days or 45 days. So yeah. Okay, I'll contact the clerk and I'll just find that information out just so that because we're in we're in agreement that we want to do this. We just want it to make we want it to work. Yeah, we want to get the candidates. Yeah, exactly.
So I'll find out, I'll get that information. So we talked about ballot position. What else was in this section? Number of certified signatures required. All right, date forms are available. We'll have to, that's also information we can get from the clerk, although that might be the elections department.
We'll figure that out. Position names appear on the ballot and we're not differentiating between the incumbents and the challengers in the drawing, correct? Yeah. Correct. And resolution of ties and defining conditions under which no preliminary election is required. So there's language of that kind of thing here.
It also looks pretty boilerplate, right? Yes. All right. So we can, you know, you guys look this over. Was there anything you thought that we should do different than these charters are doing? No, I think it's a little bit, it's not a point, but I think it's good to kind of have similar process as the other cities and towns just so somebody
Does it get confused? They move from Metro to Mall and they go, oh, they look completely different in this other city. So things have to kind of be similar. And I think just following the other cities is fine. There hasn't been a problem. We haven't heard anything about these. The only thing that we've heard problems about is the
you know, things around mail-in voting and how that's done and boxes and counting and stuff that we're not going to get into in the charter. And if other people have, you know, kind of opinions or ideas around that stuff, if that's something that can be addressed in the charter, which I don't think it can, but
maybe the clerk of the elections department might have some something that they might want us to add or have identified as a problem specific to Medford. But as you know, without that information, I think just kind of following some of these boiler plates would be fine. Okay, thanks.
So this next section is one that it's not in the Medford Charter under section seven, because we don't have section seven, but we do have something in our charter about nonpartisan elections, which is basically restating that local elections are nonpartisan. Interestingly, even though we have a short charter, ours is longer than the other charters. So, I mean, we could probably just keep this the way it is, although I would fix the pronouns and just say,
the candidates instead of his. Okay. That makes sense. Right. And what do you guys think? Is there any, is there, um, that says it all right there. Why make it any more difficult than we have to? Yeah. I mean, like I said, these other charters are, are, are shorter, but you know, since, since it's been in there, we can keep that. All right. So,
I'll take that out and put that in. Okay. So, and any candidate or anything showing the candidate taking out? Okay. Or anything showing how the candidate was nominated in the key? Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, okay, so we can leave that. The next section is about war. Now this is interesting.
because we've heard, so this section establishes number of wards and time frame for review of wards, process of establishing the ward boundaries is defined outside of the charter, right, which is what we've been told is that the state establishes the ward boundaries. Maybe we need to do, I just don't, I need more information because I,
I don't know how you guys feel about this, but I feel like we've been told clearly that the state determines the wards, right? Yes. Right. But the thing is that this, what we've kind of been confusing wards and, you know, a lot of places have voting districts.
which can have multiple wards. And I know that, you know, the Carlin Center had mentioned that it's an issue when there's a question of, you know, certain groups, you know, the lines being drawn and kind of ways that discourages, you know, different communities from voting and things like that. And but like Boston, and I think,
Framingham and a few other, they're voting districts, not necessarily a ward. They could have multiple wards in a district, so. Yeah, I don't know if we're talking semantics there or what, but, you know, based sort of what, whether they're called, because I think I've heard that some people call them wards, they can also be called districts. So I don't know if they're the same thing.
I believe a district can encompass more than one ward. Okay. And often where the problems come up is when they want to move part of one ward into another district. So you're talking about Boston? In Boston, yeah, there was just a big kind of
Brouhar and the Boston City Council about this in this past year or two where the line in South Boston and parts of Dorchester was being moved and one group of city councilors wanted it to stay and another one wanted it to move and it kind of went like right through the middle of a housing development where some people in one part of the housing development
was in one district and the other side or in another district and and that's why I think the colon said it could be become problematic because they were looking at you know kind of what happened in Boston but I don't know if anything like that would happen in the city like Metro especially with demographics or and if it did it would be you know way out in the future. I think that um what I understand is that combining wards
you can run into problems with the state because, I mean, I know that it's very uncommon for cities to combine wards. I'll have to look into Boston. And by the way, Boston is often exempted from state laws. They'll say in cities other than Boston. But when Lowell, for instance, combined wards for their school committee because they had to have ward representation as part of the settlement of the lawsuit that they were facing,
They, I talked to the clerk there and he said that they had to hire a consultant because they had to make sure that they didn't run afoul of the state laws because wards are drawn in particular ways and they have to be, if you combine them, they have to be contiguous and the population numbers are an issue, et cetera.
So I think that it's complicated, but I don't know that that's what this section of the charter is talking about. It's not talking about combining wards. I think they're so similar. What do we use? We use wards and precincts. So in every ward in the city seems to have two precincts now since they redesigned things back. Ward 1 is 1112, 2122, 3132.
You have the eight wards with two precincts within those wards. Right. And you're right. This is pretty much, I mean, I think Melrose is, well, Pittsfields is slightly shorter, but they're very similar. This is pretty boilerplate language. My question is more sort of what does it mean for the city council to review the wards if the state defines the wards anyway? I'm curious about that.
But I'm noticing Pittsville says it, Wayman says it. Yeah. They're all saying that. Yeah. Does the city council draw it up and then submit it to the state and the state reviews it? Is that what they're meaning? Yeah. I don't know. I don't know.
So let's, what if we just say, well, we're probably gonna go with the boilerplate language, but we have more questions about this section and what it means in conjunction with the state's responsibility to draw the wards. Because they also say the wards, the precincts are established under the general law. So there's a state law that probably dictates how the precincts can be drawn as well.
I'll ask Collins about that too. And then this section is pretty boilerplate too. I mean, it might be actually word for word. So that's pretty good. We just went through section seven.
And we have some questions just to review. Did anybody that wanted to? I'm going to do that. I just want to review first what we discussed and what we're going to follow up on. I'm going to ask the Collins Center if charters, if newer charters are incorporating mail-in and early voting.
I'm going to ask the city clerk about dates so that we can sort of keep them same and keep them reasonable. Date signatures are due and a time frame for the drawing for ballot position. And I'm going to ask the Collins Center about the practical function of the wards section of this Article 7. Did I miss any follow-ups?
Sounds good to me. That sounds good. Okay, get that done before the next meeting. That'd be great. So the other thing I said, I'm suggesting is that I will take what we talked about and turn it take this document and just like I started with the 1st section that we just finished.
and turn it into sort of a draft that we can present and share with the whole committee. And I'll incorporate what we decided. And then at our next meeting, we can look through, we can, hopefully we'll have answers to the questions and we can look through our draft document and see if we think it looks good and we are ready to share it with the whole committee. Sound good? Terrific. Sounds good to me. Okay. All right. Are there any members of the public who would like to speak?
Hi John, how you doing? He may not be able to hear you. I'm fine, can you hear me? Yes, yes, we can hear you. All right, great. Well, I logged on because I was concerned with the ballot positioning and I'm in agreement with the committee that we give everyone a fair chance by, like Anthony suggested, pulling out of a hat or some other random selection of order.
And I just wanted to give my support to that idea. Great. Thank you. Thank you, John. You're welcome. Appreciate you coming and sharing that. All right. So I mean, this was very efficient. That's how we like it, Melva. I know. I will also look up that study because we will use it in our final report.
as part of why we've made the decision about the ballot positions. I'll try to pull it up again and forward it to you. That would be great. Thank you. Do we want to set another meeting before we are ready to pass this on to the whole committee, just to wrap up? Yeah, if we could, the sooner before. When's our next meeting? The week from Thursday? March 7th.
Yeah. Are we from Thursday coming up? Maybe we can get one in next week or something beforehand. What about next week, Monday, same time, which is Monday? I'm good. It should be just a short meeting. So let's do it. So 2 PM, whatever that is, Monday, March, whatever it is. I'll look it up. I'll tell you right now.
Okay, thanks, Mark. March 3rd, I believe. March 4th. March 4th, okay. It's hard when you're at the end of the month. And it's a weird month because there's an extra date. You've got to leave here. Yeah, exactly. All right, Monday, March 4th at 2 p.m. And I'll follow up, and I will create the document we talked about, share it with you, and hopefully after next week, we'll be able to pass it on to the whole committee.
Terrific. Thanks. Great. Great. Thanks, you guys. Take care. Bye. Thanks for hopping on, John. All right. All right. See you all soon. Bye.