Hello, everyone, and welcome to Method Happenings, a show for and about the city of Medford.
I am John Petrella.
The purpose of this program is to give Medford citizens facts and information to help you make informed choices.
So let's give a really big welcome to our guest today, Nicole Brandly.
Nicole is a hard-working and current member of our Method School Committee.
Nicole works for everyone in the city of Method, and I think there's a big emphasis on children and students.
So, Nicole, thank you for coming on the show.
Thank you for having me.
We really do appreciate it.
I love it.
We're gonna get right into it, Nicole.
Okay, let's do it.
I start off with, just give us a little background.
Who's Nicole?
What are you all about?
Well, what am I all about?
Well, I'm a current school committee member here in Medford.
I'm just finishing up my first term, running for my second term for re-election.
I'm a mom.
I have two children.
One graduated from Medford High this year.
And then I have a rising 10th grader.
You're a very, very busy person.
Yeah.
And I grew up in Medford.
I went to Medford High.
I've worked for Medford Public Schools in the past as a paraprofessional.
And I work for a neighboring district.
I'm the administrative assistant for the director and assistant director of special ed.
Very good.
Yeah.
Great.
That's great stuff.
It really is.
You're also a very busy person.
I am.
All right, so now we'll get into what it's all about, what's going on.
OK, let's do it.
Give us a couple of reasons, just why you're seeking re-election.
Well, there's more work to do.
There's more work to do.
And I love my job.
I love working for the school committee.
I love representing this city.
I don't represent one group or one person.
I don't go to City Hall for myself.
So I represent every citizen, and that makes me really proud.
And to think that I can be the voice of our students and our staff, that means everything to me.
I trust them with my children, and I'm happy that they trust me.
And they do.
I appreciate that.
I don't take that for granted at all.
I know you don't.
I know that's the type of person you are.
Thank you.
And that's why we love having you on the show.
Thanks.
I mean, you want to share some of your, you know, what you would, what you believe to be past accomplishments?
Sure.
You've done a lot, but you want to fill us in?
Well, school committee never sleeps, I can tell you that.
We are on 24-7.
It's not just, you know, showing up for a couple of meetings a month.
You are really on all the time.
I think the thing that I'm probably most proud of is that I won.
I'm a grassroots single person, you know, running for office.
I'm not affiliated with any groups.
you know I run everything on my own my social media I have a treasurer but besides that I don't have a campaign manager and you know I'm my own manager I guess basically a one-woman show that's it
I'm grateful for everybody that helps me.
I feel like I have an amazing village in Medford, and I'm grateful for every single person.
Working on the school committee, you know, obviously budget season is very difficult.
You know, last year especially, it was very difficult.
This year was definitely easier with the override.
You know, grateful to keep those jobs.
Leading up to my run for election, I worked very closely with the school committee before even running for office.
I helped them revise the building and intervention policy, and I was really, really proud of that.
And I was involved in hiring our new principal, which is Monta Cabral, so I was on that search committee, too, and I'm proud of that.
We're very proud of you.
And the bullying, that needed to be revised.
And you did a great job.
Thank you.
I appreciate it.
It was for every child.
I know.
Every child.
There was a lot going on.
There really was.
So what do you feel was the school committee's most important action or decision in the past
term.
Was there anything going on?
Anything going on?
Yeah, I mean, actions that you took.
Actions that we took, all right.
Well, I think budget, money is probably the most important thing, right?
I mean, the override was huge.
We want to make sure that we're going to use that money wisely.
I think that was the most important thing to me in talking about the budget and the override.
I just wanted to make sure the money that we do have we were using properly.
And I'm happy to see that the money is going where it said it's going.
And that makes me happy.
I think transitioning to a new superintendent after Dr. Evey left and now transitioning to our interim superintendent.
Dr. Galussi.
Next year we'll, you know, search for a new one or keep Dr. Galussi, however that turns out.
And I think obviously a new Meffitt High building.
Right, I mean, so there's a lot of issues ongoing.
There's a lot going on and I'd like to stay apart and see everything through.
Right, yeah.
It doesn't really end.
No, no, it's a continuation.
It's always a continuation.
More work.
Absolutely.
Can you tell our audience what is your number one issue, if you have a number one issue?
Oh, a number one issue.
The school committee will have to deal with.
well i mean next election yeah so i would i would definitely say you know transitioning to a new superintendent or you know or or sticking with dr galusi who's been doing a great job proud of her um i really would love to
Showcase our you know our highlights here at method high.
I think the method vocational technical high school is really the CTE program is a crown jewel here It really really is I'm lucky enough that both of my kids are Voki's Jacqueline was in the culinary program when she was here and Dominic is accepted to the electrical program, and I'm really proud of that and I think that it's
important to note that you can be a vocational student and still go to college.
I think that that's really a myth that needs to be busted.
You know, it really does.
It really does.
You know, and my daughter's heading off to college and she was in culinary, you know, um, and I also think that I would really love to see a lot more Mustang pride come back.
I think old school, you know, you've, you've lived in Medford, you went to Medford high, you have that Mustang pride in you.
You remember the song as everybody came in on,
Thanksgiving morning or the pep rally and I think that we've lost some of that You know, I would love to see us have more pride, you know in our sports, you know in the athletic department We have a new athletic director coming in which is great And I definitely think Obviously academics is has to be a top priority and I think you know a new building whether you know we
revamp the whole place or, you know, whatever, but that's to be seen.
But I think that we need to have pride here.
Be proud of where you come from.
And by the way, the sports teams.
Yes, both my, yes, yes.
I was at a bunch of those GBL games.
Absolutely.
I went to every home football game I was at.
My daughter played for the softball team.
She was on varsity.
My son was junior varsity and called up for varsity and he was at, you know, that GBL winning games.
And it's so great to watch the energy.
And I love that people that, you know, from the city or other parents come to watch the games of other students that are just excited.
And I think that we really need to get back into that.
I think that that's huge.
It's a big part of what's going on in high school.
It really is.
What happens in school is citywide.
It's not just for people who have kids at school.
I agree.
Good point.
Thanks.
Very good point.
So next question.
How important is working cohesively with your fellow
You know, committee members, you know, now and in the future.
Absolutely.
What do you see?
What do you feel?
Well, I really feel like no one should come to City Hall for themselves.
I feel like we work for the citizens.
You don't work for the five or 7,000 people that vote for you.
You work for all citizens.
So, you know, 50, 60,000 citizens here in Medford.
I feel like I want to represent them all, you know, I really do.
And if it means, you know, stopping and talking everywhere I am, which happens everywhere you go, you know, you know, it's funny, you know, I'll go out with girlfriends and people will be like, oh, there she goes.
But it's true, it's true.
People want your attention and I think people want to be heard.
And if I can be that listening ear for someone to say, this happened to me or I'm really excited about this, I'm all for it.
So I think that that's really important.
Of course, working with our fellow members, the mayor, the superintendent, our assistant superintendents.
All the department heads the directors it is important.
It is important that the staff is heard The teachers are heard the students the families, you know I'm I I think really you don't walk into City Hall for yourself and if you walk into City Hall as an elected official and you are there for yourself then You're not there for the right reasons You know
That is a great answer.
And I know it's coming from your heart.
I do.
I can't tell you how much that means, because I'm not going to get into too much here.
I'm not a politician.
I'm a mom.
You're definitely not a politician.
I'm not a politician.
Just with that answer alone.
I'm a mom that wanted to see change.
And you do represent the whole city.
And I think that is
So important.
I hear people talk.
I want to hear everybody's opinions.
No matter what side of the aisle you're on, I think that we need to really meet in the middle.
And that's what brings community.
Exactly.
Thanks.
That's why, well, that question to me, that was like, wow.
Oh.
No, it was wow.
I love to wow you, John.
Well, you did.
That's a great answer.
You don't hear that often.
You just don't.
That's my truth.
appreciate it i really don't and i'm sure the audience is going to appreciate it that that's very very important um uh all right so now let's get into the money stuff all right let's get a question about that all right i know no one wants to talk about it
I wish I had more of it.
I wish the city had more of it.
I hear you.
The status, you know, the override, the $7 million, is there any way you can give us a little bit of the status of, you know, what happened?
What happened with that money?
Yeah.
What are we doing with it?
It's not in my bank account.
We're not, we're not out to dinner with it.
That's for sure.
Um, no.
So, um, well obviously, uh,
I think that we've really needed to work harder on maintenance, especially of our buildings.
That has definitely lacked.
And I'd like to think things are getting fixed.
That's very important.
The mayor has been great in helping us out, obviously, with funds.
We are the biggest part of the city budget.
And that's a big deal.
So override, we just passed the teacher's contract.
I was not on the negotiating team, but the teacher's contract was finalized.
I believe they said in three months, which is unheard of.
They did a great job.
They really did.
Obviously a lot of work goes into that.
And I'm grateful for the negotiating team in that aspect.
Our schedule will be changing and our day will be longer.
And that all went into that.
Yes, so we have to revamp everything.
Yes, so the high school have yeah I want to say it's a little bit over an hour maybe an hour and a quarter a week Yeah, yeah of
you know school time right so learning time and that's important you know academics at the end of the day is why we're here yeah so so yeah so I'm really proud of that um you know like I said I definitely want money to go where it's supposed to go and what better to invest in than our children right and the staff that's here you know we want to keep
the best of the best here.
And I really do believe we have it.
I'm really proud of everybody.
Yeah.
So that's money.
Nice to know.
Yeah, it's nice to know.
The money did not go towards our new high school.
I had heard that many times.
Like, oh, we need to do that because we have a new high school.
I'm like, that's not why we're doing the override.
You too, yeah, because everyone thought, oh, yeah, the money, yeah, well, it's only one year, it was going to the school, and I'm like, no.
No, no, yeah, no, my bills changed, you know, my tax bill changed too, you know, so.
Yeah, you get it all the time, I'm sure.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, absolutely.
I'm telling you, it's almost comical sometimes.
But, you know, here's another thing that I really am interested in.
A lot of people are interested in, I think.
update, any update, on the plans for a new high school?
Are we going to build a new one?
We're going to do something with what we have?
Is anything going anywhere yet?
I am a sports mom, right?
My kids play sports.
I go to these other complexes and I'm like, why don't we have this?
I wish we had this.
So do we need a new high school?
Yes, you know what I mean?
The old Mefford High burned down.
My mom was at Mefford High.
I went to this school.
It hasn't changed, right?
I've graduated 30 years ago, 30 plus.
And so, yeah, I mean, we need, who wants to come to work every day?
in you know, in not the best environment, right?
You know, everybody deserves heat and air conditioning and windows and whatnot.
So the MSBA process is a long process, five to seven years.
I am not on the committee, but we are updated on it.
So yes, we are moving, I believe we're in the third phase, if I'm correct.
Yeah, and you know, the team is working really diligently at getting everything passed in ahead of schedule, which is great.
There's a lot of parts of it.
And I'm really proud that so many people in the community wanted to jump in with their expertise.
I love that.
That's community to me.
You know, I think you want to come into a building every day that makes you feel good.
Right, you know, in my office, everybody says, I love your area, it feels like home.
And I'm like, you know what, I want people to feel comfy when they come into my area, you know, we're here a lot of hours, you know, and our staff works hard and our kids work hard.
So you want it to be, you know, a welcoming environment, foster learning.
So there's still a lot going on.
Oh, there's a lot going on there.
There's a lot.
It's a long process.
The wheels are turning.
The wheels are definitely turning.
Absolutely.
And at the end of the day, the MSBA is who tells us what will happen.
So yes, we can have grand ideas.
And I think they'll scale it back for us, if I'm correct.
But absolutely, yeah.
So I think, yeah, we have to be realistic.
There are great parts of this campus and there are parts that really need to be revamped, you know, and there's no doubt about that.
So, yeah, and so I think, you know, obviously this high school was built
for, you know, 5,000 kids, I think, at the beginning, right?
Back in the, you know, at the time.
I clapped for over 700 kids graduating.
Yeah, you know, exactly.
And I think mine was 300.
I don't even know how many was in my daughter's.
But, you know, overall, enrollment has declined.
People's families have shrunk, right?
People don't have six kids anymore.
It's too expensive.
So obviously, enrollment goes down over time.
So, you know, we'd have to tailor it to what the enrollment projections are.
So yeah, all of that goes into it.
Yeah.
So I think you've, uh, you know, you've answered the next couple of questions.
I was going to get into, you know, I mean, what do you think?
I mean, you know, listen, what I love.
I mean, we don't, we all want exactly.
Exactly.
Yes.
There's a possibility that they're going to rehab.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
And it's not necessarily a whole brand new building.
I mean, we have a building, B building, both.
You know what I mean?
Like, this is a lot.
This is a big campus and we don't, you know.
Like I said, the enrollment is down over the last 50 years, right?
You know, 60 years, whatever it's been.
So, you know, tailor it to what we need and what our, you know, our hopes are of what Mefford High will be, would be great.
That's the key, tailoring it.
Yeah, tailoring it.
To what you need now.
Tailoring, tailoring it, you know, and projections.
Yeah, and I gotta bring up, you know, we did a,
vocational school show with Rich Cormier.
If anyone hasn't seen that show, go back and watch it.
It's a great show.
I'm a huge Vogue fan.
I did not go to the Vogue.
I didn't know.
But my kids, yes.
You get a tour of the vocational school.
I had more fun doing that show because I thought, yeah, it's incredible.
The bistro, I have to rave about the bistro.
I go once a week for lunch and I try to, you know, promote it on social media as much as much as possible because, you know, the food is actually really, really good.
The price is
more than right, right, you know, and this is real life experience for these kids, like that's such hand on experience, like, where do you get that at school?
And, you know, I think busy hands, you know, are, you know, yeah, you know, busy hands keeps them busy, you know, so stay focused, stay focused.
What's going on?
I love it.
I mean, you want to graduate and go into the workforce.
That's great.
You want to graduate and continue that the path that you've been on in high school to college or, you know, fostering greatness.
But there was a waiting list.
Yeah, there is still a waiting list.
It's still a waiting list.
Can you imagine?
I know, it's great.
I mean, it is great.
It's great.
It's great, yeah.
I mean, years ago, they used to offer up some of the programs to other areas because we couldn't fill the programs and they needed the space.
And that is not the case anymore.
And we did hire, I want to say it was another culinary teacher.
There were a couple of new hires because the programs are thriving.
They're exploding.
We're thriving, and that's great.
That makes me happy.
Yeah, I like I say I just that was a great show and a boy.
I learned a lot Yeah, that tour is the best When I went to school, it was like whoa, well, you know when I went to school too You couldn't cross that line either a Medford high student or you were a Vogue student and you did not cross the line There were different start times different end times You knew you know, and I think that it was really looked down upon which is so sad because it has it really was and it is so
different now, and you know, I'm really proud of that.
Really proud.
All good stuff.
I like the good stuff.
Makes me happy.
We all love the good stuff.
Right?
But the good and the bad, it's reality, so gotta be realistic.
You gotta make the bad good sometimes.
Absolutely.
Do the best you can.
That's right.
Alright, you know, I could go on for a little bit longer, but
I'm a talker too, so go for it.
Next question.
I'm going to make this the last question.
All right, go for it.
I think we covered a lot.
We did.
I'd like to have you come back on someday.
I'm around.
I'm in Medford.
I know, I know, I know.
But this is the last question.
I asked this, and I want to make sure that,
You know, what is your, if you had your least favorite and your most favorite thing to do in Medford, it could be more than one thing, but what is your least and most favorite thing to do?
Okay, so I would say my least favorite thing to do in Medford is drive.
Right?
The traffic, you know, I work in Somerville.
It takes me sometimes 45 minutes to get to Somerville from Medford.
I think days I could walk quicker.
Right.
You know, everybody has different modes of transportation, which is great, but it's a lot, you know, so it's a lot.
So, yeah, I think probably driving is probably my least favorite.
I think you have to give a lot more time when you're even just, you know,
Just going local.
You have to give yourself a little bit extra time.
So probably driving is my least favorite.
Okay, no, that makes sense, because yeah, I have to drive to Somerville.
I drop someone off at the Y, you know, sometimes four or five times a week, and I agree with you.
I live in the traffic sometimes, and when the kids are back in school, it's incredible.
It's incredible, and just so you know, there's still traffic on Winthrop Street, even when school is out, because I sit in that some days, too.
And I don't know what's going on with Tuesdays, but Tuesdays is not a good traffic day ever.
Yeah, there you go.
All right, so now we got your least favorite, which is driving.
And I think a lot of people agree with you on that.
That might be a top one.
That's a good answer.
Thank you.
And favorite.
My favorite thing.
My favorite thing to do in Medford is to go for a walk in the cemetery.
I find a lot of peace there.
I walk through the woods.
I walk up on the stairs.
I sit, I think.
The wildlife in the cemetery is amazing.
a lot of pictures on my own personal social media about that.
The sunset.
I think the deers come out to me.
But I've seen coyote and fox and deer and the bucks are out now with their full rack.
And it's just really amazing to me.
There was a hawk the other day that, you know, was chewing on some prey.
And I was like, this is happening right here in my backyard.
It's just a beautiful, peaceful place.
It really is a peaceful place.
So it brings me a lot of peace in there.
I hear you.
Unfortunately, I have a lot of family, a lot of friends up there.
I do go up there.
I get up there once a week.
And you're right, it is.
I try to go every day.
I really do.
I find a lot of peace there.
Every time I go up, there's plenty of wildlife.
And I also see a lot of people walking around.
Yeah, it's a great place to walk.
But that's good.
Thanks.
You gave me two answers that I don't think anyone else would give me, the cemetery and driving.
Well, there you go.
Well, I'm unique.
There's no doubt about it.
Listen, I really do mean this.
I appreciate you coming on the show.
Thank you.
I had a lot of fun.
I've known your family for a long time.
Yeah, I know.
I know.
My wonderful sister.
South Medford.
Yeah, South Medford.
I grew up in South Medford.
And I knew your mom and all that.
Yeah, yeah.
All right, Nicole.
It's been a pleasure.
Thank you.
Really, really.
I enjoyed the show.
Thank you for joining us.
So this is the last question.
OK.
It's the most probably the most important question, but if someone wants to get in touch with Nicole Brandly Yeah, please let us know.
How do they do it?
Okay.
Well, I'm kind of everywhere.
So I definitely show up So anytime you want to talk I'm always available.
I plan to have a campaign kickoff party in September.
I
It's my birthday, so I like that whole campaign kickoff birthday thing.
I have an email address for my campaign.
It's branley02155 at gmail.com.
I obviously have my school committee email for family and students.
That's Nicole Branley at medford.k12.ma.us.
I'm on Facebook, and that is Nicole Branley from Medford School Committee.
And then on Instagram, I believe let me just make sure so I don't get it wrong.
It's Nicole Brantley the number for Medford School Committee Yeah, Medford SC.
Sorry.
So you're everywhere.
I am everywhere All right, so I'm sure we're gonna you know, we'll put that on the screen.
I appreciate I'm not gonna have you repeat it.
We'll make sure I think people most people know you're on the
I'm sure that gets filled up that mailbox anyhow.
Oh, yes.
Yeah, I'm sure I'm sure You know, it's that time again.
Yeah, we're gonna close out the show Thank you for having me.
Oh, please.
It was our pleasure.
Believe me.
This was a great show.
We had a great time I think the audience is gonna love it.
I really do.
Um, I
But I want to thank you, Nicole, first for joining us on Method Happenings and secondly for being a candidate for our Method School Committee.
We all know how tough it is to, you got elected and you're going for re-election.
It's a lot of work and we appreciate it.
So I also want to take a minute to thank everyone who has been watching the show and thank you for your feedback.
Whether it's positive or negative, we appreciate it and we do look at them.
So if you would like to share a comment or a candidate for city office,
If you're opening a new business, you have an existing business, if you represent an organization with an upcoming event and would like to appear on a future show, you can contact us, excuse me, at johnpatroller55 at gmail.com.
You can also be able, you're also able to see replays of this show on Method Community Media, Monday, Wednesday, Friday at usually 6 to 7 p.m.
You can also see Method Happenings on MethodTV.org, MethodHappenings.com, YouTube at Method Happenings, and also we're on Facebook.
For the Method Happenings team,
Margaret, Bruce, Marco, and Paul.
I'm John Petrolla.
Stay informed.
Ta-da!