Hello, my name is Paul DeLeva and I am the principal of Medford High School.
Medford High School is a comprehensive high school that includes the Medford Vocational Technical High School as well.
This means that our students can participate in our Career and Technical Education courses while attending their core academic courses as well.
There was a time when both schools were separate, but now we are one school.
Our enrollment at Medford High School averages 1,300 students.
For staff, including myself, there's a principal director at Medford Vocational Technical High School, three assistant principals, one assistant principal director at Medford Vocational Technical High School, 175 teachers, six guidance counselors, three adjustment school counselors, and two school psychologists.
We also have many individual service providers as well.
It is our goal at Medford High School to encourage and assist all students to become creative and critical thinkers with compassionate hearts who embrace global citizenship.
As a community of lifelong learners, we collaborate and engage with each other to develop and realize our potential.
In an inclusive environment of physical safety and emotional security, Medford High School fosters diversity and dresses the needs of the whole child.
At Medford High School, educators personalize the educational experience and emphasize the importance of personal integrity as essential to becoming engaged citizens and contributors to the community, nation, and global society.
Welcome to Medford High School.