We certainly hope that you'll come back Saturday and Sunday.
We have a couple of different things. Please return your cell phones on silent while we're off.
I just do want to thank John. I agree with what the community has done to bring the best in here. It's getting bigger and better every year. So we're really, really, really happy to be here with them.
I just wanted to say
I don't know. I don't know. I don't know.
and doing this as a program is what I'm interested in today. I'm also a secretary of the Department of Homeland Security, and I'm very humbled to be here today to be able to announce the remainder of my time that I'm going to be doing on behalf of the Department of Homeland Security. I'd like to share one and a half, because I'm not going to speak today. I'm not going to speak today.
and then to Anita for, you know, helping me think of a new jam session for him to get to know him better. So, we look forward to hearing from you, and thanks so much for your time.
What do I think about how the community has developed this year? I feel like it's just been a year that we've never heard of anything like that. I've heard that they have a helpful community plan. I know that one of the things that gets them more diversified is in the middle of our social media. There's just so many things to see on Facebook, Instagram, or on Google Docs. I don't know anything about that. So, I'm listening to you here. Big shout out to Lauren for her help.
Also to, I think it was Kenneth, I asked him to do a murder job, and I think that's what he's like. And it's been really saving me in a variety of different ways. So, thank you to Lise. Also to my partner, Taylor.
I wanted to thank you for all your help with the promotion and you mentioned that there's a couple of meetings coming up around the area today. And I'd also like to say that there are two really unique initiatives that are all around the area. I'd like you to actually have a couple of meetings. We're working on that right now. It's really just a situation. It is new. We're doing what it's all about. It's more from a self-regulation role.
I'm happy to lead the group around here. And I'd like to just give a round of applause to all of you.
and everything else I can say about the community center itself. The last thing I'll say is that we get a lot of support by generous sponsors. So all group organizations that have access to money or a discount fund, if it's a community. Rivers of West Denver Community Center is a space where arts, life, and education. I'm really excited to see more opportunities for the community. And then there's just huge projects coming our way.
And then for our council, this year we actually don't have food in there, but the Saturdays and Sundays we have food. We can use Instagram houses. We may or may not be able to come back, but we will do our best.
For her, she's a tribal man, which is a local t-shirt, meaning that this is her territory and her t-shirt is made to look great. It's made out of a local hollywood look. For her, at least, it's a t-shirt that she has, a t-shirt that says she's run by a big name that's over here in New York. She's a descendant of a woman I know over there that has a local t-shirt. It's a t-shirt that she has. So all of our P.D. trainers, which is P.D. trainers,
Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off? Um, can you turn it off?
If you're especially tired about what we do, we do a good time for that. And of course, they're involved with I know a lot of you are, because of that law. And then lately, we've been doing a little bit of a roll with that.
And I think it's important to know that we have a community.
and then to keep them off for a little bit. So, there's that alternative on the one side, and then you use, there's a lot of ways I can say it, on the one side, I love that, I'm in the area, but there's so many ways that you can get control, and then to really fire,
I'm going to get that.
Ž Ž
do do
Ž Ž Ž
Music Music
? ?
♪
do do
Thank you very much.
Ž Ž
Thank you so much. In this last couple of summers, we should take a clear day for granted. So we wanted to start off on a clear day. So I'm going to play a mix of standards
This is a statue called Gyurusai, by the late Jim Brattain.
Ž Ž Ž
Ž Ž
do do
? ?
do
Yeah.
We're going to pick up the pace. We're going to play a tune called Simone.
♪
? ? ? ?
? ?
Yeah.
? ? ? ?
? ? ?
do do
Ž Ž Ž
do
Ž Ž
? ? ?
Ž Ž Ž
We have such fun rehearsing above the region here on various nights of the week. It's nice to come together, get out, walk across the river. Here we are. We don't have far to go.
But we do have farther to go musically, and on is Mike Chambliss on the drums.
Ah, the wisdom. And at this time, we have a special shift in course as we invite the wonderful Debbie Lang to come up. I actually want to introduce Peter Barney.
So we saw it, and I wonder if you want to turn it up for us, if you can. La la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la
My love, my love, your love is great, my heart is flowered. I need your love or I will die. My very life is in your power.
I want you, baby. I want you, baby. I want you, baby. I want you, baby. I want you, baby.
rain. rain.
Why a bum, why a bum?
do do
The rain can fall on distant mountains. The rain can fall upon the sea. The rain can fall upon the flower. Since the rain has fallen, let it fall again.
There you go.
So this next song is by the wonderful Toots Eamons, who played a wonderful Hamada and wonderful jazz sax. I say wonderful.
poor little sad little blue who said, don't you cry, don't you cry, you can bet one lucky day you'll wake up and your blues will be forsaken, one lucky day that you'll overcome, you're winning.
as long as there's love in your heart to share with those that don't care. As long as you look for it, as long as there's someone like you to find someone to be true to, two loving arms we can nestle in and say,
blues and true love is coming
do do
Ž Ž Ž
you
Read a little newsletter, open a new quarter. Have you heard the news yet? All around the town, a quarter of clubs wrapped in rainbows and flowers. So make your next springtime, your falltime, your wintertime. Dry your eyes, don't fool yourself. The good times are gone, he said. Oh, what a sad little world, he said.
don't you cry
you.
This song is uh, there's a wonderful songwriting team uh, Jimmy Van Hoesel and Jonathan Burbank. And we have this song called Congratulations.
Yeah. Yeah.
I'm going to put you in your seat.
is funny. It makes a cloudy day sunny. Makes a evening of honey. Just as I think of you. Imagination is crazy. Your whole perspective
Maybe it starts you asking a daisy what to do Have you ever felt a gentle touch and then a kiss and then, and then
I find it's only your imagination. Oh, oh. Imagination. Silly me. You go around with it. For example, I go around wanting you.
And if I can't imagine the truth, what is truth?
do do do
Ž Ž Ž
do do
Have you ever felt a thrill? And then a kiss, and then, and then Find it's only your imagination again Oh well, imagination
You go around whirly-whirly Oh, for example, I go around wanting you And yet I can't measure that you want me Can't measure that you want me
I can't imagine that you'd want me to. So my son is a jazz classic player.
I just put a little sign up that my family lives here, and their last name is Golson, not related to Benny Golson who wrote this song. As far as I know. Check it out. This song's called Whisper Money.
Sweet words in my ear, not a whisper of despair. But love is all fresh in your arms until you bring back the thrill of the scent.
That's a town that died too soon. Our harmony was lost, but you forgave. I forgot. Whisper not of all those pasts. You know that I left. So now,
love will whisper from eternally.
He said so when they said it would last
I didn't want you here to stay, but like you know, we still could make it. Forget it all, answer the Cupid's call. Is it true? Is this a problem or an echo of the past? All it will take to lose my bloom is just a whisper, not a rumor. Love your love for me, that's how it's got to be.
Our harmony was strong, but you forgave. I forgot. Whisper love, love grows fast. You know we are the last. So I will keep on keeping constantly. Love will whisper home.
Bye!
Ž Ž Ž
Ž Ž Ž Ž
do
Okay.
do do
Ž Ž Ž
Thank you very much.
? ? ? ?
do do
? ? ? ? ?
do
you
Ž Ž
do
We're going to take a quick pause while we put our next act in place. If you need to use the restroom, feel free. I'm going to see if I can find some water to put out.
We'll see.
Okay.
Yeah.
You know, it's funny, I was trying to see if I could figure out a better way of communication because these things haven't sunk. They do, yeah.
In like a studio setting where there isn't like a live audience. Yeah, if you're in like a green room. But yeah, these are, I would, for the inside, maybe we'll better look outdoors. I'll see what we got. Well, here's what I was thinking. So we have a third person's ball, right? Yeah. So I was thinking what we could do is come up with at least a system where you're quarterbacking.
So when we're on the cameras, you know, we might just look back at you. It's just a matter of one, one, two, three, you know. And when, you know, we're going to switch or change our angles or whatever we're doing, we'll just do something like this. Nothing really obvious, but, you know, subtle enough where it's like you get it and you won't switch over to us. That way it comes across better.
Yeah, I have to check the stream audio, but according to how well it sounds, because it records in the past.
We might have better in-camera quality. Yeah, well, tomorrow if you want. What I might do is I might switch out the other one might have more in's. I like this one, but I think for like bigger stuff, like this would be good for like one, two cam, like some mid-light mics.
Yeah, I'll play around tomorrow morning while we're at it, because this is working alright. But I want to see how the other one does here. Well, tomorrow morning you'll be here, what, at 10? Maybe earlier. When do they open? I think 10. Well, we can check.
And I can be here first thing in the morning, so that way I can help you move all this stuff outside and get it set up. Yeah, that'd be great. I mean, I've done it before for some stuff, but yeah, it's not ideal. Yeah, but you never know. Yeah, thank you very much for assisting here. You came in straight.
on the solos there. Yeah, it's really nice having somebody who can get up there and shoot. You know, I was also thinking, if we could talk this over too, is that that camera over there is really a tough shot. The only thing I can think of is either putting it behind them, not blocking the door, so that way you get the trucker in a straight shot.
That's going to change tomorrow too.
Yeah, yeah.
And the white balance is? Yeah, right there. He's actually going home, because he's got the new cleaning bar right now. Come on. Nice, nice. All right. I know, I know. If you hear me, clap once. All right. Come on. Come on.
All right, come on, you're like bubbles in a soda waiting for you to rise to the top, come on. Let's go. All right. Okay. All hearts and minds clear? That's a little something to say in the church there, okay.
So, we love, in West Medford, and you know, probably you're from it as well, I don't mean to single us out, but in West Medford, we really love homecomings, okay? You know, we love reunions, we love backyard barbecues, we love all of that kind of stuff that gets the family together. And Anita Wood is a homegirl, as we like to say.
If I was with my homies, I would say, she's my homegirl, like that. But anyways, so she's got this very cool collective that she's been jamming with for a little while now, trying to get that sound down that they like, jazz standards, often with a twist of passion. And the band consists of Anita A.J. Wood on vocals.
All right, and then they got the baby of the group back here, Carolyn Sue. All right, ready? As you can tell, they brought up the cradle to get her. All right, it's Kyle Helmer on guitar. All right, he's a tall man. All right, it's Rose Giuliani on bass. All right.
All right. We're getting ready to do something special tonight. I just want to point out a couple of things. Donation box on the table for the Jazz Festival itself. Donation jar on the back table for the West Bedford Community Center. So if you're feeling soldiers bold, hook a brother, hook a sister up, as we like to say. And we're going to get going, OK? So hopefully your phones are still on silent or vibrate.
and enjoy the music right now of AJ and the crew.
We'll walk the dream house of love, dear Close to the sun of the day Near to the moon at night We'll live in a lovely way, dear Livin' on love in a pale moonlight Just you and I Forever and a day
I love you, my dad. You're all I'm keeping away. I'm a mom, a star, a fire. I'm only alive to love you, too. East to the sun, west to the moon, dear. East to the sun and west to the moon.
Ž Ž Ž
do do
In the dream house of love Close to the sun and the day Beautiful and nice Living in a lovely way Living on love and a few goodbyes
forever and a day. How come I die before giving a break? Up above the stars, my heart and I grew up between east of the sun and west of the moon. Here is the sun and west of the moon.
East of the sun and west of the moon. East of the sun and west of the moon.
We hope you like what we've done. The next one.
So where on the rainbow, way up high
The skies are blue and the dreams that you dare to dream, they do come true. Someday I'll wish upon a star and wake up where the clouds are far behind me. Where troubles melt like lemon drops,
The way above the chimney tops, that's where you'll find me. Somewhere over the rainbow, birds fly, birds fly. Over the rainbow, and what can't I
? ? ? ?
It's a rainbow, rainbow, rainbow, rainbow, rainbow, rainbow, rainbow, rainbow, rainbow, rainbow, rainbow, rainbow, rainbow, rainbow, rainbow, rainbow.
the rainbow.
do
♪ Music playing ♪
I want a Sunday kind of love, a love to last. But it's Sunday night, and I do know it's more than love at first sight. I want a Sunday kind of love.
I want a lonely road that leads me nowhere I want a Sunday kind of love
I do my Sunday dreaming and all my Sunday scheming, every minute, every hour, every day. I'm hoping to discover a certain
I want a Sunday night of love.
do do do
I'm
To my Sunday dreamin', and all my Sunday schemin' Every minute, every hour, every day I'm on my way to discover a certain
Someone put you in my fold to keep me warm when my days are cold. I've asked for all my life to have you too. I want a Sunday kind of love.
I want a Sunday kind of love I want a Sunday kind of love
Here it comes.
I feel the earth move. I feel the sky falling down. I feel my heart start to tremble whenever you're around. Ooh, baby, when I see your face, I know it's the one I've made. Oh, baby, I can't stand it when you don't
tenderly call my name. I know that it's my devotion. I see something I just can't tame. I feel the good news. It's nothing like a gap in the sky. I'm coming down. I feel my heart start to crumble as I lay on the ground.
do
when you
you
This is an instrumental, original, by our very own Steve Linscott.
do
do do
Ž Ž Ž Ž
Yeah, woo!
do do
do
Ž Ž
You're the one who made my dreams come true A few kisses ago And I've refelled the grain I want to move When my life is through And the angels ask me to recall The truth I've been told
Oh, you.
Ž Ž Ž
Thank you.
♪
I'm in a world full of people The one who may not dream of you
A few seasons ago I remember you You're the one who set us apart But you, I do not know I remember a two-distance bell That starts a bell Ringing out on the roof
When will you see me?
Shhh.
Yeah, you are the one For me, you'll be the moon and I'll be the sun
I couldn't be here to be your father isn't that darling where you are? I think of you dying away day and night why is it so that this love
In the silence of my lonely days, I think of you.
Stay under the height of me. Because I'm such a hungry, yearning, burning side of me. And a storm that won't be through till you let me spend my life making love to you.
do do
Night and day You are the one Only you beneath the moon
dear to me, your father is the man, darling, where you are I think of you night and day day and night why is it so that this longing for you for long
Wherever I go, in the glory of the Lord, in the silence of my companion.
The wind and the storm and it's wandering through To meet the peace and be alive and make love to you Day and night Night and day Night and day Night and day
We'll shoot for two years after you and Wayne Day. Next up is a less-played song from Freddie Hubbard's album, Who Beats the Scene. You may even know most of us, but Carl transgraphed it, and we take it out of our heads, and you won't pop it.
do
♪
do do
The next one was actually inspired by a friend in the audience, David, I'd never heard of before.
I want to take you away.
I'm all to myself, alone and apart, out of a dream, safe into my heart
do
You are so fabulous to me You are too wonderful to be what you seem Could there be eyes like yours? Could there be lips like yours? Could there be smiles like yours?
Out of the crowd. I want to take you away, away from the crowd. And have you offer my son, an open heart. Out of the tree, safe into my heart.
Oh no, we only have one more. Shoot. All right, once again, we'd like to thank Terry, I'd like to thank Jonathan, I'd like to thank Mr. Patterson, a big round of applause for Jonathan, and his partner, who is here all the time. It's just been an amazing afternoon. I'd like to introduce the band again. Steven's on the left. From Long Island, New York. Hello there, everybody.
Thank you for having me.
That's why I hired a dog. I'll give you a copy later.
¿Quién será la que viene al sur? ¿Quién será? ¿Quién será? Yo no sé si la podré encontrar
You can hear the sounds of violins on the floor
Thank you very much.
so
Music.
When marimba rhythms start to play Dance with me, make me smile Like a lazy ocean on the shore Hold me close, swear you'll be my lord Like a flower bending in the breeze Bend for me
Other dancers may be on the floor Never mind, I will see only you I can hear the sound of violins echoing When they sway I fall asleep I can hear the sound of violins echoing
Me thrill is only good on a swingin' roof, swingin' roof Wow, thank you so much, thank you guys, brutal.
I'm so glad that I ended up bringing it to you much last year and that you could make this happen. So seriously, it's a fantastic way to just, you know, start a whole celebration. And also remember that, you know, there's so many different ways you can make music with other people. I remember, I think you were just starting to kind of comment on the jam session circuit when I ran into you over in Winchester and just to see how much you've kind of developed
Thank you also to Morningside Music Studio for putting together two great bands. In addition to an area rich with talent, I really feel lucky that there are so many great community music school programs around here. Morningside being one of them. Dan Fox, who's out of town at the moment, I mean he's a busy guy but he can do it. But he's put together some really amazing ensembles and a lot of these students have been there for years and years and just keep getting better.
check out the table in the back. Along with that, there are a couple flyers for the Winchester Community Music School, which has been really amazing, and all of their offerings, and Medford Music Studio, which is run by a woman named Laura Brereton, right here in the city of Medford. Again, thank you to all of our production staff, Terry Carter, Jayla, Reese, all the folks at Medford Community Media, and please remember that our donation is conveniently placed
And there are QR codes in the back of the programs. Stay tuned for more. I'll come back tomorrow for Sita Isamah, both Bill Ward's projects. It's going to be fantastic. And for the Alive project, featuring Terry Carter and I.
So stop recording.
I love her. I love Dylan. I love her so much. I love her so much.