[SPEAKER_01]: I'm gonna go ahead and call the meeting to order at 5.02.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this is the Medford Board of Assessors.
[SPEAKER_01]: If we could do a roll call vote of attendance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Steven Pompeo.
[SPEAKER_01]: Present.
[SPEAKER_01]: John Lopes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Present.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Ellen Brito, present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I will announce that the pursuant to Governor Baker's March 12th, 2020 order, suspending certain provisions of the open meeting law,
[SPEAKER_01]: Mass General Law Chapter 30A in Section 18 and his additional March 15th order imposing restrictions on the number of people that may gather in one place.
[SPEAKER_01]: This meeting of the Medford Board of Assessors is being conducted via Zoom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Governor Baker's orders were extended that allowed us to continue utilizing Zoom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tonight on the agenda, we just have two items, which are both motor vehicle excise commitments.
[SPEAKER_01]: These excise commitments are ready to go.
[SPEAKER_01]: So this is why we needed to go ahead and have the, there are other people in the waiting room.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I'm gonna let them in.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so, oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: There we go.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we have motor vehicle excise commitment 2022 commitment number seven for 990 accounts totaling $38,737.24.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I could have a motion to approve.
[SPEAKER_01]: Make motion to approve.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've received the documents and reviewed them and make a motion to approve.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you, Steven.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will second that motion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Second by John.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, roll call vote.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it'd be Steven Pompeo.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: John Lopes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Ellen Brito, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's unanimous.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the second motor vehicle excise commitment would be the first commitment for 2023 for 37,525 accounts
[SPEAKER_01]: totaling $5,094,859.27.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if I could have a motion to approve.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I'll make that motion and note that we've received the necessary documents to make that motion to approve.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I have a second?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I will second that motion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Roll call vote.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mr. Pompeo.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: John Lopes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: and Ellen Brito, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that vote is unanimous and those two commitments authorizes the collector to go ahead and issue those.
[SPEAKER_01]: At your convenience, the staff has the warrants and commitments ready to sign.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will not be able to get in until over the weekend.
[SPEAKER_01]: But John, if you have the opportunity to just swing by the office over the next day and a half and could sign those documents, that would be great.
[SPEAKER_01]: Steven, I'm not sure when you're back.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Two signatures sufficient.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, two signatures are sufficient.
[SPEAKER_01]: We voted.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will provide a copy of the minutes in draft form.
[SPEAKER_01]: So Judy has that for her record.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll be able to sign them on Friday.
[SPEAKER_01]: Beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: The office is there till 1230.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's all I have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Our next meeting will
[SPEAKER_01]: Probably be right at the beginning of March.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will definitely coordinate with the staff to see where we're at and we will be ready to hit the ground running on and hopefully be back in person and say no snow in March.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then no bad weather just prohibit me from coming in.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it looks promising.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I just need a motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_00]: Make a motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I will second that motion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And roll call vote to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_01]: Um, Steven Pompeo.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: John Lopes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Ellen Brito.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Medford.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thanks you guys.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cause we really needed to get this one done.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I appreciate it and enjoy your, the rest of your day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thanks Ellen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take care.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bye bye.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bye now.