[SPEAKER_02]: 7 present, none absent.
[SPEAKER_02]: All please rise and salute our flag.
[SPEAKER_02]: I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America.
[SPEAKER_02]: Approval of minutes of February 5, 2018.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there a motion for approval of the minutes?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion by Mr. Russo, seconded by Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Van der Kloot.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_02]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion passes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Approval of bills transfer of funds.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there a motion on the floor for approval?
[SPEAKER_02]: Question or approval?
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion for approval by Mr. Benedetto, seconded by Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mustone.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_02]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion passes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Approval of payrolls.
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion for approval by Mr. Russo, seconded by Mr. Benedetto.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_02]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion has it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Report of secretary.
[SPEAKER_02]: None?
[SPEAKER_02]: None.
[SPEAKER_02]: report of committees minutes of the search committee February 7 2018 these These this report is actually just for our information and should be received and placed on file It doesn't require a school committee vote except for placing it on files their motion Motion to receive in place on file by mr. Zero seconded by miss V and occlude all those in favor all those opposed motion passes Mr. Superintendent So
[SPEAKER_04]: just so it's clear for everyone and anyone watching on television, the focus group for the general public is Thursday, the 15th of February, two sessions, three to five and six to eight.
[SPEAKER_04]: Three to five, six to eight, right here.
[SPEAKER_04]: The rules are that anyone can come up, there's no preferential order, no one gets any specific,
[SPEAKER_04]: Three to five minutes to make a statement.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you don't want to make a statement, you just want to give something written, it'll be taken by MASC and it'll be brought into the thing as if it were oral testimony.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, so any questions about that, anyone can come in.
[SPEAKER_04]: We're advertised, we're out there.
[SPEAKER_04]: The administrators will have an opportunity tomorrow to speak with MASC.
[SPEAKER_04]: The teachers will have an opportunity later in the day tomorrow and also they can participate in the general public if they choose to do so.
[SPEAKER_11]: Mr. Benedetto.
[SPEAKER_11]: Would that meeting be televised since it's an open forum for everybody to come?
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not going to be televised, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's intake for the individual.
[SPEAKER_04]: OK.
[SPEAKER_08]: Mr. Ruggiero.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you very much for scheduling this.
[SPEAKER_08]: Are we going to be advertising this in the transcript?
[SPEAKER_04]: It's advertised.
[SPEAKER_04]: We put it out there.
[SPEAKER_04]: I hope that we contacted you, Miranda.
[SPEAKER_04]: Did you get that?
[SPEAKER_04]: I got it, yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: OK.
[SPEAKER_04]: So hopefully you'll give it a nice online
[SPEAKER_04]: Prominence and we'll get it all over our media We'll put it out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay on the motion to receive and place this report on file all those in favor motion for suspension of the rules
[SPEAKER_02]: Out of order.
[SPEAKER_02]: On the motion to take three papers, 3, 4, 5, and 6 out of order.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_02]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion passes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Item 3, recommendation to approve submission of revised statement of interest to the MSBA.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Patterson.
[SPEAKER_02]: Good evening.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes, so an overview for all the committee members.
[SPEAKER_06]: The statement of interest is required in order to show the district's interest in a partnership with MSBA for construction renovation projects.
[SPEAKER_06]: We did submit an SOI last year, and we were at the top of the list.
[SPEAKER_06]: However, they had very limited funding.
[SPEAKER_06]: only 15 projects were approved last year.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we are resubmitting with generally the same submission, but we have tweaked some of the language to be more beneficial to what we're doing this year in this phase.
[SPEAKER_06]: So again, the attached document is the required language that we need to provide and make a motion on to go forward with.
[SPEAKER_06]: Then from that process, we have the city council approve
[SPEAKER_06]: and then we have to submit via online.
[SPEAKER_06]: And we do have a hard deadline of April 6th.
[SPEAKER_06]: So timing is of the essence for this particular submittal in order to be on that docket for iteration and expansion renovation construction project.
[SPEAKER_06]: So the whole renovation is for the Medford High School campus.
[SPEAKER_06]: And the overall items that we were looking for are upgrades to heating and ventilation,
[SPEAKER_06]: some boilers, a roof, some renovated classroom and shop areas, along with other improvements that we have identified in the language of the motion itself.
[SPEAKER_06]: So as I've already explained, the document is the same, 2017, but with greater emphasis on our career and technical education needs and facility improvements that are tied to student learning and services.
[SPEAKER_06]: So if there are any questions on the language itself,
[SPEAKER_06]: We're happy to address that.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_11]: I just want to say thank you for putting this together and moving it forward again.
[SPEAKER_11]: I think it's great.
[SPEAKER_11]: The more money we can bring back to the schools, the better.
[SPEAKER_11]: When we do the heating issues, will it also incorporate the theater, the little theater?
[SPEAKER_11]: Because we were just at an event there, and it's very cold.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I think it's mentioned in the report.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: OK.
[SPEAKER_11]: And if we don't get this money, can we look at that?
[SPEAKER_11]: some way to make that a little warmer, because we were there the other night and it was cold.
[SPEAKER_06]: So the HVAC facility itself is the issue, which is a major infrastructure.
[SPEAKER_06]: And it's not a simple fix for just one area.
[SPEAKER_06]: So there are ongoing issues.
[SPEAKER_06]: And that's our reason for going forward with a larger project, because it's very expensive to do an isolated section where you're cutting open concrete and you're getting into those pipes.
[SPEAKER_06]: We are trying to maximize what we can do and make it a building-wide infrastructure improvement.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that is part of that.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm all for that.
[SPEAKER_11]: But if we weren't to get these funds, we still need to look at some type of repairs in different areas of the building.
[SPEAKER_11]: I know that's for another day.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you for putting this together.
[SPEAKER_11]: And I make a motion to move forward.
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion to adopt the SOI, seconded by Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Van der Kloot.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Russo.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mr. Russo, I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thank you for this report.
[SPEAKER_07]: Do you know when they will give us feedback on what they've approved?
[SPEAKER_06]: So the process, again, the deadline is April 6th, so then they review all of the submissions that come in.
[SPEAKER_06]: Last year there were over 100, I believe, total throughout the Commonwealth.
[SPEAKER_06]: We were on the short list of about 40.
[SPEAKER_06]: They did do a site visit and they encouraged us to submit again based on the need and or the potential funding that they would get this fiscal year.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we're looking at the fall of 2018 when they would be voting for acceptance into the program.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then it would be a, the next step would be initial architect and OPM search.
[SPEAKER_06]: And so it's a very,
[SPEAKER_06]: long strategic process.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Vandekloot.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just for clarification, so for this initial step, all we need to do is submit this statement of interest?
[SPEAKER_03]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_03]: We don't need to submit any more detailed report?
[SPEAKER_06]: So this is our detailed report in our required language that has to be formalized.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then I will need a copy of the minutes signed by the secretary.
[SPEAKER_06]: We also have to have the city council's vote.
[SPEAKER_06]: then we have to go online through the MSBA electronic system, and we have to pull that report electronically through their submission as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: So when we say, currently the building has many tiles that have asbestos flooring or many places which, while safe, when it is sealed, our intention would be to replace it, we don't need to give the number of square feet?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, not at this time.
[SPEAKER_03]: To general?
[SPEAKER_06]: They would have an architect review and do all of those steps.
[SPEAKER_06]: I see.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that's, OK.
[SPEAKER_06]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you'd like, I could read the resolution or would someone like to waive the reading of the resolution itself?
[SPEAKER_02]: On the motion to waive the reading of the resolution and adopt the motion that we submit this SOI.
[SPEAKER_02]: to the state on the motion of Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: DiVenedetto and seconded by Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: VandenKloof.
[SPEAKER_02]: Roll call vote, please, Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Kritz.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: DiVenedetto?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Kreatz?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Jones?
Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mr. Jones?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jones?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jones?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ms.
Jones?
Yes.
Ms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jones?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
Ms.
Jones?
Yes.
Ms.
Jones?
Yes.
Ms.
Jones?
Yes.
Ms.
Jones?
Yes.
Ms.
Jones?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Jones?
Yes.
Ms.
Jones?
Yes.
Ms.
Jones?
Yes.
Ms.
Jones?
Yes.
Ms.
Jones?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Jones?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Jones?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Jones?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Jones?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Jones?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Jones?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Jones?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Jones?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Jones?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Jones?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Jones?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Jones?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, seven in the affirmative, none in the negative.
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion passes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Also, the superintendent is recommending we take a vote, that we move this paper along to the city council for their vote and their thoughts on this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion by Mr. Benedetto, seconded by Mr. Russo.
[SPEAKER_02]: Roll call vote, Ms.
[SPEAKER_10]: Kreatz.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative.
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion passes.
[SPEAKER_02]: On his paper?
[SPEAKER_02]: Mr. Benedetto?
[SPEAKER_11]: Anyone to go with you to talk to the city council, please advise us.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm sure there's many members that would be happy to attend with you.
[SPEAKER_11]: Do you plan on providing it tomorrow night?
[SPEAKER_11]: No, we needed to get approval and we have to get on their agenda.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a deadline of 12.30 Thursday because of the holiday next Monday, if you're shooting for Tuesday.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's a good point.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that's a good point.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think it was roughly the same amount.
[SPEAKER_02]: $675,000 is the total value and we would have to look for city funds of $291,150.
[SPEAKER_02]: I will have to submit a paper to the City Council to cover that match on behalf of the community.
[SPEAKER_02]: So the vote tonight is that we adopt this Mr. Superintendent.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then forward to City Council for their
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion to adopt and move forward to City Council ah there's a motion is there a second by Mr.. Russo on the motion that we adopt you write funding recommendation and forward alone to the City Council and likewise I'll put a paper together for free cash for the offset of two hundred ninety one thousand one hundred fifty dollars roll call vote, please Yes
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: 7 in the affirmative, none in the negative.
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion passes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Item 5, report on security system upgrades and funding approval.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Patterson.
[SPEAKER_06]: So again, this is a follow-up.
[SPEAKER_06]: There was a confidential report previously shared regarding placement and repairs for cameras across all of the schools within the district.
[SPEAKER_06]: are requesting the cost of all of the security cameras of $203,000 again to be brought to City Council vote for funding for that special item.
[SPEAKER_06]: These upgrades improve the level of security at all the schools, providing those very needed repairs and replacement of cameras.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we did vote in the fall to move forward with this project.
[SPEAKER_06]: This is, again, just bringing this forward with the new committee members.
[SPEAKER_06]: to reaffirm that action to move forward.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mr. Russo?
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion for approval?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Mr. Benedetto?
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you for the report.
[SPEAKER_11]: I second the motion to move it forward.
[SPEAKER_11]: But I also am requesting at this time to have an update on all the security as far as doors and locks throughout the district.
[SPEAKER_11]: So I know I mentioned it prior, but I am going to ask it, even if it has to be confidential or done in executive session.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'd like an update of where we are and how we intend to move forward to make sure our children are secure and safe.
[SPEAKER_11]: Not that they're not, because I'm sure that they are.
[SPEAKER_02]: Doors and locks or cameras?
[SPEAKER_02]: Doors.
[SPEAKER_02]: Doors and locks.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_11]: How many doors are locked, how they're opened, how many are buzzed in, if all of that equipment is working appropriately.
[SPEAKER_11]: You know, some buildings are harder than others.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'd just like an update on where we are with that and make sure that, yeah, building check, security check, like we did for the cameras, just to make sure everything that we have in place is operating well.
[SPEAKER_11]: And what we didn't, we purchased and made sure.
[SPEAKER_11]: I want the same thing for all of our doors and buzzers to buzz people in.
[SPEAKER_02]: So there's a motion.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm the motion to adopt this paper requesting $203,000 that a paper be forwarded to the city council to approve the purchase of security cameras throughout the system and a B paper that all the doors and locks be checked and a report be sent back to this committee.
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a motion by Mr. Russo, seconded by Mr. Benedetto.
[SPEAKER_02]: Roll call vote, please.
[SPEAKER_10]: Mr. Benedetto?
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_10]: Mrs. Preston?
[SPEAKER_10]: Mr. Russo?
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, 7 in the affirmative, 0 in the negative, motion passes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Item 6, financial report.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: Included in your packet was a reference sheet for the programs in the general fund, so these are referencing all of your subtotals as you looked through your report.
[SPEAKER_06]: I hope that was helpful.
[SPEAKER_06]: As an overview, just to inform our newest committee members, the school budget operates and functions under a modified accrual system.
[SPEAKER_06]: So this is an accounting system and it utilizes encumbrances for reserving anticipated expenditures as well as tracking the actual expenditures to calculate balances remaining.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we still have many payroll reclassifications that are ongoing.
[SPEAKER_06]: This is a process that has been identified in terms of our payroll codes and our payroll system is not tied directly to our general fund.
[SPEAKER_06]: So there's a lot of shifting or status changes for placements of personnel within the district that not necessarily moved according to their general fund account allocation.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's something that we are in the process of
[SPEAKER_06]: rectifying and doing a full-scale review.
[SPEAKER_06]: We have new payroll employees that are doing a great job to bring these to light.
[SPEAKER_06]: Additionally, we're going to be moving the budget amounts to go into the correct columns that were anticipated for those mid-year changes and to further improve the actual budget to the year-to-date expenses on this overall report.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I'm happy to go through each category.
[SPEAKER_06]: or answer questions as the committee.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mr. Ruggiero.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, I noticed the price increase for electricity from a little over $0.08 to $0.09.
[SPEAKER_08]: I wanted to know, have we ever looked into getting solar panels for the school, or how much that would lower the cost?
[SPEAKER_02]: We are in the process of putting on solar panels on the Andrews School.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's already been worked out.
[SPEAKER_02]: The Andrews has a DPW facility.
[SPEAKER_02]: are getting solar panels.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll be the first phase.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then we'll continue to look into the other schools as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: It has to do with the life of the roof.
[SPEAKER_02]: In some cases, they mandate that you have to go out and do a new roof in order to put them on, or they won't guarantee things.
[SPEAKER_02]: So there's a lot of little pieces that go with the solar panel installation.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the Andrews has fit the bill, and it's in really good shape.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that will be our first school to go solar.
[SPEAKER_08]: Great.
[SPEAKER_08]: Can I just request a report on that mitigation strategy?
[SPEAKER_08]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thanks.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a motion also to request a report on an update on the solar panels once they go in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mr. Benedetto.
[SPEAKER_11]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you for the report.
[SPEAKER_11]: I did have some questions, and I know that certain areas within a department's budget are higher, and it all offsets by the end.
[SPEAKER_11]: I get that.
[SPEAKER_11]: Concerning to me is that I saw a trend in one school being over in a few different areas.
[SPEAKER_11]: And I didn't know if that was because there was a greater need this year at that school, and we allocated more funding than we anticipated and budgeted.
[SPEAKER_11]: So the question might be more towards the superintendent than it would be to you.
[SPEAKER_11]: You may know as well.
[SPEAKER_11]: I noticed that on page, sorry, so many things.
[SPEAKER_11]: On page 3 of 3, the secretaries at the Columbus, they're already at 116%.
[SPEAKER_11]: And then on page 4 of 13, at the top, it says permanent part-time Columbus mentors.
[SPEAKER_11]: They're well above there.
[SPEAKER_11]: They use 376% of that budget.
[SPEAKER_06]: So again, in general context, a number of actual salary amounts need to be reclassified.
[SPEAKER_06]: So it's not necessarily the exact depiction of what's occurring.
[SPEAKER_06]: We've done a number of changes and the mentors is one of them to correctly classify, but there were additional stipends that got posted in under a payroll code that is not tied to the correct general fund account.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that is what we are ongoing cleaning up to correct and show the truer amount.
[SPEAKER_06]: OK.
[SPEAKER_11]: Because I saw it mostly, I can see it five or six times for the Columbus School in different areas, like PE teachers, psychologists.
[SPEAKER_11]: As you go through it, I saw a pattern.
[SPEAKER_11]: And I just wanted to make sure that there is a reasonable
[SPEAKER_11]: answer to that?
[SPEAKER_11]: I just didn't understand why just that one school?
[SPEAKER_06]: It's a plan.
[SPEAKER_06]: A budget is a moving plan that continues to change and evolve as the year goes on.
[SPEAKER_11]: And that's why the question is to the superintendent.
[SPEAKER_11]: Mr. Superintendent, were more funds allocated there because there was a need there this year?
[SPEAKER_02]: This has to be adjusted is what you're saying.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a bridge that goes from the payroll system into the financial accounting system.
[SPEAKER_02]: And some people, the codes
[SPEAKER_02]: are carrying to the wrong line in this financial budget.
[SPEAKER_02]: So they're being corrected as we speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: So they're going person by person.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: All right.
[SPEAKER_11]: And my other question was actually a request to see the community schools budget, because we're supposed to see that quarterly.
[SPEAKER_11]: That was voted on a few years ago.
[SPEAKER_11]: And we haven't seen it yet this year that I can remember.
[SPEAKER_11]: So there's a request on through you to the superintendent.
[SPEAKER_06]: Put it on your to-do list.
[SPEAKER_06]: We did identify that that is forthcoming in the first quarter of the new calendar year.
[SPEAKER_06]: We've got some additional items that we wanted to capture and make sure were included in that.
[SPEAKER_06]: So the plan is to have a late March report for you.
[SPEAKER_11]: When that report's presented, I'm asking through the mayor to the superintendent, could we also have, I know that a lot of the community is now using the program and everything's going through the computer program so we can find out how many hours we've donated and which schools are being used in which ways.
[SPEAKER_11]: If you could just give us a general documentation at that time as well, so we have both reports at the same time, and we can see how much, which buildings are being used throughout the community.
[SPEAKER_11]: Like if we have to put extra, you know, surprise the air.
[SPEAKER_04]: We can give you a breakdown.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'd like to see that data.
[SPEAKER_11]: I mean, that's interesting.
[SPEAKER_11]: And as we use it more, that data will become more helpful.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_11]: So that's a, I request that it's a motion to have that with the budget.
[SPEAKER_11]: I need a second.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mr. Russo.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'm not sure what the report request was.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_02]: The detailed use of the facilities by school, by item.
[SPEAKER_02]: The community schools.
[SPEAKER_02]: Anything that falls on the community schools.
[SPEAKER_04]: Who's using which school and when?
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a lot of activities that fall under that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sure, I'll second that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is a second by Mr. Russo.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you have a question?
[SPEAKER_07]: I did have a question.
[SPEAKER_07]: So for the things that are coming from the payroll system that are not lining up yet, that you're still working through, are those, they're not on here at all?
[SPEAKER_06]: No, no, they are.
[SPEAKER_06]: They're within the budget.
[SPEAKER_06]: So for example, my department, the finance and human resources, there's a secretary that's being charged in the finance clerical salaries that should be in buildings and maintenance.
[SPEAKER_06]: I see.
[SPEAKER_06]: So it's a true reclassification.
[SPEAKER_06]: They might have been in this program area at one point,
[SPEAKER_06]: And their payroll code just never got adjusted.
[SPEAKER_06]: So that's what we are scouring now at this point in time, now that we're fully staffed with our payroll department.
[SPEAKER_07]: So that's how, for instance, there's just magically no psychologists at the Roberts.
[SPEAKER_07]: But of course, there is.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: It's just they're showing up somewhere else.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's something else.
[SPEAKER_07]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_07]: OK.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: The next month should be clean.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Van der Kloot?
[SPEAKER_03]: Christina, I read your report, and I think I understand the answer.
[SPEAKER_03]: the public, we had some really cold days in January.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so how has that affected our utility usage?
[SPEAKER_06]: So as of this reporting period, we had those utility invoices through December.
[SPEAKER_06]: So it's always a month in the rears for the actual billing itself.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we are continuing to monitor.
[SPEAKER_06]: And again, we capture an encumbrance of reserve for those expenses on the conservative side in these utilities to
[SPEAKER_06]: ensure that we have enough reserved for those high usage time slots, which is usually January, February, for the colder months.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we are on track with what we have done in the past prior years.
[SPEAKER_06]: Again, it's an unknown what the remainder of February will bring and what March will bring.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we will continue to monitor those areas.
[SPEAKER_03]: OK, thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there a motion on the floor to receive and place on file by Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mostone, seconded by Mr. Ruggiero?
[SPEAKER_02]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_02]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion passes.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK, thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there a motion to revert to the regular order of business by Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stone, seconded by Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Kreatz?
[SPEAKER_02]: All in favor?
[SPEAKER_02]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_02]: All opposed?
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion granted.
[SPEAKER_02]: Report on Columbus School after-school tutoring program.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Caldwell.
[SPEAKER_09]: Good evening.
[SPEAKER_09]: The Columbus Elementary School began their after school math tutoring program on January 22nd this year.
[SPEAKER_09]: Currently, we have 23 grade three students, 29 grade four students, and 18 grade five students.
[SPEAKER_09]: We have the grade level teachers, we have a special education staff member, Dr. K and Ms.
[SPEAKER_09]: Sherman Hudson are pitching in, as well as some honor students that are helping out, honor students from the high school that are helping out to make sure
[SPEAKER_09]: our kids can be the best that they can be in mathematics.
[SPEAKER_09]: Each child was given a pre-assessment on the very first day, and the assessments indicated weaknesses in two-digit multiplication, division and word problems, and struggling with rounding off and digital enhanced topic tests.
[SPEAKER_09]: So we need to make sure that we do more work with our Chromebooks on a regular basis during the school day as well as after school.
[SPEAKER_09]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_09]: Kirsteen Patterson and Ms.
[SPEAKER_09]: Tatiana Hall, who is from Easton Bus, went out of their way and worked wonders so that we had the bus when we needed it, so I'd like to thank both of them for all of their hard work.
[SPEAKER_09]: I was at the Columbus on the very first day that they had it on Tuesday, January 22nd, and I was surprised by how diligently the teachers and the students were working together.
[SPEAKER_09]: At 345, when the tutoring program was over, there were lines of students who was going home with their parents for parent pickup, who was waiting for the bus, who was going for the after school program.
[SPEAKER_09]: So it was all very orderly and very organized.
[SPEAKER_09]: I would also like to thank Dr. Kaye and Ms.
[SPEAKER_09]: Sherman-Hudson for their expertise in all of their organization, the teaching staff at the Columbus School for stepping up when I needed them to do that, the volunteers from Medford High School, Ms.
[SPEAKER_09]: Patterson and Ms.
[SPEAKER_09]: Hall for working diligently on bus routes.
[SPEAKER_09]: We all know that's not an easy thing to get done, but they did get it done in a timely way.
[SPEAKER_09]: And of course, I want to thank you, the school committee, for giving us this opportunity
[SPEAKER_09]: to help our children be the best that they can be and improve their scores.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'd be happy to answer any questions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mr. Benedetto.
[SPEAKER_11]: First of all, I want to thank you for all your hard work to get this up and running so quickly.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_11]: There was definitely a need.
[SPEAKER_11]: This program is exactly what we need for that school and to help us with our MCAS scores there.
[SPEAKER_11]: I would like a report.
[SPEAKER_11]: afterwards and see the growth from the students as well.
[SPEAKER_11]: And I wanted to know if anybody was tracking the last year's fifth grade students to who are now sixth grade students and what program or what we're doing for those students.
[SPEAKER_11]: that didn't do so well last year.
[SPEAKER_11]: Are we mentoring them?
[SPEAKER_11]: What's happening for them as they take the sixth grade MCAS?
[SPEAKER_09]: You know, I'll look into that for you, Mr. Benedetto.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, I just want to make sure those children also get the needs and the gaps, any gaps that are missing.
[SPEAKER_11]: We don't want to just do the next group.
[SPEAKER_11]: We want to make sure the group that had the issue gets addressed as well.
[SPEAKER_11]: So I'm requesting a report on the
[SPEAKER_11]: current sixth graders who took fifth grade MCAS at the Columbus School.
[SPEAKER_11]: So there's a motion on the floor.
[SPEAKER_11]: I am hoping one of my colleagues will support.
[SPEAKER_11]: Report on sixth graders.
[SPEAKER_02]: We had requested that during our committee meeting as well, so certainly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seconded by Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Vander Kloof.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_11]: And thank you, really, for all that work.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mr. Ruggiero.
[SPEAKER_08]: I wanted to know what materials are being used for the tutoring program.
[SPEAKER_09]: So they are using the Envision materials, because those are the materials we use in math.
[SPEAKER_09]: We're trying to look at the online piece, because I don't think the kids get enough of that during the school day.
[SPEAKER_09]: And any additional materials, I know that our special education teacher has some materials that she uses with her students.
[SPEAKER_08]: Are you looking for more volunteers from the community, or do you think you have enough as of right now?
[SPEAKER_09]: Well, it's amazing to have these high school honor students step up.
[SPEAKER_09]: I think we have about six of them.
[SPEAKER_09]: They're currently working in the third grade under the direction of the teacher.
[SPEAKER_09]: But they're astute enough to take them to the computer labs and work with them there.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'll keep that in mind, if you don't mind, if we need some more people to help out.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_09]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_09]: Mustone.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is for you.
[SPEAKER_09]: What time does it go till?
[SPEAKER_09]: So the students get out of school at 2.35.
[SPEAKER_09]: From 2.35 to 3 o'clock, they go to the cafeteria and they have a snack because they need something right after school.
[SPEAKER_09]: At 3 o'clock, the students go right up to their classrooms.
[SPEAKER_09]: They know where they're going.
[SPEAKER_09]: And it runs from 3 to 3.45, which is really just enough time for them.
[SPEAKER_09]: That's great.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're welcome.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mr. Russo.
[SPEAKER_07]: Hi, Diane.
[SPEAKER_07]: Did the fifth graders last year
[SPEAKER_07]: had these less than stellar MCAS scores have particularly bad grades on the report cards?
[SPEAKER_09]: I believe they probably did.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'd have to check to make sure.
[SPEAKER_07]: Could you like to make a motion to actually correlate those if there really was any?
[SPEAKER_09]: Yes, we can do that.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there a second on Mr. Rousseau's motion?
[SPEAKER_02]: Seconded by Mr. Benedetto.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there a motion to receive and place this report on file?
[SPEAKER_02]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_02]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_02]: And on the motions by Mr. Benedetto and Mr. Rousseau, all those in favor?
[SPEAKER_03]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion passes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: The end of vote?
[SPEAKER_03]: So the question to follow up on Mr. Russo's question really is, is for the students who are in the sixth grade, are we looking at their math scores, the ones who came from the Columbus, are we looking at their math scores and seeing whether any of them need extra tutoring or?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's Ms.
[SPEAKER_10]: DeVanadero's motion.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, sorry.
[SPEAKER_03]: OK.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sorry about that.
[SPEAKER_10]: They're going to provide us with a review of what measures they have in place to help them.
[SPEAKER_02]: That motion has passed, so.
[SPEAKER_02]: All righty, report on correlation between free reduced lunch participants and access to the SAT.
[SPEAKER_02]: Good evening.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you move your notebook, it's just pressing on that.
[SPEAKER_02]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_05]: At the last meeting, I was asked to investigate the correlation between free and reduced lunch participants and the SAT in the common application fee waiver.
[SPEAKER_05]: The report that was submitted to the superintendent on February 9th is the collaboration of the guidance department and myself.
[SPEAKER_05]: And a couple of big takeaways I'd like to just point out to you and obviously answer any questions you may have.
[SPEAKER_05]: Presently, 30% of all seniors who've applied to college have received the fee waiver.
[SPEAKER_05]: Out of our entire senior student body, 45% are eligible for the SAT fee waivers.
[SPEAKER_05]: We do have only 219 of the 353 students who have presently applied for college.
[SPEAKER_05]: So it is our expectation that once all these students do apply, we will find that to be full, that the full percent of the 45% of the students that would actually take advantage of the fee waiver.
[SPEAKER_05]: We have also, I think it's worth noting that in October,
[SPEAKER_05]: The guidance intern team came to me and asked me if they could work on a project.
[SPEAKER_05]: Every year they have to work on a project and action plan for their program.
[SPEAKER_05]: And their project this year actually was an investigation of this phenomenon, or this concern, I should say.
[SPEAKER_05]: So I spent many weeks with them setting this up.
[SPEAKER_05]: And I know that they worked with the food service program very closely.
[SPEAKER_05]: And from that, we also have a variety of bullets that's listed here of strategies that we have already put in place to address this concern.
[SPEAKER_05]: And going forward, we will continue to increase the communication with students and their families regarding this really great opportunity for students.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'd be happy to answer any questions regarding this report.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you very much, Mr. Benedict-Ngo.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you for the report.
[SPEAKER_11]: I just wanted to make sure that all the students that were eligible were taking advantage of these things, and if there were any gaps, to meet those gaps.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm so grateful that you have those interns working on this project.
[SPEAKER_11]: It seems timely to me.
[SPEAKER_11]: And I like your moving forward steps.
[SPEAKER_11]: I always love to see that.
[SPEAKER_11]: This is what we're doing now.
[SPEAKER_11]: This is what we're going to continue doing.
[SPEAKER_11]: This is our next steps to make sure that we're reaching every family and every child that may need this help.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_11]: Great report.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I would also say that to receive and place this report on file by Mr. Benedetto.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there a second?
[SPEAKER_02]: Second.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can I have a question?
[SPEAKER_02]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Van der Kloot.
[SPEAKER_03]: Could you forward on to the committee members a copy of the flyer highlighting all the benefits students receive from applying for free or reduced lunch?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, I can do that.
[SPEAKER_03]: OK, I think that's great.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think it would be valuable for us to see.
[SPEAKER_03]: So thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_05]: I can also forward the action plan that was created by the intern team, if you like.
[SPEAKER_05]: It has other steps as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: Great.
[SPEAKER_05]: And one other thing I'd say is I think if we look at this data next year at the same time, hopefully we'll see an improvement in all the numbers.
[SPEAKER_02]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a motion on the floor to receive and place this report on file.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_02]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion passes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Item seven, report on vaping information program.
[SPEAKER_05]: Turn me off when the numbers change.
[SPEAKER_05]: Last Thursday evening, we had a really wonderful event take place at the Caron Theater at Medford High School.
[SPEAKER_05]: It was really the culmination of many months of work amongst the administrative team and the nursing and the health service departments to really address a concern that I think
[SPEAKER_05]: is vexing the entire nation, and the state, of course.
[SPEAKER_05]: At this presentation, there were over 80 community members, including three of our own school community members, who were able to attend.
[SPEAKER_05]: And it was a really wonderful show, presentation, question and answer section, which really kind of got at the heart of the vaping concerns that we have in our community.
[SPEAKER_05]: After the conclusion of this presentation, parents were invited to take part in a sort of a site visit, so to speak, an in-plane site view of a typical bedroom where students or children can hide items that may be concerning.
[SPEAKER_05]: And it was actually really interesting because there was a lot of conversation and discussion that took place in the bedroom as well about
[SPEAKER_05]: not only the rights of parents and the need for parents to sort of, unfortunately, snoop from time to time and keep an eye on what their children are doing, but really specifics on how to do that.
[SPEAKER_05]: So the night went very well, and we sort of proposed it as a first step for Medford High School and the Medford community, because there was also people there from the elementary to middle schools.
[SPEAKER_05]: And what I presented in the report tonight was not only sort of the success of that event, but also the steps that we are taking, because this, of course, is a multi-pronged endeavor for us.
[SPEAKER_05]: And just to kind of sum that up for you, so over the past nine months, we have spent a lot of time in our building really sort of
[SPEAKER_05]: Getting at the crux of this concern, we've held multiple faculty meetings where we've discussed the situation, presented it to the teachers to be on the lookout for.
[SPEAKER_05]: We've had community-based justice, CBJ, and building leadership team meetings on the same topic as well.
[SPEAKER_05]: And the CBJ meeting is comprised of not only faculty from the building, but also from the police departments and from the district attorney's office.
[SPEAKER_05]: We've redesigned our health classes where the health classes mid-year took on a different approach because of this ongoing concern that we identified where we're having discussions about this situation with students.
[SPEAKER_05]: We've also
[SPEAKER_05]: look to the students to be leaders in this topic.
[SPEAKER_05]: We've conducted contests for PSAs and posters, which right now we're voting on to have awards for for students who present the best view from their perspective and also the concerns that they have.
[SPEAKER_05]: In the future, we're going to continue to address the situation.
[SPEAKER_05]: This is not a one and done topic.
[SPEAKER_05]: We realize that, for instance, a year ago today, none of us, at least in our building, had any idea of what this issue would look like today.
[SPEAKER_05]: So we're expecting to be a lot of changes in the next few months and years.
[SPEAKER_05]: What we'd like to do
[SPEAKER_05]: in conjunction with the school committee is to continue the conversation on the community level by sharing information, presenting different speakers who can talk to that, as well as listening to parents and students.
[SPEAKER_05]: We're going to collect and utilize data that is at our fingertips regarding the number of students who get caught vaping and the consequences that they receive.
[SPEAKER_05]: And also, and this might be the most important piece, we need to convey to the community, especially our students, the seriousness of this situation, not only for their health, but for their well-being in the school.
[SPEAKER_05]: If at this time I could take any questions regarding that at night, I'd be happy to.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Van der Kloot.
[SPEAKER_03]: Dr. Perlow, I wanted to thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: This was a great presentation, and I was very happy I had the opportunity to attend.
[SPEAKER_03]: Apart from the information that was presented on vaping, I also want to mention that I thought it was fantastic that we had students available to act as interpreters that night for people in the audience.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that was just a great, great touch and something we should continue.
[SPEAKER_03]: And even if they weren't utilized, I don't know how much they were utilized that particular night, but the fact that they were available for people who needed translation was terrific.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_11]: Mr. Benedetto.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you, Maverick.
[SPEAKER_11]: So there were two things that really stood out to me while we were getting information.
[SPEAKER_11]: And it was pretty much from the audience members.
[SPEAKER_11]: The first was a middle school parent who said that their child came home and told her that another student was vaping in our schools, in middle school.
[SPEAKER_11]: So that was alarming to me.
[SPEAKER_11]: And I appreciated her candor in saying that there.
[SPEAKER_11]: The other thing that stood out tremendously is another student that spoke up during the meeting and asked for data to support what we were saying to her because she wasn't just going to believe that we thought it was bad for her.
[SPEAKER_11]: She wanted data and backup to support that.
[SPEAKER_11]: And that's, we have bright children and we need to be prepared with actual facts and figures if we're going to tell them they shouldn't or shouldn't do with something.
[SPEAKER_11]: So I was impressed.
[SPEAKER_11]: at that as well.
[SPEAKER_11]: What I'd like to see, and I talked to you a little bit about this at the end of the evening, is really a hard line, a very hard line that we don't allow cigarette smoking in our schools or anywhere near them.
[SPEAKER_11]: We're not going to allow vaping either.
[SPEAKER_11]: We're going to have it in our handbooks.
[SPEAKER_11]: They're going to be at our submaster, I don't know if they're still submaster nights, our welcoming nights.
[SPEAKER_11]: Our parents should know our routine.
[SPEAKER_11]: It should be initialed.
[SPEAKER_11]: It should be
[SPEAKER_11]: For a student that is vaping, we should show everybody, see, we're not doing this in MedFed.
[SPEAKER_11]: There are so many health things.
[SPEAKER_11]: So vaping, you think you're just sucking in water.
[SPEAKER_11]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_11]: It's all chemicals.
[SPEAKER_11]: And those chemicals are going into our children's lungs.
[SPEAKER_11]: And they think that this is a better choice than smoking, which is even more alarming.
[SPEAKER_11]: Because we don't know what it's doing in those lungs.
[SPEAKER_11]: Because there could be 40 different chemicals going into your children's lungs.
[SPEAKER_11]: It's huge.
[SPEAKER_11]: It's very important.
[SPEAKER_11]: And everybody's cool doing it.
[SPEAKER_11]: And, you know, the way they hide it and the way they can use it.
[SPEAKER_11]: And teachers, it can be happening right in front of them.
[SPEAKER_11]: And teachers are supposed to be teaching, you know.
[SPEAKER_11]: You can't expect this from everyone.
[SPEAKER_11]: So it has to come from the top, the sides, and the bottom up.
[SPEAKER_11]: It has to be a whole community effort.
[SPEAKER_11]: to do this.
[SPEAKER_11]: I was happy to see Penny from Team Medford, the whole group there.
[SPEAKER_11]: It was a great program.
[SPEAKER_11]: I wish it had been better attended.
[SPEAKER_11]: But if they're not coming to us, then we're going to go every athletic meeting that someone goes to, it should be presented and every coach should be trained on it.
[SPEAKER_11]: I just think overall, it's going to be a bigger, bigger picture than we ever anticipated.
[SPEAKER_11]: I want to thank you for bringing this up so quickly and seeing the need for it.
[SPEAKER_11]: And your team was excellent at everything, and Tony Vento as well.
[SPEAKER_11]: So even our school nurses were present at this.
[SPEAKER_11]: This is huge.
[SPEAKER_11]: This is huge for our children's future health and well-being.
[SPEAKER_11]: And you were very proactive.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_05]: And I would say that it is a real medical concern.
[SPEAKER_05]: And one of the big issues for us is that it's highly addictive.
[SPEAKER_05]: So we're looking at adolescents who are getting into an addiction that is
[SPEAKER_05]: as we all know, is incredibly difficult to break.
[SPEAKER_05]: And I think that requires the mental health and the health services department to work with us, because it's not something we just can punish away.
[SPEAKER_05]: We have to sort of work as really a societal problem presently.
[SPEAKER_00]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kreatz.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yep, it was a great presentation, and I learned a lot.
[SPEAKER_00]: I thought it was so interesting when Mr. Toomey was giving his presentation
[SPEAKER_00]: He was actually holding a device, a vaping device, and you couldn't tell.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're so discreet, so they come in just different shapes and sizes, and it looks like a pen, and it was really incredible.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I think it was Maureen who described what the vape was like.
[SPEAKER_00]: So when you're cooking a chicken and there's residue that goes all over your stove, how it's like that slimy film, that's what it's doing to the insides of your lungs.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's what, I just couldn't get that out of my head, that film that goes on your stove and just breathing that vape in and it's just going inside your lungs.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then going into the room, the bedroom, in plain sight, some of the places that you could hide the vape and the juice and all the components were in plain sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was like a Pringles jar that opened from the bottom.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, it was very, it was, it was really, I learned a lot.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was really, it was a great presentation and thank you everyone.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was a great job by all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there a motion to receive this report and place it on file by Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mostone, seconded by Mr. Ruggiero.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_02]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you very much, Dr. Farrello.
[SPEAKER_05]: If I could say one more thing as well, put a little plug in.
[SPEAKER_05]: This week at the high school, we're also addressing another concern with us is technology in society.
[SPEAKER_05]: We have been, um,
[SPEAKER_05]: showing to the students a movie called Screenagers, which really is about this addictive, another addictive problem in society is phone use and technology use.
[SPEAKER_05]: And we are also having a free of charge presentation for the community Thursday evening.
[SPEAKER_05]: This is due to the PTO who paid for the services and the licensure.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hopefully you all also can come as well.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's 6.30 Thursday night.
[SPEAKER_02]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_05]: You're welcome.
[SPEAKER_02]: Next up is the report on focus groups scheduled for our superintendent search.
[SPEAKER_02]: The preliminary focus groups will be held during the week of February 12, 2018.
[SPEAKER_02]: The schedule is as follows.
[SPEAKER_02]: On February 13, school administration from 12 to 2 p.m.
[SPEAKER_02]: in CCSR, which is at Medford High School in the library.
[SPEAKER_02]: February 13, teachers, 2.30 to 4.30 p.m.
[SPEAKER_02]: in that same room at Medford High School.
[SPEAKER_02]: And February 15th, the general public, which the superintendent announced would be held in the, in the council chambers.
[SPEAKER_02]: Additional focus groups will be arranged during the week of February 26 as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: So keep, stay tuned to everybody's motion to receive this report and place it on file by Mr. Benedetto, seconded by Mr. Russo.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_02]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion passes.
[SPEAKER_02]: If we could move suspension to move negotiations and legal matters to the end of the agenda.
[SPEAKER_02]: Moved by Mr. Ruggiero, seconded by Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Leanderclude.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those in favor?
[SPEAKER_02]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those opposed?
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion passes.
[SPEAKER_02]: New business.
[SPEAKER_02]: School committee resolution.
[SPEAKER_02]: Be it resolved that the Medford School Committee express its sincere condolences to the family of Kathleen McAdam.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: McAdam was the sister of retired high school teacher John McAdam.
[SPEAKER_02]: Be it resolved that the Medford School Committee express its sincere condolences to the family of Yehud Bouali.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yehud was an international student in the ELL class at the Brooks Elementary School.
[SPEAKER_02]: If we could all please rise for a moment of silence, please.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mr. Benedetto.
[SPEAKER_11]: I just wanted to say that the McAdams family were neighbors of mine.
[SPEAKER_11]: So Mr. McAdams passed two weeks prior to his daughter.
[SPEAKER_11]: So it's a big loss for our neighborhood.
[SPEAKER_11]: We've lost four people since Christmas in our neighborhood.
[SPEAKER_11]: And they were a wonderful family in our neighborhood for many, many years.
[SPEAKER_11]: And they're always wonderful, wonderful people.
[SPEAKER_11]: And they'll be sorely missed.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_11]: In old business, I don't know if we need to go over it, but the field trip form, do we need to approve that?
[SPEAKER_11]: There are two or three minor changes, and I just don't want to miss it if they need to be approved.
[SPEAKER_11]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's approved, it's subject to them incorporating the changes into the document.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just Ms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Vandervloot.
[SPEAKER_03]: I hate to say this, but there's a spelling mistake on it.
[SPEAKER_03]: OK.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, I'm glad you told me today, not tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_03]: So if you go down to the last line where it says notification,
[SPEAKER_03]: The word signatures is spelled wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: OK.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take care of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then I'll post it tomorrow to the website, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_02]: And have training, two hour training on this form.
[SPEAKER_02]: We've personally spent how many hours?
[SPEAKER_02]: All right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Negotiation and legal matters.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a matter that we need to discuss in executive session.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there a motion on the floor to go into executive session by Mr. Giro?
[SPEAKER_02]: Seconded by Mr. Stone.
[SPEAKER_02]: Roll call vote, please.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, 70 in the affirmative, 0 in the negative.
[SPEAKER_02]: Motion passes.
[SPEAKER_02]: We will not be coming out to the floor after the following executive session.
[SPEAKER_02]: We'll adjourn from the meeting.