Hi, everyone. Welcome to the subcommittee on school committee considerations of the Medford Charter Study Committee. Tonight, we have with us Ampalit Vanderclute, the facilitator. We have the members, Eunice Brown, Ron Giovino, and Aubrey Webb, and possibly one more member of our subcommittee will be joining us tonight.
The purpose of our meeting is to consider the organization of the Medford School Committee as it relates to reviewing the charter of the city of Medford, Massachusetts. So tonight, I thought that we would begin by just talking about the school committee in general. As you know, I was a long-term member of the school committee. And I wanted to review the first order of business was just to kind of look at
current organization of the Medford school committee, including election officers and responsibilities. So, as you all know, we have a school committee which has six members, plus the mayor who serves as chair. So altogether there's seven members but we make the distinction because
It's six members who elected as school committee members and one member who is elected as the mayor and then as part of her or his responsibilities serves as the chair of the school committee. This is not true in all school committees, but it has been what the way that the Medford School Committee has functioned for a very long time, according to our charter.
Also, as you all know, we hold elections every two years. And the entire school committee plus the mayor is up for election at the same time. This is also not true in some other cities and towns.
where they might have staggered elections. So part of the school committee is elected at one time, or they might have differing term lengths. The purpose of that would be to ensure that there was always some continuity. Luckily, it hasn't been in the 32 years that I've served plus the two years since then,
The issue of continuity has not been a big issue for us because there's always been some members going forth. But that is why, you know, it is a concern in some communities.
As a school committee member, I already said that it took two years to learn what you were doing. So the first two years, you really were learning what you were doing and getting your understanding the whole scope of the position and how to do. Hey, Phyllis, how are you? Welcome. Hey, Phyllis. Unmute yourself. Can you unmute yourself, Phyllis?
It took my Zoom link forever to open. I don't know why, but thanks. Sorry I'm late. Here I am. I was trying to be here early. Good. Well, we're glad to see you tonight. And everybody's here, so that's really great. So I mentioned everybody was here. Let that serve as a roll call that now we've got 100% of our attendance.
So I just wanted to review a little bit. I mean, I think sort of everybody kind of knows but I want to give a general
sense of what the school committee does. And I looked on the MASC website, and just so that I can read it, I don't have it posted for you, but I'm going to give you some, the outline. And this is on, MASC is the organization, Massachusetts Association of School Committees, that school committee members have as a resource, as a backup, as the place that you go when you need some help and
clarifications. There is, I served at some point as did Anne Marie Cunha was the president so Medford has had a representation on the statewide association. There is a
conference every year which in fact is happening right now where school committee members from across the Commonwealth come and get together. It's invaluable because you get to learn about other districts and what problems they're facing and you become less insular in your own
understanding of your school committee activities and all the issues that are faced by school committees across the Commonwealth. So this is from them, and I think it's very comprehensive. And I'm going to just give you a quick rundown of what a school committee does. First, the school committee is a policymaking
form a role. And it is the role of the school committee to make the policy and to review the policies for the school district. And that's really how you govern, you govern by making policies.
The school committee has an important finance role where they review and approve a budget for education in the district according to a process and timeline developed with the superintendent and the mayor and what other governs our particular city. The school committee appoints the superintendent.
The school committee also appoints the assistant or associate superintendents, the school business administrator, the administrator of special education, school physicians, and registered nurses.
And we also appoint our own legal counsel and supervisors of attendance. And they are the superintendent makes a recommendation and the school committee then appoints those particular positions.
The school committee also sets compensation levels for the superintendent and overall compensation limits for other positions.
The school committee has a very important role in collective bargaining. They act as the employer of school employees for school collective bargaining purposes, and they designate a negotiator or a negotiating team. There are times when the school committee becomes part of that negotiation team, but that's usually, you know, hopefully you might have settled your contract before that becomes a more active role.
And we receive advice from the superintendent about the educational consequences of different bargaining positions. The school committee establishes upon recommendation of the superintendent, the performance standards for teachers and other employees of the school district. The school committee evaluates the performance of the superintendent, and that's outlined very carefully in mass general laws on how that is to be done.
It also does a self-evaluation to evaluate the effectiveness of the school committee itself. The school committee has a role in professional development and adopts a professional development plan for all principal, teachers, and other professional staff.
The school committee receives and approves annual school improvement plans for each school in the district. The school committee has a role in advocacy. We engage in advocacy on behalf of students and their schools and promote the benefits of a public school system to the community.
A school committee has a role in curriculum, approve major adoptions or revisions of curriculum and textbooks upon the recommendation of the superintendent. The school committee establishes educational goals and policies for the schools in the district consistent with the requirements of law and the statewide goals and standards established by the Board of Education.
The school committee supports the development and promotion of the vision, mission, goals, and strategies of the school committee. School committee members consult and confer with the superintendent on all matters as they arise that concern the school system and on which the school committee may take actions.
And the school committee supports the superintendent in all matters that conform to committee policy. So I think that those are really gives you a summary of the scope of school committee responsibilities. Anybody got any questions? Yeah, Phyllis. I can't hear you, Phyllis. Can you unmute yourself? That's a lot.
That's really a lot in the big scheme of things. That's way more than I had any idea than the school committee members did. Well, it makes sense, but I guess my question would be, do different members focus on different areas?
the school committee members, does someone focus on curriculum, does someone focus on the legal aspect, assessments and valuations, or do all the school committee members all participate in all the areas?
So it depends, and I'm going to be Medford specific, and for all the years that I was on the school committee. The school committee has subcommittees, and I was, for instance, the chair of the curriculum subcommittee for many, many years. There also was a subcommittee on buildings and grounds. A budget or something, yeah.
Yeah, so there were there were different subcommittees and over the years, they change, they change as the committee members. I mean, at one point we had like 14 subcommittees. And then we sort of, so it's changed as as membership changes, but there were general areas that really stand out. They're also
Many times when special subcommittees would be appointed, for instance, if we were doing an evaluation, that would be a certain number of people. Sometimes negotiations might be a certain number of people. So, you know, if I were to sum up the school committee, there was always the, you hire and fire the superintendent, you approve a budget and you make policy.
So that's the shorthand, but for me, advocacy and, I mean, you know, other pieces of it. And I went through that just to give you a broader- I was like, oh my gosh, my head's spinning. Yeah, so Ron. Yeah, the compensation piece, where does that, and as we go through this, where does the city council cross over in terms of,
their role in that? Or is it just when they pass the budget, they're out of the loop on terms of what happens with that money? Well, the compensation piece, do you mean compensation for like raising the salary of a superintendent or I know a lot of the stuff is, you know, so the school committee negotiates a contract with the superintendent. And
uh, sets the compensation that is part of the overall budget. Um, and so that piece would be included when we submit the budget to the, uh, um, to the city council, but they can't go in and just change that piece of it.
Okay, the school committee itself does we well used to be a stipend and then it changed because of other rules around stipends, and I forget, it's a.
If I roughly say, roughly, it's about, and somebody else put this out, it's about $1,000 a month. And there are two, the school committee on the first, prior to the first meeting, the senior member calls a caucus. And at that caucus, the school committee members themselves elect
a vice chair, because the mayor serves as chair, and the secretary. And frankly, the secretary actually has the most duties because the secretary has to go in. It used to be every other week. Now, what it is right now, I don't want to say, but it's at least every other week goes in.
and reviews the bills. This is an extremely time consuming thing. So there's an extra stipend for the school committee member who does that. I always thought it was a great thing to do because you really got an understanding of what was being spent, because fundamentally you'd see every bill. So there's
there's some small extra compensation for both the secretary. The secretary does the roll call during the meetings. Oh, speaking of that, I'm hoping that somebody could jot down some notes as we're talking so we might be able to include those in the minutes of the meeting. Thank you very much, Aubrey. Okay. So let's see, what else did I need to, including election.
Okay, so all of our members are elected at large, as you know, and, you know, they governed, there are many en masse general laws, there are many, many, many laws that are directions to
how a school committee operates and where we fall under the governance of that. So there is, it's very important that school committee, as we're looking at policy, we can't, we have to make sure we're consistent with mass general law. Phyllis. Does the school committee have any sort of relationship with the Department of Education, the Department of Elementary and Secondary Education?
Well, the school district does. The district does, but the superintendent doesn't necessarily, right, yeah. Well, there certainly are times when we've met, let's see, when there was a special education review, members of the special, of the DESE would come in, and there was a role for us at that point. Again, over years when we used to do high school accreditation, there was a role for school committee members directly.
I certainly have attended different times when I've been, there's been someone from Jesse present, and we've been invited, you know, sometimes it's very celebratory because we've done something great. Yes, Jesse comes out, and the school committee members if they're available attend. But there's no sort of reporting our relationship that way that you have with Jesse, right.
the superintendent is responsible for that. No, I understand that. I completely understand. I'm just trying to figure out where the line ends with. So it's the superintendent who has that initial and the actual formal relationship with DESE. And the committee would commit certain things like accreditation and used to do that with special programs. Yeah. You could say the superintendent does all the work and we get to review it.
Thank you. Yep. Okay. Any other questions about school committee roles? I mean, that's a very general overview to give you some idea of the scope of the position. And of course, you know,
As a school committee member elected at large, I always felt responsible for every student in our district. There are times when there are some crossovers to public schools because there were some places where we do provide services to students in parochial schools, for example. There's also, by the way, I didn't mention the transportation piece since the school committee oversees, make sure the transportation
And boy, if you're a school committee, you probably, for a long time, we got more calls about transportation than anything else. But I think as the years have gone by, it's gotten smoother and smoother. But anyway, okay, so that's the big picture. I don't know if it's a question or a comment, or maybe we'll get addressed down the road, but I think what I'm interested in seeing is how much of what the school committee
does and how they operate is dictated by mass general law versus dictated by the charter versus dictated by maybe MASC versus, you know, rules that they make up as their own entity, and how much change can we affect via the charter on
their operation? So MASC does not dictate anything to us. It provides services, it gives us recommendations, it helps update, it helps us keep on track about policy updates and what we need, how we need to be updating our own
local policies, so they do not dictate to us. Much, there are many, and I went through a lot of it today, there are so many different things in the mass general laws, and part of it depends on what plan of government you have, and whether, as I was looking at them, whether you're a regional district versus, you know, and there's a lot on regional district, there's a lot on charter schools and whatever, so,
But mass general law certainly governs a lot. The local charter really just sets out. I mean, the fundamental responsibilities of the school committee.
You know, were found in the charter because I know when I first went on, but it was very simple, you know, I'm not sure that our scope really involves changing the responsibility of the school committee, because, again, this intended.
Personally, I don't see that we're going to be changing the responsibility of the school committee. I think what we're looking at is should the makeup of the school committee and how we elect school committee members be different than it currently is. And because I think going beyond that is really out of the scope. There may be some budgetary things though that
that because we have a certain budget process and the school committee has a role in presenting the budget to the city council and then the city council works on it. But I don't know how much of that we really get to change. I mean, except from the mayor city council level of budget. Well, I guess my point is that I think the feedback that's out there amongst Medford now is that
The school committee, as it stands, is a pretty unfriendly place, pretty unwelcoming place that doesn't seem to value citizen input. And, you know, seems to do what they want without any, without,
you know, and doesn't seem to want to hear from the citizenry. And that seems to be one issue that comes up a lot. I'm wondering if there's anything that is in our purview to do
to change that. Okay, I think that that's a great point and very specific. I know that myself and one of the other members used to volley back and forth on that issue because I was used to a much more lenient. And then there was some question about the appropriateness and, you know,
The committee member was able to show us that we shouldn't be quite so lenient. So I think that's an excellent question. And I think we have to put that into the next meeting to delve deeper in. But great point, Eunice. Do we have any control over that?
Right. Eunice, can you give me an example of what people, I think this is a very excellent point. Any type of the input that they try to share with the committee that the committee was not open to or listen to? Just even, because I haven't heard that and I know what you're saying is factually you wouldn't be saying it. So just for a little background for myself. I think
About, let's see, this is the end of 2023 and we're bringing in a new group in January. So I think it was the beginning of this year in January. I don't think the school, I've been watching the school committee for a while and, you know, and welcome Paulette to jump in and correct me anytime I'm
Yeah, I caution you, Eunice, please do me a favor and don't get too specific. I won't. Okay. You know where I'm going. Yeah, I do know where you're going. Early, I don't think that the school committee, from my experience watching, had specific
a specific set of operational rules. And earlier this year, a resolution was introduced to bring some more structure to the school committee and the rules and how they operate. And as a result, some of the public participation rules changed dramatically.
where people, instead of getting up to speak on a particular topic or to speak on something that just maybe they were watching a meeting, attending a meeting or whatever came to mind, the rules changed so that they now have to
If they want to speak on something, I'll use school lunches as a topic. If it is not already on the agenda, then if I wanted to speak on school lunches, I have to submit to the superintendent the Wednesday before a Monday meeting my
what I want to say about school lunch. Not an agenda item, a citizen presentation. I have to submit in its entirety what I want to say, my speech, so to speak, to the superintendent for approval.
And if it's approved that I can speak on school lunches, then I can get up and do, I can't remember if it's a three or five minute, you know, presentation on what I think about school lunches. And because, and then if,
And it states specifically in the rules that that is not an opportunity for dialogue with the school committee. If one of the school committee members feels that it is a topic that deserves more consideration, he or she can put it on a future agenda where it will be
further discussed. Can I interrupt for a second? Yeah. So that actually that provision for community participation, and asking members to asking citizens to submit to the superintendent the Wednesday before is actually very long standing. Okay. There was always on the school committee, though,
people who would, if someone came forth during that community participation time, they might let you know they want to talk and you might ask for the committee members to allow that, okay? One of the issues was that there was a period of time when, and remember I was on for a long time, okay? Where it felt like
sometimes it was a game of gotcha. And so there was certainly, and it wasn't gotcha towards the school committee members, it was gotcha towards the superintendent in particular or whatever. And that's not an appropriate way to run a business. The school committee is ultimately. But so there was however,
more of a crackdown in more recent years. But that first part that you said, that's been like that forever. And so there was a tightening and one of the members said this was appropriate. And he showed me a place where it says, and I actually went to the MASC and they said, yes, he's correct.
Um, so we can we can talk about that and I'm very happy to, to do that, but I think we should leave that for the next school committee meeting. I'm also going to say that one of the very difficult places for school committee members is that we are
always there were things that we cannot know because of confidentiality, right? So there's whole areas when it turns with specific students. So when someone gets up at a school committee meeting and they're really angry about something, okay, we might either don't know or even if you did know, you absolutely could not comment on it. It makes school committee members look stupid sometimes, but
it would be absolutely inappropriate for us or for the superintendent. Sometimes a very difficult position for the superintendent to be in, because there's someone who's angry, okay, and maybe has very good reason to be angry, and the superintendent is standing there and can't say a thing. So, general thoughts.
Okay, but we'll take that one about, you know, one of the, I think the question you're asking is, does our committee can, as we talk about the school committee, how it runs is, can we talk about citizen input at meetings specifically?
Okay. Is any other thing like that? Oh, and Ron, I did see here, Ron wrote, I am wondering whether, since this is the first meeting, if each member could take just one minute to talk about their expectations. And I think that makes a whole lot of sense. So maybe we could back up to that right now. And Ron, you want to start with what your expectations are?
Sure, thank you. I know this is a monumental task. I'll be brief because I know we have so much to do. But for me, one of the biggest things we can accomplish, I mean, having Paula here and all her experience is invaluable. I noticed that in the interviews that we haven't got a lot of interviews. I would hope that we can push for a forum that includes current and past
school committee members to understand what the issues they're having, as well as everybody in the community. Secondly, we're gonna talk about the mayor's role for sure. And I understand the complexity of mass general laws versus what we can and cannot do. I'd like to get a copy of the local handbook that the school committee uses for their guidance.
I also think strongly, one of the major reasons why I'm here is because community communication is lacking. I think that the partnership between school committee and city council is weak. I don't know whose fault that is, but it's weak. And then given the current climate of education and our children,
I want more involvement from the parents, more availability. If the parents don't choose to be involved, that's fine, but we need their voice. We need parents to have an outlet to get involved, committees to look at all kinds of things that are going on in our school, both positive and negative. So that's briefly the things that I find extremely important. Okay, good. Eunice?
I think I piggyback a lot on what Ron has said, but I think one of the reasons that I chose to join this subcommittee pretty much goes to what I just said about the community participation. I think we've seen over the last three years maybe, probably since the Columbus School debacle,
that a lot of people are very unhappy, have been very unhappy with some of the responses from the school committee to that issue, to a lot of different issues in terms of allowing the public to participate, offer input, accessibility to their school committee members, and so forth.
I'm wondering, and maybe I'm entirely wrong, but I'm wondering if there's anything that we can do under our purview to make the school committee a place that's more inviting to our citizenry. Because right now I don't think the general public feels like it's a very inviting place to be.
Yes, but I caution to say that of course one of the biggest ways that citizens show how they're feeling about their elected members is the elections which took place and just, you know, reelected all the members.
I certainly understand that there are citizens who are discontent with some of the things in the school committee, but not everybody is. So, but I think looking at the specific question of community participation, since that one is a red herring, that that would be extremely valuable. Aubrey. Yeah, I can keep my memory. I'm interested personally in learning more about the ballot. You can't hear me? I can't hear you. Yeah, you're a little fuzzy.
Can you hear me better now? Yes. Personally, I'm interested in learning more about the boundaries of what the charter impact on this is and setting it up in a way that we could have increased balance with the city council mayor and what we're talking about with families as well. So short and sweet. The last thing you said, Audrey, you're talking about what? The balance with city council, mayor and families. Okay, thank you.
OK, and Phyllis? Yeah, one of my big concerns, well, I have two major areas. I find it challenging to have parents be involved. I hear people here saying that parents want more involvement, but it's always been my experience that we can't get parents to be involved. They're too busy, rightly so. This is not a criticism toward parents.
But one of my main reasons of wanting to be part of this subcommittee is that I'm not really sure the place of the mayor on the school committee or the role of the mayor in the school committee. I think that's a big issue and concern for me. And the second thing is that I wanted to learn more about the role of the school committee in relationship to the school. And I learned quite a bit from the preamble that Paulette gave us this evening.
I'm very concerned about the quality of the educational experience for the students. And that's part and parcel of the role of the superintendent. Ron and I have been trying to interview the superintendent since when? August, I think, Ron? I think we've been trying to interview the superintendent. And I am very frustrated by that. I've called, I've emailed, I've done several things, and I have not been able to get a response
I could talk to her. Oh, that would be wonderful. Could I join you on that interview? Absolutely, that would be lovely. Okay, I can outreach to her and see if I can get... That would be great, Paulette. Just to be clear, the purpose of interviewing the superintendent is? Well, for the charter study.
For the charter study. So to get input from her about how the interactions with city council and school committee and how it affects her position. Okay. Okay. Can I just make a point though? Paulette, I know you have a longstanding relationship with her as a former member, but it shouldn't take that
to get a response from the super. We've been, the 11 or 12 of us have been appointed by the mayor to do very important work in the city. And we're all residents and we're all invested in one way or the other in the school system. But Eunice, I understand where you're going, but- It shouldn't take having you step in.
I understand that, but at the same time, the superintendent's primary responsibility is to the children of the district. And if she hasn't quite figured out, you know, the importance of this particular committee, give her a break. I mean, you know, if I now go to her and sort of say, hey, this is what's going on and we really need your input, could you make time? But I'm not gonna, I'm certainly not gonna hold her feet to the fire because she hasn't done it yet.
You know? So the other thing I thought, Paulette, was that perhaps she didn't know that this was, you know, maybe she didn't know her place in this also and couldn't find a way to figure that out. That's one thing I thought. I mean, I think for me, the critical piece is that we have to keep our eye on the real reason for the problem, the school system. It's for our students. You know, all this, we can get things straight in our own way, but I think that's really important.
I think we also need to fully understand that it's not our role to criticize school committee members, the superintendent, that's not our role. I understand why it's coming up, but that's not our role. And what our role is to say, how is the school committee functioning and is there anything that we are suggesting that goes in the charter so to assure that it's functioning better?
Remember, superintendents change and school committee members change. So it's really, you're thinking about this without specifics, whether you're frustrated with the superintendent or not, or frustrated with school committee members or not. How should it be working to be the most effective? Right. But I would still like if you could get us the interview with her. Yeah, yeah. That would be great. I'll work on it next week. Thank you. Okay.
So, you know, I think that my position here is simply to obviously I have a great interest in the school committee and I'm not.
So that's why I'm here. I thought it was really important to have some level of representation as we were discussing these things. I have to make sure sometimes that I don't
express myself and bring a certain bias to it. For instance, I'll give you a very specific. I love having the mayor on the school committee. Love it. Love it. Probably much more than the mayor. And I'm talking in general, mayors love it because for me as a member, the mayor knew every issue.
Every issue, couldn't hide, ever, always knew it. But many school committees don't have it, and it's time consuming for the mayor, and maybe we want the mayor to be doing something else, you know, like attending city council meetings every month or something. So I'm certainly open to hear the discussion, but that is a funny bias that I happen to bring of sort of saying I loved having the mayor at our meetings.
So, and I admit to the bias. So anyway, next thing. Review the placement of school facilities within Medford board maps. And was it Aubrey who was gonna do this for us? Aubrey, were you able to do that? I just took one of the maps that Eunice sent and put some location points on there, if that's what you mean. Yeah, so can you share it with us?
Oh, it says disabled screen sharing. Make her a co-host and she can share. If you click on the three little buttons by her name at the top. Try now, Aubrey. Yes. So this is one of the board maps, and this is the location of each of the schools here.
Great. And what we see clearly is that there's clusters of schools, which we, you know, because of the Andrews and McGlynn being on the same property, they are not evenly placed between wards, whatever. We kind of knew that, but I just wanted you to be able to see it. Okay.
Yep. Anybody have any comments about that? Oh, by the way, I do want to mention that in the chat, one of the members of the public who did also serve on the school committee totally disagrees with me and says, get rid of the mayor on the school board. So in the interest of being even handed, I mentioned that. Yep. So in terms of the placement of schools, facilities, you know, if it,
were so nice that it broke out, that there was a school in every ward. That would make it more easier to think about ward representation, maybe, for schools. How we do it when the schools are bunched together, does that matter? But I just wanted you to see where they were. Any comments on that? Nope. Straightforward? OK.
Discuss input received so far from school committee interviews and steps for receiving further input. So, I've informally reached out to
a couple of school committee members, but, and I tried to go through all the interviews, trying to pick up pieces, but I didn't get through all of them at the end. Does anybody who has been following all of those particular interviews have, did anybody have anything specific they would wanna add at this point? Otherwise the thought that I have is,
I'm thinking, I'm wondering whether we should, what is the most effective way to get input on this from school committee members? Is it really effective to go and interview each one, or would it be more effective to decide, make up a couple of questions and send them a email and say, please respond? So that we were consistent and
We also were saving time. One of the things I noticed when I was talking to people that kind of went through in their heads, it was sort of a new thought for them. They hadn't really necessarily deliberated on it. And as they talked it through, they might've changed a little bit.
Ward representation sounds great, but no, I did. I represented every school committee. And just in the interest of being uniform and getting feedback from every school committee member who has served, who still lives in Medford, I guess I was gonna, who still lives in Medford, you know, that we can start on from a particular date, but we should go back fairly long. I know, Ron, you've got your hand up. What do you think?
Well, maybe I'm a little bit of a dreamer, but to me, the best thing we could do is, you know, for us and for our organization, I think we, number one, have to establish a better relationship as advocates for everybody and not less, you know, folks worrying like the auditor's coming in to check what they're doing wrong. So we need to all work on that across this whole process. But to me, I see we're a listening organization. That's who we are.
we need to listen to what they're saying. To me, being in a room with all of them, everybody listening, the school committee, past, present, sitting to talk about what they want changed. And I think it gives us the ability to build on what the previous person said, to listen to, well, what if we did this? From the simplest of things, not the major things that we have no control over, things we have control of. And to me,
If we ever got that accomplished, which I know is a dream and not necessarily something that everybody wants but, you know, to sit in a room for two hours to talk about what they want us to start presenting to the public because ultimately this is about every person's vote.
And, you know, I just see us as more of helping them as opposed to criticizing. And I know they all sit there, because we listened to some of the interviews. They all have issues that they want, you know, to make it a better place. Everybody has that goal. So I really, really, and I think you are the person that can bring that credibility to what we're trying to do. And hopefully that we can make that happen.
So you're really proposing that we bring everybody together, we issue an invitation to all former school, current and school committee members, and ask them to come together to discuss their role in
Right. Yeah, I don't see why we wouldn't want to do that. I mean, I just think, you know, Paula, you've been out of the business and you want to be here because you care. I think that that runs across the board. And when we start welcoming people as opposed to, you know, saying you need to change this, you need to change that, I think it could be invaluable. And for the citizens to hear it, too.
change the reputation of everybody. We're a caring society. Medford's a caring place. I'm not giving up yet. So I'd love to see that. But I like to dream. Are you suggesting in person?
I would make the desserts. Yes, in person is so much better. It's so much better. My vision is when I become mayor is Sunday night spaghetti dinner. So everybody sits, looks at each other and gets to talk about issues. And yes, I think it live is there's no replacement for life. Well, I mean, I have to say for me, that's very different than, you know, the one-on-one interviews that
this committee started with. So I guess since I came into this committee late, it never even occurred to me that might be something we could do. I've been having informal discussions, but it would be, I mean, it would be so much fun for me personally. But yeah, if we could issue an invitation out to school committee members, and I think that would be great. So,
Is everybody thinking that that's a positive way to get input? And are there, just to play devil's advocate, are there any negatives to it? The only negative that I can see is would anybody in a group like that, would there be anybody that would be intimidated to speak their mind and say something that might be different or unusual or whatever?
Controversial or they might seem unpopular, but might be a good idea. And wouldn't feel comfortable expressing in a group setting. That they might express 1 on 1 or 2 on 1 with 2 of us in 1 of them.
Well, would it work if as part of this, we made it clear that they could contact, we could have a certain way they could contact us by an adding, maybe we would certainly could propose it to everybody to add additional thoughts. I think it would be a great brainstorming session to get, even if I don't know how many,
You've got the six current and yourself, seven. I can think of three or four more off the top of my head. It's probably, you know, 15. Yeah, so Erin, Ben Aheno, Bill Giglio, Beth Fuller, Sharon. Are we talking about former candidates or former sitting members? I think you'd have to limit it to formal sitting members. I mean, then it becomes a,
You know, I don't know how you do this in a public with the public rules. But, you know, the point is that if we send out invitation to 12 people and one response, isn't that an answer to where we're headed? So I think we really need to work hard on making it the most welcoming thing we do.
in a room with the mayor, the superintendent, the administration, the school administration, school committee members, all people with credentials that have the experience, and we just sit there and listen and brainstorm? Wow. I mean, seems like, seems like a, you know,
Okay, so Ron, you've just widened it to include the superintendent and other people. I kind of have to mull on that to say. Yeah, maybe you're right. Maybe you're right. Maybe it needs to not be done. If we're talking to the superintendent separately, and then just random people who are just on. Yeah, I agree. The superintendent can come for spaghetti after the meeting.
I think the important part, though, is that since it would be still an official meeting. How do we do it. You'd have to write.
have to be public which is okay but we can set rules of restriction in terms of you know have public participation just like we do now but um you know we're all i think if we if we did it we could do it in council chambers similar to how we've done our listening sessions um but then again i think going back if we did it
where we have current and former sitting members. I think administration and school staff need to be done separately. I think they may have different ideas and interests. I think my recommendation would be to do current and former sitting members. I wonder if we could do it in an
open manner similar to like the listening session that's, you know, happening concurrently with a, you know, another few of us. But I think, not that, I think we would want to welcome the public, but
I wouldn't want to get into a position is, you know, Paulette said earlier about any sort of gotcha. You know, sort of game either if I could just, you know, I don't want to take the meeting to a tangent here, but, you know.
City Hall is our City Hall, you know, put the councilors behind the bar and let the citizens listen and just control that environment. I just think it'd be in a happy, content, pleasant, open environment. And I think we can handle that. I know Paulette can handle it. I think, you know, again, the only thing which I'm just
Oh, there's a timing question. Sure. And because, you know, let's face it, everybody's busy in December. Got it. Right. So that puts it to January. And while, frankly, if you wanted feedback quicker, you'd send out an email with questions and say, give us your feedback. And then you might say, would you be interested in a session to discuss this, you know,
I don't know, or do you think that would kill it?
No, I think it's very fair that it's not gonna happen till after January, but I think you're right. I mean, if you could send out a questionnaire, test their interest and give an explanation of what we want to have done, there's no harm in doing that. I mean, and then, but we haven't got, not everybody has done the interview yet. So we're not even at that point yet. So- Right, but I think the thing is that we're not, so the interview,
is a larger picture thing. The interview, you're asking your person about city council, whatever. Here, we're defining it and saying, thinking about your tenure on the school committee. What changes would you like to see incorporated in the charter? Do you think it would be, is it a different way of election? Would it be better or something like that? I'd have to work on.
I'd have to work on language. And so I think that what might make sense is I will work on putting together
a email to school committee members, and I will send it out to this group, and I'll get your feedback, and you can be brutal, okay, and say yay or nay, and if it's nay, then we'll move on to something different, if it's yay or if you've got some refinements, but that would get it out. I would try and get that to you sometime by the end of next week.
Okay, does that seem like a reasonable place? So I would really need all of you to take a look at it and give me feedback. Is that fair? Sure. And I'd be happy to go through, going back as far as I did with the city council to the 2001 election and round up all of the sitting members, the names of the sitting members
Okay, I don't know why you particularly pick that one. Just, you know, some of the work that I did for city council going back to election results and looking at ward representation and so forth. We went back as far as 2001.
If you don't want me to go back as far as that, I don't have to. Yeah, well, we'll see. I'd like to see how far it goes. I can't remember where some of the members, like Beth Fuller, I don't remember what year she served. But I'd love to have her input, and Sharon Guzik, and other people who I know over the years. So I'd like to be as comprehensive as possible. OK. Unfortunately, some of the members. Paulette? Yes.
I'm sorry, everyone, I have to switch to my phone because I have to drop my car off of services and this is the only ride I could get. I'm not looking at my phone, but I think that's the best way to do it, to send that email out to us. I just wanted to say that while I had a chance to say that. I think that's a great idea. Okay. Okay, sounds good. Let's see here. So I think we've sort of got that.
Create questions, and this was something I was hoping we would do today, for soliciting input from school committee members across the state via the Mass. Association of School Committees mailing list. So we have, one of the things with the people we're talking to is we've only had one experience. The only experience we've had is being elected at large and having two-year terms.
So I thought it would be useful to send out a email to the MASC mailing list, which exists, and ask for people if they would be kind enough to give us some feedback about how their community works in terms of the makeup of their school committee, if it's ward representation,
how that works, how long their terms are, that kind of thing. So that's what I was getting at, only because I sort of feel it would be really useful for us, particularly from the people who have ward representation for school committee, to give us some feedback. What do they think? You know, how does it work in their town? I have talked over the years to some, and
You know, I kind of think what you're used to works for you, but I think we need to hear that. And I'd love to hear from them. You know, some of them do have mayors as chairs. Some of them have mayors as members. Some of them don't have the mayor at all. So that was what I was looking for. And I was wondering what information you would particularly want me to solicit if you could think of it as a question.
Would this be something that the Collins Center already has? This is personal feedback. Oh, OK. How they think about it. The Collins Center can tell us how the committees are made up. But I'm really looking at, how do you think it works? Ron.
Well, does the site have like a blog site where you can start a thread of asking people and just have a live stream of thought on those kinds of questions? I've always done it by the mailing list. Yeah, I'm just curious. But it goes out by mailing list. Yeah, I think it's a great, I think getting their feedback is great. We just have to make sure we're composing the correct email.
Yeah, so in terms of composing the correct email. So board representation is a very important one. The mayor's role on their school committee is another one. And asking about any recent changes to their policies that they feel are enhancing their ability to serve the community. I think those are.
It's always good to get. Okay, asking about any recent changes to policy that they think. That they think has enhanced their ability to serve the community. Yeah. I would use the role impact instead of enhance in case it's not a positive. Yeah, good idea. Yes, that's a good word. Yeah, you're right. I think term limits, term lengths,
And are there terms, I think I was reading about, I think we have Melrose's charter from the Collins Center, and I pay a bit of attention to Melrose because my aunt lives there. I think they have staggered terms. So instead of, like we do every two years, the entire group can change.
um uh staggered terms only means some of them will change or could change um so that would be a question i would be wondering about too yeah i mean i'm sorry that information probably the call center definitely has
Yeah, I mean, we can look at the, I was just more looking, yeah, looking just for some feedback about how they feel about how their particular school committee is set up in their town or city. Yeah, the structure of it, right? Yeah, the structure. Thank you. I might include an open-ended response to ask something along the lines of if you could change one thing, what would it be? Oh, I like that. Yeah, that's a good question.
Now, if you could change one thing about the structure of your committee, because every school committee member is going to answer, we need more money. So we need to specify what we're asking about what they want to change. And maybe we put that in there, Paulette, other than financial.
you know, assumptive to that effect. Because I think you're right, they probably will not want to work, you know, question about finances. But are we asking them in general, because, you know, again, the scope of our, it's really about the school committee. Yeah. If you could change one thing about the school committee. Now, if they say, I'd like to change the other members. Oh, God. I think we should just ask about the structure of the committee. Okay.
All right, I think one thing I know in order to get a response, I also have to work on keeping it short and sweet. Yeah.
you know, because if it gets too complicated, then we won't get the responses. It's a little bit too bad. And I realized this was when we ended up with this meeting, I could have gone down to the conference and talked to a whole lot of people in person, but then we had set up this meeting. So I was like, oh, I can't do that. So anyway, but it's always worth a shot. I mean, there are times when things go on the MASC listserv and lots of people, and there's lots of times, you know, you get six responses.
but you might get someone who feels very passionately about it. So I just thought it would be interesting since it's a resource that we can utilize, we might as well. All right. If you send that email around, I think one of the things that increases responses is a subject line. So we can help if when we're reviewing, review the subject line to make sure it looks, you know. What subject line do we need?
input requested something, and then a couple words about what it is. Something that mostly that doesn't feel like spam and that I would click on it and not get a virus. Okay. Again, I think again, let me see what I come up with as a draft. If I get stymied, I'll let you know. But I think that that's the best starting point for us right now.
Okay, number five is, and our time is at 8.08, so we're doing okay. Review any community feedback relating to the school committee organization as it relates to charter review. And I did say before I had started reading, sometimes I saw school committee mentioned, but I didn't see a whole lot of specifics. Ron, have you looked at those interviews in depth?
Well, I've looked at them, I've taken a look at them, but there's not, in general, they're pretty quick answers. We don't really, the interview process is important, the surveys are important, but there's a lot of quick answers that really need further development, in my opinion. But I just don't see a lot of the school committee people on this interview list in Google Docs.
I think Jenny might be the only one. I think Jenny is the only one. Right. Jenny Graham is on there but other than that, we don't have in I think that, you know, you know, busy time for them for sure, you know, with elections and this time.
And I think at this point, we have an outreach to them and said, would you meet us for an interview? And again, my intentions were good to do that. I've done it informally, but I certainly haven't hit everybody. And I wanna make sure that everyone is included. But again, I kind of feel like we need to start somewhere in getting feedback on the school committee
issue itself and not worrying about trying to get everyone in. But when I send out an email to everybody, that might help us when we get those feedback. So I will make it clear in the email that our committee, all of us will be looking at their responses so that we can see where they're headed. Does that sound all right? Yes.
Yeah, okay. Okay, so community participation. I think Bill was here. Bill, do you have anything you wanna say? Bill, are you here? Can you unmute him? Ron, where? Yeah, he's not being, yeah, he's there. It was me that was not on mute, I'm sorry.
No, I don't have anything to say tonight. I'm just sort of taking this all in. A lot of great points, you know, what the school committee has brought up tonight. So I really appreciate everything tonight. Okay, great. So Bill, you'll be getting a solicitation from us, your input, and we would really appreciate it. No, absolutely. That's what makes the stuff work when there's not,
much city participation in the city, it seems like, so. Absolutely, I will. Okay, that sounds great, Bill. Thanks a lot. Thank you. Okay, now we are, it is not yet 8.15, and some of this is because I've
instead of trying to wordsmith specific things here, which was what my original intent was, is I just said, look, let me send out something to you. Is that acceptable to you guys? Yes. Sure. Okay. Absolutely. So if you wanna wordsmith it here, we can do that. No, I'm okay. If there's anything that you are worried about, I'd be happy to brainstorm, but otherwise it's easier to react than it is to. Okay, now,
The other things that I think that are important is Eunice earlier brought up a specific, which had to do with community participation. And so I think that on our next agenda, we should take that specifically, okay? It's gonna take some time to get these emails together and out and feedback. I think,
that today is, what is November 8th? Boy, I hate to do the week before Christmas, but that's kind of what I'm thinking. Because I happen to know that the week of, the first week in December and the second week of December is already pretty challenging.
Are you talking about for our next meeting? What? You're talking about for our next meeting? Yeah, for our next meeting. So that would be sometime in the week of the 11th. Well, that is a particularly challenging week for me. No, it'll be the 18th, the week before Christmas. Yeah, the week of the 11th is not going to be good.
Yeah, it's my birthday. That's what I was. That's what I was referring to. I just happened to have a number of things. We'll have a meeting on the Thursday, the previous Thursday, right? Our regular monthly meeting will be on the 7th. 7th. It's Thanksgiving in between.
Um, I'll take, I'll take a look at a good calendar. Um, and if I can, if I can see a date and I know that there's subcommittee meetings, I took a look at the overall and I saw quite a few, you know, of the other subcommittee meetings that some of you are on. I wonder if, and this might be a question for Melva, um,
But now that we have various subcommittee meetings going along with our regular monthly and other listening sessions and other things, I wonder if we can put up on Google Docs who belongs to what subcommittee or who has what responsibility to something or other and a calendar so that I just happen to look at this week because I'm sort of become the liaison to the TV station. And I let Kevin know when we have meetings,
so that he can do his best. We're on television as we speak and do his best to get things up and we record them as well. And I just happened to look and we're here tonight. There's also a listening session going on as we speak. Tomorrow night, the preamble group is meeting and then the legislative executive folks are meeting Saturday morning at 10. So
could we begin to put up a calendar on Google Docs with who's on what committee and when those committee meetings are meeting so that we're getting the right people on the right dates for the right things and we're not, you know, overlapping. I think we have to ask Milva that or I will tell you, I'm not your Google Doc person. So I'm not going to volunteer to do that, though. I think it's a very good idea.
Yeah, I think I'm not sure that I'm the Google Doc person either. I'm still trying to figure out how that thing works. But if somebody is and can collate all that together and have maybe each facilitator of each subcommittee filtered to one person as soon as a meeting is set up, and then the Google Doc king or queen can
put it up and then like now you can look and say, oh, well, Eunice is on the, you know, preamble committee meeting and she's there meeting on X day. So that's not going to work for us. So, so we have a little bit more, you know, we can figure things out a bit better. Okay. Yeah. I totally agree, but I think we have to ask Milva that. Okay. I'm happy to pose that to her.
Okay, so I think that the other things, Aubrey, if I could ask you if you have enough jot downs to do a preliminary minutes of this meeting? I do, yes. Could you do, that would be great. And I think in terms of a date, I'm not gonna do a specific date right now, but I will take a look at the calendar and I'll send something out to you.
I'm just trying to figure out when I get, you know, we want to get our email off to both our own school committee members and those on the MASC meeting list. We want to have that go out after Thanksgiving. Wait, no, maybe before Thanksgiving. I have to take a look. Oh, Thanksgiving is so early.
The date that would probably most work is the Monday after Thanksgiving. So everybody's fresh and sees it and whatever. But I will take a look just to make sure my timing is right on that. My only pause about that email would be I think we're including an invitation or a request for the in-person gathering. Would it be possible to include the date for that in the email, even if it's sometime in January? OK.
I guess I was asking people whether they would be willing to get together. And then I would say yes, pending date and time, or maybe. Okay, that's a good idea. Okay, so sometime in January though, right? That's what we're thinking for that type of meeting? Yeah. So what is our target date of reporting back anything or
You know, I know, I think in our original discussion of putting this subcommittee together, we were to report back any of our findings in the monthly December meeting, which clearly is not possible. Right. You know, I think we need to push that to February or March.
I guess I'm thinking right now as we're talking that we also need to think more specific things that we need to consider. So let's just go through. We need to ask about the role of the mayor, the length of terms, right? I mean, these are things that we need to, when we're finished with this, we're gonna need to give,
to be able to know what we're recommending or what we're, okay, the length of terms, the makeup. And when I say makeup, I mean, you know, elected by wards or at large. I think that's a very complicated question in some ways because,
if there's an interplay between the city council, and I've been trying to wrap my head around this, if we go to, if at some point we were go to ward representation for city council, plus three at large, like we've discussed, and then you've got a school committee.
Do they go to ward representation? Do you have a school committee that's that big? There's not a school in each ward. If you don't go, if you continue at large, and I went back to the plan that was suggested in 1978, and even when they were suggesting ward representation for the city council, they were not suggesting ward representation for school committee.
If you have this ward representation in the city council, you've got your city council members able to run in a much smaller venue, okay, in a ward. But if you maintained school committee at large,
it's a much more expensive race for your school committee members. And that of course, as you know, school committee members always stipend is much less than the city council makes. So that seems like a funny thing to me, but maybe it doesn't matter. But that's one of the things, I mean, as we go further in our discussion, I think that's one of the questions that we're ultimately asking is what should be the makeup of
how should we do, how should we elect our school committee members? Is that what everybody else is thinking? It's part of the discussion for sure. Yeah, I think it's something that we need to explore. Okay. So maybe some of those questions are what we have to do on our next, the next time we meet is discuss those things. So I'll take a look at a calendar and figure out,
If I said 14th is a Thursday. I can't do the 14th. Okay. The following Monday would be 15, 16, 17, 18, 19th. 18th. 18th, thank you. Yeah. 18th? Nope. Nope.
I can do the 19th. Tuesday, the 19th? Yep. Eunice, I know you don't like to do it on city council nights. And I can tell you that that's the last meeting of the year and that they'll be sending Nicole, Rick, and Adam off with some fanfare that night. Right. I mean, I can miss it, you know. Yeah, no. I'm not married to it. No. You can't do the 14th.
Nope, I cannot, I have a family commitment. Yeah, Monday the 11th. Oh, that sounds good. Yeah, yep. Okay, it's not great with it, so there's, I'm also in charge of the Medford Educational Foundation, and I may need that night for that, and that's my, so I'm not certain, but I'll take a look. We'll see what they come up with.
I don't think we want to go beyond the 19th or maybe the 20th. After that, we're getting... No, my kids are arriving. There you go. I can't do that. All right. Well, we've made it to 823. I think we've got a good starting point and I'll get those potential emails out to you. You'll give me some feedback. We'll get that piece out.
In the meantime, in the next agenda, we'll talk a little bit more about the roles of the mayor and the, I mean, it would be nice to have feedback for that, but we'll see where we're at. If you have any things you would like to see on the agenda the next time, I would really appreciate hearing from you. Okay. Okay. Yeah, it was a great meeting, Paula. It was a great meeting. Oh, thank you. Okay. Any more feedback, Bill?
I don't know if he's still with us. Bill, you want to say anything else? No. OK, I think we're good. And I will put together a list of all school committee. Do we want both the seated members and candidates? I can do both. Yes, sure.
You can put that data together, but I think we're contacting the seated and formerly seated members. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Yeah. I'll gather it all together in the next several days. Okay. And units, if you find emails that would make it even easier for me. I can come up with. Okay. I mean, there's a couple that I know I have already. Yeah.
Paul, and I apologize, my phone was across the room. I was listening, I didn't get over to it in time. Thank you. Just as we're winding up, I just wanted to know if you wanted to say anything else. No, thank you very much. Okay, take care. Okay, guys, I think we're set. Thank you so much. All right, bye. Thanks, everybody. I really, really hope we get to get, like, I'm gonna propose that we get together sometime in person, just because I'd like to see you in person. With some Oyster Bay, right?
Yes, absolutely, Paulette. Bye, everybody. Where I'm from. Happy Thanksgiving. Happy Thanksgiving. Good night. Thank you, Ron, for running the meeting. No problem. Bye.