[SPEAKER_01]: So can you talk a little bit about C2.2 and what are the features that advanced this option?
[SPEAKER_00]: One of the things that we're trying to do with any of these designs is find ways of making the building more compact and easier for students to navigate and not having to go quite as far from one end of the building to the next.
[SPEAKER_00]: So this building does achieve some of those goals in terms of trying to make it a little bit more compact.
[SPEAKER_00]: It does result in an increase in the number of vertical stories that were going up.
[SPEAKER_00]: to be able to navigate up that hillside as we go.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's also important to note that it may not be a straight building here that's going up six stories.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to be moving up with the hillside as it rises up towards Edgerly Field and will help to alleviate some of the vertical implications of the building in that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a lot of people, rightfully so, my own kids included, who are really worried about the impact of this project on the students who will live through it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So can you talk a little bit about this option?
[SPEAKER_01]: This does seem to have a lot of modular classrooms, but talk about sort of the thinking that you all are doing with some of the feedback that you've gotten particularly around that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The ways that we can think about minimizing or potentially eliminating, though that may be a tall lift at the end of the day, is to think about whether or not we can open portions of the existing building that can be built not on the footprint of the existing building.
[SPEAKER_00]: By that way we're essentially creating a modular classroom building that is the new structure in place.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would not be the entirety of it completed and there will still be some accommodations that would need to be made.
[SPEAKER_00]: There would still need to be potential for students to move outside between a portion of the new building and the existing building while the rest of the construction is ongoing, later phases of construction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we have that available to us as an opportunity.
[SPEAKER_00]: The other thing that we have here is similar to what we described for the B video, the B option as we were talking about in the prior video, is to think about making some efficiencies in terms of the classroom usage model upfront before we actually move too far into the process.
[SPEAKER_00]: So if we can reduce the overall number of classrooms that we need to operate the school,
[SPEAKER_00]: that will reduce the amount of modular classrooms that we need or reduce potentially the amount of the new building that we have to have online before we tear down some other sections.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure and when I am trying to think back to our meeting and some of the things people were talking about in addition to some of the concerns like this was a really like long conversation about this option.
[SPEAKER_01]: There was also some some like excitement about this option, which if I am like recalling the conversation, the things people liked about this option was that it did not stuff the whole building up on Edgerly Field, which is really a huge climb from Winthrop Street, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: And so the the placement sort of was a little bit more inviting, I think, for for some.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the other thing this seemed to
[SPEAKER_01]: do at least in my mind was like optimize the space in a different way than some of the other designs did in that that space on the west side is limited but we're gonna like sort of use it here and that opens up what I see at the bottom of this screen which is it looks like a pretty sizable playing field with parking underneath.
[SPEAKER_01]: So can you talk about that field and what its potential is as well?
[SPEAKER_00]: sure and i just i want to reinforce as well what you mentioned about the football practice field being a sort of challenging area of the site it is elevated and it's tough to access from other areas for its current purpose so by using that for a portion of the addition construction it really does allow us a much
[SPEAKER_00]: more open area to work with on the southern part of the site.
[SPEAKER_00]: This particular option, what it was illustrating and also was included in the price for it, is a synthetic turf playing field located over the top of a large parking area down below it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so when you look at this diagram, you don't see a large, vast parking lot anywhere, and that's because it is tucked underneath the field.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we do think that this can provide a really wonderful both experience approaching the building in terms of drop off, but also alleviate some of the traffic congestion that's here.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's one of the things that we're focusing on as we look at all these options is what can we do on site to streamline the circulation vehicular.
[SPEAKER_00]: to try to actually improve the ingress and the egress from the site as well by not creating a bottleneck, by not creating situations where there has to be someone managing traffic out there, standing there, guiding people back and forth, and really trying to navigate something that is overly complex.
[SPEAKER_00]: The simplification of traffic is definitely something that will be facilitated by that field as well because it offers the opportunity to pass around it.