Amen. The 20th regular meeting of the Medford City Council will come to order. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Camuso. Present. Councilor Caviello. Present. Councilor Knight. Present. Vice President Lohan Curran. Present. Councilor Marks. Present. Councilor Penta. Present. President DeLucia. Present. Seven present, none absent. Please rise to salute the flag.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America, and to the republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all. Chair recognizes Vice President Longo Kern. Madam Vice President. Thank you, President De La Russo. I just want to move suspension of the rules to take paper 15-502 under motions, orders, and resolutions off the table.
On the motion of Vice President Lugo-Curran to take 15.502. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries. 15.502 offered by Vice President Lugo-Curran. Be it resolved that the Medford City Council be updated by a community group who is working on a proposal for the Malden Hospital redevelopment. Madam Vice President. Thank you, President De La Russo. There has been obviously a lot of talk and discussion with regards to the
site, the Malden Hospital site. The city council in Malden had a meeting probably six months back. I know it was during one of the storms. They had that in Malden that I attended. And a number of Medford residents obviously have a great concern of the development that's being proposed at that site. Three acres is on Medford property. It's Medford land. And it also, half of the project, if not most of the project,
project abuts Medford homes, families, our streets, our roads. There's great concern about the traffic, air quality, the gate, obviously, that is located on the property that leads into the Medford streets. From that meeting, you know, probably even before that meeting, a group has organized and has had private meetings, or public meetings, but on Saturdays, and things to come up with a plan
on how they see the Malden site being redeveloped. With that plan, there's open space, there's less units, less residential than obviously a developer would like. It's more environmentally friendly, it's better for both Malden and Medford, and they would like to come and propose their plan, something that they've met in work groups, they've done a lot of work on the project. I was able to attend,
just a portion of one of the meetings on, I believe, a Saturday morning. And they just put a really lot of work into it, and I think it's for the betterment of Malden, but obviously Medford as well, and something that council should be updated on. It's a community-driven project, and I welcome the discussion, and I welcome hearing more about what has taken place since the last meeting I've attended.
I know a packet was given to each councillor on the work they've done, so maybe you could follow along. Someone's going to speak on behalf of the group, Madam Vice President? Yes. Good evening. Mr. Fitzpatrick. Please state your name and address for the record. Welcome. Good evening, Councillor De La Russa, and through you to
the entire Council. My name is Bob Fitzpatrick. I live at 20 Oak Road in Medford, which is up in the aforementioned Fulton Heights neighbourhood, where this particular proposal is set to be built. So as Councillor
pointed out, I'm here just to draw your attention to an important issue that my neighbors and I are extremely concerned about, and that is the former Malden Hospital site. It is our hope that you, members of the City Council, will support us in our effort to protect our neighborhood from the impacts of ill-considered overdevelopment. We're looking to the Council for whatever assistance or guidance you can provide to us.
As residents of the Heights, we're very concerned about the current proposal to bring dense housing development to the former hospital site. We would like to see something done with the site, but it needs to be of a nature and scale that fits with the neighborhood. The current proposal does not. So if you look at this first board there, that is the current proposal. That is 375 units of housing
500 cars, underground parking. It's an extremely dense development. And when you talk about bringing that number of cars into a neighborhood like ours, I'm sure that you're all familiar with the Heights neighborhood. A few of you, I'm sure, have gotten lost up there at one time or other.
Here's a map, and you can just see how dense that neighborhood is. And what you'll also know is that we're talking very steep hills, very windy roads, very narrow streets. The winter we just went through, this was all pretty much one-ways. If you add 500 cars to the bottom of this neighborhood,
Let me grab this thing. You're going to see here, a developer will probably tell you that people who are living here are going to come out and they're going to drive down the Fells Way and they're going to come down, yeah, Fells Way East and turn on 60 and come up Fells Way West. They're not going to do any of those things. They're going to come out Murray Hill Road, they're going to come up Fells Ave, just like everybody does currently, they're going to
take the left on Fulton and the right on Ridgeway, driving through these neighborhoods, it's gonna be, you know, and again, people are already using that as a cutthroat. If you had 500 cars, it's just gonna be completely unmanageable. And I think that if you talk to the public safety officials here in Medford, they'll tell you the same thing.
As Councillor Donohue-Curran pointed out, this development is mostly in Malden. So this is an issue for us, right? Because Malden will have sort of the big say in what gets developed there. But about 20% or so is in Medford. And all of the abutters are in Medford, our neighborhood. On the other side, on the Malden side, you have Felsmere Pond,
The cemetery, you have Fellsway East. On our side, you have a neighborhood. Speaking of Fellsmere Pond, it's a beautiful little spot. If you did this kind of dense development that they're talking about, you're going to add a lot of runoff. You're going to really degrade that site quite a bit. We have a proposal that will
fit in much better with the neighborhood we think. I also wanted to bring to your attention just some of the things that folks that I've been proud to be associated with have been doing sort of on their own. We've been hosting neighbor-led discussions to get input and vision, this sort of vision that you see here. We've got petition signatures against this development.
250 from Medford and 324 signatures from Malden so far. We've hosted an information table at Felsmere Pond on Saturdays, gathered volunteers, knocking on doors to alert the community of this pending dense housing development. I think you'll see some folks came out tonight because they got a knock on the door, they got a flyer. We published letters to the editors, the Medford transcript, the Malden Observer,
and most recently Boston Globe North. We've been engaged with Malden City officials to voice our community's concerns as well as theirs and coordinating community meetings. The next one is tomorrow at the Beebe School. And then we've done some digging into land donation requirements because there's some question as to whether they should be allowed to do this given that it was a hospital site and that
the land was donated and there may be some covenants that they could be in violation of. And so, finally, we've developed this alternative plan. Now, clearly we don't own the site. We can't dictate what happens there. But when you look at a site and you say, it's one thing to say, that's a terrible idea.
That is a terrible idea. But then, so what else could you do? So we've come up with an alternate plan, you see it here, small mixed use housing, 70, 80 units, something that's within current zoning, the multi-use lawn, this retention pond, because again, we have all that runoff. If you've ever been in our neighborhood,
After rain like we've had recently, it's a torrential river flowing down the hill. So this provides water retention, lots of permeable surfaces, places for people to recreate, relax, enjoy some green space, as opposed to just bringing large amounts of traffic into the neighborhood. So again, I'm here to bring you guys
this information and to say we would really appreciate your help. Any advice you can give us, any work you can do with the city of Malden, your counterparts there to say, is there some way that our two cities can work together on this? Because again, it is mostly in Malden, but the impacts are mostly to Medford. So with that, I'll close and happy to answer any questions you might have.
Thank you, Madam Vice President. Thank you, President De La Russo. I think it's important to point out our Office of Community Development Director was at the public meeting in Malden in front of the City Council. I, as well, you know, with my help and my colleagues have requested, sent requests to her for updates and to stay involved. And I think that's extremely important. And I think it's extremely important for the City Council to be on top of the administration to make sure they know what's going on. We appreciate it. Because it seems like the City Council is receptive to what
the public wants, but not necessarily what Medford wants. And it's really important, like you said, every abutter, there are, you know, 40 homes that directly abut, plus, you know, obviously, but directly abut that property, and those are Medford homes. This is Medford that's gonna, you know, fall victim to any negative, anything negative that comes from that site, and obviously that is,
extremely thickly settled, 500 plus cars, however many units they're proposing, it's just too much. And there's been other times this council and the city has had to fight for projects because they're just too large in size. So that's one thing that I'm glad you're working on. Yeah, I wanted to say, to thank you. I saw you at one of the meetings we had over at the church, I believe in Malden.
a few weeks back, so. And I was before the city council in Malden and kept having my hand up, but if they knew you were from Medford, they didn't want to hear it to the point where they said, okay, now let's, somebody did get a question in from Medford and it was, okay, now let's hear more from our Malden residents. And we almost felt like, hey, we should have a say too, but our office of community development director was there. There may be, there's going to be a new mayor. So hopefully whoever that is can really take a lead on this and get together with Malden and make sure that our,
our neighborhood is protected. I know if you want to just maybe explain more of, you know, what you've gathered from the public meetings, whether it's, you know, that plan or something similar to that plan or components of that plan that hopefully Malden and Medford can work into the project, I think anything you take from the community's plan versus the developer's plan is going to be a
you know, beneficial. No, exactly. And, and, and we should stress, I mean, again, this is, this is, this is an idea and it's, it, it shows what you could do, right? You could have a, a, an amount of housing that makes sense for the site. You could, you could do it in a way where you had a multi-use for, you know, other purposes and event pavilion, what have you. But I mean, another,
developer designer could come along and say oh well you know tweak it you know this this way or that but but here you have like concrete example of yeah there is something else that you could do that's something that would fit with the neighborhood that you know the neighbors would be able to access as opposed to just being impacted by yeah and I can just speak as one council that lives in the Heights I mean I know the traffic and you know I know what goes on in the area and I know I drive by
the pond all the time and it is just backed up traffic. So to make that worse is obviously not beneficial for the city of Medford and is just going to clog up our roads and deep within the heights is not going to see a positive impact from this. So I thank you, Bob. And I think, you know, I thank the committee for taking their Saturday mornings, a number of mornings to meet. I've only made one meeting, but to meet and go over this and come up with these plans, it's, you know, something to be proud of.
and the city, as a council, thank you. And I'm glad you came to present. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you, Councillor. And thank you, Madam Vice President. On the motion of Councillor Penta. I'm sorry. There you are. Maybe I misunderstood it. So I want you to make this perfectly clear before I make my comment. You have what you call a retention
in your example. Could you explain that again? The retention pond? Yes. Could you explain that again and why you're calling it that? What's the purpose of that? Okay, so, sure. The purpose of that is because this is,
on a hill, and it's directly above Felsmere Pond. And the water, we have huge runoff problems already. So this is just, the retention pond is a way that
You can collect that runoff before it comes pouring down so that the water has some place to go. And you'll have like, usually do like plants or something like that so it doesn't become stagnant. So you're saying that this retention pond would satisfy the proposal of mixed use and residential home housings that you're proposing?
So if the at present proposal by the developer takes place, this retention pond couldn't service it. Well, no. So if the current proposal takes place, there'd be no place to put it. But it's not, let me be clear, it's not designed to, it's not like a septic or anything like that. It's just a topographical feature, right? It is a way to do stormwater
runoff management. I mean, if you go to like the Assembly Square development, you'll see they've done some similar things where, especially like if you're on the train, you can see they have little, but they look almost like little ponds and they have like nice grass and stuff in them. And in the rainy season, it gets kind of, it gets good enough water in it for a duck to swim around, but then it can dry out. It's, it's, it's that kind of an idea. If I understand it, once again, if I'm looking at this and trying to understand it,
This retention pond with your proposal or whoever put this proposal together seems to be somewhat satisfactory with a lesser density use of housing, correct? And by having that lesser density use of housing, the question then becomes of the housing that's being proposed, how many cars, how many vehicles? Because if it's going to be according to our present zoning ordinances, I think it's two and a half cars per unit for condos.
And if that's the case, how many cars would you proposing for how many units? Okay. Um, I, I w I would say a couple of things on that. Um, one of the things that, that, that's been discussed in terms of, of, of the mixed use housing is possibility of, uh, some elder housing being, being included in that, which would, um, which the city needs more of, and that would reduce the amount of cars that would be required. Um,
So we would hope to get the total number of cars down below 100, I would think. But we're trying to, again, reduce the impact as much as possible, without saying, well, nothing can go there. And what you're proposing, is the height of the building, are buildings higher or lower than what's presently there? About the same, right?
Yes. I think it's about the same. It's about the same. And the proposal is much higher. The proposal actually is, is just denser. You'll see, we actually have on this, on this, uh, here you can see we've marked what the height. So this is like four to five stories, two to three, two to three, four, four, three, three. So, so the height,
of the buildings isn't a particular issue, it's the density that really creates the issue. Again, just superficially, if we're looking at it from a private developer's perspective, he's trying to develop that to make the most amount of money at the highest density. And if we're looking at it from the community's perspective, City of Medford, area residents, immediate abutters, if something has to go there, it should be looked at as being the least intrusive, the least obstructive, and at the same time,
beneficial with a community. The entire community not only has a say, but there is some sense of agreement. So I would suggest that before this, your proposal or to get your proposal going, even for the purposes of a discussion that I would think that you might have to bring this back to the developer and let them know that you've already been to the Memphis city council. I mean, I, there's no way I could support what they're proposing. It just doesn't make any sense at all, but more concerned. I'm more concerned about my community, our city,
and the immediate impact that the neighbors have, because I think there's some sense of realization that something is going to be developed there, and some shape, mean, and reform. So rather than preclude it and nix it and say, no, we don't want anything, let's be realistic, let's use some common sense, and let's just see how far they're willing to compromise. And if they're not willing to compromise, then neither should you, and neither should the residents. Because to me, I mean, you were there first, you pay the taxes first, you've lived through this, and you know what the neighborhood and the area can take.
much more than anyone else, not even the developer knows that. He's just going to build it and see you later and goodbye and make his money. And he's going to leave the problem for the city of Medford. No, that's, that's exactly right. That's why, you know, um, our first, our first order of business again was to get organized to come up with, um, some kind of alternate plan. Um, yeah, we would, we would love to work with, uh, with the developer, with whoever,
and say, you know, here's an idea, what's yours? We want smaller, we want livable. Again, the city of Medford could really use some senior housing. I think that would be a great use for it. Let's come up with something that will give the developer the return that he needs, even if it's not as much as he would like, that gives the city of Malden the taxes that, you know, some amount of taxes that they are looking for, but doesn't impact. And you also have to look at the cut-through area
by that hospital section over there, because the neighborhood is going to take some of that impact. Oh, yeah. They come straight up one road, and they'll go right up Waterville and probably past my house on Oak Road on their way out to Fell's Ave and down. We've got a little tiny rotary up there in the heights. They're going to blow right through it. I'll be out walking my dog, and they'll be just driving right by. You got it. OK. Thank you. You're welcome.
Councillor Camuso. Thank you, Mr. President, and I want to thank the neighbours and especially Mr. Fitzpatrick for coming here this evening. You know, this is going to be a major impact on our community, and this City Council, under the resolution of Councillor Marks, actually worked with our Chief of Police to put up some sort of structure on the Medford side so that it's not only somewhat aesthetically pleasing,
but also just to cut the flow of traffic as a cut through. I remember for many, many years when it was the Malden hospital, it was a cut through and it'd be thousands of cars per day. Every change of shift at night, ambulances coming up there and just, it was, uh, it was chaos in the residential neighborhood. And it wasn't like our hospital that is abutted by Lawrence road, governor's ave and forest street. It was small little, uh, homes on a,
streets that's traversed by two vehicles, and you can't even fit a car parked on the side when two vehicles are going by. So it's a big difference when an ambulance is going through there with the lights on, not necessarily the siren, because when they get to that point, they'd always shut it off, as the neighbors know. But the red lights and everything else would light the whole house up. With that being said, I think we have to be very cognizant of the fact, Mr. President, that this is a city of Malden project. Malden has the
We're all and be all as far as getting the vendor slash developer into the table and actually can arrange an agreement with them. Where Medford, we're limited because the amount of housing and developing happening on the Medford side, if they do it consistent with the current zoning and they don't have to go to the board of appeals, there's really nothing Medford could do. If it's scaled back to the point where it's going to
where it's going to fit within our zoning ordinances. But I think we should send a resolve to the City of Malden, the Mayor Christensen, as well as to their City Council that we do want to work with them, same way Malden and Everett worked with us during station landing in Somerville, and as well as the City of Medford working with the Stoneham development up at the New England Memorial Hospital.
We're cognizant of the fact that some development is going to take place there. Quite honestly, I talked to several of the neighbours and they're just sick and tired of seeing the vacant building. They said they have rodents going in there. There's people that sneak in and try to take it over living there. And unfortunately, it's not conducive to a good quality of life as well. So I think we just got to send the message in a nice tone that we want to work with them. We're interested in seeing good, prudent development. But at the same token, we have to understand that Malden
is the driving force behind this, and they're the only people. Now, Malden, we'll have to realize that the city of Medford could take them to court and tie up the job for 10 years if they wanted to. But we don't want to spend our taxpayers' money if we don't have to as well. So I think we just have to send a message that we understand it. And as I said, you look at some of the developments that we had in our community over the years, and the surrounding communities did not take us to court, worked with us. But we were very amenable sitting down with them, too.
talking about traffic flow and things that we could do as our community. But I think we have to do that with Malden and at least send the message that we're on top of this. Our neighbors, our taxpayers are very concerned. And as long as we're all on this city council, we're going to continue to monitor the situation, but most importantly, send the strong message that we want something a little bit scaled back, number one, and number two, something that's not going to affect
the runoff, because I've seen projects like this where people that live in an area don't have groundwater coming through their basements, and then you do a project of this magnitude, next thing you know, the next storm, they have groundwater. It just changes the whole flow of things, stormwater, runoff water. So I just want to thank Councillor Lungo-Kern for bringing this up this evening. It's something that we've all been following.
I think we have to be very cognizant of the fact that it is Malden. And I mean, there is small groups in Malden that are saying they don't want a project at all. And quite honestly, I think that's unrealistic, because you're better off having to say something that you get there than someone coming in and saying, hey, we're going to make this whatever, something that conforms to zoning, but not something you want in your neighborhood. Certain types of medical facilities and things like that that people would prefer not in the heart of their neighborhood.
And right now, and here's the other thing, too. You want to have the developer at least come back with a proposal. If he's not interested in doing it any way except the way he's doing it, then he should tell them all that, hey, I'm not interested and move on and let the Hallmark Health go out and look at the whole situation again and see if they're interested in other opportunities. And so that's about it. And I just want to thank everyone for coming down tonight. Thank you, Councillor Camuso. Councillor Knight.
Mr. President, thank you very much, and I'd like to thank Mr. Fitzpatrick for the time and effort that he put into his presentation. I find it important to point out, like he said, it's very easy to point out a problem or a mistake or an issue, but to provide a solution is really to bring the matter full circle. So I can certainly appreciate the efforts that he's put forth, and I'd like to thank him for his hard work. Under the current circumstances, where the development are not right there, I think that the neighborhood
is suffering through a significant amount of cut-through traffic. I found myself guilty just the other day cutting down Murray Hill Drive, and when my friend Lou Entopper yelled at me, I pulled over, and he said, I want you to sit here and watch. I want you to sit here and watch. So I stayed there for about a half an hour with Lou, and we watched, and we counted cars, and we counted 75 cars in a half an hour cut through Murray Hill Road. So with that being said, Mr. President, I think there's a significant problem there right now, absent development, and it's a problem that we can handle here in Medford.
I know the Traffic Commission has taken a position that they'd like to see citizen-driven petitions when it comes to closing streets off to resident access, and I think that that might be an important place to start. If they close off Murray Hill Road to resident access only between certain hours, I think that'll cut down significantly on the cut-through traffic, similar to what they've done on Rural Ave here in Medford by the Winthrop Street Rotary, Mr. President. Also, one thing that I have learned is that if you drive down one of those streets that says resident access only between the hours of 6 a.m. and 9 a.m.,
And you get caught. It is a surchargeable offense. It's the same thing as driving down a do not enter street. And it's a surchargeable offense that goes on your insurance. So I think that this is a very effective tool to combat cut through traffic, Mr. President, signage and policing. And I think that that might be something that we here as a city council can support at this level, regardless of what they do in Malden, regardless of the development to address the issues that are in place right now, the cut through traffic problems that they're seeing in that neighborhood, Mr. President.
So I'd like to request that this committee send a request to the Traffic Commission to examine the possibility of putting in resident access only. But I'd like to see that be done through a citizen-driven petition first. So maybe we can have a conversation about that, Mr. President. I don't want to say turn the street resident access only, and then have all the residents on the street come down here and say, what are you, nuts? We don't want that. But I think it's a tool that we can use to combat cut-through traffic in that area. Thank you, Councilor Knight. Councilor Carr of Yellow. Thank you, Mr. President. Well, I see on the sheet here, it says,
The proposed development adds 375 units, correct? On your sheet here, it says that the proposed developer is planning on 375 units. That's correct. And on the proposal that your group is, how many units? Roughly 70, 60 to 80. Yeah, 60 to 80. So 60 to 80, does that make it- So that's smaller. Does that make it financially feasible for the developer?
I don't know what that—I don't know if he's paying for the land, but— I don't know. But does that make it financially feasible for him to do that without driving the cost of the housing up? To be honest with you, I don't know. Yeah, sure. Hi. Could you just present yourself before the microphone?
Thank you. My name is Stephen Kelty. I'm from Malden. I helped form some of the activities that produced this. Um, tomorrow at the BB school at seven o'clock, there'll be a six 30. I mean, it's six 30 at the BB school to be able to, uh, about an hour presentation. And part of that is the financial. So in order to achieve this part of the concept of funding, it is through park grants, fundraising and other funding sources from the state because Malden is a gateway community. So there's other grants available. So some of that will offset some of the costing.
for doing this plan. Is the developer amiable to this plan? We don't know yet. If we have a developer, that's the point is finding out where the developer would do that. The idea is that by having the same number of units on the property in a building versus spread across the entire lot, because by right under residential only, it's between 60 and 80 units.
If you're putting that all into one structure, conceivably it should be cheaper to build one structure, and the market values are about what they are. So it's in the ballpark. The question is, do you have to sweeten the pot with a bonus set of units to make it financially feasible? So that's going to be the- Is there state money available to get some of this done?
For the park stuff, basically, a park grant, say from Medford, if they help purchase the 20% of the property that's in Medford, that park grant would be up to $400,000 match. Molden could do the same. A lot of times when the communities do them together, you get an intramunicipal grant, so you get higher points. If the communities have passed the Community Preservation Act,
We're thinking about maybe even trying to pass the Community Preservation Act in Malden. I believe people are looking at putting a petition around in Bedford for putting the Community Preservation Act on the ballot. These are funding sources for doing that. And then there's also, like I said, the gateway funds. There's other mediation funds that we could possibly get. Maybe we could get some help from the federal or the state government. Thank you. Councilor Camuso. One question. Mr. Kelty, why are you there?
I see that you cut back significantly, and it's a nice plan you brought forward, but do you have any developers in mind that if it's not necessarily this developer who would actually come forward? That would have to be found, yes. I mean, we haven't shopped that. Okay, because I mean, to arbitrarily, and I'm just playing devil's advocate here, because you want this to work for our neighborhood and your neighborhood. I'm concerned about the Medford side, to be quite frank with you, but from a standpoint of getting a developer in there,
I'm just being realistic. Developers, you're going to see little interest, probably, with the scope of the work cut back by
There's a lot of developers, there's a lot of these developers who do these really mega projects, and there are other developers that take on these smaller projects. So the question is, will the current developer be willing to build... Precisely. Or would there be some other developer who would be willing to take a project of this scope? And that would have to be part of the process moving forward.
I think the main element is that there are similar kinds of buildings like that being built in Everett and other places. So it is not beyond reason that we could find somebody that would be doing that and wanting to do that kind of project at that scale. And like I said, it sounds great in theory. It's certainly better for the neighborhood, but I think at the same time we just have to be realistic. We have to sharpen our pencils and see where the money is. Because if we're not realistic, it's a waste of everyone's time to sit at the BB school or any school for that matter and come up with a great plan that sounds good, but
If you don't make it to the point where the developers want to come in, then you're going to be sitting looking at a vacant building with the temporary still fence around it. That's ultimately not the goal, I don't think, for Malden or Medford, because quite honestly, many neighbors up in that area are sick and tired of the transient people trying to break in there. The police are there all the time breaking in. There's rodent problems.
It's coming to the point where it's bad. Oh yeah, I think no matter what plan, we need flexibility in saying that if a developer doesn't come forward but we want to do it, then we'd have to decide how to pay for the demolition of the building or have that happen. I think already now, the city of Malden is already in court with Hallmark because it's been a derelict building. It's a public safety hazard.
That I believe if this developer doesn't move forward that there may be a judgment against them to take the building down So not the developer. I'm having a hallmark. Yeah, I'm sorry So the if Hallmark takes it down then we're dealing with a different situation because but now you've got a different animal We will be getting calls if that's a vacant lot now, and I'm just based upon my experience here You'll be getting calls from the neighbors in Medford and Malton if it's a vacant lot
That there's kids drinking there every weekend. So it's, as I stated earlier, the best thing for both communities is to probably come up with a realistic plan. Because I know there are people in Malden that are dead against it. Leave it alone, and that's unrealistic. Yeah, that's why we put the housing. Because by having the mixed-use housing, you have a visible presence at the park, which will help.
avoid any attractive nuisance situation. So I think whatever help that the council here can provide in terms of finding developers, helping solve the problems and make this a reasonable solution is really, we're grateful to have that help. Because the Medford side, we will, Medford working with the developer, I think significantly the project was already cut back.
From the original one, as far as the housing and those things going on in the Medford side, it's been scaled back, as you know. I don't know why it's not happening in Malden, but... For this one or other projects? For this particular one. I think this one because they don't want to fight two battles, I think. Well, yeah, and they know the Zoning Board of Appeals probably wouldn't go along with it, but there's...
Yeah, so there's other developments that's happened in the area, so maybe the people on council know other developers because there's the things down at the landing, other things. Maybe those developers might be interested in this, and some of the architecture of those buildings are really very attractive and would be probably a great asset to have those developers and those architects doing the designs for this project. I'm just, like I said, I'm open-minded to everything.
I'm just very cognizant of the fact, we've dealt with schools in Medford, believe me, that sat for 30 years, vacant buildings right in the heart of our neighborhoods here. There's people in the audience that know the buildings I'm talking about, and it just, it's not a good thing. How long has Malden been closed now? Probably since 1999, 2000? 99, so it's been 15 years. Yeah, so it's quite a long time, but all right. And I know that just to knock that down and get rid of it and get rid of the material and stuff is about three or $4 million.
just to knock it down, just to get the trucks in here and abate it properly, and you're dealing with asbestos and everything else with it. That's part of the scope of the plan that we've been looking at, is saying, these are the real costs, these are the possibilities, that's part of the reason the building is there, to help sweeten the pot.
I think we're in the ballpark. The question is, how much do we have to supplement it with fundraising? The Friends of the Brightlock Farm recently bought the land for, was it almost $8 million from the city? The city originally bought that land under the idea that they would turn around and sell it. And they, over the time that they had, were able to raise the money to buy it. There's a lot of history with Malden Hospital. A lot of people put a lot of donations toward that. It's a historic site. It's overlooking historic, nationally historic Olmstead Park.
So I think there's a lot of opportunities for fundraising on the private side if we have the time So whatever we can do to buy time by locking up some sort of agreement I think would help open up the opportunity to find the money through donations as well as through a developer I'm gonna leave this just my last comment with that and Once again, I take an approach on all these things being realistic Fundraising sounds great. We've seen it many times in this community We're gonna raise a ton of dole for this project that project that guess what at the end. I
It's back before the city council from the mayor looking for a bond because it sounded good. They were going to raise half a million dollars on their own to do it. And eventually it just didn't take off the way it was going to be. That's why we're not relying on that. Exactly. So yeah, we have, we have all the options. Okay. And um, I just like to make one motion and that is to go back to council of Marx's motion, um, of several months ago, which I think is the biggest piece of this puzzle for our residents.
and that is we do not want the opening at the end of the road leading into the Malden development to create the chaos and the havoc that was here post-1999. So if we could just send that resolution again, if Councillor Mark sees fit, where he was the original author, would you be okay with that, Councillor? Send that right to Malden and say that that's something that we need in order to be working with the people on this project. So on the motion of Councillor Camuso, Councillor Marks.
Thank you, Mr. President. And Councilor Camus was correct. This council has taken two separate votes asking that one road be closed off to any cut-through traffic, that also the city of Method put some type of barrier or structure so if need be, public safety vehicles can get in and out of the area if they have to. The chief of police was up here several months back.
And he gave us a commitment publicly that that road will not be opened up. And it was nice to hear the chief take such a stance that that road will not be opened up at all. I think it's clear, Mr. President, when you look at the aerial view that we received, that this project was built to maximize the potential of housing on the site.
And it's quite stunning when you look at it and see the greenery and Felsmere Park, and all of a sudden, smack in the middle, it looks like a mini city that's going to develop. The question I had, and I don't know if Bob can answer it or not, is the construction timeline with the existing, has there been any type of?
As far as we know, there isn't any construction timeline or plan yet. I would say it's probably a good thing from our point of view. I think that there's a lot of issues that this developer is going to have to get through before getting to the point where he could start to have a timeline and some zoning issues that would have to be worked out.
all those sorts of things before a project, you know, he can really start to schedule a project. So I think we're still early enough in this process that we can have some say because, yeah, there's no project schedule as of yet. When we met with, I believe it was one of the developers or someone from the Community Development Board in Malden, I believe at the time they mentioned that
The way the project was going to be set up, that Lund Road, even though it was supposed to be cut through for the project, was the interior roads were going to be winding roads. And that they were going to make it difficult for people to go that way. They were trying to focus people more to Murray Hill and the back of the project. And none of us bought it. We said, that just doesn't sound right. Because it could open up that whole secondary cut through at Salmon Street.
You know, because again, that traffic, as we all know, backs up on Felsway East. And so people say, hey, I can bail out here, cut across this development, and then past Fitzy's house and out to the highway. I would assume people are trying to get on to the Felsway and up onto 93 and access whichever way. And the quickest way is probably the cut through. Right. So I think they were being disingenuous when they were saying, you know, we're going to put speed bumps, and we're going to put do not come this way.
You know, we're going to try to discourage people from coming in that area. But I think, clearly, the intent is to use that as a cutthroat. I would just ask, Mr. President, that our Office of Community Development — I know it's only staffed with one and a half people. We had our budget discussions tonight. And I would ask that they play a more active role in this project. I realize it's on the Malden side, but as good neighbors,
I'm sure the city of Malden wants to work with the city of Method in that. The OCD director pledged that to us tonight. Well, I know, but I'd like to see more of an active role. I'd like to see more community outreach. We use reverse 911 for everything under the sun now, and maybe it'd be nice to notify because we could hit particular neighborhoods with the reverse 911. Let neighbors know when there's meetings in Malden or vice versa. Let them know updates.
You know, why not use the technology that we currently have to at least keep people apprised of what's going on? But, you know, I think this project will vet itself out over the years, and I'm hoping that through the input of the neighborhood and your group and the community sticking together that we'll see a downscale project, one that suits both cities and makes sense. I mean, we all want to see development.
You know, but I think we have to do it in a manner that respects neighborhoods. You know, we have, right here in Meffitt Square, three undeveloped parcels of property on the east side of the square. Talk about an area that's undeveloped. And, you know, so I'm all in favor of development, but I think we have to do it in a way that maintains the integrity of the area and so forth. And clearly, this project, in my opinion, is oversized and is not well-suited for that particular area. Thank you, Mr. President.
So on the motion of Councilors Camuso, Mox, and Councilor Camuso. I'm very sorry to speak again on this issue, but these plans were put forward by you, Mr. Kelty. Did you draw these ones? There was a charrette with the architect, the landscape architect did these things. The reason is?
The new cut-through that's proposed on, the new proposal is diverting the traffic from Lund Road, now to Murray Hill Road, and then to Falz Ave. I think, uh, I know he, I know they talked, this says new cut-through, that's why I'm a little, I think that was just conceptual.
You see what I'm saying, the city council stance is we don't want any kind of... Jones here, Cedar Road North, that isn't a guess from the neighbors of how it's going to happen. That's not a proposed... Because if you go to Murray Hill Road right now... That's not a proposed cut through. That's how we know they're going to go through.
Oh, OK. That was just a guess. It's just where you were showing us these boards, and I thought that this was the title. Understood. So we know where they're going through now. We know where they went through before, and we're just going to estimate they're going to go through again. Which, that's where the traffic commission comes into play. I just thought it was part and parcel of all. Thanks for clarifying that. Yeah. Thanks, Joan. So on that motion, all those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries. While we're under suspension,
We're going to do condolences offered by Councilors Knight and Camuso. Be it resolved that the Medford City Council offers its deepest and sincere condolences to the family of firefighter Timothy Brennan on his recent passing. And also offered by Councilor Henta under
suspension be resolved that our Memphis City Council take a moment of silence and extend to the family of mentored firefighter Timothy Brennan our expression of sympathy on his untimely passing. Councilor Camuso. Thank you Mr. President and I want to thank Councilor Knight and Councilor Penta for for joining in and having this resolution for a wonderful person. We're all friendly
here with the Brennan family in our community. I had the distinct pleasure of chatting every Tuesday night with young Timothy after our council meetings and he'd be giving me the critique in it on how we all did it on the evening and everything else. The, um, Timmy, I remember way, way back when, when I was a little kid, Timmy was a little older working with Marilyn Perica's campaign. We were just little kids walking the streets. That's when, uh,
Councilor Penta was a councilor back in 87, 88. And I remember seeing all the councilors, and it was a great race. And I just remember Timmy walking the streets, and we were just young kids. Then fast forward to 1997, I was lucky enough to have worked with Timmy in his work to get on the Memphis City Council. Ultimately, Timmy landed his dream job, and that was with his dad.
uh, was Bob as well as his three brothers, Tom, Eddie, and Jimmy. And that was a firefighter in the city of Medford. Um, many people didn't realize that, uh, Timmy has been sick for a little, little while. And, um, ultimately the, um, he, uh, gave a valiant fight and unfortunately, uh, last Tuesday evening when we were wrapping up our city council meeting here, uh, Timmy passed away at the mass general hospital with his family by his side.
So just if we could send our condolences to Helen and the three boys, and if we could dedicate tonight's meeting in honor of Timothy Brennan, Medford firefighter from Engine 4, that we're going to sorely miss at the young age of 46. Thank you, Councillor. Councillor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much. And Councillor Camuso, I certainly echo your sentiments. I think we could all sit here all night long and talk about Timmy Brennan and tell Timmy Brennan stories about what a great guy he was.
what a great public servant he was and what a great firefighter he was. But I think Chief Goulding from the Western Police Department, who formerly was lieutenant detective here in the city of Medford, put it best. When talking about Timmy Brennan, he said, if someone has a problem with Timmy Brennan, there's probably a problem with that person. And honestly, I think that that's really the way that Timmy went through life. He was a friend to many. He was a great gentleman. He was a person that I'm privileged and honored to have been able to call a friend, Mr. President, and he'll be sadly missed.
Mr. President, it's, um, it is a sad day for the city of Medford. Um, I think Timmy was looked upon by his peers as not being a lesser in rank individual, but a person who basically set a tempo, his smile, his walk, his jog. Um, and he was, he was actively involved in this community and thought and process, um, comes from a good stock of family and God bless his mother.
Um, at the wake, she was just tremendous. And I think she realized that God took him and now he's looking down and giving peace to his family. And unfortunately, um, it's the saddest part of life. And sometimes you just don't have the right word. You just don't know what to say, other than the fact that he was a good individual. He was a friend of mine and he's going to be missed. Councilor Marks.
Thank you, Mr. President. Just to echo the sentiments of my colleagues, I think we all got to know Timmy very well over the years. I remember when he first ran for public office, he ran for city council, and his slogan was, people, not politics. And that's how he lived his life. He was always about taking the time to talk to you. He'd sit down, as Councilor Camuso said, and we'd talk politics, or he'd talk about what's going on in the fire department. He was also active in the Elks Club.
He was just a down-to-earth, real gentleman. And, you know, when I saw his brother the other day, he said, you know, they got the better of the brothers. And, you know, words spoken, really, Timmy was just a unique person, someone that you meet and you become friends with them automatically. You know, you didn't need to hang around with them every day. You didn't need to go out to dinner with them. He just became your friend.
And he was always warm and welcoming. And I wish Tom, Ed, and Jim and Helen, in these tough days, a lot of solace. And I hope they get through it all right. And he will be sorely missed in the fire department. I know all his brothers and sisters in the fire department sorely miss him. And, you know, I think we all miss him, Mr. President.
On the motion, please rise for a moment of silence. While we're on to suspension, 15-508, offered by Councilors Mox and Bento, be it resolved that the Tufts University girls softball team be congratulated for winning
their national championship. Counselor Penta. Mr. President, I think the resolution speaks volumes for Tufts University Athletic Department. They have quite an array of individuals up there who are winning championships. But this girl's softball team, some people may want to call it women's, some people want to call it girls. Call it what you may. Bottom line is they've won for three consecutive years in a row.
the NCAA Division III Championship. It's a great feat. We have one of the players with us in the audience tonight. The unfortunate part of getting them up here, a lot of these students are graduating or already have graduated and gone, left home. But maybe the young lady that's sitting in the audience can come up, say a few words, and accept the accolades of
doing your college proud, but you did our city of Medford proud, too, because Tufts University is part of our city of Medford. I think Councilor Max wants to just make a few remarks. Just if I could. And I thank my colleague, Councilor Penta, for offering this with me. Tufts went 51-0 this year. What an accomplishment. I don't know, Mr. President. I can't even hit a beach ball, let alone a softball.
So, you know, it's a true accomplishment. The championship game was held on May 26th in Salem, Virginia. And as Councilor Penta mentioned, they've won three consecutive national Division III titles, and they were the first Division III softball team to win three titles ever. Consecutive titles. So that alone is an accomplishment, Mr. President. And also, not many people know, but for years,
Tufts could not host an NCAA game because their fields weren't up to the NCAA codes. And this was the first time that they were able to host an NCAA game, which I think was a big accomplishment, especially from a team that has won the national title now to be able to play at home. And we also have one of Meffitt's own, Lauren Epstein, who is the associate head coach
and played back in 2007. We won't date you, but she played back in 2007, but has done Yeoman's work in putting together a program that now is seen nationally, which is a huge accomplishment. And I wish the girls well. You could take back word from this Memphis City Council that we are on board with the Jumbos and that we are in full support of the girls softball team.
And I appreciate, Mr. President, the opportunity to speak. Thank you, Council Mox and Council Penta. Madam Coach. Thank you so much. Thank you so much for taking the time to honor us. It was obviously a very good run this year. It was, I guess you could say, the best of our three runs. Finishing the season undefeated was not something we talked about, but something everyone else wanted to talk about during the course of the year.
So it was obviously very exciting to finish the season undefeated. First team to win a national championship in Division Three with an undefeated season in the three consecutive ones. But I think what meant the most was playing at home this year in the playoffs. We've been on the road and we called ourselves road warriors, but to be able to play at home was awesome and only something that was possible because of the new field. So thank you so much. Thank you. Wish you good luck. Mr. President, just if I could, and maybe Lauren
On the way back, they ran into some difficulties getting back to Tufts. And Lauren was just explaining to me, it was like that movie, Planes, Trains, and Automobiles. They went through a lot of different avenues to get back home. And we just want to welcome them all back safe and thank them for representing not only Tufts, but the city of Meffitt. Thank you. Thank you.
Councilor Penta, seconded by Councilor Morocco. Mr. President, could we have a citation forwarded to the Tufts University Athletic Department, giving recognition to the girls receiving this award, and have that sent on a roll call vote, Mr. President. On that motion, Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Camuso. Councilor Caviello.
Yes. Yes. Yes. And the vote of six in the affirmative, one absent. Motion of Councillor Lungo-Curran to revert back to the regular order of business. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries. 15-498 offered by President De La Russo and Councillor Knight. Be it resolved that the city solicitor advise and render an opinion
to the council as to the process and parameters for the council to establish a charter review committee. It says what it wants. Councilor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much for the opportunity to speak on this matter.
Last week, this matter was filed under suspension at the request of Councilor Penta. We tabled it for this week to have the residents have an opportunity to come up and speak. With that being said, Mr. President, I think that we might want to allow the residents to come up and speak on whether or not they're in support of a Charter Review Commission. I know there's been an undercurrent of residents in the community who have spoken on this issue a number of times. There's been several meetings that have taken place by this community group to take a look at the charter. So with that being said, there is a citizen-driven effort that's out there.
So maybe some of the citizens that are out in the audience who have participated in such can tell us about their experience, about the progress and process that they've made, and then we can go from there. Thank you. Councillor Pentland, do you want to speak? No. Good evening. Please state your name and address for the record. Thank you, Mr. President. I'm Robert Cappucci of 71 Evans Street. It was about four years ago, I want to say,
Another resident of Medford and I tried to establish a charter review committee, Dr. Stirella, that you are all very aware of. From my perspective, it's a huge undertaking. I think we had to get something like 10,000 signatures just to get it on the ballot, and then it has to be voted on by the city at large.
either the mayor or this body could vote to have one formed. My support of a charter review commission or committee or whatever you want to call it stems from just a couple of simple things. We've been operating under the plan A strong mayor charter now for almost 30 years. And I just think it's prudent, practical, logical just to establish a review of the charter.
to see if that's the way we want to continue functioning our city government in the manner we've been operating it for decades now, almost three decades. Many businesses out there from 1988 we're talking here, maybe earlier, just don't operate under the same business model. And I just think it makes sense for us to review it, especially with certain things that are going on. I'll stick to the charter.
But I mean, there are reasons why we want to review the charter. We're understaffed in the police force. The building's falling apart. There's water and sewer pipes. There's pay scales. There's all sorts of reasons why we want to look at the charter review. And another reason to look at it is maybe we want to change it to go to ward representation as opposed to at large. Because I really think that's a great thing.
I know that some of you councillors are against that because it kind of like pits the city against each other, but I think that spirit of competition is good. I think when you have, like what we were talking about earlier tonight, you got the Heights, they could have like their representative on the city council, and that person could be doing all they could to become specialized and expert
and experts on knowing what's going to go up there at the Malden Hospital. And, you know, there's all sorts of horse trading. We all know who pay attention and are active in politics, the way things get advanced. And, you know, when you have different representations from different wards, it just seems in that spirit of competition, we hold each other to higher standards and more things get done.
And finally, on the topic of ward representation, that I really think this city needs, it affords the opportunity for more voices to rise, for a diversity in background, for people to get elected in their ward, to run a smaller, more economical campaign, so that we get more different people
up here on this body, with all due respect, are that the ward can, you know, keep electing the same representative for years. It's not that I am kind of for term limits, but I'm not against having, you know, the same representatives for sometimes decades at a time, some of whom I like very much and I would personally keep voting for. But again, it all comes back to opportunity.
and providing as much opportunity for more citizens who may want to run that might not be able to afford it. I mean, there were tens of thousands of dollars spent in the city election in 2013 by one candidate on the city council. And I mean, I won't mention who. People can look up the public record and find out for themselves. But that's a lot of money to spend.
for a job that pays much less than what was spent. Under ward representation, somebody could possibly win a city council seat for maybe $1,000, $2,000. It's just better to review our city charter after so many years, to look at the way city government runs, to look at some of the problems we're having in this city, and maybe open doors for new people to rise up and have a voice, because we're privileged
to live in a country where we have the freedoms that we have and the opportunities that we have, and to expand these freedoms and these opportunities only makes sense. I hope that this body, after hearing from more citizens, will deeply consider and move forward on establishing a charter commission committee and review. Thank you very much for your time. Thank you, Mr. Capucci.
Good evening. Please state your name and address for the record. My name is Michael Ruggiero. I live on 18 Pembroke Street. It's a sad fact of local politics. Our turnout, voter turnout, only one in every four registered voters in Medford actually vote for our local elections. Why do you think it's so low? There's obviously a lot of theories. But walking through the city, people are very sort of, they've given up.
on city politics, and it's heartbreaking in a way. By us reviewing the charter, we can enliven the debate, bring more people into the process, add more sunlight into the process, how the budget is made, how are zoning decisions made. These are vital issues to our community. To begin to work them, creating a charter review committee is essential.
But if you look through Chapter 43B, Section 10, it's in the Mass General Law, there are actually two flavors of charter review commissions. And I think it's important that the council know of the two flavors. I think that is the question that we're looking to ask the city solicitor, correct? Thank you.
So there are two flavors. One, if this board decides to create a commission under two-thirds vote, that commission will not have the ability to answer certain questions and will not be able to even advise about term limits or other issues like changing the mayor or significant changes to the charter. An elected board, however, will have the capacity to make significant changes to the charter or actually recommend them.
In this capacity, I would recommend that we try to move forward to creating an elected commission. So there will be a vote on the ballot. Would you like to review the charter, yes or no? And then people will vote for a number of elected people that will actually be on this position. That is the direction that we should go and I hope we have an opportunity to come to that conclusion. Thank you. Thank you very much.
Good evening. Please state your name and address for the record. Mario Martin at 17 Dependent Road in Medford. I wanted to kind of echo what Mr. Capucci and Ruggiero was saying regarding our charter. The charter is an old document that dictates how decisions are made within the city. There has been no charter review since 1986 when it was changed from a strong city council to a more centralized and depressed and stagnant administration.
Personally, I don't know why a mayor would even put himself in that position, but anyways. Without the review of a charter, the new mayor can veto ordinances and resolutions passed by the city council. It also allows the mayor to chair the city's school committee and receive a stipend. The only time this charter has ever been reviewed is to increase the mayor's salary, which sadly I think is, well, it's pretty sad.
It sounds incredibly narcissistic if you really think about it. And the last time I checked, I think we ended this back in our Revolutionary War era. Residents are really frustrated with this current, with this, you know, the way this is working. And, you know, granted, I mean, the City Council is the backbone of our community. It's the front end to allow community feedback and, you know, give the City Council an opportunity
to direct things to the mayor to better and improve the city. And that's what we need to be looking at. And we need to give these powers back to the city council so we can give it back to the community. So I'm very strongly in favor of it, and I hope that you guys would consider it. Thank you. Thank you very much, Mr. Martin. Good evening. Please state your name and address for the record.
Good evening, Anthony D'Antonio, 12 Yale Street. Um, we had a little bit of a discussion last week on this, but it's very important that we consider changing, reviewing the, the charter because, um, for instance, having in the last couple of weeks going, going over the ledgers of the city of Medford, looking at the budgets present past, um,
this oversight is missing in this city. And we, you know, I hate to say this, but the spending in the city is almost like a drunken sailor. And I hate to use that clause, but I mean, I am amazed at what is being spent in the city. And I hear people say, well, we can't do this. We can't do that because there's no money left. There's plenty of money there. It's just how we present our budget. But the fact is that the council should have a strong say
in what we do when it comes to the budget. I'm not saying yes or no on that. I'm saying why did you present this budget? No, go back and this is what you have to do. I mean, has anybody got the actual title of the type of budgeting we process in this city? You know, is it zero-based budgeting? Is it just, you know, adding on from last year's budget? Because one of the things I noticed is an awful lot of transfers and money, and that affects the budget.
And there shouldn't be that kind of excess money, surplus money in the budget to do that. But the thing is that you have to have a balance of power. You can't have one individual running a city of 56,000 people. And I actually think there's a lot more than 56,000 people in here. Because we just had an article come out on the 26,000 housing units, housing stock, with this thing saying that we're below the affordable housing percentage.
units of housing, we have 56,000 residents in the city. How do we only have 56,000 residents? I mean, if you take two times the 26,000, there's 52,000 people right there. So it's very important. And last week I talked to you through the chair, through Councilor Knight, you had asked me some information about the previous meetings. I do recall, and I believe,
to the chair also, the city clerk may be able to confirm this. I did post and time date the meetings. Uh, we did have other counselors and other prospective counselors come to the meetings. The minutes were, it was pretty much information that we gathered from the state and we passed on to each other and we read and looked at it. And, uh, then as I said, we got dumped on the, uh, on the issue before the council to pursue it any further. But, uh, as far as your request for the minutes,
I mean, the minutes were basically just chapters, verses from the State, you know, the Department of Revenue, the Secretary of State, and some from the city itself. But we had interest in the charter review, and I think it's very important. And a point that was brought up was that with ward counselors, I think the counselors can do a better job in their wards.
It's difficult to be a councilor at large because you've got all these people that need and have questions. I mean, it's almost impossible to do this. I mean, a councilor in itself is almost a 24 hour day, seven days a week job. And I think that the people deserve much better than we're getting now. And I'm not saying from the council, I'm saying from the city administration. And I think, and I don't want people to think that because we're gonna have the city solicitor render an opinion on the charter,
that this is an ongoing process and the charter is now under review, because a lot of people asked me that question last week, and I said, no, it's just for the city solicitor to render an opinion. So please remember that, people that are listening out there, that it's only an opinion, and that it may mysteriously disappear after the election. So please be aware of that, and please, if you're serious about a charter review, let's get it on board. Thank you very much.
Good evening. Please state your name and address for the record. My name is Joe Villione, 59 Garfield Ave, Medford, Massachusetts. I want to thank the councilors who voted on behalf of charter change way back when you showed courage, you showed integrity, you worked for the people. The councilors that voted against it were the same ones that voted for their own pay raise and not to show my video of the mayor with the pay to park plan. I want voters to remember that 153 days from today,
Those of us who showed up at the Charter Review hearing, we did hard work. We wrote up articles. We fought for this. And those councilors who are alleging they're doing the people's work, they need to vote for the people that are doing the hard work. So the councilors that did vote for that, thank you very much. Good evening. Please state your name and address for the record, Jean.
Thank you. Jean Martin, 10 Coming Street. Thank you for listening. I was a member of the charter review, and it is a massive undertaking if you do it through the channel that doesn't include you folks just voting for it to happen. You have to get so many votes. You have to have, there's time limits for everything. It's an 18-month process. It's going to take a lot for the people
to get active and to get engaged. But you know what? The people are ready for it. I mean, the city has changed. The character of the city is changing. From 1988 or 1986 to 2015, 2016, this city has changed a lot.
And I think that if it's done right, if you folks are behind it, and you invite everybody to come and to participate in the process, it's their way. And you can do the review, and it might stay the exact same way. You can let it happen that way. Or you can tweak it, or you can change it drastically. It's all up to you. The options are varied. It's like a menu.
of plan A, plan B, plan C, plan D, plan E, plan F. I broke it all down. I have it at my house on a computer. And they vary differently. And the one thing that I would say is that this city needs more checks and balances. We have a strong mayor, but that consolidates too much power in the hands of one person. So I would like to see it disseminated a little bit. It doesn't have to be disseminated like it was
1988, because I remember those days, and that was horrific for this city. The E plan was horrific. But there is a middle ground, and I think that we need to find that middle ground. And it's up to the people to decide what the menu of how they want to run their city is. So it's the people's choice. And I think that if you guys invite everybody, and it's done right, we can come together,
It also is a place where you can vent your frustrations as a citizen. And believe me, when things get tight, parking, money, developments, there's going to be a frustration in the people. But the people will have more of a voice. And if they feel more heard, their frustration levels will decrease. So I think it benefits everyone. And I thank you very much for listening. Good evening. Please state your name and address for the record.
Michael DiBenedettino, 8 Alexander Avenue, Medford. This is a great opportunity right now. With your yes vote, what's gonna happen is you're gonna allow the city of Medford to prosper. To prosper and to bring it from the age of the dinosaurs to the new era, an era of collaboration. This is not about one person, this is about a city.
First of all, you guys are doing a great job. You are here to support the people. And you love Medford. This is about the city that you love. It's about the city that you care for. Let's put aside our differences. Let's move forward. Let's collaborate on this one issue at least. At least one issue. And going forward, there'll be more issues that can be resolved.
Our mayor does a good job. He has a lot of responsibility. But we need someone that is open to new ideas, that listen to other opinions. And then you finally make a determination. Here's your chance to allow Medford to move forward. Please vote yes for it. Thank you.
Good evening. Please state your name and address for the record. Thank you. Yes. Ken Kraus, 50 mystic street. Um, I wanted to speak in favor of the resolution to, uh, seek some clarity about the process for, uh, the council to establish a charter review. If it decides to go that course. Um, I was not involved with the, um, citizen effort, uh, related to the charter review, nor did I intend, uh,
any meetings, and frankly, I don't know a lot about what's in the charter, which is a good reason for it to be reviewed by the whole community. I just think it's an overdue thing related to what governs our community and pretty much a standard procedure that, you know, should have been built into the charter when it was established way back when. I don't see any reason not to review it.
I do think it's important though that the process not be politicized. I don't think anybody should feel threatened by the process. I think the purpose is to review the charter and its applicability, usefulness, and relevance to 21st century Medford. And it's not a critique of the people who have been in the positions provided by, for the charter.
Um, and I think we need to look back at, um, you know, the discussion when this charter was, uh, approved and what were the issues back then and what were we trying to accomplish? Um, and did it succeed? Uh, very likely. A lot of the issues with Hemming and Hawn about today were the same ones that were being discussed back then. So those issues may kind of, um, be ongoing despite whatever, um,
plan of government we're under. But I think it would be useful to see what the dialogue was back then and evaluate where we are today and this charter, you know, from that perspective. You know, and come away with a document that we feel will best serve the community going forward. Thank you.
Councilor Camuso. Thank you, Mr. President. And this has been presented to us over the many years. And my stance has always been and still shall be that this was citizen driven, as Jean Martin said, in 1986 and 87, a very active group of community members went out and they got the signatures and they put it on the ballot. And if people are committed to changing the charter in this community,
then that is the process that I feel is the way it should be done, same way that it has been done in the past. So for that reason, I do not support this, but I certainly think that the charter review is a good thing, but I just don't like the mechanism of doing it opposite the way that it was done in the past. It's something that has such a great drive in this community
to move the city forward, that I just think it should be citizen-driven. Quite honestly, if we were to just do it with a flick of a pen on a Tuesday evening, it's an insult to everyone that worked so hard, including Councillor Penta and Mary-Anne Frazzoli and many, many other people back in 1986. So, that's my reasons and that's about it. Thank you, Councillor Penta. Councillor Camuso.
Councillor Pinto. First of all, our charter as it presently sits is, you're right, it's approximately 30 years old. And probably the biggest shortcoming in that charter is the fact that there was no review process to take place. As in everything else in government, a review is necessary. We as candidates are reviewed every two years when we're being voted on for office. I look at our city's charter
is to be the future. It's the future of this city as we're going forward. As Mr. DiBenedetto indicated, you know, it's the city has changed. It's changed dramatically. Dating back to the plan E and the plan A form of government, the mayor did serve both as the chairperson then as he serves now on the school committee. But that may be something that may want to be reviewed at and looked at right now by folks within this community.
As a candidate for mayor, one of the first things I will propose is to have the city auditor come under the control of the city council. That will present the checks and balances as to how the city administration spends its money and how it can't spend its money. We don't have that. Unfortunately, every single department comes under the control of the mayor as it presently stands in this particular charter. What councillors, whether you're for it or against it, some people like at large,
Some people like ward counselors. Again, it's an option. I think after 30 years, people deserve to have that ability to look at it. Term limits. Do we need term limits? Is it fair to say, especially for the office of mayor, the term limits should only be two years. Maybe it should be a four, no more than two four-year terms. And maybe we should have staggered or proposed staggered city council terms, one, two, and three years, both city council and school committee. That gives everybody an opportunity each and every year
whether they want to serve or whether they don't want to serve, but it keeps the people involved in the community as to what's going on. Also, the fact that the mayor, under this form of government, does have an extended amount of power. But remember what the plan A charter says. The plan A charter says that the mayor is not required to meet with the council. It doesn't say he can't. He's not required to. And that would make a huge difference as to what I would be proposing. I would meet with this council.
when and if asked, and that should be something that should be incorporated in the new proposal for the charter. Now, the gentleman that talked about the affordable housing in the city of Medford, if anybody understands how you get to the affordable housing content, if a developer were to come into this community and propose 100 units, and only 25% of those units are for affordable housing, the city gets credit for all 100. That's the way this archaic 1939 law has been written. That needs to be changed in the legislature.
This city, I will say, has gone out of its way through its limited resources in the Office of Community Development to bring in as much affordable housing as they can. And even by adding on those other numbers at the very end, we still haven't been able to reach that 10% mark on new development for affordable housing. The other parts I think that need to be looked upon is that not only the diversity that this community has, but where is the opportunity for the citizens of this community to know
that their government not only can be looked upon, it can be reviewed, but they don't have to wait for a four or a five-year period. I believe if I understand the law correctly and reviewing on the charters, you can have a five-year charter review, and if it incorporates a particular aspect of it, you don't have to go through that next five-year process to make that change. And I think in part that's what you're asking for with this resolution with the city solicitor to talk about. And I think these are the things that need to be incorporated in the speaking of it.
But the checks and balances just does not exist in this city. Now, campaigning for this office, am I talking against myself by having the auditor not be on my side and on the council side? No. That's just what good government's all about, having a good audit of your system on how your government works. That's the key to let you know that your government, your tax dollars are being spent wisely and correctly. This is a hard job sometimes. We just got our budget here tonight. And unfortunately, in this budget,
that we got, it's a combination of the prior budget director and the at present budget director. And in some occasions, one not talking to the other, as it relates to a particular thing that this council has asked for in each and every budget, the wishlist of each and every department head. Give us the wishlist, why you need it, how much it's going to cost, and how do you think you'd be able to get to that to pay for it? And we don't get that. We just get rank and file, whatever it might be. During the past two years, we've seen increases in this city take place.
Last year alone and last year's budget, the school department increased by $2 million. Absolutely no conversation with the council about it. There was no concern as it related to rank and file teachers, books and students, but it was a lot went to administration. But just think about the school system we have here. It went for almost 50 plus years with having no rehabilitation. And during that course of the 50 years, the school system just deteriorated.
So what did they do 12, 13 years ago? They decided to build new buildings. And yes, at that time, I was against the new buildings, because I felt we could rehab our old buildings one at a time. But the city decided to go the other way, so be it. Now, as we Councilor Calderiello disclosed in his first term, these 12-year-old buildings are over in excess of $1 million in repairs that are needed. They've never taken the option
that the law has told them that 5% of the annual budget for each school needs to be put there for reconditioning, upgrading or whatever it might be. We're hearing comments tonight in the meeting and we will be hearing it continuously in this budget of all the needs that need to take place. This city needs to take a step back and look at where it's at, where it wants to go and understand that we have a brand new future that's in front of us. The opportunity is so unique for this city to go forward.
Forget the mayor's office, which is a very important issue, but we have two openings here in the city council and you have two openings on the school department, the school committee, excuse me. And with that, this next election is going to bring a complete change in the philosophy of where this city of Method by its government is going. I would love to be a part of it. I'd love to have your vote, but I do support this charter vote. And I think this is very important. As I said, as I said, right in the beginning,
Probably the biggest drawback, the biggest drawback was not including a review process. But let me remind you of one thing left. When that charter review committee came out back then, and even though the people voted for plan A, the vote also was to include plan E or plan A. My vote went both ways to allow the taxpayers the opportunity to have their choice. They made their choice. They voted for plan A.
Having people, giving them transparency, giving them an opportunity, that's what this city needs right now. And with that thought, with that philosophy, we can go forward in this next election in November, and we can attain that, and we'll work for it, and we will correct it. Thank you. Councillor Marks. Thank you, Mr. President.
I think we have to keep in mind we're looking for charter review, not charter change. No one that I've talked to mentioned anything about charter change. We're talking about reviewing the charter and, and speakers have already spoken to the fact that most charters have a provision built right in that calls for a review, whether it's annual, whether it's every five years or so forth. But, um, uh, I want to thank the city clerk's office. I asked them to pull,
resolutions that were offered regarding the city charter over the last several years. And I think it's important to note, Mr. President, December 7th, 2010, offered by Councilor Marks, be it resolved that the city charter be discussed. The council voted to amend the paper to refer to the committee of the whole for the purpose of establishing a charter review committee. It was also amended that the paper would be referred to the city solicitor
to report back on what is the legal path for the city council in establishing charter review committee and who can make recommendations in the process to make any changes to the charter. That was back in 2010. Needless to say, there wasn't support at the time in 2010 to move forward with a charter review of this council. So, excuse me? There wasn't majority support, correct. Let me stand correct. There wasn't majority support. December 14, 2010.
offered by John Stirella, that the City of Meffitt, that he present a history of the Meffitt Charter. So that was in 2010 December. Petition by John Stirella, April 12th, 2011. Council speak about a charter change and our children. January 14th, 2014, offered by Councilor Moxby, resolved the city solicitor meet
with the city council on the process of reviewing the city charter and amending current charter. May 2013, offered by Dr. Starella, that he address the council on the city charter. Petition by Anthony D'Antonio to discuss charter review, August 12, 2014. So the reason why I point this out, Mr. President, there's been a number of attempts over the last several years by members of this council
to at least call for a review of the city charter, knowing that this is the tool that governs our community. And if you look at the definition of the charter, part of it says, it defines the structure of the city and town government for a particular community in which may create local offices and distribute duties and responsibilities among local officials.
That's a key right there. Distribute duties and responsibilities among local officials. If you look at the current city charter, the mayor, whoever it is, he sets the city budget. He negotiates contracts, waste management, the contract we have for parking, anything in the city regarding contracts he negotiates. He's the hiring authority. He is also the chairman of the school committee. And he is the only one that can initiate spending in the community.
talk about centralizing power with one person. That's everything that flies in the face of what the definition of a charter is, is to distribute responsibilities and powers and duties among local officials, not one official, local officials. So clearly there's a need under our city charter that was established some 28 years ago to
review the charter, see where lies some of the concerns, and also not just to review the charter, but create a citizen review board. And that's what I read off last week. I won't read it again, but this calls for actually, it may be worth reading just because if I could, Mr. President, I think it may be worth reading because
You know, we're not allowing some body or some entity to go ahead and just change the charter. We're asking a group to get together, look at the current city charter, see what deletions, additions, anything that could change the charter to improve how government operates. And it's only to benefit the residents and the stability of this community. But under periodic review of the charter by a charter review committee,
Once a community has a charter, there's often a provision for the periodic appointment of a charter review committee. Now, that was the first problem that Councilor Penta mentioned. Nowhere in our charter calls for this periodic review. It says the committee undertakes an examination to determine the charter's ongoing utility and accuracy. Such committees do not have the powers, duties, and responsibilities of an elected charter commission. Such committees are formed to review the charter and to make recommendations to its appointing body.
example, board of select and city council regarding the need for additions, deletions, clarifications, or other amendments that would improve the charter. The term of such an advisory committee is usually one year. Recommendations of the committee may take the form of a proposal special act or proposed charter amendment, but the local legislative body must act upon the recommendations before they take effect. So there's a check and balance. The committee may also find, for example,
that the charter's intent is clear, but related bylaws or ordinances may need clarification. The role of such committees can be important in assuring that the charter is working as intended, but the Charter Review Committee has no assigned role in achieving any change beyond its recommendation to the appointing body. So it's not some committee that we're going to appoint that's going to take their pen and start making changes to the city charter. That's not going to happen. There's a process.
laid out that needs to be followed. Now, that's only one aspect. There are other aspects on amending the charter. There's a home rule charter commission, and there's also a petition of the state legislature for a home rule petition. And I think we're going to find this out, as Councilor Knight mentioned, with the city solicitor. And I am ecstatic to hear that members of this council that were in opposition over the last couple of years are now seeing the light on this and seeing the importance
of a charter review, not charter change, a charter review, a simple charter review. And I'm pleased to hear that that is hopefully moving forward. And I agree with Mr. Krause. This is not a political process. This is not a way of trying to get the charter that benefits anyone in particular. You know, I've always supported representation, even as a member of the council. I always felt it was unfair, Mr. President, that elected officials
on the ballot, get their names put in order, and then the incumbents go after the elected official. That gives elected officials an unfair advantage, in my opinion. And it's a known fact that there's a certain percentage gain from where you are placed on the ballot. We've also talked about staggering terms, which other communities do. We've talked about term limits. We've talked about possibly having the chairman of the school committee be elected, or maybe one of, as with the council,
One of the members of the school committee serves as the chairman of the school committee. And that keeps the mayor in his role as the chief executive officer. And it keeps him free from the political struggles back and forth of the municipal side and the school side. So I welcome this. I've welcomed this for years. I'm glad to see the support from members or somewhat support. If you're not willing to speak on your own resolution,
That doesn't say too much, but hey, this is an open process and, you know, we'll follow the process through. But we're going to make strides in moving forward. And no matter who the mayor, it doesn't matter who the mayor is, this is the right thing to do. It doesn't matter who's sitting in that office. It could be a dear friend or it could be an enemy. The right thing to do in this community is to make sure whatever we're governed by is working for the residents and the taxpayers of this community.
And not looking at a provision, like Mr. Cappucci said, for 28 years. Who would have a business plan for 28 years is no longer in business? That business plan has to be looked at, if not yearly, weekly, monthly, daily, to make sure you're up with the times, to make sure you're providing effective communication, to make sure that you're outsourcing and networking and doing the communication that's necessary to run a business. The city is no different. And that's what we should be looking at, Mr. President.
So I look forward to these discussions over the next several months. I hope under your leadership, Mr. President, that it doesn't die off like it did back in 2010, when there was a lack of support by members of this council. And I hope we can move forward on the review in the interest of every resident and taxpayer of this community, Mr. President. Thank you. Councilor Mox, Councilor Longo, Kern. Thank you, President De La Ruzo. I'll be brief.
I want to thank my colleagues for speaking, but I more importantly thank the public for coming out and speaking on the issue. I think enough has been said, but I just want to say that in 2010, I was in support of a charter review. I am in support of it. Again, 2015, almost five years later, it's something that I think is important. I think any time you're reviewing something, it's always a good idea. Like Councilman Mark said, it's as if a business never reviewed
their plan for the last 5, 10, 28 years. Review is a good thing. Change is a good thing. And again, this is just a review. Maybe nothing needs to be changed, but everything does need to be reviewed. Ward representation, term limits. I think I said the same speech in 2010. It is time, and I'm glad that finally we will have the majority vote tonight.
You name and address for the record, please. Thank you, Mr. President. Robert Capucci, 71 Evans street. Uh, just really brief. I have a question, excuse me, based on a counselor, Marx Marxist comments. Uh, first of all, I want to thank everybody who came up and spoke and I, and I thank all the counselors for their excellent commentary and concern. I mean, it's through the city. There's a huge concern for this. There really is. But my questions are,
The Honorable Michael Marx brought up that in the past that there were already resolutions to have the city solicitor speak on the process of this. My question is, A, did he come? And B, when he did come, were there minutes kept of any comments that he might have made so that you guys can maybe meet in a subcommittee or something and discuss them? But thank you for your time. Those are my questions, and thanks so much.
The gentleman asked the question. I, if my memory serves me correct, we never had a committee, the whole meeting on it. We requested one, but there was never a committee, the whole meeting. The second part was to have the city solicitor report back to the council, um, on, uh, what avenues, uh, we can approach to do a charter review. I don't ever remember getting a paper, but, uh, it's possible that, uh, the city solicitor did send us something and, uh, maybe we can put in a request tonight cause he keeps all his opinions.
Believe me, he has them all in order and index. Mr. President, if we can ask if the city solicitor did report back in 2010 regarding the council resolution 10-707, requesting that the city solicitor report back to the council on the legal path for the city council in establishing a charter review committee. And if we didn't get any opinion, then maybe this request
resolution will then spur that again, Mr. President. Thank you. I know you have the records of the votes. From my memory, we never had the four votes to even send the question. Is that correct?
Thank you. I have a motion approved by Councilor Nye, as amended by Councilor Matz, all those in favour? Aye. All those opposed? The clerk will call the roll. Councilor Camuso? Aye. Councilor Caviello? Yes. Councilor Nye?
Councilor Martins? Yes. Councilor Pater? Yes. President Del Rosso? Yes. A vote of six in the affirmative, one negative. The motion passes. Motion to suspend by Councilor Knight. To take papers 15504, 05 and 06, taxi operator licenses out of order.
It was 1-5-5-0-4. Yeah, taxi license petitions, please. Petitions, presentations, and similar matters. Petition for taxi operator license by Jean Elsan Dumas, 195 Webster Street, Malden, Mass. Driving for Citywide Taxi, Canal Street, Method, Mass. Is the petitioner present? Okay.
Good evening. State your name and address for the record. My name is Gene Domas. I live at 195 Webster Street in Malden. Thank you, Mr. Domas. You're welcome. Councilor Carviello. Thank you, Madam President. Madam President, I have reviewed the documents and I find them in order. Sir, you understand that this only allows you to pick up people in the city of Medford, correct? Yes. And do you know where your business is located?
Yes, and Foley, Canal Street, and Midford. Thank you. You're welcome. Motion for approval by Councillor Caviello, seconded by Councillor Knight. All those in favour? All those opposed? We'll record Councillor Penter in opposition, as well as Councillor Marks. Five in the affirmative. Paper passes. Good luck. Drive safely. Thank you. Thank you. Paper 15505, petition for taxi operator license
by Sandro Mathieu, 1876 Beacon Street, number five in Brookline, Massachusetts. Driving for Star Taxi, 407R Mystic Ave, Medford, Mass. On file, Corey from the Police Department. Counselor Carviello. Thank you, Madam President. Again, I have reviewed the papers that I find in order, and you understand that this is a license for the city of Medford, correct? Sure. And do you know where you'll be picking up your cab? Yeah.
Where? At Star Taxi. Where? Do you know where he's located? 75 Madison and Malden. I don't think, you must have the wrong company. No, it's Star Taxi. I'm in like 75 Madison and Malden, that's where he lives. Do you know where the business is located? I don't know the actual location, but I know the owner.
Okay, well, when you can figure out the address, then you can come back and get your license. Sure. You should know at least where you work. It's like he's the owner, it's like I'm going to be leasing. Yeah, but you should know where the office is located. You have to go to an office at some point. I don't think he has an office. He has an office. But when you figure out where the office is, you can come back and get it. Maybe a motion to table? I'm going to motion to table.
Can you call them? Yes, sure. I'm going to call them now. OK. Motion to table by Councilor Carviello. Undebatable. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion is tabled. Paper 15506, petition for taxi operator license by Joseph Pierre, 10 Fisher Terrace, Everett, Mass. Driving for Citywide Taxi, Canal Street, Medford, Mass. On file, Corey from the Police Department. Thank you, Madam President. Madam President, I reviewed the papers and I find them in order.
Sir, you understand that this is a license for the city of Medford, correct? Yes. Okay. And do you know where your business is located where you pick up your taxi? Yes, 40 Canal Street. Thank you. Madam President, I have a motion for approval. Motion for approval by Councilor Caviello, seconded by Councilor Knight. All those in favor? All those opposed? Record the two councils in opposition. Motion is approved.
Congratulations. Good luck driving. Drive safe. Motion to revert back to the regular order of business by Councillor Knight. Motions, orders, and resolutions, paper 15-500 offered by Councillor Knight, be resolved that the Medford City Council extend its deep and sincere congratulations to the following MHS athletic teams for winning the GBL title. Boys lacrosse, girls lacrosse, boys baseball, girls softball,
Be it further resolved the members of these teams, along with their coaches, be invited to appear before the city council to receive accommodations memorializing this achievement. Councilor Knight. Madam President, thank you very much. The Medford High School Mustangs have had a rather successful year all around. And this spring is no different than the fall and winter seasons. I had the opportunity to speak with our athletic director, Mr. Maloney,
I was pleased to inform you that the boys lacrosse, girls lacrosse, boys baseball, and girls softball teams were named the GBL champions. It's very great to see the Mustangs performing so well both in the classroom and on the field. And I think that it's appropriate that we recognize them for this great achievement. I think it's very important that we recognize the fact that these student athletes represent the city of Medford across the region and their efforts in our community.
and community building are very important. They're role models to our youth, Madam President, and it's also a great, great, great honor to be named a GBL champion. So because of those factors, I would ask that my council colleagues support me in voting in favor of this resolution. Motion for approval by Councilor Knight. All those in favor? All those opposed? Paper passes.
Paper 15501 offered by Councilor Knight. Do you resolve the traffic commission review the crosswalk and parking spaces crossing with Winthrop Street at Victory Park? Councilor Knight. Madam President, thank you very much. Just the other day, I was speaking to a neighbor of mine who was driving down Winthrop Street, and a child came out behind a car, from behind a car. But the car was parked in an illegal parking spot, and there was a crosswalk there, and the gentleman had a problem with visibility.
So he went around the block and he came and he approached the same intersection from the other direction to see if he had the same problem there, and he did. With that being said, Mr. President, with the summer months coming and Victory Park being such a great park where I take my kid quite frequently, as a matter of fact, I think it would be very important that this crosswalk be reviewed. I think that we might have to take a space away or two on either side of the street just to be sure that there's enough visibility here.
Also, Mr. President, I did file a resolution several weeks back requesting that a crosswalk be put in between Cedar Road and King Avenue, and I'd like to amend this resolution to include that as well. Cedar Road and King Avenue cross Forest Street, which go to the new McNally Park, which this council voted in favor of rebuilding. So with that being said, Mr. President, I'd ask that my council colleagues support me in voting in favor of these two public safety initiatives.
So, on the motion of Council and Knight, seconded by Vice President Lugo-Kern, all those in favor? All those opposed? Motion passes. From the table. The gentleman is back. On the motion of Council Marks to take 15-505 off the table, all those in favor? All those opposed?
Motion carries. 15 5 0 5 petition for taxi operator license by Sandro Matthew, uh, 18, a 60 76 Beacon street, number five, Brookline mass driving for star taxi. Mr. Councilor, madam. Mr. Chairman's papers. And I find him in a,
And the gentleman, I think he was a little confused earlier this evening. You understand that you could drive in Medford, and do you know where you're picking up your cab? 407, Mr. Gabb. Thank you. Congratulations. Thank you. On the motion for approval by Councilor Carviello, all those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Please mark Councilor Penta as opposed. Mr. Clerk.
Motion to revert back to the regular order business. All those in favor? All those opposed? 15-503 offered by Councilor Lungo-Kern be resolved that the Department of Public Works take a look at Bell Ave in the interest of public safety and add the street to the repaving list. Madam Vice President. Thank you, President De La Russo.
I think we need an audit of many of our streets in Medford, potholes, divots, construction work, catch basins. There's a number of issues. I know the Department of Public Works is on top of many of them, and they've answered our calls on a number of things. But sometimes resurfacing roads is much more costly and time-consuming.
But Belle Ave is one of those roads that really needs to be looked at. My children, I've received complaints on it, but I also drive down Belle once in a while, and my children call it the roller coaster road, which the heights, they put their hands up in the back seat and they kind of woo. So in a way, to them it's funny, but really it's a safety concern.
despicable. People on my road, Richard Street, which is close to Belle Ave, believe that Richard Street needs to be repaved. But you look at Belle Ave, and it is horrifying. So I just think that we do need to do an assessment of all our streets and put those that really need to be repaved on the repave list. So if we could just have the Department of Public Works take a look at this and maybe give us a time frame of when maybe this can get repaved, that would be appreciated.
I'd also like to just amend this. Somebody read the resolve and had a question about several winter sand barrels that were still in our roads. It's now, you know, June. So if we could have the appropriate department take a look at maybe the winter sand barrels, that would be helpful. I know there's one at Brackett and Gaston Street, Belle Ave, Park and Doonan Street.
If we could just take a look, Cleveland and Clematis and also Park Street, I believe is the number where there are several winter sand barrels. Just question if and when they'll be removed. Thank you. So on the motion of approval by Vice President Longo Kern. Sir, you want to speak on that? I apologize.
Yeah, thanks, Brian. That's great that you brought that up. I just want to add that up the top of the heights, Fell's Ave area, we've got a few up there as well. So people are starting to throw trash in them. It's getting a little gross. And they're blocking the sidewalk. Yeah, that's it. I was just going to say, they're all blocking the sidewalk, which is, you know, elderly, handicapped, baby strollers. They're out in Fell's Ave walking into traffic. OK.
Did we get some of those streets? Did we get some of those streets, Mr. Finn? Clerk Finn. On the winter barrels. And I hope that at the budget hearing when we talk DPW that we make recommendations for more iron. And if we can put that as an amendment to the resolve, remove the winter sand barrels. The clerk has that. Thank you. Councilman Max.
Thank you, Mr. President. And I agree with Councilor Longo Kern about the condition of our roads. And it was Councilor Penter, last couple of weeks, has been mentioning about a capital improvement road project. And, you know, doing roads piecemeal is fine, but we need to have a long-term plan in place where we can address many, many roads. Because in this community, it's fair to say our streets and our sidewalks are in a tough condition.
And piecemeal is not going to make a good approach. So, I agree with you, during budget time, this is when we should be laying out the plan to look at a five-year plan of doing many of our thoroughfares. I mean, if you go down Winthrop Street towards — The President Well, let's all bring a list with us. Secretary Vilsack Well, I think what we have to do is, rather than us bringing a list, I think the city should be surveying what areas need to be done. And I can tell you, Winthrop Street, the lower half of Winthrop going towards Boston Ave,
has been mentioned 1,000 times, and that road, you take your life in your own hands going down that street, and it's thorough. Riverside Ave is in tough shape. Salem Street, parts of Salem Street is in tough shape. I mean, I won't go on, but I really believe what Councilor Penta mentioned about the capital improvement road project makes sense, and we can do many, many streets if we put aside funding, Mr. President.
So on that motion, all those in favor, all those opposed carries 15 dash five Oh seven offered by consulate Penta be resolved at the governor's Avenue wall be discussed. Counselor Penta. Mr. President, some years ago, um, I think it was 2001 when the city finally got to the wall, because I think my resolutions dated back years before that the city went out of its way. And I believe we refurbished the wall that was falling down.
on Governor's Avenue, and also I think they took out the trees that sort of like sat on the top of the walls almost five feet back, and that took some time because they believed Mr. Rumley had to go out and get insecure releases from the people who owned the property who abutted the top part of the wall. Now, if you go down there today, what you're going to look at is a complete distraction to the entire community's beautification over there.
Beside the street being in a real tough condition, if you look at the wall and if you look at the sidewalk and if you look at all the brush that's growing and all the sand and the gravel that's on the sidewalks, which almost makes some part of it unwalkable, as a street that's a gateway into the city, it really needs to be addressed. This is a perfect type of a project.
that you could use summer help for, you would hire kids for the city, and you would pick out spots like that for them to go up there and clean. Just that brush that's up, that's growing on the bottom part of the street next to the sidewalk. It's even blocking at one point for anybody walking down the street on the sidewalk, especially if you have a doll carriage, a baby carriage, or anything like that. But just the walking down there, the cement pieces, the sand, the gravel, and the street in and of itself,
It just doesn't do the city justice for spending hundreds of thousands of dollars on that wall and then to let it now run itself into a state of disrepair. It's almost like the same thing of building new schools. Absolutely no follow-up, no maintenance to it. The disrepair is taking place. Well, that's what's happening right here on Governor's Avenue. So with that being said, Mr. President, I'd like to move that to the Department of Public Works to get a response back to them as it relates to the cleanup
the removal of the brush, the overgrown brush, and the trees that are overhanging on that wall, all the length of Governor's Avenue, and have a report back, Mr. President. Thank you. On the motion of Councilor Penter, all those in favor? Opposed? Motion passes. A couple of things.
The folks that are following the Committee of the Whole meetings for the budget, we're going to be making some adjustments in the coming days to the schedule. We didn't get through everything that we need to get through tonight. So as time moves along, we'll reassess the schedule and
uh, departments to some of the existing nights and we still have to solidify our meeting on the school budget. So, uh, if I could, uh, have a motion for suspension by council Marks, all those in favor of the motion to take papers under suspension, 15 dash five Oh eight offered by councilors night and commute. So be it resolved that the city council extend it's a deep and sincere condolences to the family of Kenneth Nestor on his recent passing council night.
Mr. President, thank you very much. Today, as a matter of fact, marks the day that Kenneth Nesta was laid to rest. And Kenneth was a long-time public servant at the post office, had a root here in the city of Medford for a number of years. But more often than not, you'd be able to find him down in one of our baseball fields watching his son, Michael, Park Superintendent, coach the Medford High School baseball team or watch one of his many grandchildren play.
baseball or down the county rink playing hockey. Kenneth died unexpectedly, and he will be sadly missed, Mr. President. I'm honored and privileged to have been able to call him a friend as well. And today was a very difficult day for the family and for Kenneth's friends. And I'd ask that this council join me in Councillor Camuso in offering and extending their deep and sincere condolences. Thank you, Councillor. Councillor Camuso.
Thank you, Mr. President, and I want to thank Councilor Knight for putting this on this evening for the two of us. Kenny Nesta was a great guy. Many people would not only know him from the baseball field, but as a retired post mailman. Did the West Medford route for, I'd say, 20 plus years or so. And then in his golden years of retirement, he was a custodian for the Malden Catholic Lancers over at MC. So just a great, fantastic guy.
has wonderful kids. One of them is our PAC superintendent, Mike Nesta, another great kid and loving grandchildren. And just, he's gotta be missed. Just an all around good guy. Thank you, council. So on the motion, please stand for a moment of silence. One more I have here, be it resolved,
This is offered by Councilor Knight. Be it resolved that the city solicitor update the council on the status of 56 of Boynton Road. Councilor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much. Recently, a gentleman from Boynton Road came up to discuss a house that was condemned and in disrepair in his neighborhood. The city solicitor gave a report back to this council indicating that on the 28th of last month, the case was going to be heard in probate court.
With that being said, Mr. President, I'm hoping we can get an update as to the status of that property, because I feel as though if we don't see any action take place shortly, this council may have to take action to determine that the building is unsafe and the location is unsafe and take the appropriate steps to be sure that the neighborhood is protected. So a motion to Council Knight. All those in favor? Aye. Opposed? Madam Vice President. If we could let our citizens speak regarding the budget.
something I think we've asked for a number of times, and you can reiterate. Thank you. Please state your name and address for the record. Michael Ruggiero. I live on 18 Pembroke street. I wish to discuss the budget that was presented at the meeting of the whole. Um, while the budget is, you know, there's a lot of thorough paperwork here. It is concerning that some residents might not be able to access this document digitally. Also, um, this document, if it's presented digitally can be searched more thoroughly.
than if it's presented sort of in loose leaf paper, or if I lose it today. I asked the council to present a resolution to Louise Miller to make sure that this document is presented digitally. I know she's very busy, and she's taking over a new role in the accounting office. But this document should definitely be digital so we can search it, use it, and reference it online for people that might not be able to come in. Oh, yeah. Thank you.
I would just move that as a, put that in motion form and send that to the administration and Louise Miller, that's something that the city council has asked for a number of times, just to have the budget accessible online on the website. I think it's as simple as probably scanning and attaching it as a document.
If she can print this, she can save it as a PDF. So it would be better to save it as a PDF, because then it would be much easier to search machine-wise. If she scans it in, it will be much more difficult to search. It can be transferred as well. But if she can print this document, then she should be able to do it as a PDF. I mean, I realize it's more work for her to do, but it's important that the citizens have access to this digitally. Thank you. Absolutely. Absolutely. So if we could request that they
submitted as a PDF so that people can access it online. I think it's something that more people from home would definitely would like to access and have the right to access. It's their tax dollars that go to paying the budget, so I would just move that, move approval. I rest, Mr. President.
The records of the May 26, 2015, council meeting were passed to Councilor Penta. Councilor Penta. Yes, I found them. How did you find those records? In order. Found those records in order. Do you wish to motion their approval? On the motion for approval, all those in favor? All right. Opposed? Motion to adjourn?
What's that?