do do
you
Welcome to Breaking Science.
Anyway, so the immune system is in your blood partially. If you spin down blood, you have serum, the liquid fraction, red blood cells, and then the white blood cells, which are the major components of the immune system. So this is what protects you against nasty things.
There are multiple different arms of the immune system. There's the innate immune system and the adaptive immune system. And they behave very differently. They have these things called cytotoxic cells. As their name suggests, they are very good at killing other cells. And the major cell type we have here are natural killer cells. And I kid you not, these are like the actual names that immunologists refer to them by. There's also a property that they have called
License to kill. This is seriously, if you look in the terminology literature published scientific literature, you'll find the phrase license to kill. You have the innate and the adaptive both acting individually at different times, but how do they like work together? Yeah, okay. That's a very very good question.
So they'll feed forward and backwards towards each other. Although I presented them as separate enemies, they're really, they talk to each other a lot. They'll produce proteins called cytokines that will help them to do different functions. So how do we protect ourselves against it? We call in Jaden Smith. I promise you don't have Jaden Smith running around anywhere. It can go many, many different ways.
The classical T-cells, there were two classical types of T-cells called T-helper 1 and T-helper 2. And then now there's a couple of others, T-helper type 17. Again, don't ask about the math. Genealogists are not so good at these things. And regulatory T-cells. The answer to last week's Mustang Report question of the week is, we're both twins and we have the same birthday. I'm one of the twins.
Question of the week, what is this? This is the cloak. Hi, this is Nick Keniston with the Mustang Report and I'm here at the Medford Vocational Technical High School in the Cosmetology Shop and we're here about to witness some paraffining. What are some of the benefits of paraffining on your hands?
Well, it makes your hands soft because it takes off all the dead skin, and it makes your hands healthier since the dead skin's off. Now, if somebody outside of school wanted to come in and set up an appointment, how would they go about doing that? Well, you would call the shop, and you can make an appointment for Tuesday, Wednesday, or Thursday mornings, and then that's it. You just come in. Now, how much does something like paraffining typically cost? Outside of the school, it would cost around $15.
And inside of the school? Free. Now we're about to witness Miss Dunphy get some paraffining done. So what do we do first? Sanitize your hands. Sanitize. Many people use this, right? Yep.
It's not real hot, it's just warm.
So there we have it. Here's the final result of paraffin. Now just a quick question to any one of you. What is, you know, what do your hands feel different after getting the treatment? They're very soft and they feel very healthy. First off, I want to welcome and wish the very best of all the spring athletes here that are beginning.
their sports season this week. I hope we bring in a lot of great championships. I know it's very, very important that people play sports and get active in their school and their community because it tends to motivate people to do very, very well in school and understand the value of being a student athlete.
Because being a student athlete we hold those people to very high standards because you guys are representing us in other communities and also here very well at Mefford High School too. Sports teach you a lot of great things with regards to having a great work ethic, being committed, being focused, having a great attitude, concentration and effort in a lot of things that you do. And you can apply a lot of those great things later on in life to whatever profession that you end up going in the direction of.
So I'm glad, very happy, a lot of those great skills and things are being put in place by a lot of our coaches here at Medford High School. And I'm sure it's going to end up producing a lot of great people in our community that will do a lot of great, awesome things because of the skills and various things they learn by playing sports. And we hope to win a lot of great championships this spring. So best of luck to all the athletes at Medford High.
Hi. Hi. Hi.