A regular meeting of the Medford School Committee will now come to order. The secretary will call the roll. Mr. Scudio, Ms. Del, Ms. Dress, Ms. Postone, Ms. Carey-President, Ms. VandenBloom, Ms. Medford. Present, seven present, none absent. Please rise and salute our flag. I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America, and to the republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all.
Item 1, approval of the minutes of June 6, 2016. Motion for approval by Ms. Disceri, seconded by Ms. Van de Kloot. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Minutes are approved. Item 2, approval of bills, transfer of funds. Motion for approval by Ms. Disceri, seconded by Ms. Van de Kloot. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed?
Approvals, seven in the affirmative, nine in the negative. Approval of payrolls. Motion for approval by Mr. Skerry, seconded by Mr. Benedetto. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Motion passes. Report of the secretary. Report of committees. Committee of the whole. Superintendent's evaluation, school year 2015-16.
We held a committee of the whole back on June 2nd to evaluate our superintendent. Several of us had, well, all of us had comments and gave our ratings by the classification items 1, 2, 3, and 4. Overall, the total average was a 3.87 for the superintendent. I'm trying to see if there's anything to highlight.
Is there a motion that's highly, high proficient? So motion to approve, accept the report and place on file, seconded by Mr. Benedetto. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion passes. Community participation has been withdrawn. Report of the superintendent, report on administrative work week.
And our members of the committee will call on our Deputy Superintendent to tell us about the Administrative Work Week, which will take place beginning on Wednesday of this week. Good evening. Happy summer to everyone. We are kind of getting ready to say goodbye to our students. But again, our administrators stay at work. Most of them work throughout the summer doing different things, hiring. A lot of things come up. We're not sure when the state testing results are coming in. So when that happens,
people are back at work. Officially, we have five days after the students get out of school where administrators meet. This happens each year. And during these meetings, we debrief on what's gone on this past school year. We make our plans for the upcoming school year, try to start to make plans, and engage in trainings that are relevant to some of our new initiatives.
The schedule provides time to meet individually with administrators to address any end of year concerns that are specific to their schools or departments. And this year, our meetings start the day after school gets out, the 22nd, and they continue through Tuesday, June 28th. Again, a variety of topics will be covered this year. We will talk about budget, how we're going to make it all fit, scheduling, personnel issues,
Administrators now will receive training that week in School Brains, which is going to replace I-PASS, and also in ASOP, which is the new program and protocol for hiring substitute teachers. We also plan to spend substantial time on the teacher evaluation system. Believe it or not, it's still growing and emerging with DDMs. Those are the district-determined measures.
A next part of this is that students have input into teacher self-assessment. So again, we are still, the system is growing and growing and growing. So we want our administrators to be on board with some of the new things that need to be implemented. We will also focus on some of the new developments related to the new state test, MCAS 2.0. Right now, we don't have a lot of information about what that test is going to look like.
We do know that it is planned to be implemented in the spring, so hopefully information will be forthcoming. We find that these end-of-year meetings with administrative staff provide time for quality collaboration. Administrators have opportunities to speak with one another, to share best practices, and we also ask administrators to suggest topics that they would like us to pursue. So all of that has been taking place this past week.
We present topics and materials for administrators to reflect on. We give them homework during the summer and we ask them to bring back some of their reflections at our opening meetings that happen five days before school opens. So it's a relatively short summer as administrators close out the end of June and come back really almost mid-August. Again, as I mentioned, most people, most administrators work throughout the summer. Everybody's in and out, doing hiring.
attending to ordering materials, and so on. Officially, administrators return on August 22nd, which is a week before school begins, and then we will be holding meetings throughout that week, the 22nd to the 26th, so we'll be ready to open school on the 29th. So that's our schedule, very busy, very ambitious, but very productive. So if I can answer any questions, I'll be more than happy to. Are there any questions?
Thank you. Is there a motion? Motion to receive in place on file by offered by Mr. Skerry, seconded by Ms. Van de Kloot. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Motion passes. Report on merger of the GBL with Northeast Athletic Conference. Madam Mayor, members of the committee, as you know, for a period of time now, the GBL has diminished in its size as various members opted to go with different leagues in the area. That meant Medford, Somerville, Malden, and Everett
had become the remaining members of the GBL. Scheduling and creating athletic opportunities for young people within the GBL becomes progressively difficult. We have to find teams outside of our area, and every year it's a different situation. It also deprives our youngsters of competing against other students in other communities that could take on sports that maybe the GBL members choose not to participate in at a particular time.
So our athletic director is here. We are looking to merge with the NEC, the Northeast Conference. Many of the schools in the Northeast Conference once belonged to us, like Revere, and Peabody, and places like that. So we're looking to go to that at this point in time and see if we can't make sure that we have a robust league for our students to play in over the next several years. It wouldn't start till the spring.
So we have the fall to get used to it. It doesn't affect the Medford-Malden football game. Simultaneously, I just want to mention while we're talking about this is that Jack Dempsey, our softball coach, was named the Boston Globe Coach of the Year. Congratulations, Jack. And several of our players, senior Ashley Eisner, girls softball, named the Boston Globe's, and Boston knows all scholastic girls softball team, girls softball, girls tennis team, and lacrosse, boys lacrosse are GBL champions.
Those are some highlights from the sports side of things, and if you have any questions, Ms. Maloney and I can try to answer them for you.
So prior to our budget night, I had no idea that we were moving in this direction. We hadn't really been apprised of this along the way. So I don't really understand whether this requires a vote of the school committee to affirm the decision. I don't know if it's a decision or it's just what is happening. Could you perhaps explain that?
Well, you know, obviously, anytime we make a move of this type and change our affiliations, we would like your endorsement. So I'm not sure that it does, because you basically allow us to play any team and, you know, in the area, as long as they're governed by the MIAA and the like. But it certainly would be a good idea if you did. So just out of curiosity, are there other options? Or is this the option? This is the option. This is the option. We've been trying for an extended period of time to form a league.
Um, but very few, the middle six league would only take us and not Malden and Everett and then Cambridge bolted to.
another week and Waltham bolted to another week. So before you know it, we were down teams instead of having a robust. Yeah, I know. I know that was just, you know, dissipated. So I guess I'd like to ask, uh, Mr Maloney, whether any sports will be impacted, for example, uh, will right now our swimming season is during the winter. Um, but I know some schools have different swimming seasons. So does anybody, anything change for us?
As of today, nothing changes. We'll be meeting in September with the principals and the athletic directors. There'll be 16 teams. The plan on paper right now is there's 16 teams. There'll be two divisions of eight, and they'll seat us according to the sport, according to the strength of our team. There's going to be a north and a south. Basically, the north is going to be the more powerful one. So it's going to be a competitive 16-team league. As of right now, nothing should change with our schedule.
Thank you. Do we know if we're in the North or the South? Every sport's going to be different. So we're assuming that we're going to be in the upper tier in most sports. We're pretty competitive in most of the sports that they have right now. OK. Ms. Cuno. Thank you. Mr. Maloney, I know that you said there's 16 teams. Could you tell us the cities? I know it's us.
It's the four GBL teams Method, Malden, Everett, and Somerville. And then we have the whole North Shore. We have the two Lynn's. Lynn Classical, Lynn English. We have Winthrop, Revere, Salem, Marblehead, Swampskid, Gloucester, Peabody, and Danvers. That's 16. And Gloucester. And Saugus. Saugus too. Is that 16? Yeah. And Gloucester is the furthest for our students? Will be the furthest trip, correct. OK. Is this going to impact?
being that there's going to be more competitions, there's going to be more games, is this going to affect our busing and our budget on our busing? We're going all over the state right now to get games. So I don't think it's going to affect the bus schedule. And for the far trips, we're going to try to get creative in the fall. We can do stuff during school vacation week. We can do stuff on Saturdays.
Baseball and softball, the weather, they may be able to do double headers. So we're going to try to get creative and everybody's on the same page. Dr. Perella, school comes first, athletics second. So we'll make sure we work it out.
Okay, because I was just concerned. I mean, I know that we've traveled far now, depending on who we've competed against. I was just very concerned, especially after a regular day of school, going really, really far away and then trying to come back home. That's always something. But my concern was also the buses. Even though we are using buses now, we are going everywhere with
going from four teams to 16 teams is going to be a lot more games. Well, the games won't change. Hockey will still play a 20-game schedule. Soccer will play an 18. So the games won't change. So the amount of games won't change. It's just going to be more competitive itself. Correct. OK. And you can probably give Pat some homework to do. She'll get us in competitive bus deal.
I don't know, Bobby, maybe you'll start driving the bus. I'm very happy with the kids. I'm really happy with the kids having more competitiveness. I think that's a really good thing. There's a motion on the floor to receive and place on file by Mr. Scarry. Is there a second? Second. Motion for roll call vote.
Yes, 7 in the affirmative, 0 in the negative. Motion passes. Recommendation to approve community schools fee structure. Madam Mayor, members of the committee, we have provided to you a fee structure for community schools as you have requested. You have previously approved the rules and regs for the rentals of facilities. There are some
additional items here that were made to accommodate youth groups and also some community groups that might not have the resources necessary to access our facilities on a regular basis. And we've tried to take into account the things that have been provided to us.
Pat Velie is here to talk about this particular issue. And Mr. Maloney is also here as the director of community schools. So I'm going to have Pat take you through the changes that we've made so that you can go over them. And we can decide if we're going to go forward with this particular schedule. Good evening, everybody. So you find attached, we've already approved the wording. So we'll go straight into the fee structure. And I'll point out the changes that have been made to accommodate
certain requests and items that I was not aware of the first round. In the theater technician, we were charging $40 an hour and then splitting out the cost of the mics and anything else that might be used. We're just going to go with a flat $75 an hour rate, and then we'll use that money to replace any equipment. All right?
Below the MHS cafeteria and the classroom, we've allowed for regular scheduled MPS Booster Club meetings. They're exempt from the rental fee. The reason both rooms are selected is many times the parents just outnumber that classroom, so we have to move them into a small cafeteria. All right? Nothing else changes until you get down to Edgerly Field.
We kept the fee consistent across the board because that is how the Hormel charges, and we want to remain competitive with our neighbors right now. And then if you go to the third page, which is number 8 of 12, options added. Groups grandfathered in include the Medford Youth Soccer and Medford Youth Lacrosse. Rates for grandfathered in users are $75 an hour, practice on Edgeley Field,
and $100 an hour for games. Rental space is based on availability of field. The second one, Medford community-based non-profit groups may apply to rent facilities for $75 an hour. If a custodian, tech assistants, et cetera, is on duty, if custodial tech assistants, et cetera, are required to be hired, the posted fees for such services apply. A letter of non-profit status is required at time of rental.
Third one, registered MPS booster organizations will be allowed available times, times not otherwise booked, at the gymnasiums and Edgeley Field. It is expected that these MPS booster organizations provide significant MPS team support. This free of charge time assumes no special cost, again, no custodial, tech assistance, et cetera. If custodial, tech assistance, et cetera are required to be hired,
The posted fees for such services apply. All booster groups will be required to register with community schools. Finally, community subsidy. To underwrite City of Medford nonprofit groups requesting theater use outside of regular school hours, MPS will ask for a subsidy for user discounts.
school committee will be asked to approve each request at the next regularly scheduled meeting. And then the last change is second from the bottom of that list. Should the city of Medford revise the rental rates for Hormel Stadium, a discussion should also ensue related to the Edgeley Field rental rates, therefore providing enough notice for current renters. I'll take questions. Thank you for your work on this, Pat.
So my first question is the price for Edgeley Field. I want to make sure that, you know, the $145 is the lowest of the prices that we had. And if it's going across the board, that means for-profit and non-profit will be paying that amount, unless they apply for that $75 if they don't need any other facility use. Correct. OK. So I'm just concerned because- Excuse me.
If we're still required to pay for the bond and the bond interest in future years, I just want to make sure that we have the funds if we're supposed to be able to do that from this account. I want to be very clear that we're going to raise enough money to be able to do that and not have a shortage and have to go into our general school club accounts or the city's general account to pay for it.
Right. That would take us to the second portion of this, which is the use of the our school software. And that should increase our rental income because we'll have better tracking and better tracking just usually means more income. Thank you. Great. Um, I have a couple of questions. I hope it's okay. All right. So that was my first question just to make sure that one 45 is, is what other communities are paying. My second one is,
Up above, where it says, Groups Grandfathered, Method Youth Soccer, and Method Lacrosse. So we need to have on file a copy of their 5013C. So we have record that they are a non-profit? Yes. Okay. And I'm really happy to see this, because these groups have been using our fields for a very long time. And I'm wondering how delegation of field time is going to be handled.
I'll let Mr. Maloney answer that. Thank you. I know that when we built the Field of Dreams or Edgeley Field, it was prioritized that non-profits that took care of the youth in our community were to get first usage.
And then, out to the highest bidder after that? And I don't know if that's... That's not true. Okay. That's not true. High school first, of course. The high school, all three turf fields, the high school gets the field to six, six o'clock. Generally, they do not use Hormel because transportation issues by the time the kids get down there. So, the two edgily fields, the high school is on the six o'clock.
Method youth soccer and method youth lacrosse generally are on that field six to eight and then we go out. There's no higher bidders or anything. It's always been one 45 across the board. Uh, the prior administration had a, uh, agreement with method youth soccer and method youth lacrosse that they would pay $75 an hour for practice and a hundred dollars on Saturday for a game. Uh, that's, I think it's great that it's grandfathered in, but,
As far as that, I don't anticipate any changes there. I mean, it's important that the 8 to 11 group is paying the rack rate to bring in the money, and also on weekends that they're paying the rack rate, $145 an hour, because if you start giving up these three fields away to all non-profits, you're not going to make any money. And I know Method Youth Soccer and Method Youth Lacrosse should be very happy with this agreement. They're getting a good bang for their buck up there right now.
I spoke with the president of Method Youth Soccer earlier this year, and they had stated that they requested 12 hours on the turf fields and got six this season. A week, not total. That's not true. OK. They got more than that? The original agreement, they had six to eight on Monday through Thursday nights. This year, we gave them an additional hour on one field, six to nine.
There's 28 fields in Medford. I mean, I'm not running for politics, so I don't need anybody's vote. But we have 28 fields in Medford with grass. I'm glad that we have turf fields, but, you know, it's good for the young kids to learn how to play on the grass, because that's where you pick up some skills. We just can't give the turf field away, because people don't want to play on grass anymore, with all due respect. And I just didn't know if they had no other availability. No, we have Harris Park. We have behind the Andrews. We have Plaisted Park.
I mean, you drive around the city, Victory Park, you drive by Victory Park on a Saturday, it's jammed with soccer. Well, with the new computer system, we'll be able to see who's on our fields, and maybe the city side will get it for the parks, so that way we know, and we can look, like, okay, so you need some more time. Well, the city has time, and here's what's available for you to use that way. It might be helpful on both ends. Thank you for that clarification.
So my next question, and you might want to just hang around, Bob, sorry. So the registered Method Public Schools Booster organizations shall be allowed available times, otherwise not booked, which is great, at the gymnasium and at elderly field. I just want to make sure that these Booster clubs are also non-profit. They have to have their non-profit status filed with our offices in order to get that.
I know some are and some aren't, and this will encourage them all to become non-profit in that way there. It protects them in the school district at the same time, and that's my goal here. So if they don't have non-profit, at least if they filed the papers and they can prove that, if they're planning on using it soon, I'd like that paperwork in City Hall and give them a deadline of like September 15th or whatever you think is fair, October 1st, you know,
But we should come up with a date for that. And if they're not nonprofit, we're going to have to say, I'm sorry, you need to become that in order to use our field. So I would like that added in to the wording of that. Also, with their filings of their papers, I would like to know who's in charge of those nonprofits, their names, and contact information.
So that way if there's ever an issue, say something goes haywire on the field and some damage happens, we don't have to search for that. That's also in our database. But sometimes there's multiple people, so like if, like on their non-profit things, like, yeah.
And also, the superintendent had suggested that at the beginning of each school year, we actually recertify these groups. OK. I think that's a great idea as well. And the Hormel decision should also ensure Edgley field rates if we're providing enough notice for current renters. So are we already? Is that what Hormel's already charging? I don't know if you know that. Hormel and Edgley are both $145 an hour.
Okay, and we're not going- If Method Youth Soccer gets displaced down there or they use that field, they pay the same discounted fee. In the real cost. But if the mayor wants to convene a meeting in the future, I would recommend the Hormel Commission be involved, and both facilities go up at the same time if we're gonna have an increase. So we're gonna be getting quarterly reports on this, so we can look at this to see if this rate is great enough for us to- Should we just go ahead?
if this is great enough for us to pay our bond and pay the bills on the upkeep of the fields and the equipment that we're using, and see then if any changes are made. So I thank you for all your work on this. If you could add those things in, Pat, I make a motion to pass if those things are added in. Ms. Cuneo. No, actually everything has been asked.
And just one, on the registered MPS booster organizations will be allowed available times, times not otherwise booked. And so, booked by when? Are we talking a week in advance, two weeks in advance? How? So, like Haley Horgan for the band's very organized, so she's at Hormel twice a year. I usually get her dates 11 months in advance. Some coaches I may get it a day in advance.
So if it's available, we give it to them. If it's not available, they're out of luck. OK. What that group's talking about is like a summer camp for soccer or a basketball camp in the gymnasium that is run by our high school coaches. Haley runs two beautiful band camps at Hormel Stadium.
We have people in the Little Theater periodically. Aaron Keith does a great job in the summer with a summer program in the Little Theater. Michael Skorka will generally do something in the cafeterias or something. So we try to take care of the people who work for us and they can make some money for their programs. We're not charging custodians. We're not charging technicians. We're not paying for field workers. And the money is going directly to the programs? Correct. Okay. Thank you.
Okay, a couple of things. I was just looking at, when we have all these programs that are going on, Bob, like we have things going on in the Mosh and Can Theater and we have things going on in the cafeteria and, you know, in the gymnasium, and I understand that we're going to have the calendar and everything is, but you are the one who is in charge of all of this. But it's impossible for you to be at every single place. So what's the next step after you? Is there some, like,
Is whoever rents the Karen Theater in charge of the Karen Theater, or is there someone from the high school that oversees it while you're not there? It depends on the situation. Generally, somebody from Rich Schrader's group's there. And again, if a custodian has to be hired, there'll be a custodian on the property. Generally, we have a custodian on either at night or they're on Saturdays with the Japanese group.
Every rental is different. Generally, we have somebody on whether it's myself, Rachel Perry, a custodian, or Lisa Dunphy, or Michael McLaughlin from Rich Strada's group. Okay. So at least there's someone. Yes, there's always somebody overseeing the rental. Okay. And actually, while we're on, I mean, it's on the rental fees, but I am going to throw this in here because you were talking about coaches and things like that and schedules.
Could we make it a point that, I know it's hard sometimes, but now especially with 16 different cities and towns that parents and students will be participating in, if we could have our coaches please give out some type of schedule to parents for each and every sport because this fly-by moment is getting a little ridiculous and has nothing to do with the two of you.
Okay, but that and also to make sure that there's a contact number of who and where to contact a coach. Right. Because it's well overdue. The our school program is really well rounded. It has facets for parents, facets for administration, facets for coaches. They all have their own piece of this program and so there'll be a public calendar and then you'll be able to go into each team and see their activity. Okay.
But even on top of that, though, I mean, we had something similar. I know it wasn't the best of the best systems, because I know Bobby got a lot of calls from us at the last minute going, it just got changed. Are we here, or on the other side of the city, or another city completely? But I think ownership of coaches taking their own ownership, and I know it's great to have the calendar, and it's great for parents to go into their calendar if they're at work, or if they're driving
a game, but I think it's very important that coaches, and I'm not saying that all or none do this, but while I have the opportunity, I'd like to put it out there and say that all coaches should take the responsibility of giving some type of schedule to the students and have like a night with the parents that they give a schedule to the parent and a contact number. Our school has that component. We're very happy to have it coming in. The results go on there right away if you want to
For example, if you have two kids, one's participating in the band, one in soccer, you can download their schedules for the year. Coach's contact, email, phone number, everything's in there. The trainer's information in there. It's a fantastic software we're getting. So we're very happy about it. That sounds great, but we still need to let the parents know that. So if a coach isn't relaying that message, then the parents are not going to be able to get that message. I'll get it out.
Directions are on there, yeah. Thank you. Today I had the opportunity to look at the summer rec program that City Hall put out and I noticed that Mary Judd has her summer swim camps on there, which is great. But I know there are other camps. I know there's a soccer camp and I know that there's probably a lot of other things going on.
I would really like that to be added on an annual basis to that book, so that way everybody in the community sees everything. Even if it says, you know, the football camp is practicing here on three nights, it's only open to Meffitt High students. You know, at least then, people in the city are seeing all the great things that we're doing. But, like, I know that that soccer camp, my kids went to it when they were young.
all the way through it, and it's not on there, and it would be good publicity for that group to bring in those funds to help. So if there's a way before that's printed, if the... Right, I know it is for this year. I'm making... Right, and then parents would really have options and really can see everything going on. Because we have so many programs that we should be yelling it.
The motion on the floor for approval by Mr. Benedetto. With changes to the wording. Adding that non-profit and that the booster clubs and names of contact and offices among those groups. Point of contact. Yes. Seconded by Ms. Vanke. Ms. Desgheri, please call the roll. Oh, Jamila, I'm sorry. Ms. Crutch has a question. It's more of like an informational question. Just wanted to know about the new system.
Do you know, Pat, if the new system allows parents to like, I don't know, like create it, download an app or anything like that, or where they can create a username and password, and if they had an account, they would get a message, like a text message or an email, if it was changed, you know, and then they could check before they go to the game, like make sure I don't get an email or a text message before we head off. Right. It has a lot of that functionality.
We have to add it incrementally, so it'll take us a little while to get there. But the one thing, Ms. Cuno, that it has is it has an email list roster by coach. And so when a change needs to go out, coach has already built their email list from the list of parents that they have, and they can just send an auto message.
Thank you very much for all this work to refine the schedule.
Motion for approval by Mr. Benedetto, seconded by Ms. Vanden Heuvel. Roll call vote, please. Yes. Benedetto. Yes. Gretz. Yes. Estrada. Yes. Yes. Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative. Motion passes. I'm sorry? It's for the budget. It's the budget that comes next, that comes after this. Report on proposed succession plan for the superintendent.
Madam Mayor and members of the committee, recently there's been some discussion about a succession plan, whether we would have one. And so in response to your request, we've put one together for you. It comes in the two types of scenarios. The first scenario is that if there was an untimely or unexpected vacancy created by either illness or some other dastardly act,
and the superintendent is unable to perform his duties for whatever reason, then the deputy superintendent would become the interim superintendent. The school committee would begin a search process for a permanent replacement. The deputy would serve until either the superintendent returned or a new leader was selected. The current school system administration is an experienced team that can handle transition and maintain operations for an extended period of time. I'll just go over. We have a deputy superintendent, an assistant superintendent, director of finance and administration,
a director of pupil services, director of buildings and grounds, as well as principals, assistant principals, department directors in place. And each would be able to carry out their essential functions. So I think that should there be an unexpected situation occur and that things happen to people and things go on, whether it be illness or something else, I think we have a very experienced team in place that could step up and run the school district for a period of time. And if the committee reached a point where they felt that they had to do something a little bit more permanent, then the next thing would kick in.
If there was an announced vacancy, for example, the superintendent decided to retire, the committee decided not to rehire the superintendent or whatever the case may be, the Medford School Committee could retain the Massachusetts Association of School Committees as one example to conduct a search or a similar organization. I'll give you a little bit. A search by an organization costs generally somewhere between $10,000 and $12,000.
That's a typical search for MASC. If you went to what Lexington did, it cost them $35,000. They hired a national firm, and they found three people from Massachusetts after they did their national search. I think, you know, obviously MASC can, you know, can do a very good job. They do a lot of them around the country, and we can give you examples of it. So I think that's probably a preferred option. It's the least expensive for an experienced organization that does it around the state and has many, many contacts.
A comprehensive search process normally takes four to five months. It isn't a full year process. Now, naturally, if you're not happy with the candidates, it could take a little bit longer. But generally, if things go according to normal plan, it's four to five months to complete. The time frame may vary depending on geographical location of your search. Now, if you want to bring people in from California or Montana or Hawaii, it may take a little longer to interview them.
If you're interested in bringing people from Massachusetts, New England area, or things like that, New York, Connecticut, you certainly could do this in that time frame. Of course, a number of community focus groups that you would want to hold. Some people want to hold focus groups in different sections of the city. Some people want to do it by school. Some people want to do it by topic, special ed, ELL. You can decide whatever approach you'd want to use.
And we can give you guidelines on how to do that if you chose to do that. The typical search process, five phases, and they're as follows. Phase one is a leadership profile development. It takes about a month. You would sit and talk about, you know, what you expected in a leader. And you would create, for the organization running the search for you, the kinds of information they would need to put up brochures and do advertisements and be part of the screening process, which would be,
coming on a little bit later. Phase two would be candidate recruitment. Once that's decided, brochures would go out, advertisements would go out, and candidates would be recruited. And then phase three would be candidate screening, also about a month's worth of time. Then phase four, community evaluation of candidate finalists, because they would be narrowed down to three, four, five people. And you could do that generally in less than a month. You may want to take a little longer, but three weeks is generally a normal search.
And then phase five, the appointment and contract negotiation. Give yourself a little bit of time to meet the person that you might want to hire, and then spend some time talking to that person about terms and conditions of their contract and what your expectations are. And from time to time, an individual and a candidate decides at the last minute they don't want to be there, or the terms and conditions, so you might have to go back to candidate two, three, four, whatever you choose to do.
I've given you the MASC detailed guidelines for each phase and the kinds of things they would ask. I can give you more, but I felt tonight this was a good enough start to get going. Uh, the recent Brookline search took four, it took four months and I attached that for you. Brookline, uh, much more expansive than some places. Uh, the selection of an interim superintendent from Malden is scheduled for three months and change. Uh, they're currently doing it. They started in May and they hope to have somebody aboard by July one.
The fall river selection took a little better than three months, and that's a bigger community. But I can give you other examples of, you know, search times, but I wanted to give you a few that you could look at. I've attached some information, some brochure-like information, and some other things that people have put out. Again, we can do more if you felt that was necessary. The process for community involvement can take many forms. You can have a community survey online. You can have a hard copy survey.
You can have community forums like we've had in the past, or you can have categorical focus groups where you bring in, you know, different groups from a school or grade level, areas of interest, talk to the faculty, staff members. You can mix and match these as you see fit. And as you review this at some point in time, you may want to give me guidance so that we can refine it and develop it into the next stage of readiness for you to go forward.
And then you want to determine who's going to be on the screening teams internally, whether you're going to have the full committee and other people, or you're just going to use the full committee. So those are some of the things. Or you can combine any of the above. A formal application form, I attached an example of that for your review. You can change it. You can ask different questions. That's up to you, but I think that's typical of what you would ask and what you would look for.
And then, of course, the selection of a group such as MASC can greatly facilitate what goes on to enhance the possibilities of finding a good fit for Medford. And lastly, there'd be a transition process between the outgoing leadership and the incoming superintendent. And every effort would be made by my administration to assist in that process to ensure that the individual had the benefit of knowing where things were and what our perspectives were based on our own experience.
So the above report and attached information help allay any concerns that a succession plan is in place and a process can happen in a reasonable timeframe. Happy to take any questions you might have. Ms. Suno. Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Superintendent. I was actually pleased that I saw this report. I had actually called up MASC and asked the executive director there for the report. And he had just told me that he had just hung up with the superintendent. So our timing was really good.
Just a little bit of my insight on this is when and if this time does come, because it will come, that whether it's MASC or any other type of organization that will facilitate this, it's very important that we do get someone from the outside. I know that there have been cities and towns that have decided to take it upon themselves to do the search.
Honestly, they don't save money, and you really need to have the expertise to really guide you in the right direction. Of course, ultimately, it is our decision to be made, but I really strongly suggest the decision does not have to be made now. There's no motions to be made. I'm just saying that when the subsection plan does come into place, it is very important that we go and we get someone that has the expertise in this type of field.
I just want to thank the superintendent for putting the report together. I think it gives us a, it's good to have this outline for us and in our records. I make a motion to accept the paper and place it on file.
Thank you. First of all, I just want to say thank you for putting this together. It's very well done. It's a good basic base. It's not, you know, it's not specific to what we want to do as a school committee, but it at least has something in place if something were to happen. And I think that's what the community came forward asking for. And I think that we fulfilled that with this document. So I wanted to say thank you for that. I think there's some more work to do. And maybe at the beginning of next year, we should sit down and really
You know, in case things were to arise, have more specific what we as a committee see what our steps would be. So we don't even have to think about it in case of any emergency. So I want to thank you for putting this together so well. Secondly is, I also, for just information, when I was at a class at MASC with my colleagues, we did, down the hall, was a class on how to pick a superintendent.
So maybe it's a good idea if some of us were to take that class, so that way in the future we have some knowledge moving forward. It doesn't have to be all of us, but it might be a great idea for us to have for future knowledge in case an emergency or a different situation were to arise. So I'd like to see when they're offering that, and if any members or any of my colleagues would like to join me in taking that class.
Point of information. In speaking to the executive director, that is something that we were going to try to do something this year, but it was just that the schedule had been really busy for them and they couldn't do it. So instead of everyone trying to fit in a class, we're going to try to see when his schedule is free, and then I'd bring you the dates for them to come to us. And we could do it like a meeting of the whole, and we could have any questions that we have that evening.
And if you want to specialize it in the superintendent search or trying to learn more about a superintendent search, that's what we were trying to figure out. So that was the point of information on that. Yep, we could do it here. Yeah, we've done it in the past where they come and they go over certain things, but I think this would be an opportunity for them to come. So if I can make a suggestion.
Uh, just simply this is that you've got some outlines here, so go down it and see whether you, what kind of, what kind of combinations you like, and then we'll call a committee of the whole or some point and you can decide, you know, if this happens, we want this type of focus group. We'd like a survey online. We'd like this, we'd like that. So you put it together. So you flesh out the document based on what you would like to see and we'll give you guidance on that. That's not a difficult thing to do, but remember this was the outline so that you can get started and then you can,
flesh it out a little bit and say what I want. You know, what do you want? And it will be different in different communities. Some communities will emphasize one thing, and some communities will want to emphasize something else. So we can get started. I'm sure Glenn Kocher or Jim Harney or some of the other people that work for MASC would be happy to come out. I think they're your best bargain, to be honest with you. They do enough of them around the Commonwealth, so they've got lots of experience and lots of contacts and get along with MASS pretty well.
And you don't have to pay the fees for some national firm that, you know, we'll find somebody, uh, two communities over, you know. Thank you. Um, so I think that's, that's a really good idea, Mr. Bellson. So what I would like to do since I'm the chair of the personnel subcommittee, I'd like to put it on the schedule for, um, late September and, um, call a meeting, a subcommittee meeting to go over this and to, to put,
those ideas together and so that way it doesn't get lost. So I make a motion to have that. We can do it over the summer. Or we can do it this summer either if people are around.
Aye. All those opposed? Papers sent and submitted. Will someone make a motion for substantial rules? Ms. Cuno? So that we can recognize the Medford Kiwanis for the annual book donation we have with us City Councilor Rick Garviello representing the Kiwanis. The Medford Public Schools would once again like to thank the Kiwanis Club of Medford for their generous donation of books to our first and third grade students. The Kiwanis Club has always gone above and beyond for the benefit of Medford.
In the spring of each year, I look forward to the phone call from Kiwanis Club asking for the numbers of children in Grades 1 and 3. For the past few years, President Ricarbello called in May and said, it's that time of year again. The students are overjoyed when they receive their books. They quickly open up their bags and begin to read. This is such a great way to kick off the summer.
Many members of the Kiwanis come to all our schools to help distribute the books. Chuck Veneziano tells the students the story of the Kiwanis Club in Dr. Seuss language. The children love the rhymes students sometimes read and then trade the books with other students. Once again, on behalf of the public schools and Mr. Superintendent and Ms. Caldwell, thank you so much for making the children's summer a happy and productive time. Mr. Carvalho. Thank you, Madam Mayor. Thank you, school committee members. I think tonight's my 13th year.
being the Chairman of the Literacy Program for the Medford Kiwanis. And I realize tonight we've given out 35,000 books to the children of Medford. It's something I'm very proud of and our club is very proud of. And this year we did something a little bit different. We gave the kids book bags this year. And when you see the pictures in the paper,
see the kids, they have more with your face. And I'd like to present the book bag to all the school committee members and yourself, ma'am. And again, and again, I thank you and Ms. Cardwell for designing this program some years ago. And again, we'll see you next year. And we've also incorporated the Mifflin library the last couple of years with Sam Stenick,
And so they've gotten their message out for the summer reading also. Thank you. Thank you. On a motion to receive and place on file the recognition of the mythic wand, is all those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Motion is granted. Also, this is summer schedule. There's a recommendation to approve summer rules by the superintendent.
This is a standard procedure. So as we do this virtually every year, because we don't meet as frequently if we meet at all during the summer, I send out all kinds of information to you at different points in the summer. But from June 21st, 2016,
Through our first meeting in September of 2016, I'm requesting the school committee grant authority to the superintendent and the school committee secretary for the following. One, that the authority shall be granted to the secretary of the school committee to approve bills and payrolls through July and August, and that the school committee be kept informed of the bills and payrolls approved. Two, that the administration be given permission to open bids in order to proceed on repair and maintenance work and other essential procurements. Notice to the school committee will be provided.
Three, that the superintendent be authorized to conduct the normal and necessary business of the school district throughout the summer. And four, that the superintendent keep the school committee apprised of any special situations or circumstances during the summer months or that are projected to occur at the opening of schools in September. So in the past, it's been customary that the superintendent has sent us out a report on or about
August 1st to 7th. And that actually is not specified in this list. So while it says that you will give us updates, I'd like to formalize it and say that there will be a midsummer report will be sent out to the committee by the superintendent. So. I know over the years since I've been elected, we haven't had summer meetings, but if if we don't have another meeting from now, our next meeting isn't planned for late
Like September 20-something, am I correct? We were going to schedule one earlier because with the opening of school, we had talked about that once before. Right, but that's almost a three-month span. July, August, two months. Yeah, it's two. If one is necessary, we will certainly reach out and call if there's something that needs to be addressed.
I always felt like that we should meet before the opening of schools. That's just my opinion. I've always felt that. School opens without us meeting. It just never made me feel comfortable. And all business is just done without an email to us. And I just have some concerns with that. I really think that the opening of schools, I mean, we should meet before, make sure things are on track.
plan for September, make sure the coaches' meetings and the children. And if parents have questions or concerns over the summer, they can come to us. We can discuss it before school's open. There's a lot of things like school placements. There could be questions. There's a lot of things that could arise over the summer. And I just think it's a long span without meeting. So I think we obviously can stay in touch. And if you see something and you want to call a meeting, you just need three members to call the meeting.
Well, three would three would allow for a meeting. Okay. Is it possible if people are available, can we just put it in our calendars for August 1st to have it? You know, I wouldn't schedule a date yet. Everybody's going to make summer plans. You know, why don't we, if you agree that you want a summer meeting, we can agree to that and we'll get back to you and check everyone's vacation plans. But from past experience, you set a date and everyone is,
in different places. OK. So if you want a summer meeting, that's fine. But let me caucus everyone around and find out when people are available, and then we can get a date that we know people are going to be here. So can I make a motion to have a summer meeting? I do think it's important, because I do think. So motion on the floor for a summer meeting, seconded by Mr. Stone, seconded by Mr. Skerry. All those in favor? Did you want to talk on it?
My feeling about it is I've always found that sort of mid-August report really valuable. So I'm not really looking for a meeting to happen August 1st. I'd be more inclined to have a meeting the third week of August or, you know, the next week before, you know, either right prior to school or now. Of course, we start school before vacation, but I think we're saying
before Labor Day, but not necessarily midsummer. August 1st is, you know, I think it should be a little bit later than that, personally.
I just want to say that I mean I understand about the meeting and I have no problem having a meeting but to make it clear to people that even though we're not meeting just like the rest of the year is that if there's any concerns any questions any emails any phone calls or any type of anything that I know personally I get I go directly to the sources of where it's coming from and I make sure that I contact
the superintendent to make sure if there is an issue that is being addressed. So I don't want people thinking that just because even during the school year, if there happens to be a holiday in between our meetings and we don't meet, that everybody's not working. Because there's a lot of things that we do do. Yes, it's open. Yes, we need to let everybody know. But I just don't want people to think that if there's a concern out there, we're not going to address it until the next time we're in front of the camera. Thank you.
There's a motion on the floor for approval of the rules as amended by Mr. Benedetto to get a report by August 1st. Roll call vote. Can somebody direct my microphone? First week of August. First week of August for the report. Yes. Yes. Yes. Meeting. Rules. Rules. Rules. That we accepted. Give authority to the superintendent. Mr. Scarry. Yes.
Yes. Yes. All right, we have a school committee resolution be resolved with members of the school committee expressing sincere condolences to the victims' families of the tragic Orlando Terror Impact.
Also, be it resolved that the Veterans School Committee expresses sincere condolences to the family of Robert Sorabian. Mr. Sorabian was a prominent local businessman whose family operated a private coffee parlor. Mr. Sorabian was also President of Everett Boppert Bank and a strong supporter of public education.
And in regards to the Orlando tragedy, we have held a vigil last Wednesday evening. It was quite moving. The interfaith community was involved in it. And it was really quite heavy on the hearts of those that attended. Could you all rise for a moment of silence, please? Thank you. Madam Mayor, just a couple of comments, if I may.
I don't know if people fully realize this, but a statistic rolled by my desk this past weekend. And it's kind of interesting. About 49, 50 people were killed in the Orlando shooting. Since that time, there have been 207 homicides by gun violence in this country since that time. But they're isolated situations. And there's situations in which, you know, they're not getting the same coverage.
Orlando is truly tragic, but so isn't the ongoing gun violence that exists in our country. And a lot of it is based on mental health issues that people have, or just domestic disturbances, or drug deals, or other things like that that go on in society. But it often goes unnoticed. On an average day, based on the number of gun homicides in this country, 27 people die every day, on average, by guns.
27 people. It's horrific. Until we start dealing with mental health, until we start dealing with the availability of guns and things like that to individuals, we are not going to abate the situation. Terrorism is an issue and certainly to be dealt with. But there are other domestic and, let's say, personal issues that are every bit as tragic every day in our various communities.
The other comment is most people who've been around for a long time knew Bob Sarabian. Bob was just a terrific guy. I grew up on Governor's Ave in Medford. Bob lived on Hutchins Road, and the Sarabian brothers operated Carpathic Area for many, many years. George was the oldest. Bob was the second oldest, and Ron is still alive and still an active businessman. Bob was a very giving man. He worked very closely with John Hand. I don't know if you remember the name John Hand.
John Hand was the executive vice president of the Medford Cooperative Bank. And they were in arts festivals and all kinds of things that benefited the community. So Bob was a real contributor and someone that, you know, sometimes when a person hasn't been in the public light for a long time, new people in the community don't remember that individual because they weren't around when they were very active. So I thought it was important to at least tell you that Bob Sarabian was quite a player in this community and the Sarabian family as well.
Thank you, Mr. Superintendent. Also, while we're in suspension, if we could jump back to item five, appointment of the principal for Brooks Elementary School. Mr. Superintendent. Madam Mayor and members of the committee, pursuant to my consultations with the Brooks faculty and staff and the leadership of the Brooks parent groups, as well as my consultation with you last meeting, I'm very pleased and privileged to announce that Suzanne Galussi, who is with us this evening, is the new principal of the Brooks Elementary School.
Suzanne got her bachelor's degree from Framingham State, and then her master's in education from Wesley University. She has 14 excellent years of teaching experience in the elementary schools in Medford, and four very successful years as assistant principal of the Brooks School, and her appointment will be effective July 1, 2016. During the upcoming administrative week, we'll meet with Ms. Galussi and other members of the administration to determine how we will select
her assistant principal so that Brooks has that in place for the opening of school. Suzanne, the show's yours. Thank you. Thank you very much. I just want to take a minute to thank Mr. Belson, Madam Mayor, Ms. Caldwell, Ms. Nelson, and the members of the school committee for this wonderful opportunity to be the principal of the Brooks School. It is a very special night for me as a
the student of the Brooks School myself. When I look back at my elementary years, I have very fond memories. And as Mr. Bellson stated, almost 20 years as an educator in the Medford public school system, I'm truly honored. And I guess you could say I've come full circle. These past four years at the Brooks, I've really learned firsthand what a wonderful community it is at that school. Parents, families, and staff.
really come together and they embody the word community and they work together to collaborate and to educate, to support, to encourage. So I'm looking forward to what lies ahead and I'm truly honored and thank you very much. I just want to say thank you to Ms. Galluzzi.
In a way, I've kind of gotten to see you evolve, if that sounds strange. I've gotten to see her as a school teacher at the McGlynn when we first met, actually, with my middle one. And this is what I like. I like the idea of giving our people the opportunity to grow. And you have shown that you could grow.
You've had the opportunity in the last four years to be the assistant principal, and that in each and every day is, you know, it is a training, but, you know, the next step forward is what brought you here.
And being successful in that training is what brought you here. So when I came onto the school committee 11 years ago, and I know that we were looking for people, I remember a school committee member would always say to me, well, we need to make sure that they come from Medford first. And I didn't understand it. I didn't understand why that person would always say that, because I am a person who wants to give everybody the opportunity. I still want to give everybody the opportunity.
But I also want to make sure that we're taking care of our faculty here. That if we have young teachers that are willing to give their time, and they are giving their time, that we want to, on the other hand, give everyone the opportunity to grow. With that being said, again, I'm not saying that we shouldn't hire anyone from outside, but it is really nice to see that culture
you know, progress, students get to see you, people get to see you, family gets to see you, and it's not a culture shock knowing that they're going to get a new principal. And I just wanted to say congratulations to you for that. Thank you. I just want to say that I think one of the things that was very clear was that there was such an agreement when your name was brought forward.
you know, amongst the parents, amongst the faculty, and amongst the school committee members. We had, as school committee members, had the opportunity, well, in some ways to watch you grow personally, but also to have you present to us on any number of times and to see you actually working. So if you would, it was a classic no-brainer. Congratulations. Thank you very much. I really appreciate it. We wish you the best. Thank you. Thank you.
Is there a motion on the floor to? All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion is granted. Public hearing, school year 2016-2017, which is the fiscal year 2017 school budget.
You have in your packet tonight some changes that I'm sure the superintendent would like to highlight before we open up for comments from the general public and your staff. Thank you, Madam Mayor and members of the committee. At our meeting on the 15th, several items were identified by the committee as being important based on their conversations with members of the administration, faculty, and public with regard to the budget that was presented to you. So I'd like to address each of those items.
you have the information in front of you and give you a little bit more information and answer any questions you have before we actually open the floor and take public comment. The math coach at the elementary level will be added and funded under Title I. Title I normally has done literacy work in recent years, but we were able to free up some dollars from that. We have a retirement in that field, and we're able to take some of the money from a higher end salary.
and also mix that with some reserve monies that come from Title I over the years that we carry over. And of course, the actual salary will be based upon the teacher's contract. The coach might come from the inside, and then a replacement salary might go for that position the person would be taking. The emphasis would be primarily given to the Roberts, Columbus,
And some at the McGlynn, at this point, we don't believe the Brooks is in much need of this particular position as the other schools that I've mentioned. Secondly, a middle school librarian will be added to Block 029. The salary will be based upon the teacher's contract, Bachelors 1, 48, 863. The position will be shared between two schools. The position will eliminate one
point five para position at 11 six nine Oh, which was a library aid. The differential will be $37,173 and will be funded through combined savings generated by leaves of absences granted in the vocational and science department. Since our meeting, some people have opted for leaves of absence and we're able to recover money again from the higher salary to the lowest salary to give us the money to fund this position. Number three,
A behavior specialist for the Columbus School was added by promoting a current paraprofessional in the SPED budget, who has recently earned the credentials to fulfill this role. This is a non-unit position. The salary would be $40,000. This is a behaviorist position. It's similar to a BCBA. It's not certified, but Kathy can explain that. We do have one already on board, and they serve the same function. They work closely with the BCBAs, and I think that will help a great deal.
The current parasalary is $21,639, so therefore, the projected savings from the mid-year retirement of a senior SPED teacher that was identified to us, the senior SPED teacher will be replaced at a lower salary consistent with the teacher's contract. This is a new retirement that came in subsequent to our meeting on Wednesday. Four, three part-time kindergarten aides will be full-time at the Roberts.
Each will move from their current salary of $7,925 to $15,850. This total increase will be $23,775. Funding for this position will be taken from the revenue projections, which is listed in the budget book. I showed you where there was a revenue surplus that we put in. And assignments will be based upon the contract provisions of the paraprofessional contract. The kindergarten money at the legislature is still up in the air. It's suspect.
The House would like it, and the Senate is not agreeing right now. I don't know what's happening to the conference committee. Pardon me? Call. Everybody call your senator. Call. We would hope they would at least extend it for another year, because when they make a decision at the tail end of a year, you don't have time to make the adjustments that you would if you knew it at the beginning of the year, that you're moving forward. That's $150,000 in that grant.
that goes south, we'd have to find $150,000. I think I can do it with other things that happen and other revenue projections, but it's not the kind of thing that you want to do because that takes away other flexibilities for things that come up during the year. But this addresses the school that everyone felt was the most in need of this. Uh, the other three principals asked for other things and this would fulfill at least what the Roberts had asked for is as it's high priority.
Number five, the teacher specialist position at the McGlynn will be absorbed by existing personnel at that school. Principal Guarino reviewed the situation after the meeting and made the decision with me. She has an attached letter. While the possibility exists for an internal shift of personnel, the principal opted to use existing faculty. I would have sent somebody over there, but she wanted to use her own faculty. Number six, clerical assignments will be reviewed during the administrative week and decisions will be made regarding the realignment of personnel
And naturally, we'll cover the most key positions. There are two clerical positions which we did not fill based on retirements of individuals. Pat and I and others will be looking at how we can move some people around in order to give coverage to those positions. And we'll go from there. Another piece that I handed you this evening was a piece with regard to the older musical instruments as surplus. We checked with the city again.
Chapter 30B sets out procedures to ensure that we obtain good value when we dispose of supplies. So we have to go through a procurement process, but we will begin that procurement process if you agree that we can do that based on our discussions last week. And we will use that money in the music department, fine arts department, primarily for the band, but if there's some other use that the committee discerns is
of higher priority, we'll certainly look at that as well. So these are the changes. I would ask that you agree with me or that you give me a substitute that you think someone should consider so that we can move forward with the public hearing. Before moving on to the budget piece, is there a motion on the floor to vote the equipment surplus? Can you speak on this? Yeah. Ms. Van de Kloot. I spoke to Pat on the way in.
and noted that in the letter that it specified to be spent on new musical equipment. And I think it would be better to deposit back to the school department to be used by the fine arts department. Some of the needs that we heard last week from the band director was not necessarily musical equipment, but there were other needs. So I just wanted to give us more leeway.
Music department? Music department is fine.
So there's one vote that we need to vote surplus back. One vote for surplus, and the second would be that we request the city council to put this into a gift account. So two separate votes. Is there a question on the vote? Ms. Cuno. Actually, I would even make it a little bit more specific from what we have heard, and that is to be utilized by the finance department.
but with the majority of it, actually, it was for the BN uniforms. It wasn't... No, it was... No. I think we can... Because it was...
Let's get the gift account set up and then we can come back and give you an idea. All right, because the portion of that was we were taking away the five, but giving them, let's say, as an example, 15, they could subsequent use the five for the transportation.
but the rest of it was for the band uniforms because that has been discussed in the past, but okay. We'll bring it back to you in any case. Second. Yes.
Yes, 70 in the affirmative, none in the negative. Motion passes. On the second resolution that we recommend that the city council consider the surplus funds to be put into the gift account to be used for the music department. So the language as amended. Is there a motion for approval? Motion for approval. Second. Seconded by Ms. Cuneo. Ho, ho, ho. Ms. Cuneo? Yes. Ms. Drexel? Yes.
So I wanted to address the budget modifications that the superintendent has given us. In my mind, the superintendent has met the concerns that the school committee seemed fairly much in unison, as different as we all are,
there was a theme and these were definitely the ones that I was most concerned about and heard others speak to as well. So I'm very, very happy to see that money has been found for these, what I consider to be necessary items. I'd like to make a motion that the school committee affirm the Medford Public Schools budget for the year 2017
with the inclusion of these budget modifications. Thank you so much. I have a few questions, so if someone has a question before me, I'm willing to yield to them first. Okay, thank you. I just want to be respectful. So going through the actual budget book and some of these changes, I just want to go over
that what I wrote down is what we got and what cuts we had to make, okay? Just so I'm clear on everything. So as far as added personnel, we added 1.5 ELL teachers, one math teacher at the high school vocational school sharing it, an adjustment counselor, a high school English teacher, a behaviorist, and I'd like to know what their credentials are.
I'm sorry? I don't know what a behavioralist is compared to an ABA. I don't know the difference. All right. So a behaviorist has got similar kinds of skill sets, but they're not as advanced in these things. But this individual is going to be taking that test fairly soon. But Kathy Medaglio is here, and she can comment on the individual who we've identified within the SPED budget.
Well, I haven't spoken to the individual yet. So a behavioral specialist would be someone who's highly trained in analyzing and intervening for children with behavioral disorders. This individual has completed a BCBA course of study, has not yet sat for the exam or received the results. There's something like a three-month delay from the time that you take
the exam and actually receive your results, so. Will that person's salary have to change once they? No, the individual will be hired as an assistant and be overseen or mentored by a BCBA in the district. Thank you. So we added the behavioralist. We also added kindergarten needs to the Robins, from part-time to full-time. A librarian for our middle schools and a math coach.
which is a lot of additions to the program. And from all the changes, I think that, I don't know if I missed anyone. So cuts that I'm aware of, things that are not in the budget any longer are two secretarial positions, three Paris-fed positions, one teacher at the Curtis, one teacher at the Roberts because of class sizes, one high school opportunities for change person,
a teacher at the McGlynn Literacy Coach for grade K. Is that? You just let Ms. Corino address it. Yeah. Right. So it was a clinical supervisor in special education. Did you say that? No. OK. No, I don't think I had that. OK. OK. I just want to make sure I have. I like lists. OK. OK, so that's my first thing, just to go over what we've had and what we haven't.
So secondly, I want to thank you for going back and looking at your budget more closely. Like I asked you to the other night and to really change things around and try to fit some of the needs that we heard the other evening. So I appreciate the effort that you made to do that and bring us forward more things that this committee felt were very important in our priorities. So, so, you know, I'm, I'm, I'm grateful for you doing that.
So I want everything and a little bit more. Everything what? That you just gave me and a little bit more, of course. Surprise. So I just wanted to let you know that I'm a little surprised about the principal at the McGlynn not needing that literacy, that person, because she said it was extremely important to her the other evening.
So I was surprised to read this. I believe her. There's a letter in here from her. But if we see throughout the year that that need is great, I would like you to keep your eyes on that. Because I know you do that throughout the year. So that's my first request. And reevaluate if necessary. And move staff if necessary. I'm sorry? Reevaluate and move staff if that becomes necessary. So I also received, as my colleagues did, an email from the Columbus
school teachers about the need of full-time kindergarten aides. Now, I know you've given us some this year, and we're making progress, but throughout this district, the needs of students coming in to kindergarten, and I see this not only in our district, but in the districts that I visit and the district that I work in. A lot of children come in with a lot of needs, and as a school committee member, I'm gonna tell you directly, like I have many, many times,
I want full-time aides in our kindergartens. I know that it's not in this year's budget, and I know that you can't afford to do it, especially with the revenue for the state. But I'm letting you know for next year, Mr. Bellson, what I would like to see in your budget, the first thing I want to hear is when you walk in the door, is that we are going to go district-wide with full-time kindergarten aides. So that's my second comment. But thank you for the ones at the Roberts for now. OK.
So I'm thrilled to see the librarian, because the librarians, like I kept saying the other night, first cut, last reinstated. So thank you for listening and hearing on that matter. And I would love to see her reaction when she found out that this was being added to her staff. Has someone told her? Does Ms. Dorsey know? You know, I don't know. I'll find out. Mr. Trotta knows, so he would be your supervisor. OK.
You know, if someone could take that picture, I would really like to see that. So that's another thing that I really want to talk to you about and thank you for. So as far as the clerical assignments, you know, we cut a lot in the past. They're really important. They work very hard. I think cuts are just making more people work harder for the same money.
So I really have a problem cutting these jobs. I think they're vital to our school community, and they're the first people that our parents reach out to before they come to us. So with that said, I'm wondering if, since you weren't able to change the PR person, if any of those duties or some of those duties can be reassigned, because if that person has time to help out that department, I would like to see that happen.
So let me try and answer that this way. Anytime I make a cut from something that I've got, most of the time, not always, there are a couple of things that I probably can reevaluate and say that wasn't a great move. But most of the time, it means that there's going to be something that's lost. But in this instance, the challenge to us is to take a look at the full fleet of clerical assistants and to reposition some people.
And it's probably highly likely that within the area of special education, Kathy's smiling out there, that, you know, there'll be some adjustment in that area and move away from something else. But every area, every area has got to be scrutinized. And from time to time, we see that maybe certain jobs can be consolidated, certain things can be shared, and we do that. If we can't do that, we'll never ever be able to balance a budget.
It'll always be add, add, add, and add later. So we have to look at that. So the challenge is to us not to ignore the good work that's done by the clerical staff, but to reposition it in such a way so that we can do the work with maybe a few less people from time to time or find that if we have to add a person, when we go back over during the summer, we'll come back and tell you we added a person and we'll find the money for it. So, but this is the beginning of a budget. This is a process.
And just as I came back this evening with these adjustments, I may come back with some more and say, we can do some more things. Or I might have to come back and say, you know, there's something that's happening to us at the state, the federal level, and we may have to pull back on something that we wanted to do. But that's the nature of budgeting. That's the nature of process. And, uh, but I hear you. It's, it's no animus towards any particular type of position or any person. It's really just simply a function of trying to find what the balances are.
So, if I could continue if that's all right. Thank you. So, I really appreciate the things you gave us. I know that PR person, and you and I don't agree on this, she's given years of service to our community and she's done excellent work. And I really appreciate her years of service and all the things she's done in our community, but the
The cost is very expensive in our budget. And I'm going to reiterate it like I did the other night. With all due respect to the person in the job, I wonder if we could not get an intern or have it handled in a different way and free up this person to do some other vital work. I don't know. But this is an expense that I don't think our schools really should be allocating funds towards just this. And it's a lot of money in our budget.
I have to voice what I think is right and that's what I'm doing. So I answered you in my opening remarks in my budget delivery that I felt it was a strong hire. I felt that the individual brought a lot to the table. 28 years of experience in the community. Significant knowledge of the networks of where people are.
The amount of coverage that we have received in the last several months is unreal. The amount of activity on the blog and on the webpage is huge. And that we've got 29 less kids going to charter schools right now. We've got significantly more youngsters coming back from other areas. And we've got a larger kindergarten enrollment. And I think a lot of it has to do with people knowing something about our school system. The other night, I happened to listen to the city council. Why I did that, I have no idea.
But I was listening to the city council. And while I was listening to the city council, I heard them talk about the lack of communication about things. They didn't know about this. And they didn't know about that. Well, the school department tells people about a lot of things going on. And maybe not everybody pays attention. But we have got a real strong public information process underway. And I want to keep it that way. And I think it's in your best interest. So it's your decision to make.
That's my recommendation. I wouldn't cut it. And I don't think it's overpaid, because I think if you take a teacher today, for 10 months, they make, a senior teacher with 11 years experience makes almost $90,000 with a master's degree. So I don't think it's an unreasonable salary. I gave you this slip a short time ago about what people paid. If you bought a house in 1964, it was $13,000. If you bought a car, it was $3,500. Your starting salary for a teacher
$6,000, starting salary for any job is $6,000 in 64. Things are different today. You want to be competitive. You've got to have good people in place. The knowledge this individual brings to the community, the knowledge, the work ethic the person brings to the community is invaluable and has my strong support. It's your decision. Can I follow up? Yes. So maybe the city council needs her help and we could split it among the city and the school department and have one PR person for both
Maybe that's something we need to look at. Oh, thank you. He just gave me the idea. I'm sorry. So just to finish, I had some specific questions about budget, but I'm taking a long time. So if someone wanted to jump in with their questions, I'll ask them at the end. Over the weekend while I was away, Lisa Evangelista, the PR person,
She shared an article that was in the Boston Globe when the Salamanders were released that made it to the Globe. So I was away, out of town, and I was notified in an email. It was just wonderful. I was so happy. I was like, oh my gosh, this article in the paper is about the Salamanders. It was just wonderful. So I mean, I think, I mean, when I first ran for office, I wanted to do my own PR. I wanted to capture every story. I wanted to get every picture. I wanted to get it out there. And I created a website.
And I couldn't do my job at work and then on the school committee and keep up with the pictures and the articles and the stories, but I wanted to. But I couldn't. I tried. So I feel like, I think I almost tried to mimic what Lisa was doing for the whole community.
It's like a job on its own. You know, when I would go home at night, and I would try to do my pictures, and do my posts, and do the article, and write it in such a way, and then it was so late, and I was making mistakes, you know, because I was trying to squeeze it in, to get the information out there on Facebook.
to share with the community, this is what our schools are doing. So it's actually, I mean, I really enjoy it because, you know, while we're at work and while we're going about our business, even on the weekend, you know, she's still working or getting those posts out there that can be shared with everybody. I mean, I just really like it, you know, and I tell her all the time, and Allison,
I just really like hearing what's going on and reading about the students and everything that's going on. It just kind of makes my weekend, you know. But I just wanted to share it. I'm sorry. Thank you. Mia, did you have a comment on this as well, on this topic in general? Yes, about the one patient. Well, Ms. Cuno is in line on other questions as well. Do you really wish to forward? I will, and I'll come back because I don't want to.
Thank you. First of all, I want to thank the superintendent, Pat Vila, to find or rearrange the money for us. As a committee, we all wanted, and we all agreed to what we wanted. And so I do thank you for that, because there's a lot of what we had all asked for here. I am looking at the middle school librarian that you've added. Now, that middle school librarian, is there going to be one in each school, or are they going to share that one? They're going to share that one. They're sharing that, but they're keeping the assistance that they have, correct?
Well, there's one assistant position that will be dropped down. But they'll have a full-time librarian and a part-time assistant, I mean, in each place. So they can have a full-time librarian for both schools and also an assistant will go between the buildings when the other librarian is gone. Oh, so the assistant is going, but the librarian? The librarian will work both buildings, but the assistant will also work both buildings. OK?
The other thing is that I know that we spoke about the kindergarten aides. It was important that we listened to what the principals of the schools wanted. And I think that gave us an insight. And I agree that we should have the full-time aides. However, I also think it's very important that we had to listen to what
the principals of those schools really needed. With that being said, now that we are giving the full-time aides to the Roberts, as always, I'd like to have some type of report. Of course, we can't have it at the beginning of the year because there would be no information. But at least by the middle of the year, end of the year, an update on how the full-time aides are working out.
Is it working out to what they were expecting? I know that there was a lot of discussion on, you know, spending more quality time and trying to teach students and trying to do certain things with our students. So I just want to make sure that that's that's what is going on, because it is, as we discussed at the meeting last week, is that even if we decided to do this now for the Roberts, it's something that we all have to look at for the district, because that is something that we all want the equality across the board with.
But we do understand the restrictions of the finances. The other thing I was looking at is even though I know the McGlynn School principal had written, the elementary school principal had written that with structure of different students now and that there's going to be less students, that maybe she will not be meeting the professionalists that she was asking for. With that, I still want to make sure that
We make sure that we are updated on that, that all our students have the ability, that they are getting the time that they need. It's not just being rushed because I do want to make sure that, you know, each school asks for something and I want to make sure that each school gets
at least what they had asked for. Again, even if it's not a full-time position, if we can look at it into, you know, a part-time position, or again, if we could look at it, if the kindergarten aid is something that's more important over there. I know I'm not- Principal's given multiple options, and we could have adjusted a teaching schedule to do that. She chose not to do that. Okay, so I just want to make sure that we're all clear on that. Let's see, there was something else I did want to ask, and that is,
As far as the HR person, I know to some of my colleagues they weren't involved with this discussion, but I do know that this discussion had been something that the previous committees were concerned with, parents were concerned with.
and administration was concerned with. And that was we were hearing from other districts that actually had positions of HR. And we kept on sitting here week after week saying, what are we going to do to get our voice out there? What are we going to do to get more of what our district is doing? What are we going to do more to have people understand and know what our students are achieving? And each and every week, we always came out with, OK, we'll try to have a subcommittee meeting. We'll try to get some articles out there. The superintendent tried to get a blog going.
It's impossible. You can't do what we're doing in a full-time capacity and still being in the positions that we're in. We don't have the capability of it. We don't have the expertise of it. And we don't have the networking of it if it was our full-time job. I know that there is discussion out there because the amount of money does seem high. I know that when we had this discussion,
I mean, how long have we had her? We've only had her now for, is it seven months? Hasn't been the full year. We added it at the half point of the year. Yeah, we've only had, that I know that the discussion was going to be, let's wait, let's give her the chance to at least put in a year.
Let's see what's going to be different in our system. Let's see what other things are going out. And I have to say, there has been articles, there has been blogs, there has been, you know, less students going to charter schools. There are less students going to middle man. Am I saying it was just the HR person? No. But what I am saying is that I think it's the combination of the work that everybody's doing together to get the word out there.
week after week we've been badgered in here saying we don't as a school committee and as a district I mean we were even accused what we had no science curriculum in the high school with the new science labs and everything that we have but we had students in here week after week receiving awards and those awards didn't come from us those awards came from the state
And I want people to know what we're doing. So, again, it's not saying let's not have her or have her. I just think that we have to do our due diligence and make sure that if we said we were going to keep at least a year to see what the ramifications were going to be, it's something that we need to do. And we all voted for that. The superintendent brought it to us. But as a committee, it was voted on. Thank you. Ms. Mastone. Yes, thanks, Mayor.
I would have asked for more if I knew in five days you would have given us those six things. But I do have a question. I don't know if it's through you. Two of my six children are inclusion classes, and they are wonderful. And it's been very beneficial for my kids. But a teacher did ask me if I knew if there is a cap to the number of children who require a para who can be in a class. So say you're in an inclusion class with 20
or 18 without an IEP, how many can you have with one parent? So it varies with regard to the type of class. A regular education class, it's in the contract with the Teachers Association. It's pretty high. So it's, you know, I'm not sure off the top of my head, but it's in the high 20s. OK. And then, you know, it would be because remember, this idea of really small class size, relatively new. OK. There were years when, you know, class sizes were 28, 29, 30, and so on and so forth.
Our class sizes are a lot lower than what people were used to. So when these contracts were written, they were written with upper 20s as being the example for regular classes. Now in special ed, it depends on the type of class. If a special ed youngster is in a classroom that's self-contained, it's one to eight. If it goes beyond that, there would be another pair required. If it's less than that, it may just simply be on the severity of the type of classroom it is. All right, so there's not any
number or specific. So, Kathy, I guess I can speak to this. It's legal. It's by regulation. My fifth grader last year was in a classroom that had a full-time parent, the lead teacher, and then a part-time parent when the child was pulled in. So, within a general education classroom, there is no legal requirement or number to limit the number of special education students who are placed in that classroom.
All of our classrooms are inclusion classrooms. We have some classrooms that are staffed with additional support because there are specific students who require that support. And those decisions are made on a very individual basis. Sometimes a student may require a one-to-one support. Sometimes it's just a second adult in the classroom. And the majority of our students don't require any additional support in the Gen Ed classroom. But that question does come up periodically.
Because within special education classrooms, there are very closely monitored class size requirements. But there is no legal class size requirement for general education classrooms. OK. So I can only talk about my Tegan's fourth grade year. So she had one full-time para who helped four students in her class. And then the para came in part-time with a student that was pulled in for certain classes. So a teacher asked me.
at the Roberts. So how many, so there's no number of like, you could have 10 kids who have, it would help to have a parent in one class with one? Theoretically you could, but I think common sense prevails. We have to look at what the needs of the students are and how all of their needs can be best met. But there are situations where there might be one student and that's a stressor. And there are other situations where there are, there could be 10 students in a classroom.
and everything's working well. So it really depends on the individual students and what their needs are, the other supports that are available. Okay, so then, I guess because this budget is all new to me, so if you come, I don't know, when you do your placements in August, so will there be maybe a possibility to be hiring more paras if a class or a grade has that many more needs?
Or like is what we have as Paris done? We have most of our paraprofessionals are in place because there are specific student needs that they are associated with. So when there's no longer a need, the positions close because there are always new positions that are emerging or needs that emerge. So it's not like you have a fifth grade classroom and automatically there's going to be a paraprofessional support in that classroom.
That would only happen if there are specific students going into that classroom who require support. So there is that potential that we could have students move into the district. We have students who are evaluated and maybe they have a re-evaluation that's taken place in September. So yes, sometimes we do need to increase staff. Thank you, Kathy. So that was part of what I attempted to express the other night.
with the elimination of positions. It's just if we left all positions in place as is, then as newly emerging needs arise, we would just continue to grow and grow, and then that wouldn't be helpful to anyone. So it's important to close and then reopen as needed. Okay. Thank you. Okay. Yes. Thanks, Mayor. I guess I just want to add one thing in that for the Paris that
are brought in from special education, that's also part of the IEP process of determining whether a particular student, what they need or how it works. So that's where it's sort of spelled out. I guess I just really wanted to say that the other night when we did our budget, I think that there was some level of frustration because obviously we had needs or desires that we thought were
essential. And I know, Mia, at some point you said, what is the point of all this? And kind of said, you know, there is a level of trust working with the superintendent. But the point of all of it was we went through the budget and we identified key areas that we believed were critical. And that there was a real purpose to that work the other night. And now you've seen the fruition of it tonight.
And I think that we're also saying and realizing, you know, again, this budget is a, you sort of set the bottom line, but there was movement with it depending on what the needs are. It's not a static document. Thank you. Mr. Benedetto. And then we do have a public hearing coming up, so wait for it. Sorry, guys. So I have some specific questions from my budget book. OK.
OK, so mostly under the grant section. Yep. OK. So I noticed that you have a health services nurse under a grant. And I know because I administer the MassHealth program at another district that if the nurse's salary is under a grant, then it's hard to bill MassHealth for service time. So I was just wondering why a nurse's salary would be under that.
We receive money from the Department of Public Health. It's a school health services grant that we have had for many years. This pays for part of the salary of one nurse. It doesn't pay the total salary. It pays a portion of that salary. So a portion of the salary is in the grant section, and a portion is in the health services section. So you can bill MassHealth for the portions? Right. We bill to both accounts, and we keep a record so that it can be audited. OK. Just checking on that.
And secondly is I see that there is a listing under grants. So what brought it to my attention is that there is a library meteor instructional teacher position under library meteor and they have a salary of $97,136. And then when you look under grants, it's under TriTech.
And I won't say the position's name, but there's another salary allocated for $17,682. So if you would combine the two, that person would make $114,828. So let me explain it so we can go right through it for you. The individual is Molly Layden. The individual has been and continues to be the person who gets the grant for the National Science Foundation for $1.2 million. And some of her salary is offset
by the grant. So once again, we take some grant money to pay a portion of the individual's salary. We list it in the grant section. We also list her in the regular budget. And her salary was approved through the negotiations with the Administrators Association in the last round of negotiations that we did.
Okay. So could you, I don't, I don't understand why we have a line item that says tri-tech because I thought tri-tech was a nonprofit entity, not through the school district. So I was just surprised to see it. And I might be dissed that I don't understand it. So that's why I'm bringing it up. So tri-tech is the organization that is a, let's say an offspring of Medford, Malden and Everett. And it is a,
It was founded initially when the technology park was being developed, was being thought about. And it's continued for that time and has brought us millions of dollars through different grants over a period of time. Dr. Cindy Fadusha was the original executive director of that particular program. When she left to take a position with the Harvard Medical School and the physicians group over there, Molly Layden moved up into that position, and Molly Layden
runs that program as well as our program. But the reality is that the program that she presented the other evening with regard to the youngsters developing applications at the middle school level was funded by the National Science Foundation. So we're allowed to charge a portion of her salary off to that foundation, to that grant. So that's the way we split it out so we can track it properly. And we audit it properly so that we can report to the feds.
I just wanted to be clear. So she's the executive director of Tritech and also an employee of the Method Public. Tritech is the recipient of the grant. So as a result, Tritech exists as a holding company, if you will, to receive the grant. And this is the grant that comes in through Tritech, through that 501c3, which allows us to then
rebuild it to this with the University of Lowell. So the other school departments that are part of TriTech are also paying a portion of her salary? No, because her portion of her salary, the part that she does for the grant, is paid for by the National Science Foundation. The rest of it is work she does for us directly. And then does she get two paychecks? Because I didn't believe that you could have two paychecks through the school district. It's a function. It's a function of
division of funding, not a function of two positions. She's a projects director, and the funding source is just like the nurse's position. It comes from two different sources. That's all. It's just paid for differently. If we didn't do that, we would be picking up the tab for lots of grants. So we use as much offset as we can, and we're allowed to charge to both the federal and the state, in some cases, and this. The same thing would be true of kindergarten aids.
Okay, which we just did because some of it's going to come from the state and some of it's going to come from us. So it's a normal procedure. It's one position, but it's a normal procedure funded with two sources. There's also another position that that's allocated the tri-tech then as well. Which one is that? In the one right above it that says, um, director teacher. Let me take a look and I'll be a little bit more tuned to that.
It's $64,296. OK. Akira Kamiya is the person who is the primary director and runner of the National Science Foundation grant. The grant comes to us. He is located in Medford. And that's his salary. And it's paid to us by the grant through the University of Massachusetts at Lowell. They're our partner in that. And that's a direct salary. And he works for us and the project.
How much do we get from that grant? So if I... It's a million two over three years. And those funds are allocated to these two people's salary and then... These two people's salaries and stipends to teachers working with students for equipment, materials, software, and give you a whole breakdown. If you go to the grants breakdown on the early part of the book, you'll see what's actually allocated to that grant and how it's broken down on a yearly basis.
So if you go to the front of the book in the section that's given to grants, you will see it. Here it is. It's page, I don't have a page number on it, but I'll. Can you see it? Federal grants. No, up in the front under the administrative section, I think he's talking about. Excuse me. Pat, go ahead. Tritec is not listed on the grants page.
Not listed on that grant page? It's not a state or federal grant. OK? OK. Thank you. So could we see a breakdown of the TRI grant at some point? Yes. I'll provide it to you. OK. That's great. Thank you. I'm just trying to learn as I go, because when I see something, I have to ask the question. No problem. So that's that. And I know I keep asking this.
is will there be any surpluses at the end of this budget? And if so, when will we get notification of how they'll be of all accounts? I mean, community schools, everything, all accounts, because this is, and I also would like to, at this point, sorry, to make a motion that when we get our budget book next year, that all accounts that the school committee's responsible for overseeing be presented at this time.
So that way we have everything at once, and it's clear to see it all. I'm going to say it again. In the last two months, we have given you every document on every outside community schools and all these things. And we can give it to you at the budget time. You asked for it earlier.
That's what I'm asking, just so that way I can see all entities at the same time. And when we vote for the budget, we have all those things, the most updated information so we can vote on it. That's all I'm changing is, you know, maybe we can arrange it so the quarterly report falls at that time. But I'd like to see the after school, the lunch program, all of the programs that I was listing before. Anything that the school committee oversees at that point.
Any money's going in or out, and any accounts that could have a deficit or a surplus, we should know at this time. That's all. I just would like it in that format. So I'm making a motion for that to happen, and I'm hoping that one of my colleagues will second that. I'll second. Could you repeat the motion? That all the extemporaneous accounts that go to schools, such as the Revolving and the Community Schools accounts, she wants to see the summary with this budget. But does that mean? So there would have to be a projection cut.
Does that mean you're not going to be asking for these reports every single week? No, they're quarterly, and then at budget time. So we would only be getting them at quarterly time, and then at budget time. Correct. So that means the last two months prior to budget, our administration isn't going to be running around trying to get more reports. No, we'd have the nine months we're doing here, and then again at the budget time. Point of clarification, please. Point of clarification?
As a school committee member, if I have a concern at any time, I feel it is my right to ask the superintendent to provide me paperwork to clarify any questions I have. So it could be at any time. But, right. I'm going to say it very clearly. Okay. And I want to make it very clear to everyone here. A report asked by an individual member is not a report that superintendent responds to.
A report voted by the school committee is a report that the superintendent will respond to. I cannot and my staff cannot keep doing individual reports every time somebody wants something different. It takes a lot of time. Pat worked overtime and overtime to get those reports to you at that point in time. And I think it's disingenuous, quite frankly, to keep asking for the same thing.
You want it at budget time next year, you can have it. The committee voted to get it quarterly, we'll do it. But let's not keep creating these kinds of report situations, because all it does is take us off what we're trying to do for the education of the kids.
Just to clarify it, that's what I'm trying to find out. We are a committee. We all have the right to ask the questions. We all have the right to be concerned. But this committee is a committee. And if we're going to be asking for reports, then I think we have to ask them as a committee. I don't think it could just be done every single time someone decides to ask. Right.
So that's what I want to make sure. I want to make sure that if we're going to be working on a budget next year, I want to make sure that the administration is putting in their time, making sure that we all get the information. I think it would make more sense if the fourth quarter, is it the third quarter, would be part, would be the budget report. So you're not preparing five, you're doing quarterly reports, and one of them is with the budget.
I see, okay. Yes, thank you. Right, and it's more, to clarify what I want, it's more accurate towards the end of the year, what's left in those accounts, what's not left, if we need to allocate more funding to that,
you know, we can use more funds for next year. And the other thing you need to keep in mind is just what we're talking about state and federal grants. We don't have the allocations yet. So I can't tell you what that account is going to look like going forward. I can only tell you what it's been in a given year because the state budget isn't even approved yet.
And the federal budget won't get delivered to us until the summer. And all that stuff has something to do with the way we allocate money. We have to use projections all year long to see what's coming in and to balance one account off against the other. So, yes, we can give you projections. Yes, we can give you, you know, revolving accounts at a point in time, as a snapshot in time, like the end of the third quarter going into budget, which would be typical. But to give you a projection, what's going to be true in August are going to be true in September.
is all speculation. No. We have a public hearing. I'll now open it up to the general public. This is a public hearing. If you have any comments on the budget that was presented Wednesday as adjusted this evening through the reports of the superintendent, please come forward. Name and address, please. Maria Skippington. We're from Roberts Elementary, 74 Autumn Street, Malden.
I wanted to, not asking you for anything else, I just wanted to, we wanted to thank Mr. Belson, Madam Mayor, and the school committee for hearing us and for supporting us with something that we really felt was a very important initiative, so thank you. Amanda Gass, Roberts Elementary, 101 Aberdeen, Cambridge. I second Maria's sentiment and
Thank you very much for hearing us. Many of you came and visited our classrooms. We really appreciate the support. I wanted to ask a clarifying question. So are the full-time aides for the Roberts dependent on the state budget, or are they guaranteed? That's my first. No, we put them in the budget. OK. And my second question was the original proposal that we saw last week.
There were district-wide, and I'm sorry, I am asking for other things. There were district-wide full-time K-AIDS dependent on the state budget. Is that still in place, or are those gone? There are three additional full-time AIDS at the Roberts. That's the addition. Everything else stays in place. Stays in place. So if the state budget comes through with the kindergarten grant, you're still matching it
fund full-time aides for the rest of the school? At this point in time, no. Just the Roberts. Just the Roberts.
If you were still there, I'm sorry. If you were still there is that we felt that it was important to listen to also the principals of each and every individual school. So when we heard their requests and what they were really looking for, even though we were all going to look for the full-time aides, we were also told that there were different things in their schools that they needed. With that being said, we've also made it very clear this evening that we want to make sure that down the road and in our next budget year,
If we're going to be doing this, we want to make sure that it is our wish as a committee to have that across the board. Yes. And I would like to welcome you into our classrooms for next year. Anytime I can. To see, you know, we have a very diverse population and the aides are an integral part in differentiating instruction for that. But that being said, I would also encourage you to reach out to
And I know some K teachers have reached out to you at the other schools, because while we are the only level three school in the district, and we do need this, absolutely, and I am a proponent for our school, I also can't in good conscience say that this is not a district-wide issue, and you should go and visit other classrooms as well.
And again, I thank you for your support for this issue across the district. This is fun. Thanks very much. Thank you. There was a motion.
Is there anyone else that would like to speak in support or in opposition to the budget this evening? Hearing saying none, we'll move that motion to the hearing. There was a motion on the floor earlier by Ms. Vanden Heuvel for approval of the budget, seconded by Ms. Cuno. Roll call vote, Mr. Skerry. Ms. Cuno. Yes. Ms. Vanden Heuvel. No. Ms. Kretz. Ms. Kretz. On the budget. The budget. To approve the budget.
So I want to make another statement about something. Tomorrow night, I go to the city council. This is the school committee budget. I expect that the school committee supports its own budget because when I go to that
council, I don't want to go in there and find that the budget that the school committee voted is not approved and not supported by the school committee. So I want to make that very clear. That's very strong. In my opinion, you vote as a committee, you stand as a committee, the superintendent represents you as a committee.
So given the adjustments that were made, I'm not quite sure why my colleagues now have voted against it, the two that did. And I, too, was looking for unity because that is what we want to go into and support. I do understand that people might have preferences, and I'm sure, for example, that many of my colleagues would, in fact, like to have
said we're going to do kindergarten aides across the city all at once. This is a very large budget with many other things, very important things to us. We've added an English teacher. We've added lots of different elements. I think that the committee has spoken and said, yes, there is a desire in the future to add that we're starting out with the Roberts. It's a level three school.
justification for why we're starting in this particular school. I hasten to remind everybody that when we get to kindergarten aids, the money, the dollars seem short, but the obligation of the city in terms of the additional finances for healthcare are significant.
So I think that the beginnings of this budget and on that particular issue have been addressed, and it's clearly been heard that there is a desire to increase as we go on. So I share with the superintendent frustration. I know the other night,
I had hoped to have a unified budget, and there were some levels of consternation because there were so many things that weren't clear, and tonight we've now clarified those in, I think, a very, very positive manner.
I for one would ask my colleagues to reconsider their vote, and I would like to have a discussion and see, because I'm not quite sure if that's the only issue that's outstanding, and I'm not understanding something else for that negative vote by my colleagues, that I would urge you to reconsider, because a budget is a huge
Entity, it is not a one issue question. We are here for the good of all of our students, whether they're in kindergarten or whether they're in a high school senior. Every student is important. And to hold up that unity on a budget because of one issue, especially when so much progress has been made, I believe is not in the best interest of the public schools and the children and families we serve.
It's my it's my first, you know, meeting being on the school committee listening to the budget. I sat in last year. I'm just really confused why why it wasn't agreed by my two colleagues. I guess I'd like to hear more on why they disagree with the budget, because I I mean, I felt the revisions were everything that was asked for.
you know, I'm confused why, I guess I'm just confused why it wasn't approved now, you know, because that's what we agreed on and then the add-ins were added. So I guess I would like to know a little bit more as to why there's a, they're not approving it. I guess that's my question.
I agree with my two colleagues that have just spoken. I mean, we sat the other night and we dissected everything that we wanted to dissect, and we went item by item. And at the end of the night, I know that
It was in the minutes I had asked, is this the list that we're all looking for? Are we looking for the kindergarten aides? Are we looking for math coaches? Are we looking in everything? And when we left there that evening, we said we wanted, it would have been good, or we would like to have the kindergarten aides across the board. But we also took out of respect for the principals that came up and spoke to us what their wish list was. Did they say that they didn't want kindergarten aides? Absolutely not.
But they also said, if push comes to shove, and I really need something that I need and truly need in my school at this moment, they told us what they wanted. We sat there. We tried to make everyone happy. We even left before the meeting was over saying that if we decided to do it this year for the Roberts, it was out of consideration. It is something that they've been asking for for the last couple of years, that they are a Title I school because of the situation of where they landed, you know, a couple of points off. And we said,
Of course, and we knew, I mean, that evening, it's, again, on the minutes, on the tape, we knew that the second we were going to do this, we were going to have other schools say to us, hey, don't forget about us, we want the kindergarten needs, too. It's something that we've said across the board. We even said it this evening. I said it this evening before we even voted. We have not forgotten about the other schools, but we want to make sure that we also listen and hear, we're not the people in those schools. We're not there every day.
And we need to have some type of respect and communication with the people that are there. So going to the city council in this type of vote, to me, just shows that we are not a unity. We are not working as a committee. And it's a shame, because I don't know about anybody else, but whether we approved, disapproved, whether we agreed or disagreed,
with previous or even with our own committee here, by the end of the day, it wasn't about being in camera, it wasn't about politics, it wasn't about anyone. It was about what this district needed. And honestly, I'm really confused because I thought the superintendent has done a great job with the financial director in getting us what we can at this point, especially when we're looking at a budget from the state that we don't even know what we're going to have.
And do we want to be in a situation right now that we're going to say, sure, we'll give everyone kindergarten eds. We'll give everybody everything they want. And then come October, when we don't have the money, and all of a sudden, we're giving half of our faculty pink slips because we're not going to have teachers in the system. These are things we need to look at. And so, yes, am I frustrated? Very much so. Thank you. Ms. Martin.
Thank you. Jean Martin, 10 Cummings Street. And I was going to keep my mouth shut. I really was. The council does vote, and they don't always agree either, OK? They have a two to five split vote. They can do that. That's their right. I do respect the councilors who vote in the minority who explain why they vote in the minority. But it is their right to vote into the minority. And that's their right.
And it's the same way with the Supreme Court. They have split votes, too. So I understand that you want to go in with the United Front, but it's not obligated. They're not obligated. They can have a minority vote. So I just wanted to put that out there. And you will be respected more.
if you explain why, I agree with you. Because those that explain why they vote in the minority, when I'm at home, or actually not home, I'm here all the time, but when I listen to it, I have respect for that person because they gave me the explanation. So I just wanted to say that. And it's, but, so, well, just to add to that, you don't have to put pressure on the people that voted in the minority
If that's their choice, they don't have to explain it either. That's their choice. But they will be perceived as having an ulterior motive if they don't explain it. Thank you. Madam Mayor, I wouldn't want anyone to think that we couldn't vote, certainly as we did. And it's just that, quite honestly, I was surprised. I want to make it clear, by the way, that there have been years where I have voted against the budget because I was concerned
that the entire budget level was short, and that we were not meeting the needs of our students. So please understand that it's not, that I've never, that I've always been in agreement with the bottom line, but that's really the issue. In some ways, it's the ultimate bottom line. I didn't understand why my colleagues voted against it, and that's why I said what I said. I am wondering, since the superintendent has made a statement sort of saying, geez, I'd rather go in with a unified force,
whether there was a point in my asking for reconsideration so that we could vote it again if any colleague had a feeling that they were persuaded for some sense of unity. But if there's not, then I respect your votes, and I'm not going to bother for a reconsideration.
So I was just trying to sort of feel out whether either of my colleagues who voted against the budget wanted to reconsider their thoughts. If you're willing. But you don't have to. Pretty much, I think everyone knows, during the campaign I held two town meetings at the library and at the South Bedford Fire Station community room.
There were parents from McGlynn and the Roberts and the Columbus that all spoke about the need for kindergarten aides. I have said it throughout this year that it's district-wide. It's a need. I understand the principals have their own priorities, but I think I'm here for the parents and the students, and that priority is for district-wide kindergarten aides. So that's why I'm not. And you somehow managed to find $500,000 in five days. I have, I guess, this. It wasn't five days.
200, whatever it added up to, then I have faith that you can find more. So, Madam Mayor, can I just want to say one thing. My comment was not that people can't vote against the budget. Majority rules. It's 5-2. It's a vote for the budget. It's fine. I've been in enough meetings in the course of my career to know that they don't always get a unanimous vote for things.
So that's not the issue. The issue I raised is when I go to the council tomorrow night, I want the committee to honor the fact that the committee voted. And I said that before, when I was talking about reports, I don't want to go to the council and find that individual members go there and argue against the budget. That's what I'm saying, because the budget is what this committee voted up or down.
You're a committee, you're not individuals. You've been told many times that as an individual you have no authority. It's only when you're in session and as a group that you have authority to act on behalf of the city and the school system. And so all I'm trying to do is make it clear that I don't want to go in there with a divided camp tomorrow night and find that people will argue against me from my own committee because you voted this budget by majority. And you could have voted the other way.
Or you could have voted for anything else you wanted. But you voted it. Up or down, whether you're on the majority side or the minority side, it is the school committee budget. And that's what the superintendent will represent tomorrow night. And if I'm asked about other people's opinions, I will say the school committee voted this budget. I just want to make that clear. That's why I said what I said. I don't have a problem with dissent. People want to dissent, that's business. I understand that.
Thank you. I respect your asking me, but throughout this evening I've raised concerns that I've had with this budget. I think direct services to children are my main priority, and I saw areas that allocations could be made towards that that weren't. And based on what I
I have to vote what I feel is best, both for myself and for the students within our community. So I do understand your want and need for us to be all together, but just because I don't vote in the exact same way with you doesn't mean that I don't respect your decision and why you vote, and I hope you feel the same way with mine.
and as well as my other committee members. I honestly really think about these choices and I know that we usually do a whole committee votes yes on the budget and moves forward. And I know this is different for me personally as a committee member, but this is what I feel is necessary for me to vote.
at this time, and I've given multiple reasons. And if you want me to go over them all again, I can. But I'm sure you don't. So, like, you want me to give you the list? Three paraprofessionals. Erin, you do not need to do that. To my colleagues. No, no. Three members asked me to explain why. And I really feel like I do that throughout the meeting.
And I don't mean to be any disrespect. I do appreciate the things that were added back in. And I really thank the superintendent and his staff for going back and reallocating funds so that way we were able to add things tonight.
But my vote is my vote, and I feel like it's what I have, and that's what I've done. So, Madam Mayor, just to conclude the discussion, then, I certainly want to express to my two colleagues that I appreciate their due diligence, and I respect their votes, even if I disagree with it and would have preferred it a different way. However, even though, Erin, you've asked many questions, and I can know some of your areas of concern, I still was surprised, because I thought we were more on the same page.
Now that you've articulated exactly where you're coming from, I appreciate it, I understand it, and I now understand the vote better. So thank you and we'll, if we could, did we call the vote? No. We already called the vote. Called the vote.
I just want to say, everyone has the right to do what they want to vote, and it wasn't about the vote. It was about the clarification of where we came from the other night. If we had discussed and there were members that were concerned about, I'm not going to approve this.
without having kindergarten across the board, at least we would have known a little bit better of where we stood tonight. If we had members that were concerned, and I'm not putting down anyone's concern. Everyone has the right to concern. But as a committee, when we discussed it the other night, and that's why the surprise tonight, if I had known that I was going to come in here,
saying that this budget wasn't going to be, you know, I even think the superintendent would have known if he had known saying, nope, no kindergarten aides, we're not going to pass it. I think we would have at least had a little bit of an awareness. Exactly. Exactly. Right. So that was the reason. That's fine.
We may come up. Yes. We may come back up if you take votes.