Okay, so do we have a quorum? We do. There's four of us here. It's Joe, Charlotte, and myself, and you. Okay, terrific. Okay, terrific. And has Mrs. Levine called in? Not that we've seen. Okay. Yeah, she's probably has the same problem I had.
I just gave her the number and not the meeting ID. Anyway, so did everyone get the 2 meeting minutes that I set out? Yes. Charlotte? Yes. Joe? Yes.
Okay, and Fred, you got that right? Yes. Okay, can I have a vote to accept both minutes? Sorry, a motion. I make a motion. Go ahead, Joe. Okay, I'll make the motion to go ahead and accept them. Okay, second. I second. Okay, terrific. Okay.
So, we need to take a roll call Charlotte. Yes. Bread yes. Go yes. And I vote yes. So, the meeting is that the minutes are approved now there's another there's another. There's a lady who I talked to today.
about work on our house at 20 Hillside. Do we want to talk about that now or do we want to wait till the next meeting? Well, if we haven't seen an application, we don't know what the nature of the work is. I would say- She told me and see if you think this description is adequate. He wants to put in aluminum gutters,
and she wants to cover the space under her porch with cedar shingles. Is that an adequate description for us? Where would the space under the porch be? Is it a wall? A wall under the porch? I'd probably look at the property.
So why don't we postpone this to our next meeting? Yeah, I think if she could get the work, then we can approve. Doesn't sound too complicated. We could approve the minutes anyway. So we should be considering it. Yeah. Anyhow. Okay. Sorry for this Nafu in communication.
Oh, there's another snafu. Yeah. It's actually going to take several days to produce the pamphlets. Okay. And that plus mailing time, et cetera, is cutting it too close for an October 12th meeting. Because they need to receive it 15 days in advance.
So this is my screw up, I should have had them printed weeks ago or months ago. So I apologize for that. But unfortunately, we need to postpone the public hearing. Okay, so now we're looking at November 15th, November 9. Okay, as far as I know, that's Charlotte.
November 9th, right? November 9th. Can you make it to November 9th? Sure. What day does that fall on? It's a Thursday. It's a regular November. Okay. I'm okay on a Thursday. Okay. Joe, can you make it? Yeah. Yeah. No problem. Sounds good. 6 p.m. Okay. 6 p.m. Okay. Yeah. In the big, it's an in-person meeting and it will be in the big city council chamber. Yeah.
Okay. Okay, sorry, sorry about the screw up. I should have. No, no problem at all. Yeah, yeah. I've got a couple quick things. Okay, everybody. Chris, I'm sorry. Yeah, what's that? I talked to Chris Donovan, I didn't, I texted with Chris, but it sounds like he is looking to resign from the commission. So I think we're gonna have to be looking for some new members here. So I'd like to put that up. Absolutely.
Okay. And then the second thing is... That's not surprising. Yeah, I'm not surprised. I'm disappointed. Where are the... Where can I find the recordings of our historic... these Zoom calls? Where are those located? Ask Dennis. Dennis is on top of all that. Or I can send it to you this evening.
Yeah, if you could send me a link to it. I was looking for him, I couldn't find him. I can totally do that. Okay, excellent. Okay, that was it. Oh, but I had a question for you as your design person. Should we have the background of the pamphlet be just white? Or should we choose some neutral color, like beige or gray?
You usually don't see pamphlets that are all white, except for the print and the photos. I'll leave that up to you. Yeah, it should be starting light, not attention-grabbing, maybe it's gray or orange or something. Yeah, no. I'm not going to choose forest and orange. Okay. All right. Thank you, everybody.
Can I make a motion to adjourn? I make a motion to adjourn the meeting. I second the motion. Okay. Charlotte? I second it. I approve. Okay. Yeah. Joe? I think Joe left already. Oh, he left already. Okay. Meeting adjourned. Thank you, everybody.