Welcome, welcome, trick or treat, shut the door, have a seat, come on in and rest your feet and sit here on the throne. Come on in, take a seat, and let's watch the fourth Mustang report. Good morning Medford Mustangs, this is Dr. Perella here to say happy Halloween, have a safe- Excuse me.
This is Dr. Pirelli here. I hope everyone has a really nice, healthy, and safe Halloween. I'm a dragon. I'm codename Charlie from Top Gun and Firetongue USA.
My name is T-Bo, that's Terrence Jeter Bo, T-Bo. I'm a Taurus. I'm a softball player. Napoleon without the coat. Captain America. A leopard. I'm a ladybug. I'm a Power Ranger.
I'm Ariana Grande. I'm a holy cow. I am a blend of the Mass Hatter and having a history presentation on Halloween. I'm a nurse. I'm a boy. I'm a tourist. I'm a green M&M. I'm the lady. I'm a comic book character. I'm a cop. She's Robert. I'm an alien. I'm a crayon. I'm one of the three blind mice. I'm a Power Ranger.
I'm trying to find my sisters at the library. Oh, they were over here. It's this way. Stop! It's that way. Which way? This way. I'll take you. Hi, I'm Miss She-Helm. Happy Halloween.
Growing up in high school, I used to play tennis, soccer, and basketball. And I actually didn't start volleyball later on until college. The question of the week is, what is one of my most valuable possessions? What college did you go to, and how did you decide to go there? So I went to, for my undergraduate, I went to Salem State. And then for my graduate degree, I went to Middlebury.
So I went to UMass Amherst. It was one of the greatest experiences of my life, I would have to say. I went to Westfield State University. I attended Bowdoin College in Brunswick, Maine. I went to Ithaca College in upstate New York.
I went to Union College in Schenectady, New York. And for graduate school, I went to Boston University in Boston. I went to the University of Southern California, USC Trojans. I went to Northeastern University in Boston for undergraduate, and I got my master's there as well. I went to Bridgewater State University. It's down south shore.
I went to Bridgewater State College. For undergrad college, I went to Washington University in St. Louis, Missouri. I went to UMass Amherst for my undergraduate and graduate degrees and had a wonderful experience there. I earned a bachelor's degree in English and journalism and a master's degree in education.
it was great because you actually playing a fall sport you get to go on the earlier side so you would you come I think about two weeks earlier than the first day of school. And what was your favorite memory and experience about Bridgewater State? My favorite memory was winning the intramural family feud. I am the champion. They called it Spanish boot camp. I actually didn't speak any English at all. They actually have
a slogan which is called No English Spoken Here. It just felt like home the second I stepped on the beautiful campus. It had a number of the courses I wanted to take, areas of interest. It wasn't too big, it wasn't too small. One thing that stood out is that I performed in the marching band at UMass Amherst. So I had the opportunity to go down when George W. Bush was inaugurated as president. I had the opportunity to perform at the inauguration with the UMass marching band.
My favorite personal memory was I got to be a seat filler at the Oscar Awards, because the Oscars were shot about a block from where I was living. I had some wonderful co-op jobs, so I got to travel around the country and meet a lot of people. That was the highlight. I also met my husband at Northeastern. I can happily say that on the football field, I never lost to Mr. Nascimento or any of the Tufts Jumbos. I met my wife.
Were you involved in any clubs at the school? So I tried a number of activities while I was at school. I was in a choir. I worked at a TV station on campus. I did volunteer work with incoming freshmen. What advice do you have for students applying to college and going to college this fall? I've been talking to a lot of seniors and there's this idea that you need to know exactly what you want to do before you go to college.
And I don't think that's correct. I think actually college takes place to explore what's out there, to understand what you want to do. When you're going through your applying stage, please tour your colleges. You definitely want to make sure that you get your good feel for this campus that you're going to. But once you're at school, make sure that you get involved. I would say do your research. Pick your schools wisely. But number one, don't stress about it. It'll sort itself out.
So I think there are three questions you need to ask yourself when you're applying to college. First, do you want an urban or a rural setting? Secondly, do you want a large setting or a small setting? And thirdly, how far away are you willing to go? Apply and go. You should. You'll make more money than if you don't. And my advice is to not do any classes before 9 or 10 o'clock in the morning.
welcome welcome trick or treat shut the door have a seat come on in and rest your feet and sit here on the throne nice to meet you i'm your host hope you're not afraid of ghosts