Good afternoon, everyone. Bob and Ben, I just want to thank you for helping me out last month while I was in sunny Florida. So I couldn't make the meeting. I just couldn't do it. Even by Zoom, I couldn't do it. So if everyone else will just indulge us, we need to do a little housekeeping first. We need to review the minutes of last month's meeting and just kind of give them the once over.
I need a motion to approve them. So I have looked at them. There was only one item on it that I had a question on, and it's probably because.
I wasn't here to hear the nuances of it, but I noticed that it's on the agenda again. It's about hearings information being submitted to Daria on the Friday before, so she's not under the gun putting things in the last minute. So I guess we can talk about that after we handle our two items on the agenda.
Bobby, Ben, one of you, since I wasn't here, one of you want to make a motion to approve the minutes and we can get that off the table? Yeah. Bob, do you want to? I've read it. Yes. I'll make a motion to approve the minutes of the 20th License Commission meeting. Everything looks fine. Make the motion to approve. Very good. Thank you, Bobby.
Yeah, I read it. I'll second it. Ben, you want to second it? Yeah, yeah. And also, Daria, thanks. It's actually kind of a tedious one. There's a lot of information there, all those dates. And thanks for doing that. It looks good. Very accurate. Yeah. Daria, thank you very much. OK. Thank you for the second. Ben, all in favor of approving the minutes, say aye. Aye. Done. So we'll take that off the table.
As I was saying, what I wanted to do when I was looking at the agenda, let me see here, I'm sorry.
I got them on my other screen. So we'll, we've taken, we've knocked off the minutes. And then the second item says to discuss and vote on the deadline proposal brought forth by, let's shove that to the end. Let's take care of the two, you know, event them and 25 Salem Street LLC. Let's take care of that. Brian, we're gonna start with you. You always seem to have all your ducks in a row. I looked at the package.
Again, we're very familiar with you and your events, your establishment. You've been doing great since the day you opened. No incidents, no problems. Keep up the good work. But tell us about what this event's all about, please. So Myth, in 2023, we are hosting the Friends of Bedford Family Network here. It'll be, I think, the third time that they've been here. And essentially, it's
It's an opportunity for local families to get together and raising opportunities as well for that organization, which supports the family network here in the area. So yeah, we love having them. People play games. They kind of hang out, do music. There's a lot of people involved, and also kids and family and adults. And the adults have a few benefits if it's available.
offer to apply for the application for it. Very good. Very good. I see beer and wine, your estimated number of guests of 50, three to seven. I don't know if anything else, Bobby, Ben, anything in there that caught your eye? Brian's always been good. He provides us with a diagram so we know where the beer and wine will be stored.
I don't know, I don't have any questions. Everything looked fine to me, Mr. Chairman. Brian always does a great job. Nice diagram and layout. We know he's got insurance on file and never any issues there, so I don't have a problem with it. Yeah, yeah, no.
I agree. Is it open to the public or is it a private event? It is, but they do sell some tickets in advance. They don't want to necessarily turn people away, but they want to give people the opportunity to be able to lock in a spot. Yeah, cool, cool.
Yeah, good. No, just curious about how that worked. And no, everything looks good to me. And so I would approve this. We're good with this. Yeah, yeah. One of the two of you make a motion, and let's get this one off the table. Yeah, Mr. Commissioner, I'll do that. Mr. Chairman, I mean.
So I'll make a motion to approve the application for a one-day license. This is for Event Them. This is for an event on Sunday, May 5th from the hours of 3 p.m. to 7 p.m. as presented by Brian, owner of Event Them. Yeah, make a motion to accept this one day. Okay.
I'll second the motion. Very good. Thank you, Ben. Thank you, Bobby, for that. Yeah, no, three to seven, May 5th, Sunday, 50 estimated guests. Thank you for the motion. All in favor of approving the one day for event them, say aye. Aye. Very good. You're all set, Brian. Thank you very much for coming and joining us this afternoon. Good luck with the event. I hope you have more than 50 people.
Welcome back, Alan. You guys have a great afternoon. All right. Thank you. Good luck. Second item is 25 Salem Street LLC. Attorney Farnsworth, how are you? Barry, I hope you're enjoying Ireland. I certainly am, sir. How are you? Very well, and yourself?
All good. Thank you. All good. So so tell us about this. Attorney Farnsworth or Barry, tell us that, you know, we've been hearing about this for like over a year and oh, it's an Irish pub. No, it's not an Irish pub. It's it's.
There is no food. There is food. I know you're not supposed to believe in rumors, but this is all we kept hearing for quite a while. So we see the ABCC application. We've looked at the diagram, the drawings, the menu. I can't wait. But Attorney Farnsworth or Barry, do you want to give us a good overview of what the city of Medford can expect from you guys with this new establishment?
Sure, Trish, I can take that. Yeah, I was going to say, go ahead. Yeah, so it's roughly a 65 seater, I'm not sure exactly what it is, but it's circa that. Restaurant, I would say, that has about, I think it's a 15 person bar. There is a little outdoor patio area at the back that we hope to get open at the same time.
It would be a traditional Irish bar, but as far as an Irish bar is in America, it's somewhat different in Ireland. And that's exactly where I am now. And as Trish said, I'm doing some research. I want to make it as authentic as possible. And I hope for an opening date circa August, I hope. August of this year, right? August of this year? Yes, sir. Okay. Yes.
That would be great. Yeah, that would be great. Yeah, I think, you know, when I looked at that site, I liked its visibility. I liked the size of it because I swore I wasn't going to do another big one and I won't. On top of which, you know, I knew Tacuba and the owner managers of that property and I knew they were going to do something great beside me. So I think
I think they'll be a good fit for each other. I know he's very much looking forward to it opening as well.
Yeah, yeah, a little diversity in the square. It's all good. I'm looking at the application. The 356 square foot patio outside, I didn't even know there was an outside in the back there. Nobody does. I've lived in Medford all my life. I don't know. Bobby, did you know anything was in the middle there in the back? I had no clue. Yeah, I knew there was an alley there. I think something might have came up with Takuba about,
They wouldn't allow them to transport food between the two restaurants, that and the one on the Riverside Ave, you know? That makes sense. Yeah. So I see. I didn't think there was that much room though. I didn't either. I didn't either. And so two stories from what I see, seating capacity 85, is that still the number you're shooting for? Because I think you'd sell a little less or you would just, you know, just a small patio.
Including the patio, 85 would be very close. I see. But it's really just one story, right? And just the basement is the storage, right? And the prep kitchen downstairs, yes. Yeah, yeah. But yeah. OK. I'm sorry. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, I'm looking at the plans. Yeah.
The downstairs storage would have alcohol refrigeration or alcohol storage. That would be one of the rooms that are listed? Yeah. Correct. Yeah, there's a walk-in refrigeration downstairs for that.
Yeah, got it. And just to remind my two fellow commissioners, not only is this an application for a license, a new license, but pledge of collateral, right? So it's also a pledge in there. Yeah, we do need to pledge where the whole build out, as you can imagine, is a significant investment.
And so Northern Bank and Trust have agreed to do that loan. But obviously, the requirement is that the license is pledged to them. Oh, yeah. Being a banker for 42 years with 20 fines worth, I get it. It makes sense. Yeah, it does make sense. Can I ask a question? So where is this in? You know, this is great. It's very exciting, by the way. I just think it's awesome. Thank you. And does this mean the Ford has been a success for you?
so far? Yes, the forge has gotten busier and busier as the longer it's there in truth and you know I had focused, I began to focus my attention on the Irish bar about nine months ago but we still had some work to do so I continued my focus on the forge and we're in a good place there and I feel that Medford Square in particular is ready for something new and something a little bit more, a little simpler so to speak and
Yeah, my attention won't be ever taken away from the board, that's to be very clear. Yeah, just more curious and I have to say, I don't look at it, but I'm actually really excited. I was really happy to see this come in because I'm a resident and I complain to my wife all the time, there's nothing to eat in the square.
Or there's now like a couple of things and how it's to do to go. Anyway, so I think it's great. But all personal opinion aside. So is this is this as far as like a build a buildout? Is this submitted like, you know, for a building permit yet? Or is that is that sort of in the works? Yeah. Yeah, it's already been granted. In truth, they've started demolition. They started it about six months ago. They've done first fix on plumbing and electrics.
and a few other bits and pieces, but until I get the funding released by the bank, I can't do any further work. Okay, but it's already in progress, so you just need your funds in place and this project can continue. Yeah, my contractor is ready to go. Trish Farnsworth has done what she needs to do in relation to the ABCC.
So, I mean, once the ABCC comes through, my builders will do what they're supposed to do. And that's why when I say I'd hope to open it in August sometime, I think it's realistic. Nice. Nice. I'm scanning through, Bobby. You scan through the package. I see the note. I see Corey. I see passports.
I don't see any. Sage is on the call too. So she's going to be the manager. Yes. I do want to hear from Ms. McCoy also. We're just kind of going through the, I'm going through the package here. I see a note with Northern Bank. Is she a minority owner? Is Sage one of them? Okay. Not yet. Okay. But there are a few, right? There are a few.
I have some investors. So yeah. Yes. Yeah. Yeah. It's okay. Okay. Yeah. I see that. I see the lease with Mr. Costa. I have some questions, Mr. Chairman. Sure. Sure. Go right ahead. I'm still scanning through the package. Yeah. We're with, um,
I spent some time on it and I had a few questions. One of them being, well, you already spoke about the pledge. There's no pledge paperwork here. There should be, let's see, application for amendment pledge of collateral.
It's all in the application. Yeah. It's question on the new license application, it's question I can tell you. Question number nine on page four of the application, that's where it is. And then you also check off pledge, I think on the monetary transmittal form. Yes, you do. Pledge of collateral and new license.
Yes, I saw you. I'm sorry. Yeah, I think I saw the pledge in the second. You know how the package was pretty large and Daria broke it into two packages? So I think that's in the second package, at least with mine. I didn't see any pledge paperwork at all.
I can see number nine, pledge information. Okay, yeah, there's a $711,000 promissory note and there's also a license pledge agreement, both Northern Bank.
Right, I saw that as well. But the actual paperwork from the ABCC, it's four pages that you're supposed to apply for a pledge. And that's not filled out. None of those four pages are with this application. Yeah, that's separate. I think that's if you're just applying for a pledge separately. This is well, you can do that. But
You're going to it's going to cost you another 200 dollars. If you do it all on this application, it doesn't cost any more. You only pay 1 fee of 200 dollars.
And the documents that I'm looking for is the monetary transmittal form, which is the cover page for the application for amendment pledge of collateral. Then there's a second page, which is also state application for amendment pledge of collateral. That's where you select either the pledge, the license, the stock or the inventory.
Then you need to fill out an applicant statement again, which you already have when filled out with this new license. You will also have to have an entity vote, which has the following transactions need to be checked off. Pledge of license, pledge of insurance, pledge of inventory rather, and pledge of stock. None of those documents are attached to this.
Yeah, because they're all part of the application for new license commissioner that amendment application that's amending an existing license. So, if I was if I was going in now separately for for an amendment of an existing, but there's no existing license. So, this is all encompassed in the 1 license new license application and you check off.
you know, that question nine. And if you look at the vote, I have it checked off both new license and pledge. The monetary transmittal form has both checked off. That has both checked off. And I did see the, the bank paperwork. Um, I saw language in the bank paperwork for the pledge as well, but the, there's, there's two important documents and actually she's got them right here.
This is 1. Yeah, I know, but that's the amendment application. The amendment application. Yeah, the state, but we already have an applicant statement is an entity vote. I don't know if you want to look at that, but it also specific for pledge. It's not the same as the entity vote in a new application. Well.
Yeah, no, the entity vote. I respectfully disagree with you. Um, attorney funds with, because the only reason why is I spoke with, um, Ralph, uh, from these, the ABCC director, Mr. Sacramonio, and he said that you need this. I spoke with him yesterday because I wasn't sure. And he says this package has got to be in with the new application package.
Okay, we're happy to put that together. I can have Barry sign it right away. Yeah, that's got to be done. Definitely got to be done.
Because we can't pass it with the pledge checked off unless the pledge paperwork is in it. And I know what you're saying, application for amendment. That was my question. And that's why I spoke with Ralph about it. And he says, no, you have to have that. He says, you can do it separate, but it's going to cost another $200. He says, this way, it's just $200. And they can check off as many boxes as they want on the monetary transmission form. And it's just that one $200 fee.
So, you know, that's something that needs to get done. The only reason being is the ABCC, as soon as they see it come through without that, they're gonna kick it back. And they just did kick it back with, who was it, Daria, we just got one kicked back because the pledge amendment wasn't on there. I forget which one.
So, yeah, well, that that had some that had some other issues going on too. No, I mean, I have the, I can get, you know, I have that application paperwork. We can submit that right away to Daria. Yeah, absolutely.
That that you need to do. I mean, it's just a matter of filling up a couple of times. Yeah. Then why don't we do that to save you? Because not only that is we'd have to have another quick hearing for to vote on the pledge.
Right, and it was no, the public notice clearly everything said was in there. So, I mean, we're covered. Okay, well, there's a few more questions I had to go ahead. Go ahead. I just don't want to move forward on them until we know now we can make a condition upon seeing the paperwork for the plants, but continue on. Go ahead. Let's see.
Collateral, okay. I highlighted everything on it so it'd be a little easier to find. I see all the notifications are done, the ad is done. Application for a new license.
Number two, on the page one of the application for a new license, the DBA, I noticed you had it on the drawings, but there's nothing in the box here. I wasn't, yeah, I don't know if we were 100% sure on the DBA name. Barry, you weren't sure yet, right, on the name?
I wasn't, I am now. I'm free to release that, and it's going to be called Mrs. Murphys. MRS Murphys? Yep. H-Y apostrophe S. I can send Daria a new page one of that application that will have the DBA inserted. Okay.
Then you'll get the four pages for the pledge. Good. Then as we go down a little further, let's see, page 2. On page 2,
Let's see, hang on a second. Mr. Aquino, Doro Aquino? Yes, I know, yep. This is on the number six, Postal Office of Stock and Ownership and Interest. There's no social security numbers, no date of birth. Same for Barry Rafferty. Is there any reason why?
Um, yeah, I had the day the 1st, so maybe that for some reason that isn't on your copy. There are no social security numbers though. I believe. Those have to be filled in. Yeah, well, if there's no Barry doesn't have there, you don't have a social security number. Correct. No, I do. Yeah. Oh, you do. Okay.
Yeah, just look at these queries. Do I have them on the other folks? I have. Yeah, yeah. Yeah, I have. Caitlin, Frederick, you have data breadth, social security. Yep, I have them on everyone. So we can. No, so you're missing Daro as well as Musio. Martin. Yeah, I have them on their query forms though. So I don't know why it's missing on that page too, but I can fill all of this in.
And so those are. Dataverse and social security numbers. Thanks. Thank you for that. Yeah. That was not. Yeah, you don't want ABCC to see that and kick it out because of that. OK, another thing. Barry, well, Barry, through the chair, is the Ford the only other license in the state of Massachusetts that you are affiliated with in any way? Yeah.
Okay. On page 3, number 7, occupancy of premise. You see John Costas is the landlord. It's a lease. The landlord's phone number is blank. Landlord email is blank. Landlord address is blank.
You know, God forbid there's a fire there. We can't get a hold of Barry. We got to call the landlord, whatever. I don't know what reasons they'd need it for, but the boxes are there and they're all blank. Could they be filled in? I can get that. Barry, do you have his contact info? I don't see it in the lease. I do. I don't have his address, but I'll text him. I'll get us. Yeah. Okay. Yep. Okay. So that's landline. Yeah.
Then we go to page 4, financial disclosure. We go to source of cash contribution. Other officers, stock or ownership interests are not listed in name of contributor in the amount that they're contributing.
You have three or four investors listed here that are supposed to be there with the amount they're contributing along with pictures of their accounts or where the money's coming from. None of that's listed. We never received any bank statements or anything as well. We do have Northern Bank and Trust for $711 for the term. But there's no other, the other financial interest parties are not even listed.
I guess Attorney Farnsworth, are there other parties with a financial interest in the new restaurant? Well, Barry has these other folks. It's the Molloy's. I'll just jump in there. The Molloy's are the only investors. The two Aquino brothers are my contractors and they want to work with me going forward.
and there is no financial contribution from them. So the financial contribution was from the Malloy, Caitlin and Ricky Malloy for 250,000. And I don't know what paperwork. So we should, we should, you should disclose that on the application and provide supporting documents for ABCC.
Yeah, Barry will need to show with the 2250,000 a copy of the check or deposit or, you know, from the financials. Fine, fine. And my suggestion, I don't know if the other commissioners would agree.
but the two Aquino's that are five percent of ownership, according to page 2 of proposed offices stock or ownership interest, the five percent each, whatever that,
dollar volume is, it should be located or documented under financial disclosures with their name and what the amount of contracting bothering or how much contracting worth they're giving to the establishment.
I mean, you're making them a 5% partner because of doing the contracting work. I think there should be a number in there somewhere. And even if you say a partner for contracting X number of dollars worth of work, I don't know. I don't know how that would work. I'm not a lawyer. That's attorney Farnsworth. But yeah, I don't know. Yeah, we could just say that they're, you know, sweat equity partners. You know what I mean? Because I don't want to confuse the ABCC because that's really source of cash
cash contribution because they're always just trying to track the money. Yeah, you can wordsmith that. You're right. Sweat equity or builders equity, something like that. Yeah, something's got to be in there because they are listed as ownership interest. Oh, yeah. We were disclosing them because they are in fact owners.
It seems to be a lot there, Bobby. Good catch. I still got more, Mr. Chairman. Okay. With what we've seen now, I would surmise that they would kick this back to you and then you go back and forth and you come back to us. But go ahead, Bobby. You have some more items that caught your attention? Yeah, I did actually. Next was the pledge, but we already discussed that.
Let's see. Let's see. I got on the entity vote.
It's page 18 of the PDF1. Yeah, I have that. Let's see. Okay, entity vote. At the very top, the third line down, I think you're meant to put in March 1st instead of March 1st.
Oh, yeah, yeah, okay, we can fix that. Small error, nothing big. Voted to a point, you left it blank. Yeah, saves needs to be put in there. Exactly. I mean, there's an awful lot of blank things and, you know, I was going to make a motion just to table this till next month because a lot of it's not even here. I mean, especially the pledge. The pledge is a big deal.
And I can't vote to put it through without this thing being completed. It's not completed the way it should be. Yeah, I don't know about you other fellows. I mean, believe me, I just want to see it do it right so you don't have any issues.
I don't want to see you have any issues. I don't want to come back to us from the ABCC. Why didn't you pick up this? Why didn't you pick up that? A lot of these things, it's just minor, but it's got to be done. I want to see this project continue moving forward. But you're right, there's quite a few omissions. I think Attorney Farnsworth has been taking notes. I see her hands up. Oh, yeah. We can turn this around today.
Well, that's kind of what I was hoping you'd say. I'm thinking that if the other two commissioners are agreeable, that let Attorney Farnsworth rework the package, get it to Daria. Daria, if you don't mind, send it to the three of us, and we can kind of review it. We could put something in the notes that we've looked at it. We've seen some omissions. They're going to get addressed.
and we'll revisit it as soon as possible. That way we don't have to delay this another month. Daria, what do you think? That's fine with me. Okay. It's fine with you guys. I'm fine with whatever. Okay. Yeah, I'm good with that as well. I mean, these are all points, you know, Commissioner Delfano is bringing up and, you know, he also went to the trouble of talking to the ABCC kind of like,
for, you know, on behalf of you, in a way, to make sure that, like, it was gonna go through and, you know, and it looks like it would have been kicked back. So I do think he saved you a step in bringing all these things up, too. But I think it is, you know, if it can be turned around quickly and back to us while everything is still fresh in our, you know, memory, I think it's reasonable. Because I would like to see it proceed as well, you know, assuming all these boxes get checked. So that's how I feel about it.
Yeah, and I really don't want to tie it up for another month as well. I like the forward. I dine in there. I patronize the place and it's a great place. And I think this place in Medford square is going to be just as good with the management and everything that.
You know, everything about it, it seems to work, but that's why I just want to make sure we've got it all. I, you know, I started T's cross to just just get it done in 1 thing. But, um, yeah, attorney found where they like, like the chairman and the other commissioners stated is as long as it's all corrected, you get it back to Gary or she can email it to us individually. Unfortunately, we can't me, um,
together or converse together versus emails. So if any of us has any issues, we have to just go back and forth one-on-one to Darrier and then until it gets resolved. I mean, in the meeting, it's great. We can all talk openly like this, but outside the meeting, as you know, we can't.
So if we do find anything odd or strange, we'll go through Daria. Daria will reach out to you, Attorney Farnsworth, and that's kind of how it would work. Hopefully, you'll make sure everything is— Oh, yeah. I'm going to go through it now with a fine-tooth comb. Okay. Good.
Good, good, good. Okay, so let's- Mr. Chairman, I just want to let you know that I can, and Daria and Ben, on this page, on this PDF1, I kind of highlighted everything and I'll send a copy to Daria and she can send it out to you guys. So when we get the new paperwork, it'll be easy for you just to reference what we're looking for and make sure it was taken care of.
Okay, thank you. That's a great idea. I think you should definitely do that, because Bobby's very thorough, so I'm sure that'll point to everything that needs to be updated, and hopefully we don't have to do all that email circle, because that's always tough. Yeah, yeah, it's a pain. Okay, great. I beg your pardon. Can I just have one thing to say, if that's okay? So, first of all, I serve beer for a living, and unfortunately,
few clerical errors that are there, you know, to Tricia's word, she said she'll have it all back to Daria today. If there's any concerns in relation to my work or what we're doing, I'd love to know now. I hope there's not. But I do feel sure that whatever information that was requested there would be provided within the next two hours.
Yeah, no, that's fine with me. I don't have any issues with the, I mean, Alan, the financing stuff is your forte, banking stuff rather. I mean, that's not my forte. Ben, the building stuff, that's your forte. I'm just a retired old guy that's got nothing better to do than read this thing and try and pull it apart, but, you know. I'm grateful.
No, I am too, because I, you know, I do these applications. I don't know why some of these things missing, but the pledge separate paperwork is news to me. So, but that's fine. I'll, you know, we'll do that. If you want to do any funds with, I can, I can send a link to Daria with the paperwork I'm talking about.
I have it I do have the pledge amendment application okay it's just four pages you know it's it's that's all that's required with it and yeah that's that's basically about it I mean I don't think it's anything it'll be resolved by the time we finish our meeting we we got a few minutes at the end of this then a couple of matters that we have to go over with the
uh, posting of, uh, of, of, uh, the deadlines and stuff for the 48 hour ramp, the 48 hour rule. So, you know, I don't think you're going to get your stuff that quick, but just send it to Daria and we'll review it and get it back to you or back to Daria as soon as ASAP.
Okay. Makes sense. Ms. McCoy, we'd like to hear from you a little background. Tell us a little history if you're still there. Yes, I'm here. So background about myself or? Yeah, a little about yourself, your experience in the industry.
Yes, so I've been working with Barry at the Ford since before it opened. Previous to that, I was running River Bar in Somerville, but been taking hold of the Ford, getting it, you know, operational and functioning and profitable. So is always the goal. So I'll be doing the same for the pub when that opens, hopefully in August.
Very good. Like I said, we just wanted to get you on record some of your information. I thank you. We can make a motion to table 25 Salem Street LLC until the package with all the tweaks are taken care of and then we can review it again.
okay i mean i guess because do you have to vote though mr chair because if you don't vote the three of you now right i i don't know how you guys work but do i just don't want to have to wait a whole nother month i mean i guess it would be you would vote to approve pending you know receipt of the proper documentation or something i guess uh i don't know um that's what i thought
Oh, sorry. Yeah, well, that's I was saying, you know, we could we could approve this conditionally condition on. Yeah, that was my understanding of it. Sorry for me speak. That was just my understanding of it to that if.
Very valid points, very good catch on all of this. But if our hang up is on the paperwork and paperwork does come through, and like Barry asked, if we don't have any other real concerns about granting the license because of him or because of Sage or anybody else, and then I think I would be OK with approving it conditional on that paperwork coming back.
But like we said, if it doesn't, for some reason it doesn't come back, there's too many questions, it could get tabled until the next month. I mean, for sure. So hopefully it doesn't. Bobby, your thoughts on that? Are you okay with the conditional approval or no? No, I'm okay with the conditional approval. As long as, you know, I'm just like attorney Farnsworth says, how do we do this? Do we vote again?
maybe individually to Daria versus email once we receive everything, review it. Daria will forward us all those papers. I'll read it if I like it. Yeah. Okay. All is good. I approve. I email it back to Daria. You do the same. Ben does the same. But is that legal with all of this open meeting law stuff? I don't know. I don't know what the
I'm not sure either. I'm not sure either. But we've done that in the past, and we've never heard from KP law telling us that what we're doing is not
You know, right? So I don't have a problem with it. Yeah, I say, you know, where, you know, where Zoom is, you know, is a brave new world. Let's continue doing it. We have been doing it until K.P. Law or we finally get a city solicitor that tells us, no, stop doing it that way.
Okay, I don't have an issue with it. Okay. And basically, it's diarrhea can't turn this paperwork into the ABC anyways, unless all 3 of us approve via email. So correct. If it was conditionally approved, it's, it's basically, I don't see any issues with it.
Okay, good. Then one of the two of you make a motion to conditionally approve the new license application and the pledge, and then we'll go from there. Bobby, you or me? What's that? You or me?
Yeah, why don't you do it, Ben? All right. Okay. All right. So let me see if I can get this right. So I'm going to make a motion to approve the application for the new license. The entity name is 225 Salem Street LLC. The
The address is, sorry, not 225, 25, sorry. The address, 25 Salem Street, Medford, Massachusetts. This is for a new license per the description and the plans that have been submitted on this application by Barry Rafferty.
And this is going to be conditionally based on the completion, the proper completion of this package, which is going to include all of the.
uh, the additional owners, uh, financial information we've requested from the additional owners, as well as some additional information we've requested with landlord information, um, and- and so on, as we've, uh, requested. Uh, so- so to summarize that, uh, we're gonna make a motion to approve this on the condition that we, uh, receive in a prompt amount of time, reasonable amount of time, um, all that additional follow-up information.
And can we insert the pledge, the pledge four pages for the pledge? Yeah, sorry, as well as that four page pledge collateral, which is available on the ABCC. I think we could basically just say all of the things we discussed that needed to be, because there's six or seven things here. Yeah, correct, correct. So that's the motion. Okay.
Yes, I'll second that motion. All right. Jerry, did you get all that? Yes. Okay. Thank you. All in favor of accepting the motion, say aye. Aye. Aye. Very good.
Okay, so, Attorney Farnsworth, you have a big homework assignment. Yes, we have it. And to get it back to us as quickly as possible. And then, as Commissioner Delafarno said, we'll each look at it, and if we have any questions or concerns, we'll send them through Daria, and Daria will reach out to you. Okay, perfect. Okay, very good. Thank you. All right, thank you, thank you. Thank you all. Thank you.
Sorry about that, everybody. No, no. Those are good catches. If we didn't head that off now and ABCC got it, do you think ABCC would just kick it back to them with highlight or notes saying this is incomplete, take another crack at it?
Yeah, they kick it back, you know, saying that, what do they call it? No action. And that's only going to delay it a lot longer. Yeah, because they will have to come back to us.
Yeah. I thank you for your eagle eyes. You caught a lot of things. It is interesting that some things on the application auto-populate and some don't. I mean, like why would some of the social securities and data birds carry over from the other sections, but some of them don't? I just, I don't know.
I think she just forgot to put them in the application. I mean, they were on the quipping. And all she needed to do is just log them in. And that's what a lot of this stuff was. I mean, the date of the, I forgot to tell them too, on the entity vote, the date of the meeting. Maybe, Darry, you can make a note on that, the entity vote on page,
18, what was that? 18, yeah. Third line down, it says come. Yeah, voted to appoint. Yeah, the date of their meeting. Oh, yeah, yeah, what it says on March, March, start of March.
Notch for us. I did bring that up. It was Notch. Yeah, you did say that. That form, is that an interactive PDF? Or is it a dummy thing where you just print it down and then you enter the information in there? Jerry, do you know if that's interactive on ABCC? Some yes and some are no. OK.
Because the one that I'm looking at, a Pledge of Collateral, you can definitely. It's interactive. You can just open it up and type right into it. Yeah. OK. But I know some are not. Yeah. Yeah. OK. All right. This was good. This was a good exercise. I hope Attorney Farnsworth completes it and gets it back to us as quickly as possible.
Bobby, I wanted to come back to that item on the agenda. I wasn't quite following the spirit of it. I know we had talked about it some time back. Is it more so that people aren't just dropping things off at the last second, like Monday at 2 o'clock and they're dropping something off for the Tuesday hearing? Is that the spirit of that whole item?
Hang on one second, Al. Okay. I'm sorry, Mr. Chairman, I know you had to answer something. Oh, sorry. Yeah, basically what's happening is it seems like every month that
That we're having a meeting the morning of the meeting, we're getting 2, 3 applications for 1 day licenses and, um, you know, not only is it against the 48 hour meeting open meeting law.
Um, you know, all that has to be in 48 hours before the meeting takes place, excluding weekends and holidays. So poor Daria's getting hammered left and right. Then she's sending them out to us. We're trying to read them, uh, 10 minutes before the meeting. And it seemed to be the same people kind of doing it all the time. So we, we, we left it as a, uh,
I got Ralph. I got Ralph Sacramone calling me. Do you want me to take it? Just mute everything. Daria, do you like this idea? Do you think this would help you be more efficient with the hearings? If we said, look, it's got to be Friday before the Tuesday? Yeah.
I think Friday would be ideal by like 11 a.m. So this way, because I want to get it to you. I want to have the agenda sent to you guys plus the documents because I know it's a lot sometimes and I don't want to send it to you on Tuesday or Monday. I want to have it ready for Friday like I did this Friday. Sometimes when I get things last minute, it prevents me from sending it all at the same time because I'm getting it all at different times.
So it's better off have a deadline, which is Friday, let's say 11am. So it gives me till 1230 to scan everything in and to get it to you guys before the end of the day here. Okay. So then you have the weekend and then yeah, I know I like I like that idea because sometimes Monday's a holiday.
Yeah, like this Monday was a holiday. So I didn't, you know, if I come back on Tuesday, I get bombarded with, I mean, this Tuesday didn't happen, but a couple of Tuesdays I'll be getting everything. And it's like, I'm trying to catch up from my work plus places. And I don't wanna, I don't think it's fair for me to send you guys last minute items either.
Yeah, no, no, I like the idea. I only wish I thought of it. So I say that's fine. Let's use that as long as we all are on the same page so nobody's calling us on a Monday or a Tuesday morning saying, oh, I forgot. And the event's going to be before the next meeting, your next licensed meeting.
That's great. We'll stick with that protocol and we'll do our best to get the repeat offenders in a routine so they know not to pull any last minute items. Hey, Dara, I haven't been tracking this. I know it's only April, but event them, Brian seems to be, his business, his entity keeps
growing and involving and he has so many different events do we do we track because it's my understanding we will only issue up to 31 day licenses for any entity do we do we keep track of event them
He knows per calendar year. Him and I are actually going to talk tomorrow. We're supposed to talk beginning of the year, but then he got sick and then it got all delayed because sometimes it's under him. Sometimes it's under JJ Cuisine. Yeah. So I want to explain to him how that works plus non-profit and profit. So he's clear on that. OK. So we're going to talk about it tomorrow. Good, because I saw that on the agenda items
He had one on April 14th. So yeah, okay, so it sounds like you're way ahead of us. As long as he's aware that we can't issue more than 31 day licenses for an entity, as long as, like I said, as long as he's aware of that, we'll be fine. He is aware of that, yeah. He was actually on top of it.
whenever he started actually coming in front of us. So he asked a great deal about it. Because I remember at one point, I remember a few years, Springstep and Tufts were getting very close to, you know, the 30 mark. So we, you know, that's when we started saying, hey, we should pay attention to this because, you know, you think, well, geez, 30, you know, that's a boatload. But some of the establishments do get close to that number. All right. Thanks.
I'm back. Bobby, anything new, or was he watching? We got exciting news. Attorney Farnsworth, I already got to him. He says he just spoke with her, and he said that we don't need the pledge application. She was right.
Ah, okay. And Ralph had said, um, he says, yeah, he says, I didn't know that it was a new license, which I did tell him it was a new license. Um, but he said, I said, well, what about the entity vote where they have to, you know, vote on the, uh, on the pledge? He says, no, that page March 1st, 2024, that's got pledged checked off. So that covers the entity vote. And, um, he says, and all, they also have the, uh,
applicant statement that they vote on, which he says is in the main application, which it is. And I asked him about the amendment pledge information sheet, which is the first one, and he said they didn't need it. So he said, don't worry about the pledge. I just touched base with him on all of the other things. And he says, yeah, they've got to do all that other stuff, but the pledge, forget about it. OK. So Bobby, help me understand this.
Because it's a new license, it can be piggybacked. But having an existing license and they were pledging, that would be different? Yes.
With the brand new license, it's in the brand new license application. On the first page, the monetary transmittal form, which has got all the boxes to check. I saw that. It says it's checked there. I said, yes, I realized that. Then the second thing that I had a question on was the application for amendment pledge of collateral, which is one of three sheets.
in the pledge, but it's got the same information in a new application than it does in an amendment. And the applicant statement, that's filled out in the new application. And the entity vote, it's as long as pledge is checked off, you don't need to use this form.
All right, this is good because so I think I understand if it's a new application, then it's all can be piggyback. But if it's an existing application and they're looking to pledge the licenses collateral, then that's a that's another application and another fee for ABCC. So that's not correct. OK. Yes. And the questions that I
Kind of was wondering about too, but it makes sense today where he turned in the drawings with the patio. We're approving the patio for outdoor dining. I would imagine we don't have to do a separate thing for an alteration of premise or anything like that. No, because that's all.
Yeah. I don't know what you guys did at the porch, you know, or the Ford. I wasn't there when you approved all of that. It's just all approved. It is approved all up front. All up front. That's how we did it at the Ford. Yeah. Okay. Okay.
Again, I know where you're going with that. It's like an existing license holder and then they want an alteration of footprint because they're going to push through into the back or to the side to add more seats. Then that's an alteration of premises. Yeah. Yeah, but it's already in. In this, it's already in the original, correct?
Yeah, and I also asked Ralph, I says, before you hang up, any news on outdoor dining? He says they still haven't decided. Yeah, yeah. So nobody can have any outdoor dining that's was getting it through this whole COVID thing. I mean, places like the Ford, places like the porch that already have it, you know, was part in Medford Brewing. I mean, it's licensed. They don't need to worry about it.
Yeah, they can so. You know, I just had something I had to just attend to something. I don't know if we're wrapping up or I can just for I need to be off for a 2nd, but if I'm not back on. Okay. Okay. Are we are we concluding?
Yeah, do we have to vote on that 48 hour thing or no, it's it's the law or anyways, right? Right. It's the law. Yeah. Yeah. We're on Friday at 11. We're good. Yeah. Yeah. I just want to thank you. Thank you, Ben. OK. OK. Thank you, everybody. All right. All right. I know. Thanks for digging into that, Bobby.
Daria, she'll get that to us and it makes it a lot easier now because we don't have to review and digest that four-page pledge. The other items are just, it's fill in the missing items. Again, I just find it odd that it's not an interactive PDF where it just auto-populate from one area to the other, but she'll get it to us. It sounds like she immediately picked up the phone and called ABCC. Yeah. Sounds like she'll get it to us quickly.
Okay, cool. For outdoor dining, I just want to mention that we're still able to do outdoor dining, we're just not able to serve liquor.
Oh, yeah, I believe so. Yeah. I don't know about outdoor dining, just the liquor we can't. Yeah. No, no, no. Yeah. Outdoor dining is all set because I know Planned Development and Sustainability work on that with KP law and the previous city solicitor that was here. Okay. We just can't serve liquor unless that emergency order gets approved. Gets approved. Okay. Okay. So I just wanted to clarify that. Yeah. Yeah. No, thank you.
Okay, good. Good. Um, okay. And like I said, we don't have to vote on the 48 hour thing, right? Because it's a wire anyway. So it's just we're gonna enforce it. We we wanted to make sure that we, uh,
In the area, I mean, if something comes up. Like, the day before the meeting, and it's the city hall is having an event next week and we completely forgot all about it and oh, my God and blah, blah, blah. I mean, something like that's okay.
And if you actually read the 48 hour rule for Massachusetts, there are exceptions for emergency type of things like that. So, I mean, it's, it's, you know, if it's 1 of our regulars calling up with a sob story, then it's like, hey, listen.
Uh, you can give him Jim's famous saying, this is your 1 bite of the apple after that. It's not going to happen anymore. So, you know, just in a nice way, kind of like, hey, this is the rule. Well, you know, we got to follow it because it's not everybody, especially Daria.
Right, right. And I think, Daria, you'd be the one to make that call. Because if you look at it, go, oh, boy, this is so complicated. But if it's something you're, Bobby's right. If it's something the city's going to do at the last minute, then we'd be more than happy to take a look at it. But let's stick to the rule. I like the rule. I think it's good to get all the patrons in a routine so they know what to expect and they know what the protocol is. So I think it's smart.
Cool. All right. So let's, uh, I guess, uh, make a motion to adjourn. It's two Oh seven Bobby. Let's, uh, let's, uh, a motion to adjourn. I'll second the motion. Very good. All in favor. Aye. All right. Adjourned diarrhea. Thank you very much, Bobby. Good to see you. All right. Take care. Bye bye bye.