Tornadoes!
Up next, please welcome the home team, the Medford High School Mustangs.
Fans, it is now time for some pregame entertainment. Please welcome the Medford High School band.
¶.
♪♪
Thank you to the Mefford High School Marching Band.
Fans, it is time now for the coin toss. Please welcome the captains for Malden and Medford. Joining Medford on the field as honorary captains are two members from the Mustang Hall of Fame. Our first honoree is a graduate of Medford High's 1966 class and a former member of the football team.
Please welcome former teacher, coach, and athletic director, Ron Mr. Z. Zambel. Our next honoree is a graduate of the class of 1973. And in 1972, he ran for five touchdowns and over 200 yards in the 1972 Thanksgiving Day game. Please welcome Mike Colonna.
And joining Malden on the field, please welcome a graduate of the Malden class of 1964 who made a crucial interception and returned it for an 89-yard touchdown in 1963. Please welcome Honorary Captain George Bob Baker.
Malden has won the toss and have chosen to receive.
Kicking off for Medford will be number 5, Matthew Wright.
Ball carried by number nine, Kevin Exelhom. All the way for a Mauldin-Dornado touchdown.
Here to accept the point after is number 14, Aiden Brett. Kick is no good. The score is Malden six, Medford zero.
Take control now. We can't even slow down. We don't have to go wild. Welcome to my world. Play that music too loud. Show me what you do now. We don't have to go wild. Welcome to my world.
Welcome to
Ball carried by number two, Stephens Exeter. It'll be first and 10 for Medford on the 40-yard line.
Ball carried by number two, Stephens-Exeter.
It'll be second and four for Medford.
Bumble on the play, covered by number 26 Felix Acosta, good for the Malden, touchdown.
Mauldin to accept a two-point conversion.
Number 30, Kyle Paulding is good. Two point conversion is good. The score, the Malden Golden Tornadoes 14, the Mefford Mustangs 0.
Stop looking at what you ain't got and start being thankful for what you do got. Let's give it to them, baby girl. Hey. Hey. Hey. Hey. Hey. Hey. Hey.
I just live my life.
the way
It'll be first and ten for Medford on their own 38-yard line.
It'll be second and seven.
Ball carried by number 10, Justin Marino, sacked on the play. It'll be fourth and long for Medford.
Bumble on the play, recovered by the Mustangs.
It'll be first and 10 for Medford. Ball carried by number two, Stephens Exeter. It'll be second and eight for Medford.
at the Malden 42-yard line. Ball carried by number two, Stephens Exeter. Good for a Mustang, first down.
It'll be first and 10 for Medford at the Malden 30-yard line.
Ball carried by number two, Stephens Exeter. It'll be second and seven for the Mustangs.
Ball carried by number two, Stephens Exeter. No gain on the play, it'll be third and seven.
Passed by number nine, Jack Lombardo is incomplete. It'll be fourth and seven for Medford. Flag on the play. Penalty against Medford.
It'll be third and 12. Passed by number nine, Jack Lombardo is incomplete. It'll be fourth and 12 for the Medford Mustangs.
Passed by number nine, Jack Lombaro's incomplete to number two, Steven Exeter. Mauldin will take over on downs. It'll be first and 10 for the Golden Tornadoes.
Yes, yes, yeah! Let's go!
Pass is complete to number two, Gabriel Vargas Cardoso. There's a flag on the play. Penalty is against Malden.
Yeah.
The ball carried by number nine, Kevin Exelholm. It'll be second and two for the Golden Tornadoes. Flag on the play. False start called against Malden.
Okay, we got the clock, baby. Let's get rid of that flag.
Wall carry by number nine, Kevin Exelholm. Second down or third down? I still think it's annoying. I can't really tell. I'm trying to look to see if they moved the chains. It doesn't look like they did. It'll be second and seven for the Golden Tornadoes. Oh, oh. I can hear us. What? When you said cat, we got the clock, baby. Correction, third and six for the Golden Tornadoes.
Pass is complete to number 11, Alexander Avalos. It'll be fourth and one for Malden.
Ball carried by number nine, Kevin Exelhom.
He's good for a Malden first down.
Loss on the play, it'll be second and 14 for the Malden Golden Tornadoes.
Ball carrier number two, Gabriel Vargas Cardozo. Good for Maldon, first down.
It'll be first and 10 for Malden on the Mustang 28-yard line.
Ball carried by number nine, Kevin Ekselhom. Gain of one on the play, it'll be second and nine.
Flag on the play, false start against Malden. It'll be second and 14.
Pass intended to number three, Davian McGoughy. Incomplete, flag on the play.
Pass interference called against Medford. Leads to an automatic first down for Malden. It'll be first and 10 for Malden on the Mustang 11-yard line.
Ball carried by number nine, Kevin Exelholm. Flag on the play.
Personal foul, face mask called against Medford. It'll be first and goal for the Malden Tornadoes.
And that's the end of the first quarter with the score, the Mauldin Golden Tornadoes, 14, the Meffern Mustangs, zero. Fans, if you visit our Wasabi Fenway Bowl team in the Gate A concourse, you can enter for a chance to win tickets to the Wasabi Fenway Bowl on December 17th. The winner will be announced at the end of the third quarter.
No.
Ball carried by number nine, Kevin Exelholm. Good for the Mauldin. Touchdown.
Mauldin will attempt a two point conversion. Oh, oh, yeah!
Pass is complete to number 30, Kyle Paulding. Two-point conversion is good. The score, the Malden Golden Tornadoes, 22, the Mefford Mustangs, zero.
Hey! Hey! Hey!
We're gonna be on Channel 7!
It'll be first and 10 for Medford. At their own 29 yard line.
Ball carried by number two, Stephens Exeter. Loss of one on the play. It'll be second and eleven for Medford.
Loss on a play, it'll be third and 13 for Medford. Pass is complete to number two, Stephens Exeter.
It'll be fourth and eighth for Medford.
Malden takes over. It'll be first and 10 for the Golden Tornadoes on their own 40-yard line.
Pass is complete to number nine, Kevin Exelhom. Game number about four, it'll be second and six for Malden.
Oh, yeah.
It'll be third and two for Malden at their own 48-yard line.
Ball carried by number nine, Kevin Exelhom. It'll be fourth and three for Malden.
Ball carried by number nine, Kevin Exelhom. Good for Maldon, first down.
Ball carried by number 11, Alexander Avalos. Good for Maldon, first down.
Ball carried by number nine, Kevin Exelhom. Loss of one on the play, it'll be second and 12.
Passed by number 14, Aiden Brett is incomplete.
Ball carried by number nine, Kevin Exelholm. Time out on the field.
After the timeout, it'll be fourth and two. Correction, fourth and three for Malden at the Mustang 30 yard line.
Pass is incomplete. Medford takes over. It'll be first and 10 for the Mustangs.
Ball carried by number six, Louise Barboza. No gain on the play, it'll be second and 10.
Ball carried by number two, Steven Zegziter. It'll be third down and seven for Medford.
Pass intended for number two, Stephens-Exeter, is incomplete. It'll be fourth and seven for the Mustangs.
Back to pundits number five, Matthew Wright. Fumble on the play, recovered by Mauldin.
Ball carried by number nine, Kevin Exelholm. Loss on the play.
It'll be second and 15 for Malden.
Passes complete to number three, Davian McGuffey. It'll be third down and five for Malden.
Pass is complete to number 30, Kyle Paulding. It'll be first and 10 for the Golden Tornadoes. Time out on the field.
It'll be first and ten for the Mauldin Golden Tornadoes on the Mustang 32-yard line.
Pass is incomplete.
Pass is incomplete. Penalty against Malden.
It'll be second and 20.
Pass intended for number 30, Kyle Paulding, is incomplete. It'll be third and 20 for Malden on the Mustang 42-yard line.
Flag on the play. Penalty against Malden for holding. And that's the end of the first half with the score, the Malden Golden Tornadoes 22, the Meffern Mustangs zero.
Fans, it is now time for some halftime entertainment. Please welcome the Malden High School Band.
♪
Wait, like, five seconds.
You.
John! John! John! John!
Oh my God.
The Wasabi Family Bowl raffle ticket winner is 9913991. An associate of the bowl game will contact you to schedule your ticket pickup.
¶
you
Part four.
¶¶
Behind the steering wheel
You got me in a spin, but everything is A-OK. Touching you.
Medved said to receive the second half kickoff. I believe in a thing called love. Just look into the rhythm of my heart. There's a chance we can make it now. When I look into the sun goes down. I believe in a thing called love.
There's a flag on the play. Flag was a false start on Mauldin.
Stop him! Stop him!
Touchdown Medford. Mauldin's kickoff returned by number two, Stephens Exeter.
Bedford's extra point is good.
It's Friday
Midford's kick goes out of bounds. That'll bring up first down and 10 for Malden from their own 40 yard line.
Number three, Davian McGuffey on the carry, tackled by a host of Bedford Mustangs. That'll bring up second down and 12 for Malden.
Number three Davian McGuffey on the carry. That'll bring up third down and five for Malden.
Number three, Davian McGuffey on the carry. That'll bring up fourth down and five from Aldon.
One, two, three, four.
Overrated.
That'll bring up first down and 10 for Mauldin.
The flag on the play. Holding on Malden.
Number nine, Kevin Exelhom on the carry.
Pushed out of bounds by number five from Medford.
Aiden Brett's pass to number nine Kevin Uxelholm is complete. Tackled by Emmett McGovern from Medford.
That'll bring up third down and five for Malden. All right, next time we do the wave side, we start from this side to this side, all right?
Number nine, Kevin Exelhom on the carry. Tackled by number 10 from Medford, Cole Merino. That'll bring up fourth down and four from Aldon.
Aiden Brett's pass to number two, Gabriel Cardoso-Vargas is incomplete. That'll be a turnover on downs, first and 10 for Medford.
Number two on the carry for Medford.
Pass incomplete. Pass was broken up by number 52, James Hippolyte.
Third down and nine for Medford.
Number 10, Justin Marino with the reception from Medford. The result of the play is a Medford Mustang first down. Timeout Mauldin.
I've been doing just fine. God, I gotta be down because I want it all. It started out with a kiss. How did it end up like this? It was only a kiss.
Number 19, Brianna Carullo on the carry for Medford. That'll bring up second down and one.
That'll bring up third down and one for Medford. Fumble on the play.
Fumble recovered by number nine, Kevin Exelholm. Medford will retain possession
Number two, Stephens, Exeter on the carry. That'll bring up second down and five for Medford.
There's a fumble on the play. Fumble is recovered by number four, Formalden Andrew Lewis.
That'll be a turnover on downs, first and 10 for Mauldin. Let's go Mauldin! Let's go Mauldin! Let's go Mauldin!
Number nine Kevin Exelhom on the carry. Tackled by number 58 Jake McGovern for Medford.
That'll bring up second down and six for Malden. Number nine, Kevin Exelhom on the carry.
That'll bring up third down and seven for Malden from their own six yard line.
Number 11, Alexander Avalos on the carry.
Darius Weeks on the tackle from Medford. That'll bring up fourth down.
Maldon's punt returned by number two. Number two, Stephens Exeter with the punt return. Tackled by number nine, Kevin Exelholm. ♪ I can't begin to knowin' ♪ ♪ But then I know it's growin' strong ♪
Wasn't the spring, and spring became the summer. Who'd have believed you'd come along? Hand, touching hand. Reaching out, touching me.
♪ Look at the night ♪ Touchdown, Medford. Number six, Luis Barboza on the carry. The result of the play is a Medford Mustangs touchdown.
Let's go Maldives!
Medford's two point conversion is good.
This place, pump it up!
Number three, Davian McGuffey, and number nine, Kevin Echsholm set to return. There's a flag on the play.
Kickoff out of bounds. That'll bring up first and 10 for Mauldin. From the Midfield, 45 yard line.
Aiden Brett's pass to number nine Kevin Exelholm is enough for a Mauldin first down.
Injury timeout on the field.
That'll bring up first and 10, Mauldin from the Medford 32 yard line.
Number nine, Kevin Eltshul home on the carry. Tackled by number 51. Number 51, Christian Jordan from Medford.
Second down and 10 for Mauldin.
Aiden Brett's pass to number two, Gabriel Cardoso-Vargas, is complete. That was Stephens-Exeter on the tackle from Medford. That'll bring up first down and goal from Alden.
Number nine, Kevin Exelholm on the carry. Tackled by number 51, Jordan Christian from Medford. That'll bring up second down and goal from the Medford seven yard line.
Touchdown, Malden. Number nine, Kevin Exelholm on the carry. The result of the play is a Malden High School touchdown.
Hey! Hey!
Mauldin's two-point try is no good.
Don't you know pump it up? You got to pump it up. Don't you know pump it up? You got to pump it up. Don't you know pump it up? You got to pump it up. Don't you know pump it up? You got to pump it up. Don't you know pump it up? You got to pump it up. Don't you know pump it up? You got to pump it up. Don't you know pump it up? You got to pump it up. Don't you know pump it up?
Number two and number 18 set to return from Medford.
Number two, Stephens Exeter on the return from Medford. That'll bring up first down and 10 for Medford. From their own 15 yard line.
Number 10, Justin Marino on the carry for Medford. The result of the play is a Medford-Mustang first down. First and 10, Medford from their own 36 yard line.
There's a flag on the play, Falstad Medford.
Number two, Stephens, Exeter with the reception.
That'll bring up third down and 21 from Medford.
Medford's pass is intercepted by number 26, Felix DaCosta. There is a flag on the play.
The penalty was a late hit out of bounds, Medford. That'll bring up first down for Malden, first and 10.
Aiden Brett's pass to number seven, Nathan Sullivan. The result of the play is a Malden High School Golden Tornado touchdown.
Correction, number three, Davian McGuffey with the touchdown reception for Malden.
Number 24, Darius Blaze on the carry. The two point conversion is no good.
let's go it's all about
There's a flag on the play. Delay of game, Mauldin.
Number 14, Aiden Brett's kick sails out of bounds. That'll bring up a first and 10 for Medford.
Let's go, Maldives! Let's go, Maldives! Let's go, Maldives! Let's go, Maldives! Let's go, Maldives! Let's go, Maldives! Let's go, Maldives! Let's go, Maldives!
There's a flag on the play.
Mauldin set the kickoff again.
Mauldin's kick is recovered by number eight, Anthony DeFrenzo. First and 10, Medford.
Midford's pass to number 10, Justin Marino, is incomplete. That'll bring up second down and 10 for Midford.
Medford's pass to number eight, Anthony DeFrenzo is incomplete, out of bounds.
That'll bring up third down and 10 for Medford.
Pass is incomplete. That'll bring up fourth down and 10 for Medford. From their own 47 yard line.
Medford's pass to number two, Stephens, Exeter is incomplete. That'll be a turnover on downs, first and 10 Mauldin. That'll be first and 10 Mauldin from the Medford 47 yard line.
Number nine, Kevin Exelholm on the carry. That'll bring up second down from Aldon. Second down and six from the Midfield, 43 yard line.
Number nine, Kevin Exelholm on the carry. Tackled by number 52, Samuel Nazari. The result of the play is a Malden High School first down.
Number nine Kevin Exelholm on the carry. Tackled by number 52 Samuel Nazari from Medford. That'll bring up second down and 10 for Malden.
from the Midfit 35-yard line. Number nine, Kevin Exselholm on the carry.
Darius Weeks on the tackle from Medford. That'll bring up third down and one for Mauldin. From the Medford 26 yard line.
Number nine, Kevin Exelholm on the carry. Tackled by number 52, Samuel Nazari from Medford.
Number nine Kevin Exelholm on the carry. That'll bring up second down and eight for Mauldin.
Number nine Kevin Exelhom on the carry. Tackle by number 11 from Medford.
That'll bring up third down and nine for Mauldin. The final score from historic Fenway Park, Mauldin 34,
Members, 15.