[SPEAKER_01]: Tornadoes!
[SPEAKER_03]: Up next, please welcome the home team, the Medford High School Mustangs.
[SPEAKER_03]: Fans, it is now time for some pregame entertainment.
[SPEAKER_03]: Please welcome the Medford High School band.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you to the Mefford High School Marching Band.
[SPEAKER_03]: Fans, it is time now for the coin toss.
[SPEAKER_03]: Please welcome the captains for Malden and Medford.
[SPEAKER_03]: Joining Medford on the field as honorary captains are two members from the Mustang Hall of Fame.
[SPEAKER_03]: Our first honoree is a graduate of Medford High's 1966 class and a former member of the football team.
[SPEAKER_03]: Please welcome former teacher, coach, and athletic director, Ron Mr. Z. Zambel.
[SPEAKER_03]: Our next honoree is a graduate of the class of 1973.
[SPEAKER_03]: And in 1972, he ran for five touchdowns and over 200 yards in the 1972 Thanksgiving Day game.
[SPEAKER_03]: Please welcome Mike Colonna.
[SPEAKER_03]: And joining Malden on the field, please welcome a graduate of the Malden class of 1964 who made a crucial interception and returned it for an 89-yard touchdown in 1963.
[SPEAKER_03]: Please welcome Honorary Captain George Bob Baker.
[SPEAKER_03]: Malden has won the toss and have chosen to receive.
[SPEAKER_08]: Kicking off for Medford will be number 5, Matthew Wright.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carried by number nine, Kevin Exelhom.
[SPEAKER_03]: All the way for a Mauldin-Dornado touchdown.
[SPEAKER_03]: Here to accept the point after is number 14, Aiden Brett.
[SPEAKER_03]: Kick is no good.
[SPEAKER_03]: The score is Malden six, Medford zero.
[SPEAKER_06]: Take control now.
[SPEAKER_06]: We can't even slow down.
[SPEAKER_06]: We don't have to go wild.
[SPEAKER_06]: Welcome to my world.
Play that music too loud.
Show me what you do now.
We don't have to go wild.
Welcome to my world.
Welcome to
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carried by number two, Stephens Exeter.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be first and 10 for Medford on the 40-yard line.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carried by number two, Stephens-Exeter.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be second and four for Medford.
[SPEAKER_03]: Bumble on the play, covered by number 26 Felix Acosta, good for the Malden, touchdown.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mauldin to accept a two-point conversion.
[SPEAKER_03]: Number 30, Kyle Paulding is good.
[SPEAKER_03]: Two point conversion is good.
[SPEAKER_03]: The score, the Malden Golden Tornadoes 14, the Mefford Mustangs 0.
[SPEAKER_09]: Stop looking at what you ain't got and start being thankful for what you do got.
[SPEAKER_08]: Let's give it to them, baby girl.
[SPEAKER_08]: Hey.
[SPEAKER_09]: Hey.
I just live my life.
[SPEAKER_09]: the way
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be first and ten for Medford on their own 38-yard line.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be second and seven.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carried by number 10, Justin Marino, sacked on the play.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be fourth and long for Medford.
[SPEAKER_03]: Bumble on the play, recovered by the Mustangs.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be first and 10 for Medford.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carried by number two, Stephens Exeter.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be second and eight for Medford.
[SPEAKER_03]: at the Malden 42-yard line.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carried by number two, Stephens Exeter.
[SPEAKER_03]: Good for a Mustang, first down.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be first and 10 for Medford at the Malden 30-yard line.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carried by number two, Stephens Exeter.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be second and seven for the Mustangs.
[SPEAKER_03]: No gain on the play, it'll be third and seven.
[SPEAKER_03]: Passed by number nine, Jack Lombardo is incomplete.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be fourth and seven for Medford.
[SPEAKER_03]: Flag on the play.
[SPEAKER_03]: Penalty against Medford.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be third and 12.
[SPEAKER_03]: Passed by number nine, Jack Lombardo is incomplete.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be fourth and 12 for the Medford Mustangs.
[SPEAKER_03]: Passed by number nine, Jack Lombaro's incomplete to number two, Steven Exeter.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mauldin will take over on downs.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be first and 10 for the Golden Tornadoes.
Yes, yes, yeah!
Let's go!
[SPEAKER_03]: Pass is complete to number two, Gabriel Vargas Cardoso.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's a flag on the play.
[SPEAKER_03]: Penalty is against Malden.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: The ball carried by number nine, Kevin Exelholm.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be second and two for the Golden Tornadoes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Flag on the play.
[SPEAKER_03]: False start called against Malden.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, we got the clock, baby.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's get rid of that flag.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wall carry by number nine, Kevin Exelholm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Second down or third down?
[SPEAKER_00]: I still think it's annoying.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't really tell.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm trying to look to see if they moved the chains.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't look like they did.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be second and seven for the Golden Tornadoes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Oh, oh.
[SPEAKER_07]: I can hear us.
[SPEAKER_07]: What?
[SPEAKER_07]: When you said cat, we got the clock, baby.
[SPEAKER_03]: Correction, third and six for the Golden Tornadoes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pass is complete to number 11, Alexander Avalos.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be fourth and one for Malden.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carried by number nine, Kevin Exelhom.
[SPEAKER_03]: He's good for a Malden first down.
[SPEAKER_03]: Loss on the play, it'll be second and 14 for the Malden Golden Tornadoes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carrier number two, Gabriel Vargas Cardozo.
[SPEAKER_03]: Good for Maldon, first down.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be first and 10 for Malden on the Mustang 28-yard line.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carried by number nine, Kevin Ekselhom.
[SPEAKER_03]: Gain of one on the play, it'll be second and nine.
[SPEAKER_03]: Flag on the play, false start against Malden.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be second and 14.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pass intended to number three, Davian McGoughy.
[SPEAKER_03]: Incomplete, flag on the play.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pass interference called against Medford.
[SPEAKER_03]: Leads to an automatic first down for Malden.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be first and 10 for Malden on the Mustang 11-yard line.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carried by number nine, Kevin Exelholm.
[SPEAKER_03]: Flag on the play.
[SPEAKER_03]: Personal foul, face mask called against Medford.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be first and goal for the Malden Tornadoes.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the end of the first quarter with the score, the Mauldin Golden Tornadoes, 14, the Meffern Mustangs, zero.
[SPEAKER_03]: Fans, if you visit our Wasabi Fenway Bowl team in the Gate A concourse, you can enter for a chance to win tickets to the Wasabi Fenway Bowl on December 17th.
[SPEAKER_03]: The winner will be announced at the end of the third quarter.
[SPEAKER_08]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carried by number nine, Kevin Exelholm.
[SPEAKER_03]: Good for the Mauldin.
[SPEAKER_03]: Touchdown.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mauldin will attempt a two point conversion.
[SPEAKER_07]: Oh, oh, yeah!
[SPEAKER_03]: Pass is complete to number 30, Kyle Paulding.
[SPEAKER_03]: Two-point conversion is good.
[SPEAKER_03]: The score, the Malden Golden Tornadoes, 22, the Mefford Mustangs, zero.
Hey!
[SPEAKER_07]: We're gonna be on Channel 7!
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be first and 10 for Medford.
[SPEAKER_03]: At their own 29 yard line.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carried by number two, Stephens Exeter.
[SPEAKER_03]: Loss of one on the play.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be second and eleven for Medford.
[SPEAKER_03]: Loss on a play, it'll be third and 13 for Medford.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pass is complete to number two, Stephens Exeter.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be fourth and eighth for Medford.
[SPEAKER_03]: Malden takes over.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be first and 10 for the Golden Tornadoes on their own 40-yard line.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pass is complete to number nine, Kevin Exelhom.
[SPEAKER_03]: Game number about four, it'll be second and six for Malden.
Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be third and two for Malden at their own 48-yard line.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carried by number nine, Kevin Exelhom.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be fourth and three for Malden.
[SPEAKER_03]: Good for Maldon, first down.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carried by number 11, Alexander Avalos.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carried by number nine, Kevin Exelhom.
[SPEAKER_03]: Loss of one on the play, it'll be second and 12.
[SPEAKER_03]: Passed by number 14, Aiden Brett is incomplete.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carried by number nine, Kevin Exelholm.
[SPEAKER_03]: Time out on the field.
[SPEAKER_03]: After the timeout, it'll be fourth and two.
[SPEAKER_03]: Correction, fourth and three for Malden at the Mustang 30 yard line.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pass is incomplete.
[SPEAKER_03]: Medford takes over.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be first and 10 for the Mustangs.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carried by number six, Louise Barboza.
[SPEAKER_03]: No gain on the play, it'll be second and 10.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carried by number two, Steven Zegziter.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be third down and seven for Medford.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pass intended for number two, Stephens-Exeter, is incomplete.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be fourth and seven for the Mustangs.
[SPEAKER_03]: Back to pundits number five, Matthew Wright.
[SPEAKER_03]: Fumble on the play, recovered by Mauldin.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ball carried by number nine, Kevin Exelholm.
[SPEAKER_03]: Loss on the play.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be second and 15 for Malden.
[SPEAKER_03]: Passes complete to number three, Davian McGuffey.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be third down and five for Malden.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pass is complete to number 30, Kyle Paulding.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be first and 10 for the Golden Tornadoes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Time out on the field.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be first and ten for the Mauldin Golden Tornadoes on the Mustang 32-yard line.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pass is incomplete.
[SPEAKER_03]: Penalty against Malden.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be second and 20.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pass intended for number 30, Kyle Paulding, is incomplete.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be third and 20 for Malden on the Mustang 42-yard line.
[SPEAKER_03]: Flag on the play.
[SPEAKER_03]: Penalty against Malden for holding.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the end of the first half with the score, the Malden Golden Tornadoes 22, the Meffern Mustangs zero.
[SPEAKER_03]: Fans, it is now time for some halftime entertainment.
[SPEAKER_03]: Please welcome the Malden High School Band.
Wait, like, five seconds.
You.
[SPEAKER_08]: John!
John!
Oh my God.
[SPEAKER_02]: The Wasabi Family Bowl raffle ticket winner is 9913991.
[SPEAKER_02]: An associate of the bowl game will contact you to schedule your ticket pickup.
you
Part four.
[SPEAKER_06]: Behind the steering wheel
[SPEAKER_08]: You got me in a spin, but everything is A-OK.
[SPEAKER_08]: Touching you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Medved said to receive the second half kickoff.
[SPEAKER_02]: I believe in a thing called love.
[SPEAKER_08]: Just look into the rhythm of my heart.
[SPEAKER_06]: There's a chance we can make it now.
[SPEAKER_06]: When I look into the sun goes down.
[SPEAKER_06]: I believe in a thing called love.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a flag on the play.
[SPEAKER_02]: Flag was a false start on Mauldin.
Stop him!
[SPEAKER_08]: Stop him!
[SPEAKER_02]: Touchdown Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mauldin's kickoff returned by number two, Stephens Exeter.
[SPEAKER_02]: Bedford's extra point is good.
It's Friday
[SPEAKER_02]: Midford's kick goes out of bounds.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up first down and 10 for Malden from their own 40 yard line.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number three, Davian McGuffey on the carry, tackled by a host of Bedford Mustangs.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up second down and 12 for Malden.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number three Davian McGuffey on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up third down and five for Malden.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number three, Davian McGuffey on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up fourth down and five from Aldon.
One, two, three, four.
Overrated.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up first down and 10 for Mauldin.
[SPEAKER_02]: The flag on the play.
[SPEAKER_02]: Holding on Malden.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number nine, Kevin Exelhom on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pushed out of bounds by number five from Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: Aiden Brett's pass to number nine Kevin Uxelholm is complete.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tackled by Emmett McGovern from Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up third down and five for Malden.
[SPEAKER_07]: All right, next time we do the wave side, we start from this side to this side, all right?
[SPEAKER_02]: Number nine, Kevin Exelhom on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tackled by number 10 from Medford, Cole Merino.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up fourth down and four from Aldon.
[SPEAKER_02]: Aiden Brett's pass to number two, Gabriel Cardoso-Vargas is incomplete.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll be a turnover on downs, first and 10 for Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number two on the carry for Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pass incomplete.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pass was broken up by number 52, James Hippolyte.
[SPEAKER_02]: Third down and nine for Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number 10, Justin Marino with the reception from Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: The result of the play is a Medford Mustang first down.
[SPEAKER_02]: Timeout Mauldin.
[SPEAKER_06]: I've been doing just fine.
[SPEAKER_06]: God, I gotta be down because I want it all.
[SPEAKER_06]: It started out with a kiss.
[SPEAKER_06]: How did it end up like this?
[SPEAKER_06]: It was only a kiss.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number 19, Brianna Carullo on the carry for Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up second down and one.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up third down and one for Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: Fumble on the play.
[SPEAKER_02]: Fumble recovered by number nine, Kevin Exelholm.
[SPEAKER_02]: Medford will retain possession
[SPEAKER_02]: Number two, Stephens, Exeter on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up second down and five for Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a fumble on the play.
[SPEAKER_02]: Fumble is recovered by number four, Formalden Andrew Lewis.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll be a turnover on downs, first and 10 for Mauldin.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's go Mauldin!
[SPEAKER_02]: Number nine Kevin Exelhom on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tackled by number 58 Jake McGovern for Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up second down and six for Malden.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number nine, Kevin Exelhom on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up third down and seven for Malden from their own six yard line.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number 11, Alexander Avalos on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: Darius Weeks on the tackle from Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up fourth down.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maldon's punt returned by number two.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number two, Stephens Exeter with the punt return.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tackled by number nine, Kevin Exelholm.
[SPEAKER_04]: ♪ I can't begin to knowin' ♪ ♪ But then I know it's growin' strong ♪
[SPEAKER_04]: Wasn't the spring, and spring became the summer.
[SPEAKER_04]: Who'd have believed you'd come along?
[SPEAKER_04]: Hand, touching hand.
[SPEAKER_05]: Reaching out, touching me.
[SPEAKER_02]: ♪ Look at the night ♪ Touchdown, Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number six, Luis Barboza on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: The result of the play is a Medford Mustangs touchdown.
Let's go Maldives!
[SPEAKER_02]: Medford's two point conversion is good.
[SPEAKER_08]: This place, pump it up!
[SPEAKER_02]: Number three, Davian McGuffey, and number nine, Kevin Echsholm set to return.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a flag on the play.
[SPEAKER_02]: Kickoff out of bounds.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up first and 10 for Mauldin.
[SPEAKER_02]: From the Midfield, 45 yard line.
[SPEAKER_02]: Aiden Brett's pass to number nine Kevin Exelholm is enough for a Mauldin first down.
[SPEAKER_02]: Injury timeout on the field.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up first and 10, Mauldin from the Medford 32 yard line.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number nine, Kevin Eltshul home on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tackled by number 51.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number 51, Christian Jordan from Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: Second down and 10 for Mauldin.
[SPEAKER_02]: Aiden Brett's pass to number two, Gabriel Cardoso-Vargas, is complete.
[SPEAKER_02]: That was Stephens-Exeter on the tackle from Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up first down and goal from Alden.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number nine, Kevin Exelholm on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tackled by number 51, Jordan Christian from Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up second down and goal from the Medford seven yard line.
[SPEAKER_02]: Touchdown, Malden.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number nine, Kevin Exelholm on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: The result of the play is a Malden High School touchdown.
Hey!
[SPEAKER_02]: Mauldin's two-point try is no good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't you know pump it up?
[SPEAKER_01]: You got to pump it up.
Don't you know pump it up?
You got to pump it up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number two and number 18 set to return from Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number two, Stephens Exeter on the return from Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up first down and 10 for Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: From their own 15 yard line.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number 10, Justin Marino on the carry for Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: The result of the play is a Medford-Mustang first down.
[SPEAKER_02]: First and 10, Medford from their own 36 yard line.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a flag on the play, Falstad Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number two, Stephens, Exeter with the reception.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up third down and 21 from Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: Medford's pass is intercepted by number 26, Felix DaCosta.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is a flag on the play.
[SPEAKER_02]: The penalty was a late hit out of bounds, Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up first down for Malden, first and 10.
[SPEAKER_02]: Aiden Brett's pass to number seven, Nathan Sullivan.
[SPEAKER_02]: The result of the play is a Malden High School Golden Tornado touchdown.
[SPEAKER_02]: Correction, number three, Davian McGuffey with the touchdown reception for Malden.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number 24, Darius Blaze on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: The two point conversion is no good.
let's go it's all about
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a flag on the play.
[SPEAKER_02]: Delay of game, Mauldin.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number 14, Aiden Brett's kick sails out of bounds.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up a first and 10 for Medford.
[SPEAKER_08]: Let's go, Maldives!
Let's go, Maldives!
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a flag on the play.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mauldin set the kickoff again.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mauldin's kick is recovered by number eight, Anthony DeFrenzo.
[SPEAKER_02]: First and 10, Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: Midford's pass to number 10, Justin Marino, is incomplete.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up second down and 10 for Midford.
[SPEAKER_02]: Medford's pass to number eight, Anthony DeFrenzo is incomplete, out of bounds.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up third down and 10 for Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pass is incomplete.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up fourth down and 10 for Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: From their own 47 yard line.
[SPEAKER_02]: Medford's pass to number two, Stephens, Exeter is incomplete.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll be a turnover on downs, first and 10 Mauldin.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll be first and 10 Mauldin from the Medford 47 yard line.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number nine, Kevin Exelholm on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up second down from Aldon.
[SPEAKER_02]: Second down and six from the Midfield, 43 yard line.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number nine, Kevin Exelholm on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tackled by number 52, Samuel Nazari.
[SPEAKER_02]: The result of the play is a Malden High School first down.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number nine Kevin Exelholm on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tackled by number 52 Samuel Nazari from Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up second down and 10 for Malden.
[SPEAKER_02]: from the Midfit 35-yard line.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number nine, Kevin Exselholm on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: Darius Weeks on the tackle from Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up third down and one for Mauldin.
[SPEAKER_02]: From the Medford 26 yard line.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number nine, Kevin Exelholm on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tackled by number 52, Samuel Nazari from Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number nine Kevin Exelholm on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up second down and eight for Mauldin.
[SPEAKER_02]: Number nine Kevin Exelhom on the carry.
[SPEAKER_02]: Tackle by number 11 from Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll bring up third down and nine for Mauldin.
[SPEAKER_02]: The final score from historic Fenway Park, Mauldin 34,
[SPEAKER_02]: Members, 15.