Breaking news this afternoon at Medford High School.
One student is in custody after a violent fight inside a boys bathroom.
WBC's Jordan Jagelinser is there at the high school where we're learning another student was injured as well.
Jordan.
MEDFORD HIGH SCHOOL IS NO LONGER ON LOCKDOWN AFTER WHAT HAPPENED HERE EARLIER THIS MORNING.
BUT STILL POLICE ARE ON SCENE.
STUDENTS ARE STARTING TO LEAVE.
THEY WERE GIVEN THAT OPTION ONCE THE LOCKDOWN WAS LIFTED AT LUNCHTIME.
BUT PARENTS HERE GATHERED THIS MORNING WORRIED, HOPING TO PICK UP THEIR CHILDREN AFTER HEARING THAT A STUDENT WAS STABBED IN THE BATHROOM.
You know, these kids have to know that everybody is following the rules so that they follow the rules.
There has to be consequences for actions.
Now students tell us it happened on the second floor.
We do know at this time that that student has non life threatening injuries.
There's also a juvenile suspect who is in police custody at this time.
We do not know the weapon that was used, but certainly the community here on edge after learning about the violence that unfolded here today in Medford, Jordan Jaglins are WBZ news.