Facing angry parents and a lot of questions, Medford's school superintendent will retire early.
This news comes a week after we learned that he knew about ammunition found in the middle school weeks before anyone reported it to police.
Thanks for joining us tonight.
I'm Lisa Hughes.
And I'm David Wade.
His retirement is not the only change.
Louisa Moeller joins us now with more on the breaking story tonight.
Louisa?
Well, David, Lisa, this all wrapped up less than an hour ago.
The school committee deciding to hold a security audit of all Medford schools and to appoint a new security director.
That and the decision about the superintendent taking them more than four hours.
Supporters of Roy Belson broke into applause as the mayor of Medford commended his 50 years of service to Medford Public Schools.
After a school committee meeting that lasted hours behind closed doors, the crowd learned that the superintendent will retire more than a month early on April 30th, a compromise after many parents called for him to step down.
Well, naturally, you know, I wouldn't like my career to end this way, but it's, you know, but I think that we've still been able to do a lot.
Remember, this is 50 years, 23 as superintendent.
The calls came when the public learned that a loaded gun magazine was found in the McGlynn Middle School back in December.
And while cleaning out his office, the principal inadvertently threw it away.
Belson admits he did not inform police.
Cops finding out about the clip more than two months later.
Belson has now apologized.
But some kids and parents say they still don't feel safe.
A decision was made that people don't agree with.
but it also set off a whole series of concerns in the community and that's never was my intent.
The principal of the McGlynn Middle School is on administrative leave and we learned tonight that the principal of McGlynn Elementary School also knew about that ammunition long before police did.
Live in Medford, Louisa Moeller, WBZ News.
Louisa, thank you.
Tonight we are on