[SPEAKER_00]: Hey, Councilor Matt Leming here.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm a scientist, I'm an affordable housing activist, I'm a military brat, and I'm proud to represent you on City Council.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I'm excited to announce that I'm going to be running for a second term.
[SPEAKER_00]: Two years ago, I promised transparency, I promised to address Medford's thinning budget, I promised to invest in more affordable housing, and I've kept those promises.
[SPEAKER_00]: This past City Council has been the most productive that Medford has seen in literally decades.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're investing in our public schools.
[SPEAKER_00]: We saved 40 teaching jobs.
[SPEAKER_00]: We hired a dedicated crew to repair our roads and sidewalks.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're reaching out to more residents with a newsletter, listening sessions, live streaming.
[SPEAKER_00]: City Council is now completely rezoning the city to build more affordable housing, mandate greener building practices, and bring in more commercial revenue.
[SPEAKER_00]: I worked with the city and local nonprofits to create programs dedicated to housing veteran renters, and I'm working with parents of youth with disabilities to create programming to support their kids.
[SPEAKER_00]: And together, we're going way further than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right now, the federal government is abducting our neighbors and trying to sow fear in the community, so local government is pushing back.
[SPEAKER_00]: I worked to make Medford into a sanctuary city, and I spearheaded a campaign to teach migrant communities their rights to keep them safer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Together, we need to keep fighting, we need to keep winning, we need to keep this upward trend going, we need to keep Medford inclusive.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm so proud of the progress that we've made, and I'm so grateful that more and more people want to call Medford home.
[SPEAKER_00]: Come to my campaign kickoff on June 14th.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'd love to have you there.