Hey Medford Bites listeners, today will be the last episode until the fall. We will be taking a summer break and giving the podcast some much needed attention. Hope you take the last few weeks of summer to rest, recharge, and catch up on any episodes you may have missed. If you have any feedback as we transition to an updated podcast, please email
medfordpod at gmail.com. And make sure to follow Medford Bites Pod on Instagram for more updates. Today's episode was recorded several weeks ago and includes an interview with Nicole Massalam about her race against Paul Donato for state representative. Make sure you get out to vote in the primary on September 5th. Hope you enjoy the episode and the rest of your summer.
All right, thanks so much for joining me today. If you don't mind just starting by introducing yourself with your name and pronouns and just a word or two about who you are. Yeah, thank you. Pleasure to be here. My name is Nicole Masalam, she and her. And I guess you could say, you know, I'm just a hardworking mom who cares about the community and do my best to help as many as I can. Thank you. Yeah. And, um,
We know that you aren't a resident of Medford, but a question that I always ask every guest is what their favorite place to eat is in Medford and what they like to eat there.
Oh, so we, you know, since we've been campaigning and door knocking, you know, where we've been trying out all the different, you know, cafes and hidden gems of Medford. And I got to say, we stumbled across one called Neighborhood Kitchen, which they have really great ethnic food. And it's really hard to pick a favorite on their menu. Because yeah, they're that good.
I've heard about their red velvet waffles. We've had their mac and cheese before. It's good. Yeah. It's a good choice. Do you want to introduce your, uh, your, uh,
Oh, my little helper slash campaign intern, Yara. She's five years old and she's mommy's big helper. You want to say hi, Yara? Hi. Well, I'm glad to have you here, Yara. And it's always important to have a helper. Great. So I was hoping we could talk a little bit about your campaign. So if you could just sort of name what you're running for, kind of what is prompting you to run.
Sure. So I'm running for state representative of the 35th Middlesex District. And really, you know, I've always had, you know, a passion for community service, as well as, you know, building bridges and of understanding within our community.
And I would have to say what really started me to understand the motivation for running for this particular office, you kind of have to understand what got me interested in politics in the first place. So I come from, my day job is being a mosque director. I do a lot of interfaith work and community aid work because of that. And I've been doing that here in Massachusetts since we moved here in 2013.
So we, you know, I've done work with, you know, government relations, law enforcement relations, media, as well as, you know, like I mentioned, interfaith. And that's always been a passion because I view it as helping to create and build a world that my children will be accepted in. You know, they're mixed.
my husband's from Egypt, so I have, you know, one child who's, you know, really light-skinned, blonde hair, blue eyes, and I have another son who's really dark-skinned, dark hair, dark eyes, and so coming from that type of mixed family, I really want my children to, you know, be accepted for who they are, for their faith and their cultural identity, so
you know, that's, that was the driving motivation for all of that. But then, you know, 2016 happened, and we kind of know what, you know, all of the tension was heightened, the rhetoric that was used, and all of a sudden, instead of viewing each other as neighbors and community members, many people, especially from different faith communities, racial and ethnic communities were otherized. And they,
they were blamed for things that were beyond their control, or that they had absolutely nothing to do with. And it was during all of that time, that my then eight year old son came home crying, very upset. And, you know, we had, obviously, I wanted to know what was bothering him. And
You know, after a little bit of digging, he finally explained to me that he was crying because some kids at school told him that they didn't like Muslims. And if Trump were elected, he was going to get rid of all the Muslims. And my son who was born here, raised here.
You know, I'm someone who's very involved in the community. He goes to, like, I bring my children with me everywhere. We're part of the fabric of this community. And for him to suddenly feel like he didn't belong, that he wasn't welcome, it broke my heart. And I suddenly knew that
you know, as much work as I've been doing in the community, it wasn't enough because we had been completely forgetting one very important sphere of influence, which is politics, where policies are made. And it was our political leaders at that time that were creating this mess. And none of them were hearing our voices. None of them understood our experiences because they
They didn't take the time or the effort to do so. And so I was really faced with this area of, I guess, negligence that we had been neglecting.
And so that's when I really started on this process of learning more about issues and advocacy and activism and getting involved in politics. And so I really started, you know, diving in, initially beginning with Our Revolution Massachusetts, becoming one of the very first co-chairs of that organization, helping to build a structure that nurtured and created a welcoming environment for activists
of all backgrounds. And then, you know, looking into running for office I ran for school committee here in Malden, and I began learning in that process, so much of our government because up until that point, I was like most of, you know,
Americans, we just really didn't think about how our elected representatives really impact our lives. And so during that process of running for school committee, I learned about the school budget. I learned about, you know, other issues that are voted upon in the State House and in City Council. And I really began
Learning, you know how opaque our state houses. I learned about the funding formula for our schools that the legislature knew about it, that, you know, in here in Malden, they really were trying to do the best with the budget with what they were given, but they weren't given enough.
And our state legislature knew this. They had already done a study on the funding formula and still refused to take action. And this was before the Student Opportunity Act, by the way, which didn't even go far enough, in my opinion. And it's compounded every year. Every class that goes through our schools, we are failing because we haven't invested enough in their futures.
And so I suddenly learned it wasn't the school committee that I needed to go to or city council that I needed to go to. If I really wanted to make a lasting impact for our community and be able to help change the process so that people knew about it, knew what was going on, knew how votes were being carried out, especially in committees where most legislation, you know, dies pretty much.
I had to go to the state house. And so I had the, you know, a lot of people start reaching out to me and saying like, look,
We don't feel represented, we don't feel heard because our voices aren't getting through, especially members of the LGBTQ community. I mean, I think it's pretty well known that in our district we have a representative who has voted time and time again against the rights, the basic dignity of our LGBTQ brothers and sisters.
you know, among various other things. So just hearing that, that hurt, and hearing how they also had the same motivation that I had, you know, that we're not seen, we're not heard, we're screaming, but nobody's listening.
Yeah, I think you bring up a really good point that's very relatable when you're talking about how like our national politics trickle down even to like a state that we, I think, consider ourselves like pretty liberal in Massachusetts, right, but that these national attitudes about Islamophobia, homophobia, racism, when they're, I think what I heard a lot was like,
you know we know those feelings always existed here but there was more permission to express them after the 2016 election right and and I wonder too about that with the changes that we're seeing now so like threats to Roe v. Wade and how that would change just basic civil rights that we all have including same-sex marriage right and so how do you think about that as you're running like what is what are your sort of ideas or priorities there?
Well, regarding basic human rights and dignity, we have to protect it. I think a lot of people, as you mentioned, Roe v. Wade doesn't just impact access to abortion and complete reproductive health care. It affects, as you were saying, marriage equality, birth control, and various other things that we take for granted. Because the concept, the legal precedent that is set
was the right to privacy, which, you know, and, and we've had a lot of debate about this in my household, because my husband is currently in law school. And he just took a constitutional law class. So Roe v. Wade was one of the cases that he studied. And we talked about it, you know, pretty in depth. And, you know, the right to privacy is not specifically enumerated in
our Constitution. And Roe v. Wade was what established and enshrined that and codified it in our legal system. If you overturn Roe v. Wade, like you're affecting your basically everybody's right to privacy. And I know there are many people even who are more conservatively minded, who are like,
they wouldn't want that. So they really need to look beyond like the trigger and to the actual like meat and potatoes of the situation. Because this is something we do, we need to protect.
So I think we do need somebody who's elected, who's going to represent us, who will fight for those rights. And I'm not someone who would just fight for our rights. I believe we're a whole community and we're surrounded by other states. We may be different states, but we're one nation.
And so I believe we need to offer those protections. And now we're seeing other states come up with sanctuary laws, basically, stating that they won't extradite individuals or that they'll offer them these health care services that are vitally important. Talking about folks who are undocumented. Undocumented as well, yes. Because here's the thing.
Nationally, like at the federal level, they're the ones who deal with immigration. And the immigration system is broken. It's very difficult. I don't think people realize how difficult it is to come here legally. You know, I had to, I've been through it. I've seen it firsthand. You know, for my husband, I had to sponsor him. And I've helped other individuals.
with immigration. I mean, the fees are absolutely exorbitantly high, the waiting periods are high. They don't give the people, you know, when you do apply, they don't give you the opportunity to work. Because the processing takes so long, it's almost six months before you can get a work permit. But yet they're saying you can't have any public assistance.
So you are literally forced into a situation where you have to rely upon other people, which, you know, I was raised, you do whatever you can to support yourself, you know, relying on others is your last resort, basically. And I think a lot of people have that same value system. So I think we do need to open ourselves up to take a critical look at what we've
taken for granted. Everything is not how it was when my grandparents first came to this country.
when they were children. It's not how it was when our parents and our grandparents were growing up here. Yes, the home costs are exorbitantly high. Rent, housing in particular, when it's taking up, I think in some people's instances, almost two thirds of their income. When we know it shouldn't be more than half,
And even that's really high. But, you know, there's struggle.
Wages aren't keeping up. Cost of living is soaring. And I'm seeing it firsthand with the families that I help. And so I believe there is that disconnect. And I think we do need someone who understands the realities that working families are facing right now. I'm still, you know, our family is still paying student loans. My husband and I were still paying our student loans. My oldest just turned 14.
And he's going into high school next year. While still paying student loans and now paying a mortgage and trying to raise our three children, we have to worry about saving up for his college now too. And that's a cycle that's just going to repeat itself. So I'm like, how can we break this?
We're very blessed. I mean, I told you my husband's in law school. We work very, very hard. So we are definitely blessed more than most. But and we struggle. You know, we live paycheck to paycheck. And I can't imagine, you know, how it is for other families, especially during COVID.
And you met you mentioned the person that you're running against Paul Donato right he's been yes his position for like I want to say like 20 plus years.
Representative Donato is currently serving his 22nd year in office. OK. And so I think maybe 20 something years ago, he was somebody who reflected the needs of our community. Like he was a he he maybe represented a majority of maybe his people in his neighborhood. And that's changing. And I can see that power of having somebody who
at least like resembles their constituents right and like can speak to the needs of like the varied needs of the community actually had the chance to go to a fundraiser for Sonia Chang Diaz, and she was talking about like really similar issues right talking about the cost of living right the cost of mortgages rents, paying student loans that caught like having to worry about college and how there's
she was saying that, like, there's just this message from Beacon Hill of, like, you just need to wait on those things. And her real, like, immediacy around, no, we need to, like, close this sort of the racial wage gap. We need to think about free education. And how do you call a school like UMass a public school when you pay $30,000-plus a year for it, right? It sort of sounds similar to what you're saying. I'm glad to hear it.
I'm wondering about any reflections on the last time that you ran. So what are you thinking about anything differently? Were there things that surprised you about that process? Yeah, you know, the first time I ran, I was just surprised by the outpouring of support and how ready people were, you know, and saying, we do need someone who's
who's going to raise our concerns at the state house. And I think the most difficult thing was COVID hit during that time. One of the things I've loved the most about this process is meeting all of our neighbors and in doing anti-racism work and equity work and, you know, community building work. One of the very first things that I learned, you know,
I was an advisory board member for CARE, the Council on American Islamic Relations. And so we, you know, part of that mission is to combat Islamophobia. And so we learned that the best way to do that in study after study is just one-on-one interaction.
Like meeting your neighbors. And it's the same in the campaign world. I mean, one thing that I've learned about campaigning, the ground game, the canvassing, door knocking, is the end all be all of a campaign. That's what makes or breaks it. And we weren't able to do that in 2020 because of COVID.
And, you know, I'm very perceptively different. You know, I wear a scarf on my head and I look very ethnic. I joke sometimes that I'm an ethnic chameleon at times because someone will come up to me and they'll start talking in their language, assuming I'm from their country. I'll be like, what? You know, because of that,
perception, you know, people have misconceptions or stereotypes that go with that. And because I wasn't able to go and meet them on the doors or have these very important conversations to break down those barriers, you know, that's what made 2020 difficult. And I knew, and I was
very, very humbled that even without those conversations that 45% of the district still voted for me.
And that just, I think, spoke volumes of how much our district felt, you know, about their current representation. And not just that, but I mean, it was record breaking voter turnout that year, which was very surprising. I mean, looking back at previous voter turnout for this type of race, we're looking at a maximum of 44 to 5000 people voting total. Wow.
in the primary, and we had almost 10,000. Wow, that's great. So yeah, I mean, the turnout was almost double than what it had been previously. Yeah, and you mentioned that you noticed that because of the lack of ability to see people face-to-face, there were some maybe assumptions that they made about you. Would you share what some of those might have been? I received death threats. My car was vandalized.
Um, I mean, it is what it is and the type of work that I do. I mean, it's, I've experienced it before. And, um, again, you know, people make assumptions. Uh, so it, you know, facing that part of it is hard. Um, what makes it worthwhile for me though, is that, um,
I've been in the community for so long, and I have great relationships, friends and allies from, you know, across the spectrum, that, and I even have like very conservatively minded individuals, you know, neighbors.
who support me, we have great relationships. And they saw some of these comments, and they called these people out and said, like, look, you, you know, what you're saying is incorrect, you need to, like, if you want to say something, you know, say something, but do it respectfully or reach out to her. But, you know, don't
you know, say these awful things, don't be that angry. And I, in some instances, I've actually had individuals who will come to me and apologize. And then I'll be like, you know what, thank you for your apology. Like, what can we do to, you know, overcome this barrier? Can we now, you know, maybe have a conversation about for coffee, you know, something like that. And some of them end up becoming friends.
That's great. Yeah, I would say that's probably one of the things that I hear about Representative Donato is like that people can go to him and he can help solve problems that he has like those connections. It sounds like that's what you're sort of naming for yourself to write building those connections with community members, being able to sort of get things done and be open and available for people who need to reach out to you.
Yeah, and I respect that network too, as you were saying, Representative Donato, you know, has that. But now I'm starting to get community members reaching out to me. And like I had someone who, you know, is prominent in the Asian community and was saying, I have this program that I really want to do. What do you think? Do you have network and connection for me?
Uh, and I was like, yeah, I do. Like, here's, here's what I have for you. Uh, and you know what, but I think for the type of work that you're doing, why don't you reach out to rep Donato and, you know, and see, because he might have more connections. He's got a broader community maybe. Uh, and she was like, no, I, I did reach out to him and he had nothing for me. You've been far more helpful and.
You know, so to me, I think, you know, as you were saying, what you mentioned earlier, like when he was first elected, maybe he, and I don't doubt that he had good intentions. I don't doubt that he worked hard for the community or anything like that. And I think the true test isn't our age or how long we've been in an office. It really is our adaptability and our responsiveness to the community. And it's great that he's maintained relationships, but there are always new relationships or improvements to be had.
And I think that is where we're beginning to see the disconnect, to be able to keep up with the new community, the new neighbors, new families that are coming in and helping them to feel welcome and making sure that you proactively reach out to them and adapt to the changes that we're seeing within our community while maintaining your relationships.
Sure. And I think I know that initially, when I moved to Medford, I would get a birthday card from Representative Donato on my birthday. And that's all I knew about him was like, oh, he's a Democrat. Great. And I think there's an importance to thinking about that. OK, he's a Democrat, but what does that mean? And I assume you're running as a Democrat as well.
there are different types of Democrats. And I think that information that you provided about, like, how is he voted for for basic civil rights, right? How is he voted for in support of gay marriage, things like that? Like, I don't think people commonly know those things. Right. So I think it's important to be explicit about there's differences. Those differences exist even among Democratic candidates. It does. And here's the thing, you know,
I've learned a lot about the Democratic Party here in Massachusetts in recent years, since 2016. I joined our Democratic City Committee here in Malden. I became the chair of the Ward 7 Dems. And since then, I joined the Democratic State Committee. And I can tell you that there is a rising
you know, movement of, you know, people who want to see Democrats live up to our ideals. You know, every year we have this big convention. And every so often, we go through and we create this document of things that we stand for things that we're willing to fight for, you know, for our communities to for their improvement and betterment.
But we are not holding anybody accountable to that. We have Democrats, and I say that very loosely, that are elected to office who vote more Republican than Republicans do.
you know, you can take a look at the voting records and we have everything in between, you know, people who vote for almost every single democratic value that we have according to, you know, our, as we've outlined as a convention and as Democrats across Massachusetts, across the Commonwealth have voted upon and said, these are what we find important. So you have some elected officials who will vote for everything.
um you have some who vote for none of it vote against it and you know everything in between and I believe Donato falls in in the in between phase you know um but here's the thing I there are some things that we just cannot compromise on and like I said those are human rights basic human dignity and
I think it's great to show up for the community and show up at events to support individuals when wrongs are being committed, like we're seeing with mass evictions recently in Medford and in Malden. We have predatory developers and realtors buying up rentals, our rental stock, and then jacking it up exorbitantly high. But here's the thing, it's great to show up, but what really counts is your vote.
And so when you vote against, you know, common sense legislation to lift the, um, the ban on, uh, uh, uh, rent control, it doesn't matter if you, if you're showing up at events, you, you haven't taken concrete action. Right. It's like performative. Yeah. To create a better outcome when you're voting against marriage equality, basic
you know, rights and dignities for individuals to love who they love and build a relationship. And I've spoken with Representative Donato and I respect his beliefs, just, you know, I share similar beliefs when it comes to my faith, but I can't legislate that on people.
You know, I can't force that. And to be honest with you, I would rather people be able to openly love who they love in a committed relationship than to have to hide it. And, you know, not being able to be committed to each other or engage in
risky behaviors, you know? And to have legal protection as well. Legal protection too. You know, my sister married her wife in Utah. And here's what I mean. I see firsthand how it impacts people and why it is basic dignity. So in Utah at the time, there was a law in the state constitution that said if two people were married,
And even though the mom maybe became pregnant outside of marriage, even if it was a different father, that once you were married and the child was born in the marriage, the presumptive father was the one she married. And they would go on the birth certificate and they would have full parental rights. So this is what happened with my sister. She married her wife. Her wife was actually pregnant as a result of a non-consensual encounter.
And so they put my sister's name on the birth certificate. They wanted her to have full parental rights. But then the biological donor, sperm donor, as I'd like to say, came into the picture and tried to sue for parental rights. And my sister, who was the one who
you know, loved her wife, loved her son. This is my nephew. Had worked to keep a roof over their head, food in their mouth, health care services, you know, everything. She was a parent in every sense of the word, including love, which is the most important.
And we were family and they were going to give him parental rights because here's the clincher in the lot said presumptive father, not presumptive parent. Wow. And so my sister, God bless her, fought so hard.
for custody, for full parental rights, and had to hire an attorney. And the judge didn't want to rule because he was so scared because if he did it, it was going to change the Utah Constitution. And it was going to change the law. And he's like, I don't want to do this. I don't want to legislate from the bench, as we hear so often.
But, and it was pricey. So all of our family, we pulled together. I paid a hefty chunk and gave as much as we could from our family budget to pay for the attorney fees. And they changed the law. Wow. My sister's case made it so that everybody has equal opportunity for parental rights. So now the law doesn't state presumptive father anymore. It says presumptive parent.
Is this in Utah or is this- In Utah. Oh, wow. One of the most conservative states, you know, very Republican. Yeah. But, you know, I'm like, when you, it's an experience. You know, for me, it doesn't matter that my sister has a wife versus a husband. What matters to me is that she loves someone, she committed to them, and that there was a child
who was being, you know, maybe he wasn't conceived in ideal circumstances, but he was born into love, into a very loving relationship. And it didn't matter that they were two men or two women, a man and a woman. It doesn't matter. They were his parents. My sister was his mom.
There are certain things where labels don't matter. It's the love and the values that are underneath it all that matter. And so he's my nephew, I love him. And while my sister and her wife are no longer together, which was also a precedent-setting case in Utah, when they dissolved their marriage, they got divorced, and she still has custody of her son.
which is like the first case in Utah, again, where, you know, a same-sex parent, you know, who was not the birth parent still has custody of her son. I think that's a really important thing to think about too, because I think we think about, oh, well, like if the pressure for same-sex couples to have marriages that last forever and divorce, like, you know, we also deserve those same options of like, okay, well, we want to get married. And if it doesn't work out, we also want to have the rights to get divorced, right?
And to have rights to our children still. We're all like neighbors. We're all human beings. It doesn't matter. Like we all should be protected equally under the law. That's what our constitution says. We all have equal rights. And so we need someone who's going to stand up for that. Who's going to say, you know what?
equal protection under the law, whether it comes to marriage equality, whether it comes to the ability of trans individuals to exist in public spaces according to their gender identity, you know, they
deserve respect and dignity. And it's not just the LGBTQ plus community, as you were saying, now we're seeing Roe v. Wade and we're seeing the right to privacy under attack. I mean, so many things that we've taken for granted over the years, you know, and so many people use it as validation to just, I don't need to go vote. Well, guess what? Your vote matters because now everything that we've taken for granted, we're about to lose.
You know, I have friends who are saying they've never had to encounter this in their lifetime. They never thought they would. And it's just, it's, it's mind boggling. So to me, I'm like, we live in such unprecedented and dangerous times where we can't take anything for granted.
So we can't take it for granted that someone's gonna vote for us when they have a track record of not. I think there should be no doubt. We need someone in there.
who's going to respect that and who's going to vote accordingly. And, you know, we don't. And I only speak to recorded votes. I know vote after vote against the rights of individuals, against affordability for our housing on record, mind you. And so many other things. I mean, part of
were in one of the most regressive tax systems in the U.S. is Massachusetts. I know we hear Taxachusetts, but that's no longer the case. In fact, those of us who are in the bottom income brackets, studies have shown through, I believe, the Mass Budget Policy Center. If I remember correctly, I always get the acronyms wrong, but
But the study shows that those of us in the bottom income brackets, we're paying, in effect, almost 10% of our annual income in taxes, while those who are at the top, who can afford it, mind you, like our millionaires, are paying, in effect, 6% of their annual income.
And so can you, if we were all paying exactly the same percentage of our annual income, which is what the state constitution says, we were all paying our fair share, we would be able to fund our schools and invest in the future of our children. We would be able to, you know, take care of our lead pipes that are over a hundred years old that are currently poisoning our water supply or pave our roads so that I don't have to go and realign my car like three times in one year.
and pay exorbitant prices to the mechanic. Even just the smallest things like the state of our roads end up costing our families more money when they're already on a strained budget.
These are all great points. I'm wondering if, so one question I like to ask people that are like political candidates is just sort of a more personal question. So, and I appreciate you told us a lot of personal reflections, but is there something that you want to share that like might surprise us? So something about us that you wouldn't typically share or like is like a fun fact.
Sure. So, despite how I look now, I was actually raised Roman Catholic, and I have, I come from a very musical family. We all love to sing together, so I am a trained singer, and I sang for Pope John Paul the second and saying mass at the Vatican Sunday mass.
Wow, those are surprising facts about you. Thanks for sharing that. Well, Nicole, thank you. Is there anything else that we haven't talked about that you'd want to share or anything else you think is important for us to know?
You know, I think I have a passion for for helping people and win or lose. I'm still going to continue to do that. But, you know, if what I've said, you know, resonates with anybody who's listening. We can't.
do this without you. Like it takes a lot, and we really want to reach every single voter in a meaningful relationship building way. And so we need volunteers to come and help us knock on doors, and I am.
you know, and this takes money, too. We need resources. And so I'm not taking any special interest money. I'm not taking any money from these, you know, big PACs or special interest groups of any means. It's it's one on one donations. I really want to be funded by our community, whether it's twenty five dollars or a thousand dollars or anything in between or even less. We have everything, you know,
And so just if this is something that you believe or that you could get behind, please show it in any capacity that you're able to. Yeah. Is there a website we can find more information at? Yeah. Vote Masalam. So that's V-O-T-E M-O-S-S-A-L-A-M dot com. Thank you. I'll be sure to include that in our show notes. People can access that too. Great. Well, I really appreciate you taking the time to talk with us and we'll look forward to the results of the election.
Great. Thank you. Thank you.
Thanks so much to Nicole and to all the loyal listeners of this podcast. I have had a transformative time this year working on the podcast, getting to know so many great people, and amplifying the work of so many Medford folks. Please be sure to share your thoughts about the podcast by reviewing it on Apple Podcasts or sending me an email at medfordpod at gmail.com. Thanks so much for listening. Guys, what's the name of the podcast? Medford Bites! Medford Bites!
Hey, good job.