We can start recording and I'll at least read the agenda.
I know member Reinfeld will be right with us.
Recording in progress.
Thank you.
The Memphis School Committee has a special meeting on September 25th, 2024 at 4 p.m.
to be held via Zoom.
The purpose of this meeting is provided in the agenda section below.
The meeting is being recorded.
The meeting can be viewed live on Medford Public Schools YouTube channel through Medford Community Media or on your local cable channel, Comcast 9, 8, or 22, and Verizon channel 43, 45, 47.
Again, the meeting will be recorded.
Since the meeting will be held remotely, participants can log or call in by using the following information.
The Zoom link is provided on the city and school website, and the meeting ID is 975-6605-8577.
Questions or comments can be submitted during the meeting by emailing medfordsc at medford.k12.ma.us.
Those submitting questions or comments must include the following information, your first and last name, your Merfitt Street address, your question or comment.
Member Rousseau, if you could call the roll.
Certainly.
Member Brantley.
Present.
Member Graham.
Here.
Member Antapa.
Member Olopade.
Here.
Member Reinfeldt.
Present.
Member so present, Mayor Longo-Kern.
Present, seven present, zero absent.
If we could all rise to salute the flag.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America, to the republic for which it stands, one nation under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all.
We have executive session pursuant to Chapter 30A, Section 21.2, to conduct strategy and preparation with non-union personnel or contract negotiations with non-union personnel, superintendent of schools.
Is there a motion to go into executive session?
Motion.
By Member Rousseau, seconded by?
Second.
Member Graham, roll call vote, please.
Member Brantley?
Yes.
Member Graham?
Member Atapa?
Yes.
Member Olopade?
Thank you.
Member Rheinfeldt?
Yes.
Members say yes, Mayor Lingo-Kern.
Yes, seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative.
Motion is approved to go into executive session.
And will we be coming back to regular session?
I assume now we have to.