The 28th regular meeting of the Medford City Council will come to order. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Camuso? Present. Councilor Caviello? Present. Councilor Knight? Present. Vice President Ronald Kern? Present. Councilor Marks? Present. Councilor Penta? Present. President DelaRusso? Present. Seven members present, none absent. Please rise to salute the flag.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America, and to the republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all. The chair recognizes Councilor Carviello for a motion to suspend the rules. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion granted. Suspension of the rules to take one paper out of order, that being
Request for expenditure from the law department claims over $1,000. Communications from the mayor, 15-681, dated September 24th, 2015, to President DelaRusso, members of the Medford City Council, from Mayor Michael J. McGlynn, claimant's name, Adrian Napel, and John Grebe. Date of settlement, September 24th, 2015. Amount requested, $24,000.
claimant's attorney, Adam Sherwin Esquire. Description of alleged claim, the city of Medford, the Medford Brooks Estate Land Trust, and Adrian Appel, John Grebe, the caretakers of the Brooks Estate, desire us to settle the various issues relating to the caretakers' residency at Brooks Estate that include, but are not limited to, the caretakers having become parents of a newborn baby girl during 2014, and the presence of lead in a historical structure such as the Brooks Estate,
that contains various levels of lead. A copy of the lease and settlement agreements is attached to this request. Breakdown on the request totals out to $24,000. And present here with us this evening is the city solicitor to speak to us on this matter. Mr. Solicitor. Thank you, Mr. President, members of the council. My name is Mark Rumley. I'm the city solicitor. I reside at 50 Woodrow Avenue in Medford.
This matter has been talked about with the Council a few times over the past, I'd say, 8 to 10 weeks. It would have come before you tonight with an adjusted signed agreement. There had been some changes because of the time that's passed since this was first submitted to the Council, and I wanted to avoid giving you the amended or adjusted agreement
so that you just would be receiving it tonight and not have had the opportunity to read it. Um, and so, uh, with the agreement of the, uh, of Mr. Sherwin, we'd asked the council if you would be so gracious as to, uh, table this. So I have it come up again next week. And I can assure you that in your packets on Friday, if not before electronically, a copy of the, uh, agreement with the changes will be before you. What I wanted to avoid is the,
is the reasonable complaint that you just got that paper tonight and you hadn't had an opportunity to review it. The changes are drastically different from the original, but nonetheless, as a matter of courtesy, we'd ask for this matter to come up next week. So on the motion of Council on the night to table the matter? Mr. President, I'll put it before you.
Mr. Rumley, if we — can we ask a question through you that you can relay to maybe Embelt or whoever you've been dealing with to put this settlement together? Mr. Rumley. I would have no difficulty with you asking a question. Not at all. The President. Okay. My question would be the fact that there were caretakers in there since 2007. And at the time, I believe they said it was a necessity to keep vandalism down and also to maintain the
integrity of the building. They were responsible for certain functions. And my question is, what will be from here on in, after this, if and when this agreement is approved, what will be the management and what will be the protocol for the upkeep of that particular building? Will there be a need for caretakers again? I think that's a reasonable and prudent question, and we'd certainly be able to provide you with a response. Thank you.
So on the motion to table by Councilor Knight, which is undebatable, roll call has been requested on that motion. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Luccio? Councilor Cabriello? That was a yes. Councilor Knight? Yes. Vice President Malauulu?
Yes, with a vote of six in the affirmative, one absent. The motion to table passes. Thank you very much. Thank you, Mr. Solicitor. On the motion of Councilor Caviello to revert back to the regular order of business.
Yeah, and what number is that here? Oh, yeah, 15-420, Mr. President. On the motion of Councilor Caviello to take 15-420 off the table. All those in favor? Those opposed? Motion is before us. 15-420, Keena Togo, Asha Patel, Spring Street, Super-Ed.
88 Spring Street in Medford. Counselor, as chairman of the licensing subcommittee, could you bring us, refresh our memories on this? Yes, Mr. President, this motion had been denied because it had to go back to the Lottery Commission. It has since been approved by the Lottery Commission, and it's been approved in a public hearing by the Board of Appeals. So at this point, Mr. President, the papers are in order.
And a motion for approval. Could you, can we have a read? Is there synopsis of the decision? Do you want me to read it? Please. The board visited the premises of 88 Spring Street and observed a spacious area adjacent to the primary retail portion of the store where petitioner purposes to install the keynote monitor and seating. The board found the area to be clean and convenient,
without apparent interruption of the routine traffic at the retail side of the store. Petitioner Asha Ben-Patel and her husband had operated Spring Street Super Red at 88 Spring Street for a number of years prior to the husband's premature death in 2014 at the age of 49. Petitioner continues to operate the popular convenience store, including at Commonwealth of Massachusetts Lottery Station and at Takeaway Commonwealth Massachusetts Kino Station.
while not directly related to the criteria required for the granting of a variance. DeVore was nevertheless impressed with the petitioner's reputation and worth, as well as her child's academic performance at UMass. Very good. So on the motion for approval by Councilor Caviello, all those in favor? Councilor Penta? Quick question. Is this just because the husband died and it's a change in name? Is this what we're doing? No, they had asked for the license.
And it had expired, so they needed to go to the Board of Appeals to change the zoning for a variance. And the variance had been granted. And the license was granted by the Commonwealth of Mass also. Is the petitioner present? No. This was delivered to me. Well, I don't understand. Why did it have to go to the Board of Appeals? Not conforming use.
Mr. Clerk, if you could refresh our memories. The clerk's going to speak now. I'll go back to the paper. This took place in, it was a non-conforming, if I recall, Mr. Clerk. April 22nd, around there. It was a non-conforming use. And they had Kino to go. And their application was Kino with a monitor. And that would have needed a variance to conduct that.
So we, so the council at that night couldn't grant a no objection. They sent them back to go get a variance from the board of appeals, which they did. The board of appeals granted the variance. Mr. President, can we get a copy of that law, that requirement that says that they had to go to the board of appeals?
I don't remember ever seeing that. I think we sent it to the table based on that. No, I know, but I'd like to see that. So for the future, we know. The councilor just received that decision. So the clerk will send that out to us. But if that's a Zoning Board decision? Board of Appeals made a decision on June 30th. When was the public hearing on that? June 30th. Of this past year? Yes. For this? Yes.
To the change, Kano to go, not this. That was done by the state, but as I say, the permit was refused on April 29th. They applied for a variance and they went before the Mass State Lottery Commission. And they were approved then also. So the Mass State Lottery Commission approved it? Yes.
and then it had to come back to the city, and then it had to go to the Board of Appeals, because apparently that's not in our zoning ordinance, is that correct? Is that in our zoning ordinance now and been advertised? Is that now in our zoning ordinance that's been advertised? I don't remember seeing that come before the council for an advertisement. They came before the council. Point of information, Councilor Camuso. Just to clarify for Councilor Pinto, they came before us on April 28th, and we tabled the matter pending
the Board of Appeals as well as Mass State Lottery. It's actually unfinished business still. I understand that. I want to make sure that I understand that. Rick, are you saying that subsequent to us tabling this, they had to take that back to the Mass State Lottery? Yes. And they approved it? Yes. And then it came back here to the Board of Appeals in June, you said? They had a hearing on June 30th. Okay. Can we get copies of that, please? Yes, it's in our packet.
No. The clerk will send us copies in our next packet. So, Councilor Knight wishes to speak. Mr. President, I just ask that I be recorded in opposition to the measure. I don't feel as though we need keynote followers in our convenience stores. Very good. So on the motion of Councilor Caviello for approval, which would be non-opposition. All those in favor? Aye. Aye.
Opposed? Councilor Knight. Motion carries. So on the motion of Councilor Caviello to revert back to the regular order of business. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Motion granted. Hearings 15-629 City of Medford notice of public hearing. A public hearing will be held by the Medford City Council in the Howard F. Alden Memorial Auditorium City Hall, 86 George P. Assett Drive, Medford, Massachusetts on Tuesday evening, September 29th,
2015 at 7 PM, on a petition from Asian Palace doing business as Shanghai Moon for special permit to amend its hours of operations in accordance with Metro Zoning Ordinance Chapter 94, Section 94 to 145, to operate extended hours at its business at 442 Salem Street, Metro Massachusetts. On said site being located in the C1, that's commercial one, zoning district.
The amendation is for Sunday, Monday, Tuesday, and Wednesday, 11 p.m. to 12 a.m., and Thursday, Friday, and Saturday from 11 p.m. extended to 1 a.m. Petition and plan may be seen in the office of the city clerk, Medford City Hall, Medford, Massachusetts. Call 781-393-2425 for any accommodations.
etc., etc., by order of the City Council, Edward P. Finn, City Clerk, advertised in Medford Daily Mercury, September 15th and September 22nd, 2015. When we have a portion of our meeting that's a public hearing, what we do is we first invite those who are in favor to just come up and state they are in favor of this measure. And then you may be seated.
Once all those who are in favor and acknowledge they are in favor of this are finished, we close that portion of the meeting, then invite all those up to state whether they are in opposition to that. Once people have just made the simple statement that they're in opposition, we close that portion of the public hearing, and then we go into the discussion phase to hear the merits presented by both parties, whether those are in favor and those are opposed.
And then the council has the opportunity to speak, perhaps ask questions, and then render its decision. So now that the public hearing is open, the chair invites those who are in favor to come forward to the podium and to identify yourself by your name and address and state that you are in favor.
Good evening, everyone. My name is Thomas Dobbins. I live at 84 Whitty Road. I've been a Medford resident for 35 years, and I'm here to voice my OK for the proposal. My wife and I have known the proprietors going back through Panda Palace to their next iteration to what is now Shanghai Moon. So you're in favor. Sorry? You're in favor. We are in favor. Thank you. Anybody else in favor?
Please come forward and state that you're in favor. Share your name and address for the record, please. Good evening, everyone. My name's Anthony Rivera. I live at 144 Fells Ave. in Medford. And I am in favor of it. Yes. Thank you very much. Thank you, Anthony. Sir, welcome. Steve Monahan, 213 Park Street. And I'm in favor. In favor. Evening. Maritza Carmely, 19 Pitcher Avenue. I'm in favor.
My name is Dwight Fee, also at 19 Pitcher Avenue in Medford, and I'm in favor. Very good. Jennifer Howe, 129 Waterville Road, Medford, Mass., and I'm in favor. Welcome, thank you. Matthew Arklope, 129 Waterville Road, Medford, Mass., in favor. Very good. Jackie Rivera, 296 Fulton Street, and I'm in favor. Jesse Ferricano, 132 Grand Ave., I'm in favor.
43 Brackett Street, Meffitt, in favor. It's a good hard working kids, give them a shot. Thank you. Robert Capucci, 71 Evans Street. To be clear, this is on extending the hours at each place. I am in favor, but I
I would request that you listen to the neighbors that might live there and maybe do like... Thank you. As stated at the beginning of this portion, we explained that that would happen. Oh. Thank you, John. George Theriot, business owner, 440 Salem Street, Medford. I'm heartily in favor. Janet Donnelly, Three Gibson Circle, and I'm completely in favor of this. Thank you.
Steven Papio, 18 Newton Road, Medford, and I'm in favor of this. Thank you. Michelle Respo, 293 Spring Street Extension, and I'm in favor of this. Very good. Anybody else in favor? I'm Danny Grafalis. I live on 229 Lawrence Road in Medford, and I'm the owner of the building on 442 Salem Street in Medford.
And I'm here to support the people, spend a lot of money up there. They put a lot of hours up there. They try to make very honest living. The building is getting to be very, very expensive up there. I pay $14,500 a year and it's going up all the time. Thank you very much. Thank you. Anybody else in favor? Hearing and seeing none, we declare that
portion of the meeting closed. Anybody in opposition? Anybody in opposition, please present yourself to the rostrum and state your name and address for the record. Good evening, councillors. Are you here in opposition? We're in opposition. Sorry, I'll get right away. I'm in favor. Dominic Camara, 219 Lawrence Road. Thank you. I am definitely in favor. Thank you. Hi. Welcome.
Hi, Marion DePaulo, 50 Lambert Street, Medford. I'm opposed. Thank you. Good evening. Steven DePaulo, 50 Lambert Street. I'm opposed. My name is Ray Ganey. I live at 48 Lambert Street, and I'm opposed to this. Joe Bianco, Lambert Street. I'm against it.
Lucrecia Velez, 45 Lambert Street, president for 33 years and I'm in opposition. Nestor Velez, 45 Lambert Street, I oppose it. Ashley Sanchez, 45 Lambert Street, in opposition. Thank you very much. So now that, is anybody else in opposition wishes to be recognized?
Hearing and seeing none, we declare that portion of the meeting closed. So now we open this up to discussion. So if the petitioner wants to present themselves at the podium and explain their operation to us and what they wish to do, you're welcome to do that now. Yep. Are you the petitioner? No, I'm not a petitioner. No?
It's always good to hear from the petitioner first. Welcome. Please state your name and address for the record. My name is Leo. This is my partner, Sean. We're both on the Shanghai moon. He was previously on my parents. We come here to apply for the extended hours because we spend a lot of money investing in this property, and we want to make a living.
Because I've been working in Bedford for a few years, since my parents and I moved out of the city. And I think the reason we want to expand our business is also we want people to come to Bedford, to come here, to come to my restaurant, to enjoy the time.
Hi, my name is Sean. My English is not very well, and everything Leo already said, so I just want to say one thing. I'm an immigrant, and Memphis, let me tell you, is like my hometown.
And I'm not the only one to make business. I want to be a very nice neighbor in the neighborhood. And I think now is the time to return to the other people, support me, and return the community, and return to the neighborhood. Yeah. Thank you both very, very much. Mr. President? Could Councilor Camuso?
Thank you Mr. President and I'd just like to go on record in supporting this this evening. This is a long time business in our community. A lot of Medford people support the business and
They have been good neighbors. I haven't received complaints regarding them over the years as a city councilor. And where it's going from one generation to the next, I think that they'll still continue the way the parents left off. And if I know Mr. Wu, he will be having his thumb on the business as well, making sure you boys are keeping it as clean and as good a neighborhood establishment as he always has. So I will support this this evening.
Does anybody else want to speak on this matter before the council? Either in favor or in opposition. Please come on up and state your name and address again for the record. Hello again. Maritza Carmely, 19 Pitcher Avenue in Medford. And I just wanted to say a few things about what I've observed about this restaurant since my husband and I started going there a few years ago.
What I can say for sure is talk about the character of the family that owns the restaurant. They're incredible people. They've put a lot of work into the renovations. It's my understanding from talking to them that by not being able to stay late, like other restaurants in Medford are permitted to do, and I understand it's a variance issue, but other restaurants are permitted to do it, and by not being able to do so, they're losing incredible revenue. I think I'd heard somewhere up to $10,000 a month
in lost revenue. I'm not sure where that number comes from, but obviously the owners do. And that's an important number, I think, in terms of whether this place can succeed. I can speak to the character of the staff that works there. I can speak to the character of the clientele that goes there.
Since it's been renovated, it was a terrific place as Panda Palace, but now that it's been renovated, it has more of an upscale feel. I don't know if people here have been there, but it has a much more of an upscale feel, and so I think that's going to attract the kind of community that we Medford residents want to have there. As you know, Wellington is just down the street with Yokey and all the other fancy places down there, and I believe that
Asia, I'm sorry, that Shanghai Moon can compete with those restaurants just down the street, and so I think they need to be given the chance. And so I want to suggest that that's an important thing. And as a Medford resident and as a sports fan, we don't have sports places to go to, and that's another important reason why I think they should be allowed to succeed.
But all in all, it really goes to the character of the people there and knowing that they will keep it as a clean and upscale establishment. Thank you. Thank you. If I may again, I'm sorry. I'm fighting a cold. I'd like to go home to bed. But I'd like to make a point that we know these people. We find them to be upstanding.
honest, good people with a very good business acumen for their young ages. I own a business myself, and the margin between success and outright failure is razor thin. To deny these people, as this young woman said, a chance to make extra money and cover costs in those beginning years and getting established could mean the difference between them making it and plunging the place into poverty. I've seen it too many times. I've been in this town 35 years. We've come a long way.
But I think we've also collectively made some bad decisions. And I think this would be a good decision. I don't think you'll ever have any bad feedback about these people. So, I am hold hardly for it. Thank you for listening. Thank you very much. Your name and address again for the record. George Farrott, building owner, business owner, 440 Salem Street, Medford. Member of the Chamber of Commerce, Board of Directors,
speaking here as part of all those roles, because independent business people need all the help they can get. If we want to be fan-friendly, so to speak, we need to give an equal playing field to the people who want to work hard, as these people have been and will continue to do. The atmosphere that they have created with the money that they have spent, I think will bring in the
crowd that will respect the property around them. I don't think there's ever been any issue. You'd have to speak to the police department about that. Prior, as all licenses, once issued, if there's a problem, you pull it. Let's give them an equal shot at what everyone else in the city has. I think Mei Ling's has got 3 AM. Lantana's, I think, has one. Carroll's, I mean, none of them are handcuffed with 11 PM.
And I think they deserve every chance for it, because that's what we should do in America, give people a chance to make a living. Thank you. Thank you, James. Anybody else want to speak on this matter?
I live pretty much directly across from this restaurant, and I just have to say that I was very happy when they opened up because it's a nice, clean place. It's beautiful inside, and it provides a great atmosphere to just have a nice meal and be able to have somewhere to actually hang out at night that's a decent place in our neighborhood.
And as far as being noise complaints or anything like that, I don't have any noise complaints against them. I feel it's been, I can't hear anything from them like as far as since their business started because somebody keeps putting letters on our doors of our apartment building trying to like sabotage their business saying that we should go complain about the noise.
But the thing is, there is no noise. The college kids across the street throw louder parties than what I ever hear from this restaurant. So I really hope that we can give their business a chance to thrive, because they really do provide something nice for the community to enjoy. So I think we should support that. Thank you. Thank you. Anybody else wish to speak?
Good evening. Marion DePaola, 50 Lambert Street. My husband, Stephen. Stephen DePaola, 50 Lambert Street. Welcome. We are both opposed to this. Both of us, my husband's lived here for his entire life on Lambert Street. Since I got married, I've been here since 1997. 1977, I'm sorry. It's 38 years. I've been here 65.
I'm so sorry. OK. Earlier, I just passed out a copy of the abuttus list. The reason I did that, living right across the street from the property, I didn't receive an abuttus list. So I got concerned, and I went down and obtained a copy. You'll notice there's like 18 mail outs on that. I just hand wrote to make it a little easier to follow along.
Out of the 18, 12 were sent to the commercial properties and six to the residential people. That's two-thirds to the commercial and one-third to the residential. I thought that was just a little lopsided and was a little concerned with that. I just want to make that clear. Also, too, the people on Spring Street Extension, not one,
homeowner received a direct abuttus notice. That particular property, the door entrance, has been relocated. It empties out right onto Lambert Street and right at the corner of Spring Street Extension. I felt as though at least one abuttus should have been notified of that. That's just my feeling. They went all the way across to the MBTA, and the city parking lot
gardener got his notice. So City Hall sent out a certified letter back to City Hall. I think a resident should have received something like that. Maybe just consider that something in the future if something comes before you, and it's residents. And I want to make this clear. This isn't residents against the business people. I have supported the Salem Street business people for 38 years, and I will continue to do so. I've gone into Panda Palace.
Danny's Place, I'm going back to the 70s, Danny's Place, Panda Palace was there for 25 years, wonderful people. They came in and they also wanted the extended hours and the residents back then were highly opposed to it for the same reason as we are tonight. We are so close and every square in the city is unique. We are so close to these businesses and we have to come up with a way to coexist.
None of us here as resident side want to put anybody out of business. It's not good for the city. We want good business. We want strong business. We don't want anything boarded up in our city. The prior owners of Panda Palace, I got very friendly with them over the close to 25 years. And they were very successful, opened up a second restaurant down in Weymouth, put three kids through college,
sold their businesses, went off to Florida, and I believe that they're opening up Dunkin' Donuts down in Orlando in the nice climate. So they did that all within 10 p.m. and 11 p.m. 10 p.m. weeknights, 11 p.m. on the weekends. If a business is run well, it can be done. That's my feeling. People close their doors.
in that area, 5 o'clock, 6 o'clock, and it kind of staggers out. We feel, in the neighborhood, and being there so long, the quietness, it starts to die down around 11. The thought of anything being past 11 o'clock, 12 o'clock, is just, you're cutting that time, that downtime that you have till 5 o'clock the next morning, you've got to get up again. Now, it doesn't mean it's going to be a ballroom brawl, OK? It doesn't have to be police worthy.
It could be simple things. You have your windows open in the spring, summer, and fall. Loud voices, happy people out there. It doesn't have to be bad people. It could be happy people waking us up, car doors slamming, the car alarms going off. Try to go back to sleep if that happens at 1 o'clock in the morning, and you have to get up at 5. Everything's open seven days a week now also.
People work on the weekends. My husband works in a hospital. They never close. So 5 o'clock comes around real soon. And again, no one here wants to put anyone out of business. I wish them good luck. However, we have a big investment in the city also. We have owned homes here, my neighbors here, for 50 years, 40 years, 30 years.
My husband's family was here back from the 40s on that street. So we have an investment in the city as well as the business people. I touched upon the history of the building and the longevity. And it's a good rental property. And that parking lot is a very vital part of the Haines Square area. The reason
Okay. Um, back when the grand opening was in, uh, July the 29th, I believe, um, I went over and I noticed that on the door they had extended hours posted now only because I was part of the process back when Panda Palace opened up and those owners went through the process in the right way.
They filled out their applications, and they came before the council. The same process. When I didn't get a notice, and I knew it was going to be a sports bar, since May, because I was in there picking up a luncheon special before Asian Palace closed, I was told, oh, we're going to close next week. And I said, oh, what are you going to do? He said, oh, we're going to open a sports bar. I said, really? You're going to get rid of that buffet? Are you kidding me? He said it didn't make any money. OK, and that's his choice.
This is a whole new concept. The restaurants and sports bars are two different models. And they look quite different, in my opinion. I think the reason why this got off on the wrong foot, first of all, is because we felt as though the neighbors' feet were stepped on by doing something like that, posting hours that they hadn't gotten approval for. So that's a negative point.
OK? Doesn't mean it can't be erased. OK? But it just started off wrong. Then within three or four days later, I get advertising the Wicked Local. And I passed out a copy of those to people. OK? And it's right on the top there. Sports Bar Karaoke DJ. So they all had the idea of the sports bar. And they're going to have all these functions and everything. But again, no approval.
They didn't come up and say, oh, can I do this? At least find out. Because a lot of thought was put into that advertising. A lot. And a lot of money was put into it. And I appreciate the money they put in there. Now, the thing next.
When I called a couple of counselors here, and my concern was just a couple of weeks ago when we had the Pats opening. The closing time, of course, is 11 o'clock until you people decide to approve or disapprove of this. My husband walked across the street. You can continue. Walked across the Dairy Mart, and there was a lot of clients still in the bar at 11.30 for that night.
That's a concern, okay? And the, I'm sorry? No, not that, no. So when I went to turn out the light on the porch, I said, who are all these people? He was just coming back through the door and he said, oh, they're still in the sports bar. And I said, well, it's after 11, how can they do that? Well, they did it, okay? And that's,
Again, another little salt in the wound. They should know this. As business people going through all of this, they've had the Asia Palace prior to that, and I enjoy their food. I do. But again, they're businessmen. They have to know these things. There was a lot of thought put into this place. They have to know these things.
I did call a couple of the counsels and pose the question when it comes to closing. What actually is the procedure? I want to know what's right and what's wrong. Well, what ended up happening was I did call the law department. I spoke to the lovely lady, and we ended up laughing at the end of this conversation. But in any case, my question to her was, first off,
someone is to be closed at 11 o'clock, exactly what should be the procedure? Well, she continued to tell me that the liquor side of it, there's a state liquor license until 1 a.m. I said, I understand that, but they have to go before the council to get approval for that extended hour.
What, in fact, we go back and forth in this since we started laughing. What I really wanted to find out, what was the procedure? Do you say last call? Is the doors locked? Is nothing else served? How soon a time after the closing hour do they have to get out? I wanted to know the exact thing. So what it came down to, it's 11 o'clock closing, it's done on the liquor end. She did say on the food end,
The city clerk would be able to answer that. And rather than bother you in your office, I figured I'd toss the ball to you. As far as serving food, if an establishment closes at 11 o'clock, should they? How it works out in the extended hours, I think, is that you can no longer operate. You operate like a retailer.
you know, up until 11 o'clock, so you really can't sell anything after 11 o'clock. You know, that's how we end up. So as far as staying, that's a whole different ballgame, you know. But you can't, you know. The way I understood it from the law office is that it should be done and over with, 11 o'clock. Taking your business, yeah. And the customer should be on the other side of the door. OK.
So at least we got that question answered. Um, point of clarification. If I understand the liquor law, correct. If your last calls at 11 o'clock, they cannot stay there no longer than 15 minutes after the last call. And then the drinks have to be returned. They cannot drink anymore. Correct me if I'm wrong, but if you have a one o'clock food license for extended hours, you can stay there providing your reading, but not drinking.
That's the difference. The liquor license prohibits you for whatever that time period is, 15 minutes after, if the license is 11 o'clock, 11.15, that's it. That's the max you can stay there. Thank you for that point of information, Councilor Penta. Councilor Camuso, point of information. I appreciate Councilor Penta's concerns, but the liquor license is actually till 1 a.m. The establishment closes at 11, but that particular liquor license is till 1 a.m.
Point of information. Counselor. I was just explaining the liquor law. That's all I was explaining. That has a license that ends at 11 o'clock period. It wasn't the way it came out. That's right. Thank you. Make sure we know what we're talking about. So my understanding this correctly, I'm going to go with this one more time. If, if the closing hours are 11 o'clock, so typically they could stay till 1115 for the liquor, but for the food, no.
as long as it's still water. Yeah, you can't serve or buy anything anymore. I mean, that license is stopped. But you don't have to be out. You don't have to be out. No, that's totally different from the common victor's license. What happens afterwards? It's inordinate, whatever it falls into. But as far as a common victor's license,
So am I hearing that if it closes at 11, typically someone could be in there till 11.30? Is that what I'm hearing? Yes? Point of information to present. Point of information, Councilor Marks. You know, first of all, we're talking about an extended hour ordinance that was created 30 years ago and hasn't been amended for 30 years. And I agree with you. I think there's a lot of ambiguities around
The fact that what happens, just say your hours are until 11 o'clock. Can someone come in at 10.55 and order a meal and sit there until 2 in the morning? I don't think our ordinance currently addresses that right now. Now, it may address it around liquor, as Councilor Panta mentioned, but I don't think it currently addresses it. And one thing I'm hoping that comes out of tonight is our subcommittee. We have a number of subcommittees that handle all different issues. Our licensing subcommittee, which Councilor Caviello is the chair of, we send a paper to them.
So they can meet and discuss how we can craft an ordinance that addresses some of these concerns, because they're valid concerns. And I think they need to be addressed. So I agree with that, Mr. President. And I'll make that part of whatever report that's recommended. Thank you, Counselor. Ma'am, if you would continue. Yes. Again, that was my concern, because if any type of late hours were granted, that's an open-ended, we may be into the 1.30 hour.
Which makes it even worse. That cuts my sleep in half again. And everybody else in the neighborhood. We are so close to that property. That's the main concern. Also too, if you read the police logs, which I'm sure you do, we have a lot of problems down in our area, a lot. Daytime, nighttime with the drugs and so forth.
These late hours are just gonna be a magnet. It's gonna be a magnet. I mean, just for people to, something's open, they blend in with people, it's just gonna be a magnet. That's a big concern to the neighbors. We see it, we hear it, we watch it on a daily basis, and to think that something else could possibly be open at that wee hour of the morning while we're in bed,
And this could just be multiplying in front of us. So that's a big concern to me. And this kind of open-ended thing of I'm going to order some food here, and I'm going to stay down until 1.30, it's like, where does it end? That's a big concern. Basically, I can probably speak for the rest of my friends and neighbors here. We're here to preserve our neighborhood.
We've been there a long time. We want to preserve as much of the quiet time that we all deserve after working hard all day. And that's not a lot to ask. It really isn't. You know, we've been in the neighborhood a long time. We've contributed to the city, supported the city for many, many years, generations. I understand there's a generational thing here also with the owners.
And, again, I feel as though if a business opened 12 hours a day, seven days a week, can't make it, you've got to figure out what you're doing wrong. That's a lot of hours. Now you want to add extra hours in and put an eighth day into the week. Well, why don't we make it nine and ten, and we'll just stay open all night? I mean, where does it end?
So again, we're here to preserve our neighborhood. We want to keep our neighborhoods as safe as it can be. Things are bad, and I feel getting worse on a daily basis. So again, that magnet after hours really concerns me. And after 11 o'clock, not a lot of good happens out there on the street. Not a lot of good happens.
I hope we can, you know, come to some good conclusion here tonight, and thank you for listening to us. And if anybody has any questions, I'd be happy to answer them. Okay. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Chair recognizes Councilor Caviello. Thank you, Mr. President. You know, I've been in this gentleman's establishment. They've made a major investment in our community here.
And I think they deserve the opportunity. I think they were a little confused in the beginning when they opened. And I think they've tried to rectify whatever they did wrong. But they've made an investment in our community. They've bettered the building. They're facing competition from the other restaurants. They operate the same hours in other cities.
You know, we sit here, you know, people sit here every week and say, you know, nothing ever comes to Medford, nothing comes to Medford. Well, here, these gentlemen come to Medford, they make an investment in the community, and here we are saying, no, you can't do what the other restaurants do. I mean, all they're asking for is what to do with other people that, you know, I would, you know, if we could do this with some kind of a review after 60 days, 90 days, if there was a problem, come back.
But as I said, they do deserve the same opportunity that every other business in the city has. And I say, if this is what we want, if we want businesses to come here, then we have to make it a level playing field for everybody. We can't pick and choose who we want to give special hours to and not give special hours to. Thank you, Councilor. Councilor Camuso. I'll yield to the gentleman. I appreciate it. Joe Bianco, Property Order 41 Lamb Street, which currently my mother lives in the building.
I have some major concerns for the change in the hours due to the negative impact that this will have on the resident area. I noticed you have a big crowd over here in support, but if you heard, most of these people don't live in the area. They're good friends. I appreciate they stick up for the owners, but they don't abut the areas. They don't even live close to the areas, so they don't have to deal with the consequences. If you check out that area, Haines Square,
Property values in that area haven't gone up like the rest of Meffitt. They're 8% to 15% lower than everywhere else in Meffitt. And one of the reasons is we have a problem in that area with crime. We have a big drug problem over there. It is Seeland Street, Felsway, Spring Street. There's ongoing drug investigations going on right now that I know of that I can discuss later.
with you guys in private, if you want, that I know about. So this is a big uptake. I don't know if you guys were aware of the truck problems in that area. Now, my mother lives right behind the building. And during the daytime in that area, we have a lunchtime crew that comes in there, contractors and everything. They park their trucks in there and they drink. They're in there drinking. And if you check with the police reports, you know what I mean?
A lot of offices are Dunkin' Donuts in there, but no one notices unless you're a resident. You can look out the window, you can see the guys sittin' in there drinkin' a six-pack at lunchtime. So that's, if you guys are familiar with that parking lot. I didn't hear, where are they going to drink in the parking lot? Are you familiar with that parking lot? There's two sections of the parking lot. There's a main parking lot and there's an offset. Yeah, it's there today. There's an offset right behind Dunkin' Donuts.
Okay? And there's a little corner over there and a lot of contractors go in there and they're drinking all day long. At lunchtime. At lunchtime. In the parking lot. In the parking lot. Yeah. Okay. In their vehicles. In their vehicles. And I don't want to say this, but there's also a few city trucks in there once in a while, but. You know what I mean? That could be something that you guys might want to check into, because you can see it plainly from the residents.
I'm over there, when I look out my mother's window, you can see him at lunchtime. But that's beside the issue. That's just to let you know what that area is like. It's congested, you know. But as far as the impact as changing the hours, there is a problem as it exists right now. My mother's called me and she says she looks out the window, there's people urinating in the corner of the building.
You know, they're coming out, you know, I don't know, I can't prove they're coming out of that restaurant, but I assume at those hours right now, that later on, that that's what they're doing. They're arguing in the parking lot after hours. And you can hear them, somebody's arguing, somebody's fighting about something. Cruisers will come by once in a while, you know, it's not like, you know, I've seen them being arrested, but the cruisers come by and they leave. I guess they were able to resolve the situation. There's noise, because when they're getting out of the,
The establishment at this time, they're sitting in the parking lot, talking for a little while, and they're pretty loud at night. It echoes, because you've got a building that's like a stage over there, that everything echoes off those walls. And if you're a resident, you've got your windows open at some time, you can hear them yelling, and swearing, and screaming. My mother's just, you can overhear all that. And the other effect is, if later it is open at night, after they've been drinking at the bar, they're going to all drive home.
You know, it's another liability for the city. I mean, you know, most of these people are going to be coming from across the Fells Way there, you know, coming out of Malden. They're not going to be coming from West Meffitt. They're going to be coming out of Malden, you know what I mean? Spring Street. They're going to be driving down those ways. There's a lot of, you know, traffic that's going to be impacted. And S5 is,
My concern is right now that I'm really a little bit upset about how I was told by another neighbor, and I was shown these flyers about them passing them out about their hours already, which it hasn't been approved. Now, it's either the fix is in, or these guys have it in their head. Who would do that? That costs money to do that. I don't understand why they would go out and do that. It doesn't make any sense to me as a business owner
Did you just publicize that you're going to be open until 1 o'clock like it's a done deal? How did that happen? Why did it happen? I don't know. Maybe that should be investigated and find out what's going on. Have you seen the flyers? Can anybody tell me why those flyers are sent out? We're having a meeting right now to talk about it.
It's my understanding, speaking with the business owner, that when he received the liquor license from the state of Massachusetts, the Commonwealth, which was a liquor license that would end at 1 o'clock in the morning, he was under the impression that that would be what dictates his hours of operation, not the local control. So it's my understanding that it was more or less just an error in application than it was anything else. It wasn't any intentional violation. It wasn't any type of attempt to skirt the local requirements.
But you know you're coming in front of the board to discuss this, and then you do that. Well, he came before the board. He did receive a common victuals license. And that was before the board this evening for a license for extended hours. The common victuals license would expire at 11 o'clock in the evening. The gentleman had a license from the city of Medford that would allow him to be open till 11 o'clock in the evening. He also had a license from the Commonwealth of Massachusetts that would allow him to be open till 1 o'clock in the morning. I think there was some disconnect there in understanding what it is that his actual hours of operation were going to be. But in my discussions with Mr. Wu,
My understanding is that it's been nothing more than a misapplication and a misunderstanding. Well, I'll have to accept that, but I mean, it's kind of weird, you know. But I want you guys to just, you know, I know you guys have been in Meffitt for a long time. I want you to just think about the impact of the residents, not just like everybody that comes from maybe other part of Meffitt. I mean, it's not a restaurant anymore. It's a sports bar. I hang out a lot of sports bars, you know what I mean? You guys go there, you know what happens. You go to a football game, gets a little rowdy.
Sometimes it ends up outside, and there's a lot of drinking. It's a sports bar. And if you want to test everybody coming out of there, I bet 50% of them are over the limit. And they're going to be driving through the streets of Memphis at 1 o'clock in the morning. Or from what I understand, it could be 1.30 now. I need you guys to all consider that. And if you can't, I wish you'd just table this until we can get more input.
Lieutenant there and find out what actually is going on with the crime rate in that area, the drug problem and all that, so you guys get a better handle on it. I think you should be aware of that before we... You know, it's one o'clock in the morning. What kind of people are going to be going out to go have another beer? It's the people that have probably just got stoned somewhere now and they're going to go out to eat. You know? Think about it.
I love this city and I don't want that area to depreciate any further than it already has. So I want you guys to check with the lieutenant and find out what the stats are for that area, for drugs, crime, and you'll notice that there's an uptick in there higher than other places in Memphis. And I think this would only add to it. So I appreciate your consideration on that. Thank you, Mr. Bianco.
Hi, Lucrecia Velez, 45 Lumber Street. And I've been there 33 years. And basically, we are right next to the parking lot. And the late hours will impact our way of living. The noise level, the neighborhood also. I agree with what Joe has said. It has changed a lot.
I'm concerned that the late hours will make it worse. Hopefully you will consider all the facts and make the appropriate decision on that. I appreciate it. Please. Thank you, Mrs. Falas. Counselor Camuso, the chair recognizes you. Thank you, Mr. President. And I already said a little bit earlier regarding my support, but I'd just like to back up my support.
I'm looking at this as somewhat of an economic development of the community as well. Just last week, there was some discussion regarding a sign and certain members of the council wanted to shut a sign off at the new Marriott that's coming to our community at certain times. That was thrown out there. And at that point, I was a little concerned because I think we have to be, show that we're with the times, so to say. I look back, I have another paper on later on this evening.
to discuss another piece of economic development in our community that was not supported by the Medford City Council, other than myself and I believe Councilor Knight at the time, and that was the bank across from the Medford Fire Station for a drive-thru. And there was an arrangement, an agreement with all the neighbors in the area on Thomas
And that did not have the votes, and now we're sitting here with an empty building for over a year. So, I do have concerns of moving the city forward in the economic development piece. But, you know, as we look around the community, we have some great restaurants now. We have Carroll's, who's not so much in a residential neighbourhood, but we have Razzo's and Bocelli's that are right in the heart of neighbourhoods very similar to Lambert Street area and Spring Street Extension. For some time, my wife and I owned a corner
Irving Street in West Medford, which directly abuts West Medford Square. And although we didn't have the late hours, we also knew when we moved in there, there was a potential for the Bistro 5 to petition for later hours and things of that nature. And, you know, I just look at this as an economic development piece for the community. You know, last week, too, there was some talk about parking, and certain people are for and against the parking.
and I got the numbers from last week, the meals tax has actually been up by a good amount when I compared January 1st of 2014 to 8-31-2014, and then I ran the numbers for the same time period of 2015, throw in the worst winter we've had in probably the last 35 years in the city of Medford, and to have the meals tax up during that same period of time,
and say that the businesses are suffering and lacking and are really getting hit because of the parking. It just didn't make sense and I wanted to take it to the next level and actually get data to back that up. And when I did that I was quite surprised because if you look back at the winter that we had, it was one of the worst winters in the history of the city of Medford.
As far as this particular establishment, like I said, I can go along with the review, but I think we have to give them an opportunity to operate with the later hours if something happens. I understand the gentleman that came up and talked about crime and the drugs. I'm not sure where he went, but that's all over this community right now. We just hired the other day, the city of Medford hired the first time outreach coordinator to deal with the opiate problem that we're dealing with here in the city of Medford.
She was just hired within the last two days. And so I think the city is doing our best to address that. I think part of the problem you have in some of these areas at night is because at a certain time it's shut down and it tends to attract people that may want to do not so good things, whether it's in a parking lot in a vehicle or somewhere else. And this will actually act as a deterrent from things of that nature with having a little bit more viability
going on at night. I certainly understand the concerns of the residents. I certainly understand it, but I firmly believe it. And you look at Mr. Karofalos, a gentleman that came here, it's the American dream. He's worked hard his whole life, his whole life, and he owns that building. He owns that building, he's a Medford resident, and he understands, he would be the last person that wants the neighbors that he's been next to
for all these years to have these problems. But I just feel confident through the proper restrictions, as Councillor Caviello mentioned. And as far as the other things that the other gentleman mentioned, these are serious police matters. And if you see people drinking in the parking lot in vehicles, it's a serious issue. But it's not something that's going to get any better or worse because of the permit that's before us this evening.
So for those reasons, I just think that we should give them a shake and an opportunity. And quite honestly, as I said last week, I just think Medford's getting the, and it's partly because of City Hall and this city council on occasion.
People don't want to come to Medford as much as they want to go to other communities that are willing to listen, and to open the door, open the avenue, and be for new things, or move the city forward. You know, we're at a very, very critical juncture in this community over the next 12 months. We have Mr. Wynn, who's breaking ground on a casino right over the line in Everett. And the entrance and exit to that casino is going to be on the Charlestown side.
So there was a lot of misinformation at first that it was going to be at the circle over on this side. And that's not the case. The case is it's going to be on the Charlestown side with a ramp coming from the highways and all that. If indeed the building permits are issued, which it appears it is, the last hurdle was taken up by Everett. But as I talk about the critical juncture, you know, I want to see people that have capital that want to
bring something vibrant to our community. I want to see them come here, because they know they have a city hall that wants to move Medford forward, whether it be in the corner office, whether it be department heads under the mayor's lead, whether it be the city council. I think we want to send the message that we want people to come here. We have many lots on Mystic Ave that are going up for sale every few years. And you know what? I want to see more Marriotts come to the community.
As I said last week, when we start talking about the Marriott shutting their sign off at a certain time because the roast beef place next door has to do it, it's night and day as far as I'm concerned. It's night and day. So if we could send that vision, and I think this a lot starts in the economic development office, but as I said, we're at a very critical juncture.
I think we're going to have opportunity because of that casino that we have never had in the last 50 years in the city of Medford. We're going to have people that want to come here. We're going to have people that go on the internet and see a room at the casino for $500 a night. OK, let me stay at the Marriott or the Sheraton on Mr. Gavin Medford. And I'd rather see them here in our community, Mr. President.
than over in Chelsea or in Somerville or other areas. You know, we've got to have vision like Mayor Curtatone, a vision of Assembly Row. You know, you go down there, whoever thought that legal seafood would be opened up on the Mystic River a quarter of a mile from the city of Medford? Never in a million years I thought that was going to happen. But I certainly hear the neighbors loud and clear. If you have specific police
Police issues, if you could please either talk to one of the councillors after the meeting, or we'll get you in touch with the chief of police, because those issues aren't going away, whether you have them or every business in the community closed at 10 o'clock or 9 o'clock. Those issues are there. No, no, and I understand that, but we have to take the issue. We can't make the permit become
The permit's separate and distinct from the issues you're dealing with. And I just think that we have to police that area a little bit more. And I just think that we should give them a shake. I know the councilor mentioned, what did you mention for a review, 60? 60 days. A 60-day review. And at that point, we can look at it. And if it's creating a major havoc, believe me, the chief of police will be the first one that will be down here petitioning the council to get rid of the license if it's going to create a problem.
On my end, I'll just finish with saying this has come up before with RAZOs. I remember the liquor hearing for RAZOs. I remember other hearings for businesses of similar nature. And there hasn't been one of them that have been back before us to have the license pulled or anything as a result of the extended hours. So with that being said, I just wanted to give a little bit more background on why I continue to support this. And I would hope the council has the vision to at least give them the opportunity
with the full expectation that they stay to the high standards as their father and mother have done over the past 25, 30 years, as Mrs. DePaola indicated. Thank you, Counselor. Welcome, sir. Please state your name and address again for the record. Yes, I'm Ray Ganey. I've lived in the same house on Lambert Street for 57 years. So it's nice to get new people, but it's good to listen to the people who've been here for a long time, too.
And my main concern with all this, I'm not against a restaurant in our community. And every restaurant you've said, I've been to them all. They're listed as restaurants. This is listed as a sports bar. And I've had a lot of dealings with the city of Boston with sports bars and things. I ran a feast in the North End for 18 years. Trust me, when it comes to promotion, liquor companies go after sports bars. They go after feasts. And we're a religious festival.
And there's a lot of money out there. And my concern as a resident, you know, I don't know what the plans are for the sports car, but I want to know what is this council going to do if they start having contests sponsored by Captain Morgan Rum, Budweiser.
Heineken, they all believe me. Any big sports event, the Super Bowl, you know, March Madness, there's so much money out there for liquor. You go into Memorial Square, the sports bar's there. And you'll see the difference between a restaurant and a sports bar. You know, it's fine to say, oh, people can stay in the restaurant because they're eating until 1 o'clock in the morning. They're not there to eat.
they're there to drink, whereas the people in the community are there to live. And I want you to take that into consideration, because it really got me aggravated knowing that I've lived in the same house on Lambert Street within a two-second walk from that area, and I was enlisted as an abutter, whereas a parking lot owned by the city of Medford gets a notice from the city of Medford.
I don't see anyone from the parking lot here talking up or down on this. It's ridiculous. It's a little common sense, and that's what gets voters frustrated. You know, it's all well and good. I've heard a lot of people come up here and say, and these are honorable gentlemen. They're businessmen. I've been in business. I know what it takes to be successful in business.
It's very tough, however, when we, as residents who live within a stone's throw of this place, weren't notified. And businesses were, that closed their doors at 6 o'clock. I mean, Martin Hardware, they're closed at 6 o'clock. But they're totally in favor of them being open till 1 o'clock in the morning. They're next door neighbors. But the judge goes home and sleeps.
We're right there. The parking lot behind the sports bar, behind that whole square is a mess. And it's owned by the city. And quite frankly, the entrance going into that parking lot, for residents who actually walk the sidewalks, try walking there.
I invite you all to go down there and look at that parking lot, the entrance into the parking lot, and 90% of the people who go to the sports bar will park in that parking lot. The cement is all over the place. It's all broken up. Now, granted, there's trucks delivering there all the time and stuff, but I don't think it's been paved in over 40 years, you know, probably since Mueller's was a restaurant there.
if anyone remembers that. Mueller's restaurant. They were there for years. Now, you couple that with people coming out of the restaurant, out of the sports bar, having a few drinks, walking on that. I mean, I use a cane, and it's dangerous to walk.
When it's slippery or something else, forget it. You just walk on the street. You don't walk over there. But you got to get into the parking lot. If they walk over that, you're going to have some split heads there. I guarantee it. Because it's a mess. And nobody's addressing that. I don't know if it's the abutters of the building itself that should pay for it, the new business, the city. The city owns the parking lot. But my point is this.
You're saying give them a chance with a 60-day review or something. As a resident, I think you should review it first. Don't give them extra hours first to do it. I don't think they're going to go broke in another month to discuss this by you guys.
Get the rules. I mean, Marion was up here asking questions, and Councilor Pence asked a question, and nobody had any answers up here. You know? The state liquor license says till 1 o'clock. The city ordinance says till 11. If you're in the city, you've got to go by the rules of the city. You know?
It's frustrating as residents, and I guarantee you, there'd be a lot more residents here if we were notified. With the exception of a few of us who actually see each other on a daily basis, we were able to find out about this. I think Mr. Bianco made a perfect case when he says,
It gave us a feeling that there was a fix-in. Like, you know, we've lived here all our lives, and we don't get a notification that there's a hearing on this. And yet, businesses that are closed at 6 o'clock get notifications of this. I mean, that was a... What information, Mr. President? Pursuant to the established standard, the city is required to notify abutters who lay within 300 feet of the establishment.
one football field of the establishment in the radius, as to whether or not there's a public hearing that's going on. So granted that two-thirds of the people that were notified are businesses or business entities, it appears to me based upon the map in Councilor Caviello's packet that there's quite a large radius of individuals that were notified. They definitely covered all the grounds of the residences as well as the businesses that reside within the 300-foot radius, Mr. President.
So I can certainly understand that, you know what I mean, you have some frustration about something that's going on in your neighborhood. But in terms of notification requirements, the notification requirements were met. It's a 300-foot radius from the property that's petitioning. That's a football field. People who live within a football field receive notification of the meeting. I can throw a football from my house and hit the restaurant, believe me. The Steelers might need you.
But nonetheless, I'm telling you, 300 feet, my house is within that area. And we weren't notified. That's the standard. And that's what's shown in the. Point of information, Mr. President. Councilor Knight, you finished with your point of information? Yes, absolutely. Point of information, Councilor Marks. Well, the clerk is responsible for notification, correct? Do you have a listing of who was notified?
I think Marion sent out copies. Right, but I thought you were saying this didn't look correct. I thought you said something. What I was saying, when Marion put the list, I didn't know what these written notations were. So according to your list, there were 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. There was 18 homes that were notified.
18 abutters. Abutters? Abutters within the 300-foot radius. Right. And those abutters that were directly across the street from the address. That's how it is, yeah. And this gentleman's directly across the street. You're not listed on this? Are you listed on this list? No. No. And Marion's house is closest to it than mine. Counsel, you've made your point of information. Am I correct? I think what happens, if the gentleman's correct,
There's a butter, technically there's a butter in between them, which is the city-owned property and whatever the other parking lot out there. So it's not a butters to a butters. See, the gentleman would be a butter to a butter, actually. See, that's what the state law could be, 300 feet in a radius, right? And those across, directly across the street.
These people really have, they're a butter to a butter, actually. That's what's happening. So you're saying they're the butter to the city parking lot. Which is not really. If I'm looking at this right, because this is the certified list from the assessors and the engineer, the map of that diagram, I could probably envision where they live, that they're the butter to the butter. I'm directly across the street. Right.
If I'm looking at it, I did not get notification. And the other two situations that the neighborhood has been involved in past years, I was notified on both of those occasions. I mean, you could have been, like I said, it's a 300 feet, this is a certified list. So I don't know. I don't make the list. I think what the feelings of the residents are, if you look at that as a whole, and I'm sure,
It's probably within the letter of the law, but there's a little bit of common sense when these things are being drawn up. And it was told to me that the petitioner pays for the certified list to be sent out. So I said, and so do I by paying my taxes to a salary. What does that have to do with anything? That's what I was told. I'm sorry?
I said, when I was up to get a copy of the abuttus list when I did not receive one, I was quite surprised. And then after reviewing it, we were going over it, and I said, oh, it's commercial, commercial, commercial, commercial, commercial. And it came to 12 to 6, two-thirds to commercial, one-third to residential. And it was told to me then that these lists
are paid by the petitioner, the owner, certified male. I said, that's fine. But we also pay taxes as residents for salaries for the city workers. I mean, it's just a, I don't understand what the rationale by saying that to me was, but.
That's fine. I think that things should be a little bit more balanced. I mean, to go directly across the street to the MBTA station, they got one, to the liquor store on, I think it's 260 on Spring Street. The flower shop. The flower shop. Those three consecutive ones. It was Dino's, Dempsey's, the florist shop right at that corner, shot across to the MBTA, over to the liquor store, and then from 442 Salem Street,
the property was discussing, all the way straight up to the Dunkin' Donuts. So that really covered an entire area of commercial. See, it seems like the 300-foot radius was done in one direction. It wasn't done, you know, in a 180-degree direction. Exactly. OK. And of those six residents that were notified,
The house directly next to me is a condo. So three were sent to one address. So typically, four homes were touched for this subject tonight, four homes. I know that they're individually owned. I understand that. But I'm sure the people within the house would say, did you get this? Or what's this about? Or whatever. There'd be some kind of contact. So typically, four homes got notified.
out of the 18. Just want to bring that for future things in the city, because it's going to be a lot going on in the city. It's going to be a lot of changes, hopefully a lot of good ones, so that when you see these abutted lists, you know, is this balanced here? We all set? So that's it. Thank you. The gentleman has the floor. Oh, you can respond first. I'm not going away. I think the woman brings up a very valid point.
The 300 rule is a state law. That's the minimum requirement that we have to follow as a city. The state doesn't say you can't notify 400 feet, 500 feet, 1,000 feet. They leave that up to the city. We can't do less than 300 feet. So, we've discussed this in the past, and I'm not sure where it landed, Mr. President, but I think it's a worthwhile discussion to have when it comes to notification of about as
Transparency, to me, is the utmost importance. And I don't think either side, whether you're in favor or against or whatever you might be, I think everyone wants a level playing field and to make sure everyone's notified, including business owners and abutters and anyone else. And I think that's another issue, Mr. President, as a council we have to review. And there's a lot of discussion about being business friendly and so forth in this community, and I would
say as one member of the council, uh, extended hours are something that we offer. Um, and in my opinion, it's a case by case. Uh, if we go based on what some comments were made tonight, well, these other restaurants have it. We've got to give it to him too.
then why are we voting for any of these? We've already extended hours to 12, 1 o'clock, 2 o'clock in the morning. Then why do we have to vote? It has to be 3 o'clock in the morning. It has to be done on a case-by-case situation. And there are extenuating circumstances, in my opinion, that at least will weigh on me when I make a decision. And some of it has to do with neighborhoods. Some of it has to do with traffic. There's a lot of issues.
But getting back to the business-friendly, Mr. President, you know, extended hours are not with businesses coming to Memphis. We can get extended hours coming to Memphis. They come in because they want to see our roads and sidewalks repaired, Mr. President. They want to make sure the lighting in the business districts is proper, which we've been fighting about for years. They want to make sure there's foot traffic in the community after 6 o'clock.
The city doesn't roll up the sidewalks. They want to make sure the licensing process at City Hall is not like pulling teeth, which happens in this community. So, you know, I don't buy the fact that we're not being business friendly. I think that that is set by the administration, to be quite honest with you. It's been here 28 years.
And if you look at our business districts, Haines Square is no different than West Meffitt, no different than Meffitt Square, Salt Meffitt, Mr. President. It's no different. Our business districts are going down. There's many open storefronts in this community, and businesses are struggling. I agree with that.
But I don't think it's because of extended hours. I think it's the message that this city has been sending out over the years, Mr. President, because it seems to be working in Somerville, it seems to be working in Stoneham, in Wakefield, and a lot of surrounding communities, Woburn Center, that have thriving business districts. And we seem, for whatever reason, we're right off of 93, we're five minutes from Boston, we have a river that runs through the heart of our community, and we seem to be lagging behind when it comes to economic growth.
I wouldn't be too quick to just say extended hours is the solve-all. Yeah, we want business to be able to compete in this community, absolutely. But, you know, we also have to be mindful that, you know, this community, we're land poor. And, you know, this is a commercial zone business district, absolutely. It happens to abut homes that have been there 70, 80, 90, 100 years. So I think we have to be mindful, in my opinion,
I'd like to see, and we've had this done in the past, is maybe if we can get the parties together tonight to agree upon something. Because I don't know if you've met with the owners or some of the abutters have met with the owners. And we've done this in the past, and we've been successful. Councils that have been on for a number of years, we were able to get both parties together. They step outside for a few minutes and say, what do you think about doing this or that? How can we come to an agreement? And maybe you will, maybe you won't. Who knows? But I think it's worth trying, Mr. President, at this time.
Because I can see both sides. And I know it's my job to make a decision, but I can see both sides of this issue. I really can. And I want to make it work. I want to make it work for the abutters, and I want to make it work for the business. So, I would ask at this time, Mr. President, when people are done speaking, if both parties wouldn't mind stepping outside and speaking about the issues, and then coming back before the council and see if they can come to somewhat of a compromise.
I'm in favor of that, but there are things that are still concerning me, and basically because of the name Sports Bar, because I know what it attracts. And I alluded to, you know, contests and things like that, especially among sporting events and stuff. And dealing with liquor companies and beer companies, I know how much they promote things. That's a real concern for the neighborhood.
if that starts happening. I'm not saying they're doing that, and I know they're not doing that right now, as far as I know, they're not doing that. But how does the city address it? That was my question to you guys. Do you have any idea? I've dealt with the Boston City Council on this. I haven't dealt with the Memphis City Council. I know there's a lot of promotional money out there. Of course, it deals with their products.
And the one area that they really can spend is in liquor. And it's, you know, you can see it in Malden. You can see it in Malden Square, some of the pubs and sports bars in Malden Square. You know, they have a boxing event, and, you know, it's, you know, pay-per-view sponsored by the— Point of information, Councillor Longo-Kurt.
Thank you. Sorry to interrupt. I just know that we are a lot different than Boston with regards to regulations, and our liquor laws are much stricter than theirs. I don't think some of the things that happen in Boston could ever happen in Medford, as the laws are written right now. Could I recite them to you? No.
As a resident, that's my concern, because I'm familiar with Boston. But as a 57-year resident of Medford, I'm also familiar with the fact that we haven't had any sports bars in Medford that I know of. And now I have one right in my own neighborhood. And that's my concern. Are they bringing in that same marketing as sports bars from all over the rest of the state?
do your homework. There's a lot of them out there, and there's a lot that goes on in them. I'd even like to see the police chief up here to answer some questions on it, because it can really snowball. Believe me, I really don't know these gentlemen. They seem like very good gentlemen. I'm not saying that they're of the same mentality as some of these other companies,
You know, it's a neighborhood that I've lived in all my life, and I don't want to see certain things happen to it that I've seen happen in other areas. Thank you. Point of information, Counselor Camuso. I just wanted to let the gentleman know the chief of police and all the other department heads have signed off, and that's where they normally say they would concern. Signed off on what? I'm going to give you the whole packet in two seconds. OK. You can take a look at it.
Sir, have you completed your presentation? Thank you very much. Chair recognizes Councilor Knight, who has been waiting patiently. Thank you very much, Mr. President, and thank you, Councilor Longo, for your patience as well. I think it's important to point out that the issue before this council is the approval of extended hours for an entity that has an approved common victualized license. The issue of entertainment, the issue of licensing and liquor establishment and all that falls under the
purview of our licensing commission. So some of these questions that are being asked this evening would be appropriate for the licensing commission. And I think that they're certainly worthy of an answer, sir. There's no question about that. So with that being said, Mr. President, I'd like to amend the paper this evening to request that the Liquor Commission on members thereof meet with us and the committee of the whole to address some of these questions that are being raised this evening for future edification.
As an amendment to this paper, please. Side paper. Side paper. Or separate paper. B paper. We'll put that down as a B paper, Mr. Clerk. Thank you, Councilor Knight. Madam Vice President, patiently waiting. Thank you. Thank you, President de la Rousseau. I just want to go off of what Councilor Mark said, because I, too, am in the same boat. You know, I try to put yourself in the shoes of an abutter
what's going to be a sports bar slash upscale restaurant is, sorry, I didn't know you were waiting to talk, upscale restaurant from what I saw today when I went to go visit the establishment. I mean, it's beautiful inside. And the bar is located, which I was told to decide that is, you know, the sushi bar is closest to the restaurant, closest to the neighborhood where the sports bar, bar area is closer to, you know, Mr. Throt's,
business. The main concern, after listening to everybody speak tonight, I think the main issue is with regards to noise and primarily when the establishment closes. So what I would ask, you know, if we are going to table this to allow the residents and the business owners to speak together, I think that's the main issue that needs to be resolved. You know, what is the business going to do?
This does let out, you know, somewhat on Salem Street, but very close to a residential neighborhood. So, you know, what can be done, what compromise can be made to make sure that when the business does close, whether that's 11, 12, or 1, how can we make sure that the peace and enjoyment and the quiet enjoyment of the residents is left intact? I agree with what the gentleman said. This council, I believe it's been a few years, but we did meet with the chief of police.
I specifically asked—we know about the problems in the area, and we were reassured that detectives are on it. We were reassured. Now, I think that's a stretch with regards to an upscale establishment. I think that needs to be put second with regards to this license and with regards to noise. I called in a drug deal today that happened on Richard and Doonan.
My kids and I watched a drug bust in front of my home back in 2014. It's everywhere. It's everywhere. And I can't base my decision on this one license because of what is going on in the area. That needs to be fixed. And I think, if I could amend this, that we meet with the chief of police and do get updated. I mean, we were reassured that they're doing the best they can. We know there's problems in the old Johnny's, when it was Johnny's parking lot. I don't know. We haven't got an update since it was
changed over to stop and shop, and I think that is time. But I think that the noise factor needs to be addressed, and I'm a business owner myself. I know the profit that's going to come from those hours, but it has to be, it has to, there needs to be an agreement between the neighbors and the restaurant on what can be done to alleviate that.
And I agree. I think there should be not only a 60-day review, but then a six-month review and a 12-month review. And my last point, I guess, or question to the, especially the three vocal neighbors is, this license was given, you know, this establishment opened in July. Have there been any concerns the 10, 11 o'clock hour for the last two months? And have the police been called? Or has there been any, you know, rowdiness? Because if there isn't, then maybe we can give them a chance and see.
whether that's less of an hour than they want or there are some other compromises, you know, I would just, that would be my question to the neighbors as well. What has transpired in the last two months at that 11 o'clock hour? I know that, you know, there's been a couple of times they've been in there till 1130, people have been in there till 1130, but what has the noise factor been like? Because that is my, would be my main concern as a resident with regards to this license.
And that's my main concern as, you know, as a councillor who's trying to do the right thing for all parties, but obviously going to disappoint some people tonight. Councillor, you suggested amendment. We don't even have a motion on the floor yet, but what would your amendment be if we ever do get a motion on the floor? I think I'll hold my amendments.
Right now, if the neighbors and the business owners would like to speak, like Councilor Marks suggested, I'll hold my amendments. But I just wanted to voice my opinion. I didn't hear any particular things that needed to be discussed, just general concerns. But we'll allow them, if there's a motion before us, to discuss it at the time. The chair now recognizes Councilor Knight. One amendment would be to meet with the chief of police. This is a side paper. To meet with the chief of police in a committee of the whole within the next, you know,
three to four or five meetings beforehand so that we can discuss that area and the problems that we discussed probably two years ago now, and what's transpiring, what is the department doing, and what has been done to alleviate some of the problems.
Thank you, Madam Vice President, Councilor Knight. Thank you very much, and I think it's very important to point out that vibrant downtowns do help revitalize neighborhoods, and they do help improve property value. Bustling downtowns actually provide stability in our communities. And a reoccurring theme across Medford during this election season in particular has been the revitalization of our downtown squares.
And I think that right now, you know, I couldn't agree with Councilor Marks more. There's a need for some balance. We need to figure out how we're going to balance the revitalization of our downtown districts with the needs of the residents in our community. And I'd wholeheartedly support his suggestion to maybe table the item for a little while to later on in the meeting, let the party sit down maybe in the council room and see if they can negotiate a compromise. Mr. President,
You know, in situations like this, there are winners or losers if people don't come to the table to sit down and negotiate and meet in the middle ground. And, you know, I'd hate to see the business suffer. I'd hate to see the residents suffer. So I think that, you know, that's a prudent course of action to take. And I'd move that the matter be tabled and that the parties have the opportunity to meet in Council Room 207 to discuss the future of Shanghai Moon and maybe negotiate a compromise. On the motion of Council 9th, that this matter be tabled.
so that the parties may negotiate and meet outside chambers. On that motion, Councilor Camuso. Can we just let the gentleman speak first? He's been waiting patiently at the microphone. He's a very patient man. Benvenuto, signore. Thank you very much, Mr. President. Once again, Dominic Camara, 219 Lawrence Road. As some of you know, especially a couple of my former students in Medford High School,
a long-time resident of this city, and as a teacher, as a resident, obviously, I love the city of Medford. I grew up in Cambridge, but I loved Medford since 1969. And I, within a few years, I got to go into business in the city of Medford, because I loved Medford. Now, just to put this whole conversation into perspective, in 1980, 85, 86, I was able to open up a business. What business was that? It was a restaurant in Medford Square.
And there hadn't been anything in Memphis Square for years. And in order to open up a restaurant in Memphis Square in those days, in 1985, you had to have a seating capacity of 250 seats. 250 seats. Well, I borrowed and begged along with a partner of mine, and we put together this wonderful restaurant, which was called the High Street Grill. It became very successful.
There's only two of us in the city of Medford, the Happy Attic and us at the High Street Grill that had this restaurant. And I'm telling you, I'm still in awe from that restaurant to this day. The problem was in those days that it was a hardcore belief that if you
If you had less than 250 capacity, the city of Medford would become a barroom town. All these fears, fear mongering was rabid in the city of Medford. Well, here we are 35 years later, and you can have a liquor license for 50 people, and I don't see a barroom atmosphere in the city of Medford. So change, all I know is that change is always fraught with fear, distrust, and
I don't know what else to call it. But here we are. The city of Medford is alive and well with wonderful businesses, restaurants, and I don't see a bar room anywhere. I don't see people brawling outside of anywhere. And when it comes to the extension of these so-called, you know, from 12 to 1 o'clock,
I mean, does anybody remember how wonderful it was to be coming back to Medford if you went to Boston at a theater night and you came back and you could have breakfast at Carol's Restaurant at three o'clock in the morning? And you parked and you slammed, you know, you made some noise, I guess, but my God, it was wonderful. And the general said, who the heck would want to do this? The previous general said, at one o'clock in the morning, what kind of person would do that? Me. This kind of person would want to do that. I'm a respectable individual in the city of Medford.
I have good character, so if I want to go someplace and if I'm coming back to Medford at one o'clock in the morning, that makes me a bad person because, oh my, who the heck would want to have a glass of wine and something to eat at one o'clock in the morning?
by bringing perspective to this conversation, the fear can disappear. And I do understand neighborhoods and everything else. I live two doors down from the hospital. And there was fear mongering going on. And I think Councilor Pence was at the meeting at Tufts when somebody, some people from across the way would say, oh my God, if they go partner with, uh,
partners, healthcare, so on and so forth. The ambulance are going to be woken up. I've never heard an ambulance, and let me tell you, I live two doors down. So there's always fear in this thing, but when you put it in context, I think it's fine. I don't think you're going to see much of a difference whether you open from 12 o'clock to 1 o'clock on any given established in the city of Metric. And if it helps the city community, I mean the commercial community, all the better.
I mean, the commercial sector, I'm also a board of directors of the Chamber of Commerce. They're one of my tenants, for God's sakes. And I believe in the commercial sector of Medford. It's a wonderful sector. And they support the city of Medford tax-wise. And so I think the more we encourage business, the more we encourage the landlords, the more we encourage the commercial real estate to survive in the city of Medford, the lower the residential taxes can be artificially lowered. So I think this is a win-win for everybody when you encourage the commercial sector.
And with that, I'd like to close. Thank you so much. And I will testify to your character, sir. Thank you. Councilor Camusop, on the motion for table. On the motion for tabling, at this point, I'm just going to take a little different stance, because I think we're charged with the responsibility to either vote this yea or nay. Obviously, it's a very, very nice neighborhood. Lambert Street has hundreds of people living on it. We have several residents here. But I think in the best interest of
the whole city in that particular area, I'm ready to take a vote on it and with the reviews. So as far as tabling it, I just don't see anything coming out of it this evening, to be honest, because I don't think anything's going to be said that's going to say people, OK, do you have a few points? All right. But I'm going to vote no on the tabling. I'm going to vote no on the tabling for that matter. I think we're charged to take a vote.
move it forward, because there are a lot of people that live in that immediate area that aren't here for them or against them, so. Thank you. Thank you. Councilor, do you need to speak? Hi, Don. Hi, please state your name and address for the record. Jimmy Ganey, 48 Lambert Street. I've been living on Lambert Street all my life, 58 years, and I'd like to address a couple of things. I was one of those guys eating at Carol's Diner late at night
during the disco days, the difference was we were eating breakfast, we weren't drinking. Big point. Also, you had mentioned Boston City Council. They do things differently than Medford City Council, true, but I work in the north end of Boston, all right? I'm sure many of you here have dined in the north end of Boston. You go in probably about 7 o'clock, 8 o'clock, have your dinner, maybe stroll the north end a little bit, and then leave and go back to your nice, quiet suburbs
The thing that goes on later on in the North End is that all those, when those restaurants close and those drinking establishments are open till one in the morning, you have no idea how loud it is and how rowdy it is. Public urination, fighting, and I don't, I hate to say this, but I don't have much faith in the younger generation and even less when they're drunk, all right? I've seen it with my own eyes because I work there and I get out of work at one o'clock in the morning
And I walk to my car, and I'm glad when I go home to my nice, quiet Medford in Lambert Street, right over there, I say, thank God I live over here. My mother's from the North End. It's not the same place it was years ago. I have so many friends there that are dying to get out, lifelong residents of the North End, because these yuppies that go into these establishments, they have no respect for anybody, anyone sleeping,
and they don't care about a damn thing, and they care even less when they're intoxicated. So I just want to enlighten you to that fact. I'm very happy when I leave work and I come home to a nice, quiet Lambert Street. Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Gaines. Anthony Veras, 144 Fells Ave. Just to get back to what the gentleman just said, are we really going to compare meth
We're really going to compare Meffitt to the North End? There's 30 restaurants in a row with thousands and thousands of people. We're talking about a small establishment in Meffitt. Are we really going to compare the two? I'd just like to say that there may be less people, but it means that there might be just less drunks, that's all. They're intoxicated. They're out of control. Chair recognizes Councilor Pinto.
I would assume that the reason why we're here tonight is for the extended hours. And unfortunately, these extended hours have led into a neighborhood concern. So I guess my first question would be to the two gentlemen who own the property. Can you come up here, please? I'd like to ask you a question. And I didn't get your names from the beginning, so I know you're...
These are not the property owners. These are the business owners. The property owners are in there. Well, business owners. Oh, you just said property, so I just wanted to make sure we're getting apples to apples. Did you folks have an attorney representing you? Oh, no. You have no attorney? No. Okay. I think that's one of the problems that they're having here right now because of the neighborhood. There have been situations in the past where if you had the right attorney, or if you had an attorney, let's put it that way, that recognized that this might consider to be a problem within the neighborhood.
or could present a problem with the neighborhood, they would notify, they would be talking with you, and they would have neighborhood meetings before, or maybe even subsequent to a meeting such as this, where you would be able to sit down with the neighborhood to find out really what's going on. And we had a situation like that most recently on Riverside Avenue on a building establishment of three businesses. And I think that's maybe one of the real big drawbacks that are happening here right now. As far as the business itself going forward,
You advertise for sports bar, karaoke, and a weekend DJ. That's noise. And the neighborhood is not used to maybe that type of noise, because they've never had it or seen it before. But unfortunately, you advertise something that you probably shouldn't have advertised. And that was a no-no, in plain English. So I think we know that as far as mistake, and you're not going to go forward with that. I like the idea of the folks sitting down together.
And it might work itself out even better that whatever the compromise might be that you folks can come to, that you realize that if the business is going to expand, and it's going to expand the working base here in this community, unfortunately, if it abuts a neighborhood, something's got to give one way or the other. Now, the gentleman who came here before and said, you could go to Carol's Diner at 1 o'clock in the morning and get something to eat, yeah. But you were opposite a police station. If anything took place, a police station was right there.
You're not next to a police station. Unfortunately, you've heard all the comments relative to what's going on in the neighborhood, whether it's drugs, crime, or whatever it might be. Not emanating from your place, but that's what's in the neighborhood. And so I think what you've done is you've highlighted a pretty good issue right now. And the issue is that the entire neighborhood now comes under the microscope. And it's unfortunate that it's your business, but maybe it's the best thing that now could happen. So I wish you good luck, because you've spent a lot of time, effort, and energy. But the neighborhood has a stake in this, too.
the immediate butters, because this is going to be all new to them. So, I support the idea that you all sit down, try to come to some compromise to understand exactly what's going on. When you say, weekend DJ, I mean, is that Friday, Saturday, and Sunday? You're going to have a DJ there playing music? People are going to be dancing? I don't know. That belongs before the liquor commission. But these are the questions that nobody seems to understand. Karaoke, you're going to have that on three nights a week where people are going to go up there and sing, have a good time, and laugh? That's great.
You have a noise factor, and that's something I think you're probably going to have to explain when you go before the liquor bar. As far as the sports bar goes, I mean, you can go to any restaurant, I think, in the city. They all have televisions in there right now. So, and the other gentleman who says you have these liquor people come in there and they give you — yeah, they're going to do that no matter what the bar is. So, I'm more concerned about having you come to a happy medium. I like the idea that you've spent a lot of money and you've invested it. So, that means you believe in the city, you believe in the neighborhood, and you believe in your business.
and it's nice to hear people come here to support you. And I didn't hear anyone from the neighborhood oppose you because of your business. They're just concerned about how is this going to affect them. So I agree with Councilor Marks and Councilor Longo-Curran and Councilor Caviello, not only having maybe a review, but maybe to just go down and sit down and let them have a better understanding of really what this is. It's unfortunate that this 300 radius didn't do this. I don't know. Did it do the circumference or not? Maybe it did, maybe it didn't. I don't know.
If everybody's on the same page, I don't think the council will have an objection, but I just think it's good that they understand this, as it relates to that, okay? So, thank you. Thank you. So on the motion of council tonight, to table the matter, so that the parties can be open to discussion, Mr. Clerk, a roll call has been requested by Councilor Musil, and we'll take a roll call. Just one quick, oh, I'm sorry. Can I ask one quick question? When I spoke to the law department this past week,
They have already been granted the entertainment license. I don't know if any of you knew that. That's what I was told. Again, and that's a point as far as the noise. Entertainment for what, though? Entertainment for karaoke. Weekend DJ, karaoke? Karaoke, DJ, right.
My concern, and I'd like to ask the, maybe I can just ask the owners now if that's part of it. No, actually, I'd like to have this in front of you people, if you don't mind, with the entertainment license. Right now, the back doors are open. They have two back doors. From the time people come in in the morning, which is probably quarter past 11, I don't know. I don't know the exact time.
I'm sorry, from the time that they come in in the morning, those two back doors are wide open and they don't close until like now their closing time is like quarter of 11. Those doors are closed. Okay. Was any soundproofing put into this building? And will the doors be closed?
Motion of Council of Nine to table. Mr. Clark, please call the roll. Councilor Musil? Yes. Councilor Cavanaugh? No. Councilor McPherson? Yes. Councilor Martins? Yes. Councilor Pecan? Yes.
the motion is stable. When you've had your chance to talk, someone has to come in and inform the city messenger. Mr. Larry Lepore will then inform the chair to reconvene the meeting on this matter. And we can go to room 207 down the left of the corridor.
Motions, orders, and resolutions. 15-674 offered by Councillor Knight has been withdrawn. 15-675 offered by Councillor Knight. Be it resolved that the Office of Community Development and the City Assessor examine the feasibility of business tax abatement for the purpose of attracting new businesses to empty storefronts. Councillor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much.
several months, we've all heard the concerns of many residents in our community, many of those involved in the Metro Community Coalition and other community groups that have expressed concern about empty storefronts in our business districts. And I think tonight and the issue about Shanghai Moon was a perfect segue into that. I've been doing a little research. I've been looking at some programs that they have in other communities in other states. And I think that it's a good idea for us to think about ways to attract new businesses to empty storefronts and to keep them there.
And we have a great plan for Medford Square, a plan that has been sitting on the shelf for a bit of time. And it talks about the type of businesses that we need to create in order to have a vibrant downtown business district, Mr. President.
And I'd like the Office of Community Development and the city assessor to examine the feasibility of a business tax abatement or some sort of measure that would provide some relief to new businesses starting out in the community so that they can be successful and that they can shape our squares and our business district into what we envision them to be. Folks, could you take your conversation out? Please continue, Councilor. Well, that pretty much scared me half to death, Council President.
With that being said, I think it would be a great idea for our city assessor and our office of community development to sit down and determine if there's a way that we can develop a tax abatement program or process to attract new businesses, to fill our empty storefronts, and to really help us shape and define our squares into more vibrant, more consumer, more pedestrian-friendly downtowns, Mr. President. So I'd ask that my council colleagues support this measure and join me in voting in the affirmative.
Thank you, counselor. Sir, you want to speak on this matter? Please state your name and address for the record, senator. Thank you, president. I mean, de la russo, excuse me. Robert of 71 Evans street. In relation to this excellent agenda item being offered, I had something on the table, 15361.
Remove that not for the purposes of discussion because it's the exact point the Council at night is bringing up. If you could remove that from the table too, discard it so that it's off of your paperwork. But I rise in favor of this. If we look at the city of New York, Mayor de Blasio, I think his name is, he did a tax incentive program like this, and it's bringing in a lot of business.
And in relation to everything that's been discussed tonight, in another project that I'm working on, I've taken pictures from the corner of Salem Street and the Felsway, all the way up here to Forest Street and through the square, and I got some, like, 20 pictures of storefronts that are gone. And without mentioning any names, I know that this is an issue for one of the mayoral
who wants to implement this kind of tax incentive, to bring businesses into our starving business districts, and I would hope that this measure is voted in the affirmative tonight to make Medford business friendly, and we make our city attractive for businesses and families. Thank you, Mr. President. Thank you for your kind input, senator. Chair recognizes counsel Tanta. Mr. President, I would like to
amendment attached to my amendment that I offered some months ago when I brought forward the idea of not only offering a tax abatement, but for the incentive to bring new business folks in here, hiring Medford people and giving tax breaks. I think I gave you folks all an example of what took place in a particular city down in Florida, where they took a particular area in a downtown area and they took a street, business by business by business. And what they did is they went there and they made an offering as it relates to
What the city would like to see down here, you tell us what you would do as a business owner. Because of that, you would get a tax break, number one. You would hire local people, number two. And you would get a long-term lease with the landowner on that so the abatements wouldn't keep on going. Resulting from that, it just continued to take off. It took a long period of time. The city of Lowell just got through doing something like that, and I think they just completed their seventh year of a program like that.
as it relates to taking downtown business districts as it relates to that. Earlier this evening, we heard about the fact that we don't have method people want to come here because we're not a business friendly community or whatever it might be. The unfortunate part is we only have one, one and a half people working in our office of community development. I'm offering an office of business and cultural affairs.
which will bring about an outreach for business, it'll bring out the history, it'll bring about an inclusionary of all the items within neighborhoods that are necessary to make business and development grow here within our city of Memphis, because each and every business district is different, and each and every business district abuts different residential neighborhoods or other types of businesses, and they too need to be addressed separately and independently.
So, uh, the offering here by counselor night, um, I don't know if it's because you were reading my mind or you read my mind before I, uh, you're reading my resolutions. Uh, I appreciate the fact that you're looking at this, but, um, I can assure you of this. Once I'm January comes, this will be one of the priority things that I will do as mayor of this community.
I will take this. Oh, I'm not campaigning. I am sorry. Mr. President. Um, I certainly appreciate where the gentleman's coming from and, um, I look forward to fortunate enough to be reelected to work with whoever's in the corner office. So thank you very much. Counselor for that. Thank you. Thank you. Was there a motion in there? Counselor Penta? Yeah, I would like to attach that to my resolution that I had tried to attach your resolution to counsel nights. I would like to resolution before us.
is offered by counselor night, right? But so I, yeah, I passed. Yes. Yes. It's in the same position that judges. Oh, I think it was like maybe in February, March of this year, we're going to ask for an update on counselor Penta's resolution as well. I just look it up in the minutes. So I have no problem with the night's motion for an update on counselor Penta's related motion. Mr. Clark has a B paper as a B paper.
And, sir, you wish to address us? Please state your name and address for the record. Good evening, Mr. President. Good evening. My name is John Starello. I reside at 20 Metcalfe Street in Medford. And about this offering here by Councilor Knight, it was only last December that he voted and the Hopes Council voted for a dual tax rate. In that tax rate, they voted a
$12 tax rate for residents, and double that, a $24 tax rate for commercials. Now, come along with reducing that. It should have been done at that time. I suggested at the time we have a single tax rate. It was the proper thing to do. The commercials would have been paying the same as the residents. Point of information, Councillor Knight. This resolution is the furthest thing from a single tax rate.
That could be possible. That's not what I envisioned at all and that's not what I'm seeking to do. I'm perfectly comfortable with the bifurcated tax rate that we have in place right now. My concern is that we have empty storefronts and we need to do more to attract businesses to keep them there. And we need to do more to attract businesses that are conducive to the long-term sustainability and viability of our squares. And that's why I put this measure forward, Mr. President.
plans in place for the redevelopment of Medford Square, the plan to redevelop Medford Square, and it tells us what kind of shops we need to have down there, and we don't have them. So the intention and the theory behind this was to attract those businesses that are part of the study that we paid hundreds of thousands of dollars for that provide us with the framework to revitalize and rejuvenate the area. Thank you for that point of information, and thank you for your use of the word bifurcation. Mr. President. Doctor.
Mr. President, if you want to charge the commercials less, you should do that at that time. It doesn't make sense to first charge them double and then give them an abatement. How does that make sense? You can do it all at one time. And about bringing up the single tax rate, single tax rate is something that should be considered. That is not fair to the residents. You're charging the residents that double rate. The residents are paying that $24, by the way.
When that $24 is added on, well, you have to know how these taxes are applied. And... Point of information, Councilor Knight. I believe when we discussed the single-payer tax rate, the residential obligation would have increased tremendously to the residential homeowner, Mr. President, to the point of like...
maybe close to $9 per thousand evaluation, if I believe I remember correctly. So we went through the numbers and it didn't seem to be something that was viable. And this council voted it down seven zero, Mr. President. So with that being said, I think, um, you know, I rest my case and I'll let the gentlemen move on. Thank you. That would not have permitted reelection. That was the problem. Let's face the problem as it really exists.
The concern there was whether or not you'd be reelected if that tax rate was a single tax rate. No, the concern was that people on a fixed income that are living at home and having struggling to pay their already high tax bill aren't going to be able to do it. That was my concern.
That's why I've always supported adopting the lowest residential factor, and I'll continue to do so. Then why do you have the residents pay it when it's added on as new growth? That's what happens to that tax rate. That $24 is added on as new growth. And who pays the new growth? The residents. So what you're doing is you're making the residents pay the $24. Mr. President, if I may, we've already had this debate and discussion. We voted on the matter. We voted on it to a conclusion. I'm sorry. And not debate with individual counselors. That's our procedure. Yes.
This is all through the chair, with all due respect. We're grateful. There has to be some understanding as to what happens to taxes. I mean, taxes go on to the tax levy limit.
And what happens is that $24 rate is shifted to the tax levy limit, and the residents end up paying it. The very thing that the council wants to avoid is what he's doing. But he doesn't realize that. I think what the council is trying to do, if I can help you, is apply a measure that's been successful tremendously in many urban areas to attract business and thus create
an atmosphere of urban renewal and success in neighborhoods that are both commercial and residential. And that's exactly what a single tax rate would do. It would be the same for everybody. It would be a level playing field. Mr. President, we've debated this issue to its conclusion previously. We voted against the measure. We voted it down 7 to 0. Thank you. It was concluded badly, with all due respect. Thank you very much, Doctor.
And Councilor Camuso wishes to be recognized. Thank you, Mr. President. And I agree. I think this is a great, great resolution. And I want to applaud Councilor Knight for bringing this forward. City of Medford, 1-1-2015 to 8-31-2015. Meals tax, $349,605.74 in meals tax for people participating in eating in our establishments in this community.
If they get an abatement for a new business, in that case, a restaurant to come in, you give them something, an incentive to start up costs, basically, like other communities do, this goes hand in hand. Like you said, urban renewal, development, it's what cities and towns are doing to get creative. Look at Somerville, many, many, many years ago, 1980s. 1980s.
It was all these little establishments, and people got incentives to clean up and make it vibrant. Now you look at it, and it's a mecca of walking to all the different squares. It's just, at the end of the day, Mr. President, if we give an incentive, just in this particular instance, say if it's a restaurant, you're going to make it up in the meals tax.
So I understand what John's trying to say. But at the end of the day, this is what's going to bring quality business here. It's going to put people to work. It's going to continue to grow the tax base. And it's going to get a storefront that is currently maybe vacant, something in there. And that's the intent of it, correct? Correct. And I support this wholeheartedly. I think that this is a heaven vision. I'm thinking outside the box, to be quite frank. So I do support Councilor Knight on this. Thank you very much, Councilor.
Good evening, sir. Please state your name and address for the record. Good evening, Council President. My name is Joseph Villione. I live at 59 Garfield Avenue, Medford, Mass. And about a year or two years ago, I took pictures up and down Salem Street, and I have logged the empty storefronts, not only on Salem Street, but all across Medford. Respectfully, through the Chair, Councilor Camuso had this as a campaign promise four years ago, I believe, and inside Medford, it's still there.
Now he's leaving, and he gets the great idea that, wow, Councilor Knight is right. Well, when I'm 99 years old and I'm praying a lot, they're going to say, Joe, why are you praying so much? I'm going to say I'm cramming for finals. That, I respectfully say to the chair, is what the council is doing now at election time, cramming for finals. And come January, we're not going to see any of it. We're going to hear congratulations.
All point of information, but same old malarkey, unless we get some new faces on this council. Mr. President, I failed to see what the commentary has to do with the substance of the resolution. It isn't. On the motion of council, a night for approval as amended. May I? Please state your name and address. Andrew Castanetti, Cushing Street, Medford, Massachusetts. It concerns me that this discussion here about giving the businesses a discount on their real estate
although I'm not anti-business, and this city should be more pro-business, in my opinion, within reason, of course. If anything, I would consider what I've been pushing for for many years, and that would be to have the owner-occupying real estate tax exemption under the state law instead. That being said again,
and I will pursue it in the next few weeks further. That part of Haines Square seems to have problems for many, many years and decades. A lot of turnover, fires, et cetera. Just my limited education thought, why not just eminent domain that whole block?
and give them fair market value, and put up a mixed-use type of property, a la Station and Landon, so to speak. To me, that would make good business sense and help us, the homeowner, real estate owner, occupy, hopefully. Thank you for listening. Thank you, Andrew. On the motion of Councilor Knight for approval, as amended by Councilor Penta, yes?
Councilor, your light's not lit. It might be a malfunction. Thank you, Mr. President. The chair recognizes Councilor Knight. Councilor Marks. Thank you, Mr. President. You know, I think the suggestion is a worthy suggestion. I mean, you only need to look in the community and see a long established business, Hoff's Bakery, that actually moved hundreds of jobs that were in the Wellington area for many, many years.
a Method business owner that got a better tax incentive over in Malden and decided to move his whole business to Malden. So, you know, it's great that we're sitting back talking about issues like this, but really one needs to just look at the Office of Community Development. We have one director and one part-time person in the Office of Community Development. I mean, I think that speaks volumes to the reason why we're not offering these type of incentives.
We're not attracting new business into this community. It's quite clear why, Mr. President. All you need to look at is a sister city next to us, the city of Somerville, that has over 13 people in their Office of Community Development. I had an opportunity to talk to the owner of Mystic Roasters, and she said that businesses and communities from surrounding communities have approached her on many occasions saying, we'd love to have the Mystic Roasters in our community.
What can we do to get you into our community? Do you think that's happening in the city of Meffitt? Do you think we're going out to surrounding communities saying, we'd love to see you? And maybe they are. Maybe the mayor went in and we could thank him for the pawn shop that we have at Meffitt Square. So maybe the mayor is doing that type of footwork, or the illegal massage parlor that we have. Maybe the mayor is attracting business in his own way. So I'm not quite sure, Mr. President.
But it's clear to me that this city's broken, and it's been broken for many, many, many years. And if you want to look at the reason why, it's clear to me this administration hasn't been operating on all its pistons for a number of years. And I'm hoping to see change come to fruition shortly, Mr. President. On the motion of Councilor Knight for approval as amended, Councilor Camuso. And I'm glad Councilor Marks brought up Huff's Bakery.
Because interesting enough, Hoffs Bakery was before this Medford City Council for the TIF, which was a tax incentive. And it was not unanimous vote of this city council to give them, some people had the vision to see that they were gonna put, like Councilor Mock said, X amount of people to work, gonna clean up a development behind 9th Street. That was a program that became before the city council, and
It's just another fact that this city council, and we're all entitled to our votes, there's no question. But check the record on it, it was not a unanimous vote of this city council. And now, unfortunately, because Malden is offering them a tax incentive similar to what Councilor Knight is looking to do here, they are moving. But the TIF on the Hoffs Bakery was before this city council a few years back. But thank you for bringing that up, Councilor Moxley.
Thank you. And on the motion for approval by Councilor Knight as amended. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Motion carries. 15-676 offered by Councilor Knight be it resolved the Office of Energy and Environment in conjunction with the School Department and Board of Health examine the feasibility of installing solar energy panels on MHS Medford High School. Councilor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much. Several weeks ago I was up
the field of dreams and I was sitting there with coach Perry watching the girls soccer team play Malden and it was about oh 150 degrees up there and as we were sitting on the field of dreams we could look out right across the top of Medford High School and what I saw was a gigantic flat roof and a lot of sun beating down on it and I thought that this might be a great opportunity for us to
solar or, I mean, harvest some of our solar energy, Mr. President. We have our Harvest the Energy Festival coming up in just a few short weeks, and I thought it was fitting to put this resolution forward because I feel as though, you know, provided that it meets the health and safety standards, it might be a way for us to generate some revenue that's reoccurring and non-tax-based. So, I might ask that my council colleagues support this endeavor, and I would hope that they would join me in voting in the affirmative. On the motion for approval by Councilor Knight, all those in favor?
Councilor Marks. I think it's a worthy resolution. For many years there, I don't know if they still exist or not, there were solar panels on the high school roof for many, many years. And as we all know, that high school roof has been notorious for leaks since it was built and still plagues the Meffitt High School with leaks throughout the department. But I don't see a problem looking into the feasibility, but I think we have to be mindful of the fact that that roof has been a concern for many, many years.
It's a flat roof and has had many, many issues. And also, if we can ask about what the success was of the solar panels that were on that roof and if they are still there, because this was going back some years ago. But I think it's a worthy resolution. Point of clarification, Mr. President, would the council like to amend it for hydropower as well?
And move for approval, Mr. President. On a motion of approval, as amended. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries. On the motion of Council night for suspension of the rules, to take a common vigilance license. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries, 15-682. Petition for common vigilance license by Richard M. Blau, Esquire, for TFS Newco, LLC, doing business as Tedeschi Food Shop, number 37372133 Main Street, Medford, Massachusetts.
02155 on file, business certificate 190, building department, fire department, police traffic impact, health department, treasurer, letter of compliance, state tax ID, workman's compensation application. Chair recognizes Councilor Caviello. Thank you, Mr. President. I have reviewed the papers and I found them to be in order. Could you explain to the people what your business hours are going to be? Please state your name and address for the record.
The business hours are the same as they are now. They're 24 hours. 24 hours. And do you want to continue that way? Yes, sir. Thank you. Do they have to reapply for them? Mr. President, I find the papers. I find the papers in order. Motion approved by Councilor Caviello. All those in favor? Councilor Knight. In reviewing the packet, I did see and hear some sort of release or power of attorney notice that discussed
TFS NUCCO LLC's power of attorney for licensure and permit purposes, and it speaks to having Gray and Robinson PA to serve as a nationwide regulatory council for alcoholic beverage licensure and permitting purposes. The two are separate and distinct. You're not before us this evening seeking an alcoholic beverage license. Is that correct? No. Okay, great. Mr. President, if I rest my case, I move for approval. On the motion of approval, all those in favor? Carried. On the motion of counsel and I, to revert back to the order of
Regular order of business, all those in favor, all those opposed, motion carries. 15. 677, offered by Councilor Carviello. Be it resolved that the Medford City Council congratulate Robert Emmett Skerry on his retirement from the State Auditor's Office after 33 years of service. Councilor Carviello. Thank you, Mr. President. I want to congratulate my friend, Mr. Skerry. He's a member of the school committee.
He's finally decided to retire after 33 years being one of the state's top fraud investigators for the auditor's office. And I want to congratulate him on his retirement, and now he'll work harder for the school committee. A great American. On the motion of councillor Caviello. Yes, councillor Marx. Thank you, Mr. President. I, too, want to thank my colleague councillor Caviello for putting this on, and I want to wish Mr.
I wish him well on his retirement, and I'm sure his many, many years on the school committee will also keep him busy and keep him active in his retired years as a state official. So I wish him well, Mr. President. I just want to wish Robert Emmons Carey Jr. Good luck in his retirement and give him more time to be around the schools and helping out our children.
It was opposed, motion carries. 15678 offered by Councilor Caraviello. Be it resolved, the Medford City Council requests that the mayor name the circle at La Conte Rink after Tony Bova. Tony has dedicated almost 40 years of volunteer service to the youth hockey community of Medford and still continues working with the children to this day. Councilor Caraviello. Thank you, Mr. President.
Often we kind of wait until it's too late until we make a dedication to somebody. But this is a man who's been dedicating himself to the youth hockey community of the city for 40 plus years. He's still doing it. He's the first person you meet when you come into Memphis hockey. He's kept the program up and down over the years. He's the last guy you see going out. You see him out there tirelessly working for this program.
I think if I had my way, I'd name the building after him, but unfortunately, it's after Captain Leconte. We can't do that. And I would like to see the mayor do this maybe before he leaves office, and before the winter, so that everyone will have a chance to see it. I mean, we've had multiple people go to the National Hockey League, college players. They've all started with Tony Bova at four years old, and he's the guy that everybody remembers when you first walk in the door. Again, he's a good man.
And I think we have a couple of people here that want to speak in his favor in getting this done also. Very good. Come on up and please state your name and address for the record. Thank you, Mr. President. I'm Patrick McCabe, 38 Ashcroft Road, Medford. I'm also the president of Medford Rec Hockey.
Tony's been with the program. It's very fitting. This is our 40th anniversary this year for Medford Rec Hockey. And at our board meeting the other night, Tony was talking about how he coached Councilor Penta's travel hockey team. So it's been there quite some time. Tony, the thing that I appreciate most about Tony is that
Despite the fact that he's been there for 40 years, he's still very, very patient, and he's still open to change. Within the last three years, Medford Hockey, we've grown from eight travel teams to 13. And that's all through a lot of new ideas that Tony, we brought forward to Tony, his new parents in the program. And Tony explained to us the pitfalls, and he was quick to change when he thought change was necessary. So he's a very, very impressive man.
The other thing that's very impressive about Tony is that for 40 years he's been explaining the same thing to dozens of parents with the patience of a saint. Hockey and youth sports, I know some folks here are very involved in youth sports, it's very challenging. Tony's been a pillar of the community in doing that.
We'd appreciate it, speaking for the Board of Medford Rec Hockey, and we'd appreciate positive action on this motion. Thank you. Awesome. Thank you. Deputy? Bob Jones, 5 St. Mary's Street, Medford Mass. I'm also the treasurer of Medford Rec Hockey. I rise in support of this motion. As Pat just mentioned, Tony is a staple of the rink. He's always there when you need him.
He serves us with some great institutional memory, institutional knowledge. He remembers how everybody did it and did it well, didn't do it so well, and why and when it happened and what we need to do to push things into the future. It's very fitting and well-deserved. Thank you. Thank you. Mr. President, I was there when Tony Bova, when I was president, we started the girls' figure skating program, which only Woburn had at that time.
And now they have girls hockey. I mean, the program has been a staple of the state as one of the better programs around. Chair recognizes Councilor Penta.
I like the idea of having that, and maybe we should call him Mr. Sports, because he's always a great, patient guy, and I've known him for longer than him. And basically, we all want to be in the same country.
Watch out, your mic's not working. I don't know. Press your button again. Plug your thing.
There we are. The messenger saved us. Let's try this again. Okay. What I'd like to say that Tony Bova deserves the award. Uh, we also know besides him being involved in hockey, he was actively involved, um, in men's softball. He was actively involved in keeping people, um, competitive in sports, no matter what the age group was or is. And, um, and that's a true staple to him.
But having you folks come up here and through Councilor Caviello wanting to give him this award, I think it's great. I like to call him Mr. Sports because he is actively involved in so many things within this community that involves parents as well as kids. It's deserving. He's a very humble guy and I hope he's, I know he's going to be appreciative of this when he comes up here. The one thing that Councilor Caviello indicated that you would hope he would get the award
before this mayor leaves office. There's a host of other issues. There's other people, Councilor Caviello. There are other. I understand that, but you said you hoped he would come up here. There are other resolutions that have been passed for people to get awards that are in queue, so to speak. So I would hope maybe this is the genesis to push all the other folks who are waiting. And so with that being said, I thank you for being here and being supportive of it.
Thank you. Thank you, Councillor. Councillor Camuso. Thank you, Mr. President. Tony Bova, just don't even know where to start. I echo the sentiments of Councillor Penter and Councillor Caravaglio. Just a great guy. And it's kind of ironic, too, because we saw him at the community day a few weeks ago. He had the table for Medford Youth. And when I was shooting the breeze with him, I says, hey, you look the exact same as you did as when I was a mite.
He hasn't changed a wink. He's one of those guys that just looks the exact same. Lost a little hair, right, counselor? But Tony's just a great guy. You know, I played for him when I was a mite. And I went right through, played at Medford High School. And he was always a big part of the high school team and high school athletics. And it didn't stop with hockey, as the counselor noted.
started the figure skating. It was under his leadership that girls hockey was started at the youth level, and then Councilor Lungo took over and got it initiated at the high school level. But just a great guy, and I do support this. And also to piggyback on what Councilor Penta said, there are other people that this council has looked to honor over some time, and maybe now the mayor can take some of those under advisement, and if he sees
true that they're deserving, as this council has, to move forward with some of them. Mr. President, thank you very much. I, too, have had the pleasure of knowing Tony Bova, but my relationship with him is a little different. We work together because I can't skate. I'm one of the only guys in Medford, I think, that can't ice skate.
Mr. Bova and I worked together down the hockey rink. I was operating the Zamboni and working as a custodian down there. And Mr. Bova was doing what he does with youth hockey. And through that relationship, I've always admired the fact that Mr. Bova is a very soft-spoken man whose actions speak louder than his words. He's the first one to step up to the plate, volunteer to take the charge, and be there to help.
And when he's there to help, he's sometimes more than willing to help with the youngest of children, which is sometimes the most difficult to deal with, Mr. President. And we've all been down there on picture night, right, Pat? And picture night gets a little crazy, and Tony handles it with the patience of a saint, as has been said before. So with that being said, Tony, congratulations for your 40 years of service, and thank you very much for being a part of Medford Youth Hockey and Medford Youth Sports. Really appreciate your service.
Thank you, Mr. President. And it's been said before, but what a true gentleman. He was always very consistent, still is very consistent. And to think, someone that dedicated 40 years of their life, never, ever, ever looked for praise, never looked for any type of recognition. He used to have his own sports show on local access.
And think about the thousands of children he touched their lives. Thousands of Meffitt children. And he kept Meffitt-Reck alive when years that really there was no one else to do so. And he's been a staple for that in our community for many years. And I just want to wish him well. This is a great tribute. I thank Councilor Caviello and the other gentleman that came up to present this. And I think it speaks volumes on his character.
really the need to recognize people that go over and above in the community, Mr. President, and not look for any recognition. Thank you, Mr. President. You know, it was some years ago when, you know, Councilor Camuso and Councilor Knight were young kids. That building was going to close by the state. And we had begged the mayor at that time to come in and take the building over, and the mayor didn't want to do it.
The state was going to shut down. It was Tony Bova, myself, and some other parents that went up to the statehouse with kids and got them, then Charlie Shannon, Senator Shannon, to find the funding to keep the building on and do the roof over when they were going to shut the place down because the roof was going to fall down. So again, without Tony, there probably wouldn't even be a rink there today.
Thank you, Councilor Caviello. It's on the motion for approval by Councilor Caviello. All those in favor? All those opposed? Congratulations, Tony. Thank you guys for coming down and supporting. 15672, offered by Vice President Lungo Kern. And I'm going to read this in its entirety. It's long and tedious, but it's important. City of Medford, call for city election, Tuesday, November 3rd,
2015, be it ordered that in accordance with the provision of the general laws of Massachusetts and the revised charter of the city of Medford, insofar as the latter is applicable, the city clerk be and he is hereby authorized and instructed to notify and warn such of the inhabitants of the city of Medford qualified to vote, and the law requires, to assemble at the several polling places as designed
in this order for and within the several precincts where they are duly registered voters on Tuesday, November 3rd, 2015, then and there to give their ballots for the nomination of, respectively, one mayor to serve for a period of two years from the first Monday in January 2016 to be elected by and from the qualified voters of the city at large, seven
members of the City Council to serve for a period of two years, from the first Monday in January 2016, to be elected by and from the qualified... I said that I was going to read this important matter out loud. Seven members of the City Council to serve the period of two years, from the first Monday in January 2016,
to be elected by and from the qualified voters of the city at large. Six members of the school committee to serve for a period of two years from the first Monday, January 2016, to be elected by and from the qualified voters of the city at large. One question, shall the city of Medford accept sections three to seven of chapter 44B of the general laws community preservation act?
Be it further ordered that the following named polling places be and they are hereby designated to be used at the city election to be held on Tuesday, November 3rd, 2015. The said polling places to be open from 7 a.m. to 8 p.m. Ward 1, Precinct 1, Andrew Middle School. Ward 1, Precinct 2, Firefighters Club, Salem Street. Ward 2, Precinct 1,
St. Francis Parish Center, Felsway West, and Fulton Street. Ward 2, Precinct 2, Roberts Elementary School, 35 Court Street. Ward 3, Precinct 1, Lawrence Memorial Hospital, 170 Governor's Ave. Ward 3, Precinct 2, Temple Shalom, 475 Winthrop Street. Ward 4, Precinct 1, Tufts University, Gantcher Center, 161 College Ave. Ward 4, Precinct 2,
Walkling Court, Auburn, and North Street at the Fondacaro Center. Ward 5, Precinct 1, Columbus Elementary School, 37 Hicks Ave. Ward 5, Precinct 2, Columbus Elementary School, 37 Hicks Ave. Ward 6, Precinct 1, West Medford Fire Station, 26 Harvard Ave. Ward 6, Precinct 2, Brooks School, 388 High Street. Ward 7, Precinct 1, Mystic Valley Towers, North Building Entrance. Ward 7, Precinct 2,
McGlynn K-8 Public School, 3004 Mystic Valley Parkway, Ward 8, Precinct 1, Senior Center, 101 Riverside Ave, Ward 8, Precinct 2, Veterans of Foreign Wars Hall, 114 Mystic Ave. On the motion for approval by Vice President Lungo Kern, all those in favor? All those opposed? The motion kept. Did you have something on the motion? It was just approved, Councilor.
Go ahead, sir. The citizen wants to speak first. Did you want to speak on this, sir? Thank you. Please state your name and address for the record. It's Anthony D'Antonio, 12 Yale Street in Medford. I'd like to, through the chair, ask City Clerk Finn two questions regarding the election. And before I do that, I would just like to ask him,
Through the chair, have any of the councilors seen the new lighting on the parkway from the bridge where Luminaire is to the police, state police headquarters? They put in the LED lamps up there. It's a magnificent lighting. Is this on this matter? No, I just wanted to ask that question. So let me ask this question, Mr. Finn, through the chair. Can I do this? Please.
Back in the 2010 election, Mr. Finn, you offered to the candidates the opportunity to come in and look at the voting machines that we're going to be using in the election for voting. Last year, I don't believe that happened, and I wanted to know if it's going to be an issue this year that you may put that demonstration on explaining how the voting machines work and so on and so forth. So that's one question.
What I wanted to know is at the end of the election, at the end of the day, when the polls close, what is the procedure for people to get the vote, the count of the vote in each precinct when the polls close before the ballots come up to city hall? And the last question, if you could be so kind to answer is,
What is the procedure, and how do you count for all the absentee ballot votes? And how do they come in when they come in from nursing homes, acute care facilities, and assisted care housing? That's all I have to ask. So I'll just sit down. So if I get this right, the first one is the notification on the testing of the machines.
What we're obligated to do is we send out a schedule to the parties that this is going to be taking place. The parties, if they have candidates, the state committee person or the local committee, they notify their individual. Yeah, that's my obligation to be how it happens. He's talking about the 2010, and that's exactly how.
that happened because it was a party thing. But that still holds true in the local election. But they are, we do have a schedule. Anybody's, it'll be the last week in October, Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, 11 to 1. And we'll take a certain amount of machines per day.
point of information? I know this year the big race is the mayor's race. So chairman Donato will be notified to come down on behalf of the democratic candidate, which is, well, I don't want to get into politics, but there's a democrat and a republican running. So the republican individual who's here this evening, Mr. Capucci, will come down on behalf of the republican candidate for mayor? Is that how this works? They can notify those people to come down. Yes, yes, yes. And then what about...
I know what you're saying. I'm fulfilling the obligation of the testing procedure. So I'm doing that. So it is open, but the local chair of the parties, and we do notify not only Democrat, Republican, I think the United Independence Party and things like that, they all get a letter. They all get a letter. And it's up to them if they want to come down on your behalf or
to notify you if you want to come down. No. Point of information, Counsel Penta. This is a nonpartisan election. Where in the law does it say that in a municipal nonpartisan election? Are all 16 of these machines going to be tested, Eddie? I'm obligated by the state to test the machines. All 16? All 16 machines, OK? And I'm obligated to notify the local
parties, which I do. Mr. Green, he's the local chairman. Donato, whoever. That obligation hasn't changed in 18, 20, whatever it is, 30 years we've been doing it. I've had people come down on their own. It is posted on the bulletin board, the letter that I sent out to the different parties. So if you want to come down, you can follow procedure.
Well, can you notify the candidates as well? I'm publicly asking you, can you notify the candidates as well? Will you? Will I notify them? Yeah. Well, hopefully, if you're affiliated with a big party, that they're doing it for you. But certainly, if you want, we can send it out there.
Point of information, councillor night. When the city clerk sends out this notice to the parties, the political parties, acknowledging that the machines have been tested, he does so in writing. There's a certain correspondence of something that goes out? Yeah. Is it done in writing? Can we have that included in our packet when it goes out, Mr. President? Thank you. The next part of the questions was? It should be all candidates. Yeah. It should be all 16, all 15, whatever it is.
Fulfilling the requirements of the testing. The conveyance of election results. OK. They should be posted right outside the results on every precinct.
My hope is, myself as an individual, can I go in there when the polls close and get a count on the candidates who received X amount of votes in that precinct? Yeah, you should. Yeah. As soon as they count them. So we can enter the poll. What they're going to do is run the electronic version, and they post two tapes on the wall, and many people come in and write it down and judge what they wanted down here.
And the third part was the capacity balance for institutions. Those are all logged and transported to each individual ward and precinct to be tallied there. So is there a method for the people to, let's say there's 147 people in a particular place. Do they mail them in or do we send a representative from City Hall to collect them?
Do you know what I'm saying? Because of the situations that exist up in these places. They're mostly mailed in, or they do come at the clerk's office at certain hours to do in-person absentee ballots. I wanted to make sure that. But they're not tallied at that time. No, I understand. Then they get tallied at the polling location. All right, great. Thank you very much.
When you say they're not—when are those ballots actually opened and tallied, the absentee ballots? During the course of the day. So you don't wait until the end of the day and open them up? No. So if you have 10 or 15 ballots come in at 2 o'clock in the afternoon, somebody opens them up and puts them in the machine, how are you going to know which ones are absentee? Pardon me? How do you know which ones are absentee if you're putting them in the count?
We have an absentee log sheet, just like we have the check-in. When you go in and check in to vote, right, and you request a ballot, they're going to ask for your name, right? That same procedure we have for absentee ballots. So we're checking their names out so we know who the absentee ballot is. No, no, no. Go back to the second question. If the sheet comes off with a number, candidate A gets 100, candidate B gets 90, are you saying that the absentee ballots are included in that 190?
total. But I thought they had until five o'clock of the day of the election to get the ballots in the absentee ballot to be effective. I got to get the ballots in up until eight o'clock that night. Right. So if the mail is delivered at eight o'clock at night or seven or six o'clock, I could probably get a, uh,
I don't know, a UPS maybe that comes in at 7 to City Hall. I got to wrap that up and get it out to a board. So are you saying that once you post that thing on there, that paper posting out there at 805, that has all the absentee ballots to be counted? Is that what you're saying? Unless it's an unusual circumstance. And then the board would have to look at it and see if that would count.
So let me get this straight. All absentee ballots are to be included in the 16 ballot boxes at 8.05 or whatever that time is when that white strip comes out and the totals are in. I mean, we get the majority of them all during the day anyways. We only get a very few after 5 o'clock. We actually run to the post office physically and go up there to make sure that we've got them all in there. So then just explain, for the sake of clarification,
In this most recent primary, there was a couple of, what do you call the ballots that had to be reviewed? Provisional? Provisional, yeah. Explain that. That's entirely different. That does not get counted at the poll on location provisionals. So what constitutes a provisional ballot? Well, if you're not on the regular active list,
You're not even on the inactive list. But you're pretty adamant that you registered to vote here, but we don't have a log for you. We'll give you the option to do a provisional ballot. What happens on the provisional ballot is the next two days, the board will have to do
research the circumstances, right, and see if they can find a particular link that that would actually count. Now, most of the time, if they say they're registered, okay, we end up finding out they're really registered someplace else, and that provision will probably get rejected. But a lot of times, you might have a circumstance that might have it at the RMV, registered motor vehicles, right?
And it's something that maybe they didn't relate to us. Because if you go and renew your license and all that kind of stuff, they ask you if you want to register to vote. Maybe something happened there. And we obtained that document. And we look at the back, and if it's a checkmark, that they registered. But the IRV didn't send it to us to log in. Obviously, we created a link that they were really registered.
So it's dependent on the circumstances, but it's, but it's, but if you don't show up on active or inactive, right, but you're adamant that you think you're, you know, you're a voter, you know, we'll give you opportunity to, uh, to do, uh, uh, a provision, but you get, you got to supply identification and all that, you know, the backup. For someone to come and register to vote, you do not have to show identification. Is that true or false? Pardon me? If a brand new person was to walk into the city hall,
to go downstairs to register and vote. Do they have to show an ID or not? Yeah, but they also have to put a few digits on the back that associates them with their, I think their social security. But what if they don't have one? Well, if they don't have a social security card. You can't vote? They must know their social security card. You can't vote? Well, you've got to be a citizen to vote. So you're saying that every person that registers to vote.
has to have a Social Security number. Yeah, last four digits, Jim. Pardon me? We put the last four digits in there. So they have to show you that card? Not the card, just the identification. So anybody could just 1, 2, 3, 4, and you've got to write it down? Yeah. And then once we enter into the system, that link will go into the state, you know, for verification. So that's the only way to verify if somebody is a legitimate, if somebody can vote?
I said, that's the only way somebody can verify if they're eligible to vote. No picture ID, no nothing. Just walk in there and give them four numbers that supposedly are your last four numbers on Social Security. Yeah. A lot of times, Bob, is that when they come in to register to vote, they've also been from another community. Pretty. Can you tell them to be quiet, please? They've been to another community.
We can also create the link if they were a voter another community, you know So what you're gonna do is you'll notify the council and everyone that the date that you can have these machines tested The dates you can have these machines tested you will notify us as a council Yeah, okay
And all 16 will be tested, correct? Oh, in separate days, yeah. In three days' time, yeah. You don't do them all in the same day? No, I wish I could. I'm not that fit. I mean, it takes a little bit of work. I'm a one-man band that does it. Do you have any backup machines, just in case one of them doesn't work? Backup machines? Well, that's part of the testing process.
So if one of the machines doesn't test out, what do you do? I'll contact the vendor, and he'll come down and fix it. That was the question. Do you have a backup system? Yeah, I don't. I mean, we never bought backup machines. Point of information, Councilor Camuso. I understand that we're asking questions here, but we haven't had these problems.
There's never been a question of ethical standards during an election that I've heard of. I just, I don't know, I'm getting a bad taste, almost like it's conspiracy theory here. I understand that we have to obviously make sure that the ethical standards are upheld.
I don't know of any particular situation that's leading up to these questions. If so, this should be brought not only to our clerk, but to the Secretary of State's office, who oversees the elections in Massachusetts. So that's just my— Thanks for that point of information, Counsel Penter. Are you— And last but not—oh, sorry. I'm sorry. Go ahead.
Are you finished, Counselor Penta? No, he wants the floor. Give it to him. No, no. He made a point of information, which is now concluded. I'll wait my turn. You have the floor. Counselor Penta is through. Counselor Camuso. Chair recognizes Counselor Camuso. Thank you. Counselor Penta just said that all the counselors should be notified. I think you have to take it one step further, because that would be someone that's not a current counselor may look at that and say, well, why can the counselors be notified? I would like to make a blanket. Everybody's notified. Anyone that's going to appear on the ballot,
But no, you just said that the council is getting notified. And I think you just didn't add to it. But with that being said, I think that everybody that's appearing on the ballot in November, and I'm not one of them this year, with that being said, I think everyone should be notified. That's all. On the motion for approval by Vice President Lungo Kern for the call to election, all those in favor? All those opposed? Congratulations.
The chair is waiting for a motion to take item number 15629 off the table. On the motion of Councilor Caviello that the matter 15629 come back before us. All those in favor? Mr. President? All those opposed? Would the aggrieved parties please approach the podium? Mr. President?
Chair recognizes Councillor Camuso. We're going to. So as people are coming back in, I think an arrangement was made for a 90 day at midnight and then the 91st day it would be the one o'clock if there's no problems.
I'd like to hear it from one of each party very clearly. We won't have anybody talking over anybody, but we'll allow this agreement to be reported to us so that the clerk can record the terms down in an adequate manner so that we have clarity on all of this. And the council's most appreciative to all of you for your hard work on this matter.
So if you would, please. OK. We met with the owners, and we came up with a solution that currently, for the next 90 days, the sports bar will be open
until midnight each day. They will be having karaoke, and that will be closing at 11 o'clock. But the restaurant itself, the bar, everything will close down at midnight. After a 90-day, and this is pretty much like a probationary period, after the 90 days, the motion you have in front of you
increase the hours to 1 p.m. on Thursday, Friday, and Saturday would go into effect.
With that, we request a one year probation period of those three days. If there's any problems, a year later we'll come back and review it again. But I don't foresee any problems. I think we're looking forward to having them as good neighbors. And I think they feel the same way. I wish them a lot of luck.
But for the next 90 days, they'll be open till midnight. And then after that, they're 1 PM closing on Thursday, Friday, and Saturday. So is there a review in any of this? You want an annual review after one year? After one year, we'd like to review it. That's reasonable. And have us notified this time instead of the parking lot. In a circumference of a circle, not a one section of a-
I'm sure an engineer figured it out, and whatever it is, it isn't satisfactory. And we know that, and we got that message loud and clear. But if the store owners are agreeable to those terms, very good. Chair recognizes Vice President Lungo Kern. Thank you. Just with regards to the doors in the back, will those be closed during the karaoke and late night hours for the noise level?
And they did inform us they do have soundproofing in there, too, in the room that the karaoke is in. Oh, wonderful. That shouldn't be a problem. The doors are primarily open because of the heat from the summer from the actual kitchen area. But now that the weather's changing, I don't think they'll be opening the doors so often. One thing that we did discuss, and it's really a city matter as much as a concern for us, the parking lot itself,
There's one light there in that entire parking lot, and it shines in one direction, which is fine when it's working, but it shuts off a lot of the time, and it's pitch black in there. And that's just a haven, because we were even discussing with them, they're going to have customers coming in using that parking lot.
You know, if I was a thief, you know, who's been breaking into the houses in my neighborhood, and that's been a recurring thing, knowing that a restaurant now is established there, and they have people coming from all over, and the cars are parked at 12 or 1 in the morning.
and the parking lot has terrible lighting, you know, you're opening up another can of worms. So we don't want their customers coming out complaining that, you know, I've been robbed and now you have the blue lights from the police cars answering their calls at 1.30, 2 o'clock in the morning. You know what I mean? So I really think...
Councilor Camuso is going to go down and look at the parking lot tomorrow, the area that I told you guys about, but that entire parking lot really should be under review by the city because there's a lot of potential problems there. It's a mess back there. It is. And it hasn't been swept by the city in two years. I can pretty much.
It hasn't been. For the last six years, I've been calling and being put on the list. So, I mean, that's just an ongoing thing. Thank you. Chair recognizes Councilor Camuso. Thank you, Mr. President. And first off, I want to commend Councilor Mox because I really didn't see Kula Hedge prevailing tonight. So, nice job, Councilor Mox. So, a motion for approval for the first 90 days
open till midnight, the 91st day to the 365th day, 1 a.m., with a restriction of 11 p.m. karaoke stops, and that we ask the city to upgrade the lights in the parking lot, and when I say the city, that's the mayor, because he has the purse strings. That's gonna be a separate issue. We'll bring it up right after. We'll do that as a separate paper. Do it as a separate paper, so motion for approval with the conditions.
In the probation, the one year. One year review. I'm sorry. Yep. Yes. One year. With the butters. Actual butters, not computerized butters. Not the parking lot?
They also informed us when they have last call in the restaurant itself. And it's usually, you sit a half hour before you close it. And there's no problem there. As long as the last drinks are served a half hour before they close, we're not getting people in there 10 minutes before they close and ordering a couple of drinks at a time. That won't be the case. You don't want to let people in that late, because they were there for obvious reasons. Exactly. We're only there for that reason. All the bars are there.
The bars in Malden and everywhere else, they shut the doors at a time before that, so they're not just getting the refresh. I don't think, if they're going out, we're hoping they're going out, but they probably won't even need a bouncer. But let's hope there's no bouncers. No, exactly. Good. If there's bouncers, the year review. Yeah.
If there's bounces, there may be a review before that year is up. Exactly. I mean, well, somebody said in the meeting that, you know, as the abutters, we're tying our hands because we're letting them have the one year, and we have no leverage. I said, we do have leverage. It's called the law. And trust me, if every neighbor starts calling up the police, you know, at 1 o'clock, 1.30 in the morning to come to Lambert Street,
you'll be hearing it in no time at all. So I'm, you know, they can be blamed for certain things that they're in control of and we understand that. The area itself needs a lot of help and we're not looking to make problems. We're looking to better the neighborhood and we're all in agreement with that. So we wish them luck and we're not here to, you know, hamper their prospects, but we just want to keep our neighborhood safe and
And next year, they'll cater the fishermen's feast fire in the North End. I'm sorry, Councilor. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Councilor Camuso, Councilor Marks. Thank you, Mr. President. On the motion of approval by Councilor Camuso. Councilor Camuso just offered, I believe, an A paper. It has nothing to do with the conditions, but for the lighting in the lot. We'll do that as a separate paper. I'd also like to add the sidewalk on Lambert, right in front of the entrance to the parking lot going down the street.
And we also were talking about crafting or looking at the existing ordinance that deals with extended hours, Mr. President. And if I can make that a C paper, so a B and C paper that discusses the subcommittee on licensing me to discuss any ambiguities that may be in the process of the hours of operation. And what do you do if they're extended and so forth? And when do people actually have to vacate?
And that's something we do as a council, as the legislative body. Right.
Just that we also meet with the chief of police to discuss, you know, crime in general, but get an update with regards to the. We vote on those papers. Okay. Yes.
Yes. Yes. On the big paper, which we'll combine them all together, we're going to have a meeting of the license, refer the matter to the
a subcommittee on licensings for review of ordinances and processes, for lighting in the parking lot, for fixing of the Lambert Street sidewalk, and for a meeting with the police chief to discuss crime in that neighborhood in particular.
Councilor Camuso? On this particular matter, if we could send the road renovations to the DPW Fort Worth? Yes. Because over the next 30 to 45 days, there is major renovations going on in this city. And just on that as well, ask that people be patient, because they're grinding down a significant amount of roads that they didn't plan on doing. So if we could ask for people's patience, because there's going to be a lot of roadwork going on. On that motion, all those in favor? All those opposed?
The second paper carries. Now, on the motion of Vice President Logan Curran to revert back to the regular order of business. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries, 15-679. Petition by Jean M. Martin, 10 Cummings Street, Medford, Massachusetts, to address the Council about public safety buildings. Ms. Martin, welcome. Thank you. Please state your name and address for the record.
Gene Martin, 10 Cumming Street. And I just witnessed government that works. That was awesome. That was awesome. Good for you guys. Okay. It's repetition, but repetition is the mother of retention. It is not the role of the police department to make the case of a new 911 center and police fire station for us. It is our responsibility to evaluate the need and meet it for the well-being of the whole city.
A police station is not exciting people, but necessary. I commend Mr. Carviello for taking the unpopular view of a Prop 2.5 override for this purpose. At least he understands the gravity of this issue. Police personnel wear a uniform, and that separates them psychologically from the general population, and so we view them as different from ourselves. They are human, and we often lose that humanity when we see them on the street.
Most citizens don't interact with police officers regularly, and as a result, don't really understand them. We see them most often as only male and strong, and I say that in quotes, and in not need of support. Also, keep in mind that police personnel cannot go out on strike, unlike the DPW and Teachers Union. And remember, buildings can't vote either. So who has the vote? We do.
The rules of engagement have changed drastically in the last 15 years since 9-11, and police officers are having a hard time enough keeping up. Not to have a decent building to work in only compounds the problem. Citizens who enter the building deserve a comfortable setting to inquire, report crimes, et cetera. Citizens should not experience attitude from officers. However, we must also ask ourselves, how do we treat them?
We send them the signal that they are our servants only, and that we hold no responsibility to them. Detainees deserve the benefit of the doubt until proven guilty, and therefore deserve fair and adequate treatment. And in strong hierarchies where people have power and stress, it rolls downhill, if you follow my meaning. And it shouldn't land on the incarcerated. In the past, this mayor
has gotten the city all its goodies by his political connections with the state and federal politicians and agencies. Those days are over. And money is going to be harder to get, given our $19 trillion debt crisis and a half trillion dollar annual deficit. Even if I were wrong and the money were to be there in, say, three years, that is still three years too late. I'm not done yet.
All capital improvement projects should be put on hold until this passes the contracting stage. Why? Because without social order, you have nothing. We as a society must agree on certain collective laws or chaos ensues. Can you imagine the streets if we didn't address speeding or public drunkenness? Or how about a fight between two neighbors? If you want to handicap our police and fire department, be my guest.
But don't cry to me when the police officer's morale is at an all-time low, and they start snapping on their spouses and or citizens in the street. Don't complain to me when the technology to handle a medical or fire emergency, which could have been updated and wasn't, led to an otherwise preventable death. We can't be everything to the police and fire department, but there are certainly are things we must and can do, and building out a new facility is one of them.
We have the absolute right to and should question an individual officer's conduct and or group of officers conduct who protect the institution at all costs by covering up wrongdoing. However, when we do not alleviate their stresses to the most absolute possibility that within our power, we too commit that offense to the public. We as a city need to work with our police force, or it doesn't matter how many,
there are or what kind of building we put them in. Our police officers also require extensive training for the new era that they find themselves in, living in and working in. This city needs a whole new safety plan, one that includes shelter-in-place and lockdowns for environmental or violent-related emergencies. We need a citywide
plan for traffic, including bike traffic. We need community input to make this city work within safe boundaries. Someone needs to speak for the voiceless. And while they have a union, they do not have a voice in this city comparable to that of, say, the school system. The school system has young middle-class advocates, a whole committee dedicated to its growth, and the sight of those little helpless children. It's a no-brainer.
who the politician is going to cater to. Their job description keeps expanding, and that is the police officer's job description, especially as stresses from the national end up coming down to the local levels. If you like your social order, thank a cop. If you don't like Medford police officers, look in the mirror. If you don't do anything, you have no right to complain. Thank you.
Mr. Councilor Camuso. Thank you, Ms. Martin. Receive in place on file. Motion of Councilor Camuso to receive in place on file. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion of Councilor Camuso to take papers in the hand of the clerk. All those in favor? All those opposed? Papers in the clerk. Did I miss anything on the agenda? He has to be withdrawn.
as a message was conveyed to me by the city messenger. Thanks, Larry. Papers in the hand of the clerk, we have two condolences here offered by Councilor Knight. Be it resolved that the City Council extend its deep and sincere condolences to the family of Catherine Scaramuzzo on her recent passing. Second, be it resolved by the Memphis City Council
That it's extended deep and sincere condolences to the family of Carmella Milly Natarelli on her recent passing. Both neighbors, if we could please rise for a moment of silence for both of these dedicated citizens, both fine women.
Offered by Councilor Knight be it resolved the City Administration report back to the Council on paper 15-356 regarding pedestrian signaling at Forest Street and King Ave. Councilor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much. A few short weeks before the grand opening of McNally Park, we requested that crosswalks be installed.
across Forest Street so that individuals who would like to go and utilize our new multi-million dollar park are able to cross the street safely. And I'm wondering if the administration would be kind enough to give us an update as to the status thereof. Very good. On the motion for approval by Councilor Knight. All those in favor? All those opposed? Carries. Offered by Councilor Marks. We resolve that the traffic division under the Metro Police Department monitor the speeding on Washington Street due to public safety concerns in the neighborhood. Councilor Marks.
Mr. President, I was contacted by several neighbors on Washington Street that mentioned to me that there's drag racing going on. We all know that's a long stretch of road. And just recently, a young boy was struck on a bicycle and severely hurt himself on Washington Street.
And neighbors asked that there be an increased presence on the street, as well as possibly an electronic speed machine that we have in the community, and them to step up patrol. And if we could put out a paper also asking the Traffic Commission to look into a potential raised crosswalk, in particular on Washington, because of the length of its street and the nature of cars flying down there, Mr. President.
I would ask that that also be sent to the Traffic Commission for review. Very good measure, Councilor. Councilor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much. May I be so bold to suggest that we ask the Traffic Commission to also maybe temporarily place the temporary speed bumps that we have just purchased through the Community Improvement Initiative down there on Washington Street as well to prevent them from being able to race until we can come up with a long-term solution to the problem like an elevated crosswalk.
That's a great point, Mr. President. Could we get a report back? Central Ave was supposed to be one of the three pilot race crosswalks, and there's a speed bump out there now, one of those temporary speed bumps. Could we get a report back on why that's there and when the — as well as Harvard? Harvard is supposed to get a race crosswalk, too. When that — if it is going to take place?
So on the motion of Councillor Marks as amended by Councillor Knight and Councillor Marks. All those in favour? Aye. Opposed? Motion carries. Offered by Councillor Camuso. Be it resolved that the vacant building across the street from the Metro Fire Department headquarters on Main Street be discussed. Councillor Camuso. Thank you, Mr. President. If we could send a request to the Building Commissioner to find out the status of the permits,
and everything else that goes along with that building. It's the building right next to Tedeschi's. And what's the wedding place by the dresses? Teresa's boutique, exactly. It's been sitting vacant for quite some time. There really hasn't been that much activity. So if we can get an update, and if they don't have an update, if they can reach out to the developer and find out what's going on with it.
Very good. So on the motion of Councilor Camuso, all those in favor? Those opposed? Motion carries. Records. Records of the tabled records of the July 21st, 2015 meeting are still in the possession of Councilor Penta. Councilor Penta, could you please instruct us on how this is to be addressed? Well, what would you like me to say, Councilor? I'd like a motion in one way or another. I read them.
I've read them. Want me to say I approve them? Yes. Yes. Councillor Pinto approves those records. So on the motion for approval, all those in favour? All those opposed? Records are approved. Records of the September 22nd, 2015 meeting were passed to Councillor Karafiello. Councillor Karafiello, how did you find those?
It's good to be in order, Mr. President. So on the motion of Councilor Cairo-Viello for approval, all those in favor? All those opposed? And on the Councilor Penta's recommendation for adjournment. Mr. President? Councilor Marks? Mr. President, I think it was brought up last week, but the American flag that is directly behind you, there used to be an eagle at the top of that flag. And it has been missing for several weeks now.
And I would ask that it be replaced or a new flag be put in its place, Mr. President. So noted. On Councilor Penta, while we're still approaching our... Further point, while the meeting is on. If you look up in the ceiling over there, when is it ever going to get fixed? It's over two years old. Over two years old. It's over two years old. We've all watched people almost die. Right. It's the current administration that's allowed it. There's a lot that has to be done with this building. It's about to fall over, and it's a gem.
A motion for what do we call this? Adjournment by Councillor Penta. All those in favour? All those opposed? Good night.