I'm so happy to be back at the doors, right?
Knocking on doors and talking to voters is super fun.
I really love it.
I'll just tell you a little bit about what I say to people because it's kind of fun and how people react.
I'm like, hey, you know, I'm
I'm Anna Callahan, I'm running for state rep, software engineer, and mom.
And then I ask, do you know much about the state house?
And they're like, not really.
And I'm like, oh, well, I'll tell you two fun facts that you can share with your friends.
Number one is that there's no way for any of us to know how our state reps are voting.
And number two,
is that the last three speakers of the house have all been convicted of felonies related to corruption and bribery.
So I just had someone today who after I did that, and then of course I go on to explain like why, how that, why that matters and what the policies are that we cannot pass because of this broken system, blah, blah, blah.
But somebody just today was like, I really like your pitch because when you said there were two things that are fun facts, I thought, oh, well there's only two, I have time for those.
And then when you're done, it was really interesting.
I was like, yes, that is what I was going for.
So, you know, almost everyone I talk to is convinced and they're going to vote for us, or they just want to do some due diligence.
They just want to kind of look and read up a bit.
But I've even, I tell you, I've had a number of people who, the longest conversations I have are with people who, the rare person that I talk to who has worked with Christine on something or who, you know, is a kind of regular caller and those people are,
All very, very rare, but just talked to one the other day.
And you know, she had time, I had time.
We talked, the concentration of power in the hands of the speaker,
she was interested in that, but she wasn't convinced by it.
And it wasn't until I started talking about the work I've done over the last four years and co-governance and how people who have been marginalized, who are not engaged in the political process have got to be at the decision-making table.
And that was what convinced her.
That's kind of my, you know, I keep it in my back pocket for the people that aren't convinced by the first argument, which is almost everyone is convinced by the transparency and the power of the speaker argument, but that's always there.
You know, the movement building aspect, which in my heart is kind of the true reason why I am running and the thing that will be different about me from most other people who are elected representatives.