The report is coming! The report is coming! Paula Grant, what are you doing here? Patriot's Day was on Monday! I have to warn everyone that the report is coming! Oh yeah, let's go!
The report is coming! The report is coming! The report is coming!
All right, I think he has a message for us. I'm going to hand him the mic. An important message from Paul Revere. Oh, no, he's running in. There he goes. Here they are, everybody. Let's hear it for Paul Revere.
The answer to last week's question is, on January 20th, 2001, I was playing my trombone at the inauguration for George W. Bush. The Mustang Report question of the week is, what Prince song did I sing in karaoke last week? Hi folks, today's a great day in Meffitt High School's history. We're here to celebrate one of our senior athletes, Mr. Jordan Howard.
He's going to be signing his letter of intent to UMass Amherst. A couple of people here that won't be speaking I want to introduce. I want to thank Jack Dempsey and Allison Goldsberry for all their support. Assistant Athletic Director Rachel Perry. And we have Senior Class Submaster Nick Tucci. It's great that we're in front of the Hall of Fame showcase because I'm sure Jordan will be back at Meffitt High School going to the Hall of Fame down the road. I'd like to turn it over to Coach Mike Petritus right now.
Michael. How you doing? I just want to thank you guys for being here to take part of this great joyful moment here for Jordan. I just want to tell his parents that they've done a great job. They've done a great job raising him. He's an awesome, awesome student athlete. And I know he's going to do a lot of good things in UMass Amherst when he gets there. It's been a privilege to coach him and
If it's any indication on what he's done in high school, he's gonna be much better when he gets a little bit older. By the time he's a sophomore, junior, senior, you're gonna see him all over the place. Hopefully we'll get to see him on the national team one day. There you go. All right? Thank you. Yep.
does that star-spangled banner yet wave o'er the land of the free and the home of the
Served as the catalyst that gave enough encouragement to Crystal's family to make their first public appearance. And thanks to the mayor, now the former mayor, who coordinated that,
When Crystal's mom threw out that first pitch, I believe she threw a chip on it. I'm here with Gigi and Katrina at the 3rd Annual Crystal Campbell Tournament. So today the game is between Denver and Birmingham. So girls, how did it feel today to get that win? It felt fantastic. I mean, we worked really hard and in the end we just came out on top. We were a better team.
Absolutely, I completely agree. It was a full-out team effort and couldn't have done it without everyone backing each other up, you know. It's team sport. What did it take to get to this win? A lot of hard work, dedication, a lot of seriousness. Our team is very serious, if you haven't noticed already. And just a lot of determination and fun.
Doughnuts. Lots and lots of doughnuts. Physically. But mentally? Absolutely. We had to stay focused. It's a big game for us. We had a lot of pressure being the hosts. And playing against a really good Boomerican team. So from the beginning we hit it off. We played really well and it was a great game. So one final really, really important question. Max, how do you feel about this win?
I think that they worked hard. I knew that they could do it. And I think that this shows what we're able to do, seeing that a lot of seniors left last year and some of the freshmen stepped up, like Carmen for example. And I think we're going to have a great run this year. Class of 2016, you have been an absolute pleasure to work with, see you perform, see you do well in sports, see you do well academically.
music, all of your wonderful talents. It's been an absolute pleasure. Good luck in your future endeavors and please come back and visit. Avoid early classes. Avoid dating for the first month at least. Call home often because your parents are going to miss you. Take a bunch of different classes to find out what you like and don't be afraid to follow your interests and passion instead of what you think you're supposed to do. Good luck.
Hello senior class, it's Mr. Cormier from the vocational school, electrical department. I want to wish you well as you graduate. The only advice I can give you is show up on time every day for your job.
and work like you really mean it. Good luck and have a great career. Congratulations class of 2016 seniors. It has been my pleasure to work with all of you and I wish you the very best in the future. My advice for you all is to follow your passions, go with your gut, do what's interesting to you, and if you follow your passion in life, good things tend to happen.
Good luck to the class of 2016. All right, seniors. Miss Sanford here, your co-class advisor, Mrs. Dorsey. I just wanted to wish you all good luck in your future endeavors. If there's any advice I can give you, it's that you find a good piece of every single day. Don't wait for the weekend. Don't count down until Friday. Think about something, whether it's meeting someone new, learning something new, trying something new every single day. Wish you all a bunch of luck, and make sure you come back and tell us how you do.
Hi seniors, my biggest piece of advice for you is study abroad if you can. Leave this country and find something else out there. You can always come back, but college is, or after high school is just the best time to travel and see other places.