[SPEAKER_00]: Hello to all of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: My name is Gail McLaughlin.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm the former two-term mayor of Richmond, California.
[SPEAKER_00]: Richmond is a diverse city in the San Francisco Bay Area.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm also a co-founder of the Richmond Progressive Alliance, otherwise known as the RPA.
[SPEAKER_00]: And through our joint efforts in Richmond as an alliance and with progressive electives sitting on the city council, my work as mayor,
[SPEAKER_00]: we were able to make a transformative change in our city.
[SPEAKER_00]: we were able to beat back a giant oil refinery, the Chevron Richmond oil refinery in our city, who spent over $3 million in 2014 to try and defeat me and other progressives.
[SPEAKER_00]: But we all prevailed.
[SPEAKER_00]: We prevailed because we worked side by side with the community and educated the community and uplifted the community and stood for the important, bold issues of our city,
[SPEAKER_00]: and of our time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now today, I'm here to support Anna Callahan as your state representative in Massachusetts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, I met Anna when she was living in the Bay Area.
[SPEAKER_00]: She came to Richmond and had heard about our model of organizing and wanted to know more about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: She helped us make a video about the RPA.
[SPEAKER_00]: And she also created an organization called the Incorruptibles.
[SPEAKER_00]: That organization trains
[SPEAKER_00]: candidates and groups in terms of building a local movement and running candidates for office without any corporate money.
[SPEAKER_00]: So she has taken the RPA model and spread it to other places, exactly what we wanted to happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I thank Anna for her work in spreading the model of organizing that RPA spearheaded.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an important model and everyone should learn it, become part of it,
[SPEAKER_00]: and as a result, be able to transform your communities as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, when I heard that Anna was running to be your representative in Massachusetts, I was thrilled.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no better candidate, no more knowledgeable candidate of the organizing that needs to be done, as well as the issues that need to be lifted up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I 100% endorse her efforts,
[SPEAKER_00]: I know that she will build the kind of organizing effort through her campaign that is needed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when elected, she'll keep that organizing work going, which is what needs to happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Too many candidates get elected and then they forget about organizing and the movement that they may have had just becomes inactive and ineffective.
[SPEAKER_00]: There has to be that side-by-side relationship with
[SPEAKER_00]: corporate-free progressive electeds and the community.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, Anna has the kind of understanding of issues that are so essential for transformation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Issues that she stands for are things like Medicare for All, housing for all in Massachusetts, a Massachusetts Green New Deal,
[SPEAKER_00]: She stands for a living wage.
[SPEAKER_00]: She stands for free public college.
[SPEAKER_00]: She stands for the kind of Massachusetts Green New Deal that will bring about the kind of jobs that you need in Massachusetts while bringing about a sustainable planet.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I encourage you all to become active in Anna's campaign.
[SPEAKER_00]: She not only wants people that are
[SPEAKER_00]: currently part of the civic process who have already been active in standing up in their communities.
[SPEAKER_00]: She wants your support for sure, but she wants to expand on that and get those who have not been active to participate in the civic process.
[SPEAKER_00]: She knows there are marginalized communities.
[SPEAKER_00]: that have not been empowered, that do not know the steps they need to take.
[SPEAKER_00]: She will help them learn those steps.
[SPEAKER_00]: She will stand side by side with them and all of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I encourage you all to go to AnnaCallahan.com and volunteer for her campaign.
[SPEAKER_00]: Donate whatever you can to her campaign because
[SPEAKER_00]: She doesn't take corporate money.
[SPEAKER_00]: She doesn't take corporate super PAC money.
[SPEAKER_00]: She depends on all of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So please give her your 100% support as I am giving her.
[SPEAKER_00]: We need the kind of elected officials that we know Anna Callahan will be and the kind of movement builder that Anna Callahan has been and will continue to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So enjoy the kickoff today, the launch of her wonderful campaign, and I'll be rooting for all of you in Massachusetts, for Anna, for state representative.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wish I could be with you, but hope this video shares some of my enthusiasm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thanks again.