In 1967, New Orleans District Attorney Jim Garrison brought the only legal case ever filed in connection with the assassination of President John F. Kennedy.
The trial was a strange, sprawling, and ultimately unsuccessful affair. Garrison accused a local businessman, Clay Shaw, of participating in a conspiracy. But the prosecution's evidence was thin, the testimony inconsistent, and the theories increasingly convoluted. Under pressure, Garrison's narrative began to twist in on itself.
relying not on proof, but on the idea that a conspiracy so vast would leave no evidence at all. In other words, the absence of proof became the proof. When Oliver Stone dramatized the trial in his 1991 film, JFK, he gave Garrison, played by Kevin Costner, a monologue that has since become iconic.
In challenging the official explanation of the assassination, particularly the so-called magic bullet theory, Garrison scoffs... Theoretical physics can prove that an elephant can hang from a cliff with its tail tied to a daisy. But use your eyes, your common sense. The army wound ballistics experts at Edward Arsenal filed some comparison bullets. Not one of them looked anything like this.
It's a powerful moment. The jury is enraptured. But here's the catch. That common-sense reaction is based on a flawed assumption.
The magic bullet theory seems ridiculous if you imagine the car seats aligned perfectly, one behind the other. But in reality, Governor Connolly was seated in a jump seat, lower and to the left of Kennedy. When you factor that in, the bullet's path, far from magical, becomes plausible.
And that's the point. What feels true often isn't. Common sense fills in gaps with familiarity. It makes assumptions. It skips the hard part. And while that's fine when you're deciding how to cross the street or whether the stove is hot, it fails spectacularly when we step into the strange, unfamiliar and counterintuitive.
From black holes to probability, consciousness to investment strategy, the world rarely behaves the way we expect it to. Sometimes the most dangerous thing isn't what we don't know, it's what we're sure we do.
Take your own mind, for instance. Few things feel more self-evident than the idea that we control our thoughts and actions. From childhood, we're taught that we make choices, deliberate over our actions, and bear responsibility for them.
The notion of free will, that we are autonomous agents steering our destinies, is deeply ingrained in human culture, ethics, and law. Yet neuroscience suggests that this perception of conscious control may be an illusion.
Studies using brain imaging technology, such as fMRI and EEG scans, have revealed that decisions are often made before we are consciously aware of them. In the 1980s, neuroscientist Benjamin Libet conducted a groundbreaking experiment in which participants were asked to move their fingers at a moment of their choosing while their brain activity was monitored.
Libet found that the readiness potential, a pattern of neural activity linked to movement, appeared hundreds of milliseconds before participants reported making a conscious decision. More recent studies have extended this time gap to several seconds, suggesting that the unconscious brain initiates decisions long before we experience the sensation of making a choice.
If the brain is making decisions before we are aware of them, what does this mean for free will?
One possibility is that consciousness is not the initiator of decisions, but rather a narrator, creating a post-hoc story to justify actions that have already been set into motion. This implies that what we experience as a conscious choice is, in fact, a retrospective illusion, making us passengers rather than pilots of our own minds.
The question of consciousness itself only deepens the mystery. Unlike other bodily functions, such as digestion or respiration, consciousness does not have a clearly identifiable structure in the brain.
It is not located in a single region, but appears to be an emergent property of billions of neurons firing in concert across distributed networks.
While we can pinpoint certain areas of the brain responsible for perception, emotion, and decision-making, there is no single seat of the self, no homunculus sitting inside the brain directing thoughts. This fragmentation of self-awareness has profound implications.
If the self is not a unified entity, but a collection of competing neural processes, what does that say about identity, agency, and personal responsibility? Disorders such as split-brain syndrome, which occurs when the corpus callosum connecting the brain's hemispheres is severed, reveal that the brain can house multiple independent streams of consciousness.
Patients with this condition often exhibit bizarre behaviours, such as one hand acting in direct opposition to the other, suggesting that even within a single individual, there may not be a singular coherent self, but multiple, competing selves.
If we aren't the sole authors of our thoughts, if consciousness is less a spotlight and more a shadow play, then what exactly are we?
Where does something as rich and layered as human experience come from, if not from a central self pulling the levers? That question leads us to one of the most counterintuitive truths of all. Common sense tells us that complexity must stem from equally complex causes. We assume intricate systems, whether biological, cognitive, or cosmic,
require an intelligent designer. Yet nature repeatedly demonstrates that complexity emerges from simple rules without foresight or intent.
One of the most striking examples of emergent complexity is evolution. The human body, with its vast interdependent systems, seems irreducibly complex. Yet Darwinian evolution explains how small, random genetic mutations, shaped by natural selection, have gradually built intricate life forms. No guiding intelligence is necessary.
only time, variation, and survival pressures. What appears designed is actually the result of millions of tiny, unguided changes accumulating over time. Human intuition struggles with this idea, because our brains expect immediate cause-and-effect relationships, not processes spanning billions of years.
Evolution's slow, incremental nature contradicts our instinct to see purpose and intention in complex structures. Evolution, neuroscience, fractals, and self-organization all reveal that complexity does not require an architect, only the right conditions and enough time.
While common sense suggests that intricate systems must be designed, reality proves that profound order can emerge from seemingly mindless simplicity.
If simplicity can give rise to complexity, then it shouldn't surprise us that randomness too can give rise to patterns. But here's the catch. Our brains weren't built to recognise this.
We are natural-born storytellers, not statisticians, and when we try to make sense of randomness, we often see cause where there is none, or miss the invisible structure underneath it all. This is especially true when it comes to probability.
Humans are notoriously bad at intuiting probability. We tend to overestimate rare dangers while underestimating common risks, leading to irrational fears and poor decision-making.
This is why people are more afraid of plane crashes than car accidents, even though air travel is statistically far safer. Similarly, many people feel more anxious about shark attacks than slipping in their own bathrooms, even though the latter is exponentially more likely to cause injury or death.
Our inability to grasp probability leads to flawed reasoning, poor risk assessment, and widespread misconceptions about chance.
A famous example of counterintuitive probability is the infinite monkey theorem, which states that if a monkey were to randomly hit keys on a typewriter for an infinite amount of time, it would eventually produce the complete works of Shakespeare.
At first glance, this sounds absurd. How could randomness generate something as structured and meaningful as Hamlet? But mathematically, given infinite time, the probability of the monkey producing any finite sequence of text approaches certainty.
However, many people misunderstand the implications of this theorem. First, the term infinite is crucial. In a finite time frame, even trillions of years, the likelihood of producing Shakespeare's works is astronomically low.
Second, while pure randomness does guarantee all possible outcomes given enough time, it does not guarantee efficiency. The vast majority of what the monkey would type would be gibberish, and the occurrence of Shakespearean text would be so rare that even if we watched for billions of lifetimes, we might never see a coherent sentence emerge.
Some critics argue that the theorem, while mathematically valid, is a misleading representation of how randomness works in the real world, where meaningful structure rarely emerges from chaos without some guiding mechanism. The failure to intuit probability is perhaps nowhere more evident than in gambling.
One of the most common misconceptions gamblers fall for is the gambler's fallacy, the belief that past random events influence future random outcomes.
A classic example is a person playing roulette who sees black come up five times in a row and assumes that red is now due for a win. But each spin of the wheel is independent. Previous outcomes have no effect on future ones.
Humans evolved in environments where probability was not explicitly calculated, but rather intuited based on experience. Our ancestors did not need to compute precise risks. They relied on heuristics, mental shortcuts that worked well enough for survival, but are often misleading in modern contexts.
This is why people struggle with large numbers and fail to grasp just how unlikely certain events are.
We can't help but anthropomorphise randomness, imagine luck as a force, see patterns in static, or believe that odds even out. But even when we do try to wrap our heads around large numbers, there's one concept that short-circuits intuition entirely. Infinity.
It feels like just a really big number, something beyond a trillion or a googol. But infinity isn't a number at all. It's a boundless abstraction, and it behaves in ways that defy common sense at every turn.
Our brains evolved to count and measure things in finite quantities, but infinity refuses to be tamed. We instinctively think in terms of limits. Objects have edges, time has a beginning and an end, and numbers, while large, should still be countable.
However, mathematics reveals that infinity behaves in ways that contradict our common sense. Consider the paradox of Hilbert's infinite hotel, a famous thought experiment devised by German mathematician David Hilbert. Imagine a hotel with an infinite number of rooms, each already occupied by a guest.
If a new traveller arrives, logic would suggest that the hotel is full. However, by shifting each guest one room over – moving the guest in room 1 to room 2, the guest in room 2 to room 3, and so on – room 1 becomes available for the new arrival.
This process can be repeated indefinitely, meaning that despite being full, the hotel can always accommodate more guests. This paradox exposes the unintuitive nature of infinity.
Unlike finite sets where adding more elements increases the total count, infinite sets can be rearranged in paradoxical ways while still remaining infinite. Even more bizarre is the fact that some infinities are larger than others.
The most famous example of this comes from the work of mathematician George Cantor, who discovered that the set of real numbers, including all decimals and fractions, between 0 and 1, is larger than the set of all whole numbers, despite both being infinite.
This is because whole numbers, regardless of their size, can still be counted sequentially, meaning they form a countable infinity. However, the real numbers between 0 and 1 include an uncountably infinite number of decimal variations, making it an uncountably infinite set.
Cantor proved this by using his diagonalization argument, which shows that no matter how you try to list the real numbers, there will always be numbers left out, demonstrating that this infinity is provably larger than the infinity of whole numbers.
Should your brain be aching or your nose bleeding? Don't worry. That is rather the point. Concepts such as this are entirely counter to that which we can understand instinctively. These ideas seem paradoxical because our brains are wired to grasp quantities in physical terms,
We can count apples, measure distances, and track time. But when we enter the realm of boundlessness, our intuition fails us. Infinity is not just a concept beyond our everyday experience. It is something that actively breaks the way we understand the world.
Infinity forces us to confront how ill-equipped we are to grasp the boundless. But if the idea of something stretching forever breaks the mind, consider the opposite. Nothing at all.
At first glance, nothing seems simpler. Its absence, emptiness, the void. Yet physics tells us that true nothingness doesn't exist and may never have.
The concept of nothing seems straightforward, an absence of something, a void where no matter, energy or structure exists. Common sense tells us that if you remove everything from a space, what remains is nothing. But modern physics reveals that nothing is far more complicated than our intuition suggests.
Even in the most seemingly empty vacuum, something is always happening. And the very notion of absolute nothingness becomes paradoxical when examined through the lens of quantum mechanics and cosmology. Even in the absence of matter, empty space is not truly empty.
At the quantum level, what we perceive as nothingness is actually a seething, chaotic ocean of virtual particles that constantly appear and disappear. These ephemeral particles, known as quantum fluctuations, momentarily appear and then annihilate one another, creating tiny but measurable effects.
The famous Casimir effect illustrates this peculiar phenomenon. When two uncharged metal plates are placed extremely close together in a vacuum, they experience a force pushing them together. Not due to any external pressure, but because quantum fluctuations between them are slightly different than those outside.
This effect is direct physical evidence that even in a vacuum, space itself is active, dynamic, and filled with energy. This leads to an even more unsettling conclusion. The vacuum of space is not a passive backdrop, but a fundamental part of the universe with measurable properties and consequences.
What we once considered nothing is in fact a deeply complex and structured fabric of reality. If nothing at the quantum level is already an illusion, what about the concept of nothingness before the universe existed? Our minds naturally assume that everything must have an origin. But if the universe had a beginning,
than what came before it. The question itself reveals the limits of human intuition. Time itself is believed to have been created with the Big Bang. Meaning the phrase, before the universe, may be as meaningless as asking, what's north of the North Pole?
But if the quantum vacuum reveals that even nothing is not what it seems, then what do we call the empty spaces where common sense should reside, but doesn't?
Let's return to that New Orleans courtroom in Oliver Stone's JFK, a film that turned doubt into drama, and speculation into something like scripture. Jim Garrison stands confidently, almost smugly, before the jury, delivering a powerful closing argument, relying heavily on this one magic bullet.
If Kennedy was shot from behind, Garrison argues, then how could Governor Connolly, seated ahead of him, have been struck by the same bullet that resulted in so many distinct wounds? It's absurd. It's theatrical. And it feels right.
But it's wrong. The so-called magic bullet theory is not magical at all. It's forensic ballistics. But the damage had already been done. The emotional appeal of Garrison's argument bypassed logic and landed straight in the gut.
That's the real danger. What feels true often isn't. In this case, common sense wasn't just wrong. It actively distorted reality, because it filled in gaps with assumptions. Garrison's argument was effective because it bypassed critical thinking. It leveraged the power of simplicity over complexity.
instinct over evidence. And this tactic isn't just confined to movies. It's everywhere now.
Today, common sense is used not only to dismiss ideas, but also to discredit people, especially experts. Somewhere along the way, being an expert stopped being admirable and began to be viewed with suspicion. The very word expert now often carries a negative connotation in public discourse,
as if years of study, experience and evidence-based thinking are viewed as red flags rather than qualifications.
This isn't just cultural fatigue. It's a performative rebellion against institutions, academia, science, and media. Against anything that seems too complex, too elite, or too difficult to grasp at a glance.
Instead of saying, I don't understand that, can you explain? We're increasingly hearing, I don't understand that, so it must be a lie. And this mindset opens the door to conspiracy thinking. If a claim contradicts what feels intuitive,
It's not just wrong, it must be deceptive. Climate scientists have become part of a global hoax. Virologists are accused of inventing pandemics. Mental health professionals are dismissed as peddlers of made-up disorders. Engineers explaining 5G technology are met with suspicion, not curiosity.
Even the shape of the Earth is up for debate again, as if centuries of measurement and observation can be outweighed by gut feeling. What's dangerous here isn't just misinformation. It's the growing assumption that any form of complexity is a con. That if something doesn't align with your intuition, it must be part of a plot.
that truth should be obvious, simple, and easily felt. And if it's not, someone's probably hiding something. But truth is often not intuitive. It takes effort. It takes uncomfortable revisions to what we thought we knew.
And yes, it takes listening to people who've dedicated their lives to understanding things most of us haven't had time to study. We can and should question power. We should demand transparency. But scepticism is not the same as cynicism.
Real skepticism looks for better evidence. Cynicism looks for villains. And that difference matters.
Because if we reject every uncomfortable truth in favour of what feels right, we end up not just misinformed, but manipulated, ironically, by the very forces we think we're resisting. Common sense is helpful, essential even, for getting through the day. It tells us not to touch hot stoves, not to walk into traffic,
Not to trust someone who gives us a bad feeling. It's the brain's shortcut system, built from experience. But when we're dealing with the big stuff, how time works, what consciousness is,
how probability behaves, or why a bullet can curve in ways that don't feel right. That same shortcut system can lead us wildly off course.
Understanding where our intuition falls short is how we grow. It's not a sign that we're stupid or out of touch. It's a sign that we're curious, open, and willing to stretch beyond what's familiar. That's where every great scientific discovery has come from. Not from trusting gut instinct, but from saying, wait, what if I'm wrong?
But that requires trust. In a process. Not a person. One of the most dangerous trends of our time is the growing distrust of science. Not of individual studies or researchers – healthy scepticism of findings is part of the process.
but a broad ontological suspicion of science itself, as if science were a belief system or bureaucratic cabal. It's not. Science is not the discipline of stating the obvious. It doesn't promise to be right forever. In fact, its greatest strength is that it doesn't try to be.
Good science doesn't say, this is the final truth. It says, this is what the evidence tells us right now, until something better is proven. It's not a priesthood, it's a process. Often slow, often frustrating, but it works. And the proof is everywhere.
We now accept without hesitation that the Earth orbits the Sun, a fact that once seemed laughable and heretical. We accept the germ theory that diseases are caused by invisible organisms, not curses, bad air, or divine punishment. These were once revolutionary ideas that contradicted everything people believed.
However, over time, with evidence, replication and refinement, they became established facts. Not because someone powerful said so, but because the method worked. It's not a cathedral. It's a construction site. The motto of the Royal Society, one of the oldest scientific institutions in the world, is Nullius Inverba.
take nobody's word for it. Or, more plainly, prove it. That's the point. Not authority, not certainty. Evidence. The truth is, nobody's born knowing how relativity works, or how to read the stock market, or diagnose a heart attack. These things are learned.
And the first step in learning anything meaningful is being willing to admit that your instincts might not be enough. So the next time something feels obvious, take a beat. Ask yourself if it only feels true because it's familiar.
Because once you start looking beyond what feels right and start chasing what is right, even when it's strange, even when it's uncomfortable, that's where real understanding begins. It's not about throwing away common sense. It's about knowing when to disregard it.
That's how we move forward. That's how we make sense of a world and a universe that so often seems, seems to stubbornly refuse to make sense of itself. And as for the headache and the nosebleed, turn the lights off.
Take a Tylenol, lean your head back, and don't worry about the details and jargon too much. If you don't understand everything you've heard, you're in good company. Most of us don't. And can't. At least, not commonly.