[SPEAKER_00]: One thing to realize is that every time we turn around, scientists are saying, oh actually we were wrong, climate change is way worse than we thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, we need to look at everything through a lens of environmental justice.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Green Justice Coalition has the right idea which is to put together
[SPEAKER_00]: Marginalized communities of color that are most impacted by climate change with labor and environmental groups, and that is how we develop a Green New Deal.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have to commit to sourcing our electricity from 100% renewables by 2035 at the latest.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have to divest from fossil fuels.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have to convert government transportation to electric.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have to make sure that all new housing is passive housing, is zero emissions housing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But more than that, we are eventually going to have to have a plan for how are we going to switch our private transportation to electric?
[SPEAKER_00]: How are we going to retrofit all of our housing and commercial buildings so that they are not
[SPEAKER_00]: also emitting carbon emissions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so it's a very complex problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, the way we go about it is through a coalition of groups that really centralizes the voices of the people most impacted by climate change.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I really want to say that the people of Massachusetts are totally ready for this in every poll, willing to pay extra money for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The legislature is not ready.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have to get rid of the concentration of power and the stranglehold that the speaker has over the state house, because that's how we can get this done.