One thing to realize is that every time we turn around, scientists are saying, oh actually we were wrong, climate change is way worse than we thought.
So, we need to look at everything through a lens of environmental justice.
The Green Justice Coalition has the right idea which is to put together
Marginalized communities of color that are most impacted by climate change with labor and environmental groups, and that is how we develop a Green New Deal.
We have to commit to sourcing our electricity from 100% renewables by 2035 at the latest.
We have to divest from fossil fuels.
We have to convert government transportation to electric.
We have to make sure that all new housing is passive housing, is zero emissions housing.
But more than that, we are eventually going to have to have a plan for how are we going to switch our private transportation to electric?
How are we going to retrofit all of our housing and commercial buildings so that they are not
also emitting carbon emissions.
And so it's a very complex problem.
And again, the way we go about it is through a coalition of groups that really centralizes the voices of the people most impacted by climate change.
And I really want to say that the people of Massachusetts are totally ready for this in every poll, willing to pay extra money for it.
The legislature is not ready.
We have to get rid of the concentration of power and the stranglehold that the speaker has over the state house, because that's how we can get this done.