So let's start the meeting. Hi, Daria, Ben, Bobby, good to see you guys. You got my email, the order, I thought we'd address them. So Nick's here. Nick, tell us a little.
We don't have any housekeeping to do, there's no minutes to review. Will you get them to us the next meeting, Daria? Yes, I'll try to, yes. Okay. All right, so we'll forego the review and the vote of the minutes, and let's just jump into the agenda. Nick, good to see you as always. Tell us a little about the event on October 28th.
You too, thank you. Yes, it is the annual Halloween pumpkin float being put on by the City of Medford over at the Wright Pond. It's basically...
Again, we did the same thing last year. I'm not sure what happened last year, but might have been rained off. We did the year before. As I said, we have a designated spot. Basically, everything is obviously all our people are all TIP certified. We have the insurance liability. We shared all that. And the imagery of where it's going with Daria. Yeah. Yeah, we received it.
I can't think of anything more, really. I won't be wearing a fancy dress costume. You're right, it was a very successful event last year. It didn't rain, right? I think, was it a little cold? I'm just trying to remember what it was last year, the weather. I think it was just cold. I went to it, so it was chilly.
I, this is very straightforward. It's a fun event. I don't have any questions. The insurance is in order and we have a diagram. I see where the bear garden is. It's going over near the snack shack as we used to call it when we were growing up. I don't have any questions. Bobby, Ben, any concerns, questions from you guys? No, it looks good to me. All the paperwork's in order. Looks good on my end too. Yeah, yeah.
Well, let's do a motion. Let's get this, let's get Nick on his way. Sure thing. I can make a motion. I'm gonna make a motion to approve the one day license for Medford Brewing Company. And this is for the Wrights Pond Halloween Pumpkin Float. And the date is October 28th, 2023. Nick's provided us a certificate of insurance and a diagram.
Very good. I second the motion. Very good. Uh, thank you. Uh, all in favor, except in the one day license for October 28th, but met the brewing company. Say hi. Hi. Very good. Uh, Nicholas, you're, you're all set. Best of luck. Thank you, gentlemen. And I see mechanic. Take care, Nick. Uh, okay. So the second one is, um,
Winter Hill Brewing. Breck, do I see? I see Breck. Breck, are you with us? Yes, sir. How are you guys? Good, good. Good. All right, let's take a look.
This is your annual event. Is this your third year doing this or second? So this is, I think this is the third, but maybe the second in this location. So the first one is probably licensed in Somerville. The space is unique. It almost straddles Somerville and Medford. So the licensing for this is on the Medford side.
on the Memphis side. Yeah. Again, just we're familiar with the event, but refresh our memory. Just give us a good overview of the event and what you have serving and who's serving. Just give us a good overview, please. Sure. So this is Saturday, November 4th. It's Neighborhood Produce's annual anniversary party. So they provide stuff like cider and non-alcoholic cider and donuts. I think they have
uh, pizza on the food side and we do the, the beverage service. So we'll do beer and, and wine. I think it's 12, 12 noon to six o'clock. Um, in the evening, we probably cut a little bit before that last year, but got a pretty good turnout and it drives a lot of business into their, their storefront too. So it was, it was definitely a success last year. I had a good event. Nice. Nice.
I was a little late getting the schematics to you, but I sent those through this morning with the exact location of the event and the setup in that parking lot. Yeah, no, no, we have them. And as I said before, I'm very familiar with that spot because I used to hide my car in there when we'd go to sound bites for breakfast. So yeah. Certificate of liability insurances.
It's up to date, it's current, it's got enough coverage. Yeah, I don't have any questions. Bobby, Ben, anything on your mind with the event? No, I don't recall any issues last year. Yeah, everything looks fine to me. This is 645 Boston F. That's right, yeah. Yeah. No.
It's good. Yeah, yeah, no, everything looks good with me. I don't have any questions, guys. Yeah, that end of Boston Ave has changed tremendously. Humbruck, all the construction, everything that's been done now, they fixed the bridge. It's just amazing, that whole corner. Yeah, it's totally different with the stop right there. Yeah, yeah. Good, good. Either of my fellow commissioners want to make a motion to move forward with the one-day license, I'm all ears.
Yeah, I'll make a motion. I'll make a motion to grant a one-day license to Beergarten at 645 Boston Avenue on November 4th, 2023. All right, go ahead. Okay, did you say November 4th? November 4th, yep. Sorry. Yep.
Okay, that's what I had. Sorry. All right. Yeah, I'm going to second that. Very good. All in favor, accepting the one day license for Winter Hill Brewery on November 4th, say aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye.
Okay, so the third one, I thought what we do is the City of Medford, the event on Sunday, November 12th. Oh, Teresa, there you are. You're in the top left corner here. How are you doing? I'm doing well. How are you? Good, good. Tell us about the event, please.
Yes, so I am the Community Preservation Act manager for the city. So I help manage the CPA help fund public projects around the city park projects, you know, some nonprofit organizations are funded by us to provide advocacy.
for attendance. So we do a lot of really great things. And we want to celebrate that. So this is technically the fifth year. So it's our five year anniversary. And essentially, the event will just be a very short speaking portion with about an hour's worth of networking beforehand, you know, just rubbing elbows, and what have you.
During that networking time, we want to be able to provide beer and wine, complimentary beer and wine to any attendees to the event. And like I said, then it will end with a speaking portion. It's from 3 to 5 in the afternoon. So I believe that Dodgers, a Patriots game that day. So we hope to have a good attendance. I know, I know. There's so many diehard fans out there right now.
We hope to draw in somewhere between 50 and 75 attendees. Very good. Oh, so the venue space, yes. We're hoping to hold it at Shiloh Baptist Church. They are a private entity that owns, it's not a public building, but yes, Shiloh Baptist Church over in West Bedford.
Oh, it'll be inside. Will it be inside? It'll be inside. Okay, so they have a space that they rent out for private events. Okay, so it's an inside event. Teresa, tell me, I see wine and malt, beer and wine. Who will be providing which
entity will be providing the adult beverages? So the products themselves will be donated, and then the disbursement will be by CPC staff members, all well over the age of 21. I see. Okay.
We typically have you provide us like a diagram or like a layout, but you don't have that, right? Unfortunately, no, I don't at this time. I can pull one together. I'm just not sure if it would be in time for the next time since the event is November 12th. I don't believe you mean until the next time. You know, Ben, it's a good idea, at least
get if you could put one together and just get it over the diary. We know where the event's going to be, where we're familiar, because we've seen other events held inside. So we're kind of familiar with it. But it wouldn't hurt to if you could, you know, it doesn't have to be done by an engineer, an architect, nothing like that, you know, but at least we have something for the for the file, because this is one of the things that design a diagram is what we ask of everybody, if you don't mind, please.
Okay, and I apologize. I didn't include that. But I will certainly get that over. Thank you. No, not a big deal. Yeah, I'm looking at the space. I mean, I think other than that, I don't, I don't have any questions. It's not a great deal of people are for a very long time or at night. I mean, it sort of seems pretty, pretty safe. Yeah. Okay. Bobby, any questions on your
No, everything looks fine to me, Mr Chairman. Yeah, everything's good. You know, I think we can grant it with the stipulation of the sketch just being sent over the diary issue. Fine. Yeah, just so we can put it in with the file. Sure. So let's uh, Bobby, Ben, you want to make a motion?
Yeah, I can do it. Okay, so I will make a motion to approve the one day license. It's the city organization celebration for. This is the city of Medford Teresa DuPont. Yes. And yeah, it's for Sunday, November 12 at one home street Medford.
subject to a diagram approved by us being submitted to us prior to this event, the sooner the better, so we can just say yes and be done with that. Okay, sounds good. Very good. Thank you all in favor of approving the one-day license for Sunday, November 12th, for the City of Medford, say aye. Aye. Very good. Tracy, you're all set. Yeah, just like I said, it doesn't have to be done by an architect or engineer, just
You know, give us a lay of the land, so to speak. Okay, I will do that and I will have that to Daria by end of day tomorrow, Thursday. Cool. All right. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. I'll take it. All right. Good luck Teresa. Good luck. All right. Did I see Eric? Yeah, there's Eric. You made it back in time, huh? I followed the speed limits as you recommended.
So we'll entertain the November 9th for the trustees of Tufts College. All right, tell us a little about the event that's going to be taking place November 9th. All right, so our Data Intensive Studies Center Program, otherwise known as DISCS, it's a science-based grad program that
researches singles, anything from single cell RNA sequencing to a whole lot of other things I don't really understand. They are holding a one hour cocktail party from 6.30 to 7.30. Party actually ends at eight o'clock on November 9th. We close about a half hour early. So we're seeking a beer and wine license for this occasion. Expect a hundred guests in our
JCC, our Joyce Cummings building, which is located at 177 College Ave in Medford. We have, we'll be serving food at this event. We have two bartenders along with a manager who's Tamara Kenny. She's listed on the application sitting to my right here. Let me see here. What else we had?
It's really about, we have TUP, we have, we'll have detail from Tufts police with us. It's again, a grad program. We separate our atrium within this facility, which is, I believe I'm estimating around 65, 6,000 square feet. There'll be a section marked off for the, for the party, for the reception. Okay.
Eric, do we have, I've been in the building, it's a beautiful building, but I don't know if we, again, do we have, have you presented any type of designs or drawings or give us an overview of where the event is, like on what floor and any kind of design? I sent in a, I just handed off to Daria.
The diagram and the insurance is what you gave her when we were running out the door, correct? I did, but we'd like to have a little bit more detail on that diagram. Our conference and event services team that generates the diagrams and manages that building, they just have not got to that event yet, so we can show you where within the atrium. If you've been there before, you go past the reception desk to your left. It is a carpeted area that would accommodate 100 guests pretty easily.
We put stanchions up and that's where the TPD works to keep our group separate from the general community of Tufts. I say, I say, okay, Ben and Bobby, we.
Myself, Eric, and Tamara, we didn't realize this was a Zoom, so we were in the hall. And I know as we were running to get back to our computers, I know Eric was handing off the insurance in a diagram. So Dario does have that information, in case you were wondering.
Yeah, so I, I'm okay with that. And, you know, Eric and Tufts are no stranger to us. Their events have, we've not seen any problems with their events. They're always very professional. So I don't have any problem with this approving that, you know, just subject to us just seeing the diagram and seeing the insurance.
And Eric, I would just say with the diagrams, like they get easier as you go. I think sometimes people think they have to be something, but it's sort of just representation of it. So yeah, if that, if what you have already is sufficient, we'll tell you, but yeah, that's, that's the standard we have, you know, looking forward, we just, you know, approve where it is and, and everybody can, you know, move on. Very good.
So I would make a motion to approve that with those stipulations, unless Bobby has any thoughts on it. No, Eric said the magic words. They were going to stanchion it off, and Tufts PD was going to be there. Yeah. We'll look at it. I'm a little familiar with the building. I've gone into Starbucks and picked up a coffee, and I know there is access to that building.
to the public if they go into Starbucks and go into the building. And obviously for students that aren't graduate students, they have full access. But Tuskegee being on the scene, Stanchion Doff, it's kind of as for more than that. I think I feel really good.
So, okay, yeah, I'll do this. So we will make a motion to accept the one day license, this is for the event on November 9 2023 from 630 to 8pm for Tufts catering and.
the trustees of Tufts College, I guess it's the... Trustees of Tufts College, yeah. Okay. Tufts Catering is what we usually say. And that's for at the Cummings Center at 177 College Ave in Medford, just subject to an approved layout and insurance. Good. I second the motion.
Very good, all in favor accepting the one day license for November 9th for Tufts University say aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye
We see you coming before us for one day license for Saturday, October 28th. Tell us a little about the event, please, if you don't mind. That's actually it's a private event. So we were approached by a community member about hosting basically a family gathering, family reunion. And so they inquired about alcohol for that event. And I said that we could do it. We just have to pull proper permits and go through our
our regular process of carding people, IDing people, wristbands, and all that, and they were fine with that. So I said I would inquire about pulling the permit for that. And so it's a small gathering, but it's a private event. OK. Yeah, I see baby shower. OK. Yeah. I know. I think it's like a combination family gathering, because when they first approached me, they mentioned baby shower. And they're a lovely family, but I was
surprised by the time because I know when we had our daughter, Jen was like, I want to be in bed by like seven o'clock. I don't know what these parties are going so late for. So I don't know. That's interesting. Daria, are you there Daria? Yeah, I'm here. Brian, we have a number of his layouts in insurance. You have that in the files, no? Yeah, I do. Okay.
Yeah, I sent that late. I honestly, I forgot to send that, but I did. Yeah, I emailed you right when the meeting started. I apologize. Okay. Yeah, that's good. All right. Again, I'm fine with you. I'm fine with the event. The private event, it's a very small crowd, so it's not open to the public. So it is. Yeah, no. Ben, Bobby, any questions, concerns? No, Brian's.
show us the layout before, it's gone well before, seems pretty, pretty, I don't know what I said, pretty safe again. I'm okay with it. Okay. Yep. Brian's always does a good job. I don't have any issues with this at all. Yeah. No, me neither. Good, good. So let's make a motion and let's get Brian going. Yeah.
All right, I'll just, I'll just do it then. Okay, so I'll make a motion to accept this one day license for event them studios, Brian, make a zoom. Awesome. Yeah, awesome. Okay. And that's for Saturday, October 28.
2023 from 6 to 10pm. Yeah, assuming we have on file Brian's proper insurance and layout. So that's, that's it. Very good. Okay, I'll second that motion. Good. Thank you, gentlemen. Brian, you one day. Oh, all in favor say aye.
Hi. Hi. Very good. Brian, you're all set. I hope it's a successful event. And you keep finding ways and new ways to stay relevant and keep the business going. I applaud you. I was always impressed with your whole concept right from the start. Thank you. All right. So enjoy. Thank you very much. You're all set. I actually have another one. There's another one. Oh, you do? It's a collaboration. Yeah. Oh.
We've been doing collaborations. We did that, um, event, uh, about a week and a half ago. And it was, it was awesome. I have to say just a small attended, uh, performance singer or songwriter performance. Um, but really drew some attention to the area. And to be honest, we got a lot of phone calls just about where's a local restaurant or a place to get some food before. So we were able to.
kind of supports like nappies up the street and then Italy Fiore, I think is how they pronounce it. But it was really got a lot of online presence, just recognition. So that was great. So the events that we've always done with JJ is great. And she's a well-known photographer. So she's gonna be doing our next exhibit gallery at the space.
Um, it's going to feature some of our work, you know, with Kurt Cobain and local musicians over the past 30 years or more. So, um, the gallery opening is, uh, would be the request for, for alcohol. Okay. Seems okay with me as well. Yep. And she carries her own catering license as well. So you have all the insurance for that, um, already. So, yeah.
Yeah, I'm fine with that. And you have the same thing, 40 guests for that one also? Yeah. I mean, typically, that's probably about what it'll be, you know. But again, the gallery will be up for about six weeks through the holidays and stuff. So definitely a good one to come check out if anyone's ever in the area. So that's some great Boston music history and just good work. Nice. OK.
I don't have any other questions, Ben. Bobby, anything? No, everything looks fine to me. Yeah. Want to make a motion?
All right, I can make a motion. Make a motion to grant the one day license for a photo show gallery opening on November 2nd at the location of 342-344 Salem Street, Method for between the hours of 5 p.m. and 9 p.m. I second. All right, go ahead.
Thank you, gentlemen. All in favor accepting the one day license say aye. Aye. Very good. Brian, you're all set. Hope it's successful. And good to see you. You too. Everyone have a great afternoon. You too. Take care. Gary, anything else? That was easy lifting. Six one days, bang, Zoom.
I did get a question. It was for one of the clubs that was mentioned before. The Casa Benifica. It's kind of a complex question, so I don't know if I should be
for something that we should discuss or ask Ralph, but from what I'm reading, it says, my question concerned amending a license to pledge collateral to a lender who asked for a lien on my client's license in conjunction with their refinancing of their mortgage. It's the nonprofit social club and their license, I believe it was a local non-trustworthy license.
The lender has been pushing to get the pledge amendment done. I am wondering, because of the type of the license, nonprofit, social club, even if my client defaulted on their mortgage, which they're not in any danger of presently, and the lender tried to exercise its lien on their license, what could they even do with it?
Is the license transferable? And then it says the lender couldn't take the license and sell it or open their own restaurant or bar or social club with alcohol, correct? And then he said, so what good is a such pledge slash lien to the lender? He said, he's asking because the lender keeps pushing to get this done.
This um there's a lot of answers in that in those questions um I guess the first thing and I don't know the answer can a club.
pledged their license as collateral for a while. I don't know the answer. Do we know if it was a regular for-profit? We've seen some of the new restaurants pledge their liquor license as collateral. We've seen for-profit, but can a non-profit pledge? I don't know. Bobby, do you think there's a difference between profit and non-profit?
Um, I'm not sure on that. But what I do know is they basically follow the same rules as 138 section 12, which is regular restaurant. Whether pledges and a nonprofit that that's a little tricky. Yeah, I just that's the that's the part I don't if they were for profit. Yeah, go right ahead. We've seen that we've we've approved quite a few
pledges liquor license pledged as collateral for loans. We've done that. I just don't know where it's a club. That's the wild card in all of that. Would KP Law, would they be able to give us an opinion whether a non-profit or a club can pledge their liquor license? What kind of mortgage is it to buy the building?
What do you mean to buy the building? I think it, what are they getting money for? Or what's the lender lending them for?
I think it's because of their refinancing of their mortgage. It looks like it says my question concerned amending a license to pledge collateral to a lender who asked for a lien on my client's license in conjunction with their refinancing of their mortgage. So like with their personal own? I'm assuming of their mortgage unless
Yeah, that's a good question. Is it a mortgage on their primary residence or is it a mortgage on the building where the club actually is housed? Yeah. I feel like it's not as valuable as the bank thinks. I mean, right? It's a club license. It's not like it's for a profit, like we keep saying. Right, right. So meaning it's not as valuable as like, I think they're just checking a box.
and they're not letting it go and making a bunch of questions. Who sent the email? A lawyer? Yeah, it looks like it was a law firm, yeah. Well, shame on them for asking those questions, because that was going to be my comment, is that they should be talking to their legal counsel for the rest of the answers to that question, because
All I'm concerned about is can a club license, a nonprofit, pledge their license as collateral? And if the answer is yes, like a for-profit, then that's the answer. Right. Yeah, we don't know what the results are, if they should default on the loan. I mean, we're not lawyers. To pledge, yeah, we can grant the pledge, but we can't tell them what the penalties or the results of it are going to be if they default on it.
That's between the bank's lawyers and his lawyers, I would say, just like you said, Al. You hit it right on the head. I think that's a little out of our wheelhouse. We'll be getting out of our, going out of our lane. Yeah, and I'm curious if I should just refer to ABCC as well, because that's, I feel like, when he, I talked to the person on the phone, the attorney, Dave,
and he didn't, he had like general questions that I thought were kind of not this type of questions where like, I don't really know the correct answer to it. So I don't know if I should refer him back to, well, I don't know if you spoke to ABCC, but maybe have him talk to ABCC, see if they can give him a better idea on his questions. I don't know. Ultimately that'll,
be where it has to be finally approved anyways. Yeah, yeah. So I'm sure Ralph might or whoever he talks to might give him a little bit more of information because I'm sure they deal with, you know, this type of stuff on the regular probably versus like us where we get this like once, once in four or five years.
Yeah, well, we've had a few pledges and it's just a matter of- No, I mean like the questions, not the actual pledge. Yeah, but that's as far as our expertise should go illegal. If the question is can a nonprofit or a club pledge a license as collateral and if the answer is yes, then okay, yes. Now, all the other legal stuff, oh, that's,
We're not lawyers, that's not our place to offer any legal advice. That's where their attorney would have to, you know, once their attorney puts the meter on, he or she's gonna start looking into the ramifications of a license being pledged, if there's a default. All right, anything else? That was it. Okay, can I circle back to 55 High Street
It's my understanding that they're from reading some of the narratives that there's going to be a manager in a license changeover prior to the next November meeting. I don't know. Nobody has reached out to me. Okay. Well, this is why we're bringing it up. What I'd like you to do is I'd like you to reach out to Chris Remick. Okay.
and stay with him, okay? Because I want that done by the next November meeting. I want that all in place so we can review it at the November meeting. Because there's no way we're gonna allow that, and then we're into December, and then it's snowing, and it's January. No, no.
The only thing, the only thing is that it's going to be on them on when they do their application because technically, if they want to be on paper which they will, I think for some things, they will have to be on paper I could be wrong but I think I looked into this before. If they have to do a legal ad. The deadline would be next Thursday.
And that's fine. All I'm asking of you is to stay with them. Stay with Mr. Remick. Just let him know about the timetables because I want to see that in front of us in November. Okay? Yeah, because no way are we going to drop the ball and then that goes on for months. We may want to look into it too.
November 30th, 31st is the deadline for renewing a license. So if they're gonna be getting a new license or, I mean, if it's just a new manager, it shouldn't affect anything, but if they're gonna get a whole new license, they're probably not gonna wanna renew this one with the old owner,
Information on it, but like you say, if they can be before us. By the next meeting, then if there are plans on receiving a new license, that's going to come before us and it's also going to go.
it's going to be renewed by the end of November. So we're going to have a couple of weeks. So all I'm asking of you is just to stay with them, encourage them, push them along, because I don't want them to miss the window, because the window is very short, because it's already, what, October 18th.
Yeah, it depends upon how they want to handle it. For the license renewal. Right, for the license renewal, that's right. Well, right, because we're not going to likely renew the license as it is right now with Mrs. Baker, Ms. Baker as the license holder. I mean, we don't know.
But that's the case. So if they don't get their stuff, they don't get switched over before then they might come to the renewal date and then it does not get renewed. Right, right. That's why I'm saying we have to stay with them because what I don't want them doing is dragging this beyond November 30th and then, okay, now we have to take some action on this.
And then they come back and then we have to do a special meeting to accommodate them when it's actually their responsibility completely. Yeah, yeah. Yeah, as long as they're aware of what's going to happen. If it goes beyond November 30.
Yeah. Yeah, just that. That's all I ask of you is just stay with Mr. Remick. I understand he's going to be the new manager. The license will probably be in his name as the manager. Just stay with them and make them aware of the timetable in the weeks that are remaining. OK.
Yeah, it would kind of be a shame to let that go by the board that they didn't take action on it. And now they have to close the business December 31st because there's no valid license. That's right. Something's got to be done by November 30th or they're all done. Right. Right. So I just, that's all I'm just asking to just keep it fresh in their mind. This is, this is how we do it in residential lending when we're under,
and specific timetables, we just, everybody's aware, the attorneys, the sellers, the realtors, just, you know, when time is of the essence, I hate to use that phrase, but really, yes, when you think about, you know, hell, this year is almost over. I mean, I can't believe we're halfway through October, and it's just November, December, and then goodbye, 23. Yeah. And the other thing to keep in mind, too, is,
We wouldn't be doing anything taking any type of an action against the issues that are going on there. This would be something that they've created on their own.
just by not renewing their license. Whether it's them or anyone else that has a license. Paperwork's not in by then. December 31st, they have to close their doors. There's not any retaliation or anything to do with what's going on there. Ralph told them. I don't think they came, but he told everybody.
Yes, he did. About November 30th. That's why I'm kind of, because that's fresh in my mind. I mean, I, I love his frank talk and, and I think, you know, they, they heard what he was saying about it's such a hard stop November 30th. So I just, you know, just want to make sure they're aware of it. I wish they came. I wish Chris Remick or Mr. Carroll came to the, um, the training class at which one of them came, but they didn't. So.
I got nothing but good feedback on it from people that did attend. Yeah, no, it was good. It was very good. I just didn't realize for the insurance, we can just come and shut the business down. What's that? Workman's comp. Oh yeah. I had no idea that they could just shut it down instantly, shut the business down.
That I learned, you know, family members and stuff that are in there, they have to be listed, you know, and that stuff makes sense. They're an owner.
Yeah, not if you're an owner, right? Not if you're an owner. You can't just have your kid, you know, child labor. Free labor. All right. All right. So if we have nothing else, Daria, then I guess we could do a meeting adjourn. It's 1.51. So I'll motion to adjourn today's Zoom meeting. Do we have a second?
A second. All right, good. All in favor say aye. Thank you for all your help. And we'll be talking. Sounds good. All right. Bye, everybody. All right.