We have Shane or Kevin.
We have Shane.
Shane are we all set?
Medford City Council Committee.
The whole of June 24th, 2025 is called to order.
Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Councilor Callahan.
She's here.
Vice President Collins.
Councilor Lozaro.
Councilor Lemming.
Councilor Scarpelli.
I see Councilor saying on zoom president bears present six present one absent the meeting is called to order, there'll be a meeting in the Medford city council committee of the whole at 6pm and city council chamber second floor Medford city hall at five George P has to drive Medford me and via zoom.
Action and discussion items 25 109 submitted by Mayor Brianna lingo current executive session litigation settlements votes may be taken dear President bears and members of the city council.
I respectfully request and recommend your honorable body and or executive session pursuant to general law chapter 30 a section 21, a three to discuss strategy with respect to litigation concerning Alicia Nunley Benjamin versus the city of Medford.
I also recommend that the council's agenda state in the executive session notice that votes may be taken.
Attorney Lindsay Gill from Peabody and Arnold will be present to provide the council with guidance on this matter.
Thank you for your kind attention to this matter.
Sincerely, Brianna Lugo Kern, Mayor.
Is there a motion to enter executive session pursuant to General Law Chapter 30A, Section 21A.3?
So moved by Council Vice President Collins, seconded by Councilor Lemming, and a note that votes may be taken.
On the motion, Mr. Clerk, when you're ready, please call the roll.
Mr. President, can you tell me the EMGL number again?
It is General Law, Chapter 30A, Section 21A3.
Thank you.
enter executive session.
Yes.
Councilor Callahan is absent.
Vice President Collins.
Yes.
Councilor Lozaro.
Councilor Lemming.
Yes.
Councilor Scarpelli.
Councilor Singh.
Yes.
President Behrs.
Six in the affirmative, one absent.
The motion passes.
We will enter executive session and we will return after that.
We're going to reconvene.
Someone's on the air.
All right.
Is there a motion on the motion to adjourn by Council let me second by.
Councilor Zaro, all those in favor?
Opposed?
Motion passes.
We'll reconvene at 7 p.m.
for our regular meeting.