Come to order clerk her to be please call the roll council bears vice president care of yellow council night council marks council Morrell councillor Scott Kelly president Falco present all seven members present at this time I would ask everyone to please rise to salute the flag I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America and to the Republic for which it stands one nation under God indivisible with liberty and justice for all
Hearings. Notice of a public hearing. Petition for grant of location, National Grid, North Andover, Massachusetts, underground electric conduits.
Thank you on the motion of console tonight to waive the reading for a brief synopsis by the petitioner seconded by console appears all those in favor all those opposed the motion passes at this time I would ask the representative from National Grid to please step forward and give us a brief synopsis of the project if you could start off by please stating your name and address for the record
Good evening, councilmen. My name is Moses Okokoro. I'm from National Grid Electricity. My address is 117 Medford Street, Malden. So the purpose for petitioning, signing this petition in, is to provide an electric service to a customer at 87 Medford Street. Basically, we'll be running two four-inch conduit from an existing pole across the sidewalk, heading towards the property, approximately about six feet
You know, caught on the sidewalk. Yeah, thank you. Thank you. You're welcome. At this point, I declare the public hearing open. Open to all those in favor of the petition. At this point, I would ask for those in favor of the petition to please come forward. If you could please state your name and address for the record again, if you are in favor of the petition.
Yeah, Moses Okokoro, 170 Medford Street, Malden, from National Grid. Thank you. And you are in favor of the petition? Yes, I am. Thank you. You're welcome. Anyone else in favor? Please come forward. Hearing and seeing none, I declare this portion of the hearing closed. Anyone in opposition of the petition? Anyone in opposition? Anyone in opposition?
Seeing and hearing none, I declare this portion of the hearing closed. If you could please come forward again. Thank you. Are there any questions from the council at this point? Councilor Knight.
Mr. President, thank you very much. Thank you, sir, for being here this evening. Did I hear you correctly when you said that the disruption was going to be along the sidewalk and not on the street? Yeah, on the sidewalk, yes, sir. All sidewalk work. Yes, sir. Thank you very much. You're welcome. Councilor Scarpelli. Simple question to follow up with that. Again, the sidewalks would be repaired and repaved to
the existing OBETA condition, correct? Yes, sir. Okay. The contractor will take care of that. Okay. And one thing we did have in the past, I think that making sure they follow in the proper timeline, in the past we've had different contractors that have worked for National Grid, not National Grid's fault, but had their
Companies come out at odd hours and one night at 10 o'clock at night we had an issue with this. Make sure they follow the proper protocol of times. That would be appreciated. Okay, thank you. Okay, thank you.
Thank you, Councilor Scarpelli. And I just want to make a quick note, and that is that the engineering division did review this application in a, if I'm just going to read further, just that the engineer division recommends that this grant of location be approved with the following conditions. The grant of location is limited to 60, uh, two foot, uh,
Duck Bank is described in the GOL documents as follows. National grid to install beginning at a point approximately 190 feet southeast of the central line of the intersection of Winter Hill Road and continuing approximately two feet in a southwest direction. National grid to install two to four inches of conduit to riser pole 590, that's 590, to pad 87 located inside the customer's property.
Number two, before starting work, the contractor shall notify dig safe and shall obtain all applicable permits from the engineering division. The project must obtain a street opening permit pursuant to section 74-141 of the city ordinances prior to commencing work.
Number three, no other utility structures, conduits, duct banks, pipes, or any other apparatances are adversely impacted. National Grid shall ensure that all sewer, water, and drain lines are marked prior to any excavation. Any disturbed concrete sidewalk panels shall be replaced in kind. Asphalt must be replaced with asphalt.
Number four, installing the proposed conduit will disturb the existing driveway apron for 87 Medford Street.
The existing apron has hairline cracking which will worsen with this installation. The engineering division recommends that the entire driveway apron be removed and replaced. The new apron shall be six inch depth of concrete and be installed per city standard. So those are the recommendations from the engineering division. At this point, I'd recognize Councilor Knight. Mr. President, motion to adopt the conditions requested by the city engineer.
On the motion of Council Knight, seconded by Councilor Beers, Councilor Scarpelli. If I can, again, I'm sorry. How long is this process? How long is the project gonna take? Well, the process of digging usually is just about a day. They'll open the site. Just one day? Yes, and then cover, you know, the same day. Okay, and the neighbors will be informed. Exactly. Okay, thank you. Thank you. You're welcome, sir. Move approval. Second that. Thank you, Councilor Scarpelli.
On the motion of Consulate Knight, seconded by Consulate Beers to approve the paper as adopted, as amended, with the conditions by the Engineering Division. On that motion, Clerk Urneby, please call the roll. Consulate Beers.
Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. 70 affirmative zero in the negative. The paper passes. Thank you very much. Thank you. Have a good night. Motions, orders and resolutions.
Offered by council tonight, be it 20-064, be it resolved that the city administration provide the council with a list of vacant positions funded in the current fiscal year budget. And be it further resolved that the council be provided with an organizational chart reflecting transitional roles and responsibilities until the aforementioned vacancies are filed. Councilor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much.
We've had much discussion about pre-budget meetings that are going to be coming up, much anticipated pre-budget meetings, I may say. The question comes to whether or not we have some vacant positions that are available here in the city. I know the council's been talking about its priorities. We have a priority meeting tomorrow. One of our number one priorities is getting legal counsel for the city council. So in an effort to better understand the financial picture here in the community,
and also better prepare ourselves for the budget. I'm requesting that the city administration provide us with a list of vacant positions that they're looking to fill, as well as a list of the transitional roles and responsibilities that are being covered by whatever department head in the present until such time as those vacancies are filled, Mr. President. So it's just an effort to gather information so that we can better prepare ourselves for these pre-budget hearings and also make a better case for ourselves to – a better case in terms of what our financial standing is in order to attain legal counsel here for the city council.
Thank you, Consul Knight. On the motion of Consul Knight, seconded by Consul Scott Pelley. All those in favor? All those opposed? The motion passes.
20-065, offered by Vice President Carviello, be it resolved that the Memphis City Council request that the DCR install sound devices on the traffic signals at Whole Foods in efforts to help those with sight issues cross the street in a safe way. Be it further resolved that this be sent to the Office of Diversity and Disability. Vice President.
Carviello. Thank you Mr. President. Mr. President, this was brought to my attention by someone in the community that has sight disabilities. And I don't realize, but we have
Two housing complexes, both on Walking Court and on Austin Street, that have many disabled people. And Whole Foods is their place where they go shopping and do most of their work, most of their food things.
I would think that we request that DCR install the sound devices for people that are blind, so they hear when the lights turn, similar to what we have in Method Square. So, and I also ask that this also be sent to the officer, diversity and disability, and have them also make the request to DCR and Representative Garbally, so we can get this done in the interest of public safety.
Thank you, Vice President Carvello. Councilor Beers. Thank you, Mr. President. And maybe Councilor Carvello can answer. It says traffic signals at Whole Foods. Do you mean the entire South Street, Auburn Street, Mystic Valley Parkway intersection? Yeah. I'd just like to amend the paper to name the streets on the intersection, if that's all right. Yeah.
And also to capitalize Whole Foods if possible. Okay. So Councilor Beers would like the streets to be mentioned in the resolution. In Whole Foods to be capitalized. Auburn Street in Mystic Valley Parkway. Is that Auburn on the south side of Mystic Valley as well?
It's Auburn on both sides. Correct. Yes. Counselor Knight. Mr. President, I'd just also like to amend the paper to request that it be sent to the city engineer and traffic engineer. As we're all well aware, there are various times the state will come to the city to request certain rights away, permits and the like, to get work done. And we can sometimes get mitigation from the contractors that are performing work in our community. And this might be an aspect where we can negotiate mitigation. So I'd request that we make those two entities aware.
of the council's request as well, so that in the instance that an opportunity comes up, we can possibly negotiate some mitigation that this can be something that they can ask for. Thank you, Councilor Knight. We have a resident that would like to speak on this issue. Thank you for coming down tonight. If we could please have your name and address for the record. Rosemary Tehan, T-E-E-H-A-N. And I live at 19 Brooks Street in Medford. Thank you.
And let's see, I'm requesting this because there is not an audible signal there right now. And to cross it, there's a flat island in the middle. So I don't think I would cross the street without
If I use the cane for mobility, I don't think I would cross the street the way it is now by myself, because it would be too easy to veer. And the other problem with having no audible signal there is I have to guess when the light changes. And so sometimes,
there's just a pause in traffic. And so I'll start to go and, you know, the cars start to come. So, and, you know, of course, Macy will stop when she does see that happening, but it has happened a couple of times. And so it's a little nerve wracking to cross the street and especially on the way back because
There is, you can't even press a button until you get to the middle of the island. And so I'm crossing, again, at my best guess. And actually, when I hit the island, I figure I'm probably all right, so Macy just goes. But again, it is my best guess when I go. Thank you. Thank you.
Councilor Cavill. Do you have any further comments?
Thank you. As the young lady mentioned, that's a very dangerous intersection with it, because you've got cars going, traversing on all different ways. And at one point, there's like a four-way intersection there, from the cars turning in and out of Whole Foods, going in and out onto Auburn Street. So it is a safety issue, and people just drive like maniacs in that road anyway, so. Correct. Good, thank you. Counsel Marks.
Thank you, Mr. President. I want to thank Councilor Caviello for bringing up this very important subject. I would request, as maybe a B paper, if we could send this to the Traffic Commission as well as our Human Diversity and Disabilities Commission regarding other street signalization throughout the community to see where upgrades for sound devices are needed throughout the entire community. Thank you, Councilor Martins. Thank you.
Okay, we'll take the B paper first. On the motion of Council Marks, seconded by Councilor Carviello. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? The motion passes. On the main motion offered by Councilor Carviello, as amended by Councilor Beers and Councilor Knight. Seconded by Councilor Scarpelli. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? The motion passes.
On the motion of Councilor Knight to take papers in the hands of the clerk, seconded by Councilor Beers. All those in favor? All those opposed? The motion passes. Offered by Councilor Marks, be it resolved that a no parking here to corner at the intersection of New Bern and Memphis Street be installed. Councilor Marks.
Thank you, Mr. President. I was contacted by a resident on New Bern Ave, New Bern Street, I'm sorry, regarding this particular intersection onto Meffitt Street. If this car's parked at the corner, it makes it increasingly difficult to pull out into traffic. And they are very concerned regarding public safety. So they've asked that a sign go up on New Bern,
that says no parking from here to corner at the intersection of New Bern Street and Meffitt Street. Thank you, Councilor Marks. Thank you. Councilor Beers. I'm not sure if it should be an amendment or a B paper, but I think a B paper to at least if we're sending this over to also review similar conditions at Bradshaw and Spring Street. I don't actually know if the residents want to sign, but I think it's similar conditions, dangerous to turn. So if the traffic engineer could review that.
So on the BP, Bradshaw and? Spring. Bradshaw and Spring Streets. So we'll take a, yes, Councilor Marks. Mr. President, I think part of the concern is naturally the public safety concern, but there are many residents in this community that are not familiar with the parking rules and regulations, and one of them is no parking 20 feet within an intersection. Correct.
And many residents think they're far enough back or may not be quite familiar and say, hey, I'm a good distance. I'm a car length away from this intersection. And they're getting tagged, Mr. President. So we know Park Method is doing their job. But I'd like to at least be able to get notification out to residents that there is no parking at any intersection within 20 feet of that intersection. And that's throughout the entire city.
I actually didn't know that, so that's helpful. And I think part of the review should be yellow paint, right? There should be a marking of some kind. Something. Signage, yellow paint, just to notify residents, as well as keep the streets safe. Would you like to make that as an amendment to your resolution, Councilman?
I'd like to make an amendment, but I'd also, I don't know how we do it as a council, but I think it would be great to notify the public on some of these issues that I'm hearing around the community. And one of them is parking within 20 feet of an intersection. And again, as we probably all hear, parking too close to the apron of a driveway.
I get a lot of calls regarding cars that are parking right up in thickly settled neighborhoods, right up to a driveway, and it makes it increasingly difficult to get into your own driveway. And I believe you have to park, I think it's two or three feet, I can't recall, I think it's three feet from the apron of a driveway.
And that's seldom enforced, but it's also an issue too, Mr. President. And I think these reminders to the public to let them know that these are rules and regulations that are out there to benefit everyone are helpful. Absolutely. So I'm not sure how we get that out other than me just mentioning it now. But I'm not sure how we get that out. Point of information, Councilor Scarpelli.
communications director, I'm sorry, have they followed through yet with the implementation of communication director? I believe they're actually hiring for that position. Because that's a great, that's one of the avenues that I think most communities use and they go out through social media, city website, maybe if there's someone now that's doing that, we could recommend that.
I mean, it'd be nice, just if I may, it'd be nice maybe to even put something, or maybe send a copy of this paper to the police chief, maybe they can put something on the police website, like Councilor Scarapelli said, the city website, if there's like, it's always good to have like an FAQ type page, you know, frequently asked questions, but maybe that's something that comes up, or actually even Park Medford, so, I mean, there's a number of venues where this resolution probably could be sent if you wanted to. I'd take all those suggestions, that's great. Okay.
Thank you. Thank you, Councilor Marks. And thank you, Councilor Scott Pelley. Councilor Morrell. Thank you, Mr. President. I was basically going to say everything that was just said as a communications professional.
There's a number of avenues we can take. But also, I know, not that I've ever gotten a ticket, but I know when you're trying to figure out how to deal with that ticket, you end up on the Park Medford website. So if there was a place to kind of explain, here's a number of reasons you, and I know it says it on the ticket, but while you're here looking at your ticket issue, let's see some other things that you should probably be aware of parking in Medford. So I think just easy access to this information in addition to signs, in lieu of signs and painting that we can't have everywhere.
Thank you, Councilor Murray. Mr. President, also, it's New Bern Ave. I was correct originally, and then I corrected myself. New Bern Ave. On New Bern Street. OK, New Bern Ave. New Bern Ave at the street. OK. We will correct that in the resolution. Thank you for letting us know. Councilor Caviello. Thank you, Mr. President.
With what Councilman Marks brought up, I've received calls from people that Park Method does occasionally go around and do that, and they also, they tag people who park in front of their own driveways.
And I've gotten a lot of calls from that. People say, I'm blocking my own driveway, why are they doing that? But they do on occasion go by and they tag cars that are in driveways and the ones that are too close. I don't know how often they do it. Maybe there's something we should maybe direct the people to watch a little closer, especially at night time. Thank you, Councilor Caviello. Mr. President, if I could? You absolutely can. One minute, please. Councilor Marks.
The one stipulation with Park Method, they only enforce streets that have resident permit parking. So the other several hundred streets in the city that don't have it, don't get that type of enforcement. So I think we have to have a consistent policy, whether you're on a resident permit parking street or not, where these infractions are enforced.
Thank you, Mr. President. Thank you, Councilor Marks. So we have a B paper offered by Councilor Beers. On that B paper, seconded by Councilor Scarpelli. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? The motion passes. On the main motion offered by Councilor Marks, as amended by Councilor Marks, to send the paper to the mayor's office, the chief of police, it's a park method, to post,
to post notifications with a guide to parking near street corners. Into the future communication director. Seconded by Councilor Caviello. All those in favor? All those opposed? The motion passes. Records. The records of the meeting of February 4th were passed to Councilor Behrs.
Council of Beers? How did you find those records? I am incredibly disappointed to say that I found them pristine. You want to move approval of those? I move approval. Thank you. On the motion of Council of Beers, seconded by Councilor Caviello to approve the records. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? The motion passes. Anything else?
And before I conclude this meeting, may I wish a very happy birthday to our Vice President, Consul Caviello. Consul Caviello.
You hope you had a great day? Well, let's say, where else would I want to spend my birthday with some of my most favorite people? I'm 66 years old today. All right. Thank you. Well, happy birthday. Hope you have a great day. Thank you very much. I know, getting old. I'm the senior now. Senior citizen. I once again won't let you know how old I am. On the motion of conduct.
On the motion of council, I ask Scott Pelley to adjourn the meeting seconded by Vice President Caviello. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Meeting adjourned.