[SPEAKER_00]: Greetings.
[SPEAKER_00]: My name is Dr. Lori Hodgdon, and I want to extend to you and your family a very warm welcome to the Curtis Tufts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Curtis Tufts is a therapeutic public day school serving students in the Medford public schools and surrounding communities for over 35 years.
[SPEAKER_00]: Curtis Tufts accommodates students with a variety of learning differences who are on an individualized education plan and have struggled in a traditional classroom setting.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will find that student success is our priority.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Curtis-Tufts focuses on meeting the individual needs of all students through differentiated learning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Students learn in an intimate setting with class size that is limited to eight students and a maximum school total of 40 students.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Curtis-Tufts is fully staffed with highly qualified professionals, including teachers, adjustment Councilors, and a building administrator.
[SPEAKER_00]: Each year will provide important transitions and the acquisition of new skills that will enhance students' ability to apply learning in many ways.
[SPEAKER_00]: We are committed to providing a challenging and rigorous curriculum that helps each student progress at a developmentally appropriate rate and provides a safe environment for all students.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mother Teresa has said,
[SPEAKER_00]: In this life, we cannot do great things.
[SPEAKER_00]: We can only do small things with great love.
[SPEAKER_00]: In her quote, Mother Teresa very powerfully captures important wisdom about how to approach life and schooling to make it more fulfilling and significant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Teaching and learning offers us all numerous opportunities to focus on a number of small things that culminate over time to produce students that are prepared to do the great things of life.
[SPEAKER_00]: With this in mind, ultimately, as a school community, we are judged by the actions of our students and the way new student learning connects and impacts the world beyond our school.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your students' experience at Curtis-Tufts will provide the social and emotional support needed to be successful while focusing on learning.
[SPEAKER_00]: I value lifelong learning and believe that all students can achieve when they feel safe and supported in learning.
[SPEAKER_00]: I aim to make our students' learning experience at Curtis Tufts engaging and exciting by working in partnership with our students' families and guardians.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the new principal of Curtis Tufts, I believe that it is my responsibility to maintain and to continue to build a supportive and collaborative spirit at our school.
[SPEAKER_00]: Together as a school community, we will build on the traditions of the past and meet the challenges of the future in innovative and exciting ways with our Curtis Tufts students at the center of our work together.
[SPEAKER_00]: I look forward to meeting all of you in the near future.