[SPEAKER_05]: Let's call the meeting to order.
[SPEAKER_05]: And do you have minutes?
[SPEAKER_05]: Do you want to read the minutes from last time?
[SPEAKER_05]: Sure.
Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are minutes from last meeting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Present were Christopher Bader, Charlotte Scuderi, and Joseph Brennan.
[SPEAKER_00]: Meeting was called to order at 6 or 7 p.m.
[SPEAKER_00]: Open meeting law complaint filed by Ryan Howard.
[SPEAKER_00]: Abutters need to be notified ahead of meeting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hayward, Hayward.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hayward, sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ryan Hayward.
[SPEAKER_00]: Abutters need to be notified ahead of meeting in issuing certificates of appropriateness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Notices were sent out to anyone living 300 feet to the house in question.
[SPEAKER_00]: Motion to appoint Christopher Bayer to address complaint was approved.
[SPEAKER_00]: Application for certificate of appropriateness for 298 High Street, Medford, MA.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stainless steel chimney caps to be added to home.
[SPEAKER_00]: Motion to approve was granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: South Street historic district approval.
[SPEAKER_00]: City Council will hold its second vote at 7 p.m.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tuesday, August 13.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ryan Hayward states there is a conflict of interest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Christopher Bader sold house to chimney cap applicant.
[SPEAKER_00]: City system defied building certificates in historic districts.
[SPEAKER_00]: System is being worked on by city building department.
[SPEAKER_00]: South Street District Mapping.
[SPEAKER_00]: Map needs to be filed with the Registry of Deeds.
[SPEAKER_00]: District will not be official until documents filed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ryan Hayward asked what upcoming plans HCC had.
[SPEAKER_00]: Christopher Bader confirmed he would be retiring from commission at the end of his term.
[SPEAKER_00]: Staff Jessica Martinez read minutes from July meeting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Motion to approve minutes passed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Jeffrey Bartel asked where 298 High Street was located.
[SPEAKER_00]: I forgot about this guy.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's located in Marm-Simmons District.
[SPEAKER_00]: Meeting adjourned at 6.28 p.m.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, perfect.
[SPEAKER_05]: Let's see.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, that seems good.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what I proposed this evening is, first of all,
[SPEAKER_05]: talk about the South Street District, talk about the website, have members introduce ourselves, and then I'll have answers.
[SPEAKER_05]: Sound good?
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: So the South Street Historic District is all set, with the exception of filing the
[SPEAKER_05]: the map with the registrar of deeds.
[SPEAKER_05]: I should have done that before this meeting, but I didn't get around to it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And I didn't know it would be anywhere near metrics or the registrar of deeds for that matter.
[SPEAKER_05]: So either I can do that or a member can volunteer to take care of filing the map with the registrar of deeds.
[SPEAKER_05]: As far as the website is concerned, the city has expressed interest in taking over the website from the third party that currently hosts it, but they have pretty much dropped the ball.
[SPEAKER_05]: Is that fair, Teresa?
[SPEAKER_05]: They say they don't have the resources to actually
[SPEAKER_05]: Um, they don't have the expertise to actually put a copy of the old website on our website.
[SPEAKER_05]: So this is a problem, a problem that, uh, so, you know, I'm, I'm stepping down this evening.
[SPEAKER_05]: This is a problem that the new chair or whoever we, we designate as, as the, uh, um,
[SPEAKER_05]: as the person to deal with website issues will have to deal with more.
[SPEAKER_05]: So that's where that stands.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's an important matter, and it is not a satisfactory proposal.
[SPEAKER_05]: And so, let's go around the room and introduce ourselves so we get to know each other a little bit.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm Chris Bader.
[SPEAKER_05]: I've been on that commission for 23 years.
[SPEAKER_05]: I've been chair for at least the past 10 years.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm not sure when I became chair.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm a retired artificial intelligence consultant, and I no longer live anywhere near Medford.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, this is really exciting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Joe, you wanna?
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm Joe Rodane.
[SPEAKER_02]: I live on Winter Street.
[SPEAKER_02]: I've been on the board for two years.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not really a general contractor, I'm a carpenter.
[SPEAKER_02]: I work in the area and on all the homes and newer homes and that sort of thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Charlotte, do you want to introduce yourself?
[SPEAKER_03]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Charlotte Scuderi.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm a realtor at Remax Andrew Realty.
[SPEAKER_03]: I have been on the board for I think
[SPEAKER_03]: four, five years?
[SPEAKER_03]: That's all right?
[SPEAKER_05]: At least.
[SPEAKER_03]: At least, okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: James?
[SPEAKER_04]: My name is James Mackey.
[SPEAKER_04]: I live on Lookout Road.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm an architect, and I have been on the board for 11 minutes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Emery?
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm Emery McGowan.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I live on South Street, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: South Street, Chalk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, he had one of the old shipbuilder's houses, luckily.
[SPEAKER_01]: One of the most beautiful houses on South Street.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, really pretty.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a couple of them, a couple of shipbuilders.
[SPEAKER_01]: I live in the big purple one, so it's purple.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I bought the house 27 years ago.
[SPEAKER_01]: I moved from, I grew up in Medford and then moved to suburbs, did not like it.
[SPEAKER_01]: came back.
[SPEAKER_01]: Um, I, when I am retired now, when I worked, I worked as an interior designer and I worked with real estate people doing renovations and, you know, foreign plans and whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I said, don't give me a house that's new.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want old, I want it virgin.
[SPEAKER_01]: Boy, did I get it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was, it was vacant for like 10 years.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I hauled away 15, 30 odd dumpsters and
[SPEAKER_01]: kept everything that was good, you know, all the molding and all that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it looks still very much the period that it was built, 1830, well, 1834.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's my story and that's why I'm interested in, you know, I'm interested in history and houses, obviously, and that's my story.
[SPEAKER_05]: Terrific.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, Asita, can you introduce yourself?
[SPEAKER_06]: Hey, sorry, I think I lost my internet for a second.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm Hasitha.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm an architect.
[SPEAKER_06]: I work with the architectural team at Chelsea.
[SPEAKER_06]: I've done multiple redesigned restoration projects of historic buildings, and that was the main key for me to apply for the historic department and be a part of this community.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I don't know what we are talking about right now.
[SPEAKER_06]: I just missed my internet and then just joined back.
[SPEAKER_06]: So a little introduction about me was that and I just had a baby boy.
[SPEAKER_06]: So he's keeping me occupied and sorry, I was not able to be in person today.
[SPEAKER_06]: So no problem.
[SPEAKER_05]: Congratulations.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: I look forward to seeing you all in person and having some chat with you guys and understanding what our
[SPEAKER_06]: commission does for the community and be a valuable asset to you guys and the community.
[SPEAKER_05]: Great.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, welcome.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you guys.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, so that's that.
[SPEAKER_05]: So,
[SPEAKER_05]: We need to elect a chair, a vice chair, and I would propose we elect a secretary, a secretary being the one who will deal with making sure that the minutes actually get posted, and that, and also, we have website issues that I mentioned, so the secretary
[SPEAKER_05]: probably could be the person designated to just make sure the website gets up and running, that either it continues with the existing provider or the city takes it over or whatever.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, can I have a volunteer for chair?
[SPEAKER_05]: Joe?
[SPEAKER_05]: Anybody else?
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, let's take a vote.
[SPEAKER_05]: Uh, can I have a second to, uh, can I have a second to, uh, uh, for, for Joe's nomination and Marie.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I'm nominate.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm seconding his.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: So I technically I'm no longer a member of the commission, so I'm not going to vote.
[SPEAKER_05]: Uh, but let me, uh, let me call Charlotte for Joe.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, I will.
[SPEAKER_05]: Joe.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Anne Marie?
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: Asita?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, Joe's nomination is carried unanimously.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Congratulations, Joe.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_05]: Appreciate that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: Can I have a volunteer for vice chair?
[SPEAKER_05]: Charlotte is our vice chair.
[SPEAKER_05]: Are you considering continuing, Charlotte?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, I don't think so, not this year.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: I could volunteer for that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Excuse me?
[SPEAKER_06]: I could volunteer for vice chair.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, sure, Hasitha, sure.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, can I have a second for St.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hasitha's?
[SPEAKER_05]: Are there any other volunteers?
[SPEAKER_05]: I'll second that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, so Hasitha,
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, can I, so let's just call the roll, Charlotte?
[SPEAKER_03]: I vote for yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, Joe?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: James?
[SPEAKER_05]: And Marie?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, Azita?
[SPEAKER_05]: You can vote for yourself.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, that's good.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, now, do people think we need a secretary?
[SPEAKER_05]: I do want someone to deal with the website issues.
[SPEAKER_05]: Or we can just leave it to the chair and the vice chair.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm open to ideas.
[SPEAKER_05]: What do you think, Joe?
[SPEAKER_05]: If someone wants to be secretary, OK, then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't look at me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not that terrible.
[SPEAKER_05]: OK, let's leave the office of secretary open.
[SPEAKER_05]: And maybe one of the people who isn't here can take care of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: OK, that is pretty much it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Welcome, everybody.
[SPEAKER_05]: I think we're in good hands.
[SPEAKER_05]: And so the official part of the meeting is it, anybody have any other business?
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, can I have a motion to adjourn?
[SPEAKER_05]: Motion to adjourn, okay, second?
[SPEAKER_05]: I second.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, so all in favor of adjourning, Charlotte?
[SPEAKER_03]: I accept, yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, Joe, yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: James?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: And Marie?
[SPEAKER_05]: I see that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, perfect.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's it.