I mean, it doesn't take that long and it doesn't cost that much. I realize you're trying to make some money, but I guess this is one of those cases where you gotta spend some money to make some money. Yes. Okay. And can you tell me, she's dressed in pink? Yes. Okay. You know, that's unfair, you know, bringing along a partner to,
I hope you have a successful event. Okay. And you just get back in touch with Kevin with those two items and we'll be all set. Okay. You better say goodbye. Thank you so much. Have a great day.
Hello. This is that all day. Kickball. Yes, yes, yes. This is a turning event. This is October 11th. Is that Columbus Day? So that's Columbus Day weekend, but I was actually hoping to see if October 12th, the Sunday was available instead.
I think they actually take the whole thing. Yeah, I take, I use all four fields. So the only conflict will be is girls softball, which I think is already in.
I know the past the past two years, the softball league has been very nice and has given us the day. Yeah, obviously, that's totally up to them. But no, I think so Sunday, that's right. So Sundays, I think softball doesn't start till 1230.
Oh, your event's still five o'clock though, right? Yeah, so it does go all day. I don't necessarily use all of the fields all day, but I definitely can't give like a set time on which field would be open at what, you know what I mean? Yeah, I know softball. Yeah, that's how it's been in years past. We usually just tell softball and they just make sure they don't schedule games that day. I don't think that would be an issue. I think Paulette is actually on the call
I'm here. Hello, everyone. Shining in. It shouldn't be a problem. That's usually a practice day more than a game day. We have double headers on Saturdays. So I'm sure we can work something out. You know, I'm always flexible. Thank you. Sorry, October 12. We said right. Just Yes. Yeah. Thank you.
Any questions, Laura? No. Fee is usually $25, right? Yes. That's what I paid in the past. Yeah. Chris, any questions? Oh, Chris. Yeah, he just wrote, no issue. So, Ms. Rocco, enjoy your day. Thank you very much.
and hope to see you next year, too. Yeah, this is year 10, so we'll see. That'd be wonderful. That'd be wonderful. That's wonderful. We like what you're doing. Thank you. Thank you guys very much. Have a good night. All right, hang on. Bye. She's quite aware of the requirements for the- Yeah, she's been doing it. Yeah, she's been doing it.
Yep. Okay. Wow. So just go on. It's all fields, September 1st to October 31st on Mondays, Tuesdays, and Thursdays from eight to 10. Mr. Fonz, what is he on the call? Sam. He's not. We'll tell you this. Method youth soccer.
Request to use the following fields for fall, August 25th through November 15th. Placed at lower, Mondays through Fridays, five to eight. Saturdays, eight to five. Sparrows, Monday through Friday, five to eight. Placed at upper field, Monday through Friday, five to eight. Saturdays, eight to five. Victory, Monday through Friday, 5 p.m. to 8 p.m. This is a repeat request.
They're going to release them on PlayStats. So... I don't see this camping right now, so I might not be around. They're going to release them on PlayStats. So... I don't see this camping right now, so I might not be around. They're going to release them on PlayStats. So... I don't see this camping right now, so I might not be around. They're going to release them on PlayStats. So... I don't see this camping right now, so I might not be around. They're going to release them on PlayStats. So... I don't see this camping right now, so I might not be around. They're going to release them on PlayStats. So... I don't see this camping right now, so I might not be around. They're going to release them on PlayStats. So... I don't see this camping right now, so I might not be around. They're going to release them on PlayStats. So... I don't see this camping right
We have, we have, yeah, I don't think we have it. This is going from August 25th, which is next week, November 15th. Yes, there will be a little bit. He'll hit the first weekend.
Although no, sorry, Victor, he only has Monday through Friday, right? Apparently he needs weekends. Yeah, it's only weekends that there'll be a conflict. Okay, good. So this is a repeat. Chris, you all right with this? Yes, sir. Laura? Yes. Okay.
I don't believe so. I didn't see it on the city calendar. Well, you know, they do make changes quite often. And they don't always tell us about it.
There was a special meeting today at 11 a.m., but I don't see anything on the calendar for tonight. There was a special meeting at 11 a.m. today, but I don't, yeah, but I don't see one tonight. Sorry. You're welcome.
Okay, so that's on the way. Let's see, let's see. We'll get two more, right? I do have a couple of latecomers, too. So one of them is, you've been waiting for something to get started. What can we do for you? I'm actually looking to go to, I started a program with, I want to say it's in between Netflix
and then trying to be able to get the use of Morrison Field for training sessions for soccer. So what I have been doing for the last 25 years, I'm the regional manager for a nonprofit organization, which is called FC Stars. And we wanted to be able to make sure that we didn't exclude some of the inner city kids from not being able to play club soccer. So we're giving them an opportunity to be able to do that at a much reduced price.
and they're only paying a third of what anybody else spends. And we're trying to be able to get the practices. We were supposed to get three teams, and unfortunately, I think it's only one team, and then hopefully two teams next spring to be able to play out of this area. The person that's coaching the team is actually probably someone that you've dealt with in the past, William Lewis, which is a baseball, he does hockey here in town. So he's a, he's gonna be the coach of that team.
And we're looking to be able to get more method kits. And so I reached out to the athletic director, which is John Preston and waiting to hear from him. So I don't know from him, but we do have a lot of modeling kits. We've got some method kits and we have kids that are also from different areas. And we're looking to be able to see if we can get this going. I've done this in the past with
a lot of, um, we've been successful where we've had teams here in the past and we were at the high school and we were able to do a lot of different things and it was great. A lot of the kids went on like the Salve's, uh, Aiden Salve and then Aiden was trying to pick up. Oh my God. Just, um, and, and it's been, it's been great. And I've had a bunch of kids that come from all the method. So I'm telling them to restart this all over again and then make sure that we can turn it on and
have the opportunity to do that. And we're a non-profit organization. Do you have a 501C designation? I do, and I can make sure it's CLI as well. I don't have a copy of the schedule in front of me, so I have to rely on
Mr. Bailey and his only copy of the schedule. My defense, I only got it today. I did get it printed out and I got you a copy. You do have a schedule, right?
online. Yeah. Oh, yeah, I can see it. Yeah. So I just want to Morrison. Morrison is the one part that we don't have much going on. That's why we just give somebody something more for Saturday. Yeah. That was one Saturday. Sunday was it a Sunday? I think I looked at it. I think it was the young lady that just Saturday or Sunday. Yeah, I got what day. Yeah.
A Sondra drive organization. Yeah. That was a Saturday. Yep. No. Wednesday. Yes.
It's no conflict. The only thing is, what time does it get DACA once you start hitting October 29th? October 27th? No, 29th. That's right. October 29th is the next day is homing. Yeah. And our last game is November 7th. So you changed it too? No, no, no. Where do you play your games at? In Bedford. In Bedford? Yeah.
The only thing is there's no light. So sunset for October is 541. You think that we, if there's nobody before us, you think we'd be able to come in earlier to be able to offset that? Yeah, there's nothing, there's nothing on the calendar. So if you want to do like a three to five as it gets darker. I think that they get out at- At 3.30. I mean, that age group is, what are they?
2014, so there'll be 11 years old, right? So I'm trying to think of, do they get out of school at 2.30, or is it 3 o'clock? So even if you went from 3.30 to 5.30, you'd probably be able to get the season in reasonably. You know, the last half hour will probably be just about dark, I would think. Yeah. You know? Okay. But, I mean, you know, 5 to 7, we're getting there.
I mean, you could in the beginning of September, but once you get into October, you're going to, yeah. Because I was more concerned about having someone come in after us. And I was like, if I, if I do earlier and someone comes in. Yeah, you got the whole. Because there's no lights. Yeah. So nobody's coming in after. Yeah. That's just, that's just not going to happen. Yeah.
And that's probably our most underutilized park in our portfolio. Was that draw by it's actually pretty nice. They cut the grass. Yeah. Yeah. It's okay. It's nice. You didn't get out. I didn't get out. Yeah. Well, I'm just going to tell you, you know, we've had some dog issues in the past. So you might want to just check that, you know, and give us a heads up before you start.
Because we have a great director. They're very good. And they'll kind of fill in the holes if there are any. We've had that in the past.
Yeah, I dealt with that when I was the DOC over in Reading. And it was funny because it was about conservation land. So what I did, obviously, I brought a bucket and sand, right? And then I sat in front of the board, the Reading board, and they're like, you're not supposed to do that. It's conservation land. And I'm like, well, how long would it take for someone who comes out
and covers the whole, because we're not going to be able to play. But then if I've sent you an email, then it becomes a liability. And then it's just on your part, because you haven't done your work, right? As soon as I mentioned that, that thing was like, you know, and then they covered everything. I was more worried about liability than that's a big thing. But what about that fourth kid breaking his hand? You know, that's what I was concerned about. That's how I wanted to take care of it myself. And it was just an interesting situation.
So do we want to do 3.30 to 5.30 or do you want to just look at the sunset times and then just tell me what you want? If, if, uh, if you tell me no one's going to be there, I will say great. And then like, you know, if you can use the time, the daylight for now, and then if you have to keep on cutting back, if it's okay with you guys, I would be, it will be okay with me. So we're going to start off from the 27th, but today is the 19th. So that's next week. Uh, 19 and seven was 26, right?
August 27th, yeah. So that's next Wednesday? Yes. So you're going to start next Wednesday. And why don't we start at 5 to 7? And when you find that it's getting a little dark, let us know that you're going to be there. Because you don't want to issue a second order. That's a pain in the butt. Yeah, I'd rather know ahead of time. What are we making from 3 to 7?
and giving them the flexibility to go when he wants. All right, what are we going to do for fee then? I can do a flat fee if you want. Yeah. Okay. Yeah. I can do like a per day, but what are we charging? No, I have to look. I don't have that stuff at the top of my head anymore. Usually for outside organizations, it's $50 an hour. Yeah.
But I could do a flat fee. So even though it's more hours, I can do $50 a day, I could do $100 a day. And we would reserve the four hours. Yeah, I would do a flat fee. So you do three to seven, I would just say flat free $100 and figure it's going to be a two hour reservation.
So that'd be $90 to $50. That's what the outside organizations charge. I mean, obviously you guys set the price. You can do a sport fee. That's $200 for the whole season, but that usually has to be open for just Method kids and all. I'm taking that into consideration, you know, cause we got a multiple kids. We got other kids from other places. Right, right.
Usually what we do is we usually say the majority is Medford kids. So $950? $950 is right, yeah. $950. That would be $50 a day times 19 days. 20, 21. 21 to 20, right? Well, you put down 19, not me. Well, no, I meant the LSU that I said. I'm sorry, when William said he couldn't be there.
Oh, you're doing what's yeah, Tuesdays. Yeah, you can do Tuesdays. Is that good? I'm sorry, you couldn't do Fridays. I did the Wednesday, Friday, and then I changed the Wednesday, Thursday. So it comes out to 20 days. Yeah. Was it Wednesday, Friday, the first $1,000. Okay, that's good to me. All right. Now, you know, you need your disability insurance obviously with the naming the city of Redford as the
additional insured, and you send that to Mr. Bailey. And Mr. Bailey will take care of the rest. Sorry, we said $100 a day, flat fee? 50. $50 per day. 20 days, right? Yes. For a thousand. $50 per day. Okay. And then we're reserving three to seven, right? Yes.
So that's your permit, from three to seven. Utilize it as you will. Please don't over abuse it. But that's what we'll do this year. Okay, now if you get two teams next year, we'll talk about it next year, that's fine. Right? Sounds great, I really appreciate it. Right, anything else? Christian, do you have any other questions? Is he still there?
I'm good with this.
physically like a copy of it so I can have it with me. I'm going to give it to the pro just in case if anybody else. Oh, yeah, you'll get a you'll get a person, you know, people come in, they're like, Oh, we're supposed to be here. You'll be on on our website, you'll be on the calendar. So this is also a public view. Okay, so you'll have something something you can say, we have this time. Yeah.
So the public can view it that way, or your coach can always pull up and say, here's the calendar, it's here. But when I put this in the computer, you'll also get an email with the permit number, with all the dates listed. So if you want to print that out and have that on you as well, that would be your hard copy of the permit. Excellent. Fantastic. There's a lot that we do in Nigeria to be able to have the opportunity because in this country it's pay to play.
And we can give these kids an opportunity to play in this real thing. And I love to be able to give back. And also, this is good. So thank you very much. I appreciate it. You're a Somerville guy, huh? I'm a Cambridge guy. I say we. Yes. Actually, I moved back down the street. I moved down the street from Prospect Street, from Prospect Street in Cambridge to Prospect Street in Somerville. But I used to hang out with all the Metro guys when I was growing up. Oh, yeah? Don't tell me about that before we move every book together. All right. Move it inside. That's great.
Appreciate it. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you for joining us for the next hour. Good night. Night. You too. All right, the last permit that I see. You said Paulette? Yeah, Paulette for MYGS. And then I have one. Hi. Hi, Paulette. How are you? I'm well. How are you? Not too bad. We're going to make you sit for 30 seconds while we
Confer on yourselves. Any questions? I don't think I have any information on it. Trish, you don't have any information on this? Oh, OK. I have these, yes. I was looking for Paulette's name. Trish? No issues with softball. No issues. Paulette? Yes, sir. For being so patient and kind and letting that young man go before you,
No worries. All right. Thank you. I just have one quick question. We are planning the spooky scrimmage again for this year, but we don't have the date last year. We needed to extend it on the day that we did it. So I'm just throwing that out there now that Kevin, if you don't mind, I'll be back in touch. Cause I'm actually sitting outside of my next meeting to figure out when we're trying to get that done. Yeah.
We're all set for an additional day. You said one day? It's actually just a couple hours on one of those days were already permitted because we do the trick-or-treating under the lights at Columbus. At Columbus? It's at Columbus, yeah. No worries. Yeah.
And come out and watch. It'll be fun. Anybody that wants to come. Yeah, I think I will. I think I will. I think you should. I haven't seen you in a while. Come out and hang. I'll do that. I'll do that. Thank you. Well, you can go to your next meeting.
Oh, thank you. Can't wait. All right. Thank you. Have a good day. Bye. Okay. The one, the one permit that we did not look at was the box and ultimate. Sorry. Can I, no, there's one more. I do this. Let me just came in today. So you're supposed to reject them.
because that was a couple of weeks in advance. Hey, Kate's right here. You can. I'm here. You guys already know this one. You've already approved it for the Royal Park, but this is just the same thing. Oh, yeah. How are you? Good. I'm great. We had a great exhibit the first time around and we had some interest to install it by the slave wall at the Brooks Park.
So we saw the art and we didn't have any questions. And I didn't think we had any issues with any of the artwork that was done. And I actually went back, I went back up to the, to the Royal house and I couldn't, I couldn't quite figure out where you guys were going to put it, but I'm sure. Yeah, it was, it was right along the, that brick wall in the Royal park.
Okay. Yeah. So we, we had pretty, I think you were unable to make the last meeting because we looked at the odd one meeting. Yeah. She'd had the meeting and then she gave me the yeah. And then she sent out an email with no one objected and we just approved it. Yeah. Yeah. You didn't have to go to it. Right. She didn't miss a meeting.
Yeah, you're looking to move the installation to just another location. Yeah, yeah. So it's the Brooks Park on Grove Street by the Grove Street and Ravine intersection. There's the slave wall that is there and we have some of the artwork is relevant to that slave wall, so we wanted to move it there. So it's it's on kind of the West side of the.
train tracks along Grove Street. That's on Method Land Trust, right? Is that Method Land Trust land? No. It's Brooks Park. Brooks Park is a part of the land trust? It's part of the Brooks Estate. It's Brooks' son. Brooks' son's house was there. We had given some money from the CPC
can then do some exclamation last year or two years ago. And so where the slave wall is, behind the slave wall is where his house was. So they can do an exclamation and so on and so forth. So what side of the wall are you going to put the artwork? We haven't fully scoped it out, but I think it's going to be, it'll either be behind the wall or it'll be just south of the wall.
And how will you, so if you're not going to attach it to the wall, are you going to have like sticks, you know? Yeah, we have frames that we stake into the ground. Oh, OK. All right. So they're going to be done a lot of times? Yes. And so this is an additional one. It would be moving back to another location.
traveling art show, I guess. Right. Yeah. And then it's going to be at the event them in October, I think. So we're just making the most of it by the insurance policy runs out in the middle of September. So I thought maybe I'd get another chance to make use of that. So, um, I just have one, one kind of question. How many people do you anticipate we'll see this over a period of time?
Are you talking about, what do you mean, a little bit more than? Two weeks. Two weeks. I think we had about 150 visitors. I can't say for sure, because we had visitors that were coming in just online. So Royal Park, it was a place where a lot of people were walking and traveling to.
with just walking their dogs in the neighborhood and it's near the bus stop. So I don't necessarily know, you know, it's just along the side of the road. So I don't necessarily know how many people would actually stop and walk along there to see it, but it would give it visibility. The reason why I asked the question is because that's a passive park, if you will.
And quite frankly, it's passive for a reason, because there isn't an awful lot of parking. So when you're talking about Ravine Road and Jackson Road and so on and so forth, you're talking about residence areas. We've had requests to use that park for weddings and so on and so forth over the years. We haven't really allowed that.
Gotcha. And so I kind of question how spread out you're going to anticipate, because it's in anticipation. It hasn't been done, obviously, at that place. And we don't have any idea about how many people you're going to have and how much participation you're going to have. So I guess that's the question I ask is,
I would say that on average, we probably had at most like 10 people a day visiting when it was in Royal Park. So it wasn't, we didn't have like a massive number of people and it would only be, you know, when I was visiting, there were only a handful of people that would be there at one time. Okay, well, I just, I thought, like I said, there's not enough, A, you can't park on Grove Street,
So you'd have to pop on the side streets. I think that we'll probably hear some rebuttals from some of the residents maybe after a while, but c'est la vie. I mean, it is a park. So yeah. Chris. Chris. Oh, Chris.
I think he sent a message that he says he was good. No issues, sorry. No issues. Thank you. All right, Ms. Godin. Ms. Godin? Yes. Okay. Ms. Godin, I guess we'll okay, and good luck with it. Thank you. I don't know what the police will have to say about it, but you know, sometimes people,
you know, they get very territorial, especially in that area. And I'm happy to hear that as far as if that feedback comes back to us and that way we know how to plan for the next one. All right, well, good luck with it. Thank you. Thank you so much. I go down Grove Street quite a bit, so I might have to stop in front of the Paul Beale House and walk over and check it out. Check it out, yeah.
some prizes up last time. So there might be some things you can enter in to win some artwork. So please do. All right. Wonderful. Yeah. All right. Super. Thank you so much. Thank you. Any other surprises over there, young man?
There is no the last minute permits the USTA right now the city solicitor is looking at the draft of the contract between USTA and the city. There are some legal concerns that he has first before we even really discuss the smart access and everything else. So.
I've already reached out to USTA with some of our city solicitor's concerns and just bringing it back from USTA's legal team. I reached out to USTA after talking to the city solicitor about his concerns. He didn't ask the questions you did?
I did, and we thought it would be easier to not have the two head lawyers all over the world, that I should just reach out to them directly, talk about where the concerns are. No. Sure. No, but I think the city solicitor has a good point, once you start bringing in lawyers, that it just gets overly complicated. So he brought his concerns, and the USCA, if their lawyers have more questions or more legal terms that I don't know about, then
then we'll have them reach out to our city solicitor to get the information. So we'll take this till the next meeting or until such time as we receive an answer back from USTA. I have a list of questions that we'll move on to that. Oh, by the way, when you were out last month, we distributed the original letter to the commissioners. Yeah. So I asked them,
if they had any questions to write them down for this meeting. So that's why. Yeah, I think we need to first even see if we can get this past the legal term. We can talk about the logistics. We also need to just approve meeting minutes of last month. I'll entertain a motion to entertain the meeting note from July.
I entertain a motion to accept the meeting notes from July. Motion to accept the meeting notes from July. All those in favor? Aye. Motion passed. Are there any other items to discuss?
I want to adjourn. There we go. Imagine for that one. Thank you very much. I'll see. I'll see you later. Yeah. Thank you. We did. Yeah, one second. You know, I never see any of