Okay, great.
Good afternoon, everyone.
Thank you for attending.
We'll continue doing Zooms, I think, all the way into 2025, I think is the last thing I heard.
I know I kind of miss being in person, but I get all the benefits.
This is going to be a little bit of a long meeting.
I don't know if you're aware, but this commission takes off in July and August, you know, very nice.
So we're trying to cram almost three months of requests into today's agenda.
Also, we're gonna do, I like to do all the one day licenses at the beginning because they're really quick, but there's a dozen of them.
So I don't think it's fair to the one pledge and the two transfers.
to wait out after a dozen one day licenses.
So we're gonna mix it up a little bit.
We're gonna take care of those items first and then we'll take on the one day licenses at the end.
So everyone who's here for one day license just kind of cool your jets until the end.
Before we start, we have to do some housekeeping.
We have three months of minutes to review and approve
I've looked at them.
I had just a couple of questions, but Bobby and Ben, what say you?
Anything caught your attention or are you good with them?
I was good with them, Mr. Chairman.
I didn't see any issues.
The only thing I think I saw was on that
One one day application for Salem Street.
I forget what the name of it is here that they had the wrong date.
It said Saturday, June 20, I believe.
Yeah.
The May 17th minutes you're referring to.
Yeah, they meant May.
I have it circled too.
Let's first look at March 15th.
Let's look at those minutes first.
Yes.
Let me just, Daria, thank you.
They're very concise.
The only item I was a little confused with is number seven on the March 15 minutes.
For Boston Glory, I have circled out of the six one-day license applications, I circled June 24th and July 21st.
So we had approved, I believe, those six dates, but yet I see a one-day license request for June 24th.
in July 21 as part of the package.
So is that just an oversight or did we not convey that we approved those six day licenses?
You're talking about Boston Glory, correct?
Boston Glory, yeah.
Number seven on the March 15th.
Just kind of refreshing my memory.
So we did approve it, but they're doing it in a different location.
They're not going to have the beer garden just in one area, it seems like.
So they want to make sure they include the new area with the request.
I see.
So that's why, yes.
So they emailed me and I just said, come to the commission because, so this way we can just discuss it today.
Okay.
All right, perfect.
And that was the only thing that jumped out at me.
I'm sorry, Barbie, did you have any questions or Ben, anything on the March 15th minutes?
I didn't, that's a good catch.
No, everything looks good to me.
Okay, good.
Then let's make a motion.
Let's get this one off the table.
So I'll make a motion to approve the minutes from March 15th for the Liquor License Commission meeting.
And I'll second the motion.
Very good.
Thank you for the motion and the second.
All in favor, say aye.
Aye.
Aye, very good.
All right, Daria, that one's etched in stone now, the 15th.
All right, let's jump to the 19th minutes.
I look through, I have no question marks, nothing underlined, so I'm good with these.
Thank you, Daria.
Ben, Bobby, what say you?
I'm good with them.
I can make a motion to approve them too.
Bobby's good with it.
I'm good with it, yes.
Okay.
So look through it, all looks good.
I'll make a motion to approve the minutes from the April 19th meeting 2023 for the license commission.
Thank you.
I'll second the motion.
Very good.
Thank you for that.
All in favor to accept the minutes for April 19 say aye.
Aye.
Very good.
Thank you.
All right, we're rolling.
All right, let's take a look at the
The May 17th minutes.
Yeah, Bobby, I had the same, I circled June 20th.
I wasn't sure about that with the event them incorporated.
So that was my only question there.
Yep.
That's the only thing I saw around that as well.
Otherwise I saw, you know, reading this, it looked accurate to what, what happened during that meeting.
So I would, um, I'd be okay with that.
I'd make a motion to approve it.
Okay.
Very good.
I second the motion.
Thank you.
All in favor of accepting the minutes for the May 17th meeting, say aye.
Aye.
Very good.
All right.
Those three are off the table.
Thank you for that.
That was painless.
All right.
Let's jump into, as I said, we're going to push all the one day licenses to the end.
So let's start with Anthony's Liquors, the transfer of license.
Let's start with that one.
I saw Attorney Meridian.
I saw you there.
So, Attorney Meridian, let me just say that in the late 70s when I was going to school, I spent a lot of very cold Fridays and Saturdays in that ice chest in the back.
My sole job was to make sure there was plenty of cases of beer.
available as people come in and buying them and taking them out.
So I had clothes, and I had a coat, and it's summer, and I'm freezing my butt off.
So I just wanted to share that with you.
I'm very familiar with Anthony's Liquors.
Hopefully all good things then.
Yeah, all good things.
Thank you for submitting the package.
If you don't mind just giving us a good overview of what's transpiring, we see a transfer and then we also see a pledge of a license and inventory included.
So if you don't mind giving us a little narrative, that would be nice.
Sure.
So with me is Vimal Patel.
He's the sole shareholder, officer, and director of 269 Spring Street, Incorporated.
And he's purchasing Anthony's Liquors from SNDB Corp.
So requesting a transfer of the license to 269 Spring Street, Incorporated, approval of Vimal Patel as a manager of record, and approval of the pledge of the license and inventory to Rockland Trust Company.
So, it's going to be no changes to the footprint is the same story main their store hours 8am to 11pm and Sundays 10am to 11pm.
The most very experienced and running package stores.
He owns a few other ones.
in the area.
We'll have two or three employees.
He's TIP certified.
His employees will be TIP certified.
And he does use an ID scanner to help combat underage alcohol sales.
Again, this is a straight transfer of interest, a new business ownership coming in, but there'll be no changes really to the store at all.
You won't recognize anything like that.
So with that, any questions the board has for myself or V-Mobile, we'll welcome those.
Thank you.
Thank you for that.
I'm a banker, I'm not a lawyer, but your summary of transaction, I thank you for that, this document here.
Should the seller be SNDP Corporation or am I just getting all mixed up?
No, you're correct.
I can fix that.
And so, okay.
All right.
So I, you know, I did read the purchase and sales agreement.
And I, I said, I think, I think because with Nicolette, I saw her, she got it right on hers.
Hers was right.
So I just wanted to, okay.
So it should be SNDP corporation for the seller.
All right.
Bobby, Ben, any questions, anything jump out at you?
To me, it looks pretty straightforward.
I thank you for submitting such a complete package other than that little minor, little glitch there.
Are you the same entity that owns Cappy's now as well?
No, I represent Cappy's, those buyers, but this is a different, different Patel, different, there's no, there's no connection between, between those.
Okay.
So same last name.
No, I'm looking through here.
No, I don't have any questions.
Yeah.
It's pretty straightforward.
Bobby, anything that caught your attention?
Anything through the documents?
No.
I went over it the other day when Darius sent them over and everything looked in order to me.
Yeah.
I'm fine with it.
I was fine.
It all made sense.
I see, you know, I see the purchase price.
I see the,
the assets in there, the inventory.
Yeah, Rockland Trust will be, that's where they want their collateral.
Yeah, no, I don't have any questions.
It looks pretty straightforward.
You guys, if you wanna make a motion to move this along, I'd be fine with that.
Okay, let me just get the page here.
Okay, I can make a motion, if you like, for the transfer of license for 269 Spring Street, Incorporated, located 269 Spring Street, Medford, Mass., and it's for a transfer of license, a pledge of inventory.
And license.
Pledge of collateral.
Yep.
I think that's it.
I'll second that, the transfer of license.
Very good.
All in favor of moving forward to transfer our application along with the pledge of license and inventory, say aye.
Aye.
Very good.
All set.
That one
Thank you, Attorney Meridian.
We appreciate the complete package.
You make it easy every time.
Thank you.
Thank you so much, guys.
Okay, good luck.
Yep, thank you.
Let's jump to Method Wine and Spirit, please.
Attorney Angelique, I think I saw you on my little laptop screen here.
Yes, I'm here.
I'm Nicolette.
Thank you for making me look good in front of John.
He's my supervising attorney.
So that was really good.
You got it right in your summary of transaction.
I said, that one's right.
So like you said earlier, I'm another attorney with Demarcus Law.
We represent KV in this transaction.
With me, I have Vatzel, who's going to be a 50% shareholder with his wife, who is not in this meeting today, and Kruppel, who's going to be the manager of record.
KV entered into an asset purchase agreement to get all of the business assets and the alcohol from Trident Liquors, which is the seller here.
We are seeking approval of the transfer and approval
Scruple as the manager of record.
I submitted the full application like you had mentioned, but just to highlight a few things, there is no change to the store footprint.
There's no change to the store hours.
They'll operate within what's allowed by law.
Scruple is TIP certified.
They anticipate only having three to four employees.
They will have a point of sale ID scanner to combat underage.
sales.
Krupal is a manager of another store in Lowell, so he does have experience.
And Vatzel also has experience working from 2011 to 2015 as an employee in another package store.
Thank you for your time.
And if you guys have any questions, we'd be happy to answer.
Thank you for that narrative.
We appreciate it.
I see there's no pledge of inventory or license in here.
It's just that it's pretty straightforward just to transfer application.
So that's correct.
Yeah.
No, very, very simple.
I, I went through it myself.
I read, you know, the purchase and sales agreement.
Uh, I'm in mortgage banking, so, oh, I just love reading purchase and sales agreements.
You know, that's all I seem to do, but, um, I, I don't have any questions or concerns.
Uh,
Commissioner Delfano or Ben, anything on your mind, anything jump out at you in the package?
Nicolette, you had mentioned when you were just speaking, it was a transfer of license and change of manager as well.
On the first page, I just see under the number one box, transfer of license checked off.
Is that management operating agreement, is that also supposed to be checked or am I looking in the wrong place here?
So management operating agreement would be if we had a third party coming in to manage the store, an entity or another business.
With the transfer of the license, there is a section in that ABCC application for naming the manager of records.
So that's included within that checkbox.
Okay.
Very good.
That answered my question.
Thank you.
Yeah, that was the only thing I had.
Yeah, no, it's pretty straightforward.
Yeah.
Ben, anything from you?
Alan, only question, you said there's no pledge of inventory?
Correct.
Or the license, neither one, unlike the other one, yeah.
There's no bank financing here, so.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, there's no note in there or nothing.
Yeah.
So that purchase price we're looking at and then the estimated inventory, that's it right there.
Correct.
Okay.
No, I mean, it's pretty dense and it looks complete.
Now let's have a motion so we can keep moving forward.
Okay, get to the top here.
So I'll make a motion to accept the application for the transfer of no alcohol business license.
Sorry, so it's Khabib Corp doing business as Medford Wine and Spirits.
Who are we actually transferring it from?
It's Trident Liquors.
Oh, okay, right.
Okay, so from Trident Liquors to KV Corp.
So I would make a motion to approve this transfer of license.
Very good, thank you.
Second the motion.
Very good, thank you for the motion.
All in favor of accepting a transfer of application or the transfer of license from Trident to KV, say aye.
All right, very good.
It's approved.
Very good.
Thank you, Attorney Angelique.
We appreciate it.
Nice package.
Thank you very much.
Have a nice day.
Okay.
Yeah.
The Catracalla restaurant, Bocelli's.
I have to, uh, Ben and Bobby, I have to recuse myself from this one.
Uh, as you probably aware, there's a family high to this restaurant.
So, uh, I don't want anyone ever to point a finger at me or at this commission and, uh, raise a conflict.
Uh, concern.
So I'm going to recuse myself, um, Ben or Bobby, which one, which one of my fellow commissioners want to take the lead on this one?
Bobby, you can.
OK.
Very good.
And let's see, who do we have here?
Sheila Grant, and I have my client, Kayla, right here.
Kayla, OK.
Very good.
So we're just here on the pledge.
We were through on the transfer.
We haven't consummated the closing yet.
This is the sort of final part of the closing.
We have a few other things to do before the closing.
But the pledge is pretty straightforward.
Upon the closing, we'll sign the promissory note.
And I believe you have a copy of the asset purchase that has an exhibit, the promissory note, in it.
Yes, we do.
We're happy to take any questions you might have.
Uh, no, it looks pretty much straightforward.
I know that you weren't able to, um, to do both things at once last time because of the way the financing and everything was going.
Um, yeah, all the paperwork looks in order.
Um, I don't have an issue with anything on here, Ben, how about yourself?
No.
Um, right.
I'm familiar with us approving the first part of this already.
So, um, this looks,
Yeah, this looks fine to me.
I don't think that I have any specific questions here.
Okay.
Let's see.
Okay, then if you'd like, Ben, why don't you give me a motion?
Yes.
And yeah, and I'll be able to second it.
Okay, so just...
So I'll make a motion to accept the application for the pledge of collateral, um, from, uh, to share, uh, suffering, uh, or Sarah Kim, um, Inc, which is, uh, doing business as Pacelli's.
Okay.
I'll second that motion.
All those in favor, raise your hand.
Aye.
Okay, the motion passes, and the pledge has been granted.
Thank you very much.
Good luck.
Good luck with your new business.
Okay.
Very good.
Thank you, Bobby Van, for doing that.
Appreciate it.
No problem.
That was an easy one.
That was all done before, and we basically
just needed to look over it and approve it, that's all.
Good, good, good.
Okay, so let's jump into the one day licenses.
As I was saying earlier, I counted up 12.
The newer ones, the last seven, I think, or eight, I'm not sure.
Those will come under all business,
I think it'll come under any and all other businesses.
Those are the, for the one days, that's the, for the Medford public library and event them studio.
So, so those two, those will go last.
So we'll, we'll start with the ones that are on the agenda.
So let's talk about the two one day licenses for Boston glory.
Who's here representing them?
I am Luke Johnson.
I think Katie Lloyd is also here.
Okay.
Thank you.
It's broken.
Yeah, that's okay.
We can hear you fine.
So tell us what happened.
As I said, I was looking at the minutes and I noticed we did approve.
So there's been a location change.
So kind of, if you don't mind, Luke, give us a little narrative, please.
Yeah, so essentially we had it stationed in the grass right next to the beer garden that is stationed in the grass right next to the stands, the bleachers.
However, that was sort of impairing the fan's experience and the vendor's ability to sell.
So we met with the Hormel Commission a week or so ago about moving the beer,
to one section of stands, so the closest section of stands to the parking lot.
They thought that would be okay, and now we had to bring it to you.
I see.
Darren, was there any kind of rough drawing or design or anything like that so we could kind of visualize?
I guess I could do Google Earth and
and see where that is.
Just a question on, same thought, Alan, is it, so to Boston Glory, to Luke or Catherine, is it, it's just still contained within the fencing of the stadium, of course?
Yes, yes.
Yes, so currently the beer garden is, it was approved for the Northeast section of the stadium and we're not,
necessarily moving the beer garden, we're extending the perimeter into the northeast section of the bleachers, which is that first section only, just so fans can enjoy a beverage and see the game at the same time, sit with their families and so forth.
Okay, so instead of like standing and having a beer, you can go and sit and have a beer.
Yes, the northern section, the grass area, it's challenging to see the game.
It's a bit distant.
So if they can just sit in that first section, they'd be able to see much better.
And is this the only section that you can sit in and have alcohol?
Yes, yes.
So our intention is to extend the perimeter.
We'll rope it off.
We'll station a volunteer to ensure that beer cannot go beyond the first section.
And everyone who purchases a beer will have a bracelet.
And our beer garden is currently managed by keys, cans, and bottles of Braintree.
So they'll be going through their whole process and monitoring all of that with us as well.
Yeah, OK.
I mean, well, you guys had this at least the past two or three years and there haven't been any problems.
And I mean, it does sound reasonable that people would be able to sit and have a, you know, sit and drink, not just have to kind of stand in a, you know, in an area and seeing as it's still contained.
I don't have any issues with it.
I think if this were to be the setup moving forward, you should just have a diagram like you had originally that shows us what the plan is so that we can see it better.
But I don't have any issue with what's being presented here.
Thank you.
We submitted the revised application and we'll be happy to include a diagram moving forward.
Yeah, yeah, just say you know it doesn't have to be by an architect or engineer just, you know, some, I have Google Earth pulled up now of home now, and, you know, it could be something as simple as that just a snapshot of that and, you know, just say okay here's where, you know, we plan to, you know, sell.
Yeah, I don't have any questions.
You guys have been stellar.
No incidents.
And how are you guys doing?
Are you gonna beat New York this time or no?
Definitely not.
We just lost to them last weekend.
Yeah, that's right.
It was June, because your home game and away game, right?
With New York, yeah, the Empire.
Okay.
All right.
Now, I guess we'll then we'll be okay then, even though you lost.
Okay.
I don't have any questions.
Bobby, Ben, anything?
Yeah.
No, I just do want to say, because we're on a meeting with other people, you know, other license, like, you know, people getting licenses, we do appreciate you guys not going in front of us before changing anything about a license we granted you in any plan.
That might sound basic.
but that is definitely the right way to do it.
So that's just appreciated.
You handled it this way, so.
Thank you.
Appreciate it.
So I'm good to make a motion to approve this.
I just wanna confirm the dates though, that's June 24th and- Can we, Ben, I'm sorry to interrupt, but can we throw a condition in there, a design or a plan, just something?
If you don't mind, yeah.
Yeah, you know, we'll approve it, but we would like you guys to actually submit a diagram of it.
Yeah, we can do that within the next couple hours.
Thank you.
Like I said, doesn't have to be an engineer or an architect, just, you know, give us the lay of the land, so to speak.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's right.
So I'll just keep going.
So it's June 21st and June 24th.
June 24th and July 21st.
July 21, yeah.
Oh yeah, sorry, I read that wrong.
July 21, right, okay.
So I'll make a motion to accept the June 24th one day license for Boston Glory.
We can do them together?
Yeah, might as well.
I will also make a motion to accept the July 21st one-day license for Boston Glory with the condition that a diagram is approved by the commission ahead of those events.
Very good.
I'll second the motion.
Thank you for the motion.
All in favor of approving the one-day licenses for Boston Glory,
On June 24th and July 21st, say aye.
Aye.
Very good.
The one day licenses are approved.
Thank you.
All right.
Best of luck.
Thank you so much.
Good luck.
Thank you.
Let's do Method Brewery.
Hello.
I actually have another question for you, which I'm happy to stay on until the end, which is not on your agenda, about another matter other than the three one-day permits I'm looking for.
Is that allowed, or is there something I need to get on?
Sure.
Yeah, if you want to hang around, sure.
Thank you.
Okay, so tell us a little about what's going on.
Tell us about the events.
Thank you for the
The design, we appreciate the help.
So give us a little narrative of what's going on.
I was going to say, I wish that was my handiwork, but sadly it was a slightly more skilled person than yours, truly.
So what we've got, we've got the Pride event coming up.
We were asked to be a beer sponsor, so we're going to do some beer pouring there, which you've got the map there.
And then we did these last year.
There was the Farmer's Market concert series as well.
I believe you should have a map for that, which is not quite as nicely put together as the one you have there.
And if not, I can certainly get one to you, and that's for two concert events planned for July 20th and August the 31st.
Okay, so help me understand.
I see one one-day license for June 25th.
Are you asking for another one, another date in addition?
So we should, yeah, so there should have been the request also for the farmers market concert series.
We're at two dates as well.
So we're looking for three.
I'm looking for that too.
Sorry, I'm checking, hold on.
Yeah, okay.
I have the 24th as well.
I have the 25th.
Yeah.
But I don't have the other one Nick is referring to.
Nick, are you talking about the farmer's market?
Yes.
The farmer's market concert series.
So 831 and 722, right?
Okay.
Hold on.
I'm going to forward it to you guys.
Okay, I just emailed it.
I see the farmers lice farmers market diagram.
So do you say you do not have the farms market diagram?
No, I do see that I do see that.
And then also just adding on with the farms market one, as per last year's request, we also have the no alcohol beyond this point signs that we put around the whole perimeter as well.
I remember two years ago there was a rogue person wandering, I think Bob you bumped into someone, with a
I think one of you did, who had a rogue beer at one stage for one of these events.
So I don't, it wasn't us, it was Winter Hill.
I'm not quite sure which one was the copper, but since then we have, yeah, we do put up the, you know, our copy on this point signs.
I think we've got four or five of them that I put around the perimeter.
Yeah, that's great.
That's great.
Okay, I received both of those from Daria.
Yeah, I haven't yet.
I have my diary.
Did you send it to Comcast or Brooklyn?
Brooklyn.
Okay.
Yeah, I don't have I don't have anything yet.
So, why don't we why don't we move forward with the 1 at hand the June 25th.
And then if I don't receive it, then I'll just recuse myself from that one, and Bobby and Ben, and you can handle that one, because I still don't see it yet.
Okay.
So June 25th, that's the Medford Pride event.
We've received the diagram.
I'm familiar with everything.
That same setup has been done before, where the beer garden is.
So yeah, so I would make a motion to accept
Um, one day license, um, for method brewing for June 25th.
Okay.
And can we, uh, can we stick in there, uh, the liability insurance?
Gary, do we have a copy of that?
Sorry, there's a chance you might not.
I am currently waiting from the same insurance company I've used for all my other permits from you guys.
I read a request for this from them two weeks ago, and I need to nudge a certain insurance company on the high street to get copies of the insurance.
Yeah, to me that's imperative that you get that.
You know, we can, we can, if my other fellow commissioners agree, we can, we can approve this, but it can be a conditional approval until we see the, you know, the insurance.
I mean, it says right on the application 200 and.
at least $250,000 of coverage, so.
Yes, so yeah, and we have the 1 million, 2 million aggregate insurance.
Yeah, yeah.
So I've given you them in the past.
I can get them to you without any question.
Thank you.
Around the corner to Pompeo and give him a kick.
Okay, thank you.
So we'll make it subject to, you know, for all of these insurances provided to us then.
Yeah, they're a little backed up on getting those three to me.
Okay.
Good.
Bobby, you want to second it or no?
Yes, I'll second it with the conditions.
All right, good.
All in favor accepting the one-day license for June 25th, Medford Pride Day, with condition upon receiving the insurance, the liability insurance, say aye.
Aye.
Very good.
That one's been approved.
Nick, and then yeah, I still don't have the other one.
So Bobby, Ben, which one of you wanna kind of take the lead on that one?
I don't have it yet.
Yeah, I've got them here, the both of them here.
Okay.
Let's see.
It's a farmer's market concert.
Is that correct, Nick?
Yes, that's correct.
And that's going to be at the Shell 2501 Mystic Valley Parkway?
Yes.
Okay.
And did we supply a sketch with that?
Or is it basically gonna be like you've done in the past there, same spot?
You did say you had the signs, no alcohol beyond this point.
It's gonna be all the same thing as you normally do over there, correct?
100% yes.
OK.
And I'll just butt in, Bob.
It is on that email.
They did provide like a Google Earth outlining it.
Oh, they did?
OK.
Yeah.
I didn't see that.
I'm sorry.
I just kind of glanced at it real quick.
OK.
Yeah.
I think I'm fine with it.
And if you want to make a motion, we can vote on it.
Yep.
So I'll make a motion to accept the, the one day license for, um, for the farmer's market concert.
So one of them is on, uh, July 20th, 2023 and second is on August 31st, 2023.
Correct.
All righty, and we'll have the insurance documents for these as well, correct?
Yes, you will.
Okay, maybe we'll throw a stipulation in there where it's contingent upon the insurance documents, Ben?
Contingent upon, yeah, that's right.
Us receiving an insurance certificate for these events prior to the first event.
Terrific.
I second that motion.
All in favor?
Aye.
Very good.
I just, I just got it myself, but that's good.
Thank you.
That's all.
That's, that's sad.
Um, Nick, your, those two one day licenses also been approved.
So I thank you.
Yeah.
And I see the, uh, the Google earth.
Uh, I can see the Google earth drawing there too.
Thank you.
Thank you for that.
Okay.
And then I'll hover until the end.
Thank you.
All right.
Let's, all right, so let's move on to the third one.
The Seminole Boxing Club, they requested a one day license.
Gentlemen, is that, Mr. Johnson, is that you guys?
Oh, you're on mute.
Can you hear me now?
Yes.
Thank you, John.
I hope it's not hot in the car.
No, we got the AC on.
We just came from another meeting.
Thank you gentlemen for coming to this commission for one day license.
Um, we, we noticed on the application, there was no address of premise, like where is the event going to take place?
But I guess more importantly, um, you're kind of new to us.
Give us a little narrative.
Tell us what's transpiring, what's going on.
Well, we want to have a one day event at Hormel stadium.
We, we, this is an event we have every year at Dillboy stadium in Somerville.
And after COVID, we haven't been able to have it for the past couple of years.
And then something just came up about, uh, their warranty on the new turf they just put down.
So Medford had, had offered us a whole ML and exchange because you know, we're trying to, this is a fundraiser we do for the boxing club, which is a nonprofit every year, but the past three years we haven't had it.
So this is why we came to Medford and this is new to me as far as the liquor license.
But, um,
I have Bruce Desmond with me, who's a politician in the city here, who's familiar with this.
I don't know if that's a good thing or a bad thing.
Yeah.
Farmer.
Mr. Desmond, farmer, sure.
That's right.
Yeah.
Very good.
So the event's going to be on August 12th, rain or shine?
Well, if it's too much rain, we're going to have to have a rain date.
Yeah.
This is all contingent upon what we get approved here and we'll go from there if I have to do another date or another venue.
If it's a rain date, we'll figure it out.
Okay.
Again, you probably heard us.
You know, in addition to the application, we always look for, you know, insurance, you know, we want to see liability insurance, heaven forbid someone falls down the, you know, the stands.
And a diagram, you know, we, you know, like I said, it doesn't have to be by an engineer or an architect, but, you know, give us the lay of the land, where's the,
you know, where is the event going to take place at Hormel so we can get an idea of where the event's taking place and where the alcohol is going to be, you know, sold or dispersed.
First of all, we usually get the ring set up around the 50 yard line.
It'll be right around the track side.
And there'll only be officials on the field.
Everyone will be in the stands.
and we decided as soon as when you come in if you're standing to the front of our mail from the outside on the where the ticket ticket booth is to the left it'll be a restricted zone for no alcohol beyond this point we got a little area down there and we'll put up signs and stuff and i'll plan on having a detail there and i plan on having a lot of volunteers
Now, is there a rain date?
Has there been a rain date picked around just in case?
Because if you need a rain date, then you gotta come back before the commission for that date.
Well, I'd say that's the 12th, how about the 19th?
Well, the thing is we can't get the boxing commission.
So if there's a rain day, it'll have to be canceled then to be to be further because the Boxing Commission is pretty busy and we can't.
Okay.
Then I guess we'll cross that bridge.
Then we'll just focus on August 12th and we'll cross our fingers.
You have great weather.
Okay.
Yes.
Thank you.
All right.
Bobby, Ben, any questions?
They're looking for wine and malt.
It looks like from Boston Glory, we know that they, as you come in on the left, right where the, before the stands are, that's where they plan on, you know, serving or selling alcohol.
So we're kind of familiar with the layout there.
I just wanted to ask you, Daniel, I noticed you're going to have approximately 900 guests.
You did speak with our police, Medford police detail desk to see if and how many details you need for that.
Well, I've spoke to a couple of people in Medford about it, but like when we used to have our events, because the Somerville police were involved in our thing,
Yeah, but he stays to volunteer for us actually, but I'm willing to pay and get in touch with the detailed people at Medford.
I haven't done it yet because this is all contingent upon the guarantee.
Right.
I haven't guaranteed anything yet, so I don't want to put the cart before the horse, but we will fulfill the requirement that need to be fulfilled.
Sure.
Okay.
Yeah, that was the only question I had where it was such a large event.
That might be a little inflamed with the 900.
I'm saying anywhere between 500 and that, because we only get like, it's tough to plan this event within like seven, six, seven weeks.
So we might coincide with another event too that's going on.
Yeah.
Well, Kiwanis, you know, they have fight nights, you know, over in Malden.
And you know, the turnout there is like four or 500 people.
So, yeah.
I kind of like the Boston Glory thing where they're gonna be setting up the alcohol near the stands and partitioning off a section of the stand so the people enjoying an alcoholic beverage can sit and watch the game or the fight or whatever.
And it actually contains them more than just having them standing around, possibly walking off.
So that might be something that we might,
even require in the future, we could take on the consideration just to keep it even more secure.
Now, you know, yeah, that's long as you know, you guys can provide us with a just a hand sketch of where you plan on putting the alcohol if you if you want to hash it around to even take a section of the seating area to section it off.
no alcohol beyond this point.
And some of the folks that are having some beverages can sit there and watch the fight versus standing in a corner.
So yeah, I'm fine with all of this.
And then the liability insurance on the day of the event, that should be added in there too.
But yeah, I'm good with this.
This is an exciting, we thank you for coming to MedFed.
Hopefully you can put it all together in a short period of time.
I just have a question.
Yeah.
How so you guys have not done didn't do alcohol at the at the other ones or you did do alcohol at the other events?
No, we haven't done it in the past.
It was just an idea of people brought up but you Yeah, you did.
Yeah, sorry.
Hold on.
No, we can hear you now.
Yeah, you're unmuted.
I have a couple of sponsors who had asked me about it.
And I said, you know, let me see what happens.
And when I talked to the guys in Medford, they said, it's a thing there.
So, you know, I said, let's, you know, let's go for it.
And maybe, you know, maybe we can do everything better.
Right, right.
No, it's a good idea.
So because it's what kind of alcohol, like how, how are you going to be, do you know how you're going to be getting alcohol over there and like, like how it's actually going to be served?
Well, I think we'd have like a pop-up tent with just beers on ice and plastic bottles with the wine and chilled, but it's just a basic tables with the tent and, you know, a licensed bartender, someone who can tell when someone's impaired not to serve them or something, you know, just to take all precautions.
Yeah, that's a must.
You know, someone's got to be TIP certified or certified.
You're absolutely right to stop, you know, if someone has too much.
Bobby, any questions from you?
No.
I noticed you're not going to be serving any alcohol until 5 p.m.
anyways, so that'll be from 5 to 9.30, correct?
Correct.
Okay.
But this does say event volunteer serving, not a licensed bartender serving.
This is what I'm reading here.
I can change that.
Like I said, that was a quick thing.
I'm new with this.
Yeah.
But I'll conform to whatever you need me to do.
Yeah, well, we can, you know what, we can add that as a condition to the approval, you know, to make sure that the servers are TIP certified or licensed to serve.
Sure.
You know, I would say, because we're not, I'm not trying to make it harder at all, actually, but because I do think it's a good idea.
It sounds like a good event.
What like the Boston Glory, which is, you know, they're the Frisbee professional Frisbee team.
They partnered up with, you know, a beer vendor to serve and then they get a certified
vendor, you know, so that works well with these types of events.
Wouldn't you guys agree, Bobby and Alan?
You know, it's something that's definitely something I'd entertain.
If I'm guaranteed to get the, you know, for that date, I definitely, that could make things a lot easier on the rest of us.
Oh, yeah.
Nick is waving his hand there.
Nick wants to say something about that.
I might be able to help you out.
I have TIP certified.
We can set everything up under Medford Brewing for you.
All right, that's something I'll definitely entertain, because like I said, we can concentrate more on the boxing.
Yeah, yeah, and rather than get bogged down with all the minutia stuff.
Yeah, Nick, wise of you to hang on, and just good luck.
Yeah.
Well, I don't have any other questions.
Bobby, Ben, if you want to make a motion with the conditions inserted in there, I think that would move it along.
OK, so licensed bartender, that's going to be our condition.
Alan.
Right.
Yeah.
Liability insurance.
Liability.
For the event.
Diagram.
That's correct.
And then, you know, they should explore because I, I don't think you're just going to put five cases of beer in your trunk and then bring it over the whole mouth.
I mean, that's a, that's a recipe for disaster.
So I would.
Yeah.
Yeah, okay.
And not to even drag that out, but like the mayor was here at one point and she was doing an event and it had liquor and we asked her the same question.
And then Nick ends up helping her out because she's got a lot to plan.
She's like, wait, I haven't maybe, you know, I do need this need.
And so that ended up working out well.
Nick, how would you reach out to Mr. Desmond or Mr. Johnson?
can you give them your phone number or email or, you know, one-stop shopping here.
I mean, I'm not steering them to you, but I'm just saying, I mean, you know, it's convenient that you're here.
We'd appreciate that if we could talk to Nick.
Absolutely.
I'll annoy Daria after and see if she can give me their email addresses.
Okay, good.
Let's go with the local guy who's done it already.
Yeah, makes sense.
Makes sense.
Okay.
So, all right, then I'm, I'm, I'm good with everything that I'm seeing here.
Sounds good.
And with those conditions, Daria, have you, you, you writing, Daria, you writing the down the conditions?
Yeah.
Okay, good.
Okay.
So we got the license bartender, the liability insurance, the diagram, and they're going to check with the PD as well.
Right.
They find out.
Okay.
Yeah.
And you guys got all that.
Mr. Desmond, you, you, I see you writing.
You got, are you with us?
Yes, sir.
I've got four points down here.
All right, cool.
The license bartender, the diagram and check with the Medford police department detail desk.
Cool, okay.
Perfect.
All right, so Bobby, you second Ben's motion?
Yes, I second Ben's motion for the August 12th.
Yep.
All right, good.
All right, so all in favor accepting the one day license on August 12th with the conditions mentioned and recorded, say aye.
Hi.
Hi, very good.
You guys are all set.
You got your one day license now.
We'll cross our fingers it doesn't rain and we'll cross our fingers you're able to put it all together.
And then we'll see you next year for the same event.
Thank you.
Okay, best of luck.
Good luck guys.
Yeah.
Okay, so that takes care of the ones on the agenda.
So wanna jump to Medford Public Library?
Alan, there's one more.
There is one more?
Yeah.
Okay, I'm sorry.
That's 321 Boston F?
Yes.
Okay, so... I don't know if you got... Oh, that was the one that there was a photo of the application, Alan.
Yeah, I don't, I don't have it.
It was, it was too big and I couldn't, I couldn't access it.
Okay.
And then I, I tried to shrink it down and it was just all blurry.
I just couldn't do anything with it.
Yeah.
So again, I'm not recusing myself.
I'll just let Ben or Bobby, whichever commissioner would like to take the lead on this one.
Well, I was able to print it out on the photograph.
So it's pretty legible, the one I got, if you want me to take the lead on it.
Yeah, please.
Okay.
Well, what it is is basically, is Patrick here?
I'm right here, yeah.
I can explain what's going on.
Yeah, Patrick, if you could just give us a little explanation of what you got going and what you're gonna be doing there, it'd be great.
So essentially all it is is my high school graduating class is celebrating their five-year reunion and they couldn't come up with a place to go.
And because of a budget, they didn't want the kids to spend money.
So they asked me if it can be hosted at my cafe.
It's not for profit at all.
It's just, they needed a place and they asked me.
So this is, it's just, I wasn't sure if I could just do this.
If it's, I don't know what the situation like BYOB is in Medford, but it's not for profit.
Like I said, it's just like a place for them to have the reunion.
So I just wanted to take the steps if needed or if necessary, or, you know, just find out exactly what needs to be done in order to have the event at the cafe.
Sure.
Well, it looks like you're heading in the right direction.
You filled out all the paperwork properly.
I noticed Dave Keene is the landlord.
He approved it, correct?
So as I was filling out the application, I gave him a call just to confirm and he said that he's more than okay with it.
Okay.
And you're gonna have a licensed bartender there and some event staff volunteers as well.
Correct.
So the event staff is the licensed bartender, correct?
Okay.
And, um, now you own the business, correct?
Um, um, the tasty cafe.
Okay.
And you have, obviously you have some liability insurance there.
You are going to need to get a, um, liquor liability, um, insurance for one day, the day of that it's gotta be at least $250,000 liability.
So what we're going to require you to do is before the event, send us a copy of that liability from your insurance company, Olicca Liability.
Okay.
I mean, other than that, it's your business.
You want to have an event like that, you're doing it the right way.
You're approaching us, you're getting your liability.
It's not that big of an event for the guests.
They're gonna be contained to the inside of your restaurant, correct?
Correct.
So it's basically, you wouldn't even need a police detail for that, it's too small.
And do you know you said what I can see in here is that you're going to be serving the liquor behind the cafe bar.
Is that like just your.
So essentially, yeah, I mean, like I said, it's just going to be as if someone came up to work.
I mean, we're a counter service cafe now.
Right.
Same exact thing.
Just everything being done behind the counter.
Yeah, so it's not accessible.
People just go and grab it and whatever.
Okay.
Okay, cool.
Yeah, I don't have a problem with this.
Mr. Chairman, Ben, you guys all set with it?
Yeah, I'm familiar with the location, you know, and so I think Patrick, just one thing is like, you guys have outdoor seating, right?
We do, we have outdoor seating like during the day, yeah.
But I mean, I don't, it's an iffy thing because this place is so contained.
Like we're gonna have to leave the chairs outside.
We don't bring them inside.
I mean, that night we could bring them to the back into like the kitchen area.
I'll make sure people don't go outside though.
I mean, there's gonna be obviously, you know, the hanging out probably for a little bit before everyone finally settles inside.
But in terms of, you know, having a setup of tables, that won't really be a thing.
Okay.
Yeah.
Cause you know, cause really what we're proving is that it's, it's inside, it's not an outside event.
Cause it just has different, like there's a whole set of different things to talk about if it is.
Right.
Now, if I, if I did like a couple of tables outside to hang out though, I mean, what are we talking to completely different rollercoaster or is it pretty straightforward?
It'd be fine if they don't take the alcohol outside.
if they want to go outside.
So that's what I was saying though.
Alcohol.
Yeah.
No alcohol outside drinking.
Cause if they want to go outside, like to fresh air or whatever, that's fine.
You don't have to remove the chairs.
It's just the, the party, the parties outside the parties on the street.
It's like, it is different.
Yeah.
Understood.
So just no liquor outside on the street or on the front of this place.
Yeah.
Yeah, right.
And yeah, I know I don't.
I don't have any more questions then.
I'm OK with it.
OK, very good.
To make a motion, let's.
Take care of this one.
OK, I'll make a motion.
And then, so I'll make a motion to accept the one day license.
This is for, um, for Patrick Pereira, um, tasty cafe Medford on, um, June 25th, 2023 from seven 30 to 11.
Yeah.
Um, or the, uh, reunion event, uh, subject to, um, insurance, proper insurance being provided to us.
Um,
and I believe that's it.
I'll second the motion.
Very good.
All in favor, say aye.
Aye.
Very good.
Patrick, you're all set.
Best of luck with the event.
Thank you.
Good luck, Patrick.
Very good.
Jerry, anything else before we jump to the others?
No.
Okay, good.
All right, then let's take on the Medford Public Library.
There's one, two, then I see three one-day requests.
Hi.
How are you?
I'm doing good.
We are kind of flying by the seat of our pants here.
We weren't fully aware that you guys were shutting down for the summer, so.
Yeah, last at least 20 years.
Hey, I'm new to this game.
Okay.
New to me.
So I'm here for Barbara Kerr.
We have three events happening this summer.
The first one is on July 22nd.
We have a concert happening at the library.
It's a two concert set for Terry Lynn Carrington.
Her and her band are coming in and they're doing a seven o'clock and an 8.30 concert.
We were going to sell beer and wine at that event.
We would have a licensed bartender.
I think on the form I said event staff or volunteer, but I think we would outsource that to someone.
I'm eyeing Medford Brewing Company.
We might be contacting you very soon.
So for that event, we have, it's an after hours event in the library.
So people are preregistered, so we know their ages and everything coming in.
We can also card at the event if that makes life easier.
So we would serve in our standard area, which is where the chapter's coffee card is in the center of the library.
Thank you for that.
We'll take them one at a time, the concert at the library.
Bobby, Ben, any questions?
We're very familiar with the events there in that beautiful new library.
I don't have any questions.
Do we have their insurance on file, Daria?
I can ask Barbara, I believe I do, but I don't remember.
Barbara says that we have it, but if we don't have it on file, we can get it.
Yeah, I bet you we do have it.
No, we do, we do, but it gets renewed every year, so I don't know.
I don't remember the expiration date.
All right, well, if it's renewed every year, then let's make that a condition that we have one for 2023.
Yeah.
So I'm good with this, so we'll take them one at a time.
So then I'll make a motion to accept the application for the one day license for the Medford Library, July 22nd, for the concert at the library from seven to 10 p.m.
Very good, subject to the copy of the liability insurance.
Very good, okay.
I'll second.
Very good.
Thank you, Bobby.
All in favor, accepting the one day license for July 22nd, subject to receiving a revised liability insurance policy, say aye.
Aye.
Very good.
Okay, that one's done.
Let's do August 17th.
Yeah.
So tell us a little about that.
It says for
a type of event that says class.
So wine class, whiskey class, what type of a class?
So it's a mixed beverages class.
So we looked for, it's Boston Shaker, they're in Somerville and they do these classes in house normally.
And we asked them to come out and do one using Medford Rum because we wanted to do a Medford historical drinking class.
It is a,
to drink lesson.
They're gonna do two different drinks and how to make them.
We have a max of 12 individuals who would be allowed to be in this class.
I will be present to ID, but we also, it's an advanced registration.
So they're gonna have to come in in advance and register with us so we can make sure everyone's over 21.
So it's a fairly small group.
There's a max of how much we're using and
both library staff will be present and also the Boston Shaker group is licensed bartenders.
Yeah, yeah.
Very good.
Boston Shaker.
Yeah.
And so there'll be two drinks, so they'll probably be doing little flights.
Okay, good.
Okay, I don't have any questions.
Bobby, any questions from you?
No, I'm good with it.
All alcohol, that's fine.
That was on that one, so yeah, that event is fine.
Good.
Okay.
Either commissioner would like to make a motion?
I'll make a motion to accept one day for the office.
I'll second the motion.
Very good, thank you.
All in favor accepting the one day license for August 17th for the mixed beverage class, say aye.
Aye.
Aye, very good, thank you.
That one's all set.
All right, so the final one is August 27th and just listening to the conversation here, I am gonna change it up a little.
I was thinking of having it out on the patio, but it sounds like that's more of a nightmare than it's
worth.
So what we can do again is standard service inside the library in the in the cafe space.
This event is again an off hours event.
It's on a Sunday when we're not normally open.
It's from one to four o'clock.
And we are doing a maker fair.
So we are doing a lot of teaching people how to make different things.
And we'll have a bunch of different classes.
It is a program that is specifically for adults.
But it is not advanced registration.
So people will be kind of
meandering in and out.
So for that event, we would again be looking to hire maybe Medford Brewing or some other outside vendor to just maintain it.
And we'd set it up kind of like a beer garden where folks could pop into a restricted space in the library that
they could have their beverage in and then they would have to leave their beverage there before heading out and I don't know, learning how to make a birdhouse or whatever they're doing that day.
Okay.
Very good.
Sam, can I ask you a question?
Yeah.
You had mentioned that you were going to approach us for the patio.
Is the patio enclosed?
It is not.
Yeah, it's not.
I was going to say, if it was enclosed, then it shouldn't be a problem.
But where it's not enclosed, that's, yeah.
And it's right on the street.
So if you just like that public drinking party, if you guys ever want to do it, the library doesn't sound like that's a smart game.
Sorry about that.
Yeah, no worries.
OK, so event inside.
My fellow commissioners, which one you wanna make a motion?
I can go ahead and make the motion if you like.
Okay, please.
I'll make a motion to grant a one-day license for the Medford Public Library for the Maker Faire on August 27th, 23, from 1 to 4 p.m.
Very good.
Ben, you want a second?
Very good, thank you.
All in favor accepting the, or approving the one day license for August 27th for the Medford Public Library, say aye.
Aye.
Aye, very good.
Ben?
Aye.
Very good, thank you.
Sam, you're all set.
You had the trifecta today, so.
All right, well thank you, and I'll make sure you guys get a copy of our current insurance if we don't have it on file, and thank you for seeing me very last minute.
Yeah, thank you.
Okay.
Yep.
Yeah.
Okay, so event them studios I think that's the last of it.
Jerry you're checking your watch are we running out of zoom time.
No.
Okay.
Running.
My phone keeps raining.
One, two, three, four.
Brian, I think you're in for five.
Let's start with the July 15th event.
If you don't mind telling us what that's about.
Absolutely.
So yeah, we did put in for five.
We've had a lot of inquiries about the space and just being able to use it.
And we kind of tried to go with the ones that
they were able to confirm clients or events that we were doing, able to confirm that they were going to do it for sure.
The July 15th, it's a game night, basically.
We have a lot of games on site.
And basically one of the main games that they want to feature is a video game tournament, a FIFA video game tournament.
So one of our employees is actually, he's run some of these events before.
So we're going to have, we were looking to host an event for that.
kind of have like an annual video game slash game day, you know.
Okay.
Can I ask you a quick question?
Yep.
Ryan, when these games, video games and stuff, none of the prizes for the winners are going to be free alcohol, correct?
No.
Okay.
That's kind of a no-no.
No, absolutely no.
Yeah, I'm very aware of that.
No, it's a ticketed event, and then proceeds go back to the players.
Okay, very good.
Very good.
I did set the layout
And I recall from our last meeting, just to indicate that kitchenette area is that sectioned off area, which is where the alcohol is served, that service counter, it's our ID check too.
So either stamped, sticker or double band at that point, that's what we did for the last event.
I just wanted to kind of note that.
Yeah, no, thank you for that.
Excuse me, we appreciate the diagram and we can actually see how it's a very controlled environment.
So thank you for that.
We'll be providing the spirit, so we'll be providing the alcohol.
We have different distributors that we've used in the past.
I can check with Jen which one we used last time.
It wasn't Kraft.
It might have been Kraft.
But I can confirm that with Jen who pulled on from there.
But I think it was Kraft distributors last time.
All right, so we'll just make a note.
Licensed bartenders, so they're certified.
Let's see.
Food will be served.
I don't have any questions.
Bobby, Ben?
All right.
Let's take this one.
A motion, please.
Yeah, you want to do them all in one or you want to do them at the same time?
All right.
Let's keep moving and then we'll do them all at once.
We'll make the motion.
All right.
So Brian, the 28th, July 28th, tell us a little about that event.
Yep.
So it is the same as our September 8th.
So we try to quarterly run a change out of the local artists that we feature, one or two typically in the space.
And so we do an opening for them.
And essentially it's an opportunity for them to invite family, friends, people in the public, to be able to come see their art and kind of create a great, a good atmosphere for them, you know, different lighting, food, beverages.
And so basically it's just, it's an art opening.
Yeah.
I remember from last time, I didn't realize you would be, you would be changing it out quarterly.
I didn't realize that.
I think that's a good time.
I, I, I've done some of these in the past and typically,
So two reasons is that the longer you hold on to somebody's art, the less it gets to be out there in other places, right?
So I think typically the average run is about six to eight weeks, something like that.
And then you can do a closing if you wish, or just change it out.
But it gives people an opportunity to, also people looking to see the art or buy the art, if you give,
the community too much time to go see it, they don't see it.
They keep putting it off.
If you tighten it up a little bit, then you tend to have more eyes on it.
Sure.
Very good.
We get that one in July 28th.
Let's jump to August 2nd.
Foundation fundraiser.
Yep.
Sasaki Foundation is a foundation that supports local design grants.
And they inquired about utilizing our space as a fundraising space.
So they do a lot for the communities in Boston and around.
So I think it's a really good opportunity for us to be able to kind of host them there.
And again, we're getting a lot of in there, I guess I can follow up, you know, after we go through these quickly, we are getting a good amount of requests for these and I don't
Um, I'm not sure how to respond for the next few months.
Um, I think the get around is basically it has to be catered.
Um, but, um, I don't want to tell local nonprofits and stuff.
We can't host their event because we can't, if they really want to do alcohol or something, but for this one, um, uh, they've confirmed the date.
And, um, I think, I think this is exactly what we're trying to do is get a place to do these things.
Yeah, no, you're giving them a venue.
It's perfect.
Just keep in mind that the city does have a rule where we only allow any entity 31 day licenses in a calendar year.
Correct.
Kind of keep that in mind.
Yeah, absolutely.
Because I can see you the way you're going, you could quickly get to that to that ceiling.
Yeah, our goals, honestly, for it.
It's kind of our peak season.
Typically, just June has been insane because most of our events are off site.
Like, you know, we had the Pride event in Boston on Saturday.
We had the Taste of Somerville.
So we did all the ticketing and we were part of that committee for that.
And so then we had a Pride event in Somerville, another one, and then
I don't know.
So we have a lot, but most of our events are offsite.
So it just tends to be that the summer is busier.
Sure.
Word of poll licenses, you know, uh, spring, summer, fall, winter.
It doesn't really happen.
Okay.
All right.
Let's jump to, uh, August 12th, a little local music showcase.
Tell us a little about that.
Uh, same idea is, you know, typically on these, we feature one or two singer songwriters.
a few vendors, and then also, because we run a local business support program called Common Roots, we actually met Nick, we actually, one of our meetings we did was actually at Medford Brewery, and we had Max running around like a crazy person, he didn't know how to take it.
But we, you know, we like to, you know, give kind of like the trifecta of, you know, it's kind of like, so it's just these showcases, you know, some music, some art,
local business and some vendors or something.
Okay.
30, 40 guests, good.
Let's look at the last one.
Our gallery opening.
That is just the next quarter.
Yeah, that's the next quarter.
We know what that one is.
Very good.
Thank you, Brian, for giving us a little narrative.
I told you before I was impressed with the whole concept and I hope you just hit it out of the park with that whole entity.
Thank you.
Yeah.
You guys, do you have two months off?
So there's no excuse to not come by and visit us over there.
So the podcast station is fine, is really running Medford bites has been there a few times.
Um, so, uh, we did a photo shoot yesterday for somebody that wanted to create some product for a 70th birthday party.
So really interchangeable and it's, um,
It's exciting, but again, I want to make sure we do it right.
Sure.
Is your podcast studio cheaper than Staples Connection over there in Somerville?
Yeah.
It's like half the prices.
That's outrageous.
Everybody's like a dollar a minute.
And I'm like, yeah, a dollar, a dollar a minute.
OK.
So we're like twenty five thirty.
But if you book it like a bunch of it, we just want people in there because, you know, we're not just
We do different things, right?
So if somebody comes in for one thing, they might see that we do other things, so.
That's right.
Good.
Well, thank you.
Ben, Bobby, questions, concerns, anything?
No.
No, none from me.
All right.
All right, so which commissioner wants to take on the one-day licenses?
We'll do them all in one shot.
I can do it.
All right.
All right, so there's five of them.
So I'm gonna make a motion to accept the one day alcohol licenses for Brian of Event Them.
The dates are Saturday, July 15th, video game competition.
Friday, July 28th, art gallery exhibit opening.
Wednesday, August 2nd, for a foundation fundraiser.
Saturday, August 12th for a local music showcase, and Friday, September 8th for an art gallery opening.
Perfect.
Very good.
I second the motion.
Thank you for the motion.
All in favor of accepting the five one-day license applications for approval, say aye.
Aye.
Very good.
Brian, you're all set.
Best of luck with all five events.
Thank you.
I do have an additional question, but I know Nick did first, so I don't want to take any more of your time, but I'm willing to pass it off to Nick.
All right.
Nick, you're on mute.
What's on your mind?
What's up?
All right.
So you shouldn't have done that, Brian.
I might take a bit longer than planned.
But thank you for your chivalry.
So I met with you guys a couple of months ago about the alteration in premises for Medford Brewing to basically for outdoor dining and consumption.
And we went through everything the ABCC requested.
We put the application with them to start with.
We then did all the meetings for abutters and all that fun.
Had the meeting, everything was approved and done.
That package then went back to the ABCC.
I met with the agent for the ABCC two weeks ago.
who looked at what we were doing and I showed him our plan and everything and he said everything looks great and he said yep it's all good in our side.
Then he said but the ABCC is very backed up to the tune of about six to eight weeks right now.
Wow.
And he said so
He said there's no issues they have, it's just he puts a packet together and then the head of the ABCC does the final sign off.
So I said, okay, well, that's a bit painful, but thank you.
And then I mentioned, well, there's the outdoor dining ordinances going on that Governor Healey re-signed for 2023.
where obviously for restaurants to then serve food and alcohol for people to dine outside.
So I asked him, I said, well, considering this is now in place, would it be possible for me to, for Metro Green to jump on the bandwagon of the outdoor dining for the outdoor consumption whilst we're waiting for their approval?
And his comment was, if Medford is OK with it, then yes, they would be OK with it.
So perhaps my question is, is there a way that we would, on a temporary basis,
able to serve and have people consume on our extended outdoor space.
Having already had the nod from you guys before the ABCC gives their final stamp on the permanent because the
Outdoor dining is the annual temporary versus what we've got in which is a permanent change.
And so would we be able to jump on that bandwagon so we can finally let people into our little patio?
Yeah, yeah.
You know, we, we have discovered that we we can grant, you know, the, the alteration of premises, we can grant license for you to serve alcohol outside.
Okay.
But we've also discovered that the city has developed a new group on outdoor dining.
team that will oversee all of this.
And so we were told that, yeah, you know, you have, you know, anyone who wants to serve outside, they come before you, you guys grant the okay, but then they have to go before the outdoor dining
group or team.
So I think that's the last I heard of it.
I see Daria is trying to get my attention.
Daria, am I just saying something old news or is there... No, so you're correct.
So I did reach out to Yvette last week.
I heard from her on Thursday.
So what
I bet she's part of community development office, and she's the one that actually sends out the applications around.
I know because I'm on it as well.
Okay, is it called the outdoor dining group or what?
What exactly is the entity that's overseeing this?
Well, it's a couple departments.
It's traffic.
It's police department.
It's fire department.
It's building department.
It's me.
I think Lisa too from the mayor's office is on it and community development office.
There's a couple people that are involved.
So what Yvette thought and what we found on ABCC website, Bobby and I actually looked over yesterday.
Bobby mentioned it to me while I called him about something else.
that had to do with his stipend, nothing to do with the actual stuff.
What was I going with this?
And Yvette was saying that because they're private property, they don't need to follow any guidelines that the city has, like putting out barriers and all of that stuff.
But according to ABCC, it doesn't disclarify if you're on private property or not.
You still have to make sure that the space is confided, I guess, so where you can't walk out with the alcohol and the city still has to approve it.
So once I sent it to Yvette, she just got back to me this morning and she said that,
Based on your email met for brewing would need to meet ABCC requirements by providing some sort of, you know, barrier, whether that's rope and cone whatever.
And if they would like the city to provide barriers, then they will just need to undergo the R.9 interview process and meet our insurance requirements for the seating area.
But she said, however, city barriers are not required.
So she was gonna let Nick know, but again, that was this morning, earlier this morning.
So I think,
The whole point is that to make sure that even though it's on private property, that the rules are still being followed because it's the process for basically us as well, because we're, you know, sit on the board.
Very well.
Is that being like the go to person for this type of.
She's actually so she's actually.
she got, um, she's moving.
So she's getting out of the job, uh, to where she's moving.
So she's kind of finishing up.
So I think there's going to be somebody else next year.
Um, so that's why it's kind of like, it's taking us some time because it's me and her just going via email, not really like where I could before, you know, go visit her.
She could visit me.
So it would be a lot faster.
Um, and again, from what city maybe fought, I don't know that we didn't
because you own private property, you can just kind of not do as you please, but you don't have to go through all the jumps.
If that makes sense.
So.
But the ABCC does specifically lay out what should be done, whether it's private property or public property.
Yeah, Bobby, if you want to chip in, because I know you're the one that actually
did the research, or caught it, I should say.
I did.
I researched it quite a bit, Nick.
And the way that I can see it is that you came before us for a alteration of premise, and we granted it.
And that was for permanent.
And it's being processed now.
The ABCC came out and inspected it.
And what he told you was correct, that you can go on the seasonal outdoor dining rules.
And because basically it's the same application, only you don't pay the fee.
So we already granted that.
You're good by us.
The only thing you have to do is follow the ABCC rules.
The ABCC rules do state that you have to have some sort of a fence, either a fence, a barricade, a rope, anything just to contain the people from your establishment to that area.
And the only way they can enter that area or exit that area is through your establishment.
It also prevents pedestrians from wandering in to that area.
It just basically, hey, don't go beyond this point.
That's all it is.
And that's really the only requirement that you need.
Yeah, I happen to, I walk around the whole city and I happened to walk by your place the other day and I saw the blocks and the boards and everything.
And technically that's fine.
You're containing your customers to that area.
And, you know- Bobby, I get that.
Yeah, I saw it too, I drove by, but it's still,
this this event or there's still this commission or group of people that have to don't they have to sign off on it?
Well, you know what they're saying?
Because sorry, I don't mean to interrupt.
That's where that's where I was confused, too.
But because it's private property, technically, the city does not unless they requesting a barrier.
So and I think
I don't know anybody else applied this year that had the same, you know, private property type of thing.
I don't have that many restaurants that have liquor that are on private property.
but you're not required to have a city barrier.
So it's basically, you know, you put up your own containment system, that should be fine.
It's been granted.
It was granted when, you know, we put the application in and you submitted it to the ABCC.
So, you know, I say you're good to go as long as the people are contained.
The only way they can get in and out of there is through your establishment.
But I think Daria touched on it if if they request city assets or resources then that's when the city would have a say in it.
Is that what you're kind of alluding to?
From what I understand yeah unless it's on public property because if it's public property then it's you have to kind of
liability reasons, right?
Okay.
But if it's private, it's just half from what I read, from what I understand, it just has to be contained.
Right, in which Nick has done.
So exactly.
Yeah, I I'm good with that, too.
Ben, what do you your thoughts on this?
Yeah, it seems like it would hold them up all summer.
If you go to BCC, we wait on him.
And that's the prime time.
And I don't know, I don't want to hold this business up from
You know, making more money and having clients outside something we've already approved.
Yeah, no, I agree.
I agree.
Um, I don't know.
Can we put in the record that we we've kind of reviewed next concerns and the way we're interpreting
uh, ABCZ rules in the city rules that we're, we're okay that we've given him the green light to, to move forward as long as it's contained in the only way in and out is through the, through the establishment.
Nick, does that sound logical?
That's wonderful.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
So, um, one of you want to make a motion or just, uh, or we just kind of agree that's what we're going to do.
PB, David Ensign — Herndon, continue.
Nick, that's good.
Can I jump to Brian, or do you need to have a follow up?
No, just say thank you very much.
Enjoy your summer.
And I'll see you next year, probably for the usual one day licenses.
All right.
Take care.
Brian, you've been very patient.
Thank you.
What's on your mind?
What's up?
I like listening to this stuff, too.
educational it's it is educational yeah you know better for the next time anyways yeah double thumbs up for daria today too i know she got thrown a lot and i appreciate her uh get me on this and get this done so i want to acknowledge that first um i just honestly we're we're um i just want to make sure that you know moving forward through the next few months that
I address any inquiries properly.
For example, we had a group from, I think it was First Baptist Church on Salem Street, they wanted to do a birthday party.
I said, that's great, that's fine, we can host you, we can make it happen.
And I said, but I just, one thing to be aware of is I just don't think we can do alcohol.
And they're like, well, it's a private event, right?
And I said, yeah, but I said,
But we're still the host.
So I think if you wanted to do that, it would have to be catered.
You'd have to have it catered.
And I think based on their budget and their concerns, they just wanted to make sandwiches and do stuff like that.
And so I think in that case, I think if they decide to move forward, then that's fine.
I think they're going to be fine with that.
I don't think it's a priority.
But just to go back, we're not trying to be a bar.
every event we do is alcohol.
That is not intentions.
But at the same time, if there is another fundraising thing, if something comes around, I don't want to squash that potential without knowing exactly what a potential prop, like what I should do.
And I think my assumption is the only way is that from now and through mid-September is to it has to be privately catered.
And I just wanted to verify that, know exactly what I need to tell them.
Is that why we have a cap on it?
That's why we have a maximum amount of one day licenses.
Absolutely.
Exactly.
And I don't intend on, we don't intend on going above that or you can, but we're not trying to be, it's just the summer tends to be,
peak season.
This is when people want to get together and do stuff.
So, um, I want to make sure I say that we can't, we can't service alcohol for any of these upcoming events or it needs to be privately catered or if there's anything else, I just want to have an exact answer if we do get inquiries.
Well, you know, you mentioned, uh, if I made through the chair, you mentioned that, um,
You mentioned a caterer, a catered event.
There are caterers out there that have state licenses and they do not need an approval through us.
They have to notify our commission and the police chief at least 48 hours beforehand to let us know that this event is going on in the city.
But these caterers, they bring in all their own alcohol,
they bring in all their own food, they transport all the alcohol, everything's done all above board.
And, you know, it's a smart move on your end, because they take all the liability.
And it's the same thing with Nick from Medford Brewing.
I mean, if you run out of 31 day licenses, and you're having a fairly large event, it might be
advantageous for yourself to hire someone like Nick Winterhill or whomever to do these events.
And they don't go against your 31 day licenses being licensed under them.
But you're right.
And if those folks, you know, did want to have alcohol and use your place, then they'd have, you'd have to apply for the one day license and you'd have to have liability and everything.
So, you know, that's kind of the way that works.
So, basically, you have to get a license from us for anything, except have it catered.
If you're having it catered by a licensed caterer through the ABCC, you don't need to come through us.
Yes.
So if that happens, actually, Bobby, if there's a licensed caterer, they've already we're have no we've no interaction with that.
That's why they have a catering license.
That's right.
But then I think, Brian, could the real question be what it's like you mentioned the Baptist church, you were saying, like if they wanted to serve wine, but they were going to have sandwiches, would that work?
Is that kind of what you were hinting around at?
Well, no, it's more that I didn't apply for a license for that event.
It's they asked for a date in August, but they couldn't confirm that day.
I didn't want to come to the board and say, yeah, I'm going to need alcohol for this event.
It gets approved and then they change their mind.
So it was kind of I said, if you, you know, anybody who's inquired that has gone beyond just step one, I said,
we reached out and said, you know, if it is an event that you are interested in having alcohol, we need to know by Tuesday, the yesterday.
So they, we had a hard date that we need to know because if we were going to have to put any last minute applications in for it, that it has to be done.
And that goes through September.
And so these are the ones that, you know, we were able to internally lock in or were inquiries.
So that means that for the,
for the duration from now until mid-September, if we are to serve alcohol, my understanding is that it has to be through a private caterer because we cannot pull any additional license respectfully during the seasonal break, no?
Correct, correct.
And then when we come back, then we're back in play.
Yeah, exactly.
And I just wanted to have a clarification on that.
And can you just lastly,
When it comes to private event, is that like my family and I like hanging out in the office, not the office, like in the middle room?
Does that mean I can crack a beer or does that mean I can't?
Or what is the difference between like my daughter, you know, she had her first birthday.
We had a little party there and stuff like that.
And, you know, no big deal.
But I was kind of like, would this be,
private thing?
Does this count as alcohol?
Does it not count as alcohol?
Like, you know, I mean, I wasn't sure.
You know, again, the church event is technically a private event, but it's a public.
It's a public thing also.
Yeah, so it's kind of like, I just gotta get it right, and I gotta make sure that I'm confident in my answer.
Bobby, you were gonna say, a family event's a family event, but go ahead.
I mean, something like that, that you're close to the public, you're having your daughter's birthday party, you've got only invited guests, you wanna have a couple adult beverages, no one's gonna bother you, just as long as you keep an eye on it and make sure the kids aren't having them either.
Yeah, like you would in your house.
Yeah, same thing.
Yeah, Bobby's Bobby's right.
A family event is a family event.
It's, it's when you introduce the outside world into the public, then it gets different.
But yeah, a family event is fine.
And so that church event counts as a public event, even though it's Yeah, it's a it's an outdoor outside entity.
It's not your family, unless you're saying the church is my family.
You know, no,
So I understand.
Yeah.
So if it's an outside entity, not directly related to my entity, I suppose.
Okay.
That's one way to look at it.
Correct.
Yeah.
Just want a clarification.
Great.
Okay.
Anything else on your mind?
No.
You guys do anything?
Podcasting?
Go check out some local art?
And you said 15 cents.
Is that what you were saying?
How much did you say?
$0.15 for what?
For the art?
Brian, thank you for your time.
Any other questions, you can always reach out.
We didn't forget you either on your questions that you submitted.
We're working on them.
We're just about done.
Daria will send you out something in writing just to, you know, it basically we went over almost everything today, but there was a couple of other things.
Yeah, we'll get it out to you.
I appreciate it.
And it's extensive.
It's just I, um, I think what it really comes down to is, is that it's easier for me to have clarity so I can be clear with other people.
Because, you know, it's not he said, she said type of thing.
It's like, this is what it is, this is why.
You know, A, B. And it just saves people time, and I think, you know, and it keeps things safe, and it prevents problems down the line.
And I've been through enough to, you know, I wanna.
So, again, I appreciate that.
No super rush.
I don't wanna anticipate any issues with any of our events, but definitely not anything alarming.
Okay, cool.
All right, sir.
Thank you.
All right, everyone.
Thank you all.
All right.
Bye-bye.
Gary, anything else under any and all other business?
That was a boatload there between Medford Public Library and Event Them Studios.
I believe that was it.
I hope that was it.
I think that was it.
Okay.
Um, I do want to, you know, Penelope thought that she might want to, um, be our go-to with the ABCC about, uh, classes.
Um, but, um, a couple of things I, I want this commission to get back together so we can wrap up, um, vetting the guidelines.
So we need to.
So we need to do that.
And then I don't want Ralph to think we forgot about him because I am still interested in his offer to train, regulate the regulators.
I forget what he was calling the training, the regulators, which is us.
So, you know, now that we're going to be, we won't have hearings the next two months, we can find time.
I'm not going away, I'm staying in class.
I don't know about you, your schedules, but let's, I'll reach out to you guys, because like I said, I do want to have another special meeting so we can wrap up the ordinances and the guidelines.
So we got to tackle that first and be done with it.
Bobby, okay?
Yeah, sounds great.
All right.
Daria, anything on your mind, any questions?
Um, no, I think we resolved the big one that was laying on me heavy with which was meant for brewing.
Yeah.
That's why I just wanted to make sure that everybody was okay with whatever because I don't want to say yes to something and then for it to be like, well, Darius said that's fine.
Yeah, and then it blows up.
No, I, I think you kind of hit it on the head if we, if he's using public assets or city assets, then, you know, it's like, wait a minute, you know, now, things have to get a little more scrutinized, but where it's all private, and as long as he's following the rules.
Yeah, but I don't think he was, I think the problem was that he didn't have to, like, follow the guidelines, which is
you know, secluding the area.
So I don't know if that was his plan or not initially.
So that was, I think the problem is that to make sure that that gets secluded, that's what Bobby pointed out to me.
Cause again, and I called him about something else yesterday that had nothing to do.
Is it all right if I sign off?
Okay.
All right.
Thanks Ben.
Talk soon everybody.
Thank you.
So it had nothing to do with Medford Bruin, but then, um,
Yeah, I don't remember, but anyways, sorry.
My head is kind of like all over the place.
I don't know about something else.
And then we started talking about that.
And that's when Bobby was like, oh, I went over the rules and regulations.
And he's like, it doesn't state anything about private or public.
So it doesn't matter.
So it just has to be, you know, roped off.
So I'm not sure if that's what he was doing.
So I just kind of wanted to let Yvette know.
So this way, not just much for Bruin, but anybody that comes in front of,
you know, that committee.
We also make sure that that's done because it is ABCC rules.
So that's kind of involve us as well.
So I just want to make sure we're aware.
And, you know, not just we're aware and don't kind of say anything.
So that's all.
That's all.
The ABCC, where is it?
Guideline extension of premise to patio and outdoor areas.
Number three, it says the premise must be enclosed by a fence rope or other means to prevent access from public walkway.
I believe in the temporary one, it states the same thing, only it states all, meaning,
whether your private property, public property, you know, any of that stuff.
And it's it's just basically you got to have it sectioned off bottom line.
Yeah.
And I don't know.
I don't want to use the city's assets to use his own.
Yeah.
We don't want a permanent anyways when he gets his.
But my understanding is that if he uses city assets, then he opens himself up to the outdoor dining commission or committee or group.
Yes.
So my concern was more of from reading that, my concern was that because it's a private property, city kind of left it.
Not left it, but you know what I mean, like they just kind of were like, you're doing on private property.
Just make sure it's safe you follow the ABCC rules.
Yeah, so ABCC kind of just says you want to make you still the city still needs to make sure that it's roped off, and there's no public access to the actual outdoor dining because that's where it serves.
So I think that's where I wanted to make sure that we cover us as a city and us as a commission.
And that's just, we need to make sure that this happens with everybody else who ever applies in the future.
Just to make sure that even though it's private property, we're still making sure that they're roping it off or whatever, and nobody else has access besides the patrons.
That's right.
Because I remember when we back in pre COVID when we toured
night shift in Everett, that clearly was private property.
And all they had was like, like what you see in a bank, you know, the posts with the rope.
That's kind of all they had because it was private property.
And yeah, you know, they had a rope and posts, you know, and that's what they were using to secure that area.
And the only way you could get in that area was to go in the establishment and go out through the side door into that area.
So I do remember that.
Okay, good.
All right, then we've been here long enough.
Daria, Bobby, thank you for your time.
Appreciate it.
We covered a lot of ground.
There was a lot there.
I mean, it was 12 or 14 one-day licenses.
I thank you for putting in the time and effort today.
All right.
Meeting adjourned.
I'm making the motion.
Bobby, second my motion and so we can go.
All right.
Thank you, everyone.
Thank you, guys.
Have a great fall.
Bye-bye.