Welcome to the sixth edition of the Mustang Report. I'm Victoria Rasche. I'm Jocelyn McCarthy. I'm Katrina Rasche. And this week, we'll be showing you a video from the Crystal Campbell Peace Garden. And we'll be introducing the new guidance counselor, Mr. Klein. We will be showing you clips of the spirit week last week. Also clips of the girls, boys, and soccer team, and the girls volleyball team senior night. And a flash forward to next week, we will be covering the faculty football game. Stay tuned.
Congratulations to three members of the Mustang Report, Gigi Braga, Victoria Rasche, and Katrina Rasche. They have won first place with the MIAA Sportsmanship Award. They will be traveling to Gillette Stadium in November to show their award-winning video at Patriot's Place. Now, here's our video. The runners were through. The first bomb explodes just a few yards from the finish line.
A big part of Crystal's life was Medford High School and the activities that she participated in with the band and softball at Medford High. She loved the team and the girls have been loyal to her from day one.
They have spent a lot of time raising money for scholarships so that children can continue after high school on to their college career. They have put together this tournament in memory of Crystal. When we first heard about the tragedy, we were shocked and felt like it was our obligation, as Crystal's fellow Mustangs and softball members, to do something for her legacy. So we decided to dedicate our softball season to carry on her spirit, not only in our hearts, but also in our community.
Mustangs on three. One, two, three. Mustangs! The Crystal Campbell Scholarship is awarded every year to a deserving Medford High School senior who exemplifies the qualities of school spirit, sportsmanship, and community service.
Crystal Campbell's legacy will live on through the annual softball tournament, the Medford Strong t-shirts, and the scholarship fund throughout Medford.
do
you
so
Nice. What was your role in C3 Day? So C3 Day, that was like my first big project at Medford High School, and I kind of created the idea for what the seniors were going to do when they were off campus. So I created the idea, created the title, and then really researched all the different opportunities that seniors were going to have. And really, I think my biggest role was really encouraging them to go big and make this a really meaningful day for them that's going to have an impact on what they do in the future.
Do you and the guidance counselors have any future plans for the students? Future plans for the students? Yeah, I think, I've been super impressed with the guidance department being new here and I think the goal is to really help students to understand what do they want their future goals to be, what do they want in the long term for themselves and their families, and then really backward planning with them so if you have this goal in the long term,
What do you have to be doing five years from now? What do you have to be doing three years from now, one year? What do you have to be doing a week from now? What do you have to be doing tomorrow to help you reach your long-term goals? Awesome. What do you think your strongest asset is at Medford High School?
I'm pretty high energy. I like really working with a variety of students and I think just being creative with what we can do here. I'd actually say my biggest strength is I've been incredibly impressed with the population of faculty and students at Medford High School.
If there's something strange in your neighborhood Who you gonna call? Ghostbusters! If there's something weird and it don't look good
Yeah
Happy Halloween, Medford High! For some of you seniors, we have a special poem because you have another holiday this weekend. A Halloween haiku written by Cullen Burke. The scariest day, it is called deadline day. It is Halloween. Have a jawful Halloween, Medford High!
I can't feel you, who you gonna call?