Hi, guys.
Thanks for coming today.
We're going to call to order.
I'm going to do a quick roll call.
Kayla Lesson?
Present.
Roberta Cameron?
Here.
Carrie Weaver?
Penny Taylor?
Present.
Lisa Sun?
and Lisa Ann Davidson present.
The next item on the agenda are the minutes, approving of the minutes.
Did everybody get a chance to read the October and November minutes that Aditi sent?
And if there are no edits to the meeting minutes, excuse me, from October 2nd, 2024, I'd like to request a motion to approve the minutes.
So moved.
Second.
And then we'll do a roll call for a vote.
We've got Kayla.
Aye.
Roberta made the motion.
Penny.
Aye.
Lisa made, seconded, and I also approve.
And let's see.
If there are no edits to the minute meetings for November 6, I would like to make a request to a motion to approve the minutes.
So moved.
Second.
Okay, we'll call for approving.
Kayla?
Aye.
Roberta made the motion.
Penelope seconded it.
Lisa?
Aye.
And Lisa-Ann?
Both minutes have been approved.
Next item on the agenda is the working groups, and we've got the Declaration of Trust.
The Declaration of Trust is ready to be signed by all members.
However, since tonight's meeting is a virtual one, I would like to postpone the execution of the Declaration of Trust to the next meeting in January.
Do we need a vote on that?
I don't think so.
I don't think so either.
And then the second, the next is the action plan committee and Roberta.
So, um, yeah, I will talk through the data that I sent to everyone.
Um, so the action plan committee has been working on gathering background data on housing needs and, um, housing conditions in the city that will inform the action plan.
And in addition, we've been preparing to host some stakeholder, some, um,
focus groups with stakeholders to learn more about their perception of housing needs and priorities in the city.
So,
I will talk more about the stakeholder meetings after I first just give a rundown of what we've learned about the data.
I prepared a two-page summary of what we've learned so far, and that's what was submitted in the meeting packet.
And I would love if you could all indulge me in running through a presentation that we prepared that we're going to use for the stakeholder groups as well as the
a later public meeting or a series of public meetings in the spring.
However, we do this after the new year.
So this just gives us a chance to rehearse and learn, get some feedback from you if there's some changes that we need to make.
I'll give Kerry.
Roberta, sorry to intervene.
I think Kerry Weaver has joined us.
I'll wait a moment.
And do I have the ability to share the screen?
Yes, I'll make you the co-host in a minute.
I think you can now share the screen.
And then I'm going to turn this into a slideshow if I can see the screen.
There we are.
From the beginning.
Okay.
So just click through slides that don't have data.
Introductory slides about the Affordable Housing Trust and the purpose of the meetings.
So the data highlights, the first thing that we looked at is who actually lives in Medford.
And we learned some interesting things.
The population of Medford has grown slightly in the last decade between 2010 and 2020, but most significantly, all of that growth occurred in young adults between the ages, sorry, I have to,
I'm going to minimize you all on my screen.
Between the ages of, I think, 20 and 35, we've gained over 4,000 young adults in that age cohort, while all of the other age groups, younger, older, stayed the same, roughly, or declined slightly over this period.
So as you might expect with this change in population, we're seeing more non-family households, which is how the census would describe households with roommates.
By the way, I meant to say that the picture on the left here may or may not be an actual photo of my next door neighbors who moved in a few months ago.
The population is also gaining.
We have a higher proportion of people of color and people who have immigrated to this area, which may be because Medford is still sadly relatively affordable compared with other communities as much as it is feeling unaffordable to many of us.
And another interesting thing that I noticed is a smaller proportion of people with disabilities in Medford, which could be accounted for because of the age of our housing stock and the lack of accessible housing stock.
So, sorry, I'm trying to go to the next page.
So then we looked at what does Medford's housing look like?
And on the screen, you see a chart to orient you as to what this chart is telling us.
The bars represent the amount of housing that was built in each time period shown at the bottom.
My apologies that I can't make the time periods.
appear any clearer than they are, but that the first small column is before 1900, and then the very large column is houses that were built between 1900 and 1920, and then it's 1920 to 1940,
1940 to 1960 1960 to 1980 and then 99 is 80 to 99 is the 2nd to last in the last column is housing built since 2000.
The colors represent different types of housing.
So the blue, the bright blue color is single family homes.
The lighter pink is two family homes.
The darker pink is small multifamily, three to eight units.
And then the purple is condominiums, which among the condominiums that we see in the older housing stock tend to be conversions from original multifamily, small multifamilies.
And the condos built since 1960 are typically purpose-built condominiums.
I'm sorry, the purple is large multifamily, and the very pale green is condominiums.
And then there are miscellaneous other types of housing.
And public housing, you'll see, was mostly constructed in the mid-20th century, not very much of it, and none since 1980 or 1990.
So you can see, first of all, that the very
uh... the diversity of housing that we we have a fairly diverse housing stock uh...
I don't have the numbers visible to me that you can see on the spreadsheet that I need to see what are some of the numbers to go along with the diversity.
But we stopped building diverse housing basically in the 20th century after 1939.
So a lot of our housing is very old, and we saw that the housing units are large relative to the households.
The number of one-person households is much bigger than the number of one-bedroom units, which is also perhaps part of what's driving the non-family households.
People are combining with roommates to be able to live in larger housing units.
And finally, the housing is very expensive, and we're seeing assessor's data showing us that the cost of housing is really increasing.
And especially newer housing is more expensive, and housing in the fewer units in a building, housing tends to be more expensive as well, relative to when the housing was built.
So who is struggling with housing costs in Medford?
About 5,500 households have less than 50% area median income in Medford.
That's out of around 22,000 households overall.
And of those households below 50% area median income, two thirds are housing cost burdened.
About one third of all homeowners in the city are over the age of 65 and the median income for all people, households over the age of 65 is $44,000.
So that's a really stark fact for us to reflect on.
So seniors are experiencing the highest rate of housing cost burden compared to any other age of household.
But on the other hand, we're also seeing another story, which is that the cost of housing is going up so rapidly that people who are moving into Medford today have to have a higher income just to access housing, just to be able to move into Medford, which is why we're seeing that the median household income for renters is rising rapidly.
So that's reflecting what it costs to move into Medford.
And I just prepared this chart actually hot off the press a very short time ago.
This is a chart that shows what the income needed to rent an apartment or to purchase a condo in Medford or to rent a room in Medford.
So the average room rental is about $1,000 a month.
And to be able to afford that,
to pay less than 30% of your income, you would need to make about $40,000 a year.
The average income needed to rent an apartment in Medford is about $120,000 a year, where the average rent is about $3,000 a month.
And to purchase a condo in Medford, the average condo price right now is about $637,000.
And the income needed to be able to afford that is somewhere around $200,000.
So the columns represent the income, the average wages by industry within the Boston region.
So within the Boston region, people who are working in arts, recreation, food service, and hotel are making less on average than the income needed to be able to rent a room.
The people who are working in retail, transportation, healthcare, business support services, education, government, construction and real estate.
And that represents about 64% of the jobs in the Boston region.
Those folks can afford to rent a room, but they can't afford to rent an apartment on their own in the city on one income.
So those are typically people who are combining with roommates or partners to be able to rent an apartment.
And there is no industry in the Boston region that pays an average wage sufficient to purchase a condo on one income.
in the city.
So the higher paying industries include manufacturing, finance and insurance, business management, professional and technical services and information.
And people who work in those industries on average can afford to rent an apartment on one income, but would need a second income to be able to purchase a condo today.
And the yellow column just represents seniors to see where they fall in this affordability and income range.
Not that seniors are a. Wage earners necessarily.
So that's just some interesting and sobering data that we've put together.
The other thing that we've looked at is housing strategies and initiatives that the city has been undertaking in the last 5 years.
These include and I will welcome having some more input from.
The from the city staff to give us more information about these, but just a very quick overview.
They've been working on amending zoning in particular, Wellington station, mystic of court or Salem street court or and affordable infill zoning.
Building on city-owned lots, including small lots scattered throughout the city and large lots in Medford Square and the Wellington station area air rights.
Facilitating housing development by building partnerships with non-profit organizations and working with the Medford Housing Authority to redevelop, reposition some of their properties.
Supporting households by
Undertaking housing rehab program, down payment assistance, rental assistance programs, recruiting and assisting landlords, renting to voucher holders and low income tenants.
And advocating for affordable housing, fair housing, tenant fair, like, undertaking initiatives related to fair housing, tenant rights, displacement, prevention, building community support for affordable housing and identifying additional and I'm sorry.
I.
I need to think about how to present this slide.
So these are some initiatives that the city has been undertaking, and some that are just things that need to be undertaken.
And the ones that are colored in blue text on this slide represent initiatives that may potentially, the affordable housing trust may be partners on.
So identifying additional sources of revenue for the affordable housing trust is also
And I also wanted to just give an overview of what the existing resources are.
Now, we've heard at our previous meeting about the federal funding program, CDBG and HOME.
and CDBG and HOME.
And so we also have right now already 9.49% units on the subsidized housing infant
And there's a caveat, which is that 639 of those units are waiting for building permits.
They're 40 B. Developments, which we're given credit for on the subsidized housing inventory right away.
But if we wait too long before the building permits are issued, or before the developments are constructed, we're not going to be able to do that.
those units will fall off the list until they are actually constructed.
The subsidized housing inventory is showing that we have 2,439 units, but in fact, some of those units that are counted are actually market rate units because of the way that the state counts units toward the subsidized housing inventory.
It's a useful metric, but not necessarily reflective of how much affordable housing is actually available to Medford residents.
And the community preservation act program has total annual revenues of about 2Million dollars a year.
So, a minimum of 10% of that can be allocate or must be allocated toward affordable housing.
But the amount that the city has spent over 6 years has been closer to a 3rd of the total.
CPA revenue, so it's been about 4 million that we've spent on affordable housing so far.
And as we mentioned, the CDBG and home consortium resources.
So that is all that I have, and I welcome your comments, questions, feedback.
I want to start by saying thank you, Roberta.
You did a lot of work in putting this together.
It's on the action plan committee.
It's myself, Penny, and Roberta.
And I love the new slide.
It really sort of gives the aha moment on how much somebody needs to be earning in order to afford to live here.
So thank you, thank you, thank you.
So comments, questions about the data?
Our next steps are that we need to actually convert the data worksheet or the data summary that we've given into some text that will be the text of our plan.
And then we're going to be undertaking some engagement to learn more from stakeholders and the public.
Before we begin to draft our own
goals and priorities after what we've learned.
So the stakeholder meetings remind me the dates.
I don't have them on the top of my head for the stakeholder meetings.
of December 4th, which is Friday.
No, I'm sorry.
December 6th.
Today is the 4th.
Thank you.
Our first one is Friday at 2 o'clock and then I believe the next one is on the 13th.
It's December 10th.
Sorry, it's a Tuesday.
Tuesday at 2 p.m.
So we've identified or we've invited a list of, I think, close to 30 stakeholders.
These include nonprofit organizations, city staff, regional agency staff, and I think some realtors,
Add to the list if I'm forgetting any categories of people who we've identified and so we'll be meeting with them over 2 meetings to facilitate a conversation about what are the needs and opportunities that they see here.
Again, Roberta, thank you.
If you're open for some feedback, I know you said you were thinking about sort of like how to present that slide on the initiatives.
Maybe just putting it in just saying exactly like housing strategies and just letting them know that the blue, exactly what you did today, like the blue is what the trust is trying to work on.
I had it formulated better in my head.
I lost it, sorry.
I had all these notes written too, which I don't have available on my screen, so I'm going to remember to have a printout to read from before I
Before this Friday, I think on that 1, it is like a footer note that it's blue and maybe just moving that up.
To like, right underneath could do that, but it's great.
Thank you so much.
Roberta.
I feel like I've seen a taste before, but seeing it again, and this presentation with that chart is really striking.
I haven't had a chance yet to dig in to find a version that I created about at least five years ago, but I think that the changes are very sobering too.
For one thing, I just updated this from 21 data to 22 data and the average wages have gone down between 21 and 22.
And this is region wide.
This isn't just in the city.
So, um,
I want to look a little bit more at that data, because I think that's very interesting that our costs are going up so rapidly while we are actually experiencing a real decline in wages.
And early versions of this table that I made, or that chart,
used to compare the cost of an apartment, a condo, or a single-family house.
And I dropped the single-family house off of that list and only show a room, an apartment, and a condo, reflecting what is meaningful to people who are looking for housing right now.
On that is 3000 the average rent right now.
I like all apartments.
I just did a quick search to see what that would be, and I found Craigslist.
I'm coming up with something maybe closer to 2,500, but that includes a lot of older apartments.
And if you look at the realtor sites, they're skewed more toward newer apartments.
So we don't have access to a data set unless somebody can get us
a proprietary data set.
We don't have something that will give us the actual averages, but I'm not sure that that would show up anyway because a lot of the older, more affordable units are not listed on MLS, and so they might not show up in COSTAR.
So, Craigslist
A windshield survey might still be a better gauge.
So just a quick eyeball gave me somewhere between 2,500 and 3,000, depending on what source I'm looking at.
And those are for smaller apartments, like one- and two-bedroom apartments.
Well, thank you, Roberta.
I appreciate it.
I hope you feel good on being on the practice run.
Yes, I'm very glad to have a practice run.
These things, the more you do it, the better you get, and it makes such a huge difference having a real audience.
It does, and I will look through my slides and do a little spiel on the trust and how we do it and how we came about.
So I'll be prepared on Friday as well.
So thank you, thank you, thank you.
And we also want to try to be prepared to deliver, because all of you, I'm going into a little bit more detail because I know that you're really interested in the data itself.
But for our meetings, for our stakeholder meetings,
We want to rush through the presentation so we can give as much time as possible for the conversation.
And remind me, we have one hybrid meeting and one strictly Zoom, correct?
Yes.
Thank you.
The first one is a hybrid meeting.
On Friday.
Yes.
Great.
Thank you.
All right, so Aditi, did you want to provide an update on the overall housing strategies outlines in the housing production plan?
Yes, I think Roberta did a great job of providing a summary of housing strategies, so I'm just going to add to that.
talk about certain projects that address these housing strategies that Roberta talked about as part of the PDS reporting to the trust.
So this is just part one.
So I'll do my best to provide certain updates on the projects, ongoing projects, but hopefully in the next meeting, we'll have Alicia join us and talk about all these projects in detail.
I'm going to share my screen.
Can you all see it?
All right.
So.
I think Roberta briefly explained about the different housing strategies.
So these are the housing strategies.
I know it's a little hard to read.
But I'll talk about some of these housing strategies.
The ones in blue are in progress.
The ones in red are not initiated.
And the ones in orange are completed.
So the different housing strategies are outlined in the housing production plan and comprehensive plan, and I've just grouped them under common themes.
I'll talk about some of these themes in detail.
One common theme is to amend and update zoning to allow for multifamily mixed-use
housing types and different housing types across the city.
And then also include affordable infill and smaller infill housing.
The main strategy here is the city is undergoing zoning overhaul.
And as part of the zoning overhaul, the aim is to update the zoning to allow multifamily housing and affordable infill.
And another
Big change is the MBTA communities.
As you may be aware, Medford is now an MBTA community and Wellington Station has been identified as the MBTA zoning district.
The zoning overhaul.
City, in collaboration with Innis Associates, is currently doing an overall of its zoning ordinance.
This is to streamline development process and to modernize the zoning ordinance, as well as increase housing supply, reduce emissions, and promote vibrant, walkable neighborhoods in Medford.
So the zoning overhaul is grouped into three different phases.
Phase one is completed.
Phase one mainly focused on citywide policies and redefining certain definitions, as well as smaller changes that need not require additional research.
Phase two is currently in the process.
And as part of this phase, the city is looking at primarily two zoning districts or corridors and modifying their dimensional standards and boundaries.
Examples are Mystic Ave Corridor and Salem Street Corridor.
And as we speak, I think Mystic Ave Corridor is going before the Community Development Board this evening.
Third phase is yet to begin and hoping that this will begin end of this year or early next year.
And in this phase, we are hoping that certain affordable housing strategies are also addressed.
So the example of Mystic Ave Corridor, this is the current map of Mystic Ave Corridor with its existing uses.
So currently there's single family, two family, three plus units and other residential uses as well as commercial industrial.
But the proposed one is redefined into
four sub-districts, Mixed-Use 1, Mixed-Use 2, Mixed-Use 3, and Commercial.
So Mixed-Use 1 allows for commercial and residential uses at a lower scale in terms of the building size and massing.
Mixed-Use 2 also includes both residential and commercial uses, but at a medium scale of massing size.
Mixed-use 3, again, is similar to mixed-use 1 and 2, which includes residential and commercial uses, but the scale of the building is proportionately higher compared to mixed-use 1 and mixed-use 2.
And then the commercial sub-district mainly includes commercial uses and does not include residential uses.
So this Mystic Ave corridor allows for multiple dwelling as of right.
And it also allows dormitory, fraternity, and sorority houses as of right.
Lodging and boarding has to go before the CD board.
It requires a special permit.
And the other types of residential uses are not allowed.
The Mystic Ave corridor also has development incentive bonuses.
I believe this, I'm not sure if this is finalized yet.
In the previous presentation before the city board, this was what was presented.
So as part of the development incentive bonuses for affordable housing, this corridor is subject to inclusionary housing.
In addition to that, if the inclusionary housing affordable units
are designated, 20% of these units are designated at or below 60% AMI, then they can build another additional story.
If 30% of those affordable units that were generated through the Inclusionary Housing Ordinance are designated below 65% AMI, then you can build two additional stories.
The second type of incentive bonus is to provide an additional 20% affordable units in addition to the inclusionary housing ordinance.
Or you can provide 30% more additional units that is in addition to the inclusionary housing ordinance.
I know it's a little confusing.
Provide an example if you're interested, or we can move to the next slide.
Basically, it's categorized into two different types of development incentive bonuses.
One where the inclusionary housing ordinance, you designate 20% of those units for households that are below 65% AMI.
And the other type of development incentive bonuses is in addition to the inclusionary housing ordinance, you provide 20% more affordable units.
So I just want to, I'm sorry, Aditi.
So option one, the affordable requirement, everybody who's building is going to do 20% at or below 65% of the AMI.
If they're doing more than the 20%, then they can do an additional story?
No, everybody is subject to inclusionary housing ordinance.
So that means if a project has
10 to 24 units, then they're subject to 10% units affordable.
If a project has 25 to 49 units, then they're subject to 13% affordable housing units.
And then if a project has 50 or more units, then they're subject to 15%.
So if.
When a project is subject to, let's say, 15% affordable units, if that project has 100 units, then they would provide 15 units, which is affordable housing.
But out of those 15 units, if they designate three units at or below 65% AMI, then they can receive an additional story to build on.
And what is our AMI already for inclusionary?
Is that up to 80?
Yes.
Okay.
So our IZ ordinance, inclusionary ordinance says up to 80%, but if they want to go, if they want to bring it down to 65%.
All right.
Thank you.
That was my disconnect.
No, it is confusing and it makes sense to ask questions because yeah, there are two different approaches.
Moving on to MBTA communities, so as I mentioned earlier, the Wellington station has been identified as an MBTA zoning district and it's an overlay zoning district called the Wellington station multifamily overlay district.
And here multifamily housing is allowed as of right.
This overlay district is subject to inclusionary housing and site plan review.
Approximately 130 acres of this land area is part of the MBTA community zoning district.
This also has development incentive bonuses for affordable housing.
It's the same percentage that's been proposed for Misty Cap Corridor.
Another important theme is accessory dwelling units as of right.
As you may be aware, Affordable Homes Act now allows ADUs as of right in single-family residential zoning districts.
So this supersedes the existing ADU ordinance outline in the city's ordinance.
This will be in effect from February 2nd next year.
The new act did not have principal dwelling or did not have owner occupancy in principal dwelling or ADU.
But our city's ordinance currently requires owner occupancy in the principal dwelling.
We haven't updated the city's ordinance yet.
We are waiting for EUHLC to provide a little more guidance on updating our ADUs.
The next strategy is fair housing, tenants' rights, and housing displacement prevention.
So promoting fair housing choice with an updated analysis is one of the strategies that was outlined in our housing production plan.
This is usually
undertaken by the North Suburban Consortium.
The last fair housing study was done in 2019, but currently HUD is updating its rules on affirmatively furthering fair housing.
So NSC aims to include this study in their next five-year action plan since the rules are not concrete yet.
The next strategy is tenants' rights and resources, informing tenants of their rights and resources.
The city adopted Housing Stability Notification Ordinance in 2023.
So as part of this ordinance, the city developed tenants' rights and resources, and the city also informed land
landlords of this ordinance.
As part of the communication, I think a letter was sent to them early this year that they required to provide tenants' rights and resources to their tenants at the start and end of their tenancy.
Another strategy is to encourage mixed income and mixed use residential developments in vacant or underutilized city-owned lots.
So currently, the city has issued requests for proposals to develop city-owned lots.
This is behind Medford City Hall, along Riverside Ave, and then along Clippership Drive.
The project aims to have mixed use development that includes affordable housing, multifamily housing with ground floor commercial use.
And I think the existing parking would be improved as part of the development.
In the RFP, I think the city requires, proposes to provide at least 150 residential units with a mix of one-bedroom units to support the graduate students and seniors and those who are looking to downsize.
In addition to inclusionary housing ordinance, if the new projects provide 20% affordable housing at 80% AMI,
or 15% of those units at 80% AMI with an additional five units at 50 to 60% AMI is preferred.
And bidders are also encouraged to provide deeper affordability by providing affordable units to those at 60% AMI or less.
As Roberta mentioned, we have three affordable housing developments in the pipeline.
Two of them are applying for building permits soon.
These two, 4000 Mystic Valley Parkway and 970 Fells Faye are two 40B projects.
There are about nearly 200 units from both the developments that are affordable.
But as Roberta mentioned, since it's a 40B unit,
All units will be included in the subsidized housing inventory.
We also have a very small project, our community housing development organization, that's the CHODO, is building three units.
It's under construction and aims to finish by March next year.
I think there are other strategies here, for example, extending affordability restrictions of those units that are expiring soon.
City has been able to successively extend the affordability restrictions.
We talked about housing rehab program in the last meeting, so that is in progress.
The city is also supporting Medford Housing Authority's housing development projects, talked about Walkling Crote receiving HOME funds and also CPA funds.
We also talked about HOME and CPA funds in the previous meeting, and we've established an affordable housing trust.
So that's completed.
We've also expanded the staff capacity.
And currently, we are trying to foster partnership with mission-driven developers.
Enhanced community education.
We are trying to collaborate with Housing Medford.
We've applied for CHAPA's technical assistance.
We have not heard from them yet.
I did follow up, hoping to hear from them soon.
We are also doing a study on community land trust.
The working group is meeting once a month and providing feedback to the consultant who's leading the study.
And then we've talked about linkage identifying funds to do a next study to add affordable housing linkage to our existing linkage program.
So these are some of the strategies.
Hopefully in the next meeting.
We'll have Alicia join us and talk to us about some of these projects in detail.
Yes, Roberta.
Thank you Aditi.
That was a great presentation and a lot of like, it's so important to get an update on on the progress that we're actually making on all of these.
One question I had about the Medford Square parcels.
Is the RFP already out for that?
Yes, it is.
Okay.
And I did not see in your description anywhere that we're including some type of requirement to retain some space for the city government.
Or civic space of some kind of an, I think there is civic space, but I'm not sure exactly what the requirement is, but I'll have Alicia talk about it in the next meeting.
If that's okay.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay.
Yeah.
I'll make a note of that.
I've been advocating for some time that before we give up our last bit of land that the city owns, we need to think about what the city needs in the future and incorporate our needs into the plan for what to do with those parcels.
So I hope that that's still part of the discussion.
Yes, and I'll add that to my note and we can definitely ask Alicia about it.
Yeah.
Thank you, Aditi.
And great presentation, really appreciate it.
And I'm still wrapping my head around the Medford's inclusionary requirements and whatnot, because I'm familiar with a little bit lower AMIs.
But does anybody have any questions for Aditi?
Could I just maybe offer something, which is also a great presentation.
I feel like I learned a ton.
But as regarding fair housing, I believe a statewide office of fair housing was approved under the Affordable Homes Act.
And I wonder, that's probably something else or guidance is forthcoming, just the nature of city's relationships or access to that office.
But just wanted to flag there is state progress on that a little bit too, which hopefully impacts us.
All right, so thank you.
Our next item on the agenda is the meeting schedule.
Thank you for putting together the calendar year of 2025.
I have already started writing 2025 on my date.
I'm ahead of myself.
But anyways, 2025 schedule, you'll see that the meeting, I think there's a change in the meeting for January because I think January 1st is actually on a Wednesday, which is a holiday.
So we are proposing to meet on January 8th.
which is the following week at an earlier time, I think at five o'clock, yep, five o'clock start time.
And then we've done the schedule through, let's see, June, and then we'd close for July and August.
There are no meetings during the month of July and August.
And then resume on the first Wednesday of the month, September through the end of the,
end of 2025.
Does that sound like a good plan for everybody?
Thank you.
That's really great to see that all lined up.
And 1 thing that I just want to put on our radar is that the application cycle for Community Preservation Act funds will, I don't know, like, if we want to just make a mental note that in May or June, we probably need to at that time.
Hopefully, we'll be finishing with the plan by then, and that will inform us what, how to develop the application for CPA funds, but the application will be due by the end of next year.
So, um, we'll have to talk about it in June, so that can prepare the application while we're on summer break.
Thank you, Roberta.
That's helpful.
I just started that in my notes.
Okay.
Thank you.
All right, and we've reached the end of our agenda, so.
I had just one question about the declaration.
I forgot to mention, I think when we sign it, we should have a notary present.
Is that correct?
Okay.
Yes.
So I've spoken with Daria, who is the administrative assistant to the mayor's office, and she's notarized.
Okay.
And if people haven't notarized, you probably just need to bring a form of ID for the notary to verify your identity, and then that's all you'll need.
A valid ID can't be, it can't be expired.
Or a library card.
Yeah.
Membership.
Right.
Those, those don't count.
Thanks.
Excellent.
All right.
So then we may have a motion to adjourn.
So moved.
Second.
Do we want to do a roll call for adjoinment?
So Kayla, you did the motion.
Roberta?
Yes.
Carrie, did Carrie come in?
Yep, there she is.
Carrie?
uh penny you did the second lisa yes okay and i say vote yes as well all right guys thank you everyone thank you have a great holiday season