Oh, I forgot, I forgot Ed. The 11th regular meeting of the Medford City Council is called to order. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Camuso? Present. Councilor Caviello? Present. Councilor Knight? Present. Vice President Longo-Kern? Present. Councilor Mox? Present. Councilor Penta? Present. President Del Rosso? Present.
Seven present, none absent, please rise to salute the flag. Aye. I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America, and to the republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all. Mr. Counselor Penta. Suspension of rules to allow a citizen to speak. Paper 15-5-329.
On the motion of Councilors Penta to allow a citizen to speak. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion passes. 15-329, petition by Michelle Casey, 98 Terrace Road, Medford, to address the city council regarding the Lawrence Memorial Hospital. Mrs. Casey, please come forward to present yourself to the council. Please state your name and address for the record.
Hi, my name is Michelle Casey and I live at 98 Terrace Road in Medford. Thank you very much for taking the time to letting me speak tonight. Um, I was here about a year and a half ago in regards to the noise at the Lawrence Memorial Hospital. Um, I'm sorry to say and report that the noise still continues without any resolution from the hospital. Um, this has been ongoing for almost five years now.
The hospital says that they want to be a good neighbor and they want to resolve the problem, but they're not doing anything in regards to helping the situation. They continue to tell me that they're going to continue to monitor the noise. This is, it's a noise that goes on 7 by 24. It wakes my family up in the middle of the night. My home vibrates. It is just a constant noise that we just cannot escape.
I've spoken with a couple of acoustical engineer firms, and they have told me that in order to measure the noise and figure out what the noise is, they need to come in my home, which I am more than happy to have them come in my home. I do have a quote here that I can give to you, that it would cost $400 for this measurement to be done. And I've asked the hospital if they would pay for this, and they basically have not answered me.
I also, back in August of, August 27th of 2014, the Board of Health, the Medford Board of Health, came out and did some noise measurements. And in the report, it does say, in fact, that there is a noise, but they can't seem to identify the noise. The woman that did this report did work for the hospital for 20 plus years, so I don't know the credibility of this report that, you know,
She did have a very longstanding relationship with the people at the hospital. I'm at a loss. I don't know what to do. Short of selling my home, which I'm not in a position to do, I love my neighborhood, I need help. And I'm pleading and begging for you people to help me get this issue resolved. So I don't know if anyone has any questions, but I'm more than happy to answer them.
And I know from, if I could just say from the chair, I know Councilor Pente has in the past arranged meetings between the citizens and the hospital and has been quite active in this matter. I'm wondering if he has anything to suggest tonight. One of the concerns that I have after speaking with Mrs. Casey is the fact that she's been constantly wanting to get a communication and a dialogue that would be representative
of the hospital's interest in the matter. And I believe the e-mails will prove out that at one point in time when the hospital was coming up for a takeover, so to speak, for which Mara Healy, the new Attorney General, did not allow between the Mass General Partners and the Lawrence Memorial, something went askew right after that, even though she was getting some type of correspondence back and forth.
The bad part about the whole story is the fellow that used to be the president, Mr. Michael Sack, took a walk as soon as the deal didn't go through. And as soon as that deal didn't go through, he was making all kinds of promises. We were going to do this. We were going to investigate it. We will have people come out there, spoken to Mrs. Casey and other neighbors. And she's not the only one. There were other letters that were written to the hospital. And now it just seems like it's just gone nowhere. You know, she's a taxpayer. She's a citizen.
You know, and unfortunately, however you want to look at it, there is a problem that does exist over there. Now, does it pound 24 hours? I mean, seven days a week? No, but when it does come on and when it does happen, it's disturbing, disturbing enough that at times, as a matter of fact, correct me if I'm wrong, you have an email that you received from the hospital that says,
you could bring your office up to the hospital and work out of the hospital. I most certainly do. So for them to put that in writing and to recognize the fact that the problem exists, it does exist. And with that being said, um, I don't know. Um, Alan McDonald supposedly is the gentleman supposedly in charge. I don't know. This council hasn't even given me given an update as a result of the merger not taking place. Unfortunately, um, what seems to be going on over there. I mean, I'll just say this too.
as far as the hospital goes. Michael Sack did a hell of a job moving everything out of the Lawrence Memorial to the Melrose Wakefield. That hospital is now in such, I don't even know what kind of a state it is in right now, because a lot of people don't even know what's going on at the hospital. We as citizens and as counselors don't even know what the hospital's capable of doing. They've reduced their emergency, strike that, they've reduced their intensive care unit.
They've reduced a lot of the other programs that they had there, and a lot of it's been shipped over, because that's where Michael Sack was going to go if this deal went through, and he was going to be independently of this whole problem, this situation. She's a resident, she's a taxpayer, and she's been before this council numerous times. Now, the Lawrence Memorial Hospital needs to be, for $400, I mean, this is incredible. They don't want to, they're talking about a multi-million dollar merger, and for $400 to keep the neighborhood and the neighbors at bay, in peace?
I mean, what is it? So, you know, can we force them to do anything? No, we can't, but we're here to defend and protect our taxpayer and she's living it. So I would suggest, Mr. President, that we get in touch if it's Alan McDonald, whatever it might be, and hopefully that the council supports the request to spend the $400
to have this person of this company come in and do the job. I mean, what's $400 when you're talking about hundreds and thousands of dollars? You're talking about a neighborhood. But to say, we're going to give you a room up here, and you can run your business out of our hospital, that to me tells the whole story. And that's it. So I would hope that my colleagues would be supportive of the fact that we would make the request that the Lawrence Memorial Hospital honors the request of the taxpayer citizen, employs
pays the $400, and let's just see where we're going with this thing. Because it's obvious, it's a problem. People don't come to this podium if it's not a problem or to receive some kind of recognition. It's a neither-or thing. And unfortunately, tonight she's here because it's a problem. Thank you, Counselor. So on the motion of Counselor Penta, that the Memphis City Council request of Mr. McDonald, president of Hallmark Health. Acting president. Acting president at Lawrence Memorial Hospital, that the investment of $400 be made
through the name of that company. What's the name of the company? Acitech in Cambridge do the onsite evaluation of Ms. Casey's home. On that motion, uh, vice president Lugo current. Thank you. President DelaRusso. Ms. Casey, if I may ask you, I can't recall. Do you know if it's a generator or what, where the noises is coming from? I I'm suspecting that it's a generator, but I'm not an engineer. Um, what I can tell you is that there is,
somewhat of a power plant that is up to the, if you're looking at the hospital from my home, to the left of the hospital, and that noise, you know, it is a seven by 24 noise, 365. Okay, and how many homes, how far up Terrace do you live? How many homes? I'm the second home on Terrace, so where my home sits in my, I face the hospital and I face that
power plant, if you will. I just want to go on record support and Councilor Penta's resolve. Not only do I think they should do the noise study, see if it's in with reasonable limits or if it is actually a breach of your quiet enjoyment. I think we should just go further and ask that they resolve that, that issue, whether they fence it in better or create a sound barrier. You know, something needs to be done. That's a residential neighborhood. And it sounds like to be woken up in the middle of the night is not something anybody would enjoy.
And we did, I remember we asked these questions and we tried to push for this a year and a half ago. And it's a shame that the Lawrence Memorial Hospital isn't trying to resolve some of these issues for their neighbors. I think asking you to work from their hospital is just, it's out of line. I mean, you should be able to work in the quiet of your own home and it should be quiet. So I will support councilors resolve and ask that they, whatever the, if the noise level is,
not sufficient for quiet enjoyment, that the hospital does something to remedy the situation. Thank you, Madam Vice President. Councilor Caviello. Thank you, Mr. President. Um, what was the last time you met with Hallmark? I met with them, um, over the summer. I've requested to meet with them again and with a change of leadership. Um, you know, I'm, I'm the low, low one on the totem pole for them. So you, you, you haven't been in any kind of discussion with them?
I've had a few emails from them. They did take a walk last summer to my property. It was the president at the time, Alan McDonald, and their director of facilities. They all heard the noise. They all, you know, stood there and agreed with me that there is, in fact, a noise. But again, they just don't want to make the investment to figure out what it is. And our board of health is saying that they agree that there is a noise?
Yes, in the report that I just handed this gentleman, it does say that there is a noise, they just can't pinpoint what the noise is. I did ask, I've asked the hospital, I've asked the Board of Health, I've asked everyone, come into my home and hear what I hear, you know, experience what I've experienced, and no one has taken me up on that offer. When I talked to the engineering firm, I explained that to them, and they said, well, they have to come in the home to hear the noise, because when you close it off, you can really hear how loud it is.
So, you know, again, I have been so accommodating to the hospital to try and work with them and figure it out. And, you know, I know all of you are very busy people. Does this noise happen, like, during the daytime? It happens during the day. I do work from home. Can I come by any of the noise one day? You absolutely can. Can I come by tomorrow? Well, actually, tomorrow I am in meetings all day, but I would be more than happy to have you. I'm curious. Sure, absolutely. I'd be more than happy to.
Whatever needs to be done to make it go away, I think should be done. I mean, $400 doesn't seem like a large expenditure to see where the noise is actually coming from. And when I talked to the engineering firm, they quoted me $800. But when I explained the situation, they said that they would reduce the rate because they felt so bad for me. So that's why they came up with that. If you call me on Thursday, I'd like to come by on Thursday and hear the noise myself. Absolutely. I'd be more than happy to have you at my home. OK. Yes. Thank you. Thank you.
Councilor Knight. Um, thank you very much. And I think, uh, Councilor Caviello and I are on the same page with this. And, um, I certainly appreciate, uh, Ms. Casey going through the trouble of having to actually invite people into their, her home to get this problem resolved. Um, I think that it might make sense instead of having Ms. Casey have to open her home to multiple people who want to go there on multiple days or multiple times to see exactly what's going on for themselves, that maybe,
We have an on-site meeting with Alan McDonald, our code enforcement officer in the Board of Health, as well as the Council, to see it for ourselves, to all be there in the same room at the same time, so that none of us can say, we didn't hear it, we did hear it, we weren't there at the time when it was going on, that we all experienced it ourselves. And I think we'll all have a better understanding as to what's going on, what Ms. Casey has to deal with, and what course of action we need to take. I mean, the Lawrence Memorial Hospital, if they continue to go back and forth with Ms. Casey on this topic for over a year and a half, but not be willing to invest $400,
But they probably spent $5,000 worth of manpower just responding to her inquiries. It doesn't make much sense to me. I think if they're really committed to addressing the problem that they will pony up the money. I certainly have concerns as to whether or not the council's in a position to tell them to do such. However, I think it'll be really beneficial to everybody. We've heard it once before. We've given them a year to resolve the issue. They haven't resolved the issue. Mrs. Casey's been more than patient.
I think it's time that we take a little field trip, Mr. President, maybe, and bring some members of our administration and members of the hospital down there to exactly see what's going on, and then we can have a real informed discussion about it right there on site. Very good. So on the motion of Councilor Pinter, as amended by Councilor Knight, Councilor Marks. Thank you, Mr. President. I agree with all the comments. However, I think at this point, because it has been going on for so long, I think Ms. Casey, as well as Alan McDonald, the acting president of the hospital,
both have come to a mutual agreement that the noise is coming from Lawrence Memorial Hospital. I mean, I don't think anyone's disputing that. And I think my opinion would be to have the acting president come before the council. You know, you could do a site review and all you want, but I think we're better off having Mr. McDonald come before us, requesting at that point, because when he was before us not too long ago, I don't think we knew about the $400 study and so forth.
and now to present it to him saying this is what we want, this will be the first step, even though you've been dealing with this for a long time, this will be the first step in trying to figure out what the cause of the root cause is. Originally, I thought there was some concern about the silo that is actually probably closer to your home.
the giant silo out there, and that's not emitting any type of noise. Is that correct? Again, I'm not an engineer, so I really can't, I don't believe so. I really believe that it's the tower that is up on the hill to the side of the hospital. That would be my professional opinion. Right. So this is not rocket science to figure out where this noise is coming from. And I know Lawrence Memorial Hospital's very busy,
with possible merger and so forth, and they have a lot going on on their plate. However, this has been going on far too long, and if we invite Mr. McDonald up here and get no answers, I think then it's incumbent upon this city, including the administration, the mayor, to get on the phone and see what he can do with his department heads to leverage some issues with the hospital themselves.
So that would be my recommendation, Mr. President, that we invite the President up here. We could do it. I agree with the walkthrough. If members want to do a walkthrough, that's fine. But I think the walkthrough has been done. It seems to have not accomplished any answers. And I think at this point, having Mr. McDonald come before us publicly will help the situation. So I would move that, Mr. President.
On the motion of Councillor Penter as amended by Councillors Knight and Marks, Councillor Camuso. Thank you very much. And thank you, Michelle, for coming down here again. Is it the boiler room tower that you're referring to? I believe so, yes. Okay. Like the smokestack that's out there? Yes. Exactly. Just so we're in the area, we can pay attention a little bit more to the exact area. And I just assume that the issue was resolved as I believe some of my colleagues. So I certainly support
support the $400 piece, as well as the few amendments that were put forth this evening. So hopefully we'll get some solution for our neighbours. Thank you, Councillor Caruso. So do you wish to say anything else, ma'am? No, but I just want to thank you all very much for your time and for helping me resolve this issue. Thank you. So before we take our vote, we're going to invite one more citizen who wishes to speak. Please state your name and address for the record.
Thank you, Mr. President. I'm Bob Capucci, 71 Evans Street. Just two quick points. Councilor Pinto brought up this merger. That's not going to happen. I work in the medical device industry, and the company which I'm employed, to be quite honest with you, I don't really recall who said this, but we watched that merger with keen interest, and I'm hearing reports that that merger is being blocked on the South Shore.
And it might actually go through up here. That merger might still go through. So if that President, Mr. McDonald, comes up here through your governmental contacts, I would find out that I'm getting reports in the industry I work in that that merger might still go through up here on the North Shore. And on the point of the noise issue, whatever resolve that happens, I mean, for her benefit and her neighbors, too, no doubt, please do
whatever resolve happens, make sure the noise is contained. And I say that because these sound barriers that are up here on Route 93, what they're actually doing is it's blocking the sound on this side, but it's catapulting the sound in that direction.
And as far as Garfield street, up Salem street, the noises from the highway are a big problem from the residents down there. I have a lot of friends that live in that area and they said that to me. So please make sure that the noise is actually contained. Thank you for your time. Thank you. And on the motion of Councillor Penter as amended by Councillors
A night in marks. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries. While we're on to suspension, Councilor Caravaglio. Mr. President, if we could take issue number 15-031. From unfinished business, 15-031, offered by Councilor Caravaglio, originally a discussion of 56 Boynton Road problem. Councilor. Thank you, Mr. President. I don't know if many people know, but
There is a house 56 Boynton Road that's been abandoned now for a couple of years that's stuck in probate with the Commonwealth. And it's been a problem for the neighbors with rodents and other things like that. And we have one of the neighbors here who would like to speak on it this evening. So I think I'd rather have them speak on it. There's a petition, there's some pictures that the neighbor has brought with him.
So I think the neighbors speaking on it will be a lot better than me. Thank you. Sir, please state your name and address for the record. Certainly. The name is Mark Crowley. The address is 59 Boynton Road. And I do want to thank the council for their time this evening and thank Councillor Calviello for the opportunity to get this on the agenda. Mother Nature hasn't cooperated with us when we originally tried to get this on the agenda,
month ago it seemed like there was a storm every weekend that things got canceled so fortunately now we're back up here. So as I mentioned, I live on Boynton Road. My neighbors and I, we're just up the block from the library as well as St. Joseph's Church. It's a quiet residential street with very close-knit families. Unfortunately on the street, as Councilor Caraballo alluded to, there is a vacant house which was declared quote dangerous and unsafe by the Medford Building Department more than two years ago.
The resident of the home and son of the original owners, Mr. James Bagnullo, excuse me, Joseph Bagnullo, passed away in December of 2012. An inspection at that time by the Medford Building Department resulted in the condemnation of the home. The presumed heir to the home is Mr. Bagnullo's sister, Norma, though after two years, that is, again, Councilor Kellery, I'll refer to, probate status is still incomplete. For many years prior to Mr. Bagnullo's death, the house was in deplorable condition, as you'll see some of those photos there.
At the time of his death, Mr. Bagnulli had himself abandoned living in the first and second floors, sheltering himself in the basement as the upper stories had already become unsafe even for him. Current and former neighbors did our best to look out for him and his mother for years, decades in some cases, checking him periodically, bringing him food, caring for the dog, raking leaves, shoveling snow. However, in the two years since Mr. Bagnulli's death, the property has been vacant and fallen into further disrepair. As you'll see in these photos that I provided, the property is completely overgrown.
and quite literally falling apart. Sections of the roof have collapsed, leaving the interior open to the elements. Vermin are frequently seen entering and exiting, including coyote, red fox, possum, raccoons, snakes, mice. A rusted car, one of three actually sitting in the yard, continues to sit there, sunk into the ground, certainly presents an environmental contamination threat. Simply put, this is not an acceptable situation in a residential neighborhood.
certainly not a residential neighborhood. This is a street with more than a dozen young children living on it. St. Joseph's School is just down the block, and students walk by it every day. Not only is the structure unsafe, open to the elements, and easily compromised, but the trees and yards have not been kept up. Large dying trees and deep voids in the walkways leading up to the doorways are poised to create additional hazards. As property owners and taxpayers, the residents of our neighborhood should not be subjected to this hazard. Heaven forbid any of us try to sell our homes and try explaining that to a prospective buyer.
Now, that being said, not seeing any action on the property from the owners in September of last year, I had reached out to the Medford Health and Building Departments. Both indicated there was nothing that they could do, that it was going through probate. Now, the Building Department assured us that the property is, and I use their quotes, secured and posted to prevent unauthorized entry. I think you've seen the photos, and that certainly does not look like a secure property. And by secure, the Building Department, they put a small padlock on one of the three doors.
Frankly, any of those doors can be taken down with a strong breeze and rodents really can't read signs, so they tend to go in one way or the other. Furthermore, as a vacant property, there is no posting with emergency contact information. Medford's vacant and foreclosing property regulations require that all these vacant properties be registered with the city. Name and 24-hour contact information of owners are supposed to be posted. That ordinance also requires that same individual to inspect and maintain the property on a monthly basis.
Needless to say, there is no contact information. We've never seen monthly inspections. With all the historic snowfall that we've seen in the past month or so, never once did anyone ever come by. It continued to be up to the onus of the neighbors to take care of this property. Now, there has been a recent development where the attorney representing the likely heir of the property, a gentleman by the name of John Cervone, visited the property back in late January. I was at that visit, along with some of our neighbors.
And we asked about their plans for the home, both near and long-term, and he assured us that they planned to rehab the property. I watched a little bit of HDTV, and I'm not a contractor, but I assure you, I don't think you can rehab that property. Now, we further pressed him about his immediate plans to address the safety concerns. We asked about snow removal, clearing the trees, et cetera. His response was, quote, we'll look into it.
not too impressed by the need to act. We actually commented about the rodents and vermin, and he said, gosh, all neighborhoods have those problems. So I think, frankly, he seemed to be taken aback that, as neighbors, we were asking him to do something. So between the city's lack of action and the less than motivated owner representative, my neighbors and I have shouldered this risk long enough. The problem has gone on too long. We no longer feel that, after many years of patience, that we need to continue to take care of this property.
You know, state law through the powers granted to the health and building departments requires immediate attention to properties that present a public nuisance, specifically ones that are dangerous to life and limb, vacant, open to the weather. And certainly it is well within the city's authority to seize the property and further demolish it. So at the same time, it also, the state regulations allow and grant the authority to city bodies to not only seize the property, to demolish it, place a lien on the property,
and then any sort of associated costs associated that get passed on to the owner. It's been more than two years, and this property has been in a rapidly worsening state, and the health and building departments have not taken action as required by state law. As I noted, this property is a disaster waiting to happen. I'm certainly no member of this council who would like to wake up each morning and stare at this hazard as I do and many of my neighbors. Those of you with small children can certainly understand the fear at a parent's heart, you know, having your kids play around and being near this thing.
And for some of you councillors, you're actually a lot closer than you think. I know Councillor Knight, Councillor Penter, Councillor Camuso, you're within several hundred feet of this property in Boynton Road. For that reason, my neighbours and I, we're bringing this issue before the city council, asking for immediate action. We're asking you to direct the health and building departments to act immediately. State law gives property owners 24 hours to remedy a vacant property. I think after two years, we're well past that 24-hour period.
Now, that said, the same authority that rests with the health and building department also does rest within the city council. Per state law allows the, you know, if there is inaction on parts of the health and building departments that the city council can itself also declare that the property be seized and remedied. The laws are there. This isn't optional. It's simply not enough for the city to place a red X on the property and feel that they have done their job.
And it's certainly not acceptable for the owner's representative to simply say they'll look into addressing the danger this property presents, especially after nothing has been done for years. I appreciate the challenges of the legal system, but that's not an excuse to not address an immediate public safety matter. The fire department doesn't refuse to put out a fire if there's a probate matter on the home. They go in and they do what's right and what's necessary. We've had enough. Personally, I live right across from this place. I walk out my door every single day with my daughter when I take her to school.
I shouldn't have to constantly be telling her to stay away from the haunted house. Residents and taxpayers, we really demand action. And we really do want to see this property taken care of. And I do, I know I have a neighbor of mine here. Actually, my daughter has asked, if the council allows, she'd like to actually say a few words. She's very eager to say something. So I'm going to hand the microphone off to her. Good evening. Please state your name and address for the record. My name is Caroline Crowley, and I live on 59 Boynton Road.
And I live across the street from this house, and I just wanted to put my voice out. I, along with many other kids in my neighborhood, love to play outside. The kids along my block are very scared of this house for many reasons. We see raccoons, snakes, and many other wild beasts come out of this house. We feel very unsafe and unsecure with this house being in our neighborhood.
that thus we have given it the name The Haunted House. It makes us very sad that this house rots when new families could move into a new house where The Haunted House stands. Again, I just wanted to voice my opinion in this matter alongside my father. I think that not just adults have their opinion in matters, but children should have a say in things too. Thank you. Thank you. We were at dinner at Salvatore's just prior to this, and I was trying to explain to her what this evening was about. She's like, Dad, can I say something?
want. But honestly, we look at this thing every day. We've been patient long enough, and it really is time for some action to be taken. Thank you so much, and I'm happy to entertain any questions. Councillor Caviello. Thank you, Mike. I agree, it's not right that your neighbours have to come look at this every day. It's been a long time. I've been in touch with Paul Mulkey a couple of times on this, and he keeps saying the same thing, the thing they can do that they can do.
I have a question for you. Yeah. Does this house have any historical value that it couldn't be turned down? No, I would say not. In fact, my wife is a member of the Medford Historical Commission and who actually has authority over saying whether or not buildings can be turned down. I know. Is it over 100 years old where it couldn't be turned down? No, it's not. Like you said, looking at the pictures, I don't know who's rehabbing this. There's not much rehab. You go around there, literally you see into the roof. It's not fair that your neighbors have to look at this and yourself and your children.
Again, I don't know what course the city has to force them to either tear it down or... Well, I'll quote you... Tear it down or even fence it in so no one can get in there. Yeah. I appreciate the notion of fencing, but I think at this point in time... I know. It's an eyesore. Like I said, you shouldn't... Let's say it drops your property value and everybody else's value in the neighborhood.
I would think that we want to have our attorney contact their attorney and get them in here and try to get some kind of remedy on this. I'll quote Mass. General Law, Chapter 143, Section 7. If the public safety so requires and if the aldermen are selected in so order, the inspector of buildings may immediately enter upon the property with the necessary workmen assistance to cause such unsafe structure to be made safe or taken down without delay.
They said the house is condemned, so I would think that'd be enough. I would seemingly have to disagree on that circumstance. I would say if the whole notion there is to make the structure safe, I would definitively argue that building is far beyond the condition of being considered safe. Mr. President, if you could get the building inspector to answer this and find out why he hasn't. On the motion of Councilor Caviello that the building inspector
report back to the Medford City Council regarding the actions taken and need for further action on the property at 56 Poynton Road. Councilor Longo-Kern. Thank you, President DelaRusso. Mr. Crowley, John Cervone, he's the attorney for the estate.
He is correct. He is the sister Norma has engaged him as the attorney to navigate the- Is he out in Waltham? He is out in Waltham, yes. So it's been in probate for three years?
Yes. And I personally, I I've been through probate with family members and it does not take. Yeah, it takes, it takes about a year. So the sister Norma, she must be the executor. She, the, the Norma is, um, it's, it's an unusual history with the property. The, uh, the original owners, uh, Mr. Bagnullo's parents, uh, lived at the home along with, uh, Mr. Joseph Bagnullo here. Uh, the father passed away. I'm going to probably say 20 years ago, uh, at the time the mother was living there as well. And then Mr. Joseph Bagnullo moved back and moved in with him.
The mother passed away, I want to say, about six or seven years ago. Now, the father neither had a will, nor the mother did not have a will. Mr. Bagdullo here, he did not have a will. So really, the only remaining known heir is the sister, who lives up on the north shore of the Chelmsford of Billerica. So there was really no action at the time. And frankly, I've been hounding the building department.
pretty much for the past three years consistently. And the answer has always been, yeah, it's going to the legal system. Yeah, it's going to the legal system. And frankly, the naming of John Cervone as an attorney, that only first came to being around in the January time frame. For the prior two and a half, three years, there was never a name of an attorney that was surfaced. So my humble opinion, I think that there really was no action being taken on the part of the sister to try to move this thing forward.
I mean, I just feel like three years in probate court is a little long, so I'm wondering if they started the probate process late. I definitely get that suspicion, yes.
because obviously the land's worth something. So hopefully somebody will buy it, tear it down, and build a new house. I'll be honest. When I went to go visit Mr. Russo at the building department, he had a list of developers that have contacted him. I've had a number of developers knock on my door, send me letters saying, would you sell it to me? And I said, if I could sell it to you, I would. But yeah, no, in this circumstance. What's that? Thank you. So yeah, I've had more than enough developers. And the other neighbors have said, hey,
Thank you. Someone wants to buy this place. I think Carviello had a good point. I think we'll see if one of our solicitors, city solicitor or assistant city solicitor could reach out to Attorney Cervone and ask where they are in probate and how much longer it's going to take and see if we can find out what they plan on doing with the property as soon as possible. It might be particularly tricky where there may have not been previous wills of the previously deeded people. Therefore, it's in land court as well.
So we will make that amendment to the main motion by Councilor Longo-Curran. It would be then this children, if he had no children, it would be the sister's property. Sister would get obtained by inheritance, yes. So, I mean, I think she'd be able to sell it. It's just a matter of if it's finished going through probate. That is what I've heard as well. Councilor Knight.
And if we can get an update, I know we asked the building department why they haven't done anything. If we could also get an update from Karen Rose with her take on this and why she feels that the city can't do anything. And that's where I- Further amended by Councilor Longo Kern. Councilor Knight. Thank you very much, Mr. President. Mr. Crowley, thank you for taking the time to come down here this evening. Certainly. When did the meeting take place through the chairman to the gentleman with Mr. Cervone?
The, uh, meeting was on January 21st of this year that, uh, Mr. Cervone, uh, visited the property with his contractor, uh, to have a meeting as well at the, at present at that meeting was, uh, John Cervone, uh, myself and several other neighbors, uh, to, uh, you know, we were engaged, uh, engaged the attorney and, um, you've, you've indicated represented that you've made official complaints with the board of health and the building department on this issue in writing and I've got a link telephone. Okay. Um,
Can you do me a favor and just give me that site again that you gave through the general laws? Oh, I'm sorry, yes. Yeah, that was Master of the Law, Chapter 143, Section 7. You referred to Selectmen and Board of Aldermen? Oh, the one with respect to the aldermen, that one is State Law, Chapter 139, Section 13B. I'm happy to send you an email with a whole bunch of the other references. Mr. President, that'd be great. That'd be great. Thank you.
Um, Mr. President, I think it would make sense for us to have the city solicitor also render a legal opinion as to whether or not this council under, um, GL one, four, three, section seven and nine. It's Al, uh, has the power and authority to, uh, prompt the end of the building department and the board of health to go in there and see if we can get rid of this house and, uh, take the necessary steps that we need to do to beautify the neighborhood and ensure that these residents have a strong quality of life. Um, Mr. Crowley,
was absolutely correct. I do live within walking distance of the house. I've been by the house. I've seen the house. Um, I've seen the house. We called it a haunted house. I think when we were kids and, um, you know, I, I think that, uh, they've been very patient up there. They've, they've taken appropriate steps, done their homework and made this very easy for us. Um, so with that being said, Mr. President, I don't think the motion of council car VLO is amended by vice president Longo Kern and counselor night. Thank you. Counselor Camuso.
Thank you, Mr. President, and when this originally came before us, I went back into my records, my electronic mail records. And on January 7th, 2015, I have an email from Paul Moki, who's our building commissioner. At the time, the gentleman at the podium brought it to my attention, as well as several members of this council. This issue is now with the Attorney General's office on this particular house, because they're looking at, as you know, and you've been part of the discussions, you didn't say it this evening.
but the Attorney General's office has a program where they'll actually take over the property and get it up to code, up to par, and it would all be leaned and everything like the gentleman said. With that being said, I think the city has to at this point, looking at the pictures, the roof, the holes in the porch, you get the X on the front, and for those that don't know that, that's for the fire department if they show up to, you don't go in.
The building down here had the X on it, the red X, and that's strictly to keep our public safety officials safe. And before I go any further, I want to tell you, you did an excellent job. Very, very good. You should be proud of yourself to get down here with your dad tonight. But with that being said, I really think that the city has to at least go out there, spend the money, even if it's a couple thousand dollars at this point, and at least board it up, fix the hole in the
In the porch, there's a big hole in the porch that I saw. Things that are definite safety issues as of right now, if someone walks on that porch, the roof should be at least closed. I think that we should do that and at least lean it for that portion right now. As the gentleman at the podium stated, it's an eyesore and it's in the proper authority's hands of the Attorney General's office.
But I think it's incumbent upon the city to do the immediate need of at least shoring it up enough to the point where the AG's office comes in with either a bulldozer or whatever the outcome is, but at least make it safe for the exact time being. Because if a child goes up there, just walks on the porch, runs up on the porch to have them call 911, a young kid walking home from school or something. I mean, there's a big hole in the porch that we just saw.
That is definitely a very much safety hazard. So if we could also make that part of the record and also ask John Bevuso and Paul Moki to give this council an update from the Attorney General's office on exactly where it is. The other thing is too, I believe there are some neighbors, as I told you in the past, that are very much interested in purchasing the piece of property. And if there's been any more developments on that, if we could also ask that question as well. And as far as the- As amended by Councilor Camuso.
I believe the issue here is the people that are in the line of the heirs and the common heirs, even when it's not in the will. Is that what it's called, common heirs? The line of succession. All of them are incapacitated from what I hear, and that's what's making it difficult. And I believe that the attorney may have been appointed by the court or the AG's office as well. I can't say that with 100% certainty, but knowing a little background on it and where it's at,
and the timing seems about right. January 7th, I was told that the Attorney General's office is on it. January 21st, there's an attorney out at the site. And there's been communication between the AG's office and the city. So I'm assuming that the attorney is probably appointed through the court by the AG's office. I do know that it has been in the Attorney General's program until as early as the middle, early of last year as well. So the attorney certainly is a byproduct of hoping
Exactly. And I certainly understand your frustrations, but unfortunately, as you know, the city still has to follow the certain procedures. We could go in with the wrecking ball, and I'm sure all of us, including the mayor, would be for that if we could. For sure. But we have to follow the appropriate procedures and get court orders and all that stuff to proceed. Absolutely. But in the interest of public safety, I think it has to be shored up, at least to the point where it's not... Or put a fence around it. Quite honestly, there should be a fence around it right now. Well, certainly a fence would be, you know,
as amended by Councilor Camuso. Thank you. Councilor Marks. Thank you, Mr. President. And, um, you know, back some years ago, the city council voted on a city ordinance call called the clean it or lean it ordinance. And, uh, this particular house would be an ideal situation to implement the clean it or lean it.
And that's at just the minimum of getting in there and taking out all the debris around the home. You have, as you mentioned, there's a car, a rusted car in the backyard, and there's a rusted gas tank on the back of the car. And if you look at the picture on page six, it's surrounded by thousands of dried up leaves that happened to go from that property onto the neighbor's property. And that's a situation waiting to happen.
You know, I'm dumbfounded why the city hasn't played more of an active role, Mr. President, in seeing that this house, at least the exterior be cleaned up. That was mentioned. The roof that you can actually see through, it has a giant skylight that I guess birds and anything else, squirrels and anything else that wants to get into the house. You know, I find that ironic, Mr. President, that
It was only a few years ago that on Momola Way, there was a dispute between neighbors and one neighbor thought to get back at the other neighbor by making his front lawn, maybe members of the council remember this, look like a junkyard. So the neighbor put out an old tub on his front lawn. He put out a toilet. He put out a hundred different items on his front lawn. And we all know Momola is a nice trimmed area.
And just so happens to be across from the mayor's home. And within a matter of a day or two, this is just some debris on his front lawn. Every city department, every city entity, the fire department, police department, code enforcement, building commissioner, they were down at that home immediately. And that house was cleaned up overnight. All the stuff that was on that lawn. And you know, it's amazing that
This hasn't taken place, Mr. President, at this site. You know, I remember dropping my kids off at St. Joe's for many years and driving up and saying, wow, what's going on with this property?
And then I saw the red, the scolodex that was put on the house that says, don't go in there. And you know, I don't want to make light of this, but no, absolutely not. You know, honestly, the city administration in this city is so used to seeing condemned city buildings that they may look at this house and say, this house is in good condition.
Honestly, you know, I hate to say that the red X should be on the police department. It should have been on the DPW yard. It should have been on a host of other buildings that should have been condemned to this, this house. But honestly, Mr. President, this, this issue, we need to meet with the city solicitor immediately, find out what's going on. In my opinion, the wrecking ball should have already come out and then answer questions after the fact. That's what should have happened, Mr. President.
And that that's what, and also Mr. President, if we can make it part of the report, is this tax delinquent, is this a home been up to snuff when taxes? I'm not sure if you've looked into that yet or not. I amended by councilor marks that the city treasury report back to us regarding the tax situation on the property. Mr. President. And I, you know, I know all the members mentioned about having the city solicitor and the building commissioner,
But I think there needs to be an emergency meeting set up. You know, tomorrow can't be quick enough. And if we want to do it on site, all the better. But this is absolutely unacceptable. And in my opinion, no neighbor should have to drive by or live next to this home. And especially with storage of gas on site, we have rules and regulations about open storage of gas. And clearly, I can see not only the car, but a gas tank
a separate gas tank on the back of the car. How old is the car? It's rusted out. This is, I believe, the thing. That's what it's called. Is this not the thing? You know, it's funny. It's kind of an amalgamation. It's a Jeep, I think, originally of some sort. It's got to be from the 1960s or 70s. Perhaps the gas is evacuated. Well, we're not sure of that. It's in a metal container that's rusting.
So that's, that would be my recommendation to clean it and leave it immediately. Not sure why we have ordinances when the city doesn't enforce them. So that would be immediately. And then the boarding up of the roof, like councilor Camuso said, the porch, and then a meeting on, uh, whether or not, uh, this city I think is at the point where the wrecking ball should come out. Mr. President level this property, clean it up, and then, uh, worry about whatever suits that may be taken after the fact, because in my opinion,
I don't think these people have a leg to stand on with this particular property. And the infestation in this home is going to lead to infestation in the neighborhood. And that's a concern. And that's a concern if I lived next door that I'd be concerned about. So those would be my recommendations, Mr. President. It's nice to put up a sign saying City of Medford Danger Keep Out and the X, but that falls far short of the mark, Mr. President.
and what the city should be doing. Thank you. Counselor. Counselor care of yellow. Thank you. And then we'll take just on one last thing. Uh, I'd have to make a motion that we have the fire department immediately go down there tomorrow and remove the car. Uh, again, uh, with the exposed gas tank and who knows if there's any gas in there, but, uh, as a fire department can immediately get the car out of there.
uh, further amended by councilor Caviello that the fire department, uh, investigate the gasoline in the truck and remediate the situation immediately. So on the main motion of councilor Caviello as amended by the other counselors, all those in favor. Do we know from the building commissioner if the gas has been turned off in the home? We've received no communication to my knowledge from any, uh, departmental head.
regarding said property council. I can clarify. I believe shortly after the passing of Mr. Bagnold that the gas and other utilities were disconnected from the property. Okay. I would just say if we can have a report from the building commission or the building department to make sure in light of what we've seen in the news regarding gas and explosions recently, I don't want to alarm anyone, but we should have a report from the building department. Further amended by council marks that the building commissioner give a comprehensive report
regarding utilities at the property. On the motion of Councilor Caviello, as amended, all those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries. Thank you very much, sir. Thank you so much, all of you, and I appreciate the time and hopefully the prompt and speedy address. Would it be appropriate for us to return to the regular order of business? Moved by Councilor Camuso. Returning back to the regular order of business, 15-314, offered by Councilor Knight,
Be it resolved that the Medford City Council recognize Andrew Cronin and Adrienne Perrazzo on their receipt of the Boston Bruins Sportsmanship Award. Mr. Cronin is a member of the GBL Champion Medford High School Boys Hockey Team, and Ms. Perrazzo is a member of the GBL Champion Medford High School Girls Hockey Team. Both have had outstanding interscholastic hockey careers at Medford High School, while exhibiting the highest levels of sportsmanship and leadership
be it further resolved that they be invited to a future Medford City Council meeting to receive recognition and council commendation. Councilor Nice. Mr. President, thank you very much. I believe for those people at home who aren't watching the city council meeting this evening and are watching the Boston Bruins, in between the first and second period this evening, Mr. Cronin and Ms. Peraza will be awarded the sportsmanship award by the Boston Bruins.
And I've spoken with both their coaches, and I've actually had the opportunity to speak with both of them as well. They're both great kids, great student-athletes, and both have had really great accomplished careers, both in the classroom and on the playing field, Mr. President. Their coaches would like to come down and say a few words on behalf of the children when they do receive their citations, if this council is so willing to adopt the resolution. So I would like to reserve comment for the people that work directly with them and know them best, Mr. President. However, I'd ask my council colleagues to support this.
Uh, it's just another great thing. And another great representation of Medford, uh, you know, at the highest levels, Mr. President. So I'd ask that my council colleagues support the resolution. Seconded by councilor Camuso on the motion of council night. Seconded by councilor Camuso. They're certainly all welcome coaches in family. All those in favor, all those opposed. Passes 15 dash motion by councilor vice president Lugo current for suspension of the rules for the purpose of
Petitions, presentations, and similar matters. To take petitions, presentations, and similar matters. On the motion of Vice President Lundquist-Kern, all those in favor? Aye. Aye. All those opposed? Motion carries. 15-325, petition for a common vigilance license by Boston Bread LLC for Panera Bread Bakery Cafe, 499 Riverside Avenue, Medford, Massachusetts.
Sir, please state your name and record, and your name for the record. Should I do it twice, or my name and address? Your name and address for the record. Got it. Please. I'm getting there. No problem. Jason Berg, 45 Taylor Court, Streamwood, Illinois. Came a little late for tonight's meeting. Very good. I'm actually for Panera Bread and with Noodles and Company, which is also on the, I'm not sure where it is on the agenda. That's next. Or the franchising for both. We'll have you speak at that time. OK.
Councilor Caviello, Chairman of the Licensing Committee, for recommendation. Thank you, Mr. President. I reviewed the papers, and I find them in order. What are your hours of operation going to be at Panera? So we will be back. I understand we need to, I don't know if it's in front of you or for a special permit. We'd like to open at 5 o'clock in the morning and be open until 11 at night. So what are the hours now? The hours, well, we're not open yet. I mean, what are your hours, proposed hours? Proposed would be 5 a.m. to 11 p.m. No, your hours for when you opened originally. What are you looking for without a special permit?
Well, we're going to come here before. We're going to come see you before. License allows 7 to 11. So currently, you're going to operate 7 to 11? OK. And do you plan on serving alcohol on the property or no? No. All right. Listen, everything looks good. I think Panera will be a welcome addition to our community. And I recommend approval, Mr. President. Motion for approval by Councilor Caviello, Councilor Camuso. Thank you. And I second the approval.
Council marks was very instrumental with this new development down there in working with the neighbors in the entire Medford City Council To put a charcoal filter on so that the neighbors aren't overburdened by the smell down there. So just to Like to bring that point up And we actually have the filtration system right here. The gentleman just gave us so uh Once again, thank you. I know the neighbors were very interested in that
As well as this evening, I got a few phone calls from people that were down in Florida that live on 4th Street, and just wanted to make sure that it was brought up this evening. Very good. So on the motion approved by Councilor Caviello, seconded by Councilor Camuso, Councilor Penta. Quick question. Has the drive-through issue been resolved? Yeah, with the charcoal filter.
No, the drive-thru issue, not the charcoal filter. There was a drive-thru. Well, so the landlord came in for the special permit for the drive-thru. And I believe there's an issue with how it was, how the exiting was, but that has been, there has been a modification to that. So when was that done? Because we, I haven't seen the modification. No, the last time there was anything proposed, it was up to the planning board. We never saw the final, the final result.
We passed it on the condition that it be resolved, as requested. Turn your microphone. Right. Traffic, if you want to say that. You're right. That's right. And they put a pitch to it, a curve, a pitch, I don't know what you'd call it, so you weren't directly coming out into the traffic. I thought it was either you coming in or coming out on Riverside, but you're exiting. No, no. We're talking inside the parking lot itself.
No, I'm talking about them coming in or out off of Riverside Avenue. Are you coming in or off of Riverside Avenue? Out. Okay, that I can't speak to that. That's something that's a lot of hard work. Because that was the issue, remember? You brought up the idea, why can't they go back in between the two buildings if they exit and go down Commercial Street? Their license was granted on condition of straightening that out. And we saw the drawings, if I remember correctly, which included, I think, egress out to Commercial Street and
they were going to have signage that prompted you to take a right onto commercial, but you were able to go back into the stop and shop parking lot. Correct. But they were, they were prompting you to go out. And it was further recommended if we recall counselor to, uh, uh, have Riverside Ave painted, uh, indicating not to block the, uh, egress onto Riverside Ave, not to create a gridlock. Is Riverside Avenue an entrance or an exit?
I believe it's both, but I don't want to speak. I'm not going to, I don't want to speak to that for sure. That's what it wasn't supposed to be. I don't, I, I've never, I'm speaking out of information. Counselor cafe. Oh, and that other stuff. He's not pregnant. This gentleman is here for an hour and he's probably not qualified to answer those questions. The chair is in agreement with you. Can we get a report back on that? So this gentleman, I don't think I'm not from that. I don't think he's qualified to answer those questions. Yeah.
The chair will, the clerk will give us the decision regarding that matter. I mean, give us the report. They give us the final report. It's in our record. Can we get a copy of it? There's an entrance and exit from Riverside F and there's also an exit from the back of the pocket. So there is an entrance and exit from Riverside.
The issue was going into the stop and shop in Fells Plaza. We fought to get the additional entrance slash exit going in there. And Ocean State people agreed to let them use it. Right, and then to go out onto commercial. And then long term, I believe it was Councillor Marks or Councillor Penta, asked that to look into the feasibility of having a, what did you call it at the time, right turn only onto the Fellsway. So that you wouldn't even have to stop at a light.
There you go. This is not a motion for approval by council. KVL seconded by council. So all those in favor of a copy of the records, you can get a copy of the records. Yeah. The chairman will, uh, the clerk will, uh, forward the official document on the matter. All those in favor. All right. All those opposed. Congratulations to our friends at happy bacon. Thank you. 15 dash three 26 petition for common vigilance license by
Camera Noodles, LLC, doing business as Noodles and Company, 491 Riverside Ave, Metric, Mass. On file, business certificate, building department, police, fire, health, treasurer, letter of compliance, estate tax ID, workman's comp, application, et cetera. We open this up. Please state your name and address for the record. Jason Berg, 45 Taylor Court, Streamwood, Illinois. Thank you very much.
And we give the floor to Councilor Caviello. Thank you, Mr. President. Mr. President, I have reviewed the records again, and I find them in order. If you could give us a little, I don't think many people know about noodles. Can you tell us a little bit about noodles and what they're going to be? I think people think it's an Asian restaurant, but it's really not. I've seen some of your other establishments. Absolutely. We're actually new to the New England area. This will be our fifth one in the New England area, fourth in
fourth in Massachusetts. We have one up in, in Nashua currently, uh, currently right now, basically, uh, it's, uh, we call it noodles, your world kitchen. So basically you can get pastas from a different variety from the Mediterranean, from Asian, from, uh, American fair, as well as, uh, soups and, uh, some sandwiches and salads as an example of the menu I've, we're passing around to you right now. Again, that's another welcome addition to the community.
Will this establishment be serving beer and wine or any alcohol? Beer and wine, yes. Have you applied for your license there? We're working on that right now. Again, I wish you guys nothing but the best. Do you have a date for when this is looking at opening? So they're looking to turn the base building over to us in July when we'd start construction. So we would open about 11, 12 weeks after that. So somewhere in the fall?
So it would be definitely be this fall and we would do them both Panera and noodles while probably simultaneously. Again, let's say, uh, you'll be, you'll be a welcome addition to the community. Thank you. Is there a motion for approval? Counselor motion for approval was seconded by council. So did counselor Fenton wish to speak question? You, your hours of operation is 7am to 11. Are you coming in for extended hours or not? So the Panera is 7am to 11am. Sorry. The Panera is 7am to 11pm currently, right?
but we will come in for additional hours and request to hope to open at 5 a.m. The noodles and company will only be open from 11 a.m. till about 11 p.m. as well. So the noodles will not open early. Just the Panera or not require additional hours. I actually,
Through the chair, I was gonna ask about the timeframe too, but Councilor Carviel already asked. What about a filtration system on top of noodles or will that one system take care of all three? Well, we haven't looked at it. We have 11 currently operating noodles and company and we have not experienced really any odor because we don't have any grease fryers or anything of that nature. So there hasn't been a conversation around that.
And if it became a problem for the neighbors, would you be willing to, I mean, what's the avenue to request that? So, um, well, there's two avenues. There's a, there's a, there's a very, very, very expensive avenue. Uh, and, but we would set ourselves up in case something did, something did arise where we could address something and, you know, after the fact. So is there any build out that would have to be done prior to, that's what I mean. We would set something up. So just in case, but yes.
Oh, just make that a condition that something is set up. So if need be, filtration system is needed, that it's there, it's ready. On smash burgers, as opposed to a recommendation, if they agreed to, you know, that's what I mean. They, they would have, they just make it, they agreed that they would recommendation on a special permit. You couldn't put the condition on that.
It's a recommendation then, I think. So we're going to be clear about this, that the counselor, uh, vice president, uh, is making a recommendation that in your build out that you adapt your, uh, HVAC systems to, uh, accept the possibility of needing charcoal filtration as you've done with an era and your drive through. Yes. Thank you.
We did it for all three. I don't think we did it for noodles. We had to do it separately with the hamburgers. From what I heard from the landlord, it was the Panera was the charcoal. It was this full system for smash burger. And there was no comment from noodles. At least that's what she had told me. Yeah, I'd make that recommendation, please. So as a motion for approval as recommended, all those in favor. Aye. All those opposed.
Congratulations, your license is granted. Thank you. I just have one question. As far as outdoor dining licenses, is there a hearing? Sorry, obviously I've said something. You should have come here last week. Oh, boy. You can apply. You can apply. You just come back in front of the council. Okay. And the Board of Health has guidelines regarding that. Okay.
And as you prepare your site for that, maybe it would be helpful to know that the council has had concerns regarding noise generation at later hours in open-air dining areas, as well as concern for safety, lighting, and that those fixtures be designed in a way. I think you have nowadays ADA requirements there, but this concern that people
not gain access to those areas when the stores are closed or when dining has ceased at one establishment and not the other, et cetera. Yeah, correct. So at the end of each night, we would stack the furniture and it would get locked up. Something like that, yeah. Now with the noodles, it's a little bit different. At the noodles we have, or we're proposing, at the noodles, a gated area. So that would be enclosed. I mean, you could obviously exit, but it would be in a closed area.
Thank you. Very good. Congratulations. Thanks very much. Thank you. Thank you. Good luck. Thank you. 15 dash three 24 petition for class one auto dealers license by Lawrence M Gordon, president of colonial Volkswagen incorporated for colonial VW of Medford three 40 mystic Avenue, Medford mass. Oh, two one five five, sir.
Are you Mr. Gordon? I'm Brian Lafferty from Colonial Automotive Group, 626 Main Street in Concord, Mass. Thank you for entertaining our license. As the city council knows, I believe we're going to be moving our Volkswagen agency down to the new facility. Hopefully we're going to be open in a couple of weeks and the existing facility is probably going to, we're probably going to move one or other franchises into the existing facility.
So the operation at the new building will be essentially what was going on at the current Volkswagen facility. Thank you. So chair, uh, recognizes, uh, councilor Caviello, chairman of licensing for recommendations. President, I have reviewed the paperwork and I find it, uh, on an order. And, um, again, you guys did an excellent job in the building. Nice addition to the Avenue. I mean,
Great. Thank you. I appreciate the council saying that we really enjoyed doing business in Medford. Yeah. You guys have been good neighbors and no, we appreciate it. The city has been very good to us and they did an outstanding job with the property and thank you. Good luck. I appreciate it. Thank you very much. Thank you. So on the motion for approval by councilor Caraviello, council Camuso. Yeah. I'd just like to also comment on the, the build out of the property. You know, you look back a few years ago and Mr. Gav, when you first entered Medford before century bank was there, it was just the old building, a century bank.
next door, it was wide open, it was a truck place. It's just, you guys did an unbelievable build. I especially like the little wall out front. It's a lot of character and it's just a great escape. A little wall's a quarter of a million dollars. Yeah, a little wall. Marshall challenged us. We had a meeting in the beginning when they heard about it and he kind of challenged us to do well for that part of the city. He gave you an interest free loan.
No, he doesn't give anything away. No, I just, I just, seriously, it's a great, it's a great addition to the neighborhood. And especially now, too, if another, if you do move your franchise over to the other building, you'll be doing more updating, I'm assuming. We'll have to redo that facility, too. So we're looking at, we're looking at potentially two brand new
state-of-the-art auto sale places on Mr. Gav. Then you throw in a couple of the Graverones. I mean, Medford really is becoming... We did have a Nissan facility a couple of years ago. Yeah, the motorcycle dealership, the Nissan dealership. Mr. Gav really is becoming like the quarter-of-a-mile zone. They get the auto mile, we're like the auto quarter-of-a-mile. We're not there yet, but... Which one? Physical therapist, yes. Did he get his sign? All right.
So, yeah, but seriously, Mr. Gavrelli is on the rise. Look at the China, I don't mean to digress, Mr. President. A few years ago, this council took a bold vote to move forward the development of Dragon Villa, and look at it today. It's bustling with harrows, and at the time, there was some neighborhood opposition, but the council did what they felt was right, and look at it today. So, we're all there in the parking lot meeting. Good luck.
Thank you. The motion of President Caraviello, seconded by Councilor Camuso. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? License granted. Congratulations. Thank you very much. Appreciate it. Good luck. Thank you. Motion to revert. We can take 15.312. Motion of Chairman Caraviello to take 15-312 off the table. All those in favor?
All those opposed? Motions before us. 15-312 was tabled last week because there was some, uh, for unity cab, uh, was tabled last week because, uh, uh, their absence from a subcommittee meeting. They were present, I think, this evening. They were present this evening, Mr. President. And so the paper is before us to change licenses. To upgrade, upgrade a car. Yes. Uh, I reviewed the paperwork, Mr. President, and I find an order, a motion for approval.
So on the motion for approval by Councilor Caviello, all those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries. Congratulations. You can go ahead and move your cabbie medallion from one car to the other. It has to get it certified from weights and measures.
Mr. Brooks. All right. Thank you, Mr. President. So long as you're in compliance with the regulations overseen by the city clerk. So congratulations. Thank you. Drive safely. Two hands. Yes. Very good. Are we referring back to the order of regular order of business by councilor Camuso? All those in favor. All those opposed. 15 dash three one nine offered by councilor Knight.
be it resolved that the Park Commission lift any and all prohibitions concerning the playing of street hockey in our public parks. Councillor. Thank you very much, Mr. President. I was down La Conte hockey rink one evening and a number of young kids came up to me and I was talking to them about the game of hockey and whether or not they play street hockey. And one of the things that came up was that they're not allowed to play street hockey in the tennis courts at Placetet Park, although Placetet Park is lined for street hockey.
Which got me thinking, I said, well, why can't they? Has the park board put a prohibition in that's in place? And I did a little bit of research, and I don't see the park board actually taking an official action prohibiting such. However, there are signs up at the tennis courts that place the park. So I'm sure that the reason that the signs went up was because of outcry of some of the neighbors, I would imagine. However, in this day and age, when we're sitting here looking at an opiate addiction problem in the city of Medford,
a childhood obesity problem across the United States of America, I think that keeping kids out of our parks and keeping kids out of our recreational areas to participate in organized and unorganized athletics, it may be misguided, Mr. President. It may not be the right policy. So, you know, I'd like to see if there are any prohibitions in place concerning the playing of street hockey in our public parks, what they are, why they're in place, and whether or not they make sense, because right now I don't think that they do. Very good. So on the motion, I must say that
On my brief street hockey career in my youth, we used to play in the middle of Yale Street. I don't think you get away with it now. It was less traveled back then. So on the motion of Councilor Knight to request clarification from the Park Board. Please. Vice President Longo-Curran. Just the Park Board and
Director of Parks from DPW, Mike Nestor, maybe ask why those, I'm sure the Department of Public Works. I did ask Mike actually, he was the first person I spoke with about this and he said he's aware of no prohibition. Very good. Yeah, if we could just ask for history, why are there signs up then? There must be a reason. So I agree with you. I mean, I feel like our kids should be able to play. I don't know if there was any problems that had been caused in the past, but maybe if we can get some sort of update from anybody that may know.
and then try to move forward and try to resolve the issue. Mr. President? Councillor Camuso. I will support sending this to the Traffic Commission for an answer, but there was a lot of opposition to the street hockey, particularly at Playstead Park, from the houses down the end of Century Street at the time, senior citizens and stuff, they were very vocal. And I think that's why those signs did go up, but I'll support at least getting an answer from the Traffic Commission. Very good. Very good. So on the motion, all those in favour?
Motion passes. 15-320 offered by Councillor Knight. Mr. President, I withdraw the resolution at this point in time. On the motion of Councillor Knight to withdraw. Motion to withdraw. Yes. 15-321 offered by Councillor Penta. Be it resolved that the City Council further review the Craddock Bridge Rehabilitation. Councillor Penta. Mr. President,
This seems to be an ongoing saga that, well, it goes back many, many years. But just going back to January of this past year, strike that, January of 2014, we had received a public information bulletin that came out of the offices of Representative Donato and Senator Pat Jalen, indicating that after a long delay, and finally, money being put into the transportation bill, that the work on the aquatic bridge would be taking place.
and the work was expected to begin in the spring of 2014. That was the press release that came out. Subsequent to that, and I brought up that same question again earlier this year, there was a subsequent report and a story that came out in our local press that basically, from our director of OCD, who basically said, they know what we're expecting, meaning Department of Transportation,
We want communication with the people in our city. And at that point in time, DOT had made the comment of the following that the MassDOT project manager, Paul King, said, construction would take place day and night in order to finish the project in about two years. Night shifts will run from 10 or 10.30 p.m. to 6 a.m. and day shifts from 6.30 a.m. to 7 a.m. to 3 p.m.
Now, with that being said, and that was the report that just came out January 21st, 2015, a year after the fact, we had discussed this on the City Council. Then there was a letter here dated February 24th, 2015, just about a month after the January notice. It says that the project is expected to complete within 1,300 calendar days from the receipt of the notice to proceed.
and it states further, I encourage you to take advantage of this opportunity to reacquaint yourself with the project and ask that you share this invitation with the community's emergency service division and any other local officials or departments who may have any interest in this matter. That was a letter sent out on February 24th. We never got that letter. Mr. President, your name is on the letter. You were C.C.'d. Paul Gere, Cassandra Cugliatos,
Pat Jalen, Paul Donato, Sean Copley, and Christine Barber. Five elected officials got this letter. And we have yet to see it or hear or discuss it. And something is radically wrong. Absolutely radically wrong. I just cannot believe this council had this discussion in January. It was reported out. And then on February 24th, an official letter from DET in Boston with your name and four other elected representatives got this letter.
indicating that the project is going to be complete within 1,300 calendar days from the receipt of the notice to proceed. That's number one. 1,300 calendar days. There's 365 days in a year. That comes out to three years and 56 days, if that's around the clock. And if you want to make it around the clock and double it up, it comes out to
One year and 78 days, for which they won't do, because they've already told you what they're giving you for time schedule. Mr. President, I don't know why you didn't send it to us or get it. You're on here. You were CC'd. City administration was CC'd. The mayor was addressed to the mayor. We haven't received it. Yeah, the start date. And the start date is as soon as the intent to do, do, do, do. I will give you a copy of it.
Here's a copy for yourself. Thank you. You're welcome. I just think that the business community in this city is getting shot change so bad, so bad. We as councils have been on top of this issue for months, if not years. This started off as less than a $3 million project, and now they want to build a $13 million Taj Mahal bridge. It's only nothing more than 121 feet. And to tie up the business community in this city of Medford
to tie them up for well in excess of, never mind one year, two years, or three years, whatever it might be, to do what? What are they building here? We're not asking for anything outrageous. Just go in there and take care of the bridge the way it is. This isn't the Longfellow Bridge that they're spending millions and millions of dollars. It's a simple little bridge of 121 feet. And with the technology that's out there today,
But the technology that's out there today, and to say that it would take at least a year, at least a year if they wanted to even think about changing the conduits for the electric, the telephone, the gas, that's preposterous. We can go to the moon and back with a simple little phone and you can talk to someone.
You did the FAST-14. Sure, the bridges were built ahead of time. But this isn't a FAST-14. And if you read the whole thing, and it basically tells you, if you want to acquaint yourself with, what's there to be acquainted with? Shutting down businesses? The mayor of this community got this letter on February 24th. This council discussed it in January. The director of OCD said there has to be communication between all parties involved.
All three things have taken place. Councilor De La Ruza, whether you got the letter or not, I don't know. But five other elected officials got it, and none of us, not one of us, have been informed about this change in the process.
1300 calendar days. Figure it out. Around the clock, 24 hours a day, divided by 365, comes up to three years and 56 days. And if you want to double up the days and you give them good measure, it comes out to one year and seven. It will never happen. The cost of the overtime will be a killer for this bridge. Mr. Mayor, I'm asking you, Mr. President, I'm asking you to call for the Department of Transportation. The fellow's name is Paul Stedman.
He's the acting district highway director to appear before this council and explain, one, why we were never apprised of the letter and the information enclosed. And I want him to tell the people in this community when, in fact, that bridge construction is going to take place so every single business merchant that might be affected will know about it. And also, I don't want to hear the excuse that no mitigation is going to be provided for in this construction period.
Those are his three tasks, those are the three things, Councilor, Mr. President, and I would have hoped that my council colleagues would vote unanimously on a roll call vote and send that to him because this is just completely out of control, out of control.
You have elected people coming in here telling you one thing, having press releases go out. You have newspaper articles dating back to January of 2014 telling you it's going to start. We've been hearing this for years. I think it's since 2000. I think it was you, counsel, a long ago. I think I brought it up. It was you, 2007. We talked about the Craddock Bridge.
and you brought up, you just wanted an update as it related to the structure and the safety and the concern of the bridge. That bridge has been there for well in excess of over 100 plus years. It's sitting on solid granite. It hasn't sunk. It doesn't intend to sink. Why are we building a $13 million edifice?
What all we need is the road to be fixed so people can come and go to work and the business community in downtown does not have to be put aside or put out of business because I think that's exactly what would happen once this bridge closes. If I could just respond to that. Sure.
If I were in receipt of such a letter, I would have certainly forwarded it to the members of the council. Um, I cannot, uh, find it in my, uh, council briefing book. And, uh, I'm not aware of, uh, the clerk's not aware of, uh, well, if anything, it looks like it would have been addressed. Uh, the overall point would have been addressed directly to your office if you do a proper procedure. So it didn't get addressed like Memphis city council. I would, then I would open it up and,
made multiple copies, so if you could just address individually. But it was, Mr. Clerk, it was addressed to our Council President, State Senator Jalen, Representative Donato, Representative Garibaldi, and Representative Barber. And not one of them ever responded to the content of this notice. We had our conversation in January on the Council floor. It was reported out. Nothing, nothing like this was reported to us. And this came out on February 24th. Yeah, but he's asking me if he
if I received his letter. You wouldn't receive his letter. You're not Fred DelaRusso. He's Fred DelaRusso. That's what I'm trying to tell you. That's what I'm trying to tell you. I didn't receive it directly. You call that guy tomorrow. You just tell him. We're going to schedule a meeting and invite him, request his presence before us to update the council on the project, to address the issues of mitigation, which Councilor Penta has exercised leadership on.
and to address the subsequent issues, particularly around the length of time of the project and its effect on the business community. Councillor Knight. Thank you very much, Mr. President. Several weeks ago, we put a resolution forward relative to the Craddock Bridge.
working with our state delegation to coordinate the release of some bonded funds that were attained in the transportation bond bill, so that when construction on the Craddock Bridge begins, we don't have to wait another 50 years for the lights at Main Street and South Street to get fixed. And in my attempts to speak with some officials from MassDOT after
sending an email to an individual over there to ask for an update on the Craddock Bridge, and he sent me an email back saying, send me an email to remind me, which was just crazy to me. It was brought to my attention that they're looking to start before the end of this month. But when I followed up with some individuals in the DPW, they said, there's no way this project can start by the end of this month. So I certainly think that there is a huge communication gap here.
There is definitely a problem with the top-down communication from the super agency that we call MassDOT in the city of Medford, Mr. President. You know, I think that Councilor Pente is right on track with this one. We have to get somebody down here to fill us in on what's going on so that we can plan accordingly and move accordingly so that we can get done what we need to get done. You know, I think it's very important that these lights are addressed at the same time that the construction is addressed, that the bonded funding is addressed at the same time the construction is addressed.
And if the construction's coming out, and it's going to stop by the end of this month, I think that we really need to get rolling on this, Mr. President. So I applaud Councilor Penta for bringing the issue forward, and he has my support on the resolution. So you're going to call this guy and have him come in? Councilor Caviello. Thank you, Mr. President. On the motion of approval by Councilor Loco-Kern. Thank you. I attended most of the meetings with Councilor Penta, and one of the biggest concerns was even to
La Rondiz Rondo was communication, that there was minimal communication between the DOT and the OCD office on where this was going. Now, when was the last time we had a meeting, about a year ago? Carol's Diner, we had a meeting about a year ago. That was the last thing we heard. I heard that they were going to put the spring, the temporary bridge was supposed to be put up, and the ramp was going to be closed because they already have signs
saying that the ramp is going to be closed soon. So, but I haven't seen no mention of anything else, but again, um, we should have had some kind of meeting with the DOT, uh, just to keep us abreast of what's going on with this. And I say, yeah, a year that it's just the ridiculous. And I say, councilor Penta gets a letter that everyone else got that we know nothing about. Not acceptable. Was that letter published that you have? How did you get that letter?
Is that why I didn't get it? But like I said, it's been a year since we've had any contact with the state on where this is going. And I think at that time they said that they were going to get it done in less than two and a half years.
It was going to be two shifts doing it to get it done quicker. I don't know if that's still the case. It seems it, right? They're going back to one shift. At that time, it was supposed to be a double shift to cut off a year. Again, I think the DOT We really don't know. We don't know. It started at $3 million, went to $13 million. Now they're saying it's $10 million. Who knows what this bridge is going to look like?
And there was talk of them working 24 hours a week. Absolutely. Yeah, absolutely. Councilor Camuso. Two questions. The temporary bridge was supposed to go in prior to anything that was supposed to be the first piece of the puzzle. That's supposed to go in the spring. That's supposed to go in the spring. Exactly. So they've already, if you go by, you see the signs saying that the ramp is going to be closed by the spring on the 93 and on route 16. Okay.
And they're notifying the trucks already. So there's going to be some kind of notices on 93 for the trucks not to get off there. Yeah. Cause then the trucks only option before was going down to the Meffitt square exit and now they can't go on route 16. And the second thing is I think we have to, um, given the construction that's going to take place, I think we have to look now, I think is the reasonable time period to start looking for a new location for the bus stop in front of the real estate and the restaurant.
because certainly I don't want to have a bus stop around construction vehicles and there's going to be so much going on down there in that immediate area. People waiting for the bus should not have to be breathing in the diesel fuel exhaust and all that stuff. So if, um, if this city council, maybe that is, do we have a transportation subcommittee? If we can maybe send it to transportation to come up with a feasible relocation for the bus stop, um,
that's in the immediate area, but definitely that bus stop has to be moved, I think, for public safety, as well as for convenience to the people that traverse that area during this magnificent construction project. Councillor Kerrio. If I'm not mistaken, Councillor Camuso. That's amended by Councillor Camuso. I think the bus stop was talked about at earlier meetings, and they were very objectionable to moving the bus stop at all. Well, you know what?
You are correct, but my philosophy is the council is the only authority that has the jurisdiction to move the bus stops. At the time, I was adamantly against moving the bus stop because of the people using it, many senior citizens, children, and other individuals.
I'm not gonna sit here and allow senior citizens to breathe in the fumes from trucks hauling out debris and backhoes and everything else. That's, as far as I'm concerned, we're just lining people up to get sick. Part of the objection was people were objecting to the extra amount of time it would take for the bus to go up and make the extra loop. Yeah, well no one said that. We could possibly move it across the streets, closer to where the overpass is coming from Route 16, down to Route 16 from 93,
On the other side, across from the police station, something. I mean, I certainly wouldn't want my wife or my grandmother or my son waiting for a bus within 20 feet of construction vehicles. The bridge is right there, and the bus stop's right there. So if the members of the council agree, I think we should start looking at this as a subcommittee to move it. But I'd like to get a roll call vote on that, Mr. President, and come up with a feasible solution for the users, but also for the MBTA
Very good. So on the motion of for amendment by Councillor Camuso to send it to the subcommittee on transportation to address the movement of the bus stop and alternate routes in alternate locations for that. And on the main motion of approval. Yeah, we can do that. Yes. We, I was waiting for, for that on that one in particular is waiting for
This one on Main Street at the beginning of Main Street in the square, the one that Councillor Camuso mentions, because we received such resistance from the MBTA, because it required the changing of the routing of the buses, that's what made that difficult. This one in South Medford, I was just waiting word back from the solicitor on the property to do that. And I was waiting for word back from him only so we can just expedite it right here on the floor.
So, on the motion for approval by Councilor Langel-Kern, as amended by Councilor Camuso. All those in favor? Roll call. Roll call has been requested. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Sir, you wish to speak on this matter? Yes, please. My name is Michael Wajiro. I live in 18 Pembroke Street. I'm curious, have there been any complete architectural sketches of this bridge? Because I'm not aware of any. And if possible, could the council request one?
like a complete architectural sketch of what the bridge will look like, timetables of how this bridge is being constructed. You'll be getting before we did then. You'd be a better guy than us if you'd had them. So the DOT has like an architect on the plan? That they've changed multiple times? They just haven't shown it to you guys? We've seen some renderings.
but they've changed, but they've changed. Okay. They're public on the motion. Mr. Clerk, call the roll. Yes. Yes.
Yes. Seven in the affirmative, none negative. Councilor Penta's motion passes. 15-322 offered by Councilor Penta. Be it resolved that the mayor's ongoing refusal to respond to council resolutions timely or in a timely fashion be discussed. Mr. President, I don't know if you were on the council at the time, but it goes back some years ago that the mayor got himself in this
where I think it was in a December of a particular year. And as a result of the council resolution coming forward, and I think there was a newspaper story, I don't know what, one of the Boston newspapers, all of a sudden we started getting council resolutions responded to, something like 25. Okay, here we have tonight another page with some 20 plus resolutions not being responded to timely. Ones that I consider to be important are
We sent a resolution upstairs to our city engineer regarding the MS4 program and what the involvement might be as it relates to the city of Medford, our needs and the cost. And I believe I made a notation of a letter that was sent as it related what the EPA was going to be doing and to relate to the charge. It was going to be almost like an $800, $900,000 hit to the city of Medford. And it would have been nice if she jumped on board or at least the city of Medford jumped on board.
for the purposes of saying it would be a nutcracker at the particular time. We've had multiple issues regarding the water and sewer issues here in the city of Medford. Also, as it relates to expenditures for programs yet to be decided upon, and sitting on a $7.5 million surplus. We've constantly have been talking over the past, I think since the mayor decided to bring in the kiosk issues, constantly, again, with the mayor, making no responses other than saying within the purview of the council,
Well, if all these things are within the purview of the council, then maybe we should just take the action that needs to be taken. Also, we had a street revitalization program. Where's his response to that? Where's his response to Councilman Longo's 3-1-1 program? We've had cable issues. The dog park. Five months. 3-1-1. 3-1-1. The dog park. Constantly on the cable issues in this community, where he's sitting on approximately $300 million of taxpayers' money
strike that, $300,000 of taxpayers' money, of ratepayers' money on cable issues. You know, we have asked and we've asked for where is that public hearing on public access, the whole Comcast 10-year contract, which is coming up April 18th, and once again, no response. And I know that will be coming up at another time. I just think it's terrible. You know,
Again, we as a council, we've had our issues between and amongst ourselves, but at least we were able to discuss them. We were able to get them out on the floor and talk on them. You vote them up, you vote them down, whatever it might be. This mayor, if it doesn't fit his agenda in any way, he just will not respond. And I think what happened back then was a motion and a movement for, I think it was a motion of, what was it? Not non-support.
What the hell was the motion? What was the motion? Do you remember, Councilman Max? Because the mayor was refusing to respond to a vote of no confidence. That's what it was, a vote of no confidence, because he wasn't responding to our council resolutions, which basically, they're not for us. They're for the taxpayers of this community. And then all of a sudden, immediately, you saw 25 of them come at you, and everything went good for a while, and now we're right back to the same old thing. So with that being said, Mr. President, we do have a rule that talks about 10 days.
that I believe it's 10 working days subsequent to any resolution that takes place. So, Mr. Clark, I'm going to ask you to do the following on your sheet, just to put one additional line in here, and that's the 10-day line, okay? If the response hasn't come in in 10 days, you have department respondent, date respondent, I would like to have you another line in there to put the 10-day notice, that the 10 days has come and gone. That way there, you know,
It's fair and it's open for everyone, and that way people aren't going to try to figure out what the hell are all these lines supposed to be. So, with that being said, Mr. President, I just think it's about that time. Craddock Bridge, another perfect example. You know, you get the letter, no information coming back, forthcoming. You have to find out all this stuff on your own.
It's almost like you have to be your own detective to do your own work, because the city administration just doesn't want to participate. But then all of a sudden, when they want something, they're on top of you. You've got to vote for this, and if you don't vote for this, you're anti-this. Councilman Marks, perfect example. He and a group of people started because the mayor wouldn't do anything with a dog park, because the mayor said it was going to be over $200,000 to do a dog park.
Council Marks and a group of people get together, they figure out a place, they put something together, and what's the mayor do? The mayor tries to, you know, grandstand and take it away. With all due respect, Councilor Camuso, it was your issue that brought up the thing on the opiates and the drugs and the addictions in this community. And the mayor pulled not only an end run, he tried to pull the rug right from under you to try to make it look like it's his deal now. And that's not right. Councilor Longo, you had the thing on 311. Nothing, no response to that at all.
It's just, we could go on to each council and what they were here for. He's just not responding. And these resolutions are too important. So Mr. Clerk, my council colleagues, I'm asking that the clerk change his tracking system to include one extra column and that's the 10 day. Once the 10 days are up, at least we know it. And then the council at that point in time can either take its vote to override them or do what needs to be done.
On the motion of Councilor Pinto, all those in favor? Wait a minute, these people. I'm sorry, Mr. Citizen. Please state your name and address for the record. Thank you, Mr. President. Robert Cappucci, 71 Evans Street. I'll be 45 this year. I grew up my whole life in Medford. Over the last few decades, I'm sorry, I hate to say it, but I'm seeing Medford deteriorate. We've got all these wonderful resolutions that this council has offered.
to combat things like string of robberies on Salem Street recently, this heroin addiction problem, the police department falling apart, the police force itself understaffed, the fire department doesn't have an internal email system. I was shocked when the president of the union said that a few weeks ago here. I mean, we can just go down the list of things, and it all comes back to our strong Mayor Plan A charter.
You can, with all due respect, Councilor Penter, you can put the 10-day line on it, but at the end of the day, the real power that this council has is on the budget and cutting the budgets. You can make resolutions and recommendations, but it's, and with all due respect to the mayor, I mean, I see him at events, he's a really nice guy, he always says hi to me, but it's just that office. There's too much concentrated power in one office. Now, I tried years ago with Dr. Sturela
to get a petition going to have our charter reviewed. And it's been almost, what, 30 years, Councillor Marks, since our charter's been reviewed? I mean, how many of these small businesses out here work under the same business model as 1986, 87, 88? I don't think any of them. If this council has the power and authority to implement a charter review,
It's long past due. I love Medford with all my heart, and I'm just seeing it change, and not for the better. Don't get me wrong, there's a lot of good things about Medford. We have a lot of great potential here, location to the city, right off the highway here. We could do so much for the businesses and the community of Medford. With all due respect, I know you folks work hard,
But it makes a lot of us ask, why is this council one of the highest paid in the state? Why is the mayor one of the highest paid in the state? For all that money, it seems like, including yourselves, we should all be getting a little bit more. And all these resolutions that are coming down the pike, that are going unnoticed, unrecognized, unresponded to. With all due respect, again, to the mayor,
What Councillor Camuso said a few weeks ago was spot on. It's leadership that's tired. And we need to review the charter of the city government here in Medford because it needs to be looked at and based on recommendations by the Charter Review Commission, it most likely probably should be changed. I think a lot of great testimony for that change was given tonight by the Honourable Robert M. Penta. Thank you so much for your time.
deeply take that under advisement. Thank you. Thank you very much, Senator. Sir, please state your name and address for the record. Joe Villione, 59 Garfield Ave., Medford. I like that word, override, I heard. That's a good one. I have been talking about public records requests to this council. The mayor has emails. The mayor has notes. Start putting public records requests in and start requesting those notes, those documents. It's very important.
I'll give you a quick story. Today, I went to the mayor's assistance office, very nice woman. She got to another woman who does thewhen the mayor has the press conferences, she said, Mark is handling it, meaning Mark Rumley. So I went to Mark Rumley's office. Now, this is the third visit. Mark was in a meeting. I talked to Janice. She's very nice. Mr. Rumley got back to me and said, Peter Epstein is the attorney for the city. And I wrote back, Mark, you're not answering my question. When is the Comcast public hearing?
So just me, a citizen, as the council president calls us, Mr. Citizen, yes, if the council can't get this, but think about this, I'm asking, that letter you saw from Comcast, it was eight months to a year ago that I started putting in public records requests, November 20th, and I finally got information on St. Paddy's Day. I mean, I asked in November, the letter came in in December, and you city councilors and all the citizens out there, Councilor Pinto's right.
You have to be a private detective around here. And today, I'm in the private detective mode. Comcast knows. Peter Epstein knows. You people all know. They are not responding to this Comcast public hearing because they don't want to have it. On the motion of Councilor Penter, all those in favor. Roll call vote has been requested. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Councilor Camuso? Yes. Councilor Cavillo? Yes. Councilor Knight? Yes. Vice President Longo Kern? Yes. Councilor Marks? Yes. Councilor Penta? Yes. President DelaRusso? Yes. Seven in the affirmative, none negative. The motion passes unanimously. 15-323 offered by Councilor Penta. Be it resolved that the continued lack of the city's public safety action after having been
put on notice for well over three weeks regarding its downtown lighting and the chronic power outage problems, once again, having occurred this past week in Medford Square, costing the businesses thousands in loss of revenue, employee time, and loss of product. And this is at least the third time within the past year this loss of electricity has occurred, be it further resolved that a representative from National Grid and the mayor's office
needs to appear before the council to address this matter and address what upgrades are needed, when it will be completed, and will businesses be reimbursed for loss of revenue and product, as well as the ongoing kiosk fiasco that continues to upset customers in small business locations throughout our city. Councilor Penta. On this matter, Mr. President,
There are six street lights that are out in the heart of Medford Square. I mean, you have to be blind, or maybe you will be because... Visually impaired. Visually impaired, or whatever you want to call it. I don't know what the mayor doesn't see that everyone else can see. Maybe he doesn't go out at nighttime, or maybe he doesn't go through Medford Square. Problem being, everyone that does go to the square, it's a public safety hazard, it's a public safety risk. Once again, this past week,
Electricity went out in Medford Square. Many businesses were affected by this, affected to the point that it's not the first time that this has happened. And as a result of the businesses being out and lost employee time and loss of product, again, the employees were not notified. There has been no updates. You just have to figure this out. And I think when you hear all the sirens going around on a particular morning trying to figure out what it is, was it a bank robbery or was it something? It was the lights that were out. Also, those lights that were out
I believe the same situation happened again today when the electricity went down at the McGlynn School. And as a result of the electricity going down, I don't know if it was an extended period of time or what have you, I was led to believe and I thought that these schools all had backup generators for the purposes of if they lost the electricity. No, I don't know. This is a couple of parents called up and they were upset over the fact of the matter is that, you know, this took place today. Why and how it happened, I don't know, but apparently it did.
Back in, I think it was 2001 or 2003, if the city remembers correctly, I think it was in June or July, there was an extreme power outage in the city, and it was down for an extensive period of time. And National Grid came in, and I believe that it had something to do somewhere off of, I can't think of the name of the street, where they have their transmission lines. And they came in there and they put a brand new electrical service into the city of Medford, Mr. President. And what they did,
And I believe they put a corollary line that was next to it. So just in case, the outage because of the use of electricity, I believe it was a hot summer, this would not happen again. It would just jump to this other line. Now, whether this happened at the school today or not, I don't know. Whether all the businesses or how many businesses got affected in Medford Square, I don't know. But it's apparently, you know, when people call and express their concern as to why this is happening, and they can't get an answer, and it's going to be corrected,
You have to deal with the business in and of itself. Was there a loss of product, loss of employee time, a loss of business? And the overtime that the police department had to pay to go over there now is direct to traffic and to move people around. Now, you take all of that, and you just add on one more effect, one more effect that's affecting the people here, and that's the kiosk and the square once again. And what's going on, I don't know. But this was one heck of a week. Because no sooner did we meet this past Tuesday night,
Last Tuesday night, the very next day I'm in Medford Square and there's a gentleman at 634 trying to put money into a meter. And I was there with my wife and we said to him, listen sir, you don't have to. It stops at six o'clock. He says, I don't know that. No sign said that, okay? Six o'clock, eight to six. No sign said that. This was 634. I have another one. I have another one here. This one here is dated on 324.
738, supposed to start at 8 o'clock in the morning, 738 AM, giving out tickets. Now, people who are paying, anyone who might be paying right now, you have to realize something. It's 8 to 6 in the morning. It became effective March 15. That's when the Traffic Commission voted upon it. That's when our city solicitor said it was legal and we could do it. And that's when the bounty hunters from Tennessee said it's OK, then we're going to go with these new laws. So every dime and every quarter that they're collecting
is I would say it's right now it's illegal. They are wrongly collecting and taking money out of that, out of those meters from people that are going there. Councilor Caviello, you said on December 23rd in your resolution that you wanted a 60-day report, a financial report as to what they were doing, effective when it becomes operative. Councilor Knight, that was your term, when it becomes operative.
And we agreed to that. January 15th is when they went online. March 15th has come and gone, and we have received absolutely nothing. Today is March 31st, nothing, zero. Mr. President, again, this past week on Riverside Avenue, not Riverside Avenue, the ring road, excuse me, where the ring road is, once again, that truck that they own, those bounty hunters from Tennessee,
who park their truck illegally, illegally on the ring road, and they have the audacity to go out there and give tickets. It's not marked like it's supposed to be in the back. They're giving out tickets erroneously, because if people are getting there before 7, strike that, before 8, and after 6 at night, they're still tagging them and giving them tickets. Councilor Camuso, they want to go back.
Remember what we talked about? They thought it was going to be a great idea, putting the $5 thing down there and place that road by Winthrop Street. Now we're down to one, with a main plate. A main plate, okay, the other guy's on vacation. A main plate of a guy sitting down there, okay, and that's all that they're getting. Those cars that were parking there have now filtered their way into the West Mefford area. Go to the downtown West Mefford Square.
Warren Street and all the side street. That's where the cars are parking. Go to West Medford and strike that. You go to Medford Square, the people, they say, oh yeah, the spots are there. The spots are there because people don't want to pay to put their money into the quarter. Go into CVS and talk to the people there. They're actually having fights with people who are in the armory parking in the CVS parking lot, which that's not their parking lot. Because people don't want to pay to put that quarter in there.
I was talking to a dentist's office. These two women that were in there. I was in the eye doctor today. Four people in the last two days basically saying, you know, we're not coming back to the square because, you know, it's bad enough you can't figure out where the kiosk goes and where it's supposed to be. Five or six cars up, five or six cars back. But how do you go there and put the money in there? How do you know when you go to a doctor or a dentist you're not going to be longer than what they expect it to be?
The stupidest thing of this whole thing, Councilor Camoso, I'm going to go back to what you originally said in the beginning. If in fact the mayor had meters put in, people would understand what a meter looks like. They would know how to put the money in the meter. These kiosks are just doing damage. Go to the gentleman.
Pardon me? Boston's doing 1,000 new meters. But remember the new meters that Boston is doing. Don't give them any compliments, because they have figured this thing out. If it's prime time of the day, and that metered spot is something that they need, they can raise the price on those meters mechanically, technology, from where they are. So you could pay a quarter or one minute for 15 minutes, and you could pay a quarter for five minutes if they decide that that's the route that they want to go.
Mr. President, I have a resolution on here, as you know. What I would like to do is to take my other resolution that is, it was from last week, 15-307, take that off the table, and I would like to make a motion, take the motion from that, Mr. President. Mr. President, we have Councilor Blumel who wanted to speak next.
Yes, with regards to the parking program, I think we need to sit down as soon as possible with the Chief of Police, somebody from Republic, whether it's at a Committee of the Whole meeting. There are some serious issues. Let me communicate from the Mayor's office regarding setting up that meeting. So I'm going to call for a Committee of the Whole meeting next week.
which will include members of the traffic commission and members of the administration who are key to this and representative Nash of the Republican parking. That would be great. I mean, we're all getting the emails, the complaints, the concerns, and it just seems like Republic really, really, really needs to get it together. There was three people waiting in line for a kiosk and I got calls that they're standing there giving
tickets out to the people that are actually waiting in line for the kiosk. I also got complaints with regards to the kiosk in front of Alamo Roast Beef, Cosmopolitan Realty. They're giving tickets even though people are paying for time. You know, the people are fighting with the actual person giving a ticket, saying, look at it, it's five, I have till 5.50, yet he's giving them a ticket at 5.30. So there's just some serious, serious problems. It's bad enough to get a ticket.
if you don't pay, if you went over or you're stuck in a doctor's office, to actually pay and get a ticket or to be in line to pay and get a ticket while you're standing there. I mean, people are getting apologized to by the actual parking enforcement officials. So we need to have Republic get a grip and everybody be on the same page and run this program. I mean, this program's tough enough. We need to run it properly.
We need to run it properly and we need to give recommendations. We've helped change the hours, reduce the hours by two hours a day, but more needs to be done or this isn't gonna work and our businesses are gonna suffer. Councillor Marks, wish to speak? Just if I could briefly, Mr. President, on the two different points that Councillor Penta raised in his motion. I think from National Grid, we should also get back, I think it was two years ago, Councillor Penta, when the last outage, was it two years ago?
that they said it was a transformer, a faulty transformer, and that they were upgrading it. As you probably recall, too, we have a problem with the signal lights down in the square, too, and that was being upgraded at the same time. But if we can get a report back from National Grid, this frequency is far too often on Riverside Avenue Square, and it poses a real hardship on the business owners. And secondly, Mr. President, I was told that they had to hold off work until the 300-pound
the cement planter, which was placed strategically over the metal grate in the sidewalk that leads to the transformer underground was moved. So whoever put these planters in the square, put one over the access box into the transformer. So I think the city should look in the rest of the length of the square to see if any of these giant planters are placed on an access box.
Councilor Pentland has been mentioning this about the kiosk. It's unacceptable to have no hours of operation listed, or I should say hours of operation that are no longer in use. And in reality, it's robbery. It really is. There's no other way to call it. If you know that you're charging for a time that you're not supposed to be charging for, that's robbery. That's white collar robbery. If a businessman
did something contrary to what was advertised, they'd be charged by the Federal Trade Commission. I don't know how they're allowed to get away with that. I really don't. And I don't know why this administration who signed the contract isn't standing up on behalf of not only every resident, but anyone that comes into our community and say, you know what, enough's enough. The hours were changed to have ample opportunity. Councilor Caviello talked about having the signage
regarding the times to be put on the kiosk itself so people can clearly see it. He also talked about having it so you could see each kiosk from a distance, having some type of flag, something that shows where the kiosk are. Councilor Camuso mentioned about changing the color of the tickets that they're giving out from white to a red or an orange ticket. You know, I just don't see anything happening, Mr. President, with this program.
Um, and it really frustrates me when I see residents being tagged, uh, or having to put money in a meter that the hours of operation have changed. It really frustrates me. And, um, you know, something needs to be done immediately. And, uh, we, we may get to the point where we need to tell people, stop feeding the meters. I mean, it may, it may have to come a groundswell, say stop feeding these meters until this
company is able to get their business in order, I don't think they should be charging, Mr. President. I really don't.
You know, we were sold a bill of goods. These machines were going to be able to put money in with your iPhone, this, that. We sold a bill of goods, and meanwhile, they can't change the hour of operation. They can't indicate on the screen, hey, now it's 8 to 6. It used to be 7 to 7. That, to me, seems like a basic, you know, key entry that you plug in the central computer, and it goes to all kiosks. I don't understand what's happening.
I really don't. It's frustrating. And I would hope, Mr. President, under your leadership that we get this meeting immediately. And if the mayor doesn't want to attend, good luck to him. But we'll call all the other parties together, Mr. President. Thank you. Thank you. Councilor Camuso. Thank you, Mr. President. I do know that just from firsthand experience that they can be reprogrammed and they are programmed right now. So at seven o'clock, they don't accept any more money.
15 minutes of 7, quarter of 7 the other day, the machine would only take one quarter from me on Saturday evening because it was still programmed to 7 o'clock rather than 6 o'clock, but it didn't allow me to put in anything after 7. So it's definitely the information technology side. It just has to be adjusted. I think what we should also ask the city administration to put out a reverse 911 call advising the entire community
That the meters are now in effect until 6 p.m. With the new revised hours so that people it's one way to get it get it out there quick a big blast to the community and And then word of mouth and everything else will take over from all the businesses in our business districts But that's an effective way to get it out there at least Real quick to as many households as we can until the signs of change as councillor mock stated I mean even
I was trying to be helpful to someone the other day in West Medford. The gentleman was a Saturday night, my wife and I were on the way to Medford Square, and there was a guy in West Medford, 6.30, putting his money in the machine. And I turned, we pulled over, the machine's on, sign right here says 7 o'clock, they're going to Bistro 5 or something, they're all dressed up. I'm not gonna argue with the guy, I'm trying to do him a favor, he's getting argumentative with me that I'm telling him that the thing's off at 6, so. Meantime, I come down the square,
And I just go up to see if it will accept the money, because this has been a topic that's been discussed here at the council. And it did take my money until 7 o'clock, and then it shut off, maximum amount of time allowed. So it can be done, if we can get an update. Hopefully it's done prior to the meeting you're going to call next week for reprogramming these machines, and also reverse 911 call to get it out there. Point of information, Mr. President. Point of information, Councilor Marks. Considering, Mr. President, that this particular company has the plates,
of everyone that fed the meter from six to seven, it can reimburse these people. I would offer that as, as a motion that, uh, since this was implemented, that people receive reimbursement if they fed the meter from six to seven, Mr. President. And it's at no fault of the residents of this community. It's the fault of, uh, Republic and this administration too, Mr. President. So, so on the main motion of the reverse to, I'm sorry, Penta,
for approval amended by Councillor Marks, Councillor Camuso and again by Councillors Marks and Vice President Lungo Kern. I can support that but I think they purge all the information according to the contract. They have to purge anything that's not a violation.
I'll support it in theory, but I would be surprised if they can actually do it. But I understand why you want to do it. I would doubt if I could, I would doubt that they're purging anything if they're not able to turn the machines off in the right time. So I'm not sure what they're doing to be honest with you. Point of information and councilor Camuso is all set. Um, yeah. So if we could ask the administration to do the 911 reverse 911 call as well as reprogram the machines, the company reprogrammed the machines.
Fort Worth and refunds if you can do it. Councilor Carviello. Thank you, Mr. President. Mr. President, now that snow is all gone, I think it's time that we stripe the parking spots where the parking is. I mean, the signs are very confusing. I have no idea where these free spots are. I look for them and I don't know. I mean, I've seen, I mean, I see 30 minutes pay meter. I don't know if that's, if I can park there for 30 minutes or I got to pay for 30 minutes. I mean,
There's nothing that says free parking. So I'll give you my own little story today. I was in the square, I went, I parked, and I come out and I see the gentleman standing at my car. I kind of wait, and I look, I said, geez, I said, I look at my ticket, and I got a few more minutes left. So I walk up to the guy, and he's punching my thing in, he says,
I said, listen, I still got a couple more minutes. He said, Oh yeah, I know. He was standing, he was waiting for my two minutes to expire. And then he was going to write me up a ticket. No, he was following me. The signs are confusing. Uh, you know, they're, they're, they're, they're still saying seven to seven. Um, you don't know what spots are free. Uh, you know, it's very confusing and I know they're still taking money on Sundays. Amended by councilor Caviello.
Councilor Knight, point of further information, Councilor Banta. The sign here, Councilor Caviello, the sign says 30-minute limit parking. Yeah, but is that free? No. Well, those are the two- It says pay META. Thanks to Councilor Marks, those are the two free 30-minute parking that at the last, I think it was March 3rd or March 15th at the Traffic Commission, they now put them in all four squares. So you see the signs there. But they say 30 minutes pay META. No, this says 30-minute parking.
And then it says Monday through Saturday, 7 a.m. to 7 p.m. People think they gotta pay the meter. It doesn't say free. People are parking there and they're paying the meter. That's what a bounty hunter does. Gets as much as they can when they can. Pay the meter where it says pay the meter. Counselor Knight. Sir, you wish to address us. Please state your name and address for the record. Good evening. Anthony D'Antonio, 12 Yale Street, Medford.
The magic word I saw in Mr. Councilor Penta's motion was kiosk, and there's many problems with the parking program as it exists. However, all I'm here for right now, because it was an intro for me to come up here and speak, is a suggestion to the City Council. What I would like to see, you know we've had one bad winter. Everybody, every business owner has been affected one way or the other. We've had this parking program that's been implemented. The residents have been impacted by it.
There isn't one business, 80% of the businesses out there have been affected negatively in remuneration for their work. I mean, it's been terrible. I know some people in business, and they're hurting, and the winter didn't help, and the implementation of the parking program didn't help. I have a suggestion. Can this council, through a vote or whatever, say, okay, we've got a very special weekend coming up,
What do we say? We knock off the parking enforcement Friday and Saturday so that the vendors and the businesses that do a lot of the business, especially on this coming holiday weekend, get a little bit back. I think the city owes it to them because you can't do anything about the snow, but we can certainly do something about this terribly implemented parking program because it wasn't ready. It was not ready for prime time. And if anybody should get a ticket, then on the, uh, onus of Republic that they,
not only reimbursed, I just canceled the tickets out, but give the people a chance to do some shopping again. I mean, it's like a ghost town out there, you know, on Saturday. Now, a week ago, we had the leprechaun race. That's a great cause. I mean, that's, I have no qualms with that, but maybe the next time, maybe do it on a Sunday or something, because that also affected the businesses because I didn't realize the enormity of the blockages to get into the square. Usually I can, I can get into the square by all the sides. They had everything blocked.
It was a good event, but then again, it also affects other people, the same way as the bridge is going to affect a lot of the store owners. And I still want to see why they want to put the bridge there. And I want to see where the safety issues are. Why are we letting buses go over it? Why are we letting trailer trucks go over it? There are safety issues there, but I think they can be corrected. I don't want to get too off the subject, but we ought to send state engineers over to Rome and have them take a look at the Coliseum, what they're doing in rebuilding the Coliseum.
I mean, it's incredible. I don't agree with what's going on with the state, with this program. But anyway, the thought was just to see if we can do something for the people this weekend. We'll have Barry Clemente give a little tune. Thank you. Thank you. Ma'am, you wish to address the council. Please state your name and address for the record. Thank you. Jean Martin, 10 Cumming Street. And I just want to say two things, which is number one, how you can have a meeting without the principal person who signs the contracts
is, you know, why are we doing this again where you're setting up the fall guy to be the chief of police again? So he takes all the heat. It's just, I mean, I know why you guys know that you have to do it this way, but why are the people putting up with this? Why are the people not getting behind the chief of police and saying, look, he's got enough to do?
doing his job, why isn't the mayor, who is the responsible party for this, the one taking the heat for his own program? He's the one that signed the contract. Okay? That's just number one. And number two, because it's just not fair. It's not right. It's just not the way it should be done. It's not fair as relative.
The mayor uses his administration as the fall guys, and then he makes deals with them. And the people need to just start calling the mayor and tell him to show up to these meetings, because he's the one that signed the contract. He's the principal party here. It isn't the chief of police. He has enough to do dealing with an understaffed police station. Yeah, like, why is he doing the favors for the mayor? I don't know, because he's dealing with a building that's 50 years old, and he's dealing with an understaffed police department.
That said, the other part of the problem that I see is why is Diane McLeod the ticket person? She's in charge of multiculturalism or whatever, diversity or something like that.
What does diversity have to do with parking tickets? And why, again, did she take that responsibility on when it's completely non-related? Why isn't it in the position of the, I don't know, police department or something, put a captain on it, somebody that understands the policies of public parking. Put one of the captains on it, put, you know, something, I don't know, hire a guy.
to do it, hire a person to do it. If that's what you want to do and you're going to make all this money, then make that part of the deal. Give them $20,000 a year part-time to take on parking tickets. But why is Diane McLeod, the diversity person in charge of ticket judgments, makes no sense? There's a reason for that behind the scenes that we don't know. That's all I got to say. Thank you.
Good evening, sir. You wish to address the council, please state your name and address for the record. My name is Michael Ruggiero. I live in 18 Pembroke Street. I would like to bring to the council's attention the part of the contract, the RFP attachment, page 17 report, subsection 16 AA, says that the Republic Parking has to provide daily, week, I'm quoting, daily, weekly, monthly, and annual field sortable reports
summarizing all citation, boot, tow, collection, repayment activity. As of right now, according, if they have delayed that reporting for over 60 days, they are in violation of their contract. They only have 30 days to actually report that information. Also, under the signage section, also from the RFP attachment, they are required, under section 12, signage.
They are required to replace or repair missing damage signs within 48 hours. So they are also responsible to maintain signs. If they are in violation of the contract, which appears to me, just from what we've heard and what's been said so far, then if they don't fix it in 30 days, they have to leave. Thanks.
Will the clerk please read the amendments back? The clerk is going to read the amendments back. So 15.323 is what we're working off of here, is that correct? We are dealing with 15.323 offered by Councilor Penta. And we have a reverse 9-1-1 amendment, a reprogramming amendment, a refunds amendment?
uh... we get the reprogramming of the uh... kiosks and creating a refund uh... reshaping parking spots uh... let me see this one here is uh... more related to the electricity side uh... report back on the
who is placing planters on the access boxes, and report back on the past outage at Riverside Avenue 2 years ago.
That's on your regular resolution, isn't it? Yeah. Point of information, Councillor Camuso. Could Councillor Penter introduce his resolutions by topic? Because first we've got the kiosk stuff, and then it's in with this one, and then we have the National Grid stuff. Would you be amenable to do that so we can... But it all happened this week.
I understand but listen we did proper parliamentary procedure I must say so I would just rather vote on it it's like voting it just doesn't make sense the way we're taking a vote on this I'd like to at least break it down by topic you get National Grid you get the kiosks then you get the power outage it's we're all over the map here
Why don't we have something before us? Let's take it. We've gone through the amendments. So, on the motion of Councilor Pinto for approval. Roll call. Roll call vote has been requested by Councilor Camuso. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Camuso. No. Councilor Caviello. Yes. Councilor Knight. No, Mr. President. Please be recorded that I'm agreeing in theory, but I'm in opposition based on the language. So noted.
Do you have that Mr. Clerk? Vice President Ronald Kern? Yes. Councilor Mox? Yes. Councilor Penta? Yes. President Del Russo? Yes. In the vote of five in the affirmative, two in the negative, the motion passes. Request of Councilor Penta to take 15307 off the table.
All those in favor? Roll call has been requested on that. Roll call has been requested to take this item off the table. This was to suspend the contract last week. It was the motion to suspend the contract. Roll call to take it off the table. On the motion of Councilor Camuso to take the matter off the table, a yes vote would take it off the table. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Camuso? No. Councilor Caviello? Yes.
Councilor Night? Yes. Vice President Lowell-Curry? Yes. Councilor Marks? Yes. Councilor Penta? Yes. President DelaRusso? No. A vote of five in the affirmative, two in the negative. The matter is before us. Councilor Penta? Last week when we were discussing 15-307, there was a bunch of resolutions and amendments that were on there.
One of the amendments reads as follows. It's offered by Councilor Knight. It says, amended by Councilor Knight, that a meeting be called with all the parties concerned as previously requested in 30 days and prior to that meeting within 14 days, the Council meeting to share their concerns, complaints, and recommendations. But if I understand it correctly, you, Mr. President, are going to be calling
this meeting for next Tuesday night. Is that true? I'm going to probably do it for Wednesday night. So we have all the departments heads here and we're not at loggerheads with the council meeting itself. The 5.30 City Council meeting. I'm sorry? 5.30 City Council meeting. Is next week? On Tuesday. Is on next Tuesday. So that's why. I'm not going to be here.
No, no, I want to go to the amendments.
So I'll be announcing, uh, by the end of this week, the, uh, schedule for the committee of the whole regarding, uh, the parking and inviting the, or requesting that the, uh, parking commission, uh, and others, uh, be present with us, uh, the floor to counsel Penta. I just want to make sure everybody has enough time. So they can't say that they can't be here next week. They've got other commitments and stuff like that. So, um, with that being said,
I'll be willing at this point in time to hold off on my resolution to opt out of the contract until that meeting takes place, but subsequent to that meeting, that resolution, Mr. President, I will once again reinduce that the city of Medford opt out of the, where's the wording here that says the following? It says, put it back on the table for the purposes of a vote. So.
motion to table. Well, I think it would be maybe just to leave this in the, we just took it off the table and we're going to put it back on the table. So that way there are parties that you want to put together at least have more than enough ample time. Everything that councilor Caviello was talking about these reports and everything, you know, and that, and that's it. And I'm under the impression that the, uh, the per diem reports are generated automatically. Absolutely. Go to the appropriate. I mean, we're not the, uh,
organization that ought to receive them. So I mean, they're in the purview of enforcements or the police chief, and I'm sure. But you also have constant violations in the contract. And Mr. Leggero was correct. The two sites and sections that he announced. The fact that the cars aren't even. But we asked for them. Yeah. I don't know if they're our business, but in any event, there's a motion to put this back on the table. All those in favor?
All those opposed? Back on the table. Revert back to the regular order of business. 15-3-28. Oh no, 15-3-24, offered by Councilor Caviello. Be it resolved that the Medford City Council offer condolences to the family of Sam Roslando, good man, who passed away after a long illness. Sam was longtime director of the Metro Youth Hockey and was active in other
uh, various youth activities and, uh, quite the sailor. Thank you, Mr. President. Uh, you know, those who knew Sam, um, I've known Sam for many years. Uh, our kids grew up together. I think, uh, Paul and, uh, Councilor Camuso and Councilor Knight, they knew him from Utah. I mean, he was the guy that started the concession stand on the rink when no one else wanted to do it. Sam took it on on his own and built it up into what it is today. Uh, he was active in little league and law, anything to do with the kids.
Sam was always there for her. He had an illness a couple of years ago that held him down, but he was an avid boater, and again, passed away last week. And if we could have a moment of silence for him. I appreciate it. Please stand for a moment of silence for the repose of the soul of Sam Roslando.
15-328 petition by Joe Viglione of 59 Garfield Avenue, Medford Mass to address the council about new community media platform. Mr. Viglione. Good evening, city council. Um, last Thursday was the final date of submission for a proposal for the access television station. I take that as a vote of, um, no confidence. Uh,
On March 26th, only one entity submitted a proposal to City Hall. And I heard from an AXS TV veteran today that the other cities and towns around here are afraid of Medford. That was the exact terminology. And I said, well, they should be afraid of the mayor because the restrictions being put on this new station are something that the old regime didn't have to adhere to. So while they've yet to be punished, we have these really strict rules for
the next access station. Now, I have a four-point plan for access TV in the city. Number one is education. Number two is community involvement. Number three is use of technology at home integrated with the TV station. And number four is recouping monies from the previous nonprofit, if any monies are due. The station is a hub, a meeting place for the arts community, for all the sports in town,
I hear from so many people involved in sports. You know John from Medford, famous TV and radio calling host, host and caller. He's, he's, you know, number one, but there's Tony Bova's hockey games and Chris Donovan's out there. He came back very excited. He couldn't be here last week. He was doing his dad thing. He said he was very excited about the sports event he was at. These people are craving to put the sports of Medford
on public access television. So when the city solicitor, who I think is a great guy, and we get along wonderfully, but I was in his office and he goes, Joe, you know, to me, public access is obsolete. And I quickly responded, Mark, education is never obsolete. Now, I've said it here before. I'm going to say it again. This new media station is going to be heavy on education. Computers. In Stoneham, where I'm a member,
Amy, the executive director, and she's also on the Mass Access board, and I'm a member of Mass Access. She goes to the senior center just about weekly, and they have laptop computers with the Final Cut Pro program, and she's at the senior center teaching the seniors of Stoneham. Now, as Access is flourishing in Newton, you cannot get a show on in Newton. Boston, Somerville, Cambridge, Burlington, Malden, it's flourishing. Here in Medford, the mayor will say, well, no one's interested.
No, Your Honor. People have been beaten down. They've been ridiculed. They've been harassed, including counselors. And all we wanted to do was to do what happens in other communities. I want to bring that to Medford. And I'm looking for anyone in the arts, anyone from any walk of life to support me, because we will build a new access station. Now, the mayor wanted a corporation already in place.
I could have put the money down and built a corporation, but then if we don't get awarded the contract, I'm out all that money. So that was another restriction that really was kind of not Medford friendly. And the second part with my discussion with Mark Rumley was we're already paying for this. As a counselor noted earlier, this $300,000 or more, we're paying for this service. Now I'm here tonight because last week was the submission date.
And Arthur DeLuca from the old regime was out there and he said, you are the only one. So I held back. I tried to get Somerville involved and they were interested. I think, um, there were other entities that were interested. Malden was interested, but for some reason they backed off. So I waited till last minute cause I was trying to get corporations involved. The restrictions were too great. As I heard from an insider, they are afraid of Medford after all.
of the horrible stuff that went down. They're just afraid to come in here. And the mayor likes that because when he goes up for election, November 3rd, in a little bit more than 200 days, Mr. D'Antonio won't be able to go on TV and talk about issues. There's no TV to go on. There's color bars. Now, if you read carefully the contract, and I urge all members of the city council to go down to the clerk's office and look at the Comcast Xfinity book.
My reading of the contract isnow, correct me if I'm wrong, but I don't think it was in there 10 years ago. Comcast has the right to take away a channel not being used. This is very, very suspicious. We need channel 3 for our access. We've suffered long enough.
There should be hockey. There should be baseball. When you counselors bring our wonderful sports teams up here and congratulate them, think about this. I appreciate you congratulating them, but I would also like to have DVDs of them performing on the football field, on the soccer field. And I would like those DVDs at the library because Burlington Public Library has my interview with Jojo White. He's my current show that's going out right now, Jojo White of the Boston Celtics. So I interviewed Jojo White. We taped his lecture.
It was done along with Haverhill TV. And that is now at the Burlington Library. So anyone can walk into the Burlington Library, see the library lecture. It's on Burlington Cable right now. It's going up on Stoneham. It's going up to my 24 stations. I'll be having hundreds of stations as I've joined Mass Access. And now we upload to Mass Access. Stations around the Commonwealth can now take my programming, download it, and broadcast it, or cable cast it. This is wonderful stuff that I want to teach this community. Now, you know I've got close to 40 years in this.
And I didn't want to run the access station. I'm only doing this as my civic duty. I'm trying to help the whole community out. That's all I'm doing it for. I want my show on the air, but no one else is doing it. I want everyone's show on the air. So those are my four points. And I will just wrap it up and just say the use of technology at home, the community involvement, the education. And the final thing I will say is in my hand today is the Lincam
lawsuit, which goes to court April 2nd, Thursday. Chilling, if you read it, and I gave the city council, every member of the city council has four pages from this. I specifically want you and the mayor and Mark Rumley to look at the term fiduciary duty and read page 29, altering, defacing, destroying, transferring, or disposing of any records, books, accounts. Well, wait a minute. We know there were no meeting minutes. Yes, law enforcement's looking at TV3, but here you go, people.
This is the precedent. They have no books, and they think they can just walk away without telling the community what they did. If I have the honor of running this station, one of my priorities after the education is to try to recoup the monies and try to get to the bottom of the TV3 mess. Thank you. Mr. President? Councillor Camuso. The gentleman just stated that the bid deadline, I believe, was last week. If we could ask
the procurement department, as well as the solicitor, if there was any qualified bidders, number one, and who they were. If at this point, I'm assuming it's public record if the bids were opened and if they're qualified and responsive to move forward. On the motion of Councilor Camuso. Ma'am, please state your name and address. Jean Martin, 10 Cumming Street. And I just wanted to say a couple of things.
First of all, the city has been, I say this every time, the city's out. I mean, we've lost. We've lost a whole history of like 20 years of this city because of the debacle. And that was under the mayor's regime. And I actually have to use that word because that's basically what it is. It's his word and that's it. But that said, I'm sorry to say these guys got away with it. It's a waste of time because there's no money to be gotten to go after these guys. It's sad that they got away with it.
But the mayor is still the mayor, and the mayor is responsible for at least what goes forward from here, from today forward. Or when that whole thing was done, he's definitely responsible. And he should be responsible, and he should own up to what he did, that he was neglectful in oversight of that debacle that cost us a bad reputation.
Not just in the city of Medford, but in Malden and Somerville and Winchester and all the surrounding communities, we have a bad rep. That's what I just heard from Joe. We have a bad rep out there. And it's going to take a lot to repair it. Now, if we have to hire a professional, no offense, I don't, Joe is too involved from the old times, but I hope he has a show on the new one. I hope he gets a show on the new one.
But I think an outside person, somebody that is completely unbiased, doesn't know a thing about the past, completely fresh, a fresh set of eyes coming from maybe even outside the city, coming in, hire them to get this thing started, to get it up on the media that's now popular. Maybe it's not TV, maybe it's computers.
whatever it is, whatever the new technology is, have them get it up and running. If we have to hire somebody from the city, let's do that to get it done. Thank you. Thank you, and welcome back. Councilor Caviello. Thank you, Mr. President. You know, seeing that if the deadline comes and goes and we have nobody, I still can't understand why the city can't change direction and hire a person to run a non-profit station for the city of Medford.
We have one of the largest colleges in the country at Emerson University. That's all they do is produce TV shows. They're a factory for actors and producers. Boston University has a huge program. This state is one of the most technology-savvy states in the country. Why can't we hire a person to run the station if we can't find the company? There's money there to pay
a competent person, a decent salary to run the station, Mr. President. If we can't get a company to come in there and do it. Again, there's going to be people that know how to run non-profits. They do this for a living. Thank you, Councilor Kerrio. Councilor Pinto. I don't think it's a matter of getting a non-profit person to run it or a for-profit person to run it. Point of information, Councilor Caruso. Public access cannot be for-profit according to
the federal standards. And we will have something in writing on that from our city solicitor, I'm sure. Maybe I said it wrong. What I'm saying, whether you have a non-profit or a for-profit company come in here, not to run public, to run an access channel. With that being said, I mean, there's absolutely no transparency. This council just got through voting last week, and we all agreed to it, that they may not go forward and sign any contract with Comcast until a public hearing takes place.
Now, if I heard the gentleman correctly today, he was told that a fellow by the name of Peter Epstein is the only person that deals with this on behalf of the city. No, it's been three, it's going on three weeks, three and a half weeks now since the last time I spoke to Mr. Epstein and he called me back. He said he has not heard anything from anybody here in the city of Medford. Well, today's March 31st. We're dealing with 18 days because according to, from the letter from Xfinity Comcast, they want this thing signed on it before the 18th of April.
How it got into the building, and nobody knows how it got here. It's not time-stamped or anything. Pardon me? No, no, no, no. Oh, it could be. But this letter was dated December 18, and it was hand-delivered by UPS to the city of Medford. So I'm quite sure if somebody wanted to go to UPS, if they'd be willing, they'd be willing to tell you who signed for it. But that's not the point. The fact of the matter is we just found this out last week.
This is absolutely crazy. You know, we haven't had public access in the city, I think, since December or November of 2013. And that means the last quarter of 2013, all of 14, now coming into 15. And during that period of time, that's when Verizon came into the picture. So not only do we have Verizon, we have Xfinity. But unfortunately, just think about it. Who in their right mind would want to make a bid to put a public access station up at the high school in the back?
in the back end of the building where it's not on a main street. The mayor didn't even listen to his own three-member person that he had a panel and powered from February to March of this past year, February to Memorial Day. And the first thing, it has to be in a centrally located position. Well, behind the high school, up in the high school is not a centrally located position, especially if you have to get off the bus and it's dark at night, there's no protection there.
But that's not the fact. The fact of the matter is this, that we as a council do have a voice, and the voice is this. It's unfortunate, but maybe it's the only voice that you can do. You have injunctive relief. This council can go into a mode of injunctive relief. This council can get a hold of 10 rate payers and ask them to go into a mode of injunctive relief. This council can stop the mayor in his tracks at budget time because he has not listened to the biggest issues that this council has been able to talk about.
The priority of this council 2014 was a new police station. That was his number one priority and all seven of us agreed upon it. And you haven't seen one thing from that guy across the hall to respond back to a new police station by this council or any citizens. His only comment was through Mrs. Burke when she was down here, maybe in seven years, in seven years.
I mean, we'll all be out of here, gone someplace, and who knows what the financial condition of the community is going to be. I don't know. None of us know. But you have $7.5 million sitting in a Water and Sewer account, but no indication of where that money is going. If you get $300,000 in this particular account, no indication where that money is going. And if the gentleman at the podium is correct,
that you can't find somebody who's reputable to build this station, then all we've done is absolutely nothing. And if I understand correctly, if Comcast has the availability through the contract that the mayor does sign to take that channel away from the city, well, where is the 5% worth of revenues that the city basically would have as it relates to the contract?
That's the agreement, it's 5%. 3% goes to the city, 2% goes between public access, channel 16 and channel 15, which is the educational channel. This has been floundering way, way, way too long. The mayor has just been a constant refuser to participate with this council. He's been a constant refuser to be transparent with this council. He's been a constant refuser to want to be part
of Medford's city government. This is not a dictatorship, this is not an emperorship. This is a group of elected officials that have to answer to the people. Every one of us have to answer to the people, including him. But so far, he's got a free ride because nobody wants the job maybe anymore. Because maybe everybody realizes that it's decent, that the job isn't worth it because of what they're gonna have to go through. The guy has never woke up in the morning, ever had to open a door,
turn the key, hire employees, pay workman's comp, pay for the electric, pay for the gas, pay for everything that makes a business have to run. And then, at the same time, tries to tell the taxpayers of this community what they have to pay for and how they should be taxed continuously and continuously and without a voice. It's not fair. It's not right. Mr. President, I don't know where we can go with this. The council was as clear as a bell not to go forward.
requesting the mayor not to go forward with a 10-year contract. You know, if he does go forward with a 10-year contract, again, the people of this community have been snickered. And, you know, where do we go? What do we tell the ratepayers of this community? What do we tell the citizens? What are we here for?
if we can't do anything that makes any sense. This doesn't mean you have to be against him on everything, but it seems to be that way because he just doesn't want to talk to us. He just wants to talk to the newspaper. You have to find things out through the newspaper. Like today, he had to find out through the newspaper about the dog park that supposedly now looks like it's coming out of his grand scheme of things. That became a genesis of people that had dogs who were so upset not being able to have a dog park in the city of Medford.
And every time they came up with the idea, oh, no, it's going to cost too much, $200,000, $300,000, whatever it might be. Well, if you do some work, as Councilor Marks and the committee did, and shop around, you will see that not only you can build a decent dog park, there are monies out there. And so be it. You know something? We talk about this stuff each and every week. I think the coup d'etat's going to come when we have that meeting toward the end of the month as it relates to the kiosk. We'll find out what this is all about, because businesses and the folks
They're going to start to tell you that they're hurting. They're going to tell you that business is off and customers are leaving because of the craziness of the kiosk. And you're right, Councilor Caviello, when you turned around and you said, you put the money in the kiosk, you don't know where you're supposed to go, left, right, up or down, five or six spots, whatever it might be. But if they think they're going to go out of their way to mock and spot off the kiosk when the streets are in deplorable condition, the crosswalks don't even exist anymore, the potholes are beyond help, then there will be a problem around here.
And that gentleman who's here, I don't think he's gone now, he's right. He's right on the RFP as it's being an amendment to the contract. They have obligations. And I think it was the lady who appeared here some two or three weeks ago who made the comment. She made the comment as clear as a bell. We can sue them, or we can get out of the contract, but there is an offset. And there are offsets to that. And the offsets to that whole contract are the failures and the intentional neglect and the results
I call them the bounty hunters from Tennessee, them taking our money, running around and not adhering to the law. They can't even get their cars straight. They can't even get the details straight. And the police should be all over them. They should be out there towing their cars because they're supposed to be mocked. This week they're mocked on the ring road over there in a spot that they're not supposed to be. They've been in front of hydrants. They've been in front of handicapped spots.
Mr. President, I don't know where we're going. You know, this is frustration talking here right now, as you can tell. You got a new haircut, I can tell. But that's beside the point. The fact of the matter is... Thank you, and thank you to John DeVito. Counselor Camuso. Thank you. On the TV public access, people have referred this evening that there was one bid. Do we know who it is and who the board of directors are and stuff? I know we're going to ask the question, but does anyone have any idea?
Winchester decided not to, all the local ones decided not to put in, right? All the local ones decided not to put in, okay. And I am that person, Mr. Camuso. I'm the one who submitted a proposal because no one else would. So I'm fighting this good fight and I'll do respect Jeannie, but after 40 years of this and all my connections in AXS TV, I can put together a great team instantly. All we need is the mayor to, and I think, I think it was Councilor Caravaglia, right?
This is craziness. Let's just reactivate MCC TV3. Give us the new nonprofit. I don't want to stay in forever. I don't want to do the Frank Polari thing of 28 years. I just want to go and guide the ship and help get it started, because I got other things that I'm doing that I just want to get it up and started. But what I wanted to say, too, is this is happy anniversary, Mayor McGlynn. It was two years ago tonight and tomorrow that the color bars went up.
So we have a very important night here. Color bars, well, you're taking our money. You could have had Chris Donovan and I go to the head end and bring compact disc players and DVD players and broadcast sports and stuff. We would have done that for you. The proposals on your desk, Mark Rumley told me he gave it to you. We would have done that for you. So we have access. We could have used the high school channel. I got a lot of sports. I got a lot of Pat Fiorello shows we could air. Lots of good stuff, Your Honor.
Two years ago tonight, it was December 17th, the last Ziggy Bush show aired, December 17th, 2012, and April Fool's Day 2013, happy April Fool's Day, your public access channel went off the air and it hasn't come back tonight. Two years. I have a question for the gentleman that submitted a bid. Yes, sir. Do you feel that if you're in charge of that access TV that the people would be coming out of the rafters to participate, Medford residents?
Yes, sir, I do, because I have a program to do outreach. I'm very good at outreach. But you were involved with a lot of the past TV3 stuff that was going on. I helped shut them down, and I'm proud of it, because it wasin fact, you benefited from TV3, sir. You benefited from a board member putting you on the air when he wasn't supposed to. So while your colleagues were being bashed, you never once defended them. I won't allow that. I will adhere to the rules, and I will be very transparent.
And I just want to open it up and guide the ship and set the laws down. And then I want to walk away and do my show. And do you have to? Well, I thought you can't do the show if you're a nonprofit. That's what the mayor's new thing is. That came up. I think you said it last week. Somebody has said it last week that if you're the new board or the new nonprofit will not be able to produce their own shows. That's what Mayor McGlynn and Mark Rumley have put together for their proposal, which is why it scared everyone away, because you have to have people guiding the ship. You have to have people explaining, doing, showing how to do it.
Unlike the previous regime, I don't run over to the senior center and put myself on TV. I usually get behind the camera and help the public. I've put Jeanne Martin on the air. I've put State Rep. Paul Donato on the air. I've put Paul Camuso on the air. I've put Bob Penter on the air. I've had Mayor Menino on the air. So I don't need to be on TV. I would love to not be at the council every week. I would like to be behind the scenes at AXS TV.
I've been doing it for 40 years, Paul. I don't need to be on the TV every week. Our community needs it, and I'm just here putting myself on the line. I mean, you can pick me apart, you can throw rocks at me, but I'm trying to help my community. I'm asking legitimate questions, Joe. I can put a board together. I can put a board of directors together quickly. Do you have the financial backing to get your nonprofit off the ground? I would go to businesses. I can do this, Paul. I can put it together.
It's a non-profit. You can't accept money from businesses to... Wait a minute. You just said you're going to go to businesses to get the money to get your non-profit off the ground. Is that what you said? No, no, no. Our non-profit can be sponsored by businesses as TV3 was sponsored by businesses. It's very simple. So do you have the financial backing to get it off the ground? That's what I'm asking. Yes, I do. Okay. Right now, if you received a bid,
You'd be able to get it up and running? I'd put it up and running tomorrow. I've said this for years. Construction. You can do the construction. You can do everything. I don't have to do the construction. What do you think the $300,000 is for? You think I'm going to pay for the construction? The construction's a whole separate bid. You're the city councilor. Why am I teaching you? Why am I teaching you that the Comcast contract is in? Why am I teaching you about the construction? That may have been paced for that. First of all, I'm asking legitimate questions. And because you don't like the questions. You should be prepared as a city councilor. You should know. Let's wrap this up.
You should know as a city council that the mayor is paying for the infrastructure. Absolutely, it's a separate bid that went out. Right, I don't have to pay to get access to AV to put the equipment in. It's not coming out of my pocket. Well, you need someone that knows how to design it and everything else to make it happen. I have all those people, Paul. I know how this works. Well, they're here every week with you, so I'm just sort of questioning the backing that you have as far as getting the job done.
The job will be done instantly. Well, and the mayor doesn't, like I said, I have a motion and here's the other thing too. Happy anniversary color bar. Thank you. Appreciate that. Um, the other thing, Mr. President, we're still waiting for our report back from the solicitor. If the funds can be used for upgrading technology in the community in lieu of the public access. So if we could maybe ask the city solicitor for an update on that, because, um, as amended by council, so all those in favor,
On that motion, Councilor Pinto. I don't think you can, because the way this new contract is written or being amended, if it's not used for public access, then they have the right to take the channel back. It cannot be used. It's only to be used one of two ways, public access, or they take it back. But it also can be used for the education channel and the government channel, doesn't it? No, public access is PEG. It's public access, educational, and government. But we could do, if the city administration decided to, he could do EGG, get rid of the P and do EGG, educational and government.
You have to read the contract the way it's written. And I'm fully aware of the contract. Instead of peg, he could do egg. Educational in government, if we want it done. So we have a motion on the floor by Councilor Camuso. Ma'am, we could just do briefly. Briefly. Yes. Gene Martington coming straight. And I just wanted to say, um, well, I disagree with Joe.
on who should run the new station. I want to give my props to Joe. I think that without Joe's efforts, we would still be dealing with that group of people that was a bunch of delinquents. So I just want to give my props to Joe for that. If it wasn't for him educating me on access TV, I wouldn't know any of that stuff. So I want to thank him for that. I want to give him his props for that.
Thank you. Thank you. Okay. Well, anyway, but anyway, um, I hope that, uh, we get a new station because the city deserves it. Thank you. Thank you. So on the motion of, uh, Councilor Camuso as amended Councilor Knight. Will the clerk please read back the language of the resolution? The resolution asked by Councilor Camuso that, uh, uh, the purchasing, uh, agent, uh, update the council on who has made the bid for the contract.
if there was a qualified responsive bid. And secondly, qualified and responsive bidders. Qualified and responsive bidders. And the other one is the update from the solicitor on the status of the money, the PEG monies. The status of the PEG monies from the city solicitor. Move the question, Mr. President. Motion to move the questions. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed?
The records of the March 24, 2015 meeting were passed to the Honorable Counselor Camuso. Counselor, how did you find those records? I found them in order and I move approval. On a motion for approval, the records by Counselor Camuso. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion passes. Motion to adjourn by Counselor Knight. All those in favor? All those opposed? I'm opposed. Meeting adjourned.