Welcome all to the second regular meeting of the Medford City Council, which is now called to order. Gentlemen, please remove your hats. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Caviello. Present. Councilor DelaRusso. Present.
Councilor Falco. Present. Councilor Knight. Present. Vice President Leno-Kern. Present. Councilor Mox. Present. Councilor Scarpelli. Present. President DelaRusso. Present. Seven members present, none absent. Please rise and join us in the salute of the flag. I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America
and to the Republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all. Wow. Commendations 15-777. Commendations were offered by Councilor Knight for the Medford High School class of 2015 Greater Boston League Champions varsity golf.
Medford High School, 2015 Greater Boston League Champions, Varsity Boys Soccer, and Medford High School, 2015 Greater Boston League Champions, Varsity Girls Soccer. At this time, we invite Councilor Knight-Ford to lead us in the presentations. Varsity Golf, Boys Soccer, and Girls.
At this time, I'd like to ask the golf team to please get up and come over to the right side of the room, please. And I'd also like to ask Coach Dyer to come join me on the podium.
And I'd like to ask James Riccardi to come up and help me present the citations. First of all, on behalf of the Medford City Council and the residents of the city of Medford, I would like to congratulate you on a wonderful season. Again, you've shown great success and you've made us proud, Coach. So thank you very much for your leadership and your guidance for these young individuals, shaping them into fine upstanding citizens and solid student athletes.
I'm in my hands here this evening, Coach. I have a citation here from the Medford City Council, which reads, the Medford City Council takes pleasure in awarding this council commendation to Ray Dyer, coach of the 2015 Medford High School Varsity Golf Team, in recognition of capturing the Greater Boston League title and participating in the MIAA Golf Division I North Tournament. Coach, congratulations. Thank you very much. I'd like to ask
I'd like to ask Mr. Mercati to come up here and help me pass these citations out to some of his colleagues. If he would be so kind as to read the names off, we'll have him come up and we can congratulate him. Connor Frazier. Basketball player. Yeah, basketball. Justin Kelly. John Michael Keating. John Michael. Come on up.
Aaron Delano. Tommy Vinot. Anthony McKillop. Chris Joba.
Zach Maffeo. Trent Mullen. Thomas Conerny. Henry Howard.
Last but not least, James Riccati, my helper here. Let's give him a big round of applause here. I'm sorry, I have Emily Brady. Emily Brady as well.
I want to thank the city council for inviting us here tonight. It's always a pleasure. Um, we had a very interesting year this year for the first time since I've been the golf coach, uh, 11 years now, we had three starting freshmen on the team. And if anybody here plays golf other than the golf team, you know how difficult the sport it can be. So for them to step in and win the GBL title this year was quite exciting for, for the whole team.
And we have them all back for another three years, so the future looks bright. Thank you very much. The Medford High School GBL champs, the golf team, ladies and gentlemen. If I could take a moment to ask the boys' soccer team to rise and come over to the right side of the room, please.
I'd also like to ask my friend Mateo Cuno to come up here and help me pass out these citations if he's able.
I see Coach Petritus over there as well, and I'd like to ask Coach Petritus to join me up here on stage, as well as any of the other members of his coaching staff that may be here with him.
Once again, we're here honoring the Medford High School Greater Boston League Champion Soccer Team. And it's really great seeing Coach Petritus on the sidelines, wearing the blue and white. And here in my hands, I do have a council commendation which reads, the Medford City Council takes pleasure in awarding this council commendation to Mike Petritus, coach of the Medford High School Boys Varsity Soccer Team.
in recognition of winning the Greater Boston League title and securing a playoff berth in the MIAA State Division I Boys Soccer Tournament and reaching the semifinals for the 2015 fall season. Coach, congratulations. You've done a great job with this group of young scholar-athletes, and I'd like to thank you for all your hard work over the last several years. My friend Mateo here is going to help me out by calling his teammates up to pass out these citations.
We got the coaches out of the way here. We'll save this for last. Sammy Reed. Sammy Reed.
Sean Mahoney. Jordan Howard. Ryan Palmer. Joal Rosa. Sean Allion.
Igor D'Souza-Vieira. Curtis Brown. Josh Crespo.
Joe Morera. Jonte. Jeremy Hollings. Hamza Usman.
Simran. Will Mucci-Reilly. Matt McCarthy. Matt McCarthy.
And lastly, I'd like to present my helper, Mateo Cuno, with his citation. If I could take a moment to introduce Coach Petritas for a few words. I just want to thank the city council for inviting us here. Hopefully we win the whole thing next year. We came short this year. But thanks everyone for coming tonight. Thank you.
2015 GBL Champ Boys Soccer Team, ladies and gentlemen. I could ask the Girls Varsity Soccer Team to please rise and come over to the right of the room. I'd like to ask Colson to join me if she's available, as well as my friend, let's see who we're gonna pick for this one, Emma DeRoses.
Come on up. Off you shy.
Again, once again, we have the Greater Boston League Champion 2015 Medford High School Girls Soccer Team here with us. They've shown great success over the last couple of years. I know that they were here once before last year anyway. And I think maybe for the past five years since then. Say that again? Seven? Oh, all right, all right. So for the last five years, they've been the GBL champs. And it's great to see such success in the soccer field, also in the classroom. The coaches done a great job.
modeling a program that's going to make sure that these individuals are strong contributing members to society who also have a strong focus in the classroom. So thank you for your work, coach. In my hands here, I have a citation which reads, the Medford City Council takes pleasure in awarding this council commendation to Allison Colson, coach of the Medford High School Girls Varsity Soccer Team, in recognition of winning the Greater Boston League title and securing a playoff berth in the MIAA State Division I Girls Soccer Tournament for the fall 2015 season. Coach, congratulations.
Daniella Ramirez Sam Sinidi
Julia Silva. Jonna McNamee.
Olivia Barrows. Fazana Afraz. Emma DeRoses.
Dora Barrett. Colleen Hardy. Isabella Sanchez.
and Carmen Diorio. For my special helper here, Gigi Braga. I can take a moment to introduce Coach Colson for a few words.
Thank you so much for inviting us here. We had such an amazing season. I couldn't be prouder of all the girls. Thank you so much. Ladies and gentlemen, the 2015 GBL Champion Medford High School Girls Soccer Team with Sarah Clark.
15-776, offered by Counselor Caviello. Congratulations to the Medford Junior Mustangs, Medford Youth Football, Junior Varsity Football Team, Eastern Massachusetts Champions, Commonwealth Youth Football Conference Champions, undefeated. Medford Junior Mustangs, Medford Youth, chairing varsity, junior varsity, and freshman Commonwealth Youth Chair Conference Champions. Counselor, there you are. Thank you, Mr. President.
Thank you, Mr. President. First of all, I'm going to make a motion that we all wear bow ties next week. I didn't know how popular they are. All the guys came out with bow ties tonight. Jesus, are they back? All right. If we could have the coach come up. Two coaches come up. Coach Iozza. Coach Gannon. Coach Gannon.
Coach Gannon. Coach Gannon. Coach Gannon. Let me see a few kids. Coach. Coach is here.
All right. The Bedford City Council takes pleasure in awarding this council accommodation
to the 2015 Medford Junior Mustangs Junior Varsity Team, 5th and 6th grade, in recognition of capturing the 2015 Eastern Mass Super Bowl Championship and the Commonwealth Youth Football Conference title in the 5th and 6th grade Junior Varsity Division, completing the season undefeated with an overall record of 10-0.
If we could have those players come up here. Guys, line up over there please. If the players could come up here. All right. Ben Messersmith. Ben Messersmith.
Ryan Navarro. Ryan Navarro. Jake Norsella. Kyle Orlando.
Jonathan Remy. Galegero Otato. Congratulations. Tyree Butte.
Jaden Biagi. Isaiah Blake. Congratulations. Everson Charles.
Stephen Douglas. David Jankowski. Josh Jean Rene.
Diago Jerger. Congratulations. Ash Kosla. Ash Kosla. Dylan Lorenza.
Derek Lezu. Dominic Rizzo. Romello Robinson.
Rudolph Ross. Marcus Scott. Miles Taylor. Dominic Terranova.
Kevin Gannon. Luke Gotti. Tony Huna. Daniel Ayoza.
Thomas Driscoll. Congratulations. Osmond Alcorum.
Congratulations. Keith Wilson, coach. Stephen Douglas III, coach. Stephen Douglas II, coach. Paul Navarro.
Jay Holtz. Jay Holtz. Sean Gannon.
And it's my pleasure to give this last one to our head coach, Rich Ioza. First, I'd just like to thank the City Council and City Council Carvajal for having us here tonight and sponsoring us. We had a great season, undefeated season. This program has been around five years now. It's improving every year.
Beathard Junior Mustangs, the cheering program did great this year. Thank you girls, you had a great year. All our teams made it to the championship game this year, so it's been a great year for the Beathard Junior Mustangs, and thank you guys. Thank you to the parents for being very supportive. Thank you.
Next, if we could have the freshman junior, the freshman cheering team. And if we could have... And if we could have Coach Rogers come up here. Coach Rogers. And our...
Our assistant coach, Honoree Messersmith, and our teen parents. No teen parents? No, who shows her here? Teen parents, shows her here? Okay. First of all, it's my pleasure, coming from a family that's had two cheerleaders for daughters. I know all the hard work that these girls and their parents all put in, it's a year long,
I think they all deserve a lot of credit. So, the Memphis City Council takes pleasure in awarding this council commentation to the 2015 Medford Junior Mustangs third and fourth grade Frosch cheerleading squad in recognition of capturing first place in the Commonwealth Youth Cheerleading Conference Championship in 2015 Frosch Small Division.
Isabelle Amaro. Isabelle. Lilliana Amaro. Lilliana. Lilliana.
Alyssa Cerullo. Brianna Cerullo. Isabella Cogliano. Christy George. Christy George. Kiera Messisman.
Sarah Sweeney. And finally, assistant coach, Maureen Messerschmitt. And team parents are here, Mr. Rulo. And last but not least, our head coach, Lisa Rogers.
I just wanna thank the girls for an amazing season and it's just, only way to go is more up and it was just a great season. Thank you so much. If we could have next, the Memphis Junior Mustangs Junior Varsity cheering squads five and six.
and Nicole Schaefer. And assistant, can you borrow my cell phone? Yeah, but coaches aren't here, so one of the other coaches. Okay, all right. Jabria Adelise.
Mikayla Jakes. Miam Aluso. Angel Noe. Alysia Fanico. Alicia Fanico. Erin Ricciardi.
Harmony Tucci. And Lindsey Vasquez. Lindsey, not here. Okay, and we have assistant coach, Michaela Burley. Assistant coach, Jennifer Noe. And we have our head coach, Nicole Schaefer.
Okay, the JV cheering coach staff couldn't be here tonight, so on their behalf, I'd like to congratulate these girls. They're a great team, they worked very hard, and they really deserve to win first place. Thank you. Is nobody from the varsity squad? Is the varsity squad here? No.
On behalf of the varsity squad, the Memphis City Council takes pleasure in awarding this council combination to the 2015 Memphis Junior Mustangs 7th and 8th grade varsity cheerleading squad in recognition of capturing first place in the Commonwealth Youth Cheerleading Conference Championship in 2015 varsity small division. Coached by Sylvia Belcastro. Again, we want to congratulate them and hopefully they'll be able to come in another night to pick their team up.
Thank you for all the young men and women who came up here tonight.
If we could call for a five minute recess and declare out the room. Thank you.
City Council will reconvene.
On the motion, Chair recognizes Councilor Scott Pelley for his motion to suspend the rules, to take communications from the Mayor. All those in favor? All those opposed? Before us, 16-020, to the Honorable President and members of the Medford City Council, City Hall, Medford Mass, et cetera, re-amendment to Article 4, Division 4, City Solicitor Section 2-020.
651 entitled Appointment and Qualification and to Article 4, Division 4, City Solicitor, Section 2-652 entitled Term. Dear Mr. President and members of the Medford City Council, I respectfully request and recommend that your Honorable body approve the following amendment to Article 4, Division 4, City Solicitor, Section 2-651 entitled Appointment and Qualification.
into Article 4, Division 4, City Solicitor, Section 2-652, Entitled to Term. The purpose of these amendments is to change the term of the city solicitor from one year to two years, and to have the term run concurrently with the term of the mayor. An amendment to the revised ordinances of the City of Medford, Article 4, Officers and Employees, Division 4, City Solicitor, Section 2-651,
appointment and qualifications be it ordained by the city council of the city of Medford that article four division four revised ordinances of the city of Medford as most recently amended is hereby further amended to by changing the language of article four division four city solicitor section two six five one entitled appointments and qualification said section precisely states presently states there shall be a city solicitor. He shall be appointed annually by the mayor. He shall be an attorney and counselor of the courts of the Commonwealth.
Uh, the language of said section, a two five, a six five one shall be amended to read as follows. There shall be a city solicitor. He shall be appointed by the mayor. He shall be an attorney and counselor of the courts of the Commonwealth amendment, uh, to the revised ordinances of the city of Medford article five officers, employees, division four city solicitor section two, six 52 term be it ordained.
by the city council of the city method that division four of the revised ordinances of the city method as most recently amended is hereby further amended by changing, changing language of article four division for city solicitor section two, six, five, two, uh, entitled term said a section presently states he shall hold office one year from the first Monday in January and the year of his appointment and until another shall be appointed and qualified
The language of said section 652 shall be amended to read as follows. He shall hold office for term of two years from the first Monday in January and the year of his appointment and until another shall be appointed and qualified. Respectfully submitted Stephanie Burke, Mayor. Before us to explain this is the city solicitor. We have a slew of papers that we discussed for amendments of ordinances in committee of the whole.
And it was requested that these be reported out with some inquiries made through the mayor's office on that. And the clerk will enumerate those inquiries that have been asked for. I made a report from earlier tonight pertaining to this particular topic. There was a certain amount of recommendations being written.
recommendations were written explanation from the mayor on the role and need of the new chief of staff position. A flow chart with the, on the executive office, executive office by position, title, duties, and salary. A further explanation on the, on the prior positions that won't be filled. The impact on the,
current budget, uh, on the new hires. And, uh, will there be, uh, any additional new secretary of administrative, uh, hiring at the mayor's office and also any new, uh, salary increases, uh, will be forthcoming in the future. Did we get, is that all in substance? Yes. Madam vice president that covered everything. Uh, council marks that covered everything that you had in there. Yes.
So, Mr. Solicitor, if you would. Yes, my name is Mark Rumley, Mr. President. I'm city solicitor. I reside at 50 Woodrow Avenue in Medford. The paper which is before you, 16-020, is one which would change the city solicitor's term from one year to a two year term which would run concurrently with the mayor. That's the purpose of that particular suggestion and amendment.
And could I make a comment about the papers, the questions that are referred out? I believe that I explained as to the positions which are on the council agenda tonight, those resolutions that pertain to the proposed amendments and the creation of a new position tonight, that at least in terms of those salaries, I did explain on those positions what the salaries have been, were, and what the changes were.
I just want to save the answer to a question, if it's not necessary, because I believe I was fairly clear in Committee of the Whole as to the positions before you tonight. Also, with that committee report that was just read, do we have a motion to adopt that? Yes. Yes. On the motion of Vice President Long and Kern, all those in favor? All those opposed? So the committee report is adopted. Motion will be adjourned at the table until the questions
On the motion of Council and Knight, lay the matter on the table until the questions have been answered. All those in favor? All those opposed? Yeah, we have one more that's going to come up now. That's been tabled.
So 16-021, to the Honorable President, members of the Medford City Council, re-amendment to Division 4 by the addition of a Division 4A entitled Chief of Staff and Policy, and further adding Section 2680 entitled Appointments and Duties. Dear Mr. President and members of the City Council, I respectfully request and recommend that your Honorable body approve the following amendment to Division 4 by the addition of a
Division 4A, entitled Chief of Staff and Policy, and further adding Section 2680, entitled Appointment and Duties. The purpose of this amendment to the revised ordinances is the creation of a position called Chief of Staff and Policy to advise the mayor on policy matters and to act as personnel director. An amendment to the revised ordinances of the City Method, Article 4, Officers,
and employees division for a chief of staff and policy section two six 80 appointment and duties be it ordained by the city council of the city of Medford that article four of the revised ordinances of the city of Medford as most recently amended is hereby further amended by the addition of division for a entitled chief of staff and policy and further adding section two dash six 80 entitled appointment and duties said section shall state
there shall be a chief of staff and policy who shall be appointed by the mayor. The duties of the chief of staff and policy shall include the following. A, advise the mayor on matters of municipal policy. B, manage communications and information both to and from the office of mayor. C, act as director of personnel being responsible for advising the mayor on matters of employee compensation, benefits administration, and fostering employee services
safely, safety, and welfare. D, advise the mayor and department heads on matters of employee discipline. E, be responsible for representing the mayor in all collective bargaining sessions, including all grievances, arbitrations, and all matters relating thereto. Respectfully submitted, Stephanie Muccini-Burke, mayor. Again, the city solicitor is here to report to us on this matter.
Thank you, Mr. President. On paper 16-021, this is not an amendment to an existing ordinance, but rather the creation of a new ordinance which would provide for a chief of staff and policy to work in the executive office with the duties you've just described. As I said in the committee of the whole meeting, Mayor Burke has indicated that chief of staff and her vision would be beneficial to the city.
And in order to implement that vision, this is a position that she puts forth to you as a positive recommendation in order for her to allow the executive branch to move forward in a fashion which is filled with discernment and filled in a way that a professional attitude and professional advice can be given to her by a chief of staff. Also, if I may, the one thing that a chief of staff can bring, because I've seen it in other people,
who have held this position even though it wasn't called it, is somebody who can sit down with the mayor when the door is closed and speak frankly and openly about municipal policy and difficulties. That provision also applies to department heads who can come in and perhaps be just as free to speak with a chief of staff without having to wait to see the mayor whose calendar is always busy
and to be able to speak to the chief of staff freely and openly. And all of that serves the purposes of good government. Madam Vice President. Thank you, President De La Russo. I'm not necessarily against this new position. I believe that, you know, maybe the $106,000 salary has to be looked at and just compared to other chiefs of staffs in our surrounding communities.
I think my major concern as one counselor is a number of things that we've requested from the mayor herself with regards to seeing the big picture on the topic, on will this chief of staff need secretarial workers? What else is coming down the line? We have four or five different amendments, changes, new positions that are before us tonight, but I think we all decided to table them because
I'm hearing rumors of increases in salaries in other positions. I'm hearing rumors of other new positions that are being brought on board. And I want to make sure that it all fits within our budget that we have to come and meet on and discuss and review and approve come June. So I do want to see the big picture. Therefore, unless anybody in the public wants to talk, I will move to table this as well until hopefully we do get a bigger picture on everything that is going to be encompassed and hopefully our
seven or eight requests will help us out in that matter and enlighten us of what is coming down the line within the next six months, the big turnover and change. If I could add one thing to that, Mr. President, I heard the Councilor's concerns, the Vice President's concerns, both here and in the Committee of the Whole. I just would like to remind the Council and those who are hearing this resolution for the first time is that, budgetarily, the Chief of Staff position will have a zero impact on this fiscal year's budget.
because it is not a matter of adding dollars to this budget, but rather putting a person into this position at a classification that's already been funded. But I just wanted to make that clear. On that matter, though, you also said you're not sure if, if I made through the chair, you're not sure if this person's going to need one or two or three secretaries or if they're going to be using the mayor's four secretaries. And so that is, that's an issue. Well, I also, but I did say that I'm sure that the chief of staff, like any other, uh,
department head, and I use that term synonymously, will have clerical assistance because you wouldn't expect anything less. And that's my issue. Will this assistance be from the four, I believe, four new people that are in the mayor's office now? Will we need additional secretaries? Because if you continue to add and increase salaries and add positions, that is going to have an impact on the budget. So that's where I'm hoping we can get the full picture. And whether that's another committee of the whole meeting or
written answers, I definitely want to see what's coming down the line. Motion to table is discussed in committee of the whole, Mr. President, until the questions are answered. I think somebody would like to speak. The motion to table is undebatable. All those in favor? Roll call. I withdraw my motion to table to allow residents to speak on the matter.
Good evening. Please state your name and address for the record. Good evening. My name is Robert Penter. I live at Zero Summit Road in Massachusetts, and I think we're in an area right now where we have a unique opportunity to really look at what our audiences are saying and where we can be going, because if we're going to relegate ourselves to changing audiences, maybe we should just look at the total picture. The total picture revolves itself around to the victor goes to spoils, and I understand that.
But rather than change our municipal ordinance or any ordinance, maybe we ought to take advantage of what the law already allows for. The new administration does have a unique opportunity to hire any individual he or she would like. Massachusetts General Laws, Chapter 4, Section 7, Sixth A, allows for coterminous appointments that would exist to that of the mayor in this particular situation.
And what would happen there, that the individual who would be appointed would not be subject to any municipal ordinance. They would just be subject to this particular law, which happens to be state statute, and every person that's in the mayor's office, which is an administrative appointment, would find itself in a co-terminus position as it relates to the term that the mayor sits in that office. If, in fact, a new mayor were to come in in the future, the person sitting in that position would then be reviewed
at a subsequent time by the then new mayor for the purposes of whether they continue to be coterminous or whether in fact they are going to be eliminated. They would come under the same privileges of having a review to their job, their job application, and what have you. The second portion that you would have to look at is these individuals are serving at an at-will position.
The mayor chooses individuals to work in that particular office, his or her office. And by looking at having that person sit in that particular office, you have to take into consideration the fact that are we putting people in there because of a municipal ordinance? Are we putting people in there because it's going to be coterminous? Are we putting those people in there because they're at will?
Now, if you look at all the state rules and laws and regulations as it relates to at-will contracts, you can have these made in such a way that you can fire them and hire them anytime they want. They can leave anytime they want. You can have an employment contract that basically relegates what their terms and duties are in this particular office. And to do that, that sets the tempo of making sure that you do have and you have hired the right person. For example, you might hire somebody and the person just doesn't work out six, seven months down the road. Then what are you going to do?
If you stick with the municipal ordinance the way it is, you're not going to have the same luxury of either an at-will or a coterminous type of an individual, because that way the other review factor would be part and parcel of what's going on. Second of all, and more importantly, whether it's this position or any other position, you have to look at the conflict of interest issue that revolves around the people in this particular case. In this particular case, you already have one individual that's working in the office, I believe it was on or about January,
in January, early January, and this individual also happens to be on the, on the transition team. Well, being on a transition team and also getting paid by the city of Medford for being an individual working in the mayor's office right now, I think presents itself, Mr. Solicitor. And I asked the question, I begged the question, so to speak, is there a conflict of interest? Because the impartiality of a transition team is supposed to bring the recommendations
to the administration. But when you're getting paid by the administration, and you're also on this transition team, you're also, I think, if you look under the conflict of interest law, you're possibly looking or possibly indicating that there could be a conflict, there might be a conflict, or it could appear to be a conflict. And really, that's what you don't want right now, especially starting off with a brand new administration. So I would suggest to my colleagues, as you review this thing in your committee of the whole, that you
look into this thing a little bit further, over and beyond changing a municipal ordinance or adding or subtracting to it, and look at the term that's allowed by state statute under the term of being either coterminous or at-will employees, because your responsibility back to the taxpayers is not the same as that of the administration. If you appropriate money for those particular positions, the question then becomes, after that appropriation, you have absolutely no control. You'll have absolutely no control over that employee.
other than the chief executive officer making the final decision. So if you want to ask the hard questions, this is the time to do it. But you do have options, and your options are either serve coterminously, number one, at will, number two, and more importantly, I think you really need to look at the conflict of interest that presently exists in the office, because I don't think it's right that someone who's on the transition team at the same time is getting paid well in excess of $90,000 to sit in the mayor's office at the present time and take on another job and duty and responsibility.
the same job and duty of responsibility that will come up in the next issue that's going to be presented before you. I'll be more than happy to answer any questions, but I just think you really need to look at this thing more in its totality as to what's going on. And I really think Councilor Lungo-Kern is right. I think you need a listing of every single person, their job classification, who they're replacing, and more importantly, what's the difference in the salaries, because that's going to make a big difference as to why are we making these changes at all and for what reason.
And I think you deserve that. And that's what transparency is all about. And you should not be afraid to ask the question. It's the taxpayer's money. And it's your duty and responsibility, as it was mine when I was sitting on that side, to make sure that the money was accounted for properly and appropriately. So that's it, if anyone wants to ask any questions.
16-022 to the Honorable President and members of the Medford City Council, re-amendment to Article 5, Finance Division 2, Procurement Section 2931, entitled Procurement Office or Appointment Term and Authority. Dear Mr. President and members of the Medford City Council, I respectfully request and recommend that your Honorable body approve the following amendment to Article 5, Finance Division 2, Procurement Section 2,
931, entitled Procurement Officer Appointment Term and Authority. The purpose of this amendment is to provide for a new position that has two components, Chief Budget Officer and Chief Procurement Officer. An amendment to the revised ordinances of the City of Medford, Article 5, Finance, Division 2, Procurement, Section 2, 931, Chief Procurement Officer Appointment
term and authority be it ordained by the city council of the city of Medford that division four of the revised ordinances of the city of Medford as most recently amendment is hereby further amended by changing the language of article five, uh, finance a division to procurement section two nine 31 entitled procurement officer appointment term and authority set sectionally previous, uh, presently states,
Article 5, Finance, Division 2, Procurement, Section 2, 931, Chief Procurement Officer Appointment Term Authority. There shall be a chief procurement officer who shall be appointed by the mayor. He or she shall hold office for a term of three years from the first Monday of January in the year of his or her appointment. The chief procurement officer shall have charge of the purchasing department.
Purchasing Department shall be under the direction and control of the Director of Finance slash Auditor. Language in Section 5, Finance, Division 4, Procurement, Section 2, 931, Entitled Procurement Officer. Appointment, term, and authority shall be amended to read as the following. Article 5 of Finance, Division 2, Budget and Procurement, Section 2, 931. I've made a mistake in reading. It originally said March, so it's going to be amended for the new one.
to reach January. There shall be a Chief Budget and Procurement Officer who shall be appointed by the Mayor. He or she shall hold office for a term of three years from the first Monday of January in the year of her appointment. The Chief Budget and Procurement Officer shall, in collaboration with the various departments, A, annually prepare and submit a proposed operating budget and capital improvement budget to the Mayor on a timely basis for submission to the City Council, B, attend all City Council budget subcommittee meetings,
Committee of the whole meetings and regular or specially scheduled meetings of the Medford City Council that pertain to budgets. C, have charge of the purchasing department. D, perform all duties required of a chief procurement officer under Massachusetts general laws. E, report directly to the mayor on matters that pertain to budgets. F, report to the director of finance slash auditing on matters that pertain to procurement. Respectfully submitted, Stephanie Muccini-Burke, mayor.
Mr. Solicitor. Yes, Mr. President. Again, this is one of the amendments that was talked about in the Committee of the Whole. This would take the position of Chief Procurement Officer and graft onto it, if you will, the position of Chief Budget Officer. As will come up later in the proposed amendments, that salaried position would go from a CAF 16 to a CAF 19. So it would bring together the marriage of two different positions.
And that's the purpose of this amendment. On the motion of Vice President Luglocurrent to table, seconded by Councilor Caviello. On that motion. Thank you, Mr. President. It was brought up by Councilor Caviello during a Committee of the Whole meeting that the position of procurement officer requires a special license. Yes.
Now, this new job title is Procurement Plus Budget Director. And as Councilor Caviello mentioned so eloquently inside the Committee of the Whole meeting, is that Louise Miller now has her license. But what's to say the next person that's hired is going to have that procurement license or is brought in for budgeting and doesn't have a procurement license? I just think the administration is tying their hands with putting both positions.
together. Right. Well, let's, let's go through, let's peel back a couple of the issues that you've just alluded to and ascribed to Councilor Caviello. First, the idea of certification. In fact, Louise Miller is properly certified to be a procurement officer, whether or not in the future, Mr. Or Mrs. Smith or Ms. Smith might apply for the position and not have that, that type of determination is going to have to wait to the future. Secondly,
As far as tying hands go, if Louise Miller is also the budget officer here, she will report as the budget officer to the chief finance auditor and, excuse me, in the procurement to chief finance auditor and to the budget to the mayor. If the mayor at some time in the future decides that Louise Miller should not do both jobs, then she will surely have a discussion with Louise Miller and that will probably end in a way which will have her stop doing one.
The point is this. We can go forward into the future and look at different nuances, different combinations and say, what if this? How about that? This could happen, but what we are is in January of 2016 with a new mayor who's decided
that this is the way she wants to proceed with her administration. So while I, like everyone else, would like to have a crystal ball and to make sure that nothing goes awry in the future, what we have to do is to act on the basis of the facts as they exist now. I say this respectfully. I take it respectfully. My only issue is that when Louise Miller was originally hired, she was hired as
the procurement officer. And then her description morphed into a number of items. And I'm not, to be quite frank with you, I'm not opposed to any of the changes that is offered by the administration. I think it's a long time coming. I was hoping to see a constituent person, which was mentioned on many, many occasions, something that I feel is needed, in addition to a chief of staff, someone that will handle the constituent calls and be able to get back to people in a timely fashion.
And I've yet to see that. But my only concern is that many of these positions have morphed into other positions over the years. And as we know, we used to have a director of personnel and a budget director that no longer exist. Then we had someone that was a procurement officer that was doing the duties, because as far as I know, Louise was still signing off on the paperwork and also was budget director and I believe at some point was personnel director. That's correct. For a period of time.
That position morphed into three what I would consider department heads. So I only bring up that issue because I would hate to create a city ordinance and then in six months from now, a year, two years, whatever it might be, be unable to find a person that suits the procurement requirements, which is certification, and also the budgeting requirements.
And that may be a special person that is unique to Louise and not unique to a lot of people out there in that profession. I understand your sentiments, Counselor, but I would also say, and I'm probably preaching to the choir on this, ordinances like other enactments, other regulatory schemes are always in a state of flux. They reflect the needs and the desires of the government at that particular time. So if there are needs that are unforeseen right now in the future, I'm sure that this Council in its wisdom
and the mayor in her wisdom will take appropriate action to address that. I'm not saying that to be a funny guy. What I'm saying is that this is not necessarily the end of proposals from this administration, certainly not the first night. And so when you talk about the need for this officer or that officer, no one should draw the inference that these amendments and proposed amendments tonight or new ordinances is the end of the universe as far as proposals from this administration.
I don't know what they are because I'm not the mayor. But I do know that ordinances are always, and views of government, are always fluid. They're always in a state of flux. So I understand your sentiments. I don't think anyone's saying that this is the end and the final. But, you know, for many years, we've received piecemeal. And one of the biggest issues with this council, besides transparency, was the fact that we receive things in piecemeal form. And as we receive tonight,
These are great first steps, but I as one, like Councilor Longo mentioned, would like to see the overall picture. What is the current organizational chart of the administration? What's it going to look like? What's the additional staff that's going to be needed? There's talk about a 3-1-1 system. The 3-1-1 system is only as good, and we heard from Councilor Scott Pelli, who happens to work in Somerville, and they've had this system for a number of years.
It's only as good as the staff that you have on. And we all know many of our departments, DPW, you can go through the list, are understaffed. So it's great to say we're going to implement this new program, which I've been pushing for for a number of years.
But I've yet to see any substance behind it that's going to say, with this new program, we're going to be able to staff it appropriately so people get timely calls back and their issues are addressed in a timely fashion. So these are the things, I guess, I'm not part of that 28-person transition committee. But these are the things that I have questions on. And the reason why we asked that it be tabled is
that we see an overall picture. I follow that, Councilor Mox. And like you, I am not a member of the transition team either. And I would also say that 311, as a citizen, I might say, is a very meritorious program. But it's also totally and completely outside of these amendment proposals this evening. I just mentioned that parenthetically. Thank you. Motion to withdraw my motion to table. On the motion, Councilor Longo Kern has
Withdrawing her motion to table. Councilor Caviello. Thank you, Mr. President. I want to thank Councilor Marks for bringing up the point. I don't think we mean any disrespect to Louise because I think we both agree that Louise Miller is very qualified to do both positions. And I have full confidence that she can. And I think we're both looking at the position going forward, not at this particular moment. But I said, you know, I have full confidence that Louise
Miller is competent to do both of those positions. Thank you, Councilor Caravaglio. Chair recognizes Councilor Knight. I yield my time, Mr. President, to the gentleman at the podium. Mr. President, Mr. Gentleman at the podium, please state your name and address for the record. Tom Zook, 29 Garfield Ave, Medford. You know, I sit here at the City Council meeting and I keep hearing about we need to raise taxes. We need to raise taxes.
Is the city that broke and now all of a sudden we have this abundance of money that we're going to hire all these new people? That's what we have to look at. I mean, just two, three weeks, two, three meetings ago we were discussing raising taxes. I believe what came out of the committee of the whole meeting was that the sum of
The financial impact on the current fiscal year's budget would be $953 for the remainder of 2015, if I'm not mistaken, Mr. President, just for personal peace of mind. So if these ordinance changes were passed this evening, the impact it would have on this year's budget would be $953 based upon what was presented to us this evening.
We're not going to pass it this evening. We've all agreed to table the matter until— But in the very near future, she's going to want those positions filled. Am I right? I think they're filled by now, is what she's saying. She's trying to reorganize the structure of government. I mean, direct our comments to the chair. But they are filled already. You've made your point of information. You may continue. All right, I will. Ma'am, please state your name and address for the record. Jean Martin, 10 Cumming Street. And I just wanted to—not on the positions, but on one point that the solicitor said that I was in
a definite disagreement with, all due respect, these people get paid a lot of money and they get paid to think. When I was a private in the Army, I was told point blank, you don't get paid to think, you know? And I said, I think, Sergeant, and he said, private, you don't get paid to think. But anyway, these guys get a lot of money, a lot of money. They get paid to think about the future. They get paid to think about what's going to happen in five years from now.
So with all due respect to the solicitor, it's not about the positions. I don't, you guys wrangled that out. The point is, is that yeah, you guys are getting paid lots of money to think down the future. And that includes the mayor. So she needs to think what's going to happen in five years. So that's all I wanted to say. And thank you. And with due respect to the solicitor. Thank you. Good evening.
Thank you, sir. Please state your name and address for the record. Watch the button there, please. I did. Bob Penta, 07 Road Method Mask. I'd just like to bring your attention to the number F section over there, where it says report to the director of finance auditing on matters that pertain to procurement. On January 5th of this year, the city administration appointed Ann Baker to also be the city treasurer, beside being the city auditor. She can't do that. It's illegal. It's against the law.
and I don't even know why she's being allowed to do that. The second section of the law is very specific as it relates to where we're going on that. Chapter 41, section 52 states that all accounts are rendered to be kept in the departments of the city shall be subject to the inspection of the city auditor or officer having similar duties. Now, the term city auditor and town auditor is interchangeable under our state statute. Then you go to chapter 41, section 55, and it's clear as a bell.
The town accountant shall be sworn to the faithful performance of his duties, shall hold no other town office involving the receipt or disbursement of monies." So, I don't know where you're going with that. I think Mr. Solicitor, you need to look at that. I could be wrong, but the way I read that, your town auditor or your city auditor, which is Ann Baker, is also now, as of January 5th, the city's tax collector. She can hold both those positions, a direct conflict of law.
Uh, it's conflict of interest, excuse me. And the law is very specific, especially chapter 41, section 55. I think a committee of the whole is so important to understand all the ramifications, you know, what this is all about. Um, you, as I said before, you have a lady that's a come on board from the transition team at $106,000 a year, um, as the director of budget and personnel. And that's what her title is, unless that's going to change in the future, what have you.
These are issues that I think the council needs to know. I think you need to know all the names, the dollar amounts, and wherever you're going. But the conflicts that possibly and potentially arise, and this is one. It's as clear as a bell. She got appointed in January. She is our city auditor. And apparently, she's going to be the city treasurer for another 60 days. You can't do it. The law is specific. It's not me saying it. It's the law. You only can serve one master. You only can serve one position at one time, especially in the city or town.
And with all due respect, I just think before you guys just jump in, ladies, before you jump into this thing, I think you really need to understand the full ramifications. Not only that, but the background of the individuals that are accepting these positions. Again, the mayor, whoever he or she might be, has that privilege of hiring whoever they want. But if there's a potential conflict, that needs to be addressed. And then if there's also a possibility that, I'm not saying take the job out of a classification, I'm saying take the job out of a time sequence.
and make it run coterminous with the mayor, whether it's a CAF 14, 18, 22, whatever it might be, as it designated to the terminology, chief of staff, secretary. I've got no problem with that. That's not the issue. The real issue is the person that's being hired, whether it's at will or whether it's coterminous. But more importantly, in this particular case, I think it needs to be addressed immediately. Ann Bega cannot be the city auditor. She cannot be the city's tax collector at the same time. The law is specific, chapter 41, section 55,
says it, I don't say it, and I would expect that the city takes the appropriate action on that matter, just to make sure that they don't get themselves in any kind of a quandary as a conflict that possibly could exist. Thank you. When a person stands up and says that there's conflict of interest, so there's something awry going on, and they just says, well, the city should take a look into it. The brush has already been used on an appointment and said,
It's illegal. That particular statute, if you read it carefully and went through it, you'd know that it does not prohibit a temporary appointment of the city auditor to the position that she has at the city treasurer's with the retirement of the treasurer collector, Mr. Pompeo.
But to stand up and to say there's a conflict of interest on this other matter, but yet have nothing to say except to read a statute and say that's it, so you should do something, and it has nothing to do with the papers in front of you, I think that that's steep. I think that that's disingenuous. I think that that's precipitous.
There's going to be another city treasurer at some juncture. Ann Baker is not the city treasurer for the future, but somebody has to have those duties held right now. That has nothing to do with the amendments before you. All it is is trying to just paint somebody with a black brush in order to reach another result. It's not fair. As a city employee, I say that's not fair, and it's not true. Mr. President? Chair recognizes Vice President Longo. I'll yield to Councilor Marks.
There's no yielding chair recognizes counselor marks. Thank you, Mr. President. Maybe Mr. Solicitor, if you could answer something that does the treasure collector report to the city auditor in the normal course? Yes. So, so I can see what you're saying, but how does the oversight exist?
when it's one and the same person? That is a legitimate question, but it does not rise to the level of a conflict of interest which is prohibitive. Now, one might say that an accountant shouldn't hold both jobs. That would be a matter of accounting standards.
The question is whether or not it's illegal under the laws of the Commonwealth of Massachusetts. I've read that statute, the one that deals with towns and town accountants. And you'd really have to stretch that statute to say that it would put the appointment of the finance auditor into conflict of interest.
What has to happen is the machine of the city in terms of finances and dollars has to move, and it will move until there's a treasurer-collector appointed, which hopefully won't be in the distant future. But we looked at that statute, and I looked at it specifically, read it line at a time. You'd really have to stretch that to say that it's illegal to undertake a temporary appointment.
So, so getting back to the question regarding the auditor's responsibility. Yes. Then where is the oversight now with the treasurer collector? Is it within an Baker in the auditor's position? Yes, it would have to be. So she, she will be overseeing on a temporary basis, her office and the treasurer's office, right? That's the one person. Yes, that is true. So she has a concern in the treasurer collector's office. Yes.
She reports back as the acting treasurer-collector. As incongruous as that may sound. OK. And why is it assistant treasurer-collector? There is one. Why would that person not assume the responsibilities? That's a question which is not before me, because that was never broached. It's a very valid question. Right, but it's also not. You have a very capable person in that role. There are a number of questions which are valid, reasonable, but are yet not before us.
Thank you, Mr. President. Thank you. Mr. President, I would like to make a response since the city solicitor challenged. Point of order, Councilor Knight. I don't really think that it's an appropriate forum for a citizen and a city employee to be debating at the floor of the city council meeting. It isn't. We've met, we've had our committee of the whole meeting. We have some questions that need to be answered, Mr. President, and that's all well and good. We're going to be having another committee of the whole meeting on that when those questions do get answered. However, I don't feel as though it's appropriate for
individual citizen and a member of the administration to go back and forth at the podium here at the City Council meeting. I think that it detracts from what we're here to do. Thank you. Thank you. Sir, this isn't an opportunity for you to debate. This is a meeting of the City Council and this is a meeting of the City Council. It's a meeting of the City Council, Mr. Penta.
I'll address my comments back to the City Council so we don't have to have a discourse back and forth between my friend, the City Solicitor, and myself. If he wanted to take that one step further as to what I said, I didn't say it was illegal, I said it has potential for conflict of interest. And Councilman Marks is absolutely right. If there is at present an Assistant City, what's her name, Treasurer, no, Mrs. Baker, an Assistant, there's two Assistants in both of those offices.
Whether it's Ann Baker as the auditor or Fred Pompeo's office as an assistant, they both have two capable individuals that could assume either one of those roles. And my argument is, and it's very specific in here, I have a difference of opinion with my city solicitor friend, whether either one of those two assistants assume the position, but making one person assume both of them when you have other people just as capable
and able to do the job presents and begs the issue. And that's what the issue is. How's the checks and balances going to take place? A city auditor is supposed to be the checks and balances as to how and when the city spends its money. So if the city auditor wants to challenge, you know, what the treasurer-collector has done in the past, which has been her job, now that person is assuming both those positions. She will have a conflict between herself as to what role am I supposed to play, the auditor or the treasurer-collector?
And that makes no sense at all. And especially since you have the personnel that are in this building, well qualified, work their way up to the ranks, they should be given that opportunity rather than even get into this discourse that we're having right now. That's what begs the question. Why are we even discussing this? There is no need for this. You have people in this building, they're getting paid, they've been trained, and they do their job well. But to take one person and put it in charge of two, which is the checks and balance person, how do you checks and balance yourself?
That doesn't make any sense. The law is very specific. You only can serve one thing. And whether it's temporary or not temporary, we're not at that juncture of the road. Where we are right now is the fact that you have personnel that are capable and able of doing the position. And that's what you should be talking about, and that's what should be being addressed. Not one person assuming two positions and scratching their head and saying, what would happen if something were to happen? Thank you.
Councilor Knight, I do believe that the executive branch of our municipal government does have something that will be called administrative prerogative, Mr. President, which would be the right to hire, fire, and create positions that they see fit if they fall within the scope of our ordinance. With that being said, Mr. President, I motion that we table the matter until all questions are answered as previously discussed and agreed upon in the committee of the whole.
On the motion to table by Councilor Knight, all those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries. 16-023, to the Honorable President and members of the Medford City Council, City Hall, Medford, Mass, 021553, Amendment to Chapter 66, Personnel, Article 2, Clash Specification and Compensation Plan, Section 66-33, Entitled Officers, Employees-Non-Union. Dear Mr. President and members of the City Council,
I respectfully request and recommend that your honorable body approve the following amendment to chapter 66 personnel, article two classification and compensation plan section 66 dash 33 entitled officers, employees, non-union of the revised ordinances of the city of Medford. The purpose of this amendment is to change the compensation plan for those positions that have been created and amended pursuant to the common responding resolution submitted to the council for its consideration.
an amendment to the revised ordinances of the city of Medford chapter 66 dash personnel article two classification and compensation plan section 66 dash 33 officers and non employees non-union be it ordained by the city council of the city of Medford that division four of the revised ordinances of the city of Medford as most recently amended is hereby further amended by changing language of chapter 66 personnel article two classification and compensation plan
Section 66-3, Entitled Officers and Employees-Nonunion, as follows. Amendment A, classification CAF-21 pleasantly states in pertinent part that it applies as follows. CAF-21, director of budget slash personnel, the language of CAF-21 shall be amended to read and apply as follows.
CAF-21 City Solicitor, Chief of Staff and Policy. Amendment B, classification CAF-19 presently states in pertinent part that applies as follows. CAF-19 Clerk, Treasurer-Collector, Director of Public Health slash Elder Services, Chief Assessor.
Language of CAF dash 19 shall be amended to read and apply as follows. CAF clerk, treasurer, collector, director of public health slash older services, chief assessor, chief budget officer, and chief procurement officer. Amendment C reference to director of budgets and personnel presently exists in CAF 21 is hereby deleted reference to city solicitor as presently exists in CAF dash 20.
It's hereby deleted, respectfully submitted, signature on file. Stephanie Muccini-Burke, Mayor. Mr. Solicitor. Thank you again, Mr. President. These amendments would apply to the compensation schedule, and they would mirror and mimic the ordinance changes or creation that have been talked about in the earlier three papers. I think we went over them fairly deeply in the Committee of the Whole.
basically what they would do is ascribe a salary classification to each one of the positions as amended or as created. Chair recognizes the Vice President. No? This is a committee of the whole, Mr. President. A motion to table by Councilor Knight, second by Councilor Facco. All those in favor? All those opposed?
16-024 to the Honorable President and members of the Medford City Council, City Hall, Metro-Massachusetts 155, reamendment to Chapter 66, Personnel, Article 3, Personnel Policy, Section 66-64, entitled Vacation. Dear Mr. President and members of the City Council, I respectfully request and recommend that your Honorable body approve the following amendment to Chapter 66, Personnel, Article 3, Personnel Policy, Section 66-64, entitled Vacation of the revised ordinances of the City of Medford.
The purpose of this amendment is to allow new employees to accrue vacation from the start of their employment, but to prohibit them from using any vacation time that accrues until after the passage of six months from the start of their employment. An amendment to the revised ordinances of the city of Medford chapter 66 personnel article three personnel policy section 66 dash 64 vacation be it ordained by the city council of the city of Medford that division four of the revised ordinances
The City Method, as most recently amended, is hereby further amended by changing the language of Chapter 66, Personnel Article, Personnel Policy, Section 66-64, entitled Vacation. That same section presently states, generally, all...
permanent officers and employees of the city with the exceptions noted in section 66-61 shall receive a vacation without loss of pay in each calendar year if he or she has actually worked for 30 weeks in the aggregate during the 12 months preceding June 1st in such calendar year. The language of said vacation
of said section 66-64 shall be amended to read as follows. And I'm taking the amended version that was presented to us by the solicitor and committee of the whole. Is that correct, Mr. Soliciting? Yes. So the amended one shall be read into the record tonight, the one that you distributed to us. Yes, because the other one had a phrase in it that should have been corrected. Correct. So the language of said section 66-64 shall be amended
to read as follows. Vacation. General. All permanent officers and employees of the city, with the exception of noted in section 66-61, shall receive a vacation without loss of pay in each calendar year, which shall be based on the number of years of their employment. During the first six months following the inception of the employment, said permanent officers and employees of the city may not utilize any vacation time
but this requirement shall not prohibit the accrual of the same during that six month period. Mr. Solicitor. Thank you again, Mr. President and members of the council. This is an amendment that this really had been talked about for some years. It's the ordinance that deals with, uh, working, uh, the aggregate of 30 weeks before, uh, in the 12 months before June one in any calendar year,
is an odd thing to apply. This just clarifies that and says, doesn't change any vacation, doesn't add any vacation. It just says when a new employee comes into the city's employment, that for the first six months, they can't take any vacation. However, they will accrue the vacation and be able to take it at the end of the six months. It has no budgetary impact on anything. It is clear. It is a good personnel policy. And I will say this,
The first time that this was talked about was years ago, and the person who talked to me about it was President Mayor Burke when she was in the personnel position, and she was going over the rules and said, this doesn't make sense, and it needs to be cleared up. And when she mentioned it to me after she was sworn in, she said, do you remember what we said a few years ago about vacation? And she had her notes. This reflects those notes. It's clear. It's good personnel policy.
And I don't think, um, I know the questions that you've asked on those other positions and table those papers. I suggest, and I recommend that this one be acted upon because I think it's a good change and a clear change. And, uh, it doesn't have any budgetary impact and it assists all employees, especially those who are new to understand what their obligations are. Move approval on the motion for approval by
Councilor Knight, this would be the first reading on this ordinance change. On the motion of approval of Councilor Knight, seconded by Councilor Caviello. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll for the first reading. Councilor Caviello. Yes. Councilor Falcone. Yes. Councilor Knight. Yes. Vice President Leno-Kern. Yes. Councilor Miles. Yes. Councilor Scott Kelly. Yes.
Yes. With a vote of seven in the affirmative, none in the negative. It passes the first reading. Motion to waive the additional readings, Mr. President. On the motion of Councilor Knight to waive the additional readings. All those in favor? All those opposed? Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Councilor Caviello? Yes. Councilor Falcone? Yes. Councilor Nye? Yes. Vice President Long-Term? Yes. Councilor Monk? Yes. Councilor Scarpelli? Yes. Councilor Galbullo? Yes. So we'll vote a seven in the affirmative, none in the negative. 15. Thank you, Mr. President. 16-024 is ordained.
Motion to revert back to the regular order of business, Mr. President. The motion of Councilor Knight to revert back to the regular order of business. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries. 16-014 offered by Councilor Knight, be it resolved that the Memphis City Council hold the Committee of the Whole to discuss and establish goals and priorities for 2016. Councilor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much. Two years ago when I was sworn in as a councilor, we began an exercise where we would meet in the Committee of the Whole to establish goals and priorities for this council moving forward.
We'd use that as a template and a basis for our direction as we continue to make legislation here as a legislative body in the city of Medford, Mr. President. I think it was a very helpful endeavor, and it also allowed us an opportunity to begin to prepare for budget discussions. When I look at the agenda for this evening, I do see another paper on there offered by Councilor Falco relative to establishing a budget template and budget formats, which I'm going to be in full support of tonight, Mr. President. But I think that this is really a good way for us to start the discussion and to look forward to June.
to see what our priorities are, what steps we're going to take to keep Metro moving in the right direction and to improve the way that we do business. Very good. I'd ask my council colleagues to support the resolution. On the motion of approval by Councilor Knight, seconded by Councilor Falco. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries. On the motion of Councilor Caviello to take 16-025 out of order. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries.
16-025 offered by Councilor Caviello, be it resolved that the Memphis City Council request that the Mayor examine the possibility of establishing a Veterans Advisory Committee as allowed by Massachusetts General Laws, Chapter 115, Section 12. Councilor Caviello. Thank you, Mr. President. Mr. President, I've looked into this, and we have a Veterans Department here, and I am the Veterans Subcommittee Chairman, and Mr. Lindsey does a very good job in what he does, but
I think his office is understaffed and could use probably some help on some things. And this would be a way at no cost for the city to put together an advisory board to give him a little bit of help in the office and maybe some guidance. And also it would get a chance to
Get some other veterans involved with the board, possibly some younger veterans, along with the old ones. And maybe we could set some policies and a direction for our veterans office in the future, Mr. President. So what I say, I would hope that Mayor Burke would take this under consideration. So on the motion approved by- I think we have someone, a gentleman who would like to speak this evening. On the motion of council, Clerk Caviello for approval.
The chair recognizes Vice President Longo Kern. Thank you, President Del Rosso. I just want to thank Councilor Caviello for finding this Mass General Office 115, section 12. And I agree. I think any chance you can get to get the board shall consist of not more than five, not less than five or more than 15 residents of the city. So, I mean, we'd be lucky to get 15 veterans to help out Mr. Lindsey and advise him on, you know, maybe different ways that he should be.
I have mentioned to other veterans, and they probably have a half a dozen that are already interested right now. So I hope that the mayor looks into it, and obviously does an open public process to try to get interested veterans to help out and get involved. I think it's a great idea, and hopefully we can implement it. Very good. Chair recognizes Councilor Nye. Mr. President, thank you very much. I also had an opportunity to take a look at Chapter 115, Section 12. And as Councilor Longo-Kurtz said, that it would be comprised of between five and 15 members.
that are residents of the city. But in looking at the general law, and I may be wrong because I haven't had a chance to examine it thoroughly, there is no requirement that those individuals on the Veterans Advisory Committee be veterans. Right. Okay. So with that being said, Mr. President, I think it might make sense for us to maybe request that a certain percentage or portion of the individuals appointed to the Veterans Advisory Council when established be veterans.
whether it be 50% plus one of the individual positions that are established by the mayor if she takes us up on this offer. I think that that would be... I think that that's a good approach, Councilor Caravaglio, taking a two-fold approach where we send the request to the mayor, and then we have an opportunity to make some recommendations and act on her response would probably be the best course. So I certainly support the resolution, but ask that the Veterans Subcommittee also take a look at it. Very good. So on the motion of Councilor Caravaglio,
for approval as amended by counselor Knight to send to the, uh, veterans subcommittee. Roll call vote has been requested. Mr. Clerk, if you would please call the roll. Councilor Cario. Yes. Councilor Falco. Yes. Councilor Knight. Yes. Vice-president McCurran. Yes. Councilor Mox. Yes. Councilor Scott Pelley. Yes. President Del Russo. Yes.
vote of seven in the affirmative none in the negative the motion carries on the motion of vice president low current to return back to the regular order of business all those in favor all those opposed the motion carries 16-0 1 5 offered by councillor night be resolved that the Memphis City Council be provided a monthly report of all three one one calls councillor night
Yes, Mr. President, as we're all aware, the city is going to be soon rolling out a 311 program where individuals can make service requests. And I think that it would be a good idea if the administration would forward these reports to the city council so that we can have a good understanding as to whether or not the program is actually meeting its stated mission goals and objectives. So with that being said, I asked my colleagues to support the resolution. Move for approval. Motion for approval. Chair recognizes Councilor Falco.
Thank you, Mr. President. I think this is a great resolution. I definitely support the 311 system. I think it does bring a great deal of transparency to the issues that, you know, the issues that the city addresses on an everyday basis. But what I'd like to do is, if we could possibly find out what type of reporting is actually available from the system. I mean, usually these systems have all kinds of reporting that are available. It'd be good to actually see what's available. I mean, in particular, I think it's great that we're going to
that we can get some type of reporting, but I would like to see, I mean, to be specific, the issues that people call about when they are reported, the department that handled the request, the status of the issue, when they're resolved and the duration of time it took to resolve the issues, because I think that will answer questions with regard to staffing and when we're looking at budgets. So if we could get some detailed reporting with that information, I think that would be beneficial for everyone.
Very good. So as amended by councilor Falco, that, uh, the city council also receive a report back from the mayor's office as to what type of reports the new system can generate and how they may be tabulated, presented and, uh, uh, have their numbers crunched. Absolutely. Very good. On motion for approval, uh, madam vice president. Thank you, president DelaRusso. I want to thank my colleagues for, um,
the request, I think it goes along with requests we made a few months back when we did find out that the 311 system was going to be implemented. We just asked for updates on how it was going to work, how we were going to be able to view the system. So maybe we have not got that response. I'm trying to look exactly on the date we requested that, but maybe a quick 30-minute committee of the whole meeting with whether it be the mayor, whoever, whatever department head is going to run the system.
so that we can ask questions, because if there is glitches or anything like that, we're going to get the calls from the residents. Who do we call? What's the number? How do we do it? How do we process it online? Where do we go to look to see what order it's in? So maybe if we could get a committee of the whole meeting to discuss, ask questions, and be able to understand what is being implemented. From what I understand, the go date is March 2000, which is only a month or two away, so I would like to know
exactly how the program works myself so that I'm able to explain to residents who have questions with regards to how it works and what the process is. So that would be my request. That would be good to have a meeting on it, yes. Thank you. And I think one of the things is that because we received it in the springtime, everyone was trained on it, and now it hasn't been used.
I think they're doing retraining and they're going to do, uh, I don't know. We'll receive it all in the community. The whole chair recognizes council. I just want to, uh, reiterate what council Longo just said that, uh, we need to have a presentation on how this is going to work. This is a very important system, uh, in our community. And, um, at the very least, I think we should have a committee, the whole meeting. So, uh, the sooner we can set that up, the better. Well,
we'll schedule something soon because this is something that the entire council has asked for for years. And I didn't even from through the chair, I didn't even know of a training that went on. So I think we all kind of just need to be brought on the same page that anybody can call us and ask questions. And we know how to navigate the system ourselves. Um, if a resident can't or isn't computer savvy, we can say, I'll look into it. Let me, and then we'll be able to check whether it's the website or some somewhere on the,
Internet to be able to figure out, you know, how to answer our constituents' questions. That would be helpful for us. Thank you. Great. So on the motion of approval, all those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries. 16-016 offered by Councilor Knight, be it resolved that the Substance Abuse Outreach and Prevention Coordinator update the Council on their efforts. Councilor?
Mr. President, thank you very much. I recently had a discussion with Karen Rose at the Board of Health, who would be the department head that would be responsible for the Substance Abuse Outreach and Prevention Coordinator. She was pleased to inform me that the incumbent on the position, Ms. Penny Funiali, has had her child and is on maternity leave. So she will be unable to appear before the council to highlight some of the efforts and successes that the program has had since its inception. With that being said, Mr. President, Ms. Rose did
commit to having Penny appear before the council when she does return. So I'd ask that the council approve this resolution and then when Ms. Funigalli returns from her maternity leave, we ask her to come up here and tell us exactly what's going on with the new office and the new position that this council created. Very good. On the motion for approval, all those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carried. 16-018 offered by Councilor Falco, whereas the City of Medford, uh, the Medford City Council is required to pass the 2016-2017
Medford City budget and in a timely and complete information is required to perform this task. Whereas the school department produces a written narrative budget summary with goals, objectives, priorities, and staffing vacancies, be it resolved that the Medford City Council request a budget template format from the administration for the upcoming budget for review and approval. Councilor Falco. Thank you, Mr. President. Uh, one of the most important responsibilities that we have in the city council is to review and approve
the yearly budget for the city. We have a fiduciary responsibility to the taxpayers of our city to make sure that the budget and the budget process is fair and transparent. The resolution that I offer tonight is to take a proactive approach to the upcoming budget cycle. When I was on the school committee, we had a budget that had a written narrative with summaries and goals, and I believe that a city budget should be comparable. This year, I'd like to see a city budget with an overview and detailed analysis.
Each department should produce a mission statement, organizational charts, a list of personnel goals, objectives, accomplishments, and performance metrics. That's where the 311 system would really come in handy. Above all, I think that the budget needs to be easy to review and very descriptive so that the public can understand how their tax dollars are being spent. Information like this makes the process transparent, and it's much easier for residents to read.
Our current process seems to be a binder full of spreadsheets, and I think that it can be improved upon. I'm sure that the new administration will make improvements. I'm confident of that. But I believe that as a council, we should be proactive in this request of the aforementioned recommendations in preparation for the upcoming budget. I move for approval. Very good. On the motion for approval by Councilor Falco, chair recognizes Councilor Caviello. Thank you, Mr. President. I want to commend Councilor Falco for bringing this forward.
From my first term on the council, I had always been critical of our budget process and the budget that we've gotten. And I hope that this year we get a budget, not a budget summary like we've gotten in the past. So again, I hope that Mr. Falco's motion for this new type of budget goes forward with our city administration. I mean, this will be our first budget with Mrs. Miller.
and hopefully she'll take the suggestions, uh, uh, with her. Very good. Thank you. Counselor. Counselor chair recognizes Councilor Marks. Uh, thank you, Mr. President. It's a breath of fresh air to have someone with a council of Falco's background in budgeting, uh, in his, uh, profession, uh, on the council, because that's been a bone of contention, uh, with this council for many years, uh, receiving a line item budget from the administration and really nothing else.
No narrative, no clear direction on which way the city's going. And with that being said, I happen to have done a little research on outcomes-based budgeting. And you're probably familiar with it, Councilor Falco. But if I could, Mr. President, I just want to read a little narrative. Because I think this is the exact direction, at least I as one member of the council, and from what I'm hearing from other members of the council, would like to see take place in this community.
It states the new fiscal reality facing cities and towns across the Commonwealth necessitates that communities must be more judicious and prudent than ever before in their approach to providing services. Outcome-based budgeting, as opposed to the more traditional line-item incremental budgeting where expenditures are increased or decreased by a percentage from prior year levels, outcome-based budgeting is unique in that it ties in strategic planning,
Performance management. Outcome-based budgeting requires the mayor and department heads to develop an improved set of government priorities for the coming year, such as enhanced public safety or increased economic development. These larger priorities then cascade down through the departments and permeate each of their own annual work plans. Resources are then calibrated toward the specific activities that are designed to realize those outcomes.
I mean, I think that's exactly what we as a council have been talking about for years.
You know, it's great to get a line item budget, and there's 10,000 line items on that, and we go through and we say, okay, last year you gave line item 003 10,000, this year it's getting 11,000. There's no rhyme to reason. Why is it getting 11,000? We don't know. You know, one line item goes down, one goes up. And it never really addresses priorities. We've been talking about public safety, the police department.
We've been talking about the need for additional cruises. We've been talking about the need to repair roads and sidewalks and so forth, the leaking ceilings and preventive maintenance in our community on some of our city-owned buildings. And really, every year, we never really address those particular issues in the budget. It's more or less just looking at last year's budget and adding or decreasing lines. There's really no rhyme to reason.
And this outcomes-based budgeting, I think, it may not be the solve-all, but it allows us to hear from the different departments. It allows us, as Councilor Peto would state year after year, that if you had a wish list, you used to ask every department head, what is your wish list? And, you know, the department heads would either be open with you or not. But this outcomes-based budgeting forces their hand to say, hey, the administration wants to act upon public safety in this community.
And those particular department heads that have public safety within their budget would have to raise particular areas in their budget to address the needs of the community and what direction the mayor wants to go in. So, I support this wholeheartedly, Mr. President. I thank Councilor Falco for putting this on. And, you know, the ultimate goal is to ensure that each dollar in the city has a well-designed purpose.
each dollar is accountable to whatever resources they're earmarked to. And as we all know, at the end of a budget year, at any given year, we're transferring millions of dollars that we thought were appropriated for this particular use. A million dollars is going towards this, and at the end of the year, we have a million dollar surplus. And I think that speaks volumes on the need to dig a little deeper, I think,
So, that's what Councilor Falco is saying, and I hope this is part of the new process and the budgeting process. I thank you for offering this. Thank you, President DelaRusso. I, too, want to thank Councilor Falco for bringing this forward. I don't have the budget background, but I know two years ago we requested goals and objectives. To go even further is great.
I think that's something that should be reported every year by every department head. Goals, objectives, I like how you've furthered it with priorities, staff vacancies, accomplishments. I think that's necessary, and that's something that should have been done for a very long time, and I hope the administration makes that changes. One clarity, I just want to, you're looking for the template format. I just want to make sure that this also includes, you're asking each department head for those list of things, or is that how the template works?
Yeah. Thank you, Mr. President. The template would basically be, I want to see what the administration is going to provide us with regard to data. Are they going to provide us with mission statements, organizational charts, list of personnel? Those are the types of things I think we should see. And I'd like to know in advance, are they going to, you know, they should let us know, send us a template. You're going to see for, you know, the DPW, for example.
You're going to see a mission statement. You're going to see an organizational chart. You're going to see a list of personnel goals, objectives, accomplishments. So you're going to see that for each department. But I want them to confirm that they're going to send that to us. I don't want to find out when we're looking at a budget book in June that it's something different than what we would really like to see. So that's why I'd like to, I'd really like them to confirm sooner than later that when it gets to budget season, this is what we're going to see. So we can be prepared and we can know how to, you know, we can better analyze the budget as a group.
I'm in full support of getting the template, and I'm in full support of requesting a list of goals, objectives, priorities, and accomplishments from each and every department head months before. I think that's a great idea, and I hope that's something that we can work as a council to almost mandate through the administration, because we are the ones that vote on the budget. So if we make it very clear that this is something that should be done, then I hope to see that done before June.
Thank you, Madam Vice President. Chair recognizes Councilman Scott Pelley. If I can, I'd like to applaud my fellow councilman, Mr. Falco. We were both on the school committee, and I remember our first meeting when the first budget we went through, we received a budget book, I believe Friday or Father's Day, and to vote on a Tuesday. So we learned relatively quick.
that how we needed to work together collaboratively as a committee to make sure we get the answers that we need before we pass the budget onto the city council. Again, the mayor will present us with a budget, and I think what John's asking for and what we've done in the past with the school committee with having pre-budget meetings where department heads presented us with all of that information gave us the tools to make sure that we made the proper decisions. I know that the bone of contention
that's been talked about recently is the PR person. The PR person is something we talked about back in May of 2011 as part of our pre-budget conversations. So it's important that this is how we, it's the first step that I think that led us in a direction on the school committee in a positive direction, making sure that we're working with transparency. So again, I just want to applaud your resolution and
pretty excited about making this happen, so thank you. Thank you, Councilor. Chair recognizes Councilor Marks. Just a quick point, too. This council has requested, I believe, unanimously over the last several budgets that also within our budget book, we receive a column that shows whether the account was in a deficit or had a surplus the previous year. And I, as one member, know that's very helpful to look at. And, for instance, snow and ice, we end up funded by hundreds of thousands of dollars every year.
It's the only account that you can budget deficit spend. And but it's helpful, I think, especially as new members of the council, those two new members to see what accounts every year go into deficit, whether it's overtime or whatever have you, and then make adjustments accordingly. And, you know, I think any good budget person will make those adjustments on the fly. So year after year, you don't have the same accounts that are in deficit or surplus.
where money is being transferred. So I would again ask that be part of this report that the previous year that we receive whether or not that account was in a surplus or deficit. So as an amendment at the end of the motion. Thank you. Point of information, Counselor Scarpelli. Just for clarity.
as we move forward, the, the wishes of the school, this city council to ask for department heads to come to the rail or come to this meeting that would have to go through the mayor's office or that, that wouldn't be our privy, correct? That is correct. Okay. But we can, we can request the mayor's office that we ask for a pre-budget updates and from department as we move forward, just to make, make sure that we're clear. I think that council marks made that loud and clear, but we can always request. Thank you.
Thank you, councilor. Chair recognizes Councilor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much. And again, thank you, Councilor Falco, for bringing this matter forward. I think Councilor Scott Pelley hit the nail on the head. It's a partnership. It's a partnership between this council. It's a partnership between the administration and the school department and the community, Mr. President. And the school department had great success last year, putting together a school budget that was probably the best school budget that I've seen in a very long time. And I think that part of the reason the budget was so successful, because they had
the narrative budget summary that was there. They understood exactly what it was that they were working on and they didn't have to pry through 600 pages of line item budgets and ask every single question about every single line item because there was a narrative there, there was a mission there, there was an objective, a stated goal. And I was very pleased to vote in favor of the budget, Mr. President, because of the fact that the school department's budget was so strong and the work that it did in restoring adjustment counselors, so on and so forth. We could go over the successes time and time again as we have in the past.
However, we also passed a resolution back, I want to say in September, requesting that this council or the budget subcommittee meet quarterly with the administration to determine whether or not forecasts are meeting collections and to see where we are in terms of surplus and accounts and stuff like that, Mr. President. So with that being said, I'd like to see that those meetings start to begin getting called as this council did vote for unanimously by way of a roll call.
With that being said, I certainly support this resolution that's before the council today. I think it's a great idea. It's a great approach. It sets the tone for us to start working together now on the most important job that we have, which is setting the budget. So, Mr. President, I move for approval and I'd ask for a roll call. On the motion for approval, the citizen at the podium will speak before we take a vote. Good evening. Please state your name and address for the record. Andrew Castanetti, Cushing Street, Medford, Massachusetts.
As a taxpayer, I also would like to commend and thank Councilor Falco. It's a great common sense request to the city to get some budget information and hopefully the best information possible in due time so it's not too late. And hopefully better spend our taxpayers' monies
Thank you for your listening. Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Castaneda. So on the motion of approval by council night as amended, all those in favor, roll call vote has been requested. Mr. Clerk, if you would please call the roll council. Caviello, council Falco, council night, vice president, Lennon, current council marks. Council Scott Pelley, president Della Russo. Yes. For seven affirmative, none in the negative.
Motion passes. I must apologize. I forgot. Uh, it skipped over a resolution 16 dash 0 1 7. I'll be resolved that park method update the council concerning what steps they are taking to ensure the prevention of cyber attacks to users of the smart phone payment application. Counselor night. Um, Mr. President, thank you very much. As a frequent,
user of the smartphone application relative to the park mobile system, I received an article, and the article was in an online magazine called The Register. The headline was, Car Park Mobile Apps are Vulnerable to Hacking. And that made me rather concerned, so I continued to research, and I found another site called Hack Read, which said, researchers find critical vulnerabilities in the Android parking apps.
and Info Security Magazine. The headline would read, Researchers Find Major Security Flaws in Parking Apps. And what's happening, Mr. President, is that because of substandard encryption, which, quite frankly, means nothing to me, but might mean something more to some people that are a little bit more tech-savvy than I, these phones are becoming vulnerable to attacks because the information is up in the cloud and people are able to get at it. So with that being said, Mr. President, there have been a number of suggestions and recommendations made by these
And one of the biggest recommendations was that you use a credit card as opposed to a debit card to fund your purchases in your mobile app because of the fraud protections that are in the credit card system. However, Mr. President, we do have a parking program here in Medford. We do have a ParkMobile app here in Medford. So I would like to see what steps the ParkMobile people are taking to ensure that we do not have substandard encryption and that our consumers are protected.
from cyber attacks, Mr. President. And in segue to that, if anybody has been affected by a cyber attack of some sort, I would ask that they report the matter immediately to not only the police department, but also the Office of Consumer, the Medford Consumer Commission, rather. The First Floor of City Hall. First Floor of City Hall, the old Medford Savings Lives Office. So with that being said, Mr. President, I'd move for approval. I think that this is a basic
resolution that will allow us to understand what steps are being taken to keep consumers in the community safe. On the motion of approval by Councilor Knight, Chair recognizes Councilor Caviello. Thank you, Mr. President. Seeing that we're talking about the parking, it's been about a year now with the parking just about, I think, almost a year. And I'd like to see a report on our first year on monies collected, not collected, tickets, a full report. We got one about two months ago, I think.
It was filled in detail, surprisingly so. Yeah, so like I said, I think we're just about at the end of our first full year. I'd like to see where we stand with that and where we're going. I see more and more meter heads popping up in the city. And I'd like to maybe get a report on that too. Awesome. So on the motion of approval by Councillor Knight, as amended by Councillor Caviello, that we receive the first annual full report in detail
summary of action on the traffic parking enforcement. Chair recognizes Councillor Scarpelli. If I can, to add along, because we're talking about traffic and parking, if we can, too, through the chair, I've gotten some calls about some of the signs in Meffitt Square, the new signs that have been erected that I believe you need a master's degree to read them and to follow along. It's been very difficult for some of our seniors
to follow along. I think there's six different bullets in one. I believe Ms. Reynolds would say it was a carry on sentence as it keeps going on and on. So if someone can look into that too, it's important to get clarification for that. As amended by Councilor Scappelli, that the Park Medford, which has a purview over those signs in the contract,
review the content of the new square signs in Medford Square as they are difficult on the eye. On the motion. Hi citizen, you're welcome to speak. Please state your name and address for the record. Hi, my name is Cheryl Rodriguez. I live at 281 Park Street. Since you opened the park Medford a little more, um,
During the period that you were supposed to have the free Saturday parking, several people reported on Facebook and just parents speaking that they were paying for parking on the Saturday. The meters were not off. Park Medford still hasn't figured out how to turn their meters off. So maybe when you get your report, you might want to see how many people paid when they weren't supposed to. That seems like a breach of contract. And since we're always talking about the contract and how much it'll cost us to get out of it,
Maybe there should be some ramifications when they don't honour their contracts. Thank you. Mr. President? Sir? I'd like to speak about... Please state your name and address for the record. Bob Henton from Zero Summit Road, Medford, Massachusetts. I'd like to speak about the contract in one particular area. If you go back and look at the contract and look at the proposal that was made, we were talking at one point in time of possibly having zones here in the city of Medford.
And to date, there are no zones, and none of the METAs are identified as being in any particular zone. As Ms. Rodriguez just got through saying, during this past month of December, people were putting money in the METAs, and the METAs were accepting them.
I think the question needs to go a little bit further to the Park-Metford office to find out what their technology is, because they should be able to shut down that meter that indicates that they will not accept the money on any particular day. As far as the new meters in downtown Metford Square, I think Councilor Caviello can attest to this, because I think he was a product of it, putting the money in the meter, and the meter did take the money in Metford Square. So you have situations here that even where you have the pay park ones, and now you have the stanchions
where you put the quarters in, there are some problems. I think it would behoove the council not only to have your first annual update, Councilor Caviello, as you were talking about, maybe to have them come in here and find out, especially with two new councillors, what your concerns might be. They indicated that they have all this technology. They have this computer app technology and whatever it might be. But there definitely are concerns. There are people still getting tagged for no reason at all. And more importantly, there are no zones. City of Boston is very clear
on how they address their issue relative toward their parking and their meters, their zones and their territories. It would be very easy to put zone locations on each and every one of the meters and each and every one of the, you know, it doesn't take a lot to put, you know, the number, whatever it might be. And you don't have to go through the same thing. And on Christmas Eve day, Christmas Eve day in the afternoon, people were getting tickets right up until six o'clock at night. I think that's just a little bit disingenuous, as I said before,
They're nothing but a bunch of bounty hunters coming here to Boston and Medford, Massachusetts, to get as much money as they can. And it's just not working out. And with the two new councils on here, I would hope that they would be brought up to date that the past council, the very past one in December, voted seven to nothing to give the senior citizens in the city of Medford the break of not being able to pay, because that was one of the concerns that was attributed by the president administration that they would do. So I think it's an issue that needs to be addressed, and I think it's an issue
that should work well for the City of Medford, especially for the seniors in our city. Thank you. Chair recognizes Vice President Mungo Kern. Thank you. If we could just maybe amend, if Councillor Knight doesn't mind, to ask Park Medford, you know, what's being done to shut off meters, and is that a possibility? We did ask before, and I believe they said they were working on it, so the residents are right.
Sunday, the leaders should not be accepting money. It's not under contract. So I agree wholeheartedly. So if we can maybe get an update on that. On that amendment. Mr. President, I put the resolution forward to address issues of cyber security. Although I can understand why certain people are coming from Facebook and this guy got a ticket this day. It is what it is. There's an administrative procedure that's in place. If you feel as though you got a ticket,
erroneously that you go through the appeals process. With that being said, Mr. President, I have no problem amending the resolution. However, the principle that I wrote for was just exclusively for cybersecurity, and we kind of went off on a little tangent and went down a different kind of road, Mr. President, and that's not where I was looking to go. But with that being said, I'd ask that we
several amendments and move forward. On the motion for approval as amended and now to sever. So the amendments are? Annual update. Annual update. What technology do they have to shut the matter off? To shut the meters off. To shut the meters off.
So then we'll take them one by one. So on the amendment for an annual update, all those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Motion carries. The signs to be reviewed and report back to the city council as to the content of them, and can they be simplified for the average reader?
All those in favor? Aye. Those opposed? Carries. To have a check on shutting down the meters, are they shutting down when they're supposed to so that people aren't swindled into paying when they shouldn't have to? All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed?
And on the main motion of Councilor Knight, that report be given to the City Council as to cyber attacks and efforts to maintain cyber security in the payment system. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? The motion carries. Thank you all. Petitions, presentations, and similar matters. Petition by Gene Martin, 10 Cummings Street, Medford, Massachusetts, to discuss
preparing Union and Swan Streets to be converted for a municipal parking lot. Citizen Martin, welcome and please state your name and address for the record. Hi, Gene Martin, Municipal Lots. But anyway, this is, well, I'm going to be talking about two different little blocks. This is a citywide issue. This affects the Medford Square projects. This affects the business community. And I just want everybody to know that all of the
department heads need to be in and understand what I'm trying to get across. Because this is a citywide project, even though it's going to be talking about two small blocks. First of all, reorganizing Union and Swan Street. There are two small blocks between the police headquarters and the DPW yard. The first block is between Union and Swan, which are more like alleys than streets. And I recommend anybody just drive down Mystic Ave and Main
And go up those, quote, streets, they're more like alleys than they are streets. The second block between Swan and James is a little bigger. These two blocks, separating the police facility and the DPW yards, are small privately owned businesses. Along Union Alley, and I call it alley, are the following, Alsar Automotive, Carly Fence, Stevens Auto, and Lew's Custom Exhaust. Swan Street, A&P, Collision Center,
After that, a junkyard, complete eyesore, and then Eastern Tool Company. If you go down that road, if you look from above, and actually as you're going down it, there's a huge junk area. It just looks like an eyesore. On the left is a marble and granite company. James Street has all truck company. Unfortunately, the new public safety building is going to need at least the lots on Union to Swan Street to meet code.
for the current footprint, which is one-third too small, and so union to Swan is not an option, but rather a mandate. Whether or not we move the businesses on James Street is still optional. Since we are going to have to disturb that area, we might as well do it right to begin with. It makes sense to turn those two whole blocks, including James Street, into city-owned lots
so that we can increase our building space for other related departments. We need to work with these business owners and find them new lots for their businesses. And this is where you come in, Mr. Delarusso and Mr. Carviello especially, because you're both on the rotary and you need to be, you know, pushing for this, I think. Not only do I see the new police fire 911 facility staying where it is, but I see buildings that house other city departments.
in it like public health, building management, engineering, water and sewer, cemetery, any departments that seems compatible with police, fire, and DPW. The other aspect of this change is that it will impact the new square's view over the Mystic River. Currently, the view is ugly. So seriously, if you put those fancy condos above the storefronts, you know, where CVS is and all of that, they're gonna have an awful view.
I'm telling you, if you look down, do the aerial thing from, that's why I did this, aerial view, it's all junky, it's ugly. So it'll increase your property values of the Medford Square project as well, not to look over the river and then to, you know, to see all that junky stuff, mostly automotive places. And I'm not saying get rid of them, I'm saying help us move them. One other aspect of this change is that it will impact the new square's view on the Mystic River. Currently, the view is ugly.
As soon as these businesses are, some of these businesses are dumpy and crappy looking. So if you are going to gentrify the square with condos above the storefronts, then you need to clean up that view for them anyway. The losers appear to be the businesses. However, Carly Fence would do better on a front lot on Mystic Ave with a better eye-catching sign.
The other businesses will have a harder time finding lots because they are automotive by nature and have a lot of grease and oil and stuff requirements. I believe that the city would be short sighted not to consider the whole area between the police station and the DPW lots.
as possible office and building structures for city business, leaving more room in city hall for new areas of interest. As you know, the city is growing and it needs more space. Um, my point is, is that since this isn't going to happen tomorrow, we need to help plan with the five year vision of, you know, breaking ground at the police station. And if you do, you're going to have to do it where it is.
because it's centrally located, it's easy to find. You want police, fire, and 911 all in the same area. Clearly the current building size is not big enough, the footprint is not big enough. So you're gonna have to take over that little alley anyway.
So since you're going to do that and you're going to disturb the area, you might as well do it all in one shot with the business community, with all the department heads, with everybody on board and visualize what you want it to look like. And it'll serve as a, everybody will be happy. But what I'm saying is if we just take, take it by eminent domain, you're going to cause a lot of trouble. So if you, if I think that we all need to work with the business communities down there,
and find them another home inside the city where these automotive, mostly automotive places, body shops and whatnot, can do their business along Mystic Ave or someplace. There's got to be someplace for them. So if you don't, you're going to have to take the ground anyway. And it'll cause problems if it happens abruptly. So plan it well. Thank you. Thank you. Mr. President, Mr. Martin, if you'd like for your information. On the motion to receive and place on file by Councilor Knight,
Chair recognizes Councilor Caput. For your information, there's going to be some building going on down there, so I think Joseph's Limousine is planning on building a building down there, because they were on the Board of Appeals docket for this one. So I know there is some construction slated for down there. So they're going to build higher? Well, there's nothing there on the property. They are going to build a permanent garage there. Oh. Well, I think, I don't know. You guys got to stop it, man, because where are you going to put the police station?
Well, again, that's their property that they own. I know. But where's the police station going to go? But again, that's their property that they own. We just can't go and- With all due respect. I don't want to argue. But that's their property. Well, I understand that, sir, through the chair, with all due respect. And you know I respect you. The city has an obligation to provide public safety first before anything else, even my house. So when it comes to public safety,
the city should be able to take my house for public safety. I wouldn't like it. I would not like it. But that's, that's the, where are you going to put the public safety building? If not in the Medford Square where it is, where are you going to put it? That's my question. So I'll put that to the chair. I'll put that to the president. If not in Medford Square, right where it is, where are you going to put it? Thank you. The chair on
On the motion to receive and place on file by Councilor Knight, all those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries. Congratulations. Thank you. And papers under suspension too? All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries. 1516-026 offered by Councilor Caraviello. Be resolved that the Medford City Council request a timeframe
for removing the three old payphone stands in Medford Square and one in West Medford. I think you asked on this not too long ago. Yes, I did, Mr. President. Two were taken out, but there's still one at 43 Salem Street. There's two in front of the CVS on Riverside Avenue, and there's one across from 491 High Street that is still left standing there, and they're just eyesores.
on the sidewalk, there's no phones on them. 140 High Street? 43 Salem. Yeah. There's two at the CVS, in front of the CVS on Riverside Avenue with broken phones. And there's one across from 491 High Street. 491 High Street. Right in between St. Rayfield's Church and the gas station. Very good. Thank you. They're not kiosks. They're not kiosks.
They did take out the one at the Brookline Bank in front of the member's credit unit. So those two were removed, but there's still some other ones that need to be removed, Mr. President. And you also had on 16-027 be resolved that the Memphis City Council request the electrical department to remove the hanging wires at the bus stop at 382 Main Street. Again, thank you, Mr. President.
It was brought to my attention on Sunday that at 382 Main Street, which is Arthur's Pastry, right at the bus stop, there's been wires that have been hanging down, I guess for about a year. And I never really noticed them until Mr. Giordano brought them to my attention. So if we could have the electrical department go there and take them down, because they are kind of low.
Very good. So on the motion for approval for both those papers, all those in favor? All those opposed? Carries. 16-028 offered by Councilor Knight, whereas January 6, 2016 marks the five year anniversary of his passing, and whereas Michael J. Callaghan was a lifelong resident of Medford, and whereas Michael J. Callaghan is credited with protecting and preserving Wright's Pond as an open space, and whereas Michael J. Callaghan is credited with 48 years of public service
to the Commonwealth of Massachusetts and the citizenry of Medford. Be it resolved that the Medford City Council hold a moment of silence in honor of Michael J. Callahan, and be it further resolved that tonight's meeting be adjourned in remembrance of Governor's Counselor Michael J. Callahan. Please rise and join us in a moment of silence. And I think Counselor Knight wants to. If I may, Mr. President.
Michael Callahan was a good friend to me and many of us behind this rail, as well as many of us in the community. He was a mentor to me. He taught me more about government in the short time that I was able to know him and be around him. And he was a great guy who had his head on right. He understood that government was about people, about helping people, and about making sure that it's working for you, Mr. President. He's sadly missed. I think of him every day. And I appreciate the Council indulging me as I bring this resolution forward. Thank you, Counselor.
A couple of papers in the hands of the clerk. Offered by Councilor Marks. Be it resolved that long time Medford resident and my neighbor, Johnny Amari, be recognized for celebrating his 50th birthday. Councilor Marks. Thank you, Mr. President. Many of us know Johnny Amari for many years in this community.
Johnny has been an active member of this community for a number of years. He's a great guy. He just celebrated his 50th birthday, Mr. President. I had the opportunity to attend his birthday party. And let me tell you, Johnny hasn't changed a bit over the years. He's the same guy I remember. I grew up on Stearns Ave, right next door to Johnny. And he's the same gentleman I remember from years ago.
And many of us refer to him as the mayor of South Method. And he truly is, Mr. President. He's a staple in that particular section of the city. And I just want to wish him a happy 50th and another 50 for Johnny. Happy birthday, Johnny. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries. Offered by Councilor Marks. Be it resolved that the Winchester Street detour be discussed regarding public safety for area South Method residents. Councilor Marks.
Thank you, Mr. President. MassDOT came out with their construction detour information just recently, and I received a number of calls from area residents that were concerned about the increased traffic coming down some of the side streets. And I know the south side of Harvard Street
is to be completed and reopened on January 22nd. After the sidewalk is reopened, the gravel sidewalk on the north side will be closed for grading, curb, installation, and paving. The north side walk is estimated to be completed by February 5th, assuming no weather-related delays. And work cannot occur on the north side until the south side work is completed.
Each side requires its own lane closure. During the construction of the Harvard Street sidewalks, Winchester Street, and this is why I bring this up, Mr. President, is being used to detour traffic. The result of this is that there is an increase of speeding vehicles. Residents trying to exit their driveways onto Winchester from Morton, Granville, and Wareham are experiencing near misses trying to get out of their driveway. The recommendation from the neighbors I spoke with
They'd like to see, at least for the next several weeks, the temporary electronic flashing speed sign, speed limit sign, appear on Winchester Street to try to slow down some of these people that are using this particular area now, and that an increase in police patrols during rush hours be implemented to help alleviate some of the concerns of the neighborhood, Mr. President. So I would ask that those two recommendations, the temporary electronic flashing
speed sign be placed on Winchester Street, and increased patrols during rush hour, during the rush hours on Winchester and those surrounding Morton and Granville and Wareham. Very good. Some of those concerns were brought to my attention. I've already spoken to the chief about them, but these are excellent measures, Councillor. Thank you. A motion for approval by Councillor Marks. All those in favour? All those opposed? Motion carries. Offered by Councillor Caviello, we resolve that the Memphis City
Council petition the traffic commission in regards to moving the Jersey barrier by the Craddock bridge so that people can cross the street to frequent businesses. Also request temporary crosswalk in that position. Councilor Caviello. Thank you, Mr. President. Mr. President, you know, we spoke about this last week in the meeting, and on a Wednesday night, I met with the DOT, with Representative Donato at Carol's Restaurant, and they came down and promised to make
the necessary changes to that. And we explained to them how, you know, making an opening in one of those Jersey barriers would help out the people because now when they're parking on the other side there, they have to walk all the way up to the corner of the cross. They agreed to do it, and up until today, they still haven't done it. And I spoke with Representative Donato again, and he has recommended that we petition the traffic commission to get them to get on the
the construction company. And also, when they do that, if we could possibly put in a temporary crosswalk, so make it a little bit easier for people to cross there. But again, you know, they're killing the business over there. At least we should do our part to help out any way we can. Absolutely. On the motion for approval by Councilor Caviello, Councilor Marks. I thank Councilor Caviello for bringing up this important issue. However, I would state, Mr. President, when DOT was before us,
with all their high-paid salaries. They mentioned there's going to be a 24-hour hotline. There's going to be contact people we can get a hold of. Now we're hearing we have to petition our own traffic commission because we're unable to get a hold of DOT, as Councilor Caviello just mentioned, to make some small — these are minor changes, which makes — Mr. President, we met with them at 10 o'clock that evening, and they agreed to make these changes, and they just ignored it. Right. Right. So — so, that's my issue. You know, if —
elected officials, as Councilor Caviello, are unable to address some of the minor concerns, Mr. President. Maybe we have to put a halt on this project. Maybe it's about time. And I mentioned this several months ago, and, you know, I got a lot of feedback from people that were supportive of it, that we put a temporary halt on the project until some of these questions that are being asked by area businesses, Mr. President, and issues that Councilor Caviello just mentioned about the Jersey Barriers
are addressed, because it seems to me that DOT is not a willing partner in this, and they're going to go down kicking on every issue. And so, you know, if the council sees fit, I think we should offer a resolution, Mr. President, asking that if these issues are not addressed immediately, then a halt to the project be taken. And we take a vote on that, Mr. President. The President. Is that a suitable amendment, Counselor? Counselor, if my colleague would like, I'd be happy to put that on. As amended by Counselor Marks.
So on that motion, did you want to speak council? No. Okay. On that motion, all those in favor, roll call vote. Mr. President roll call vote has been requested. Mr. Clerk, if you would please call the roll timeline. So we know when we can, uh, should we wait a week to get a response? Well, we'll go into the traffic commission, which means monthly on this. Um, they don't meet again until next month. Correct. Which is right.
It seems like a long time to wait. If I may, I mean, we were here on Tuesday. We passed the resolution that was seven days ago, which was five business days ago. Councilor Caviello met them there Wednesday evening at 10 o'clock, which was in essence, really Thursday morning. So that was only three business days ago.
I think we need to give them an ample opportunity to get it done. I think council marks is on the right track. We need to put some sort of timeline in there to see if we can effectuate this change in a certain period of time. But I also want to be cognizant of the fact that it's really only been three business days that have passed since the request was made. So I don't know if we've gotten a refusal back from DLT saying that they're not going to do it. Please counsel. Um, the DLT came the next morning, they removed,
the barrels and the barriers from in front of one of the businesses. And he said that that next morning, he would also open a space up between the Jersey barrier to let the people cross. Then, according to Representative Donato, he's saying that they're not doing it now. Point of information, Counselor Scarpelli. Again, please, forgive my naive train of thought here, but what city department,
and director is overseeing the building. That should be OCD. So if OCD, why don't we... The city engineer has called you the point person on this project. Well, I think that we, for immediate action, we make the amendment that we send the department that's directly in charge there in the morning to give us an answer ASAP.
Would that be the engineering department, Mr. President? I'm under the impression that the engineer has been the point person. Based on my discussions with Mr. Daley from the DOT, that engineering has been. So if we could do that also. Refer to the traffic commission as well as the engineering department for immediate action. And Councilor Marks, you wanted a time frame if you would. I would say if we don't hear, if this is not resolved by next Tuesday,
And next Tuesday we take a vote to stop the project to stop the project. Bring the matter forward next week. It's not fixed. And if we could have an amendment that we have a suitable answer as to why this wasn't done, it'd be just small fixes. And it was all supposed to be worked out for the benefit of the businesses. So on the motion for approval, all those in favor, all those opposed motion carries unanimously records.
Mr. President, before we go to the records. Oh, yes, by all means. Mr. President, over the last, I think it's been three months now, I put on two separate resolutions that were voted unanimously by this council asking about the temporary speed bumps that were placed on Harvard Street and Central Ave. I'm under the impression that the one on Harvard Street now is gone.
as recently as a day. That has been removed. I have yet to get a response on two separate resolutions. Those two locations were part of the pilot program that involved three raised, not speed bumps, three raised crosswalks, of which Winthrop Street was the only one that was placed in. And I've yet to get a response, Mr. President. I know there's a new administration now, but I'm hoping that we can get a response back from someone in engineering or someone in DPW.
or someone in the building that's in the know why these two speed bumps have popped up in the community, why one now is gone, and what's happening with the raised crosswalks that the mayor came out with a press conference saying that this was part of the initial pilot program to help with pedestrian safety in our community. Three years ago. Right, three years ago, and to help mitigate some of the concerns we have with increased speeding in our community, Mr. President.
So I really would like to get an answer on that. This is a public safety concern. This is, this is not just some pie in the sky issue. This is a public safety concern. We read all the time in the paper about pedestrians being struck and killed. And it's not in every other community. It's in our community too. And, and really, uh, to not address these concerns is a detrimental Mr. President. So, uh, on the motion of council marks that the, uh, uh, mayor's office report back immediately to the city council,
regarding the status of the raised crosswalks, the aforementioned raised crosswalks, and the temporary speed bump program on Harvard and also on Central. On a motion for approval, all those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries. Records of the meeting of January 5th, 2016 were passed to Councilor Caviello.
Councilor, how did you find those? And I find them in order. And you move approval? I move approval. On the motion for approval of the records of the January 15th. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries. On the motion for adjournment by Councilor Caviello. All those in favor? All those opposed? Meeting adjourned.