Hi everyone and welcome to Method Happenings, a show for and about the city of Method.
I am John Petrella. The purpose of this program is to give Meffitt citizens facts and information to help you make informed choices. And our guest for today's show is Paul Donato, Jr., candidate for our Meffitt City Council. Paul, welcome to Meffitt Happenings. John, thank you and crew for having me here today.
Our pleasure. We're going to start right off, Paul. We're just going to go right into questions here. So what we normally do, first question, just tell us a little bit about yourself. Who is Paul Donato, Jr.?
So my name is Paul Donato, Jr. I'm a lifelong Medford resident. I was born here at the Lawrence Memorial Hospital. I've never left. I attended Medford High School and Davenport School, Roberts Junior High. I've been all over the city. So the whole thing, you... Yes.
Part of my work history is I'm in the hospitality industry, catering and concessions. If you come by the farmer's market on Thursdays, you'll probably bump into me and my children selling Italian ice. Yeah, you do a good job with that, too, by the way. Thank you very much. Yeah, you really do. So you're a lifelong Method resident. Yes. Good to know. So what are the reasons
I mean, thank you for running for council. We appreciate it. But what are the reasons making you run for Medford City Council? I mean, why do you want the job, Paul? The reason why I want the job is I want to be the voice for the people of the citizens of Medford that aren't being heard.
There's a lot of people out there that they don't have this, they don't have an opportunity to be heard. And I just want to be that person to represent the people of Medford. To put out information, listen to the people, do what the people want. Yes, that's correct. There's a lot of stuff going on that people need to know about. Okay, do you want to get into what's going on? I mean, a few things maybe?
Charter change. Okay. That was a big one. That was huge. Yes. I don't agree with a lot of things that's happening. Zoning, taxes, cost of living, the infrastructure and roads. Yep. And I think a lot of people agree with you, Paul, because the roads.
Yeah, the roads, the infrastructure, yeah. There's a lot of people listening and watching that are going to agree with that. So, you know, some of those are good reasons. You know, as a council, let's say you get on the council, you become a council member. Any solutions? I mean, what do you look to do to resolve all these issues? In my opinion, Mr. Gabb is the gateway to the city.
Okay. And about 35 years ago, people on the council had an idea to change Mystic Ave and it was outvoted and it didn't happen. And I believe that that is where we should start. We should focus our attention on Mystic Ave commercial and industrial zoning.
high-rises we have that whole side of uh... ninety-three right that we could put high-rises and mixed-use pedestrian walkways and bear garden things that uh... we deserve not only for us but bring some other people into it
So why, I mean, do you see any steps? I mean, what's this, the current people running the city, do you see, I mean, what do you see getting done? Do you see any steps being taken as far as, you know, Mystic Ave is a great one, the squares, I mean, what do you see? So I don't think that the focus should be on neighborhoods and residentials at this time. Okay.
I think that we should focus on our commercial. We have Cane's Potato, the old Cane's Potato Chips, GE. Oh yeah, I forgot all about that. Cane's, yeah. Cane's Potato Chips, GE. I mean, there's high-rise buildings there. You can build as high as you want, or 14 stories, 30, whatever it may be, and it's not gonna take away sunlight and ruin the neighborhoods that we currently have. People move to this city,
years ago in the 50s and 60s because of the neighborhood feel and the The comfortability of knowing your neighbors and I don't think that's happening anymore. I think that If they try to change the zoning in the neighborhoods It's gonna ruin some of that feel Yep. I hear you. Yeah, I don't want to see that in my yeah, no, I mean I I agree I agree with that I mean it seems like they're
you know they're focusing on parts of the city it's all residential and what they need to focus on i agree is the squares mystic ave so much that potential that we have here in the city that uh... we're not using right now those sites have been empty for a long time on mystic valley parkway you want housing that's the perfect place to start so i mean
Basically, my next question, I was going to follow up on the zoning. We're discussing it. We're talking about what your opinions are. I think you covered it all, really. So roads and infrastructure. Right. You can't put Band-Aids on the streets right now. OK. We need billions of dollars. Not millions, we need billions. So we've heard, yes. Billions of dollars.
And I don't think that they should be just patching up roads. Let's start in the bottom. Let's put in new gas lines, water lines, sewer lines. While we're at it, cable and electric. I think that they could, you know, if they're digging up the streets and the streets open, let's move the pipes underground. Right. Right. So this way we can
protect ourselves from future storms. I mean, we haven't really had any snow or some serious storms. We have been lucky. But we don't know what's going to happen 25, 50, 100 years from now. The infrastructure is over 100 years old. And I believe that we need to start there and getting some of the funds from the electric and the gas companies. And we'll let them pay for it.
I know that when you dig up the street, they should be doing curb to curb. Pat's work. Yeah, no, I hear you on that. And I'm only laughing because we all know, I mean, we've seen it, oh, I can name a dozen, Winthrop Street, I mean, all over the place.
where they come, I mean they do, they'll go up the length of a street. Willis Ave, they're doing stuff right now. I don't know how that's gonna end up coming out. In my study that I've been doing, the city of Medford does about 10 streets a year, complete streets. Okay. And I think that we need to have a 10 year program and we need to build it up to 30 streets, to 40 streets a year. Okay. In order to get to that 10 to 15 year goal. All right, yeah. To fix all of our streets.
It's a plan, yeah. Let the electric company and gas company pay for some of that infrastructure repair. They're the ones that are digging up our streets after it's just repaved. You just mentioned Winthrop Street, they repaved it. How many times? Three or four times they had to cut it up, open it, and start again. Yeah, I know some people that live up there, they weren't too happy. It just kept, it was like,
The ongoing saga never ending digging. Yeah, that's what it seemed like. Yeah, but uh, yeah, you know great answer, uh Yeah, it makes sense to to sort of do it all at once get it done do it right and while you're open
That's a novel idea. Fix everything at the same time. And then move on. A little bit at a time. Now we're going to get into economic development.
In this city, anyhow, I mean, it's stagnant at best. We just haven't, you know, and I don't know what the reasons are. I have no idea what's going on. But you mentioned Mr. Gav. There's so much potential. But anyhow, what are you going to do to get? Well, I know the current council voted to change Salem Street. We can start with that if you'd like. Right. Yeah.
I think that if a new council is elected, we can bring back some of those ordinances and things that they have changed. If we can change the council, we can change some of the things that they have brought forward. I know you're talking about this, but I don't think the council should be talking about
issues not in the city of Medford. Okay. Right? I know we didn't bring it up, but... Yeah, no, it's... I mean, yeah, I mean... Let's focus on what's going on in our city. Okay. It's not that I'm concerned about what's going on in other parts of the country and in the world. We all are, right. But right now, Medford needs us. Yep.
And let's focus on Medford before we start focusing on the rest of the country and the world right now, in my opinion. Yeah, no, that makes perfect sense, because there are a lot of issues in Medford. We discussed some. Parking, there's so many issues that we could talk about. And the zoning, I don't know how you feel about it. I'm going to get back to it, but it just seems like it's
It's just being pushed. It's not even a question of, it's just like being forced. You're gonna take this, we're gonna build or do whatever with these lots. It's confusing to people, it's complicated. The people need to be informed. They're not being informed properly. Robocalls, brochures, let's, if we're gonna do this, let's do it right. Let's not rush it.
Yeah, yeah, I mean just like the charter change it took the charter change was in process for 10 years, right? It took the charter commission two years to come up with a plan And they came up with a great plan. I thought so they came up with a great. I thought so at the last minute
There was some doors, backdoor deal or whatever. Yeah, something happened because it got changed. Or they tried to change it. They tried to change it. And thank God the mayor stepped up. Right. And at the last minute she conceded to a few things. Right. And I think that she did a great job by keeping ward representation. And hopefully it passes the legislature. Yeah, so.
Yeah, she definitely, what we would say in the old days, I say the old days, but she told the line for us. She really did. She did. When it came to that. She held her ground. She did hold her ground. She did a good job.
talking about a lot of good stuff. I like what you're saying. I do. No, I like what you're saying. It's interesting. So this is kind of like a general question, okay? What
What do you see for the future of Method? What do you envision? Let's bring in some big-name companies. Right now the mayor is looking at Budweiser for Market Basket. If Market Basket doesn't work, they have their own internal problems going on right now.
my opinion again this is my opinion with uh... encore and everything that's going on and they're trying to build a soccer stadium there's nothing for families and children to do okay in that area and i believe that uh... something like just throwing it out there a great wolf lodge something for families that you know
We can get a good tax break from a big hotel chain like that to come in. That's a perfect location. Indoor activities, something for families to do. Grandchildren, children of all ages can go in there and enjoy themselves. I really do hope that the mayor and everybody can get together and bring in a market basket. But if that fails, that's just something I'm throwing out there, in my opinion.
big business is what we need. And I'm going to say, at the beginning of the conversation, I drive around the city all the time. You made some great points because I live down, I'm on Windsor, so. Oh, okay. Yeah, and I drive by the old Canes factory, and it's been like that, oh, jeez, I don't know, Paul, how many years? Almost 10 years, I believe.
The building is horrible looking. It's, and it's, let's be honest, I mean, it's huge property. It's a big piece of property. Yeah. And then at the end, the commercial street on the, uh,
It goes all the way almost to the end of Riverside Avenue. That whole piece of property goes from Mr. Gallibert. There's a lot of potential there. A lot of commercial growth. And then even on the left-hand side, now that's all, I don't know what happened with that. That's gone, but it's empty. Of course, they pay less taxes.
Yeah, no, I mean, it's empty. Everything from there is also gone. So, but yeah, I mean, when you look around, yeah, I could think of, like you said, you made me think of it, put it that way, but there is a lot of room for, you know, some good size stores, development, even what you mentioned earlier, you know, for kids and, yeah.
I mean, there's a lot going on. We just did Medford, Malden, and Somerville, I believe, have a program for undeveloped children. Right, yes. They just started. They started that recently. That's correct. And I think that we need to start focusing on our children and their education and things for them to do. I wish I had some of those things when I was younger.
Yeah, I mean, well, we had things to do. We did. We had the movie theater. We had, uh, well, Papageno's. Papageno's. Actually, I worked at the movie theater. Yeah, so there you go. Yeah, I remember the movie theater. And then we had, we had quite a, you know, Woolworth's, uh, a lot of, a lot of things to do. And the square was always busy. There was a McDonald's in the square. I don't say to bring that type of,
Right, no, I understand. I like the mom and pop, the Alamo, the nappies. We have some great cuisine and great restaurants in the city. I don't want to see chain restaurants like that come into the city. But more mom and pop stores would be nice. Just like they did in Somerville. I'm not going to mention Assembly Road. No, I know. You can do a lot of things but keep it like a
I don't know what the words are. Maybe you could describe it better than me, but I always think like, yeah, we want to grow, we want to, but I agree with you, small business, but down on Mystic Ave, and you mentioned where Cain's and all that, let's bring in a big lodge, or that's where you put up your 10, 15 stories, whatever. Correct. Yeah, with. Housing and mixed use. Yeah, you can do a lot of different things. There's a lot of things can be done around there. Yeah, that makes sense, yeah. Yeah.
That's interesting stuff you brought up. All right, so now let me get into my favorite things to ask people, the personal questions, okay? I'm just gonna, I ask this of everybody, what is your least, your least and most favorite things to do in Method? You've been here a long time, and I don't, you know, if it's a small list, big list, but what is the least, what is the most favorite?
Oh, jeez. The least favorite thing to do in the city is right now to walk the streets. I've been walking the streets since I was a kid. Right. But walking the streets right now, the sidewalks and streets are in deplorable condition. It's dangerous. Yeah. A lot of ADA requirements that still aren't being met on a lot of streets. OK. I've noticed overgrown trees that are ruining the sidewalks.
And I'm all for the trees, Methods of Trees City, and I'm proud of it. But we have to, I think, replace some of the trees of the roots that grow up and out. Yeah, they're up and over the sidewalk. And ruining our sidewalks to the new type of trees that grow down and don't disturb the sidewalks.
That's a great answer. The least favorite is to walk. Oh my goodness. No, it's true. Now that I think, because I have a dog, I walk. I'm down by the rink, you know, I'm on Walker Street.
And I tell you, it's tough over there, too. Now that I think about it, like, you've got to really be looking down. Yeah, you've got to pay attention when you're walking. Yeah, you really do. Yeah, it's a lot of raised sidewalks and concrete and asphalt. Yeah, that's kind of a good answer. I like that answer, you know? And it's true, so. Some of my favorite things to do in Medford? So, Medford is, without a doubt,
Location, location, location. We are five to six miles from Boston.
we're so lucky that we can hop into the North End, Chinatown, Government Center, State House, all of that stuff is right down the street. Like I said, location, location, location, everything in business, that's the first thing you look at is location. And I think that we have one of the greatest locations here in Medford, and some of the restaurants, the cuisine, everything we have here in Medford, it's family orientated.
Yeah, no, I hear you. I hear you. And we want to keep it that way. Absolutely. Yeah. No, I hear you. So that's why I said big business, but not too big business. Right. Yeah. You're more or less like taking sections and doing... I'm not putting words in your mouth, but you're taking sections of the city and you're
You got a good vision, I would say, for what needs to go in this section, this section. And I like that. We're not going to just do the whole thing the same everywhere. Or at once. And right now, I think that that's the problem. They're trying to do the zoning all at once. And the residents and the citizens of Medford need to digest one thing at a time. Right. So let's, like, Mystic Ave, again,
The gateway to the city, that's our gateway to the city.
We know that the infrastructure is fairly new on Mystic Ave, and can handle some big high-rise buildings, and it's not gonna take away sunlight and air rights from some of the neighborhoods that they're currently talking about. I have a single-family home, and I don't want a monstrosity next door to me that's gonna take away my sunlight and air rights.
even though the planes fly over. I still want to see the numbers on those tails when they drive by. We all get that, I know. We all get the planes, whatever it is. It seems like a week and then they go away for a couple and then they come back.
Yeah, no, I understand that. I know a lot of people that single families and you think about what they want to do and Yeah, I guess you could probably you could really do a job on a neighborhood You know doing it like that it just doesn't yeah, I
Yeah, that's South Medford, North Medford, East Medford, Wellington Glen, we have Hillside, West Medford, and I don't think people started to realize about the zoning until the word West Medford came out. And then that woke people up. It woke everybody up.
I think that Salem Street, unfortunately, got the brunt of it right now. But if a new council is elected, maybe we can bring back some of those things that they have changed. Make changes, but do them the right way. Do it the right way, and don't rush. There's no rush. There's no rush. Again, Mystic Ave, the gateway to the city, start there.
Don't start in the neighborhoods. Don't start on the congested areas. Start on Mystic Avenue. We have plenty of room. You want housing? There's got to be developers out there that would love to build a 14, 15-story building with mixed use and 10% affordable housing. I mean, we can make some concessions to get them in there. Right. And it's not going to hurt the neighborhoods. It's not going to hurt the neighborhoods. Yeah, no, it makes sense. It makes sense. That's where that stuff would belong.
All right, so I got one last question. Someone which is kind of important probably. If someone wants to reach out to you, Paul, get in touch with you. What's the best way to do it? How would they do it? Do you have a website or what's going on? We just set up a website. It's Donato, D-O-N-A-T-O, the number four.
Okay. Uh, dot com. All right. And my email address is Paul at Donato for medfit.com. Okay. Now for all the people watching it that are like me and I start to write something down and then I never finished. Can you just repeat it one more time for them? Yes. I'm sorry. Paul, P-A-U-L at Donato, D-O-N-A-T-O, the number for medfit, M-E-D-F-O-R-D dot com.
Great. Excellent. Unfortunately, the show's going to come to an end. I enjoyed talking with you. I really did. I appreciate you and your crew for having me here. It was nice. I enjoyed the conversation. It's like I'm having a Saturday morning coffee with the guys. It was pleasant. Nice conversation. And a lot of good points were brought out, I think. So I want to thank
Mr. Paul J. Donato Jr. again for joining us on Method Happenings. And secondly, I want to thank him for being a candidate for a Method City Council. A lot goes into running for city council, and it takes a lot to step up and do it. So I want to thank you for that, Paul. I also want to take a minute to thank everyone
who has been watching the show. I want to thank you for the feedback. You know, we get positive, negative, we'll take it all. The other thing is if you would like to share a comment, if you are a candidate
for any city office, you're running for re-election, if you're opening a new business, if you'd like to open a new business, if you have an existing business, you represent an organization with an upcoming event, would like to appear on a future show,
You can contact us at very simple. My name, John Petrella, P-E-T-R-E-L-L-A 55 at gmail.com.
And you will also be able to see replays of this show. They're putting us on Method Community Media. We're on every Monday, Wednesday, Friday at 6 p.m., 6.30. Sometimes you'll see the show at 7. You might see more than one show.
But I want to thank everyone for watching. I want to thank Paul again. And you can also see Method Happenings on MedfordTV.org, YouTube, and Facebook. So from all of us at Method Happening, I'm John Petrella, and stay informed. Thank you.
Ta-da!