So if everybody could, Alva, do a roll call. Chief Buckley. I will be acting as Chief Buckley's designee as Sergeant Canava. Commissioner McGibbon. Here. Commissioner Hunt. Here. Commissioner Borzynski. Commissioner Velasca. We know she's absent.
Great, okay, roll call was? Three present, two absent. Three present, two absent, and then somebody would like to approve last meeting's minutes. Motion to approve the minutes. Motion by Commissioner Hunt, seconded. Seconded. Yeah, Tim and Alicia, you guys are gonna be the duo here. Seconded by Commissioner McGibbon. Roll call, Iowa. Commissioner McGibbon? Yes.
Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Sergeant Canava? Yes. Okay, three yes votes. We have moved to approve last month's minutes. Great. If somebody would make a motion, I think- Joe, can we hold off this? Todd, you gotta go. Are you in a hurry? You're still muted, Todd. He needs a button.
I believe I made him a co-host. He texted, he says no, he's fine. So can I make a motion to take the residents item 2024-12 Greg Corsello out of order and take him first? Great motion by Commissioner. Second. Seconded by Commissioner Given. We're good with that? Yeah. Good. Greg, we have two of you, so I'm just going to click on this one and ask you to unmute and hopefully it works.
Can you hear me and see me. Yeah, great. Good evening. Hi. You can just explain obviously 164 Harvard street permit parking variance for Wareham street. You and I had actually spoke here at the police station.
You had received a variance already last year, I believe it was? Yes, that's correct. And you're here, him and I had spoke because he was denied a variance to renew that this year at the parking department. So if you wanna just explain a little further how you received the variance, sorry, how you had your parking permit, explain for the commissioners.
Sure. I had a variance. I'm at the end of Harvard Street on the corner of Harvard and Maine, and so there's no street parking right in front of my building. There's street parking further down the block, but it's significantly further of a walk to get from my apartment to where I could park on Harvard. A couple of years ago, I've been parking on Wareham Street, which is right around the corner.
Turned into resident only parking. So last year, me and my roommate at that time, Becca, Becca actually reached out to chief Buckley and got a variance from him directly. We went and got resident sticker or we got passes from the.
Town Hall is where I picked them up. Then I had been under the impression that that would just be a renewal process this year, and then it seems like a change to a full reapplication. That's why it's so late in the year to get that renewal. Then my roommates this year, Becca moved out, my roommate Matt moved in, he went to the traffic commission in Philadelphia.
He's November, December, and was able to get a pass for our apartment, for our living situation on Wareham Street. And he got that all approved. So hopefully this is just a simple reapplication. Great. Sorry, we're just pulling it up so that everybody can see it. And I do remember that the chief gave a number of
permits last year, and I don't remember all the details, but that would imply why it didn't get codified and carried over. Yeah, Alicia, thanks for pointing that out. This was part of when engineering looked at the width of the street and determined that there was an additional area of our street that couldn't accommodate parking without being on the sidewalk, so chief went door to door to help accommodate these folks in that interim period. It's my recollection.
Right. Okay. I think I have it here. So yeah, I'm the I'm the tan the lighter tan two story building to the right. Yeah, right there. Okay. You don't have off street parking with your apartment. I have one spot straight in this narrow driveway, but my roommate and I have two cars.
So it's the idea that you both get a parking permit for the street, whoever gets home first or whatever parks there and the other one parks on the street kind of thing? Yes, that's correct. We've been switching off, but since I haven't had the parking pass, I've been in the driveway and he's been on Wareham. Okay. It's just we try to make sure that people who have off-street parking are using off-street parking and are not taking a parking spot when they could have been in their driveway.
of course, and I definitely prefer to park in my driveway whenever I can, but it's whoever has it or gets on first, like you're saying. I mean, Wareham Street, just from the view of this, is a far walk from this residence. There's not really a cut through either which way, so I mean. Yeah. So I would move approval of this. Okay. Is that a motion by Commissioner Hunt, seconded?
Just a quick question, any issues with capacity on Wareham Street? We got plenty of parking there? No, we have actually in the past approved a couple people on Wareham Street. It's probably one of our lighter streets for permanent parking. The only thing is, I believe, Greg, you already have approved this, correct? Has this already been approved in the past or do we need to
We need to reapprove that because the chief just went door-to-door. Is that what you're saying, Todd? Sorry. So Chief Buckley approved me and Becca, the last roommate, for last year. And then my roommate Matt has approval this year, but my approval has lapsed for this year. OK, sorry. So in order to do capacity, because there's already a car there. It's just rotating out. So second the motion. Great. Roll call, Alba. Commissioner McGibbon? Yeah.
Commissioner hunt yes yes and this passes just give us I would say a few weeks here and then go down back to the traffic the traffic department at City Hall and they will award you the gym silver is an attendance he he sometimes will put it on the list too okay yeah and just hopefully we'll expedite this as fast as we can and it should be
move forward. We're getting better with our processing here at the police department, so we'll make sure it gets over there. Perfect. And is there someone I could reach out to here to ask, like, when it's sent over, or should I go straight to the track? You can call me. Yeah, you can call Alva. Jim's raising his hand. Okay, Jim's over.
Great. Jim Silva. I made you a co-host, so you can unmute yourself too. I did. I'm all set. Yes, you can reach out to me. I work for Mayor Lungo Kern's office. My number is 617-645-2767. I'll put it in the chat, and you can reach out to me directly as Alvaro alluded to. I will add it to the list. I see Matthew's there at 164 already. Excellent. Thank you. Adding it to the list, that means he could actually try tomorrow?
Yes. He doesn't have to wait weeks, right? Hopefully tomorrow it should be fine. Okay. Great. Great. Thanks, Greg. Thank you, everyone. Sandra Dorenzo. All right. I'm loving this new quick system. Yeah. We did just get the Excel spreadsheet so that we can add in things here as they come to, so we'll do that right after the meeting and hopefully they'll be updated.
you know, by the hour. I don't see the other member of the public. So if we revert to the regular order of business, we'll go to Todd's item. Yeah, I'm not seeing Sandra D Renzo here is as well. So if we want to go 2024 dash 10. Todd, take it away. You can unmute yourself too. I made your co host.
All right, so I'll be quick. Basically, Alfred Street, we got some complaints through the mayor's office from a resident. This is one of those kind of former situations where Alfred Street itself is already resident permit, so the green areas are resident permit, the green arrows. It's the yellow arrow areas that are long businesses that in the old system of doing resident permit,
it was kind of left unrestricted along businesses, right, to be. And then that new wave recently in the past couple months, we have that Bonner Alexander example where we're changing these yellow areas to be two hour except by permit. The two hour is like business friendly, but the except by permit allows the turnover in those areas to exist so that residents could use those and non-resident people aren't parking there for
you know, 10 hours at a time and things like that, so abusing it because it's unrestricted. So the proposal is to sign it as two-hour 8 a.m. to 8 p.m. except by permit, and then permit parking only 8 p.m. to 8 a.m. excluding Sundays and holidays, which is the same exact sign we've used several times now in areas like this, along the business properties on a residential parking street.
And then the language is just to indicate where exactly the signs would be matching with that, the yellow arrows. The yellow arrow at the end on the bottom right ends after one space because the last space is actually in Somerville. So the bottom screen, that's Broadway, Somerville. And the top's Albion Street, Bedford.
So the complaint by the residents is not enough resident parking because the areas in yellow are completely occupied by vehicles that are, you know, business that might be left on the street for hours or days on end. I don't suppose we have any idea why businesses are leaving, people are leaving vehicles on the street.
It's another auto repair type place, so it's similar to the Mystic on Alexander Issues. It's right there, you can see it right there. We've been up here and we've had a lot of arguments with him. He believes that he went to City Hall and
that his property goes on to these lots and the street and he owns the parking spaces, even though we've explained to him that this is a public street in Medford. So he decided that he would use the 24 hour, 48 hour variance and move his vehicles every 47 and a half hours. And they are registered to him.
So these aren't even the vehicles he's repairing. These are actually registered to him vehicles? Majority of them have been. Usually it's a vehicle that he has in the wintertime. He usually does a lot of plowing in this area for his business. So sometimes he'll have some of his winter vehicles there. So at the very least, if they are registered in his name, he'd need to get a business permit or a resident permit for residential use.
and get a permit right now, he doesn't have to get either. He apparently owns Insight Construction, Tim, and he's packing a lot of the trucks there. I don't know what his connection with Insight is. He may be a passion loaner or what. Street legal vehicles? What's that? Are they street legal? Yes. Well, they're not commercial.
The inside trucks that he has, usually he knows that he knows he can't park a commercial vehicle on there. So he'll park those inside of his lot and then the vehicles in which he can, you know.
I don't even think that would even.
I don't think we can make an agreement like that. No, neither did I, so I just kept ticketing him and that was that. It's a good way to get the parking that you've been taking advantage of regulated. The resident who brought this to attention is Laura Coleman. Yeah, I've actually spoke with her and advised her to come through this traffic commission. The only way we can kind of move forward with anything is, you know,
Yeah, proper signage and other than us going there every single, I mean, we've ticketed this particular location a heavy amount. And I think he figured out the loophole a little bit of the $48 violation. So I think this will help. Well, I'm in favor of things like this. And if it's consistent with what we've done recently, and we should continue to try to pick away at these. Sounds good.
Move approval. Great. That was a motion second to roll call. Commissioner McGiven? Aye. Commissioner Hunt? Aye. Sergeant Canaba? Pass as well. Three nothing and that moves for approval.
And that is the item of agenda. So the resident, the one that's on the agenda that there's nobody here for, is there any reason why we should take it or do we need to hear from the resident about their application?
She's actually asking for visitor passes. She already has a variance for her vehicle for Marshall Street. She has in the past received two visitor passes for Marshall Street. This year she only got for her personal vehicle.
Do visitor passes need to come back to us every year? Why, if she's gotten them in the past, or is this one where there's no record of her having gotten them before, so we need to clean it up? I didn't have any record on my part, but they might have at the parking department, which I'm not too sure, but she did not get the visitor passes. She went early, and it might have been where they were deciding on the process for the visitor passes.
So she just wanted to make it legal where she had it before, and that if that went on record, she wouldn't have this problem again. So it looks like 120 is a corner house and it's in that section of Wintersheet that doesn't have parking on street at all. So their only choice is side street. So seems like a no brainer. Do you need me to bring it up?
And she isn't on the variance list for Marshall Street. I didn't see her on my list, Jim, and I'm looking at the variance list location. Usually it's by the street that the variance issues on and nothing on Marshall Street with her name.
He doesn't have her on the list? No, and I don't have, I have his list so I don't have it. Well it seems like at this point we would need her here to kind of explain the situation or no? I don't think she wishes to receive them in the past. She has received them in the past? For years.
I just, I think it could be the same situation where we're updating the variance list. Again, she's not on the list that the parking folks have. So, as you know, some of the other folks in January had to revisit the variance and this obviously was one of those, I'm assuming. Then we should take a vote on it, yeah. Yeah, so that way it would be easier for her.
it'll go on the records finally once we vote on it then it'll actually be on the record as opposed to nowhere uh so you'd be voting for the various in the visitor oh it would have to be both yeah both so felicia and tim if you're comfortable with that if you're not then we can
I know we've spoken with her before and she's yeah I guess I kind of don't understand really why we would give parking permits and not visitor passes, I mean I feel like do we think some people don't ever have visitors like.
I would agree, and she has had them in the past, and we've never had an issue with her abusing them or anything like that. She's not a landlord in that case. It's really strictly for visitation, so I totally agree with that. I move approval. Yeah. Second by- Second. Yeah. Roll call, Alba. Commissioner McGibbon. Yes, indeed. Commissioner Hunt. Yes.
Yes, we will make the notification to her I think Alva has her information so we'll let her know that it's passed and yeah.
I was just thinking that that's one of the things that we should just be looking at in the big picture, how this works. We always have the right that if somebody were to be abusing a visitor's permit, that we could revoke it, right? It may not even have to come to this board. No, it doesn't. It says on the back. Okay.
to pass itself that you're out of the program if you abuse it. Okay. I think that's helpful to know and that theoretically if somebody lost their permit because of abuse, we would indicate that perhaps in this same list of variances so that we would know that there was a history and you can't just come back a year later and they're all new members of the Traffic Commission and they don't know about your history. No, that would definitely.
That also makes me feel more comfortable about just approving something like that. Yeah, I mean, I don't know of anything that we've ever had someone abuse their Mr. or Mrs. of parking, but there's always the potential for it. I don't recall anything. We can discuss those off camera. Well, motion to adjourn.
I think we have a motion to adjourn. I think we have a motion to adjourn. I think we have a motion to adjourn. I think we have a motion to adjourn. I think we have a motion to adjourn. I think we have a motion to adjourn. I think we have a motion to adjourn. I think we have a motion to adjourn. I think we have a motion to adjourn. I think we have a motion to adjourn. I think we have a motion to adjourn. I think we have a motion to adjourn. I think we have a motion to adjourn.
Seconded by Commissioner McGiven.
9.28 p.m. have a nice night and drive safe and stay after cell phones. I thought he said 9.28. I'm sorry did I say 9.28? I'm so used to doing this at 5.28. We also have a record number of agendas. Drive safe, no cell phone usage. Bye everybody.