[SPEAKER_00]: Hola, soy Briana Elacalde de la Ciudad de Medford, and I'm here with the good news of the week, which is to highlight a great event that's coming up this Sunday at the Andrews Middle School from 3pm to 6pm.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's our Hispanic Heritage Month celebration.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hispanic Heritage Month is September 15th to October 15th.
[SPEAKER_00]: So please come down on Sunday to celebrate with us.
[SPEAKER_00]: And today, I'm with Jennifer, our liaison, and Lizette, our community connector.
[SPEAKER_00]: Both work for Medford, helping with all of our needs.
[SPEAKER_00]: So Jennifer, I'll turn it over to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hi, my name is Jennifer.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm the Spanish community liaison for the city of Method.
[SPEAKER_01]: We help with mass health applications.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have food pantry.
[SPEAKER_01]: We help with housing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything you need, you can call the city.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have a multicultural language line.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you can call us, and either me or Lisette or one of the other liaisons or connectors will give you a call back.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yeah, so don't forget to come to our event on Sunday.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hello, my name is Lisette.
[SPEAKER_02]: I am Medfern's connector.
[SPEAKER_02]: I help connect everyone to the things that the mayor's office offers.
[SPEAKER_02]: Jennifer is here to help with anything related to MassHealth applications, anything related to food, or anything related to home problems, anything that you need.
[SPEAKER_02]: We are here to help you, and don't forget that
[SPEAKER_00]: Wonderful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So bottom line, if you need help or you know somebody that needs help, we have connectors here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not only Spanish connectors, but these are two of our over 10 connectors and liaisons that are making sure everybody feels welcome and supported.
[SPEAKER_00]: And don't forget to join us this Sunday.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thanks.