[SPEAKER_02]: All right, welcome to the Medford Charter Study Final Report Subcommittee Meeting, July 29th, 2024.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did everyone have a chance to review the minutes?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll make a motion to accept those.
[SPEAKER_02]: Second.
[SPEAKER_02]: All in favor?
[SPEAKER_00]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, basically, we're just, I mean, thank you, Gene,
[SPEAKER_02]: those recommendation sections and also for your comments.
[SPEAKER_02]: I went through some of the drafts that I had written and made changes, so that was really helpful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think we're in good shape on that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you have any questions or comments about what you did, Gene or Maury?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I did have a question, but Maury, did you have any thoughts or questions?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nice job.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thanks.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'd like to provide demographics from the survey.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the community engagement section, because I feel like that would help respond to people's, the criticisms I've heard that it's not reflective of, and if it's not reflective, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that we're in a better position if we say it up front, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: So was David doing an analysis?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I need to figure out how to get in touch with David.
[SPEAKER_02]: I, you know, he said he was going to be around all summer, but he hasn't been responsive.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we'll have to try to get in touch with him.
[SPEAKER_02]: But we have like the, I mean,
[SPEAKER_02]: I can find them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you have the data.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just a question.
[SPEAKER_02]: He was going to make a survey report.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what we asked him to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I could do the analysis myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would take time.
Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if he's already doing it, I thought, well, then I don't need to.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, that's good.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we should connect with Javid and see exactly what he's going to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: If David is unable to do the survey, he already created something for us that did not include the demographics that he shared at a meeting.
[SPEAKER_01]: At a full meeting?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, at the full meeting.
[SPEAKER_02]: That was a while back.
[SPEAKER_01]: I may have missed that.
[SPEAKER_02]: We'll look into that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because we have
[SPEAKER_02]: the demographic pie charts, right, that the survey created?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, we do?
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I downloaded because I remember seeing the I thought the V was gonna put that all together.
[SPEAKER_02]: He's Yeah, we have to check with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But there but Google, you know, Google surveys,
[SPEAKER_02]: did create pie charts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it in the survey folder?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a good question.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, it might just be in the survey results.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it didn't get pulled.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, jeez.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is that really?
[SPEAKER_02]: This must be new.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_02]: I tried to minimize so I could look in the.
[SPEAKER_02]: They said I can't minimize Zoom while I'm recording.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's never happened to me before.
[SPEAKER_02]: It'd be a new thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK, so I'll look and see, because the other person, Danielle, created the survey.
[SPEAKER_02]: So there's a certain way you can look at the survey results.
[SPEAKER_02]: And whenever I would look at the results, I would see the pie charts.
[SPEAKER_02]: I assume it didn't go away.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was able to download an Excel spreadsheet with all the results.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I'm not the owner of the survey, so I don't know that I can see that.
[SPEAKER_02]: The person who could see it is Danielle.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I should be able to see it because I think she gave me access to it, so I'm just trying to look for it right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you have that, that's fine because then I can just say,
[SPEAKER_01]: you know, 10% were, you know, 40% were renters or you know, whatever, because I think yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Compare that to like Medford demographics if we have that and just to yeah, so we'll talk about how representative it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So yeah, I see what's in the folder is just the Excel spreadsheet.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so I know they exist because I saw them.
[SPEAKER_02]: So let me ask Danielle about that.
[SPEAKER_02]: There might be a special way that I can maybe dig up the link she gave me a long time ago to look at the survey results, but I'll ask her.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the other important thing,
[SPEAKER_02]: to remember about that demographics info is that it include the percentage of people, I think it's in the pie chart, who said they didn't want to answer.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because some people, because remember, we had prefer not to answer as an option.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I think that's in the pie chart.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so Jen, did you have any other questions about or thoughts about what you put together?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, with the Article 8, you know, citizen participation, I just did it broadly and I didn't, you know, go through each one or what it does.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's how we talked about presenting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, definitely.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, and that one in particular was sort of challenging because it had all those different parts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I just, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: said they include X, Y, Z, and then talked about the requirement that at the ballot, you need to show that you have at least 20 or 25% of the registered voters participating for it to be valid.
[SPEAKER_02]: So- I think, yeah, I think that's okay for that one.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it is pretty,
[SPEAKER_02]: thick when you get into the- I mean, you could break it down and say, do different recommendations for each one, but I think it makes sense to group them together.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think it's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, if we broke them up, it would be like the referendum, the free petition,
[SPEAKER_02]: citizen initiative measures, citizen referendum measures, and then recall.
[SPEAKER_02]: There would be like four, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you might want to lump citizen initiative and referendum together.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I think they have the same numbers, but then the referendum has different numbers.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe it's worth doing that since recall is
[SPEAKER_02]: going to be seen maybe as different than those things, but I don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you think, Maury?
[SPEAKER_00]: I think recall should be by itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: We can keep the other three grouped the way it is, it's fine, but I think I'd pull recall out of there and just make it a separate line item and
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want to be linking it with everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of like a horse of a different color, you know what I'm saying, by itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I think that's a good point.
[SPEAKER_01]: OK.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you mind doing that?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I can rewrite that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we'll just have two.
[SPEAKER_01]: We'll have like citizen initiative and then recall.
[SPEAKER_01]: OK.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Great.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I think we're in pretty good shape.
[SPEAKER_02]: What else?
[SPEAKER_02]: I've done a little bit, but I need to do more on putting all that public comment that we've collected with the survey and through emails into the issue sheets, that Google sheet, because we figured that that would be the easiest way to include it in the final report.
[SPEAKER_02]: Say that again, Milva?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_02]: We have a bunch of public comment.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like the survey also gave people the opportunity to write, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, um, and you know, I mean, they're all kind of hard to access because they're in that Excel spreadsheet.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was going to put them into the Google issue sheet under this under, you know, which,
[SPEAKER_02]: would represent a good amount of work, but it seemed like sort of the best way to give, to put that public comment into the final report was to have it consolidated into that issue sheets.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, and have a link instead of attaching the issue sheet.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So here's a link to all the comment, like email.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: But maybe, do you think maybe if the public comments from the survey can be exported,
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe we can just, I've never exported from, I don't know what the, it seems like there probably is a way to export them, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel like that's waiting comments received from the survey over all the other comments.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's true.
[SPEAKER_01]: Though I don't like highlighting those and not highlighting
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, public comment we got via email or other means like if I yeah, no, I was just thinking maybe you do you set up a link with with all different categories, whatever it is, and they can access if they want to see public comments, or if they want to see public emails, or they want.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all there on one link and what's.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, and that was the idea of the issue sheets.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was just thinking of a way to lighten the workload, because transferring all those.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I can do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you want help?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I can help you.
[SPEAKER_01]: We'll see.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll start it and see how it goes.
[SPEAKER_01]: OK, thanks.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm on vacation for like 10 days, mid-August.
[SPEAKER_01]: OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, you know, there were a few comments that were sort of frivolous, and I don't know how we feel about, like, if we just make a judgment call, then I'll put those in the issue sheets.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's, like, another category, but if they're not at all relevant, I don't think they should be included.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to know what you're doing about fixing Mystic Avenue or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not relevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: That sounds good.
[SPEAKER_02]: So basically, the main things we have to do now are put together the append, just sort of do this little bit of revision on sections, put together the appendix, which I started a folder and put the materials in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: We'll have to figure out how to structure it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I keep forgetting that I can't minimize anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you all see the appendix holder?
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's see, what's in there now?
[SPEAKER_02]: And there's probably more that needs to go in there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, we could just, I don't know, have you ever made an appendix, Gene?
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you know what style?
[SPEAKER_02]: We don't really have to follow any particular style.
[SPEAKER_01]: I use Word and use their headings and a table of contents.
[SPEAKER_02]: We're going to have a table of contents for the whole report, but also a table of contents for the appendix because the appendix is going to be a lot of stuff in there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can put that in your main table of contents and then add links, click on it, and it'll take you to the sections if you use.
[SPEAKER_02]: So if you end up format, like doing formatting the whole thing and putting the table of contents in, will you do the appendix too?
[SPEAKER_02]: That means you would decide how to organize the appendix, which is fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: There aren't a lot of references to the appendix, but I did make a couple in the introductory letter, right, where I said I referenced a Collins Center memo and the generic modern charter, and then I just put appendix number or whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know how.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's sort of like a footnote, but not exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: We can do the appendix in the order they're referenced in the document.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know, or by section.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So right now we'll just keep collecting.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then the footnotes is the other thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: The footnotes are going to be before, maybe at the very end after the appendix.
[SPEAKER_01]: I had put them in the, let's see, I put mine in the, I think I had one footnote.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, you put them within the recommendations.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, that's probably makes more, that, that makes more sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then I will footnote my recommendations too.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then we don't have to have footnotes at the end.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's good.
[SPEAKER_02]: I like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there anything else that we were, that I mean, that we're supposed to, the call-in center offered to read the final report too.
[SPEAKER_02]: So should we, should I just throw it together now in draft form and send it to them?
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe in case.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I mean, you can just send them the link to the folder or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can go through and clean up, because I see people made edits, so that it's cleaner.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you want to go through any of the edits?
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't think there were any.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think you gave, like I had questions for you, like what languages?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I told you that, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I don't see any ones that we need to discuss.
[SPEAKER_01]: OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's good that you put that in there.
[SPEAKER_02]: I asked Frances, but I haven't heard back yet about the translations.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I know I have a bunch of the handouts.
[SPEAKER_02]: There must be electronic versions of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Frances would have those because I only ever, we only ever got the hard copies.
[SPEAKER_02]: I have the hard copies.
[SPEAKER_02]: I suppose I could scan one.
[SPEAKER_01]: To put in the appendix or?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do we want to put them in the appendix?
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you think?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, because we, we talk, did we talk about, do we need to put our flyer in the appendix?
[SPEAKER_02]: You know?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't, I don't, I'm, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel like you don't want to just put a ton of stuff in there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: I know, so maybe we just say that we did translation so we don't include all that stuff.
[SPEAKER_02]: The flyers and the glossary, we had a glossary that was translated also.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, okay, so.
[SPEAKER_01]: A glossary with key terms?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like I said, I have them in the ad that I used to bring to all our events.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're downstairs.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: But yeah, we have flyers in different languages and then we have the glossary, which was just basic because remember we talked about how people wouldn't necessarily know even what a charter is or what word representation is and things like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it was just, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see in the Article 6, you had a question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you did have a couple comments maybe we should talk about the you don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh yeah, that's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the annual meeting.
[SPEAKER_01]: I thought it was an ordinance or that they were creating an ordinance.
[SPEAKER_02]: They did create an ordinance and the ordinance has been passed, but I don't know that that annual meeting is part of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But isn't okay, so I could I mean there's a bunch of there's Yeah, there's a whole timeline in the budget ordinance for Different things but a meeting an annual meeting with all the branches of government.
[SPEAKER_01]: I I'm not sure that's it Okay And then you want wanted to know whether we should list the reasons we declined to adopt the
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Budget lines.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you think?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I think we could say that as it's prohibited by state law.
[SPEAKER_01]: If we do that, should we cite it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: I used to know all these numbers off the top of my head, but I'll find it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, might do it as a footnote.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that works.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, I would footnote it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the right way to go.
Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll find it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll find it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think I can find it pretty easily.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so that's good.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything else is pretty, like I, did I have any questions?
[SPEAKER_02]: Introductory now, article two, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do we end up, Bilba, on the?
[SPEAKER_00]: Ethics.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do we end up on that?
[SPEAKER_02]: We're voting.
[SPEAKER_02]: We're going to talk about it and vote on it on Thursday.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thursday.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: All right.
[SPEAKER_00]: I thought that's what we did, but I wasn't sure because it's been so much.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, I was just reading over this the wardrobe is the article to when I was trying to I was thinking it would be good to put stats in about because I said It's the smallest in the state for a city of our size and if I could find exactly, you know, how many I think there's only two others And and you know the numbers on at-large versus Ward and then
[SPEAKER_02]: hybrid, I don't know, I was thinking maybe of trying to find the stats on those, but I'm not sure how easy it will be to find them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Cause you know, municipalities are sort of independent and I don't, the only organization I feel like that would keep those stats is the Massachusetts Municipal Association.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so I could look there, I'll look there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't we have a table with all 351 cities?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: We had a table with just about 50-60 cities.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, it's weird because there's some places, because the city town thing, like Framingham just became a city, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: So there's some towns that are probably really cities, but they haven't decided to call themselves cities yet.
[SPEAKER_02]: But mostly we were trying to compare municipalities that were more like us as opposed to, because towns will have
[SPEAKER_02]: town meeting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you prepare that or did Collins Center prepare it?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I actually found that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was prepared by problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know exactly who prepared it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I got it off the Somerville Charter Study website, their materials, and then I double-checked each one.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's really hard actually because sometimes the websites aren't up to date and when you look online for a charter to check and make sure that the composition is what that chart said, sometimes the charters online aren't the most, so I did it to the best of my ability.
[SPEAKER_02]: But Somerville's committee had two part-time employees, so I'm guessing they put it together.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that's probably who put it together.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know if anyone wants to get in the weeds on it, but it'd be nice to provide to someone if they wanted to.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know.
[SPEAKER_01]: At other cities and towns just to see where Medford stands and look at the data themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is useful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like I said, it's hard sometimes to keep it updated.
[SPEAKER_02]: When I was looking up,
[SPEAKER_02]: Because I wanted to double check everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there were some cities that said, or one or two, I think it was Brockton, that said four-year term for mayor.
[SPEAKER_02]: When I looked in their charter, it said two-year.
[SPEAKER_02]: And their charter hadn't been updated on the website or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it was very recent that they switched to four year.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then I'm actually unclear on whether some places could switch to four year with that.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, there's so many processes that are involved.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think our laws have not been updated in the last couple of years because we don't have a city solicitor.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So like the things that have been passed have not been put on our website because they want to review them before.
[SPEAKER_01]: So maybe that's in other cities that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So.
[SPEAKER_02]: So so I think it's pretty accurate, but, you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: We maybe could include it with the caveat that that it was created in 20, you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know, when did I do it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Probably, yeah, we could put a date on it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: We could include it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, I think it's mostly accurate.
[SPEAKER_02]: There might be a couple of things that are changed.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it still gives the sense of, it shows you kind of visually, oh, wow, look.
[SPEAKER_02]: We're only one of a few that don't have ward representation.
[SPEAKER_02]: It shows you the size of the councils.
[SPEAKER_02]: It shows you the size of the school committees.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think it was really helpful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And even the ward representation, there's only a few cities that don't have it, and Cambridge is one of them, which this isn't in the chart, of course.
[SPEAKER_02]: But Cambridge has ranked choice voting, which, you know,
[SPEAKER_02]: So even though they have at large, they also have a process that kind of mitigates the potential issues.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because interestingly, in the Lowell lawsuit, in the settlement, one of the options for Lowell was to go to rank choice voting.
[SPEAKER_02]: They said either ward representation or rank choice voting.
[SPEAKER_02]: And they did the word representation.
[SPEAKER_02]: I thought that was interesting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so maybe we'll put that in the appendix.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll put it in there.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll put it in the appendix folder.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or like a link to it, because people might want to... Yeah, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's not that big.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like a huge document.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's an Excel file.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're putting together the appendix, then can you just choose to put some of the things in as links and some of them as whatever?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right?
[SPEAKER_01]: We'll have to, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Change access to the ones we want to share.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or maybe.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if I need, does the owner have to do that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So if I need to do that, you can just let me know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I'll put it in the folder for now.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you know,
[SPEAKER_02]: If the time comes when we're making the appendix and we decide, you know what, we don't really need this in the appendix, we can just not include it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But right now, we'll just lean on putting things in the folder that we think we might include.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because we have a lot of materials.
[SPEAKER_02]: We do.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think we're pretty good.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there anything else we need to do?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, so.
[SPEAKER_02]: We have to decide when we're going to give it to the committee.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it now my turn to put in, am I putting it in a full document or is Daveed doing that or?
[SPEAKER_01]: Putting what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Merging it all into one report.
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I doing that now?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a good question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or are we letting people, like do you want the call-in center, let people edit it first?
[SPEAKER_02]: I would like, I'm going to give the Collins Center a draft version, and I was going to just throw it in a document for them, but that won't be the final document, whatever you, because you're going to figure out how to put it in, so you can format it right and stuff.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you want to do that, because we, because the other thing we have to do is share it with the committee, with the wider committee.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we can either, we can do that now, we can share the folder with them, and they can just look at it in pieces, or we can put it all together.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you think?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I have time now, so I could try to put it in a file.
[SPEAKER_01]: OK.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would be great.
[SPEAKER_01]: See how far I can get.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only thing I would like, let's see.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm just thinking about just the stuff that has to be little changes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, like the stuff that's in highlighted, would you just keep the highlights or?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then we.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then we don't work in this anymore and we work in that document.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so the one thing about Google Docs and Word, they don't play nice always.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just FYI.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a consultant, most of my stuff I'm doing with Teams because that's a Microsoft product.
[SPEAKER_01]: It acts a little better.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a warning.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think we can still do it this way.
[SPEAKER_02]: You mean some of the comments might not transfer?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes the formatting, it gets all,
[SPEAKER_01]: Messed up, we can see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or the footnotes, you can't see the footnotes.
[SPEAKER_01]: They disappear, but they're there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just doesn't always, perhaps purposefully, they don't always... I could make it a PDF and then put it up, but then it's hard to edit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anyways.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I'm just wondering, I mean, in one sense, it makes sense for you to do it now in case you have to sort of make changes and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_02]: But on the other hand, if we need to keep working on it, should we wait until we're done with the edits?
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you think?
[SPEAKER_03]: Hm.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: We would like to give the full committee one document to look at and not sections.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that?
[SPEAKER_02]: I think it's okay to give the committee, you know, to tell them to just go into the folder and look at the different sections.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that's okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you think, Maury?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I think so too.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, soon to be like a lot of maybe extra work.
[SPEAKER_00]: We don't have to do work that's already been done to try to put it together on one whole draft form just for the committee.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, because if it's going to maybe create potential issues for our final editing and stuff to move it now, then maybe we should wait.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what do you think?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I think it might be easier if we share the pieces.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there might be more might be more work to try to create 1 document, put it online, then there's issues.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then we have to that's what I'm thinking.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we'll keep it the way it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, um.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe we'll wait until after this next meeting.
[SPEAKER_02]: I guess what.
[SPEAKER_02]: When should I just tell the committee, you know, feel free to look over the final report.
[SPEAKER_02]: We're not, it's not on the agenda for Thursday.
[SPEAKER_02]: We can tell them, maybe what we'll do is make it on the agenda.
[SPEAKER_02]: What we have, what's on the agenda is, yeah, what's on the agenda is for us to give a report to the committee so we can just tell the committee.
[SPEAKER_02]: you know, we have a pretty, we have a draft.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, we do, we have, you know, a completed draft of the final report and, um, that I will be sending them a link so that they can look at it and then give them a timeline to make any changes or comments or edits.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, uh, cause we're in the process of closing this.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then we'll, um, and then we'll, we'll sort of vote it through at the September meeting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I'd wait till after our meeting because people are doing the draft charter now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I'm just saying I will tell them at the meeting that this is going to be the process.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then they'll have that time.
[SPEAKER_02]: And we're going to have to see how it goes on Thursday.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think we can do this.
[SPEAKER_02]: We can finish it at our October meeting without having to have an extra meeting.
[SPEAKER_02]: But we'll see.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, the whole committee.
[SPEAKER_02]: So as far as we are concerned, we pretty much have our tasks, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't think we... I mean, we're done with the draft.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's just putting together, you know, the appendix materials and I have to add a few footnotes and... You're going to get the survey percent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I'll talk to Danielle, try to get in touch with David.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I think we're good.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you think?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I'm going to send it to the Collins Center if they have.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't anticipate that they're going to say much about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll just share their comments when they say if they have anything that makes us think we need to make big changes.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I don't think that will happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: We didn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Did we take any pictures or?
[SPEAKER_02]: I know, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, we must have had pictures at Wright's Pond.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a picture.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think there's one picture I can think of from Wright's Pond because it was taken by Matt when he was running it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that one.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I feel like maybe Ron took pictures.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm really bad at taking pictures.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe Danielle.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ron or Danielle might have taken pictures at Wright's Pond.
[SPEAKER_02]: We didn't take any that day at the farmer's market, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I don't know any of the hearings.
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess we could do screen grabs from the.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be kind of nice to include pictures.
[SPEAKER_02]: We needed a committee photographer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or just like a picture of all of the committee members.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would be good.
[SPEAKER_02]: But since we've never actually been in a room together, right, all of us.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, we did actually.
[SPEAKER_02]: We were at City Hall.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe we can.
[SPEAKER_01]: meet when we are near the end or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if it's not a meeting and we don't talk at all about charter, we just going, getting together for a photo, I think it's okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's not, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: We're not going to, we're not going to have any discussions or any picture.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Um, you know, there's all, it's,
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: We could get together for a social event, but I don't even know how coached that would be.
[SPEAKER_02]: I guess I'd have to ask someone.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or we could just post it publicly and say, public for a photo.
[SPEAKER_02]: As long as we post it, we're fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know how easy it would be to get everybody together.
[SPEAKER_02]: Last meeting in October could be in person.
[SPEAKER_02]: That sounds like a good idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: That might be what to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But we might not have everybody.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Photoshop, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: Photoshop people.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: All right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a big deal.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I like the idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: I like the idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: All right.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's something to think about.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the meantime, we could put out a message to the committee and say, does anybody have any photos?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe we can send out the full report.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could say we'd love to include photos if you have any.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gee, that one didn't, when we went down to
[SPEAKER_00]: Not walking court, where was it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Did I take pictures?
[SPEAKER_00]: I thought one of the people in charge of that place took a picture or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, maybe they did.
[SPEAKER_01]: From the housing authority?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: From one of the listening sessions?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: They say it would be anonymous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was going to say, would we- I don't know that I could use those.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, I think what would be great is if we had, if we had a photo of the whole committee, that would be good.
[SPEAKER_02]: So maybe we can, you know, I mean, it would have been great if we had thought about doing a group photo at that first information section when we were all there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, Wright's Pond or the- That was not- No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wasn't there tables or any way they can take a clip off of that with everybody at the table or something?
[SPEAKER_02]: We could do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Of course, that would have been John and I feel like there was somebody else who had to leave.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, Laurel, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It would not have Phyllis and David.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's true.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Photoshop.
[SPEAKER_02]: Somebody with Photoshop skills.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe my son.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, me neither.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's something to think about.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe we can at some point, you know, take a committee photo.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll bring it up at the meeting and see if, or I'll see what people think about having an in-person meeting in October.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know.
Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or I'll just ask on email.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know if I want to take up meeting time with that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or maybe it'll be such an efficient meeting that we'll have plenty of time.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know, though.
[SPEAKER_02]: We have a lot to go through Thursday.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't hold your breath on that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Come on.
[SPEAKER_02]: All right.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think we're good, then.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, we've done our part.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you for all this.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's great.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is going to be really exciting when we have the whole thing put together and we see it in
[SPEAKER_02]: all our work in this form.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think it's awesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: You guys have done a great job.
[SPEAKER_00]: You spent a lot of time and effort on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: All right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good job, Nova.
[SPEAKER_01]: You too.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_02]: All right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thanks, guys.
[SPEAKER_01]: See you Thursday.