Hey guys, did you hear about the girls that did the Jimmy Fun walk for cancer?
No, I didn't actually.
That's really cool.
Mr. Heining is training for a marathon.
Did you guys hear about that?
Oh wow, I didn't hear about that either.
But I did talk to Mr. Scary.
He's the new coach for the basketball team.
Looks like a good season.
Did you hear about the motorcycle run for Crystal Campbell?
No, I didn't, but that sounds really interesting.
Oh, guys, I'm on the volleyball team.
We finally won a game.
Nice.
Did you guys go to the parade?
I was there interviewing.
It was pretty cool.
You guys want to know a joke?
Sure.
Where do fat cows go on vacation?
Where?
New York.
Do you guys remember that time we went to New York?
Oh yeah.
That was fun.
Live from New York, it's the Mustang Report!
I'm Victoria Rasher here with Brie Forcier at the 385th Medford Parade.
How are you today, Brie?
Good, how are you?
I'm great, thanks.
Did you know that this is the first parade in eight years in Medford?
I did.
So are you excited to be walking in this parade?
I'm very excited.
Who are you walking with during this parade?
I'm walking with all the lacrosse girls in Galoosie.
So what's the thing that you're most excited to see?
I'm actually very excited to see everybody dressed up.
It's pretty cool.
Thanks, Marie.
Have fun at the parade.
Thanks, you too.
I'm Victoria Rasche here at the 385th Medford Parade with Mr. Galussi and these two lovely ladies.
Who are these two lovely ladies?
These are my daughters, Olivia and Sophia.
Hello.
We're here today, you know, to come out for the parade.
We always love a good parade.
We've got the lacrosse team, a bunch of other sports teams, swim team, crew team.
So we're all here to support the mayor.
He's been very good to all of us, kind of his last hurrah.
And say hi to Medford.
It should be a great day.
That's great, guys.
What are you guys looking forward to the most?
Being in a parade.
I'm excited to be in the parade.
That's great.
Thank you, guys.
I hope you guys have a lot of fun.
Thanks so much.
Hi, I'm Katrina Rasche, and I'm here with the Medford hockey team.
Hey!
Are you guys excited for the parade?
Yeah!
OK, so when does your hockey season start?
I don't know.
It already started.
You guys win any games yet?
You won two games.
Who got the goals?
What are you guys looking forward to most for the parade today?
Not walking?
No.
Are you guys gonna skate the parade?
Yeah.
Wear your ice skates.
These are our skates!
They're your skates?
Okay.
Well good luck today guys, walking the parade.
Wave to us if we're on the sideline, alright?
Now say bye to Medford.
Bye world!
I'm Victoria Rasher here at the 385th Medford Parade with Mickey and Minnie.
How are you guys today?
Pretty good.
Good.
What are you looking forward to most for this 385th parade?
Seeing all the little kids, seeing their excitement.
Have you had a lot of little kids come up to you?
A ton, actually.
I held a baby today.
That's exciting.
So what does it take to prep to be Mickey and Minnie?
A lot of practice walking.
You've got to really see, look at your steps.
Are the heads heavy?
No, they're actually really light, but they're really big, so walking around is kind of tough.
That's exciting.
Well, have fun today, guys.
I hope you attract a lot of little kids.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
I'm Victoria Rasche here at the 385th Medford Parade, and I'm here with Sean Freeman, the boys' crew captain, and Nev Jacks, the girls' crew captain.
So how are you guys doing today?
Doing well.
How about you?
I'm great, thanks.
I'm awesome.
How are you?
Good, thanks.
So what are you guys looking forward to most for the parade?
I think representing the crew team and what we've done and showing our Medford spirit.
That's great.
How about you?
Yeah, pretty much the same thing, just showing how much we've grown and how well we've done in the past seasons and what a future we're looking forward to.
So does this kind of half a mile walk, does it count as a practice for you guys today?
No, we usually don't practice on Sundays, but it's nothing near what a practice would be for us.
Our practice is like super hard.
Practices, they're definitely intense and they're like working our team and
Yeah.
If you had, Sean, one word to describe your amazing crew team, what would it be?
Committed.
What about you, Neve?
Commitment, yeah.
And team spirit.
Yeah, commitment.
Nice one.
Thanks, guys.
Have fun today.
So when did your swim season start?
We're going to have an informational meeting on Wednesday, October 14th, but the season doesn't start until the Monday after Thanksgiving.
So I know there have been rumors about your 4 a.m.
practices.
When do you guys practice?
So it's just a rumor.
We do practice like every other team after school now.
We don't do morning practices.
And we have an amazing new facility.
It's one of the best high school facilities in the state.
So it's a really great opportunity to be swimming for Medford High.
So do you have to be a really good swimmer to try out for the swim team?
Honestly, you just need to have the motivation to become a good swimmer.
That's great.
All right.
Thanks, guys.
Hopefully, everyone else tries out for the swim team.
I won't, because I'll drown.
But thanks.
Hi, I'm Cariann Lucharis and I'm with the Mustang Report.
I'm here checking out the weather all around the school.
We're supposed to get a flash flood warning, three to six inches of rain.
Right now it's humid outside and be safe.
Hi, I'm Katrina Rasche and I'm here with the Mustang Report and we're here with Mr. Heineck from the English Department and he's training to run a marathon.
So Mr. Heineck, how do you train to run a marathon?
So what a lot of people do is you download an 18-week training schedule and the first 15 weeks basically increase the amount you run.
Mainly on the weekends it's basically designed for people who have jobs.
So during the week you're running four or five days and then on the weekend you gradually do
A little bit more, a little bit more, starting around six or seven, and then it gets all the way up to 20.
And to get technical, what it does is you do, say, seven, then eight, and then you go, the third week is like five.
And then it goes 10, 11, and then it goes to eight.
And sort of you move forward, and then you move back, and your body acclimates to doing more work.
So are you taking 18 weeks to train?
I'm doing the whole thing exactly as prescribed.
I'm doing my homework.
And this way, if I follow it, I'm putting my trust in the experience of a guy named Hal Higdon, who wrote a book called The Marathon.
And the guy's in his 70s.
And when he turned 70, he ran seven marathons in seven months.
So he's run over 100.
And so he's sort of like the official marathon guide.
So I'm just sort of following along.
So would you want to run over 100 marathons?
No.
No, not at all.
All I really want to do is do better than I did last time.
I ran one when I was turning 40, like a bucket list thing.
And it went well for about 18 miles, and then it was terrible.
So this time I decided to sort of train more thoroughly, be better prepared, and eat.
Because the first time I didn't eat while I was doing it, and so I ran out of energy.
And now I know you've got to eat while you're running.
Hey!
Hi, I'm Carrie Anne and I'm back with the Mustang Report.
We're outside 3rd Cap.
I'm here with Lydia Ryan who's an expert on flash flooding.
Lydia, what do you think about all this flooding?
Well, there is a collapsed drain pipe on the roof and it's caved in about 30 feet down from the roof and they can't find it yet.
However, it's causing leaking to come down from the ceiling and cause major flooding problems and we had a bunch of puddles here but they seem to have cleaned up and now they put giant trash bins here
to collect the rain from coming down from the roof.
Do you have any advice for the students that are going to be walking by here?
Don't walk under the rain.
Thank you.
Back to you.
I'm here with Dr. Perrella, the initiator of the What Would Tucci Do?
So, can you tell me the information about What Would Tucci Do?
Sure, absolutely.
Actually, I don't think I could take full credit for What Would Tucci Do?
initiative.
Although, WTTD project, as we like to call it,
My wife and I, who was also a big fan of Mr. Tucci, were talking about how the man is amazing and seems to cure and fix every problem that there is.
So we sort of came up with that slogan, what would Tucci do?
And then it somehow materialized onto a t-shirt and I was fortunate enough to find them in a box and I just passed them out to random seniors.
That's sort of how it played out.
That's amazing.
So if you got a stain on your tie, what would Tucci do for you?
Well, the first thing he'd probably do is he'd be the first person to identify the stain in the tie and tell me where it came from and how it probably can be fixed and resolved again.
He most likely would approach the tie carefully, maybe removing it from my neck without me even knowing it.
And at that point, somehow, between his language and the way he looks at the tie, the stain would sort of evaporate from the fabric.
That's how I would expect it to happen, though I haven't seen it yet happen like that.
Thank you, Dr. Perlow.
You're very welcome.
If there was a brand new building and there was an older lady on the top floor, what would Tucci do?
I think Mr. Tucci would go in and save the old lady's life.
Good answer.
What would Tucci do?
He would strike him off.
If there was a wing on the pool, what would Tootie do?
Um, he would definitely just cover the blowhole.
Yeah, so would it damage the ceiling?
If there's an angel in distress, what would Tootie do?
Pick him up and spin him around.
If David Ortiz became a vampire, what would Tootie do?
Teach him how to play baseball!
If Tootie was in a dance battle, what would he do?
He would tap dance.
If Kanye West won for president in 2020, what would Tucci do?
We'd run against him!
Go Huggies!
Woo!
If it's your birthday, what would Tucci do?
Call you down to his office and tell you to run out and break the pencils.
If someone tried to assassinate the president and vice president, what would Tucci do?
Give him detention!
What would Tucci do?
What would he do?
Kyle!
Are you okay?
Thank you Mr. Tucci.
If there's a llama in the hallway, what would Tucci do?
He would get on it and ride it like Paul Revere!
Woo!
If there's a llama in the hallway, what would Tucci do?
Do you have a hall pass for that llama?
If somebody ran in late, but Mr. Tucci knew, what would Mr. Tucci do?
Deliver the baby in a snowstorm.
Exactly.
Hi, I'm here with Mr. Tucci, and we have to ask him about the what would Tucci do.
So, have you seen those shirts around the school?
I've seen them, I walked in this morning and I was totally taken aback and surprised and it's a good thing that got me thinking today on this Friday and it's fun to see people wearing the shirts.
So how do you feel about this what would Tucci do movement that's sweeping the school?
This is a movement but it's caused me to ponder the question too as well.
What would Tucci do?
And it's a very deep answer that I've been consulting a lot with Dr. Prowler about.
And him and I have been spending all day talking a little bit about what would Tucci do.
And he's kind of been my therapist today.
Okay, so I think we have to answer the question that all our viewers at home are wondering.
What would Tucci do?
Well, it's a very deep question, like I said, but keep in mind that I am a person that loves Medford High School, in particular, the senior class.
So what would I do?
I wanna see the senior class go on and graduate.
I'm gonna do everything I can to make sure that does happen.
So how's that for an answer?
That is an amazing answer.
Thank you so much.
Back to you.