Good evening. Happy holidays. Thank you. And welcome to the 39th regular meeting of the Medford City Council. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Camuso. Present. Councilor Caviello. Present. Councilor Knight. Present. Vice President Lungo-Kern. Present. Councilor Marks. Present. Councilor Penta.
President Donald Rousseau, present. Seven present members, none absent. Please rise to salute the flag. I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America, and to the republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all.
Thank you. Chair recognizes Councilor Caravaglio for suspension of the rules to introduce the members of the Medford Kiwanis Key Club. Thank you, Mr. President. Mr. President, it's my honor to introduce the Medford Kiwanis Key Club to sing a couple of songs for the citizens of Medford and our honored guests this evening. Two wonderful Christmas carols from the members of the Key Club. Why don't you come up front.
Welcome to you all.
Jingle bells, jingle bells, jingle bell rock. Jingle bells swing and jingle bells ring. Snowing and blowing, the bushels of fun.
Now the jingle hop has begun. Jingle bell, jingle bell, jingle bell rock. Jingle bells chime in jingle bell time. Dancing and prancing in jingle bell square. In the frosty air. What a bright time. It's the right time to rock the night away.
Jingle bell time is a swell time to go riding in a one-horse sleigh. Giddy up, jingle horse, kick up your feet. Jingle around the clock. Mix and a mingle in the jingling feet. That's the jingle bell rock.
Jingle bell, jingle bell, jingle bell rock Jingle bells chime in jingle bell time Dancing and prancing in jingle bell square In the frosty air What a bright time, it's the right time To rock the night away Jingle bell time is a swell time To go riding in a one-horse sleigh
Giddy up, jingle horse, take up your feet. Jingle around the clock. Mix and mingle in the jingling feet. That's the jingle bell. That's the jingle bell. That's the jingle bell rock.
Oh, the weather outside is frightful, but the fire is so delightful. And since we've no place to go, let's go, let's go, let's go. It doesn't show signs of stopping, and I've lost some more from hopping.
The lights are turned way down low Let us know, let us know, let us know When we finally kiss goodnight How I hate going out in the storm But if you really hold me tight All the way home I'll be warm The fire is slowly dying And my dear we're still goodbying
Don't you love me so? Let it snow, let it snow, let it snow. Let it snow, let it snow, let it snow.
While we're under suspension on the motion of Council tonight to take paper number 15816 to the Honorable President and members of Medford City Council, dear Mr. President and City Councilors, I respectfully request and recommend that the sum of $250,000 be transferred from sale of real estate to be used for improvements to the five business districts with kiosks as recommended earlier this year. A representative of each business district
will recommend to the new mayor some proposed uses. I also respectfully request that the sum of $147,687 be returned to the sale of real estate account from snow and ice removal. We now anticipate state reimbursement for this purpose. Happy New Year, it's been a blast. I remain your friend, the Honorable Michael J. McGlynn, mayor, with us this evening.
is Louise Miller, uh, director of budgeting and finance for the city of Medford, who will explain to us this paper. Good evening and welcome. Good evening. Um, this is a request by the mayor, um, as a result of a commitment that was made to the Medford business groups in the five different business districts for, um, going forward capital improvements to the business districts.
Um, the first installment of $250,000 is being funded through the sale of real estate account. And in years going forward to the extent that funds are available, it will be funded. Um, we anticipate with additional revenue, which will be going into the general fund, um, but from parking revenue. And if I may point out that this was at the, uh, request of the city council. Thank you. Very good.
On Madam Vice President. Thank you, President De La Russo. Ms. Miller, do we have an expected total budget? You said the coming year. Is this going to be $250,000 a year? That is my understanding, is that if the funds are available, that it would be on a $250,000 a year basis. It will be part of the operating budget. And if I understood correctly, the new mayor will then
establish an advisory committee on the disposition of those funds? That is correct. Can you give us some examples maybe of what will be done with the money? It has to be used for capital improvements. So, you know, improvements to the sidewalks, perhaps improvements to lighting, lane markings, you know, anything of that nature. Trees even?
So it's going to come upon the recommendation of the committee from made up of business men and women. That is correct. Yes. Spend the money. Okay. On the motion of council caviar for approval. Do I have a second? Seconded by counselor. Uh, Camuso, all those in favor, if I may, if I may, if we could call is requested, uh, required. I apologize. Madam vice president.
just because it's almost a random $250,000 figure, if we could get an update, um, maybe at year's end every year of what the money's been spent on and how much has been used out of that two 50 versus how much is remaining just so we can have an idea of how to fund it each year. Um, I just feel like kind of don't know where the two 50 came from. So want to make sure that we budgeted correctly each year and are spending it, um, accordingly and the way it should be spent obviously.
So on the, uh, motion for approval, uh, by counselor Caraviello, seconded by councilor Camuso as amended by vice president Longo Kern, uh, council Penta. Why couldn't that money be incorporated as part of the office of community development who was desperately in need of folks to have a professional consultant come in as we talked about before?
just taking $250,000 and spending it randomly at five squares doesn't make as much sense as having a paid professional and here's where the money could come from. It would even have to come out of the city's budget and you would have a working operating capital to work with. I mean, the city is in desperate need of getting good professional people and I think this would be a better way to spend the money. If I would use the money to be spent, that's what I would go because
You need a professional person who's going to be able to tell you what's wrong, why these squares are not multiplying. Just to correct the sidewalk or plant a tree or do a window or put a facade, that doesn't still help the business district. And I think what you really need is a hardcore look and a reality check as to why these businesses aren't multiplying or doing as good as they should.
So I would like to amend this to go one step further that that money be considered for the purposes of having a paid professional consultant be incorporated into the office of community development for the purposes of business development for the entire five squares in the city of method. So that's an amendment by council Penta that a consideration be given to using this money towards the hiring of a business development specialist in the office of community development. Mr. President, if I may. Yes.
because the money is from the sale of this particular year, the money is from sale of real estate, the money must be used, this initial $250,000 for capital improvement. Sale of real estate funds cannot be used for a salary. And that's just for this particular year. Well, when this first came up, Mr. President, when they were talking about the $250,000 and there wasn't a definition on how this money was going to be spent, there was nothing that required the fact
you know, you couldn't use it for salaries. Now you're putting a requirement on it that wasn't there in the beginning. And that right there in and of itself is just, you know, it's, it's stifling the whole idea of moving forward. Why can't this money just be put on hold until next year and then incorporate into next year's budget? If it's an, if it's an, if you're telling me if it's into the real estate account, why can't it just go into the real estate account and become effective January 1st when the city council, the then city council can make its recommendation.
The sale of real estate account can only be used for capital improvements. So that's all that I was saying. So no matter when those funds are expended, there are currently $470,000, $407,000 in that fund. Those funds can only be used for capital. But why is it going into the real estate account? Why can't it go to free cash? That is the way the paper was written by the mayor and is being proposed to you. This is being, where does it say that Louise?
That what? That's a 250 has to go into the real estate account. It says, right. I respectfully request and recommend that the sum of $250,000 be transferred from sale of real estate. But that doesn't mean that the council can make a subsequent request to send it to free cash. I would move amend the motion that it'd be sent to free cash. That way the, the incoming council can have a better intelligent way of learning how to spend the money. We'll have to do as a beep paper because it's contradictory to the main motion. Okay.
Uh, chair recognizes counselor marks. Thank you, Mr. President. Louise, how is, uh, the representative of each business district going to be selected? I actually do not know that. Um, I assume, or I shouldn't assume, but I believe it's going to be the mayor selecting a representative from each of the business districts. But I do not know that for sure. The new mayor will have to determine that. All right.
Mr. President, with all due respect, I think at this point, I would ask that we lay it on the table. There are a lot of unanswered questions on this particular proposal, and I think it warrants more discussion. And, you know, we may look at having $250,000, a quarter of a million dollars, spent to improve communication between the Chamber of Commerce and the City of Method.
We may choose to spend the $250,000 to promote small business to come back into our community. There may be a number of initiatives rather than saying every business district will get $50,000 and go off and do what they want. And maybe it would be worthwhile to, you know, have us as a community look at the larger picture rather than break us into five separate business segments and say, what can we use with a quarter of a million dollars? And it's not just for the first year.
It's the second, it's the third, and the fourth. And by year four, you're talking a million dollars, and this is not chump change.
And, uh, I, I think, uh, we're better off. We have an economic development subcommittee that we refer this to the economic development subcommittee, find out who these five representatives are, uh, or maybe there's more than that. Uh, meet with them. Let us hear what their needs are because this clearly states to us, it says, uh, the business district will recommend to the new mayor, some proposed uses that doesn't say the mayor is going to implement them. It doesn't say the mayor is going to act upon them.
It doesn't say anything other than they're just going to recommend uses. And, um, you know, I'd like to see a little more than, uh, what we have in front of us tonight. So I would ask that this be sent to the subcommittee on economic, uh, uh, development. Very good. So that's also, uh, contradictory to the motion that's before us. So may we do that as a seat paper?
If you want, we could do a motion to table. It doesn't matter to me, but... Are you motioning to table? We'll do a motion to table. On the motion of Councilor Marks to table, all those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Aye. One in opposition. Councilor Camuso. Motion is tabled. Thank you. Undebatable.
While we're into suspension, this is a wonderful evening of celebration tonight. Two members of the city council will be retiring, leaving the council, and we wish them well. They each have many members of their families and friends and longtime supporters with them here tonight to help us in that celebration.
But as is custom, we'll give, at this time, invite each of the counselors the opportunity to make a final address on this occasion and to speak to their colleagues and to the people of Medford. And then after such presentations,
uh, of, uh, speeches on behalf, uh, from both, uh, members will, uh, adjourn, uh, to enjoy some refreshments and presentations of, uh, gifts from the city council. So at this time we're going to do you want to do them afterwards or do you want to do them all together? Okay.
15-809 offered by Councilor Marks, be it resolved that Medford City Councilor Robert Penta be recognized for his four decades of public service and dedication to the city of Medford. Councilor Marks. Thank you, Mr. President, and it's my honor and pleasure to speak on behalf of a colleague I've served with for the past 16 years, someone that I've grown to respect and admire, and someone I got to know outside of
uh, this reeling and, um, consider, uh, not only a friend, uh, but a close friend. And that is a councilor Bob Penta. Um, Bob is the longest serving city councilor in this city's history and also the longest serving consecutive city councilor with 18 terms or 36 years. Mr. President, that alone is an accomplishment in this day and age, you know, far too often,
You hear about people serving public office and within a year or two, you know, something comes up or, you know, their name is besmirched and, you know, things happen. And here we have a gentleman that served with distinction for 36 years, the residents of this community. And I really find it amazing that someone that's been so vocal in the community and willing to talk on every issue,
You know, there are times that we'd have tough votes that, you know, we'd discuss ahead of time and say, well, what do you think about this and what do you think about that? And then we'd have a crowd of people come up, a crowd of residents, and there may be 150 residents in the audience. And surely, Mr. President, you'd see one by one the councilors
say, well, 150 people here. I was going to go this way, but now I may go that way, you know, counting the number of votes out there. And I can unequivocally state, Mr. President, that that never happened with Bob Penter.
There were times when this audience was filled with people, and you can count on Bob standing up, speaking his mind, never swaying on the number of people here, the number of emails, because he was a man of conviction, a man that had principles, a man that felt that he was doing the best on behalf of the community, whether there was five people here or 500 people.
And that's a trait that you have to admire. It's something that I admire because it's not an easy task. You know, the easy thing to look out in the audience and say, there's 100 people here. I'm with them. Because as an elected official, you want to be everyone's friend. But it's the harder thing, Mr. President, to stand up and stand by your convictions, no matter what the odds are. And that is Bob Penta. You know, when you look at the years, 36 years, you know, a lot has changed in 36 years. Jimmy Carter was President when Bob Penta got elected in 1980.
A postage stamp was 15 cents when Bob Penta was elected in 1980. And Billy Joel's song on the charts was, It's Still Rock and Roll to Me. In 1980. So as you can see, a lot has changed over the time. And the one thing that has remained constant is Councilor Penta's commitment to this community and the residents of this community. That has never wavered in 36 years. You know, Bob fought for transparency.
He fought for fiscal responsibility, a common sense approach to city government, and never, as I mentioned, never changed his vote no matter what the odds were or what the issue was. Bob was always true to himself and always represented the people in that manner, Mr. President. Bob served for many years on a lot of different boards. We'd be here all night if we went through every one of Councilor Penta's accomplishments, but just to name a few,
Bob was a member of the Community Advisory Board for the New England Memorial Hospital. Bob served on the Board of Directors for the West Medford Community Center. It still does currently. Bob serves on the Board of the Brooks Estates. He's one of the Board of Directors for the Brooks Estates Land Trust. He is a member of the Mass Municipal Association Board of Director and past member of the Public Employee Policy Environmental Committees. Over the years, there's been a number of issues in the community, and I can tell you firsthand,
When the parking program came up, and there were a lot of people pro and con on the parking issue, it was one person that went to every one of the five business districts.
One person that went into the business, no matter what size you were, no matter what your business was, and asked, how is this impact your business? Is this going to be good or bad? And that was Bob Penta. No one else went around to every business district. And I'm going to speak for every one of the councils, because I didn't hear anyone else going around. Bob Penta went to every business district. He didn't have to do that after 34 years on the city council, being the senior member. He did it because it was the right thing to do, and he wanted to be in touch with the small businesses in this
community to see how this parking program would impact business. And, you know, that took a lot of time and effort and things that don't go noticed. That wasn't on the front page of the transcript. That wasn't in every post that you read and on social media. But that was something Bob did to be in tune 36 years or 34 years after getting elected. I think that speaks volumes for his character, Mr. President.
Also, Mr. President, Bob Pinto was one of the first to offer a line item in our budget. Never happened before in this city's history for the arts. Bob realized the importance of having a strong art community in this city, and Bob witnessed firsthand what the arts can do with their own minimal money, let alone having money put aside in the city budget. There are thousands of people that get impacted in our community from the arts.
And that was Bob Penta's resolution to speak up for the arts in this community. And I know many of the artists will always be beholden to Bob because of that. Bob was the first elected official when we had the embattled Meffitt Housing Authority with their executive director come under a lot of controversy a few years ago. And many people didn't want to talk about it because, you know, it's just an issue we didn't want to touch. Bob Penta was the first elected official
to stand up and say, something's wrong. Something's wrong with this housing authority. More is going to come out. And eventually more did come out, but that Bob had his ear to the grind constantly. He had his finger on the pulse of this city and he wasn't afraid to speak up. Um, you know, Bob was the first, uh, elected official to stand up, uh, with the potential merger with partners and Lawrence Memorial hospital. He was the first to put it on the agenda.
He put it on the agenda 25 times, but he was the first to put it on the agenda. And he kept it out there. He kept the issue going so people knew what was going on. People that worked for the hospital knew what was happening. So, you know, I give him a lot of kudos for being the first on these very important issues, not only to bring them up, but to make people in the community aware of what's going on in our city. The clean up and fix up week. It still hasn't happened, and I hope under the new administration,
This is an issue that Bob Penter has brought up for several years now. And think about it, with the new trash program, you have to be very selective what you put out on the curb now. And Bob devised a program that you can put out once a year, whatever you want, and the trucks will come by and pick up your sofa, your bureau, whatever it is out there. And I just think that's an ingenious way of getting people maybe that want to clean out a cellar or an attic or
have the kid coming back from college, and I want to make some room to allow residents to toss out more stuff on the sidewalk without calling. Bob Penta called for charter review 10 years ago. There was no discussion 10 years ago. Now there's a lot of discussion about charter review because our charter hasn't been reviewed in 28 years. And there's a lot of discussion now, and I think many elected officials are on board now. But it was 10 years ago that Bob was calling for charter review.
and to take a look at the city charter, which is the master plan on how this city operates. And that was Bob's vision 10 years ago. Also, public access. We've been without public access for several years now. Bob Penter has been the champion to bring back public access in this community. Not for Bob Penter, not for this council. We're on Tuesday nights. For the people in this community, local programming that we used to have in this community, which is very important,
to the success of this community and to the well-being of our sports programs and arts and culture in this city. Bob Penter has realized that for years and has been an advocate and a champion for public access in this community. The Courtyard Nursing Home, when neighbors got up in arms because they leveled all the mature trees in the back of the Courtyard Nursing Home, Bob Penter stood aside all the neighbors and said, what are you doing here?
And he forced the hand of the nursing home to plant mature trees to act as a buffer, like it was originally, between the neighborhood and the back of the courtyard nursing home. And that was Bob Penta that stood up on behalf of the residents of this community.
So, you know, I'm proud to say these comments about my friend, Bob Penta. He will be sorely missed. I know I'm not the only one that's going to miss him, but he will be sorely missed. And my wife will be happy because I'll be getting home an hour earlier now on Tuesday nights. So I'll be home in a reasonable time. But honestly, I hope to see
you around, Councilor Penta. I hope to see you stay active. You have such a knowledge that we as a community need to tap and stay involved. And I've always envied your record keeping. I mean, you would pull out resolutions from 1983. I can't find the resolution from last week. And you would have a catalog. Susan, your house must be like the CIA. You must have a file on each
It's amazing. Over the years, the information that you're able to obtain and access through your cataloging and due diligence, I think, is just another part on how you treated the job. This wasn't just a side job that Bob Penta did on the side. This was Bob Penta's full-time job, and he treated it like a full-time job.
know there's a number of residents here that would like to present Councilor Penta, in addition to what we as a council are presenting, Mr. President, there are a number of residents that would like to present Councilor Penta with the gift for his 36 years of dedicated service as a public servant to the residents and to the city of Method. So at this time, I would ask that the residents come up with the gift that they have, Mr. President,
and present it to Councilor Penta. Thank you, Anthony D'Antonio, 12 Yale Street. Councilor Marks and through the chair, there were a few people, several people,
I would like to say a few words before we make the presentation. I figured it would be better, uh, to do that first, if that's okay and agreeable with you. Uh, don't want to make this, you know, um, too long, but, uh, I'd like to give them the opportunity to speak first and then I'll come commence with the gifts. Thank you. Welcome. Good evening. Address for the record. I form a student president of the council for Della Russo.
Mr. Griffin. My name is Jay Griffin. I live at 8 Arbor Glen Lane in Methuen. I want to congratulate Councilor Camuso, another former student, on his service to the city. But in particular, I want to address my remarks to the citizens of Medford and to one of my closest friends, Councilor Penta. I just want to take a few minutes of your time to reflect on my thoughts about Boab.
Bob Penta speaks his mind, as Councilor Mark said. He doesn't sugarcoat anything. His speech doesn't pander to any group. He says what he feels. Councilor Penta has been an outspoken champion of preserving Medford's proud history. Without his support, there would be no Brooks Estate. Councilor Penta served with me on the executive board
of the Medford Brooks Estate Land Trust. Bob raised money and promoted the estate every chance that he had. The carriage house would not be in such a terrible state of disrepair today if the city had supported the reuse plan that he had pushed before. Bob Penta also served on the executive board of the Medford Historical Society with me.
He was always the first to volunteer when we had special events, exhibits, and tours. Councilor Penta made sure that the city funded the restoration of the Historical Societies Museum on Governors Avenue and the preservation of the Craddock or Peter Tufts House at 350 Riverside Avenue.
Many years ago, I came before the Medford City Council to address problems that were taking place in Royal House Park. I actually brought a brick from the wall and slammed it down here. We had kids in the park drinking. I found hypodermic needles. There was no lighting. The wall was too high. Everybody could hide.
Bob worked with Bill Slagle, and between the Royal House Association and the City of Medford, we spent $40,000 to put the new wall around Royal House Park. At present, there is no lighting. I just drove by just to be sure. There were two lights there.
He had three lights put in, two that illuminated the park and one that would shine on the house. As you go home tonight, Fred, look, it is pitch black. You're waiting for trouble to happen. The fence between the park and the house has been destroyed. There's big holes in it because the beech tree came down. So now this is in this city council's hands. I can see
In the future, if you don't put some kind of lighting in there, you're going to lose one of the premier national historic sites in the state of Massachusetts and in the United States of America. It's classified as one of the top 20 in our state. I cannot believe that we can't put in green LED lighting and illuminate that whole area. It's a plus for the city of Medford.
The city of Medford has three historic homes open to the public. The Craddock House, built in the 1600s. The Royal House and Slave Quarters, built in the 1700s. The Shepherd Brooks Manor, built in the 1800s. Any other city would support the efforts to preserve and highlight 300 years of outstanding architecture.
These houses, if preserved, would draw tourists who would eat in Medford restaurants, shop in Medford stores, and this is something that Bob has championed his whole time on the council. He's always been a leader, not just giving speeches when the chamber's full like it is tonight. He has spent countless hours on many executive boards, at many meetings, trying to preserve Medford's long and rich heritage.
At this time, I'd like to ask God to bless Bob and Susan as they begin the next chapter of their lives. And I dropped the gauntlet down to the current city council administration to correct these inequities. Thank you. Thank you. Welcome. Please state your name and address for the record. Ray Scaffo, ninth sunset Avenue in Medford.
I just want to take a couple of seconds to thank Paul Camuso for the time that he served on the council and I wish you well Paul. Um, good evening tonight. I want to, I would like to talk to you about my friend Bob Penta. This, this is Bob's last city council meeting after over 30 years of service to the citizens of Medford. The people of Medford could not have had a more honest, dedicated and passionate council.
Bob always believed his first obligation as an elected counselor was to the people of the city of Medford. Bob's passion for Medford is evident to anyone who knows him or whom he worked with him. Some people have mistaken his passion as a liability, calling him argumentative or outright mean. However, this liability is his greatest asset. Bob always
directed his passion towards making sure the citizens of Medford were being treated fairly. Bob's passion was often demonstrated in his willingness to ask why. Why are our property taxes rising without a substantiated budget? Why are our water bills rising when there is more than $7 million in the city's water account? Why have citizens of Medford been charged $3.25 per month and now up to $5
for local access TV that has not existed for over two years. Why are these costs going up when there's another $325,000 available in the city coffers with all this surplus? Why is our infrastructure failing and falling into this repair? Why does the city need a charter review so that you, the city council can have better checks and balances.
There are over 6,500 voters in Medford who, like Bob, want to know why they are passionate about this city and sad to see him leave the council. They know, like I do, that Bob always fighting for them in the betterment of the city of Medford and hope that he will not go away. Bob's passion has inspired a group of citizens, including me, to fight for the good of our city.
When the call comes to fight, all 6,500 and more will be there to fight again. On behalf of all his supporters, I want to express my thanks to my friend and his greatest strength, his wife Susan, for their dedication and service to all the people of Mexico.
Welcome, please state your name and address for the record. Anita D'Antonio, 14 Yale Street. Councilor Penta, Bob. I want to thank you for your devotion in representing all of the residents of Medford. You are our advocate on the city council and you fought with passion to achieve the best outcomes for all of the residents of Medford. With grit,
and determination, you communicated the frustration of so many of us as our voices and concerns fell on deaf ears or were ignored time and time again. I personally want to thank you for standing with me, my family, and my friend and neighbor, God rest her soul, on a particular issue. Because of you, my neighbor felt vindicated and realized that someone actually listened to her point of view.
understood it, and pushed back the bullies. You endured unwarranted backlash for your efforts. But what you did will never be forgotten by me, and I will be forever grateful to you. Harry Truman, a Democrat, and you're a Republican, in case anyone missed it the last time, said, fame is a vapor, popularity
is an accident. Riches take wing. Those who cheer today may curse tomorrow. And only one thing endures, character. Your character endures, as does your love for this city. God bless you and Susan. Thank you. It's so long, not goodbye.
Thank you, City Council, Council President Del Russo, for being allowed to speak here this evening. My sentiments also to Councilor Camuso. We had a few nice battles, but we always walked away smiling. I have a few words I'd like to say. I'm trying to do this in a different approach. I have two quotes here I'd like to read. First one, be more concerned with your character
than your reputation, because your character is what you really are, while your reputation is merely what others think you are. That's from John Wooden, who was one of the most winningest coaches in college basketball, who won 10 championships in a 12-year reign with an unprecedented seven in a row, seven consecutive wins. The second quote, I believe there's an inner power that makes winners or losers.
And the winners are the ones who really listen to the truth of their hearts. That's from Sylvester Stallone, otherwise known as Yo Rocky, okay? Now, why these two? One is a fictional character portrayed by an actor, and the other was an actual human portrayed by a human, okay? But what did they have? They not only taught the talk, they walked the walk.
They did so with compassion. They did so with integrity. And they were determined to have things go the right way. But it was always for the other person. It wasn't for themselves solely. And that's what Bobby Penter is. I knew Bobby Penter back in the days of driving canteen trucks. He gave most of the food away to the needy kids in Roxbury and Dorchester. A lot of people don't know that.
He was always being yelled at for not being able to pay his bill because he was giving the food away to the hungry people. But he's always been, no matter what, no matter what kind of adversity there was, he stood up. He stood up for what he believed in and what he felt the people wanted him to believe in. And with that, there's a lot of baggage that comes with that. And a lot of people don't understand, but he has conviction, he has integrity, and he's been a really good friend to me. And I hope he feels the same way.
about me to him. Now, that's all I have to say in that regard. What I would like to do right now is I'd like to give Mrs. Penta, Susan, the backbone of Mr. Bobby Penta. I'd like to present her with something. Where are you? Come here.
She earned those roses, let me tell you. Now, we know you worked very hard during the campaign this past year. And your supporters and your friends felt that the two of you deserve something to show our appreciation for your efforts. So the first thing I have is a gift certificate for a lovely meal for the two of you.
to a place called Il Posto in Somerville. So the two of you can go and enjoy a nice meal. To start your new year off, a bottle of Dom Perignon. And we hope that is just the beginning of a new life for you and Susan.
And for Councilor Penta, we have a special gift for you. Would it be okay if Councilor Penta could come over to the podium, please? What we have here is a 1904 edition of the City of Medford on parchment paper that's framed
The inscription says, Robert M. Penta, thank you from the citizens of Medford.
Thank you, everybody. Susan Penta, Zero Summit Road, Medford, Mass. First of all, I want to thank everyone on the council for all your support of Bob. And it's been a crazy year.
Looking forward to some time off just to relax a little bit and find ourselves again. And I've said it before and I'll say it one more time, Bob Penta, I love you. You are an amazing man and I'm proud of what we did and how we did it. And I'm saying it publicly now because you are an amazing person and I believe that you
love this city more than anything else. You really do. And I tell people all the time, it reminds me of the song, you don't know what you got till it's gone. And I think that people will notice when you're gone. So don't go too far. OK? I love you.
I know some of the councilors want to speak. Chair recognizes Councilor Caviello. Thank you, Mr. President. And I want to thank Councilor Marks for bringing forward all of Councilor Penta's accolades and the things he's done over his 36 years. You know, I've only had a short period of time to work with Councilor Penta, four years, and I've learned a lot from him. And, you know, in my last four years, I've got to work with two great leaders here and behind the rail, and I've learned for both of them.
I first worked with Bob Pinter maybe about 20 years ago when the mayor asked the Chamber of Commerce to start changing the current liquor laws. And Bob Pinter was one of the first people we worked with. And that was the first time I got to work with him. And he was very helpful and supportive during those years. And as you can see, the laws have changed. We have a lot of restaurants, and we were very successful.
And that's in good part due to Bob Penta and his hard work. And like I said, I'm very proud to serve with him in my last four years here. And like I said, there's not a man that has convictions that would never move. If Bob Penta was on your side, he'd stay with you till the end. Again, I want to thank him for his 36 years of service and I'm glad to be your friend.
Thank you, President De La Russo. I'm sorry to keep everybody from their cake, but — and everybody did such a great job talking about Counselor Penter. But I have to say a few words. I want to thank you, Bob, for your many years of dedicated service. You've been servants since before I was born. I want to thank you for —
With that being said, I guess I've learned from the best. You've taught me many, many lessons. You've taught me to stand up for what I believe in, because you always stand up for what you believe in. You've taught me to ask questions and do my homework. God knows, as it was said before, your library at home is quite large.
You have kept the administration on their toes. You've asked questions that all of us, you know, want to ask. You ask questions that the taxpayers need us to ask, and you've taught me to do that, and I so greatly appreciate that. You've been a true role model. You've put politics and family first, which is something that I obviously family first, but you put the city of Medford before
anything else, which is extremely important in the position that you have held for so long. I hope that one day I can be half of the counselor that you are. When election night came out and it was past 8 o'clock, somebody brought a bottle of champagne to my house and I said, I can't drink it. I had this emotion of seriously just feeling like
the council will almost be empty without you. I finally realized that you weren't gonna be here come January 1st and that's a big set of shoes to fill and we will do our best, I'm sure, but it will never be the same. You've taught me so much and I really appreciate all you've done for the city and I hope you stick around and I'm sure you'll keep your voice heard and be fighting for the people even during your retirement. So I do hope you enjoy your trips to Florida and have some
fun with your grandchildren and your lovely wife. You will be missed, and just thank you for all your years of service. Thank you, Mr. President.
What can I say? You also have a motion here, be it resolved that the Medford City Council commend and congratulate Robert M. Penter on being the longest serving City Council member in Medford history. Thank you. Um, I don't even know where to begin, you know, uh, 36 years. I was two years older than Councilor Lungo, you know, and, uh, absolutely. And, um,
For the first time, I'm speechless. You know, Bob, you're really a fellow that's kept me young over the years. Sometimes you'd think that we were two kids getting ready to fight at Playstead Park. But in reality, we were both just fighting for what we really believed in. And that's something that I admire about you. I'm going out this evening, retiring as well. And the council's not going to be the same without you.
I respect your loyalty, your tenacious ability to fight for what you believe in, and you've certainly been passionate over your tenure on the council. One thing that I really admired about you, and I was going through a similar situation at the time with my dad, was when you cared for your lovely wife, Linda, and I saw a side of you that most people didn't see.
I'm sorry, I'm just talking about my dad, I get a little emotional. But you really are a good-hearted guy, you know? At the end of the day, and the good part about it was, I'd see you at Bocelli's or something, after a meeting, you'd still tell me how much I stink, but we could laugh about it, you know? But, like I said, I'm going out tonight, we're both going out as winners, we both won by fighting for the people of Medford,
didn't want to make it sound, I'm in good company of leaving this room tonight with another councillor that I know left his best battle on the field and you fought for what you believed in and for that you should be very proud. Councillor Knight.
Mr. President, thank you very, very much. But more importantly, Counselor Penta, thank you. I think everybody behind the reels has been involved in government for a good portion of their professional career. And we've all had interactions with Bob Penta. And one thing I can say about you, Counselor, is I'm certainly very disappointed that I don't have an opportunity to work alongside you for more of a tenure than I have. I think everybody behind this reel has had an opportunity to work with you a little bit more than I have.
And one thing that I've really been able to take away from working with you, Councillor, is that it's about the issues. It's not about personalities. It's not about
Winning or losing it's about the issues and it's about doing what's right for the people in Medford and you and I could maybe not get along on one issue and When that issue is over and the votes taken two seconds later something else is on the table It needs to be addressed and what's over is over. What's done is done. Let's work on the next thing counselor So I certainly appreciate the way that you can leave it behind the rail, but it's not about personalities. It's about it's about people It's about the city of Medford. It's about moving Medford forward counselor
Another thing I'd like to congratulate you on is what a hell of a campaign you were in. What a hell of a campaign. You weren't outworked, Counselor. You weren't outworked. You did a great job out there. You pounded the pavement. You're out there working hard every day.
And I don't think that anybody can ask for anything else. So thank you very much for all your service. Thank you very much for what you've done to make the city of Medford a great place, Counselor. And I know that this is a retirement party, but I'm pretty sure that you're not going to be gone for a long time. So thank you very much, Bob. It's been a pleasure working alongside you.
And if I could, from the chair, thank you, Councilor Penta. I want to thank you for the encouragement you gave me when I first ran, and all the support you gave me in that process. Though I was born once you started serving, you did serve for my father, and I learned a lot from that era. It's been good to serve with you. You've done very well for the people of Medford.
You've fought for a lot of people who didn't have a voice, and you made their voice heard. You've come to the end of your term. You have a wonderful opportunity to recreate your life, to enjoy it anew with Susan, to spend time in Florida, where all the retired politicians from Medford go, and sit around and look for things to do, drive their wives crazy,
and talk amongst themselves about how all of us left here don't know what they're doing. So we wish you well, and we hope you have a wonderful time. Thank you, Bob.
So that on the motion of Councilor Marks be approved, all those in favor? All those opposed? And Councilor Camusos, yes. Councilor Camusos, 15-817 also be approved. All those in favor? All those opposed? While we're under suspension, be resolved, offered by Councilor Knight, that the Medford City Council congratulate Paul A. Camusos on his 15 years of service as an elected official in the City of Medford. Councilor Knight.
Mr. President, thank you very much. And my relationship with Councilor Camuso is a little bit different than mine with Councilor Penta, because I think that this Super Bowl Sunday, Paul, will be 30 years that we've known each other. And our families have been friends for a long time. His uncle Fred and my father taught together in Somerville for a number of years.
Paul and I have been very familiar with one another through Medford Youth Sports, Medford High School, his inaugural campaign, and I could go on and on about Paul's accomplishments. We could go on and on about what a great guy Paul is.
how dedicated he is to the community, to his family, to his brothers, to his mother, to his late father and his grandmother. But I think that when you look at the election results over Paul's tenure and term, we'll see that he topped the ticket seven out of eight times, Mr. President, and I think that that speaks for itself. The people of Medford
The people of Medford knew that Paul Camuso was doing his job. The people of Medford knew that Paul Camuso was working. The people of Medford knew that Paul Camuso was an effective city council and an effective member of the school committee. I'm just at awe, Paul, to sit here and see you step down and retire and go on to greener pastures.
at this point in my young political career, because it wasn't too long ago that you were cheating off my papers in English class in high school. So I'd really just like to take a moment to thank you for your friendship, but more so thank you for your service, because when your political career ends,
You go back to being a normal citizen. And, well, as normal of a citizen as you can be. And I look forward to the laughs that we've had and the laughs that we're going to have. I look forward to spending time with you and with your beautiful family. And I just can't thank you enough for all that you've done for the community and for me personally. So, thank you very much for all.
I've had the pleasure of knowing Paul Camuso many years, because my son is the same age and playing youth sports together and all those things. I knew his mother and father very well. It wasn't too long ago that I was driving Paul Camuso to school every day with my son. We carpooled every day. And who knew 20 years ago that I'd be sitting beside him here behind the rail helping the citizens of Medford.
I just want to thank him for his years of service and to the citizens of Method. Your mother and father would be very proud to see the kind of person that you've grown up to be. Thank you, Mr. President. I too would like to congratulate Councilor Camuso on his retirement, although I don't believe he's retiring.
That's good for now. You know, when Paul first got elected, I remember during one of the debates, Paul had a catchy line, and the line went like this. If you need your sidewalk done, if you need a tree trimmed, if you need the snow plowed in front of the house, you call Paul Camuso. And you know what, it dawned on me. When I used to get constituent calls, I used to say, you know what, call Paul Camuso.
And let me tell you, sure enough, people would send me an email, call me back, say, hey, thank you for getting that done. I got my sidewalk done. So Paul, you were more than a help, let me tell you, that you can understand. But as Councilor Camuso mentioned,
Paul championed a lot of things on this city council, a lot of issues that he felt near and dear. He was always someone that did the homework and was present. Paul, you know, you don't top the ticket, as Councilor Knight mentioned, without being out there, without talking to people, without having your finger on the pulse. And Paul was a constituent guy.
And that's what got him elected. He thought all politics was local, like Tip O'Neill. And it's true. It is local. And you have to be out there. You have to be in the forefront. And you have to get back to people. So the one thing that I can say about Councilor Camuso is that he returned the phone calls. He went to your house when you had a broken sidewalk. And he was there when needed. And I respect that in him. And I look forward to seeing him active in the community.
active with his family, his young son, and his lovely wife. And I see your father-in-law here who never comes out, Frank Femino. I haven't seen Frank in... Hey, Frank! You must have promised him dinner tonight, because I haven't seen Frank out in a long time. But no, with all candid, really, I wish you well in your retirement, and I hope to see you active in the community.
Thank you, President DeLaRusso. I also want to congratulate you, Paul, and thank you for your many years of service to the citizens of the city. You've done a great job. I think one thing I admire is the responsiveness you had to the constituents. I think they'd call and like 30 seconds later, you'd be calling people back and something we can't even keep up with sometimes. So you've done great work. Enjoy your retirement with your family and your son. And I wish you the best.
I could tell you many stories about Paul Camuso. I first met Paul when he drove up to my house many, many years ago before he decided to run for school committee. And from that point on,
It became a relationship. He should really be working for the city in charge of constituent service. Because I think he really likes going out there and taking care of people's concerns. Because he's like myself, he's a lover of government. I like government in a different way than he likes it. But the interesting part about Paul Camuso, he has made my life extremely interesting for the last 16 years in this council.
Because if it wasn't for him, a lot of these issues really would never be magnified to the point that they are. Whether you were a supporter or a proponent for the mayor or not or vice versa. He made it very interesting because sometimes that's what you really need. You need this discourse. You need this difference of opinion. And when you have a difference of opinion, that's when you learn sometimes what the issue is about.
And when the issue is being presented sometimes, you just lose concept of it. But Paul and I, I believe we've had many, many differences. But as he has said, at the end of the night, he'll come over and shake your hand, or I'll go over and talk to him, shake his hand. It's just an issue. And that's all that it is. And you move on from the subject matter. And what's really interesting here, there's three people here that were, you people were that young when they first started? I don't believe it.
But I'm not that old, so that's the point, okay? So I want to wish you good luck. Like him, I don't think he's going away. He'll be around, and he's just taking a pause in life, and that's okay. And sometimes you need to do that to refine yourself and get yourself back in action. So I congratulate you. Enjoy your life. Enjoy your wife and your family, because that's what it's really about. The first thing in life is your family, and that's what you take care of. Good luck.
Paul, our relationship started off very rocky, and it got better over the years, very much better. What everybody said behind this rail is true. First of all, you're probably one of the few people that have topped the ticket as consistently and as often as you have. That says a lot about your commitment to this community and the people who live here. Constituent services, no one gets it done like you.
So when someone calls and leaves a message on your phone and says, I need that pothole filled, you can call them up and say, look out your front window 10 minutes later and they'll see the steam rising on the street. You get it done. Um, you understand, uh, the great complexities of how legislation locally and on the state level works. You understand the complexities of, uh, the workings of,
civic government, and the management of a city in a way that's above average of most people. And those are all to your credit, and those are all things that have served you well as a counselor, but will serve you well in whichever way you choose to serve the public again in the future.
It was difficult sitting next to you down there, because as Mr. Griffin will remember, when I was a student, I have a touch of the ADD. And you have more of a touch. And so the two of us would be ricocheting off the benches there while we should have been maybe paying attention to what was being debated on this floor.
You are a young man. You have a long way to go as far as whatever it is you're going to do. And I hope that you'll continue to serve your community in one way or another. Good luck. Enjoy your free time on Tuesday nights. And I wish you well.
I think what we're going to do is just allow both you and Councillor Penta to address, and so we'll have Councillor Penta come up first where he's the senior member by service.
You know, I had a big speech prepared, but the first thing I'm going to say, I'm not retiring, and I'm not going to Florida. I'm staying right here in the city of Medford, all right? First of all, and more importantly, you know, I was getting a little emotional sitting over there, and I was at a point maybe getting a little teary-eyed. But you know something? I'm not going to do that tonight. Tonight, this is a congratulatory night for me.
I am so thankful that I have had an opportunity for serving in government for 36 years that was never once questioned as it relates to who or what I was about and why I was doing what I did. I did it for one particular reason. I was elected by the people of this community to represent them to the best of my ability.
not for any personal, financial, or family gain. I did this for one reason, because you, the people, are the most important people in this community. That's why you elect folks like us, to be here and to do your business and to represent your finances, your education, and your wherewithal to the best of my ability. When I first ran for office in 1974, I ran for state representative and I got elected. There was a lady that I met.
And she happened to turn out to be the first woman mayor of the city of Medford. Her name was Marilyn Catino Perica. And she gave me... She gave me a guidepost that I used in this very past election. It basically was, true leadership is found in the plan that one has to offer for respectful consideration. As we all know, I did not run for re-election to the Medford City Council this past year. I ran for the office of mayor.
At the outset, I want to thank Anthony D'Antonio, because four years ago, he broke the ice, saying in this community, someone can run against the mayor. No one is invincible, no one owns the job. Unfortunately, he didn't make it, but he tried, and he got 36% of the vote. That's a huge number to get, coming out of the box for the very first time. I decided to run for this job this past time, only for one reason.
to present a plan, a plan that would give you a vision, a plan that would give you an opportunity, and a plan that would tell you how your taxes and how your buildings and how your educational system would work. I have to thank my wife, Susan. She was the campaign manager to my campaign, and you know, I don't know why, she never was involved in politics before. I needed and wanted someone who could talk to me and relate to the, as the person on the street,
and you can't say this, and this is what you should be doing, and how do we make this connection work? She stabilized me during this campaign, because everyone knows, at the drop of a dime, I could lose it, and I have, and I have, and I'll admit it, and I have, and I have probably at council meetings in the past through the years, and that's only because of my passion for the job. That's not because of any hate for or against any one person or any one issue.
You know, the one thing this community really has to figure out, and with all due respect to the incoming administration, this election was not a landslide victory. So there's a lot of work to be done here to make this city go in the right direction and to bring people together. And to bring people together, there has to be an understanding that folks need to be involved. And how do you get involved? You need to speak up. You come to that podium on a Tuesday night or whatever it might be. I will assure you of this.
I may be sitting there now up until January 4th, but I'll be behind that rail after January 4th, because if I think there's something... Because if I believe that there is something of major importance to our community, no voice should be stifled, past, present, or the future.
Because that's what it's all about. I'm 71 years old, and I'm proud of it. But I'm not old. I'm not going to sit in a rocking chair, and I'm not going away. Two particular points I want to bring up. And I think it definitely needs to be cleared up.
because it was misdirected during this past campaign for mayor. I was never against new schools. What I was against was the opportunity for the people of Memphis to have voted for new schools. That's number one. Number two, you were taking away your community schools.
So when we went to 14 schools down to four, that was a huge change in this community. And a lot of people did not have their input into that. And as a result of that, and the reason why we built new schools at that point in time, some 15 years ago, was the schools were becoming run down. They were becoming misused or not used correctly, and they needed a lot of repairs.
Well, here we are now, some 15 years later. Rick Caviale, on his first year on the term, that's four years ago, that would have made it 11 years ago, produced a paper that said the new schools are $1,102,000 in repairs. We're right back to where we were. That's why we built the new schools. There is the need to making sure that the new council, the new school committee stays on top of their buildings, because look right up there. That's almost three years old.
Three years old, and the city has yet to fix that. And the superintendent of schools was sitting right over there when that ceiling fell, and it still hasn't been fixed. People, you've got to be involved. You need to stay involved. You know, I'm over this feeling right now of being sad. I'm not sad. I'm glad because I have created a new family for myself, a family of people not only who believe, but they need and they want the change to take place in this community. They don't want it.
You know, this past election presented an awful lot of opportunities for everyone. Opportunities for people to write for or write against. Whether you liked me or didn't like me, whether you liked my opponent, whether you liked my counselors or not. You have two brand new counselors, you have two brand new school committee people. That in and of itself should open up big doors for the people in this community who want to see how and where their election process is going. And do they vote for the right people?
The only way you're gonna find out if you vote for the right people, don't wait for two years and wait for the campaign literature to come out. Watch, as I will, each and every week and each and every month, what's taking place on the school committee, what's taking place at the city council. And if you don't like it, speak up, I'll call your council, I'll call your school committee person. You just can't be a lump in the log and say, I'm against it, I don't like it, you need to speak up. And people did speak up in this last election. Unfortunately, it was a beautiful day, only 38% of the people came out to vote.
Hopefully, I think on both sides, everybody would have thought more people would have come out. But they didn't. But the 38 percent, they spoke. It was close, and I think we'll all acknowledge the fact it was close. So there's no mandate one way or the other. But there is one mandate, and that's this. I think the people of this community expect the elected politicians to do their job on behalf of the people of this community. And that's what I did for 36 years. I did my job, and I'm proud of the fact that I did do it.
You know, there's always people during the campaign that you want to acknowledge. And there's so many. I could look at this entire audience. But to me, he's my unsung hero in each and every one of my campaigns. Whenever I ask him to do anything, he just does it. And there's no questions asked. And that's my brother, Anthony. And I have to publicly acknowledge him, because that's what he is. And I just caught her eye in the back of the room.
And I want to publicly acknowledge you, Nancy. You came here on behalf of the Perica family. She and her family stood out at the polls for me on Election Day because they believed in me, and I thank you very much. Nancy Perica. You know, we could go on and on with stories here. And the second thing, I told you about the schools. And the second thing are the kiosks here in the square.
As you all know, I'm just dead set against them. I don't think they're working right. I don't think they, I don't think that, you know, you know, there's, there's a resolution on the council agenda here tonight and it reflects upon the fact that during this past campaign, my opponent put out a questionnaire as it relates to senior citizens. Should they be allowed to park for nothing? Not only do I support that, if we're going to tweak it, then let it be tweaked and give some benefit back to this community. And I would hope that this city council holds the president administration
feet to the fire by telling the Republic parking people that seniors do not have to park here. It's bad enough that you get taxed for everything else, and 45 percent of this community is made up of seniors. Give them a break, folks, because you get the water, you get the meals tax, you get the hotel tax, and you get your real estate tax, and anything else you want to talk about just keeps going up in this community. And while everything keeps going up in this community, salaries have not gotten up. Everyone that works in this building works for you. Your taxpaying dollars pay for everyone's job in this particular building.
To get your biggest bank for the buck, let them work for you. And that would be an easy way to do it. Remember, this republic company is here for 10 years, and you've got no control over it. But the one thing you have control over is the people who signed off on that contract, and they have a right to go there and negotiate. And when my opposition turn around and put that out there, and that's one thing I would be supportive of, that senior citizens of this city park for nothing in the city of Medford. They don't deserve to pay.
When I mention my wife Susan, you have to understand something. As much as a novice she is, she's been an educator for 23 years as a retired school teacher. So she knows what English, the language is all about. Sometimes when I talk too fast, I say the wrong words. It just doesn't come out right. And she says, you can't do that. You can't say that. But I am blessed. You know, Paul sort of like hit it on the head. I've been blessed with two women in my life and two families in my life.
I am a very lucky man. I am very thankful. I didn't lose an election. You know what I won? I won the people of the city of Medford who believed in Bob Penta because I believe in you folks. And with that being said, I want to conclude by saying the following. My friend, Jimmy DeVito, you'll understand this. In 1942, it was General Douglas MacArthur who had to leave the Philippine Islands because at the Battle of Bataan, they got beaten up pretty bad.
And he was supposed to be taking a submarine to leave the islands, because eventually he had to get to Australia. But he decided not to take that. He decided to take a PT boat and go up in the middle of the night to beat the Japanese at that point in time. And unfortunately, they ran into inclement weather on the whole nine yards. So as a result of that, he was one of the two days in the water. He was in open water.
But he was very lucky, because there was no Japanese boat that saw him traversing that water, getting to where he had to go to, in Mindanao. Two days later, when he finally landed there, he made a very famous speech. And when he made that speech, it was in Melbourne, Australia. And this is what he said. This is his declaratory lines. He says, I came through, and I shall return.
I took those lines and he says, how can I make that work for me tonight? So this is what I said. With that said, and with a Penta on the city ballots for the past 38 years, stay tuned. And while there may be a Penta in a pause mode, there will be a Penta to be continued in our days ahead.
I thank you, my family, my friends, and even those folks who don't like me or didn't vote for me, because you know why? You expressed your opinion, and I'm okay with that. And for all those who've supported me in my positions through the years, and may our loving and forgiving God bless all of us, and may God bless us all as he sees fit. Bon attab. Thank you.
I would be absolutely remiss if I didn't say this, because the highest thing on my scale of friendship is loyalty, and I forgot to say it. There's one person, and I will embarrass him, he's right over there, that guy right there, Michael Marks, from the day that I announced. From the day that I announced, no questions asked, he stepped up, came forward,
over and beyond my friends, my new extended family of friends, but for an elected official to put his neck on the line, no questions asked, no wanting for anything, that to me is what it's all about. These are my friends, you are my friends, and God bless you all. Thank you.
Thank you.
Counselor, you wanted to say? You know something? His tie. Listen to his tie. Huh? Listen to your tie. My tie. There. That's it. I would be absolutely remiss. My daughter, Kim. My son-in-law, Patrick. Aaron, my extended daughter. Aaron.
And Ryan. Thank you, Councilor Pinto. That was a very nice send-off, nice speech. You know, I grew up in this city. As you all know, basically the only two mayors that I remember are Mayor Parikh and Mayor McGlynn.
Excuse me. Still a little emotional, you know. During my last 16 years as a member of the city council, you know, I had some of the best times of my life, but also some of the toughest times of my life. You know, a few people upstairs right now looking down that I know are proud of me are my dad, that many of you knew, Al, and my grandmother.
You know, I remember the, uh, the parties, the election night parties at my grandmother's house. And, uh, we had some fun, you know, but, uh, you know, also in 2006, I married my best friend, Janine, you know, Janine, thank you for being there for me because as, um, as Susan knows, and the rest of the spouses of the, uh, counselors, this is a full-time job, you know, and, uh, I, I, I had the, um,
I had the, the word I'm looking for.
I had the vision. I saw that I was spending too much time actually doing this job and not enough time where it actually was important on occasion. And that's at home. Because this job does take a toll upon you and more your loved ones than you. I'd be here fighting with my friend, and I'd be getting calls at my house. You've got good supporters. They'd call and yell at my poor wife.
But you know the stuff that goes along with this job. And for that, I'm forever grateful, honey. You've been there through some of my biggest struggles in life. And you're the best. I love you. Moving ahead a little bit, a couple of years. Next best, well, they're equal.
Best thing in my life is that little guy sitting in row number two. Little Jimmy, stand up. Stand up, buddy. As Bob said, this is what it's all about. It's the family. And I'm really looking forward to just getting grounded again and getting back into some sort of sense of normalcy of not being out on, it's not just Tuesday nights.
It's many a nights and you know the constituent service part, we have people in this room. I'm only as good as the people that have supported me and got me to where I needed to be at first. And a few people that I want to acknowledge from my family is my brother John and my brother Mike.
You know, I was very lucky. I got great in-laws and, and, uh, they do more babysitting for me to get out and to do the constituent stuff. Um, and, and, uh, you know, you're going to get a little more free time on your hands now too, Jeannie and Frank, cause I'll be home a little bit more. So, uh, so thank you for all that you've, uh, done for me and my family, um, over the years and also my brother-in-law Frank. But, um, you know, my original committee, they're mostly here tonight when I decided to run for office in 1999.
I gathered the people that were just closest to me and near and dear. And that's my aunt, my campaign manager, Carol Regan, who's right there. Thank you, auntie. Another person who's well known in this community from Medford Youth Hockey and just a real great person is Len Galeona, who's right here.
Also, someone that is on the DPW, I don't know if he's still here, but Mike Nesta, another original. One of the original guys.
And also my pal, Jason, you know, right from the very beginning. My buddy, Jason Traviglione, he was there right from the beginning with several of my other cousins, Tommy, Terry, Tony, Johnny, Joey, and Artie. You know, we hit the streets. And I'll tell you a funny story. You talk about walking the streets. I'll never forget it. It was one of your neighbors on Summit Road. We're passing out the first literature. Guy calls me over. I like the thing. It looks good. But you spelt commitment wrong. I go.
You've got to be kidding me. So instead of passing out literature, we're running back up the hill trying to take the literature back. And of course, like any good politician, you tell a little fib. I blame the printer, but it was really my fault.
A few City Hall department heads that have really been there for me over the years. That's Roy Belson from the schools, Mark Rumley, who's in the room in the back there, as well as the past president of the Medford City Council, Bob Mayorko. You know, the people that were just very helpful over the years in giving me guidance, and I want to thank them for that. You know, 16 years is a long time. You know, I went back and just was plugging in the years on the computer, because I knew I had to speak tonight.
It seems, uh, it was in 2000. That's when, uh, the big race between Al Gore and George Bush, when we didn't know who the president was. That seems like many, many, many years ago. A few years later or the next year we had September 11th, you know, and, um, there was also the good things. As I was an elected official, I was able to stand here and get my picture taken with the world series trophy, a Patriots trophy, and also a Bruins trophy. You know, that's, uh,
That just tells you how long 16 years is. And 16 years is a long time. I couldn't do it, 38. No, sirree. You know, as far as the councillors, I mentioned Bob Mayorko. Other two councillors that I served with when I first got on, it was Councillor Bill Carr, who Bill was just another good guy, and Councillor Macarena, who I served with for a short period of time. I just want to thank them, because I know how
how this is sometimes on your family life and everything else. So it doesn't go unnoticed, the sacrifice that all the councilors here have made over the years. Michael Marks, you know, when we first started out, Michael Marks and myself, we were close. We were in that first little block of four who made Stephanie Muccini-Burke the president of the Medford City Council. And we drifted apart over the years. But Michael, you're a stalwart. You're a good kid.
You've got a good career ahead of you, and it's been a pleasure to serve with you. And he said he's going to be on that side, so you ain't getting home early. Ricky, what else can I say? As you said, you used to drive us to Austin Prep with Ricky. We'd be driving up to Austin Prep in the morning, and like screwballs, we'd put our hand out the window when it was 30 degrees so we could keep the hand outside the window longer. Just stupid, stupid. But you'd be yelling at us.
I'm freezing in here, you know. But you're just a great, great guy. And your wife, Carol, who certainly is also a big champion behind you.
Fred DelaRusso, when I first ran, I didn't know if I was running for the Medford City Council or running against Fred DelaRusso, you know? Everybody in this city made it a Camuso-DelaRusso race when Freddy first ran for office. I'm sure some of you remember that. And so as Fred stated, it was a rocky start, but you know something, Fred? Me and you became best pals here, you know?
This guy right here, he's there for people in their time of need, but he's also been there for me, uh, as a fellow city councilor. And, uh, and on occasion when I get ramped up, he'd tell me, Hey, calm down. And I'd listen to him sometimes.
Other times there was no stopping the kid. But Fred, you know, I really value our friendship. And I know we're going to be lifelong friends. And your dad also was there for me when I first ran for school committee. And just you come from an outstanding family. And thank you for being my friend. Adam, thank God for that English test.
You know, Adam, uh, Adam and I have been friends for many, many years. You know, Adam was there for me early on in my campaigns. And, uh, I just wish I had more time to serve with you. But, um, as I stated a little earlier, I just, uh, I'm looking forward to a little time off and, um, and having a nine to five, uh, day rather than, um, I will stay up, watch about half the city council meetings, I think. But, uh, but, uh, Adam, you're, you're just a great person.
Councilor Lungo-Kern, you know, went to Medford High School with Councilor Lungo-Kern. And just, you're just a good kid. You also fight, I call them kids. I'm only a year older than that. You're just a great person, you know. And I've watched you over the years become a good councilor, but also a mom of three children.
I find it tough with one child being a councillor. You know, you really are just, you're a stalwart, and you get out, and you really work hard, and I want to thank you for your friendship over the years. Councillor Bob, I've already said it, you're a good guy, and I'm going to miss our fights, because to be honest with you, I'm going to be honest with you, and if he wasn't there and I wasn't there, the meetings would be boring. Fair to say?
You know, a few other people that I'd just like to.
to congratulate and thank is right over here. These two young fellas over here, George Scarpelli and John Falco. I know that Bob and I leave this evening, and we're leaving it in good hands. These are two guys that are coming from the school committee. They understand the complexity of issues, and it's not always a quick, easy fix. As Councilor DelaRusso stated a little earlier, the legislative process sometimes moves a little bit slower than people would like, but at the end of the day,
This city's in good hands with the people coming on. Being that person that just drives the DPW crazy over the years, I saved the best for last. The DPW, people don't realize the work that they do on a daily basis. They're not only dealing with the stuff when they get in in the morning that they have the long list of stuff, but they're dealing with seven city councillors calling them, they're dealing with residents calling them, they're dealing with the mayor's office calling them, they're dealing with just
They stop to get a cup of coffee and people are yelling and screaming, and this and that. You know, people don't realize that the snow plowing, they think that after the DPW plows the snow away from their driveway, that they just come by to get a chuckle and put it back there. It's not. It's to keep the streets clear for emergency vehicles.
It's a job that you do very, very good. And Steve Tanagli is in the back of the room, and he works as well with Mike Nestor and Paul Gere, who's our current commissioner. And thank you guys for meeting my individual needs, because I have always taken this job. You know, the big issues are going to be debated here. It's the one by one is how you build friendships, relationships, and how you build bonds that you'll have forever.
Counselor mocks Carol Bailey who was one of my closest friends over the years. I met her her son is in college now He's ready to graduate and I met her when Michael mocks called me because she had one of those funky streets in West Medford Hercroft Park. It was the year Michael left the school committee
Half of the street went to the Gleason School. If you live right next door, you went to the other school. And through Councilor Marks, I was able to build a bond by helping out Carol and her son remain at the Gleason School or get into the Gleason School. And one by one, that's how you build a good group, a good following behind you. And I just can't say enough about the DPW because they're great. If we can get a hand for those guys because they really are.
The last two people I just want to acknowledge. I've got the wife. You'll laugh, I've got to make sure, because I'll never hear the end of it. The last two people I'd like to acknowledge. There's one other person that's retiring at the end of this year with Councillor Bob and myself, and that's Mayor Mike McGlynn. People seem to think that I've just got this rosy, great relationship with him. People don't realize how much we battle behind the closed doors.
And, you know, and even Councilor Pente, I think you'd say the same about Mike.
You know, you can battle and battle, but he always tried to do what's right for this community. He's been a great mayor. You know what? If he wasn't doing something right, he wouldn't be the mayor overwhelmingly for 28 consecutive years. So when you keep that into perspective, the man is retiring, the man's going to spend more time with his family, but I personally want to thank him for his years of service and the invaluable things he taught me over the years. So Mike McGlynn, good luck in your retirement as well if you're out there watching.
You know, it's sort of like some of those old TV shows. No one watches, but everyone knows what's going on. He still says he never watches it, but I think he's full of it. I think he watches the council meetings, and he just says that, oh, I heard of this or that, but I think he's watching. And if you are watching, Mr. Mayor, you've done a hell of a job. It's been a good ride, and best of luck to you.
The next individual and in the last individual that I just want to recognize this evening, you know There was a race for mayor in this community the first time in 28 years and that's a long time 28 years it was former mayor Parika And then it was mayor Mike McGlynn for 28 years and in the new mayor-elect, you know as I stated
Mayor-elect Burke has been a former member of this Medford City Council. And you know, I hope that I'm saying this, but you know, people say, well, when she went to the mayor's office, she didn't do this or wasn't responsive. And you know what? People got to understand, she worked for another individual. She worked for another individual that called all the shots in that office, you know?
So I really think that this city is in good hands. As Councilor Penta said, there wasn't a mandate. It was a very close election, but the people have spoken. And I think this is the time that we all have to get behind the new administration and work to make Medford a better place. Because you know what? She's in a position now where she can make things happen and not being the director of budget and personnel. And, um, and for that, and last but not least, you know,
During this campaign, I was able to spend a lot of time with her and her family. And I just got to see a side of them that I necessarily didn't over the years. And other than my dad, my dad always loved her as a counselor because she was sharp and she didn't speak all the time on every issue, but she knew the vote she was taking and was very smart. So I relied upon my dad's
thoughts over the years, and Stephanie Burke, you're gonna be a hell of a mayor. I know you got big shoes to fill, but you know what? You surround yourself with good people, be open-minded, and just always doing the right thing, and this community's going to prosper. And for anyone out there that may think differently,
Give her a shot. There's always two years from now, you can take a look or whatever. But I have the utmost faith in knowing her brains, her intelligence, and her compassion. Because in this job as mayor, you know something?
And this is very interesting. I admire the both candidates for mayor, because early on in the race, there were some things that made me ponder and say, I'm glad I didn't run for mayor. And that was when you had to make major personnel decisions based upon actions of people that may have did something within the community. The mayor's office is a job that you're actually the CEO of a community.
You're saying people may not have a job tomorrow based upon some of their actions or based upon circumstances. And so you need to be, you need to have a lot of different characteristics for that job. But Stephanie, I look forward to, and the mayor-elect is here this evening. If you could please just take a bow.
But I just want to thank everyone for being here. And I know she texted me 30 times before, because I had to go get flowers. But I'd like my son and my wife to come up here. And I got little flowers for you, Whole Foods, but Dorico McGlynn was closed.
Thank you. Hey, go ahead, ask the question. What did you just ask? I want you to know what I got him. What's in mine? Two more days. Yeah, two more days. Santa's coming. But on an all serious note, you know what? This has been a hell of a ride. And I just want to thank everyone for coming here this evening.
for me just because this is what it's all about. You know, you look around this room and there's 150 years worth of family and everything else, right James? So God bless everyone and Merry Christmas and good luck to the new city council, the new school committee and the new mayor. Let's move this city in the right direction and I'll be on the sidelines watching.
on the motion for approval by Councilor Knight. One more thing too. One last thing. After I got here and I put the people that helped me get here, it's the citizens of Medford, it's the citizens of Medford that I owe a big thank you to because without them, none of this would have been possible. So thank you Medford and good night.
Meeting is now in recess so we can do our presentations and enjoy two delicious cakes from Arthur's Pastry in South Medford. Thank you.
Meeting will come back to order. Meeting will return to order. Silence in the gallery. 15-818 offered by Councilor Camuso be it resolved that the Memphis City Council commend and congratulate Michael J. McGlynn on his retirement.
On the motion of approval by Councilor Musil, all those in favor? All those opposed? Motion passes. 15-810 offered by Councilor Penta. Be it resolved that the Metro City Council go on record as supporting a city's senior citizen exemption from having to pay to park in our city. Councilor Penta, where are you? There you are. Kind of addressed that too, yeah. You on? As I said earlier this evening in some of my remarks, one of the things that
seems to have been a concern during this past campaign was the parking in the square. But the incoming administration over and beyond the August questionnaire that was sent out and then the commitment that was made during this past campaign and one of the debates indicated that the administration would move for a senior citizen discount with Republic. So I would request that the council go on record to show the support for that as it relates to
that for which had come up as a campaign issue and a commitment made by the incoming administration. On the motion approved by Councilor Penta, Councilor Vice-President Mago-Kern. All set? Yes, I concur. As seconded by Vice-President Mago-Kern, all those in favor? Roll call vote, Mr. President. Roll call vote has been requested. Mr. Clerk, Councilor Knight, if you would.
Earlier this evening, we tabled a paper, a money paper, relative to the use of kiosks. And we're going to investigate that a little bit further in subcommittee. Audit and Budget Finance Subcommittee is going to take a look at whether or not the appropriation from the sale of real estate in the amount of $250,000 be transferred to be used for approvals to the five business districts, Mr. President.
You know, I certainly support an exemption for senior citizens having to pay and park in our city, but I think maybe we can take a look at this in a universal approach as opposed to as one item here, one item there, one item here, one item there. However, I defer to the body. Very good.
Mr. President, I would stick to the resolution. It's a separate itemized issue. It has makes no difference as it relates to what is going to be going forward with Louise Miller or anything else. It's a, it's an item that was used as a campaign issue. It was an item that was voted upon. It was an item that was campaigned on and it was an item committed upon by the incoming administration. So being isolated as it is and following forward with that, Mr. President, I think it would be a good way.
and some good strength to have the incoming administration realize that the City Council supports that resolution. Motion of approval is on before us. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Camuso? Yes. Councilor Cavill? Yes. Councilor Monk? Yes. Vice-President Humlker? Yes. Councilor Marks? Yes. Councilor Packer? Yes. President de la Ruche? No. The vote is six in the affirmative, one in the negative. Motion passes.
15-811 offered by Councilor Penta be it resolved that many businesses and individuals who continuously and generously support and donate to all charities and people in need within our city be publicly acknowledged with a big thank you for their unselfish contributions. They truly helped to make without any public recognition.
the Christmas season and at all times of the year, a better day for those in need. Chair recognizes Councilor Pinto. Mr. President, unfortunately at this time of the year, individuals, some individuals get recognized for whatever their contributions might be, but there is a whole host of community folks, businesses,
and individuals who contribute all during the year for the purposes of helping those who are in need. For example, you have one of the banks in the square, without mentioning them, has an annual thing for Toys for Tots. You have the Meffitt Fire Department, who has an ongoing Christmas season situation. But you have individual people who are philanthropic unto their own right, and they don't want any recognition at all, they just do it.
So, it doesn't make any difference whether you're a private business, a union, an individual, whatever it might be. These people, to some degree, if they're watching, should know that their contributions are recognized and appreciated, and as a result of that, it's our little way of saying thank you to them for being supportive for people in need when not asked to do so.
Thank you very much, Councilor. On the motion approved by Councilor Penter, all those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries. 15-812 offered by Councilor Penter, be it resolved that the recent Comcast cable bill be discussed. Did we just discuss this? No, it happened to come up in conversation, but the fact of the matter is in this recent monthly December bill,
from Comcast, it'll show that it's going from $3.25 to $5. Now that's an increase of $1.75 a month. The city is presently sitting on over $450,000 of PEG access money, cable access monies, and as a result of that, still having no public access television here in the city of Meffitt. And the city's use of those monies to pay for salaries up at the high school. I think it's incumbent upon the incoming city council to make a demand
from the incoming administration, whether, in fact, they are going to have cable, public access, TV3, whatever it might be. And there might be a twist to that, because I think if we have all been watching what's on the news lately, there's a movement afoot between Channel 7 to possibly take over, that for which Comcast has right now, which is Nessun, and I forget the other one, and WHCH.
And with that being said, there is a possibility, if in fact this merger were to go through, and I think it would be the second highest, a multi-billion dollar merger, what could possibly happen as a movement, because if NBC does buy out the franchise, Anson, that they're looking to buy out, they could possibly retrieve the cable location of TV3 that we presently have.
and put it in a different spot. That's okay, too. But in the contract, on page five, it says the following, PEG's access channels, any licensee-owned channels made available by the licensee in the situation as Comcast and provided for use for the presentations of PEG access programming. So if, in fact, if you read the contract and if you follow what's going on in the news, that if, in fact, this were to take place, there's a possibility of one or two things that ANSEN, WHCH,
could probably be bought out by NBC, and so wouldn't be Channel 6. It's a side issue as it relates to the main subject matter, which is public access television, but I really think you two guys coming on as new councilors, you really have to understand that if we're going to allow public access here in the city of Memphis, it needs to be worked on. And now, having a $1.75 increase per month on a cable access bill that people would be paying each and every month, that's approximately $60 a year,
That's a lot of money to people, you know, you take that it's another $60 and the Community Preservation Act It's another minimum of $165 as a rate increase. It's another 7% that's going to be taking place on your water and sewer tax bills coming out So it is going to have an effect and I I would suggest mr. President this Medford City Council go into some kind of remedial
a discussion as it relates to, you know, what's going on, not only with the rate increase, but, you know, how and why the city can collect this money, charge up to $5, and still not allow cable access television to go forward. You may want to bring the city solicitor on board on this one here to find out if, in fact, with the great increase, can they still allow, can they still continue to allow not having public access, whether it be on Channel 3 or any other channel.
Thank you on the motion for approval, but I can put down a roll call vote so that we're there. It's forwarded to the city solicitor, let him review it for the new city council and be further amended that the matter be sent to the city solicitor regarding the increase in the rate of, uh, uh, uh, yeah, they can do that. The line item in the cable bills allocated towards, uh, uh, community access.
there was a rate increase and what recourse the city has to end that and or what obligation we have to provide the service that people are paying for.
There's a value also there, too, Mr. President, of I think it's $454 or $455 million is if WHTH goes off the year, which is sort of like a sweet pot of the deal to make this thing more attractive. But I think the city needs to get itself involved, especially because of public access. I wouldn't dare to recommend, but if you'd indulge me to suggest that this also be further amended to make this a priority of attention for the next administration.
So that's a amendment by Councilor Pinto. Roll call vote has been requested, Mr. Clerk, at your discretion. Chair recognizes Councilor Marks. Thank you, Mr. President. And, uh, it's a resolution that I offered back, I think two or three times now before the council back over the last, uh, 10 years is that, uh, there was a special home rule petition filed by this council that allowed, uh, us, uh, the city to take 5%
of the cable money go up to five percent. And that was a special vote of this council. And I've offered resolutions in the past for us to do away with that home rule petition because clearly we're not getting any response from the administration regarding this peg money and the lack of having public access in the community while we still accept funds from the ratepayers. And you know in my opinion if the administration who's the
uh, authority on signing the contract is unwilling, uh, to discuss this issue that maybe we as the legislative body should, uh, file legislation to do away with the act. Uh, I have the act of my desk somewhere. Uh, I believe it was the act of 1980 or 83, uh, that created, uh, this, uh, uh, special vote of the council to allow it to take up to 5%. It went to 5%. Right.
which is a lion's share of the money for cable access, Mr. President. So, I'm not adverse to going that angle if we're unable. Maybe with the new administration, there'll be more cooperation. So, we've got to be resolved one way or another. Right. Because it's unjust what we're doing to the people. Well, it's two years worth of unjust, and I'm not sure how much longer we want to wait. Thank you. Thank you. Mr. Citizen, please state your name and address for the record.
Thank you, Mr. President. I'm Rob Capucci, 71 Evans Street in Medford. Just really brief.
We need the community access station for so many different things. It could help, you know, advertisements for the, for the five business districts for the arts and stuff going on, uh, Medford sports, things like that. Uh, also politically speaking, we got a huge election year next year with state Senate and, uh, state house rep races. Uh, the presidential primary is on March 1st. You got a number of state committee,
keep members up for election running from here from Medford, Medford candidates. I just want to make that statement. I mean, all the other things, too, that community access provides on, you know, how-to shows and things like that. We really need to have it in the city. But my question to this body, Mr. President, through the chair is, as Councilor Penta mentioned,
$450,000, that's almost a half a million dollars. What happens to this money? Do you know? Is it put in a bank account? Is it getting interest? Is some of it paid out for some things? I'm just unsure as to what happens to almost a half a million dollars. Thank you, Mr. President. Thank you, sir. It was a rhetorical question. On the motion of approval by Council Penta. It was a real question. It wasn't rhetorical.
The first answer is that the $450,000 that's sitting there is that's for the PEG access money. So if, in fact, we had a public access studio, that money would go there. That only represents 2 percent. That's 3 percent. The other 2 percent goes into the general fund, and that money is being paid for employees up at the high school, which is a real question mark because there are some questions as to whether that's even legal or not. So 1 percent goes to the fire, 1 percent to the police, and 1 percent goes to public access. That's the PEG money.
Thank you, counsel. Thank you, Mr. President. Thank you, Mr. Citizen. Good evening. Please state your name and address for the record, sir. Yes. Council President Joseph Villalon, 59 Garfield Avenue.
I'm going to look at my Verizon bill, because I wasn't aware of this raise in the Comcast bill. So I will look at the Verizon as well. And also, I have a separate issue coming up I'd like to table, Council President. It's separate from what Mr. Pinto was, Councilor Pinto was talking about. I'd like to table it and bring it up for the first meeting of the year. It's about Comcast and these channels. So if I may do that.
I'd like to table the petition I have coming up. Thank you. I'll take that as a request to withdraw the petition. Petition 15-814 at request of petitioner at the rail is withdrawn. On the motion of approval by Councilor Penta, roll call vote has been requested. Mr. Clerk, if you would please call the roll.
Councilor Camuso? Yes. Councilor Caviello? Yes. Councilor Knight? Yes. Vice President Longo Kern? Yes. Councilor Martins? Yes. Councilor Penta? Yes. President De La Rosa? Yes. With a vote of seven in affirmative, none in the negative, the motion passes. 15-813 offered by Councilor Penta, be it resolved that the superintendent of schools report back as to what budget areas in what dollar amount has the school department saved money so far this year
as he was referred to a most recent news story article. Counselor Penta. I'm sorry. I'm getting there. All right. Mr. President, most recently in a newspaper story published by the local press on December 17th, superintendent Belson was quoted as saying that the district has saved money in multiple areas. So far this year, he said, it is also possible that the position will be filled by an employee who already works for this city.
The position he's making reference to is the new public relations potential position that the school department is now being considering. But I'm more concerned about his first line basically saying the district has saved money in multiple areas so far this year. I think it would be important for the school committee as well as the city council to get a review back as to just what are those multiple areas. Also, I would just like to conclude by saying the following, whether it be this or anything else.
We have asked for numerous occasions, and the council in the past has voted for it. It's never taken place. So maybe this new school administration will take place. But at a minimum, the city council and the school committee should meet at least twice a year for the purposes of reviewing their financial wherewithals. Because this is kind of like a little bit disturbing, that if, in fact, we have money in multiple areas, when you have teachers there that are begging in time for school supplies, we're looking for special ed teachers, we're looking for teacher assistants in some of the schools,
And we're having all kinds of areas here, and whether you're for or against hiring a person at $85,000 a year to be a public relations person.
I think the first thing that needs to be considered is the teacher in the classroom, the needs of the teacher in the classroom, and the students that they have to take care of. So I think Mr. Belson owes it to the entire community of Medford, the PTOs, the PTAs, and everything else involved, that if you have multiple areas for which the school committee should be apprised of, and if they were doing their homework, they would know where these areas and how much money there is. That would demand a report back to the city council.
So I would move, Mr. President, on a roll call vote to the superintendent report back into what areas that money's coming from. And if it's not going to affect those areas that the money's coming out of, then what's the purpose of taking the money out? Why aren't you using that money to fill the positions in that area? Thank you. Chair recognizes the Vice President. Thank you. Thank you, President De La Russo. I agree. I'd like to see where the savings was.
Also, if I could amend Councilor Penta just to ask some information with regards to the mayor's discretionary funding. I think it's a fund, it's labeled mayor's discretionary funding of school projects. I know $95,000 was taken out of that fund two weeks ago and just looking to see what the remaining balance is with regards to that discretionary fund and possibly what else has been taken out of that fund in the last two years.
So I just want to see what the remaining balance is. Because I know a number of things were voted on with regards to improvements in the schools. But within the last couple of weeks, since the council did speak out with regards to the new PR job that was implemented, I've received numerous calls and emails with regards to just lack of ink and printers, the state of the books at the high school, no raises for kindergarten aides,
Teachers getting barely no money for school supplies, lack of art supplies, security, lack of security, custodial services, toilet paper at the high school, aids in the classroom, teachers not getting reimbursed for flood damage. There's just emails and people just want to stop and talk about the new position do keep coming in. So I would like to know what this discretionary funds for, how much is remaining in it, and
Any information we can get on it would be very helpful. Mr. President. Thank you, Madam Vice President. So on the President's motion of Councilor Camuso, Penta, as amended by Vice President Lagarde, Chair recognizes Councilor Camuso. Just one question. We say there was a flood. If so, what teachers were not reimbursed and where was this flood? In a flood at the Roberts and a flood at the McGlynn over the last two years. In specific. Do the teachers have not been reimbursed for their own personal money putting out there? Correct.
Well, we should want to look into this. Can the council at least give us the names after so we can get the superintendent to look at this as soon as possible? Sure. You don't want to say it on the floor, though, because obviously you don't want to throw the teachers out there. How many teachers in total on this? I know three that had damage. And when was this flood recently? One was six months ago, and one was a year, 14 months ago.
The better question, too, is, I think, how is the building flooding? Pipes. I think the pipes are breaking. Yeah, if we could get the teachers' names and find out where the reimbursement is and for what type of things they're looking to get reimbursed on. Because obviously, if they're coming out of pocket for this stuff as a result of a maintenance issue, that's a problem. Thank you, Counselor. As amended by Counselor Camuso,
Chair recognizes the citizen at the podium. Please state your name and address for the record. Thank you. Uh, Jean Martin 10 coming street. Um, in the name of transparency, every single dollar that is extra that the superintendent of schools finds is should be open to scrutiny to our visibility. We should know that that money is there as a public. That's our money. That's not his money. That's not the mayor's money. That's our money.
So we should know about that. And there are two points, two different areas that you recognize. And the first being transparency. And what are they going to do with that money that they've saved? Are they going to put it into maintenance? Are they going to put it into ink supplies? What are they going to do with the extra money that they've saved? Secondly, the more important piece,
is this is not $85,000 once, this is $85,000 a year for a salesman, a salesperson, to sell the concept of the schools. Think about that, ladies and gentlemen. It's a salesman. That's a high class word for, PR is a high class person. That could be a teacher in a classroom, that could be a cop, that could be a DPW worker. That's $85,000 a year.
That is a whole person on the ground. We have, no offense, but we have too many supervisors and we don't have enough, you know, privates. We need workers. And $85,000, it's not once, it's every single year. And personally, I think that it's a little bit of finagle the bagel behind closed doors too.
But I don't want to bring out the dirty laundry. There's no need. I do want to say that that's one full salary for a cop, a firefighter, a DPW worker, or a teacher. You want to put that towards a regular teacher, classroom teacher, then take the $85,000 and put it towards a teacher. There's no reason why we need somebody to sell the concept of schools. And also bringing up Mr. Carviello's
pet peeve with the maintenance. The reason why they were flooded is because we're not putting that $85,000 a year towards fixing those pipes. We need a maintenance schedule for all the buildings. And that's much bigger than $85,000 a year. So I will give you that, but it is a full scale salary for an employee for the city. Thank you. A motion for approval by council Penta as amended motion to set. Did you want to speak ma'am?
Please state your name and address for the record. Mr. Messenger, would you assist with the microphone?
Jeanette, but I can't give you my address over the television. It's not safe for me, so I can tell the gentleman afterwards. I don't know how many people here at the table have been educators, but I have and am an educator in special education. And I would say that while I appreciate the desire to look at the
news article that was, you know, currently published about a position being created for somebody in the public school system. This is the first time that I've heard the schools being brought up at this meeting, and I think that what's more important than this one position, which clearly, if Medford public schools are not being adequately taken care of, they need a public relations person.
Clearly they need somebody who can answer the phone calls because there's been a flood and a bunch of people haven't been, their classrooms haven't been taken care of. I can see why they would want that position. That salary would not go to one teacher. If it is a salary, it would go to two because teachers aren't paid that much. And as far as reimbursement for materials during a flood, teachers are never reimbursed, are very rarely reimbursed.
for the money they spend on classroom materials. I would love, and this came up a little bit during the mayoral debates, but not much, I would love to see city council more involved in the new year, in the new administration, with the school board. Budgets for the school really don't go before city council, they go before the school board. That's how that works, that's why we elect a school board. And this position itself,
should have gone before the school board, not city council. That's generally how the handling of schools in a public district work. So while it's appreciable to bring up a hot-button news topic about a salary for somebody, I would like to see city councilmen and women talk about more
How to support the districts and how to support the school committee. Because I think that clearly is the bigger issue here. Thank you. Thank you. So on the motion for, you requested to sever the amendments. So the severed amendments are requests by Councilor Camuso.
why the teachers, and the circumstances of the flooding. And yours was, Madam Vice President, if you could remind me. The balance of the discretionary fund. The balance of the discretionary fund. So we're gonna sever those, so we take, so the two separate, you're moving to have the two amendments voted on separately from the main motion? Okay, so on, a roll call is requested on the separate amendments,
So we'll take Councilor Camuso's amendment first. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Mr. President, just if I can clarify. Point of clarification. If I'm not mistaken, I think Councilor Longo mentioned the account, the discretionary account, and also you wanted to see for the past two years. What's been spent. What's been spent. So there's two parts to that. Yes. And then my amendment too. Right. So we're separating all three. So the first one.
Right. So the, uh, second amendment by councilor Camuso. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Camuso? Yes. Councilor Cavielli? Yes. Councilor Knight? No. Vice President Malauulu-Kern? Yes. Councilor Mock? Yes. Councilor Prenta? Yes. President Dela Ruzzo? Yes. The vote of six in the affirmative, one in the negative. The amendment passes. First amendment offered by,
Vice President Lago-Kern. Mr. Clerk. Before the roll is called, Councilor Camuso. I'd just like to explain my next vote before it's called. I'm going to support the amendment on the discretionary funding, but on the main motion, I believe that's a school committee issue. The money was appropriated as an aggregate amount for the Medford school committee to spend under their wise, um, um,
vote or not so wise vote, whatever it was, but it was a budget that was passed in June. So, uh, I'm going to leave this as a school committee may issue similar to what the young lady stated. So I will be voting no on that, but the discretionary funding I'm going to vote yes on because that's a funding that we have not seen at any point where the mayor it's mitigation or from his golf tournament or it's from some other funding source. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Councilor Camuccio? Yes. Councilor Kaviarz? Yes. Councilor Naik? Yes. Vice-President Walker? Yes. Councilor Matz? Yes. Councilor Penta? Yes. President De La Rosa? Yes. With a vote of seven in the affirmative, none in the negative, the motion passes. The amendment passes. And finally, to the main motion of Councilor Penta, 15.813. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Councilor Camuso? No. Councilor Cavielles? Yes. What was that? Yes. Yes. Yes. Councilor Night? No. Vice-President Landau-Curran? Yes. Councilor Matz? Yes. Councilor Panka? Yes. President Dela Cruz? Yes. With a vote of six in the affirmative, one negative. Five, five, five. Oh, I apologize. I have a map challenge. Five, two, motion passes.
Petitions, presentations, and similar matters. 15-815 petition by Joseph Viglione, 59 Garfield Avenue, Medford. Comcast has been withdrawn. 15-815 petition by Joseph Viglione.
59 Garfield Avenue, Medford Mass, for vetting of the Muccini-Burke transition team. Counselors, Mr. Petitioner, I find this as a matter not pertinent to the Medford City Council. The transition team is not a government-appointed body. It's not a matter for consideration of the Medford City Council, so I find this matter out of order.
We're going to declare this out of order. I rule it out of order. I've made a ruling. It's out of order. It's out of order, sir. Thank you. Thank you, sir. The chair has been challenged. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Yes vote will be to support the chair's ruling Yes for in the affirmative three in the negative the ruling stands I
Resolved that the Medford City Council send its congratulations to former Medford High School graduate and resident Jonathan Gleona on recently being named the most accurate Wall Street analyst by Bloomberg News. Counselor Camuso. Another great successful Medford High School graduate story. If we could send him a letter of congratulations on behalf of this honorable body. On the motion of Counselor Camuso for approval. All those in favor. All those opposed.
15-819 offered by councillors Caviello and Penta be it resolved that the Medford City Council commended congratulate Metro police officers Sheila Quinn and Paul Giordano for the heroic efforts rescuing infant twins and their mother and dog from a house fire on Main Street councillors Penta and Caraviello Thank You mr. President
Uh, I want to congratulate these, uh, these two offices, uh, while all of the fire department was busy fighting another fire over on the other side of town. Uh, these two officers were the first to respond this fire on main street and, um, doing what comes naturally to them and their heroic efforts. They would, they went into the building, rescued those two children and helped the mother and the dog get off of safety. And, uh, I don't know what to say. Uh,
you know, about these two fine people. They do what they do best, and thank you to them for their fine service. And, Mr. President, if we could have them come down after the first of the year, maybe a commendation with the family that they rescued would be appreciated.
Thank you very much.
And the folks were very appreciative of the fact. And as a result of that, I think we're all appreciative of the fact. And it would be nice to have the chief of police down here to also make public commendation recommendations as it relates to their activity. So on that, I move, Mr. President. I'd like to be invited when they come down for that one, okay? To great police officers, great representatives of the Metro Police Department.
On motion for approval by Councilor Caviello, seconded by Councilor Cuso, Councilor Penta. All those in favor. Congratulations to them both. 15-821 offered by Councilor Caviello, be it resolved that the Medford City Council commend and congratulate Dominic Camara on his recent retirement from the Water Commission after nine years and as its most recent chairman.
Thank you, Mr. President. Again, I want to thank Mr. Kamara for his nine years of diligent work as the water commissioner chairman. I mean, that was a thankless job, and he worked hours upon hours upon that with the rest of his committee members. And again, I wish him well in his retirement, and hopefully, maybe the new administration may be able to bring him back out of retirement to come back on the commission.
I was hoping he'd come here tonight and sing with the chorale that was here, but unfortunately he couldn't make it. So on motion of approval by Councilor Caraviello, all those, did you want to speak? Councilor, I apologize. Mr. President, thank you very much. I just wanted to take a brief moment to thank Mr. Kamara for his service to the city of Medford, not only as a member of the Water Commission, but also as a school teacher. I think many of us behind the rail that graduated from Medford High had the opportunity to
I learned a lot from Mr. Camara, and when I became a member of this council, Mr. President, I certainly learned a lot from Mr. Camara relative to how a water and sewer operations work. So I would like to congratulate Councilor Caviello for putting this resolution on and commend Mr. Camara for his service to the city of Medford. Very good. And thank you, Councilor Knight. And Chair recognizes Councilor Marks. Thank you, Mr. President. And I do want to thank Councilor Caviello.
Mr. Kamara served with distinction for a number of years on a very tough commission in this community. And, you know, people don't know this, but when Dominick first came on the Water and Sewer Commission, the water system was in terrible disarray. It was in budget deficit, millions of dollars in budget deficit for years. The city underwent its largest remetering program when we changed all the water meters throughout the whole city.
which was a giant project that Dominic was the chairman of. Also, the tiered system that took place recently and the second water meter outside was under his tutelage as chairman. And the abatements. I can remember the days going back five, six, seven, eight years ago where there was a laundry list of people that were looking for abatements because their water and sewer bill wasn't accurate because of outdated and old meters and so forth.
And it was under the leadership of Mr. Kamara that the Water and Sewer Department really turned about. And now we're experiencing multimillion dollars in surpluses and very few abatements because of a system that's functioning properly. And I want to thank him for his nine years of service, Mr. President, on a very difficult committee. And I look forward to seeing him around the community.
Very good. So on the motion for approval by uh, councilor calf yellow, all those in Oh, councilor Camuso, did you want to speak? Yes. I apologize. This will probably be my last speech at the city council, but who knows? Who knows? We get a few minutes left. Certainly this is a good one to end on as a method. City council, Dom Camara is just a gentleman and um, served the citizens of Medford as a school teacher.
with dignity over the years. And rather than retire, he took on another role post-retirement. So I want to wish him well and thank him for his years of service as a commissioner. As Councilor Mark stated, it's a job that you go into the meeting and you get yelled at and this and that. It's a thankless job, but a lot of work went into it. Very good. So a motion to approve by Councilor Caviello. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries.
Finally, offered by Councilor Camuso, 15-820, be it resolved that the Memphis City Council sends its sincere condolences to the family of Phyllis Makowski, who passed away recently. Mrs. Makowski is the mother of Memphis Police Department Detective Paul Makowski. Please join me and stand for a moment of silence for Mrs. Makowski.
the tabled records of the meeting of December 8th, 2015, the Feast of the Magical Conception, will pass to Councilor Marks. Mr. Sprooks, did you have the opportunity to inspect those records? I had ample opportunity to review the records and found it to be in order to move approval. Very good. So on the motion of Councilor Marks to approve those records, all those in favor? All those opposed? Motion passes. The records of the meeting of December 15th, 2015 will pass to Councilor Knight.
Counselor, how do you find those records? I had an opportunity to review the records and I find them in order. Move for approval. On the motion of approval for those records of the meeting of September 15th by Counselor Knight, all those in favor? All those opposed? I have it.
The ayes have it, the records are approved. Before we adjourn, there's a citizen at the podium who wishes to bid us Christmas greetings. Thank you. Please state your name and address for the record. You must be psychic, Counselor De La Russo. Andrew Castaneda, Cushman Street, Medford, Massachusetts. I'm sorry I'm late. I had to go to awake my brother-in-law. So I wanted to say goodbye to some of these counselors and mayors
And I apologize again, but I see Mr. Camuso's, Councilor Camuso. He's not here, but I jokingly used to call him Mayor Curley, and I think he's done a great job. He's done quite well for himself. And if I may say, I believe he's a definite overachiever. I congratulate him and wish him well in his future endeavors, as I wish everyone well. It's a wonderful life.
Also, I'd be remiss not to mention a fond farewell to the outgoing mayor, Michael, for he did do a lot of good things for our city of Medford on the Mystic River. And third, Councilor Penta of 30-something plus years. Six? Wow. I never ever heard any politician
seem to care for the people as you. And we thank you for your many amendments. Thank you, Counselor. And we thank you, Counselor Panther, for your many amendments that alleviated some of our tax increases.
And although I never received any yes votes in my quest to lower our real estate taxes, we always knew where you stood on all issues. On many occasions here at the public forum, it's been stated that we counselors have no power under this plan A government.
With that being said, maybe it's high time for you, Mr. Robert M. Penta, to join us, we the people, on this side of the rail and hopefully achieve your greatest accomplishments for the people and make Method great again. Thank you. I'll strike that.
Let's all work together with the new mayor and 57,000 population in Medford and make it a great year and to all a good night. Merry Christmas. Merry Christmas. Thank you. Merry Christmas. On the motion of Councilor Penta to adjourn. All those in favor. Meeting's adjourned.