Memphis City Council, 13th regular meeting, Memphis, Massachusetts. Clerk, please call the roll. President Camuso, Councilor DelaRusso? Present. Councilor Night? Present. Councilor McCurran? Present. Councilor Moniz? Present. Councilor Panza? Present. Vice President Caviano? Present. Please rise and salute the flag.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America, and to the republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all. 14697, offered by Councilor Knight, be it resolved that the Memphis City Council extend its sincere congratulations and praise to Anthony Petrellis on being named the Milliken Educator Award recipient.
be it further resolved, whereas Mr. Petrales is one of only 40 recipients nationwide, and the only Massachusetts-based educator to receive this distinguished award, the Memphis City Council presents Mr. Petrales with a congratulatory citation commemorating this remarkable achievement. Councilor Knight. Thank you very much, Mr. President.
It's with great pleasure that I bring this resolution forward this evening. Anthony Petrellis is someone who I consider a friend, and when I learned of this momentous achievement being bestowed upon him, I was very pleased, elated to say the least, Mr. President. Today, Mr. Petrellis is in the audience, and he's also accompanied by a number of his colleagues that know what a great job he does, and I think had something to do with nominating him for this award.
With that being said, Mr. President, I'd like to give Ms. Carino an opportunity to come up here and speak. She's the principal at the McGlynn Middle School, to talk about Anthony's character and why this award is so fitting. Name and address of the record, please.
Diane Greeno, Principal, McGlynn Elementary School. Good evening. What an honor for the school and the city. Congratulations, Mr. P. Anthony Petralas clearly understands the developmental age of his students as evidenced by his close attention to confidence-building activities. Creating a safe environment is clearly one of Mr. P.'s many strengths. His students work hard to make him proud.
and he combines the proper amount of direct instruction, student-focused activities, and cooperative learning. He is aware of his students' individual abilities and addresses areas of weakness and provides additional attention and support.
Maintaining positive teacher-student relationships, Anthony goes above and beyond to know both his students academically and as human beings. He possesses the ability to move students into their comfort zones and helps them develop confidence. He connects with the most troubled students and he helps them feel important and safe. Anthony is a member of the teacher assistant team, school council,
He coaches grade five basketball, he tutors, and he attends every event at the McGlynn Elementary School. During the summer, he is the director of the Summer Fund Program at the Columbus School. He emerges as a role model and is respected by both students and colleagues. It is a privilege to have Anthony as part of the McGlynn family. Anthony, you have put us on the map. We truly are the best school in the city. Thank you. Thank you.
It's a bit dark, should we come up here?
Anthony, congratulations. On behalf of the Medford City Council, Anthony, it's my privilege to present you with this citation, which reads, the Medford City Council takes pleasure in awarding this council commendation to Anthony Petrellis. Whereas Anthony Petrellis has been named the 2014 Millikan Educator Award recipient, and whereas the Millikan Educator Award is a national accolade awarded to only 40 educators nationwide annually.
And whereas Anthony Petrellis is the sole educator from the state of Massachusetts to be bestowed this great honor, and where Anthony has shown an untiring commitment to the educational excellence on behalf of the city of Medford and the Medford public schools, it is with great pleasure we extend this heartfelt thank you. Wow, I've seen these meetings on TV. I never thought I'd be on this side of the table.
I just want to thank everybody for coming. There's a lot of great teachers here that I've learned a lot from. And I appreciate it very much that I've taken a little bit from everybody and helped teach the kids at Medford and win a nice award like this. But I owe it to my school. I owe it to the teachers. I owe it to my family and friends and everybody who's around me that's helped shape me to who I am. So thank you for everybody being here and everything else.
We're going to take a quick recess, take a couple of pictures with the recipients.
Councillor O'Karn. Thank you. While we have Anthony here, I just want to first say I've known the Petrello's family for a very long time.
I've seen Anthony Petrellis at work, and what he does is amazing. Proud to have him as the summer instructor at the Columbus camp, and proud to have him as a teacher. And I just want to share this one story, because the city's abuzz about Anthony Petrellis the last week. I believe it came from my mother, who speaks very highly of Anthony. And she said that once you won the award, you must have been in the large auditorium with a bunch of teachers and students.
And somebody came up to, you know, maybe to Diane or the principal, or I'm not sure who it was, and said, where's this Anthony Petrellis? I don't see him anywhere. And somebody said, well, there he is down on the floor with the kids, like, actively participating and, you know, helping them learn. And I just thought that was an amazing story. So it just shows, you know, what type of teacher he is. He goes above and beyond the call of duty. And that's obvious from the award that was won, which I believe was only
one of 25 in the nation, so I just personally want to congratulate Anthony and his family, and all the teachers and principal at the McGlynn. Thank you. All right. 14706, offered by Vice President Caravaglio, be it resolved that the Memphis City Council present a citation to commend and congratulate Bruno Bonacorsi on his recent achievement award for his 32 years of employment with Project Triangle.
Councilor Caravelle, thank you. For those who don't know, October is National Disability Employment and Awareness Month, which is a national campaign to raise awareness about disability issues and celebrate the many and varied contributions of America's workers with disability. This year's theme is Expect, Employ, and Empower. In 1945, Congress enacted a law declaring the first week in October each year to be the National
Employee to Physically Handicapped Week. However, in 1962, the word physically was removed to acknowledge the employment needs and contributions of individuals with all types of disability. In 1988, CARMS expanded the week to a month and changed the name to National Disability Employment Awareness Month. This evening, we would like to recognize, commend and congratulate Bruno Bonacorsi
on his recent achievement award for 32 years of employment with Triangle in Baltimore. Triangle was founded in 1971 by individuals who believed that people with disabilities could learn and lead more independent and dignified lives. It began serving five people with developmental needs and grew over the next decade to an employment training program for over 80 individuals. Today, Triangle serves over 3,000 people in our area.
Bruno, who is now 58 years old, and his family are lifelong residents of Medford. There aren't many in Medford who don't know Bruno, either from being on the sidelines of Mustang football games, baseball fields, St. Clement Church on Saturday, where he presents the gifts to priests, or various city events. After leaving Lincoln Junior High School, Bruno started his working career at the Hagner Center in Medford, and then moved on to
Triangle center upon the Hegner center's closing. Bruno is the model of what Triangle teaches. He never misses a day of work. And it is truly part of his daily routine. Anyone driving by 226 Main Street at 7 o'clock in the morning will see this young man standing at the door with his lunch bag in his hand waiting for the van to pick him up to go to work. And God forbid the van is late. His job is his life.
Every week, he probably brings home his paycheck and gives it to his mother. Bruno doesn't make much money, but he has learned to become a proud and productive member of our society. He would work seven days a week if possible. Everyone in this country should have his work ethic. No one can really understand the obstacles that the families of people with disabilities like Bruno go through every day unless they are part of your family like Bruno was part of mine.
is the exact meaning of what National Disability Employment Awareness Month is all about. If I could ask Bruno and his mother to come up here.
The Memphis City Council takes pleasure in awarding this council accommodation to Bruno Bonacorsi in recognition of Bruno's recent achievement award for his 32 years of employment with Project Triangle. Thank you.
Is that better than the one the other one gave you?
You're going to say salami?
Thank you, Bruno.
That's all on the calendar. If you want to bring that up, you can. Okay. Nicole, right? Councillor Longo Kern. I'm not sure of his name. I can't stop. Nicole and Steve. Nicole and Steve. Steve. Just while we have Councillor Caviello's daughter in the audience, she's just recently engaged, so we want to congratulate her, Nicole and Steve.
Good luck with the wedding planning and hope you, yeah, many years together. Are we getting that $21,000 raise like Boston guys? 14-698 offered by Councilor Penta. Be it resolved that the council commendation be sent to Frederick Lasky, executive director of the MWIRA.
for receiving the Norman B. Leventhal Excellence in City Building Award. Fred was honored with the Environmental Award recipient for his water protection leadership at the MWRA. This award also acknowledges Fred's dedication toward our region's environment while providing clean drinking water to communities throughout eastern Massachusetts. Councilor Pentec. Well, this is very unusual to have at a Memphis City Council meeting, three acknowledgments in a row. This is like a triple play.
This is all good news. And what's going on in the world, in the city, in the town, in the states today, it's nice to have recognition for folks who really deserve it. We all know Fred. If you don't know Fred, former member of our Medford School Committee, family man. But as the executive director of the MWRA, he's the guy, unfortunately, that when you get your water bill, you think it's kind of high. It's not from him. He only sells it to us wholesale. So it's what the city charges after the fact.
The award that Fred received is kind of like unique. He received it from a company called ABC. And they're an independent membership-based organization here in the Commonwealth of Massachusetts. And what they do is they advance significant transportation development and environmental policies. And Fred, for many years, as you know, or if you don't know, has been the executive director of the MWRA. And by being there, he has brought forward many innovative and environmental-friendly
management techniques as well as work techniques that have just really advanced the MWRA to be a very sophisticated, technological, and water-environmental friendly organization. That's basically what the award was that Fred received because of his environmental participation. And as a result of that, and knowing that his wife Donna is in the audience tonight, and once again, a teacher and a supporter of Mr. Petralas,
It's just a family ongoing thing. Um, their community driven spirit is here in the city of Medford. And I think it's great that we're acknowledging three method individuals tonight. Now it's Fred Lasky's turn. And I would just like to say thank you to Mr. Lasky, uh, for doing the job, um, that a lot of people probably would not want to have, but at the same time being recognized for it. Um, because this award, uh, is a very prestigious award. It's only in its fourth year of operation.
And Fred is the fourth person to get this environmental award. So with that being said, Mr. President, I'd like to forward the commendation to Mr. Lasky. And if he wishes, he could come before the council at a future date to receive it. But I didn't want any more time to go by without the acknowledgement being recognized. Thank you, Councilor Penta. Councilor Marks. Thank you, Mr. President. And I want to thank Councilor Penta for offering this resolution.
He mentioned that Mr. Lasky has done yeoman's work in regards to green initiatives with the MWRA. And also, Mr. President, a little-known fact that while under the leadership of Mr. Lasky, the Water Authority has grown into an establishment that provides safe drinking water to many thousands of residents of this commonwealth.
And in addition to that, Mr. President, another little-known fact is the fact that it costs — and consumers probably wouldn't realize this, but it costs roughly one cent to get a clean gallon of drinking water to your home. And that's through the hard dedication and leadership through Mr. Lasky and the whole MWRA over the years, Mr. President. And I personally want to thank Fred. I've known him for a number of years.
As Councilor Penta mentioned, he's a great family man, and he really does a service to not only this community, but everyone in the Commonwealth by his leadership at the MWRA, Mr. President. Thank you, Councilor Marks. Anyone else? Okay, Mr. Clerk, did we get that? Thank you. Suspension has been asked for by Councilor Layton for a brief announcement.
Counselor Knight. Thank you very much, Mr. President. I'd like to offer the floor to Ms. Kathy Young here. Kathy is a volunteer with our Office of the Environment and Energy, and she'd like to make a brief announcement about this weekend's festival. Name and address of the record, please.
Catherine Young, 64 Medford Street. I want to thank the Council for the opportunity to speak and also for Councilman Knight for the invitation to mention the Harvester Energy Festival. It's happening this Saturday, October 18th from 11 a.m. to 2 p.m. I'd also like to thank Alicia Hunt for her significant amount of work to make that happen.
The Energy Committee supports that, but she put a lot of work into that, so I want to recognize that also. So it's the fifth annual Harvester Energy Festival. It's going to be held at Riverbend Park behind the McGlynn School from 11 a.m. to 2 p.m. Some of the events that will occur, we will be giving out the third annual Green Awards, and those are to Medford area businesses, residents, and organizations that have taken on measures geared toward energy conservation and environmental initiatives.
We'll be giving out toys for the wind turbine. That will happen. And we'll also have some tables, educational and informational tables, for Medford students, clubs, and green businesses. We'll have a shredding truck that's returning, so people can bring their boxes of paper, anything that needs to be shredded. We'll have volunteers there to help people bring it from their car to the shredder, if that's necessary.
We'll have a free raffle again this year and prizes will be including compost bin, free dance lessons from Dance Caliante, sausage sandwiches from Fred's Franks. They'll also be there selling food. What else do we have? We have gift basket from Medford Whole Foods and a massage gift certificate from Elements Massage.
lots of great prizes to get people's interest and encourage people to attend. The very popular TechniArt will be selling sets of energy-efficient lights and light bulbs again for $10. They did that last year. It's very popular. That's been subsidized by National Grid, again, so that will be a popular item. New this year, we're going to have the Be the Match program. It's from Dana Farber.
And that will be typing people for bone marrow donation. We thought that would be a good addition to have. And also, they may have their blood mobile there as well, to give people an opportunity to donate blood. Also new will be a bike rodeo, something great for the kids. What this is, is it's from Safe Routes to School, that program. It's children should bring their bikes and their helmets.
to learn about safe biking, riding, and the Medford Bike Commission will be there leading micro-tours from the festival site to assembly row and back. And they'll be primarily using the shared trails. It's about five miles, a round trip. It's mostly flat, so people of all ages can participate, kids, adults, whatever. And the Bike Commission will also be valet parking your bikes. It's always nice to have valet parking during the course of the festival. And it's going to be a beautiful day, so I hope everyone can make it.
Thank you, and we look forward to seeing everyone there this weekend. Thank you very much. 11 a.m. to 2 p.m. on Saturday. Hi, Richard Cormier, 150 Middlesex Ave. I just wanted to add to that, she mentioned the Be the Match program. Many of you might know my father, Rich Cormier. He was diagnosed with a blood disease, and he had to go through a stem cell transplant. And it was through the Be the Match program that it's a very simple program.
You just go down there, you fill out some paperwork, and they swab the inside of your cheek, and that's it. Then you get put into a database, and then anywhere around the world they can end up contacting you. And it used to be a difficult process. Now it's a very simple process. It's more just like a blood transfusion, just like when you donate any type of blood. So it's very simple when you are called upon to donate stem cells, which the chances are very rare that you get called upon. But it's a very simple process.
I was looking forward to people going out there and signing up. And my father's doing great, by the way. So. So your father every Sunday is good? Yep. Doing well. And he's actually, he's teaching right now through Skype. He's teaching some of the kids of the Vogue through Skype. They have a camera set up in the classroom and at my house. And he's doing some teaching through that, so he can get back hopefully in January. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Motion by Councilor Dela Ruzzo. Hold on. Hold on. Hold on. Hold on. Hold on.
Mr. President, I just want to echo the comments of the last two speakers regarding the Be the Match program. And, you know, it's not often that you could make such a donation that is not financial in nature, but it's a donation to actually possibly save someone's life. And I can't think of a better donation to make. And as was just mentioned, it's just the swabbing of the inside of your mouth. And I plan on going down.
this weekend, Mr. President, and I would urge residents of this community to go down and not only enjoy the event, but also take part in the Be The Match program, Mr. President. Thank you, Councilor Marks. Motion by Councilor Del Rosso to revert back to regular business. 14-699, offered by Councilor Knight, be it resolved that Waste Management perform a comprehensive inspection of the vehicles used for trash
and recycling pickup in the city of Medford. Counselor Knight. Thank you very much, Mr. President. In recent weeks, I've gotten a number of calls relative to what I guess would be labeled trash truck slime leaking out of the trash trucks, causing a little bit of a problem relative to quality of life in certain neighborhoods. I've gotten a number of calls from the Lawrence Street neighborhood. It's also happened right in my own backyard, Mr. President, along Winthrop Street.
We've seen it on Spring Street as well. So I'd ask that Waste Management do an inspection of their vehicles to ensure that they're not leaking any trash and refuse and fluid onto our streets. I think it may pose a significant public health hazard, but more or less it's really just a quality of life issue. Okay, we'll move forward something on, we'll have the clerk move something on to Waste Management. Councilor Penta. As an aside to that, we have asked for, on numerous occasions, I report back from the administration
on waste management's cost analysis with the city as it relates to not only the trash refuse, but also to the recycling. And we have never gotten that. And like we did last year, unfortunately, at the end of the year, we were hit with an expensive bill of $159,000 to offset supposedly the net of not having enough refuse, not enough recycling to meet the contract of its needs. So again, this is the fourth, maybe fifth time
We're asking for that breakdown, Mr. President. I believe the way we used to get it before was broken down over the 10-year length of the contract, what was anticipated, what had been spent from prior years as compared to the one coming in. So I think that would be helpful to the resolution that's before us. Mr. Clerk, did you get that? Did he add that up? Counselor Pender would like you to get a comprehensive report back on waste management.
Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Council marks suspension of the rules to take paper 14 dash seven Oh five and 14 dash seven Oh seven. Okay. Thank you. 14 seven Oh five to president Paul Camuso and the members of Memphis city council for mayor Michael J. McGlynn easement.
to Massachusetts Electric Company, 21 James Street, Bedford, Mass. Dear Mr. President, members of the council, I respectfully request and recommend that your honorable body approve the grant of the attached easement to the Massachusetts Electric Company. The purpose of this easement is to provide electric service and transmission of data to serve the Department of Public Works facility that is being constructed on James Street. I am attaching a copy of the proposed easement
to this request. Repressively submitted, Mayor Michael J. McGlynn. Move approval. Mr. Buckley, would you like to say anything? You're all set. Mr. President, if this matter is moved for approval and we're all in favor of it, I was going to ask for a reconsideration on the previous vote because no vote was taken.
Let's do this one first. Councilor Penta. Move approval. Move approval. Councilor Marks. Just if we could, we have, uh, the city solicitor here and we also have, uh, Mr. Buckley, uh, here, if they could just give a brief statement on the petition itself. Uh, yes. Uh, Mr. President, my name is Mark Rumley. I'm the city solicitor. I reside at 50 Woodrow Avenue in Medford first. I appreciate being taken under suspension quickly on this matter.
And one of the reasons I appreciate it is that this easement is a new easement for a power feed into the new city yard. It's in a different location than it was before. The extension of the power line will be approximately 55 feet. And the width of the diameter of the conduit itself is, depending upon where it is, is two to four inches. But it will serve the new city yards that are moving along with, I think, all deliberate speed from what I can see. So the approval of this easement would
would facilitate that even more, and we would ask for your approval. On the motion? Mr. President, just if they can give us the length of time that it would take to install this easement. Name and address for the record, please. John Buckley, 19 Suffolk Street, Medford, Mass. Once they get probably less than 30 days, they've already put the second utility pole in place with the stubs in the ground. All they have to do now is bring it across.
So we just need to go ahead, we'll notify them, and probably within a week it'll be installed, but I'll give them a little flexibility, two to three weeks. Motion to approve. Motion to approve. Councilor Lange. Thank you, President Carviello. Just electrical, there's no water, what is the entrance? The water is already installed by our water department, probably 12 months earlier, so we're in good shape. This is to bring, if you're familiar with the back entrance between Grover and Joseph's Limousine,
That's where we're bringing the service across. There was an existing pole there now. So this will only be for the utility, just for the national electric. Electric. Okay. Thank you. Councilor Penta. Is this the setup for the permanent pole that's for the permanent use? That's a permanent pole. This will be the permanent pole. That'll be the permanent pole. Then it'll go under the ground and it'll go into the pad. That'll actually service the entire facility. So right now you're just operating off the temporary. And once this goes in, it'll be. Yeah, there was already a pole there.
So this'll be the new pole that's more robust and all that. Okay. Move approval. Motion for approval. All in favor? Aye. Mr. Buckley, why here? Would you like to give us a little update on the city yard? The sides are all up and progressing. As you can see by driving down the parkway, we're all very excited. We have an excellent contractor. We have an excellent architect and this job really is, is moving along with great speed. Uh, the superstructure is going up as you speak and as you can see it, the outline of the building is there.
So we're all very encouraged. We should be in there April the 1st. There was a lot of work involved with that yard because of the old site conditions, getting rid of soil that had to be remediated, those kind of things. So there was a lot of preparation work just to get to the point that we're on now. So like I say, it's been a great effort. Everybody's been very cooperative. I'd like to thank Joseph's Limousine and Grava. They've been outstanding to work with because they're directly impacted by all
So we tried to keep them in contact with everything we're doing, but they couldn't have been better. And the people right around the corner have been very easy to work with. So that makes the job go that much better when you don't have to worry all the time about kind of nagging kind of issues. So also, it's been a great contract. The GNR is probably one of the best contractors I've worked with. They're very diligent. They follow protocols. They make sure all the OSHA certifications are there. They're really aren't any surprises. They bring everything forthright if it's an unknown condition.
We bring things to them that we'd like to consider. So it's been a great job. And as you can see, one of the first moves we made was to move the new fuel island down the street. So the above-ground tanks was the first order of business. So now all the municipal safety and public vehicles can get down to that fuel island, fuel up, and go out without actually going into the construction site. And when we're all done, that area will be maintained as the fuel island. We'll have access gates, and we'll be able to control who goes in, who goes out.
There'll also be a public area for the citizens to come down to drop off recycling, plastic bottles, those kind of things. So that'll be segregated from the DPW site and allow the DPW site to kind of be a full municipal operation. And I think every member of the council who voted for this will be very pleased when you see the size of the facility and the fact that you can handle the smallest from the largest piece of equipment and vehicle that the city has. And we did that. We took the biggest piece of equipment that we have, engine one,
brought it down there to make sure everything fit for maintenance, et cetera. So it'll have all the state-of-the-art facilities, energy-efficient, pre-engineered building. It's got all of the stormwater management runoff capabilities, retrieving the water that you recycle through and dispose of it properly. So it's been a great project. I'm looking very much forward to finally give the DPW people who go to work every day, and they used to work in tough conditions like I know you know. So to give them a first-class facility and the people of Medford
some place they can actually go to and respond to and have an emergency operations when you need it for all vehicles. So I'm very happy. Any time paid for a completion? Yeah. Looking at full completion occupancy, April the 1st, April the 1st before completion occupancy. We'll have in all projects, you always have substantial completion. Then you have a punch list, but the rate we're going right now, if the weather holds for us, we don't have any kind of mother nature things hit us. I think we'll be in great shape.
Thank you. Thank you. 14. All those in favor. Motion for approval. All in favor. All those opposed. No motion passes. Which one was that?
I'm sorry. You're making a motion for reconsideration? Yes, motion for reconsideration on paper 14699. Mr. President, the vote wasn't taken. I'd ask that it be taken in the call of the ayes and nays. Motion for reconsideration. All those in favor? Aye. Opposed? Motion for approval. Motion for approval, Mr. President. Call of the ayes and nays. All those in favor? Aye. Opposed?
All those opposed? Motion passes. We didn't vote on the last vote. Okay. Okay. 14707 petition by Robert G. Abruzzi, 92 High Street Method Mass to address the city council about mailing for the October 28th
2014 hearing for Coles extended hours. Thank you, Mr. President, members of the council. I'm here in connection with a previously filed petition for a special permit for extended hours of operation, which is to be heard by this council on October 28th, a petition on behalf of Coles.
And the issue concerns what I'm looking for is the council's approval that the mailing of notice of that hearing be sent by regular mail, which is what the state statute requires. Apparently in many cases, I know the city council has previously sent mailing by registered mail return received requested, but since that's not required by the ordinance in this particular case,
Because of the condominium building next door, there are 286 abutters, which, at a cost of in excess of $6.50 per certified male, would be an unnecessary cost of approximately $2,000. So that's the substance of my request here this evening. Councilwoman, go ahead. Who's requiring you to come before the council to
Well, I think City Clerk's Office is looking for some clarification, some direction from the Council. Do you know how many? As opposed to City Solicitor, I previously discussed this issue with Council President Camuso and Vice President Caraviello, and they each suggested that I get some confirmation of what I'm telling you today from the City Solicitor. I believe the City Solicitor did provide
via email, a copy of which I have this evening, to each of you about a week ago, confirming what I'm telling you here this evening. And how many letters total? How many letters total would you have to send? 286 on the abundance list. 286 on the abundance list. As a practical matter, more people will get the notice if you send it regular mail than certified, because my experience has been that
have the certified letters never get picked up at the post office. Councilor Knight. Thank you very much, Mr. President. I don't see any reason why we'd hold this one business to a higher standard than what's required under state statute, Mr. President. I think that this is something that's a reasonable request that falls in line with what the law is and I might certainly be supporting it. I think we should move for approval, but I'd like Councilor Moxley to obviously have a chance to talk on it. However, I don't,
see any reason why we'd need to hold them to a higher standard or a different standard than that of any other business here in the community. Thank you. Councilor Dela Rosa. Mr. President, I am in agreement with Councilor Knight. I think that we should observe the ordinance and statutes before us. This isn't something of a grave matter. And oftentimes with collective housing like you have there in the condo building, there would be a,
meeting of the residents and a consensus and single voice often represented by the leadership of their housing council or condo board. So, and this isn't something of a grave matter. It's just a occasional extension of hours of operation they'd be seeking to have here.
This will be setting a precedent going forward, Councilor DelaRosa. I think that's what we're going for. The normal means of conveyance of information is by first class mail, so I don't know why anything else would be required. Point of information, I think in some particular circumstances, such as repair shop licenses, your ordinance says that the notice shall be sent certified mail. So that's a different situation.
Unless the particular ordinance requires it, I would think that the council ought to be bound by what the state statute is. So there is no special requirement with respect to the extended hours special permit ordinance. Accordingly, I think it ought to go to regular mail. If I could, through the chair, and ask the city solicitor to instruct us, are there, in addition to
of the requirement for certified mail for repair shops, auto repair shops, and auto body shops. Are there other instances requiring in our ordinances certified mail notification? The major one is repair shop license. I came across that last week specifically when I discussed this with the city clerk. As to special permits, and this extension of ours would be a special permit, the law is set forth in 40A section 10.
And it says specifically that notice shall be sent by mail postage prepaid. So after speaking with the city solicitor, excuse me, the city clerk who told me that the notice of this sort has been done by certified mail, uh, since the, uh, Paleozoic era, we tried to look for what, uh, um, reference there was a foundation for that. So we looked through the council resolutions over the years. There is none. Uh, look through the council rules. There is nothing that applies to it.
And there's nothing that says anything except for what the statute says, which is regular mail. Now, one of the prudent things to do if you're worried about setting a precedent that might come back and be problematic in the future is to refer this to essentially a rules committee or to one of your council business committees so that you can take a look at it with some degree of depth and without having to do so in the quickness of one council meeting. But as to the special permit, the extension of hours,
4810 says regular mail. Very, very clearly. Mr. President, that being said, then I'd, uh, move approval for this, uh, this instance. And, uh, as a, uh, uh, amendment to the, uh, uh, resolution, refer this to the rules committee, convene a meeting, uh, so that we can, uh, clarify this and deal with it, uh, for the future. Yes. Councilor Bender.
Councilor Del Russo, that's absurd. You're not going to vote for something tonight and then refer it back and possibly get a different opinion. All our common vigil licenses we have voted for in the past, Mr. Clark, have been by regular mail. They haven't been by certified mail. Why would Coles be any different than any other common vigil license? Extended hours. Yeah. Why would that be it? No, let the clerk speak.
The clerk, the clerk. Okay. So it's not just for, that we've doing it for extended hours. We've been doing it this way for any special permit zoning. Okay. And extended hours for this particular case does fall within the chapter and verse that the city solicitor had indicated.
Now, before I came here, this practice was in place on certified mail, on a special permit and zoning. And to the best of my knowledge, talking to the staff that is here prior to that, they have done it. Now, going through some research and the city solicitor also looked at it, that I could not find where
It instructed our office to make everything certified mail. It could be tucked away in some amendment someplace, but there's no council resolution. There's no council rules and regulations. So it came about somewhere at some time years ago, even before I came. So the practice, when I came in, is that we continued the practice. What the attorney at Bruzy is saying, and I've dealt with,
attorney at Bruzee for the past 15 years, and he himself has been charged with certified mail, would have only been three of butters or something like that. So the practice going forward, I think, if this was the law of states, I just need some clarification to tell me, to tell our office to follow what the law is saying for all special permits. Because I don't know where it came from. It was beyond me.
You know, and it must have been a generated, maybe from the city council at some meeting or whatever like that. But, uh, this is, uh, so for me to go forward, I not only could have to do is treat, uh, Mr. Bruzzi's, uh, client, but I think anybody that falls into the special permit, you know, even if it's one, it should go out, uh, the general mail and be, and be a charged accordingly. So it's just not just the calls it's no, cause we did Kelly's,
I believe six years ago, and it must have cost them over $2,000, because they had two complexes across the street, you know, and they had drive-thru in, they had extended out, so. Thank you, President Carviello. If I could ask Clerk Finn a question about this, because it seems like an easy vote. Okay, it looks like it would be about $1,800 for coals.
process-wise, who sends out the certified mails? That would be Coles that sends out the certified mails? No. Our office would prepare all the certified mail, then charge Coles, or the attorney, the cost of the certified mail. All the work would be done in our office. And it's a lot of work. I mean, it's a lot of work for general mail, too, quite frankly.
Because it's not like it's, I want to say, a moneymaker for anybody, because the only person that is getting it is the U.S. Postal Service. We don't charge more than what the certified mail has. And now, if you understand the certified mail, in the last two years, it's probably gone up maybe over $2 per piece in the last couple of years. Since the last time we did a big project, like I said, Kelly's like this, you know. That was my question, because it would be a concern of mine if
Coles had to do the certified mail or send it out regular mail, just with regards to proving that they did so. But if that's the case where the city clerk's office sends out whether it be certified or regular mail. But it shouldn't be just, it shouldn't be really, from my end of the case, it shouldn't be just Coles. It should be whatever the law has written for all the special partners. Correct. Point of clarification, Mr. Clark, solicitor. To the best of your knowledge, is the repair shops the only one by statute
that requires certified mail? When I went through the council rules and the ordinances, and I used the search word, certified, it was for repair shops. That was it? That's all I could find. So it would seem that whether the practice was right or wrong in the past, if this be the case now, and this is the state statute, and we don't have anything to challenge this, this is what the law is. It's clearly what the law is. By regular mail. Yes. So we don't need any meeting, Councilor De La
to try to figure this out. I think it's quite obvious. Move approval. Councilor Marks. Thank you, Mr. President. And I agree. I think the fact that a certified meal is not the letter of the law, that past practice, which has happened according to the city clerk for the last 75 years, kind of goes out the window. And we should conform to whatever the current standard is, which is prepaid postage.
And that's acceptable, I think, from what I'm hearing the city clerk ask is that we direct him to do away with past practice, which was certified, and to follow the letter of the law. And I think, is that correct, what you're looking for, Mr. Clerk? And that would apply to everyone, so we're not going to pick and choose.
who this is going to apply to. Yes, but that's a separate, that's a separate, excuse me, that's a separate section of the ordinances. And I think part of the reasoning behind that is because of the use of flammable fluids and other things. If I may, thank you, President Carvello. Where you have the return receipt,
when somebody comes into the office, say, somebody says, I didn't get the notice, and you then have the return receipt to say, yes, you did. I mean, is there, can we amend this? You can require it, regular mail, but take a picture of each envelope showing, you know, that it went out? Well, we have the, we have the butters list that shows who's been sent out to.
My only concern would be if somebody comes in saying, I didn't get the notice. Well, now you don't have the return receipt anymore. I have notices probably this much out here. And the last time we did it, that they didn't go and pick up their certified mail. You know what I mean? But that's a different issue. Yeah, but I mean, it's the same thing. But they tell me they didn't get it the same time. I says, I know. But you have the proof. It was three attempts.
Here, you know, I mean, to copy, you're asking us to copy, you know, I don't know what Cole's is, 300, 400 envelopes, I mean. 286, yeah. If I could make a suggestion, you could use the rules that were used in the civil procedure rules and just have a certificate of service executed by the person that sent it out. In this case, it would be the city clerk's office. Or you could ask that the petitioner sign a document saying that they have provided
this list of abutters to the city clerk's office and just use a return of service as opposed to photocopying 300 envelopes. Certificate of, yeah, I think we should require. Well, you get that anyways from the assessor that he certified these. Yeah, he certifies the list, but a separate certification which says that mail went out to those persons at those addresses, which would only have to be a paragraph. From the city clerk's office. I would make that recommendation. Some, I mean,
going quickly, but something to prove that with an affidavit or a certification, that each one on that list was mailed by regular mail, the notice. The post office will give you a receipt and stamp it. And if you're signing up 286 and it's off on the city of Bedford, they'll time it, they'll date it, and they'll stamp it. Right, for the amount of the postage that was paid. Yes, they would, with the number of items that are on the list. Yeah. Yeah, but we don't, we do our mail service here.
I'm not going to the post office with a stack of calls, you know, mails, you know, clerk certifies everything to be sworn and true. That's his job. So, and so doing, uh, carrying out the office of his work, he can, he can do that. I think
Mr. President, we're dealing with two separate issues here. We're dealing with the matter that's before us, which it appears that, you know, Coles does have the right to just mail these out pre-postage. Anything else that we want to do that might well fall under the suggestion that Counselor DelaRusso had going forward.
that this is not just for calls specifically, but going forward, this is going to be the procedure. Right. So going forward, maybe we should consider Councilor De La Ruta's suggestion that we can go and we can refer that matter to the Rules Committee and come up with something that we can all live with. But as of right now, in this point in time, there is no requirement. So I think that what we should do, Mr. President, would be move for approval on this paper. And then if, in fact, we need to come up with a process or a policy that the Rules Committee can do such and report it back to the Committee of the Whole for further deliberation.
two other special permits in the bank so I'm ready to go. Anything we decide tonight will be the procedure we use going forward. Right, until we change the procedure. Or create a procedure. There is no procedure to change. Right now there is one. We're abiding by the current. There is a procedure and it's set forth in the state statute and the other petitioners, whoever they are, should be treated in the exact same way as this petitioner because that's the law. It's simple.
And if there are some internal controls that the council feels that those should be made, photocopying of the envelope, so on and so forth, that's all well and good. All right, motion for approval on this one. All in favor? Aye. Opposed? None. Thank you. Thank you. 6-0, motion passes. Motion by Councilor Pentland, we revert back to regular business.
14700 offered by councillor Penta, be it resolved that in the interest of public safety for bicyclists and the driving public, a state law proposal be forwarded to our state legislature regarding such matter. A further explanation to be furnished at the council meeting. Councillor Penta.
bicycle enthusiasts out there. We all know we've seen a great influx of bicyclists in our community, as a matter of fact, in the whole Commonwealth of Massachusetts. And if anybody read Sunday's newspaper in the Boston Globe, they had printed a story about bike fatalities in the greater Boston suburbs and how they've increased from 2010, 11, and 12. Unfortunately, some people died.
And apparently, that's unfortunate. It's an issue right now, I think, that needs to be dealt with as it relates to the public safety portion of it. The popularity of biking is greatly soared. And state policy, Mass. Department of Transportation, and local communities, like Somerville, who's basically one of the communities, like Boston, that's in the forefront of having bicycle-friendly roadways
and amenities that would be complementary to them. But the concern, as it relates to where we're going with all these bicycle and bicycle paths in communities such as Medford, which has a bicycle commission, just how much of an input, and more importantly, how much of a control do we have? Out of the 557 schools in the Commonwealth
signed up on the state DOT program. Only 17 of them are actually implementing bicycle safety programs that at least meet the minimal standards that Mass. Department of Transportation is asking for. The confusion that's taking place on the roadway, especially for people who are driving cars as compared to when they look at a cyclist, is that, you know, who in fact has the right of way? Who's got the rules of the road?
who's supposed to follow what, when, and how. And the educational process, once again, really should fall on local communities, because if local communities are going to start with having bicycle-friendly streets and providing certain roadways or pathways or whatever the terminology might be that you would want to have for bicyclists, an educational process needs to take place. And if it doesn't take place,
There's a concern. There's a concern to the bicyclist, the person driving the bike, riding the bike, and the person driving the car. And because of that, you know, this prompted me to turn around and think about, you know, it's great. It's a great form of exercise medically. We all know that riding a bike is great. But we also know that there's a concern that's predicating some of these safety issues. And one of the concerns seems to be the speed of some of the
cyclist when they're riding their bikes. And the other one, going through stop signs and driving through crosswalks. And they seem to be the three major concerns of the cities and towns that I reviewed in the Mass State Department of Transportation's concerns, since they've now started to inventory bicycle accidents. But Boston thus far has yet to do an inventory of bicycle accidents.
Bicycles, again, according to Section 11B of Chapter 85, bicycles shall be subject to the traffic laws and regulations of the Commonwealth and special regulations as found in the particular section. And the section that I want to get into is the bike in and of itself in hours after dark, before dusk and after dark. The operator, this is what the law says, that the operator shall display
To the front of the bicycle, a lamp emitting a white light visible from a distance of at least 500 feet. In the rear of the bicycle, a light emanating — a red light emanating for not less than 600 feet. Now, if you can imagine what it's like driving a car at nighttime and looking out 600 feet and looking at a little dinky red light, good luck to you, because a lot of the times they don't exist. And a lot of the folks that are driving these bikes don't even have these lights on.
So now we get into initial call enforcement, and where the police department, another part of their job, but bikes are having their way on the roadways, and rightfully so. And they deserve to be protected just as much as the person driving the car. And they also talk about having on the ankles some type of reflective material. And once I saw this thing about the reflective material, that's the thing that got to me. I would like to propose, and hopefully my colleagues will be supportive, and also
I had a conversation with Bruce Kulick, who happens to be the chairman of the Bicycle Commission, and I think we're on the same page on this one, that the drivers of a bicycle at nighttime wear some type of a jacket or whatever it might be of a reflective type of material. How many times have you driven down the street at nighttime and you see someone with dark clothes on in a crosswalk and you might miss them? How many times do you see a bike driving down the street at dusk and even late at night
and have absolutely nothing on that would identify them as a person on a bike by way of color, reflection, or what have you. There is no state law out there right now that makes it a mandatory requirement for the purposes of a male or female driving a bicycle having a reflector jacket type of garment on them.
This is going to be taking up the same type of fuel. It's going to be building up momentum, because as we know, the law that's out there, trying to be out there, that you can't text and drive at the same time, because we know the consequences that can happen by way of accidents. Well, the same thing is going to be happening with these bicyclists, because we know that they're becoming more and more of them out there. Each and every community, including Medford, have more and more bicyclists. And bicycle folks are going to drive
whether they come from Medford or out of town or what have you. But there has to be some mode of protection and identification that is protective to these folks that are driving a bike. And again, there is nothing in the state law that really goes out of its way that basically says, other than some little, and I'll call it stupid thing you put on your ankle, that who the hell is going to see a reflector thing 600 feet away, as compared to maybe having a reflector type jacket.
that identifies itself, green, yellow, orange, whatever it might be. It may not be the most social-looking piece of garment you'd want to wear, but if it's going to protect and save your life, you know, it does the thing. So, with that being said, Mr. President, and I don't know if there's anybody here from the Bicycle Commission who would like to speak on it or what have you, but I would appreciate not only their comments, but more importantly, their support for this because
Again, reviewing the accidents as they have been presented and looking at the statistics, and I believe the statistics are going up, they're not going down, on bicycle accidents and, unfortunately, people dying from bicycle accidents, and I believe every single one of them have not been identified with anything at nighttime that would be reflective type of material that would present a safety condition for the person riding the bike.
Sure, my name is Tim McGivern, 623 Watervale Road. I'm on the Medford Bicycle Advisory Commission. I think, are you proposing that Medford have some sort of ordinance that requires reflective vests for bicycles? Or are you proposing that the city council recommend legislature to the state legislature?
I am proposing the same way the state legislature has these amendments that have been forthcoming and the law has amended that we again amend the law that makes a requirement statewide for any person riding a bicycle from dawn to dusk that they have to wear some type of reflective type of material easily identifiable by a headlight and an oncoming car or a car behind you or whatever. I think that anything to increase the safety of cyclists on the road is a good idea.
And I think wearing a vest that's reflective when you're riding your bicycle is increasing your safety on the road, and therefore it's a good idea. So I do not oppose such a movement, but I do not speak for the entire bicycle commission. We would need to deliberate on that. Thank you. Thank you, President Carviello. Councilor Penser, I think you mentioned the Mass General Law.
which I read as that's already a requirement. One half hour after sunset to one half hour before sunrise, the operator shall display on each pedal of his bicycle a reflector. I'm not talking about that. I'm talking about wearing a jacket, something that could be seen and highly visible. If you ever get behind a car 600 feet,
and try to find that little reflector on the pedal, or on their foot, or the little red light behind a bike that 90% of the time doesn't work, and they run by battery. Or you see a little white headlight that's 500 feet away on a bike that doesn't cut the mustard when a car is driving down the street, or even if a truck is driving down the street. I mean, it's, it's. So you're proposing that the state legislate it. Amend it. Amend it, so instead of just the lamp,
which is required on the front of the bike or the pedal on the reflector be increased to a vest. To a vest. Or a garment type of material, vest, jacket, or what have you. What if we send this to the Bicycle Commission as well, or prior to, to have them discuss? I mean, there are two members here tonight. I've spoken to Bruce as well. How many people are on the committee as of right now?
10 people from Medford on the committee who probably speak to a number of other cyclists. Let's get some input. I agree with it. Let's refer to the Bicycle Commission first. That would be my suggestion. I think it's a great resolve, and I think anything to enhance safety for bicyclists is a positive step. I agree with Councillor Penter as well. Enforcement is going to be a big thing, not only for vehicles, but also to put on these vests.
I think there are some details that need to be worked out as far as what this vest or coat looks like, what it is, and do you have to wear it if you are, say, riding down the sidewalk in a type of neighborhood in Massachusetts that seems silly to wear that vest, like a pedestrian, for example, crossing the street. So I think there are things.
that can be discussed by the bicycle commission. And I would like to ask that the city council table this until we had a chance to discuss it and make a recommendation to the city council. A point of clarification. This is directed toward people who drive a bike. And I believe the cyclists that drive a bike have to wear a helmet. Isn't that required by law too? I believe so. OK.
If somebody decides from dawn to dusk they want to drive a bike on a sidewalk or a street, the requirement's going to be the same because you're riding a bike. And according to Chapter 85, Section, I think it's 10 and 11, there are certain requirements that you have to follow the same rules of the road. And the only exception to the rules of the road, I believe, if you're going, exiting, or entering on a highway and anything else that might be specifically excluded by state statute.
So I think we're all on the same page. I think so too. And the more, I think the more support we get for it, you know, and explaining it, I think it, you know, it bears fruit. This isn't like wearing a heavy jacket and the winter time. It's just, you know, it's something. I know exactly what you mean. I've seen it. I wear one myself. What I'm asking for is just the opportunity for the commission to discuss it. And we could even formalize a recommendation to the city council, but not all. Councilor Knight. Thank you very much, Mr. President.
I agree with Mr. Givern wholeheartedly. I think that the Bicycle Commission meets rather frequently. They have a large board of people that are probably much more avid cyclists than anybody behind this rail. They know the dangers that they face. They know what the city needs to do to make them safer, because they're out there every day on these roads, Mr. President. So I think it would make sense if we got an advisory opinion from the Bicycle Commission to see what direction that they'd like to see us go.
a number of issues aside from public safety and how to make Medford more bicycle-friendly. And I think that maybe if we look at this in a more comprehensive fashion, if we're going to send something to the legislature, that would be worth its weight. Would you like to see us refer it to the Public Safety Committee? I'd like to table the matter and have it be sent to the Bicycle Commission for recommendation. Then we can bring it back to the floor for discussion. Councillor Del Rosso. I'd also recommend that the Bicycle Commission, since it never has,
take the opportunity to meet with us and committee of the whole to just present to the council what they're doing, they're discussing and their role in the city so that we can be apprised of that as a body. So would you prefer to retable this or? I'm referring to the bicycle. Okay. We send it back to them and then have the president convene a meeting in the future. Okay. So if you gentlemen can take this back to Mr. Kulik.
We agree and we'd love the opportunity to do that and so we'll look forward to it. Does anyone else want to speak in this matter? Gene, did you want to speak? The motion is that we send this back to the bicycle committee for their review and they will get back to us. Councilor Pinto. One quick thing, and I brought up an issue, there's 557 schools at the present time that are supposed to be, that are allegedly participants in the Department of Transportation public safety program for schools.
And only 17 of these communities have jumped on board. Is Method one of the 17 or not? Are you aware of? Name and address of the record, please. Jason Cluggish, 16 6th Street. I believe you're talking about the Safe Routes to School program. Yeah, right. And I believe that the Roberts School has signed up.
But I am unaware of any other Medford public school has. But see, that's the issue. Signing up as compared to having the program implemented, that's the issue. There is someone that works on the Board of Health, happens to be my wife, that's working with schools. She's the, what is it called? She's coordinating the grant from the Massachusetts Health Department. And one of the programs she's working on is implementing Safe Routes to Schools in Medford.
So right now the Roberts was on the book, but we haven't implemented the program yet. I believe that it is being implemented.
which part of being implemented is working towards all the requirements of it. So I can't speak 100% on it, but we do have someone in City Hall working on that task. Okay, thank you. I should also mention that the Advisory Commission, Bicycle Advisory Commission, is looking into the Safe Roads to School.
and whether or not, you know, how Medford should approach it and whether or not we should, you know, have our schools participate also. Thank you. Thank you. So I'm just going to refer you back to the vice-chairman of the commission for their review and they will get back to us. All right. 14-701 offered by Councilor Penta. Motion for approval. All in favor? Opposed? None.
Six in the affirmative, zero in the negative, the motion passes. 14701, offered by Councilor Penter, be it resolved that the Memphis City Council take an official position on Mayor McGlynn's one-size-fits-all pay-to-park contract, since, in fact, the council found out about the signing by a press release. Councilor Penter. President, since last Tuesday night until now,
I think we've all, I'll speak for myself. I received a considerable amount of phone calls from not only Method business folks on two particular issues, this and the raising and the water rates. But we'll stick to this issue right now. And the unfortunate part about it is what we heard last Tuesday night, part of the issue is not whether you're now for it or against it. The issue now revolves itself around the fact that the mayor had made a promise that he was going to have a public hearing on this particular matter.
um, resolution 14, six 45, which was offered by myself and subsequently amended by council Lungo passed. Uh, and that was some two weeks ago, I think it was in September 23rd and asking the mayor to have a public meeting and a hearing throughout this community, whether it be here at city hall or wherever, wherever it's so big that citizens and, and, um, business folks would have an opportunity to come and express their opinion, whether they were forward against it or more importantly,
as to what the mayor's proposal was. And I think after we knew last Tuesday night coming into our council meeting that at five o'clock the mayor had sent out a press release indicating that he had signed the contract, I think that sort of like took us all off guard, especially to the point that no public meeting ever took place. Then more importantly, or as importantly, last week the president of the chamber came down here and indicated that the chamber had taken an official position for the purposes of supporting
The contract for what information Councilor Del Rosso. Did the mayor say that he was having a, if I could through the chair, did the mayor say that he was having a public meeting on this? I have not heard of any public meeting Councilor Del Rosso. The question becomes relevant because the concerns that were expressed at the meeting of the 10th of September and all seven members of the council had concerns as it related to, uh, what might or what might not be in the contract. And in fact, we as a council,
We as a council had never been advised or never even shown what the finality of the contract was. But after listening to the president of the chamber, he particularly was involved with the mayor, and the mayor allowed him to be involved in making the final decisions or agreeing to the concessions of the final decisions. Well, that's all well and good. But the Chamber of Commerce is not the Medford City Council. And the Medford City Council was owed that due respect from the mayor
that the finality of signing that contract, or before it was to take place, should have come before the council. We all discussed it, and we all had an opinion on it. Whether you were for it or against it, that wasn't the issue. The fact of the matter was to have the public hearing or the public meeting. Call it what you may. Let taxpayers, let residents, and business owners come up and have an opportunity to speak on something that they didn't even know what was going on, that they were just finding out about.
The president of the chamber indicated when the question was asked that he only represents members of the chamber. He doesn't represent any other business people. Well, I think that's an injustice to every other business person in this community who's a taxpayer and has employees. There are people that maybe don't want to become members of the chamber or just don't have the time to become members of the chamber. And they should not be looked upon as a second grade or a second class citizen.
for the purposes of whether you agree or disagree with a pay-to-park program. One information, Counselor De La Russa. I don't recall the President of the Chamber ever indicating that he had any particular or exclusive consultative role in this process any more than anybody else who may or may not have, who has made that role public or private. Mr. President, I think if you review the tape, the tape is as clear as can be.
that Mr. White indicated that subsequent to the 10th meeting of September, he asked the mayor to be a part of what the concerns were of the chamber. And as a result of that, he met with the chamber. And as a matter of fact, he said he was satisfied with the concessions. But it was the same person who, quote, in the paper, indicated that all business districts in this community are unique until they have their own special problems. And by having your own special problems, which they need to be discussed,
and be reviewed. And that was on the 2nd of October. Five days after that, the 7th of October, the mayor signs the contract. That's kind of quick. None of these people from the other sections of the city were involved. No business people. And once again, no taxpayers, no rate payers in this community. And with that happening,
It makes you subject to the question of the Chamber of Commerce. They don't know whether they have 200 or 300 members. So whatever it might be. And if it's 200 members and only a specific board, the Governmental Affairs Committee voted, what they voted for, I don't know. The Chamber of Commerce, I don't know. This discourse seems to exclude the possibility that the mayor consulted with shop owners throughout the city who may or may not have been in membership of the Chamber of Commerce.
Well, Mr. President, since Councilor De La Russo and you, Councilor Caviello, are both members of the chamber, I would see that you have a prejudice here to support the chamber's position, no matter what this one councilor has to say. I have no prejudice. Okay. Well, since you have no prejudice, maybe Councilor De La Russo does. But, you know, we also asked for what was going to be included and what was going to be excluded. One other question, Councilor De La Russo. I may or may not have prejudice in this matter, but I haven't indicated that publicly. Well, he hasn't indicated it publicly, so.
That leaves a suspect right there. And I believe it was the president of the chamber who indicated that he was happy to have been part of the process meeting with the mayor and coming to this concession through resolutions for whatever it might have been. This council was never apprised of any of whatever a concession might be. This one size fits all for all five districts, which includes Medford Square, it just doesn't work. It doesn't cut the mustard. And more importantly,
It's a recommendation. If you look at the press release that the mayor said, now I asked the city clerk today, um, I had called earlier and still I don't have it. Does anyone behind this rail have a copy of the contract either on disk? It was delivered to you moments ago by, Oh, moments ago, moments ago by the messenger. Oh, by the messenger. That's really nice. Moments ago. Here we have, we asked for it.
You know, here we have an $18 million, 10-year contract, and we just get the information now. But the chamber was aware of it, and they agreed to it. And I really have a suspect that I don't think the chamber was in agreement. I think if you took a poll of their membership and had a discussion of what's going on on those four priority sections, you'd have a better idea as to what their feelings might be. And maybe Counselor De La Russo was right, because when the mayor two Saturdays ago took a walk in the Westmethod area, I don't think he liked the response that he got, whether it was a
business person of the chamber. I'm not a business person of the chamber. This is business in this community. People are putting their daily work on their line.
They're not worried about the chamber being supportive of them, they need to make money, they have to pay their employees, they need to pay their insurance, they need to pay everything that makes a business work. Not every single person in this community or every single business in this community is a member of the chamber, and rightfully so. They don't have to be and they shouldn't be if they so choose not to be.
So why the mayor decides to pick on this one organization as to be the only organization to make his recommendations and his concessions with, I don't know, but he should have been before this Medford City Council and the taxpayers of this community to give his final decision of whatever he thought he was going to do by way of having a public hearing to get some input. On May 20th of this past year, we voted to give the mayor the opportunity to deal with a single-person contract
for 10 years, because the law says anything over three years, you have to take a vote. We didn't tell him to sign it. What we said is to go and make your contract negotiations. Come back before the council. Come back before the council and tell us what you have. The law says the council makes the vote. The council will only vote if him to go and to engage in a contract, not to sign the contract.
If that be the case, then what was the purpose of us even being here? We shouldn't even be discussing this. It means absolutely nothing. He shouldn't have even had the meeting on September 10th. This is all for nothing. But his back got against the wall because he heard from some of the business people. And unfortunately, once again, the president of the chamber said,
Most of the people in the room that night weren't even chamber members. So what does that mean? Just because they're not chamber members. They're business people in this community who pay their taxes and employ people and have residents come to their stores and buy their products so they can have a living and make a living. Mr. President, you're a member of the chamber. You and I have had this discussion numerous times on numerous occasions. And as you've been aware,
many people. You told me you went to, you told me you went to the groundbreaking ceremonies, the bank over there. Okay. Last Saturday. You told me the mayor had to run away because everybody was on top of them because of the parking thing. Not at the bank on Saturday, on Friday. Friday, excuse me, on Friday. There was nobody there complaining about parking that day.
when I was there. Anyways, I was there. You were there after the fact because you know, I was, I was there for the opening. And what did you tell me? What'd you tell me? He had to leave because everybody was complaining about that. That's something else. Yeah. That's something else. Well, same thing. You go to so many of these inaugurals. I have no idea which ones that we were at, but the fact of the matter is this, um, I just think it's unfair. And I, and I really don't know because if the press release is only nothing more than recommendations,
then they don't have to adhere to anything, this company called Republic. And the aggressiveness, as Councilor Marks alluded to last week, they're going to start at 7 in the morning to 7 at night. They need to do a million, $2 million a year as a minimum to start. You know yourself as well as I. They're going to be out there writing tickets. But the cream, the cream to this whole deal is that the mayor retains the appeal process. And to me, that is political because if it wasn't going to be political and it was going to be independent, he should have given it up.
So City Hall still remains as the political process of appeal to this whole particular program. And as what took place today at the Traffic Commission, they indicated, you know, they will still have the authority to set the places and set the rates. But we still don't know the exact spots of where things are going, and we don't really know who's going to be excluded. Well, I would assume that it is in this disc that we received this evening that, for our review,
over the next week for our next meeting. I don't know, I'm just. Well, how do you, how does any one councilor justify the fact that a contract was signed and you never even saw it? You voted for something that you asked the mayor to do, and he didn't do it. Point of clarification. Point of clarification, Councilor Van Gogh-Carran. Thank you, President Carviello. As far as I'm concerned, we had
I've mentioned this before, two, possibly three meetings with the mayor, in subcommittee, with Director Burke. And we went over, I mean, we had hours of discussion of the terms that would be in the contract. We knew how much they were going to charge per hour. We knew how many spots were going to be monitored. We knew, we were in executive session discussing the three possible people that we were going to sign, engage in contract negotiations with.
After those three meetings, this city council, seven of us, voted to allow the mayor to negotiate. So I mean, I just want to make that clear because I feel like this is something that I've pretty much already have seen. We were getting it first, maybe the third time. But point of further clarification, you hit it right in the head. You gave him the authority to negotiate, but not to sign the contract. And that's what he did. He signed the contract without any one of us having an opportunity to see it and discuss it.
Point of information, Councillor Dela Russa. I wonder out loud, do we have to authorize him to sign a contract? I thought he was the contracting authority. The solicitor is not here. I cannot answer that question. Point of further information, Mr. President. Point of information, Councillor Mayne. I believe when we were at the meeting in executive session with the mayor and we granted him the authority to enter into this contract for a term of 10 years, that we did not put any criteria upon the mayor's ability to negotiate this contract in terms of having a councillor present as a member of his negotiating team.
I think it's very important to keep in mind that we want the mayor to go into this and negotiate a contract in good faith. And the mayor can't go and negotiate a contract in good faith if he can't bring that back to the board and have confidence that it's going to be passed. You know, we gave him the opportunity to go out there and we gave him an opportunity to enter into a 10-year contract. As Councilor Longo-Kern has said a number of times, and her sentiment is something that I have echoed, we knew what we were getting into. We saw the RFP.
Councilman Marks is right. This is the mayor's parking plan. The mayor put this together. The mayor negotiated. The criteria come right out of the corner office. They don't come from this council. The authority that we gave him was to enter into the agreement solely. But when we were in the executive session, we saw what the plan was. We saw what the plan was. We knew what it was going to entail. We weren't allowed to talk about it. Point of clarification. Point of clarification. Point of clarification, Councilman Pentland. We were never given a contract to look at an executive session. The only thing we had an executive session, which was only once, that was May 20.
and that was to pick the Republic from Tennessee. Yes, we told them to go ahead and negotiate a contract, but we didn't tell them to sign it because if you read the minutes and you look at the tape, it turns around and you have to come back to the council for the vote to accept it. Mr. President, I'd be interested to see the tape of executive session. They don't make one. They don't have one. Right. Councilor De La Ruza. I'm under the impression that this council unanimously in the past endorsed a course of action
regarding a style of enforcement to be undertaken by the mayor. I think you are correct. Say that again, Councilor De La Rosa. To what? Style what? This council unanimously endorsed a style of enforcement to be undertaken by the mayor. What do you mean, style enforcement? What's that?
a style of enforcement, a means of enforcement that we specified for him to undertake, i.e., that the mayor begin by hiring employees to enforce the existing parking laws. Enforcement is not the same as pay-to-park. It's two entirely different subject matters. The mayor decided to make it even more. This council was looking for enforcement. This is about enforcement, Mr. President. No, this is about pay-to-park. This is about enforcement.
It's about paying to park. Well, I, I've had a brief conversation with him. I know there has been some changes made from, uh, the last time as far as if there's going to be some meters and some areas and there's going to be some, uh, designated 30 minute spots, uh, different areas. That's what he said in his press release. Right. So I don't know. He said those are only recommendations. I was told that that's where the, you know, again, um,
Council on my point of information. I believe that because the city retains the right to determine where these kiosks, meters, and free spots are going to go, that the recommendation would go to the Traffic and Off-Street Parking Commission and then they would be the ones who would be implementing this because they retain jurisdiction. We're not giving up any of the sidewalks or any of our streets. I don't think any of us have seen anything. I would hope that on this disc, when we get home tonight, we'll look at it and see what's
what's on there, so that's the best I can give you. Motion to table until we've had opportunity to review the information before us. Motion to table by Councilor DelaRusso. All in favor? Aye. Opposed? None. Motion is tabled. 6-0. This, this, this says parking proposal. It doesn't say parking. I, again, I don't,
I don't know what it says. It says technical and pricing. So I would hope that maybe the, again, I can't speak with what's on here because I don't know. I'd be speaking out of turn if I did say that. And there was a copy of the contract here also. So I don't know what's on the desk. This is what we received from the messenger this evening. You have one right on your desk there, Councilor Pence. If you want to read it over the week and we'll bring it up next week,
That's what's on the table for this week. 14702, offered by Councilor Knight. Be it resolved, Tufts University provide the Memphis City Council with its policy governing the handling of on-campus sexual assaults. Councilor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much. If anybody's been paying attention to the recent debates relative to the Attorney General's race, a hot topic that's been coming up over and over again is sexual assaults on college campuses.
And that prompted me to do a little bit of investigation. And I've come across a number of articles, two of which I provided my council colleagues with, as well as one for the city clerk. But in the Business Insider, I did take a look at a study. And the study was authored by Peter Jacobs, June 4, 2014. It was published in Business Insider. Here are the staggering numbers behind college sexual assault crisis.
More than 99% of sexual assault perpetrators are male. Females account for around 95% of the sexual assault victims. Nearly 80% of the perpetrators are the same race of their victim, and around 90% of the victims know their perpetrator. Freshmen and sophomores in colleges are the most likely to be a victim of sexual assaults. 50% of the sexual assaults happen on Friday or Saturday, the majority of which happen between midnight and 6 AM.
including almost 90% of the assaults when a victim is incapacitated. More than 40% of college sexual assaults happen in either September or October when there's an influx of new students. Around 80% of college sexual assaults happen either in the victim's or perpetrator's living quarters. In a 10-year study of college sexual assault in Massachusetts found that 81% of campus rapes and sexual assaults occurred in an on-campus dormitory. So these numbers were staggering, Mr. President, and when I read them,
made me want to Google Tufts University and sexual assault on campus. And what happened was a very troubling article that I came across saying that the US Department of Education and Tufts University are at odds on the way that they're handling sexual assaults. Marcella Bombardieri, Globe staff from the Boston Globe, published an article on April 29, 2014 that spoke about some of the issues that Tufts University was having with the Department of Education relative to federal funding because of the way they handled the reported on-campus sexual assault.
So with that being said, Mr. President, I think we've all sat up here and said time and time again that our most important job in this community is to keep our residents safe. I'd like to see the updated policy regarding the reporting of on-campus sexual assaults from Tufts University for the opportunity to review it, but also to send it to our chief of police and send it to the Middlesex County District Attorney for their review and recommendation. Thank you, Counselor Knight. Counselor Knight's motion. All in favor? Aye. Opposed?
Motion passes 6-0. Petitions presentation of similar matters. 14703, petition by Joseph Pierre, 194 Harvard Street, Medford, Mass., for Citywide Tax, Inc., 40 Canal Street, Medford, to upgrade cab number 14 from the 1994 bid number 2MEFM75W0
X, X, 683, 3705, to a 2007 Ford bin number 2F8HP71W87X136369. Counselor Mox. Thank you, Mr. President. The papers all appear to be in order. And at this time, I'd move approval. Thank you, Counselor Mox. Name and address for the record.
Thank you, Mr. President and the council. So my name is Pierre Joseph. I'm 194. Mass 02155. Motion for approval. All in favor? Opposed? Motion passes, 6-0. You're all set, chief. Thank you. Thank you. 14704, petition for a common fictional license by Sohel,
599 Broadway Everett, Mass, 021494 SRH Traders, Inc., doing business as DE's convenience at 308 Main Street, Medford. Counselor Marks. Mr. President, again, all the papers appear to be in order. If the gentleman just could give us his hours of operation.
Name and address on the record, please. Good evening, honorable president and all the councillors. My name is MD Rahman, and address is 6 Hayes Road, Rosendale, Boston. Motion for approval? Hours of operation, Mr. President. Hours of operation. 7 a.m. to 11 p.m. Thank you, sir. Thank you, sir. Councillor Del Rosso. How many convenience stores do you operate, sir?
Just the one, this is the first one. But I do have experience because last couple of years I worked for CVS, so I do have some customer service experience before. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you, sir. Motion for approval. All in favor? Opposed? Motion passes 6-0. Name and address for the record. Jim Costello, 160 Brook Street, Medford. Mr. Flynn, does he come down tomorrow morning to the clerk's office to get a certificate?
We'll either mail it to him or if he wants to come in Thursday, something like that. He won't be ready tomorrow. Thursday would be helpful if he came in. And one more question, if I could. He's applied for three permits from the Board of Health. Now for milk, cigarettes, and coffee. How does he go about getting those permits? Well, number one, you have to go and apply to the Board of Health. He has done that. And so the Board of Health should be
pretty much granting it. I would think that if they signed off on this here, I would think that they must be ready, those others. Yeah, okay. I mean, does he go there and get them, or does he- So I'd go up there and- Thursday too? Yeah. All right, thank you for your help. Okay, thank you. Thank you, and good luck. Thank you, sir. Motion for suspension by Councilor Dela Russo.
14708, offered by Councilor Knight. Be it resolved that the Memphis City Council Subcommittee on Zoning and Urbanism examine the issue of the use of electronic cigarettes in establishments where smoking is prohibited. Councilor Knight. Thank you very much, Mr. President. On Friday evening, I was getting some takeout at Bocelli's, and as I was sitting at the bar waiting for my food, the gentleman beside me
took an electronic cigarette out of his mouth and started smoking it. And it didn't mean much to me. And I just kind of looked at him and said, oh, wow. But the couple sitting next to me that was enjoying their dinner wasn't as pleased as I was to see this happen, Mr. President, which got me thinking, you know, what exactly is going on with the regulation of electronic cigarettes here in Medford? And I think with that being said, Mr. President, I did a little bit of research and I found some policy options, copies of which I forwarded to all my colleagues here.
possibly to regulate the sale, regulate the marketing, or regulate the use of such electronic cigarettes. I guess the end all be all resolution would be to ban electronic cigarettes in all places where smoking is prohibited. That's the ideal language from the National Center of Tobacco Control. However, I don't know if that language would actually be something that would work here in Medford. So I thought it would be a worthy endeavor for the subcommittee on zoning and
ordinances to examine it, to find out what our legal rights are and to find out whether or not it's worthwhile for us to come up with a resolution that would do such. I know personally of, um, the health department did receive a couple of calls from different people and they had gone down and spoken. And if I'm not mistaken, I think it is prohibited in places where smoking is prohibited. I can't say that for sure, but I do know of a couple of cases. Um, motion to send that to subcommittee by councilor Knight. All in favor. Councilor Marks.
Where the suggestion of Councilor Knight is offered, should we ask maybe if we can get the Board of Health to give us an opinion first? Yes. Rather than setting up a subcommittee meeting and so forth. It may be helpful. If I can amend that also, Councilor Knight. There's a store on Salem Street that just sells these. I don't know if you, it's right on the corner of like Dudley and Grossman Valvoline. Huh? No, it's not a convenience store. It's just a store that's only sells
electronic cigarettes. It's like a, they're like a distributor there. So maybe a check into what they sell there too. And I don't know, see if that falls into our code too. Councilor Penta. I'd like to further amend it to contact the state department of public health as it relates to, cause they, there is a state policy on electronic cigarettes and a cigarette is considered a cigarette no matter how you use it. So that may be able to just to cut right through the chase and get your answer. Okay.
Councilor Penta, could you repeat that back for the clerk? The State Department of Public Health as it relates to electronic cigarettes. Massachusetts State Department of Public Health. And Karen Rose, right? Got an answer quicker from Karen. On the motion of Councilor Layton as amended by Councilor Penta. All in favor? Karen Rose, too. And Karen Rose, also. All in favor? Opposed? None. 6-0. The motion passes.
14709 offered by Councilor Langel-Kern, be it resolved that the Traffic Commission reinstall the parking by permit only sign that went missing on the corner of Boston and Caper Street. Councilor Langel-Kern. Thank you, President Carvalho. I received a call on this. There is supposedly a sign missing. It did say parking by permit only.
It's on the corner of Boston and Capon Street. So if I could move approval, see if the traffic commission can take a look at this and replace it at their earliest convenience. Thank you. Thank you. Councilor Lococo's motion. All in favor? Opposed? 6-0. Motion passes. Also on this mission, offered by Councilor Marks, be it resolved that the sinking road at 48 Stearns Ave
be repaired in the interest of public safety. Councillor Marks. Thank you, Mr. President. Stearns have had some underground work done. I believe it was six months to a year ago. And part of the street I went by the other night, part of the street towards the lower end of Stearns Ave is actually sinking in where the work was done. So I would ask that clerk of the works from the city go out to that site immediately.
and see what's happening. Mr. President. Was that recently paved at Pearl Street? Yes. Mr. President, what is the information? Councilor Donovan. As Councilor Marks knows, there and Pearl Street had major work done. And those are part of the long lamented repairs in South Medford that weren't carried out in a timely fashion. But I hope that gets redone.
Quickly, I second your motion, Mr. President. All in favor? Aye. Aye. Opposed? None. 6-0. Motion passes. The minutes were passed to Councilor Caravello, who was not there at his desk. Motion to table? Motion to table until next week. All in favor? Aye. Motion to adjourn. All in favor?
Aye. Meeting is adjourned.