On March 29th, 2023, Governor Healey signed into law a supplemental budget bill which, among other things, extends the temporary provisions pertaining to the open meeting lot to March 31st, 2025.
Specifically, this further extension allows public bodies to continue holding meetings remotely without a quorum of the public body physically present at a meeting location and to provide adequate alternative access to remote meetings.
The language does not make any substantive changes to the open meeting while extending the expiration date of the temporary provisions regarding remote meetings from March 31st, 2023 to March 31st, 2025.
Amen.
Indeed.
So we get to 2025.
OK.
Couple more years, so that's good.
Yeah, yeah.
Chris, are you no longer in your house in... No, no, we moved out of the house in Medford at the beginning of April, and we've been here in New Hampshire ever since.
Wow.
And what's happening with the house in Medford then?
I've engaged Charlotte as our real estate agent.
Really?
Thank you, Chris.
And we are selling.
Wow.
Okay.
That's interesting news.
Well, I hope it goes well and works out for us.
Thank you for staying on here from New Hampshire.
Well, you know, I didn't
nothing in the statutes in the city or state statutes compels me to resign.
And you know, I took the job six months ago and not contemplating that I would move out of Medford, but I don't think I'm off the hook quite.
Okay, so we've got Melanie.
Let's see, let's give Joe one more minute.
Okay, well, six of five.
Let's keep going.
And let's see.
So we've got a pretty simple agenda tonight.
We just need to talk about the path forward for the proposed South Street Historic District.
I've got a little bit of news.
The website is back up, and I plan in the next week to add a page to the website with the
the guidelines that we agreed on a couple of meetings ago.
And I heard from Sharon Guzik.
She says she has reached out to her next door neighbor, I believe it's 6 Manning Street, about,
whether she'd be okay with putting her house in the historic district.
And she was.
So that's a small step in the right direction.
That's good.
Here's Joe.
I'm just going to run to grab a quick paper for one second.
Sure.
And we did receive a draft from Chris Skelly of the proposed South Street Historic District.
This would be the preliminary report that we would submit to the Massachusetts Historical Commission for approval.
And Chris Skelly has plenty of experience in this type of report.
So I'm confident that he can finish that up.
You're talking about the preliminary report?
Correct.
Looks great.
Yes, it does.
Anybody else have comments on it?
I did read it.
I read it a little while this afternoon.
It looks fine.
It's a little dry.
It's not really a rock.
It's some good skeleton, Fred, though, right?
It's a good skeleton.
Yeah.
I don't know how much, if any, we want to add a little.
I think so.
I didn't look at any detail, but I think it gives us the basics, the basic bones.
Kevin, can you show me how to turn the volume on?
We can hear you, Joe.
So I thought that was really great, Chris, that there's something from a group between that and the guidelines that Fred put together, some great things we can bring out to the city soon.
I think we need to review what Chris Skelly put together, but it's a great starting point, I think.
I agree.
Anybody else have comments?
I didn't get a chance to read it in full yet.
So I don't know.
Sure.
Okay.
Charlotte, Joe, any comments?
No.
Okay.
I haven't had a chance to read it yet either.
That's fine too.
Sure.
Okay.
All right.
So we need
So as I mentioned, Sharon Guzik reached out to her next door neighbor and at 6 Manning Street and she's on the owners there are on board.
Chris, have you made any progress on reaching out to to residents?
To be honest, you know, not individually.
No.
So so what we have is we have a list of probably half of them in this 18 of them.
This is the number.
I have an opportunity maybe to coming up in the next week or two to do an outreach.
If we could broadcast if I can make a motion but let me talk about it first but for an outreach there's a porch fest coming up in Medford if anybody heard that the porch fest.
I voted.
Yeah, we got it.
Somerville has has done this for a while where they kind of open the community and people can have a bit of a band a second.
And I think maybe at some point they walk through and try and hit a bunch of them with a little small parade.
I'm not sure that that's true, but it's a porch fest.
So what better porch is there in Medford than the grandfather's house?
I got in touch with Miles, who lives at grandfather's and
Kelsey, his wife, about maybe doing something for PorchFest.
And they were excited, they're interested in doing something.
So A, it's going to be out to the public, that particular building, which is really one of the iconic buildings in Medford and probably one of the lynch kingpins of our district right here.
So they're doing that.
And I asked if there'd be the opportunity, Chris Bader, if we could put out a table
Yeah, put a table from the historic district commission commission about this.
And they said, happy to sort of sponsor or allow us to do that.
So what if we put an announcement out?
And again, I know we have to do open meeting and, and let people know about these things.
Chance to say the community, um, this is a chance they can come out and talk about it.
And at the same time, let's write that letter to each of those properties, if we could.
to say these 18 properties have been told about this event.
We haven't contacted them individually with the soft velvet glove so much, but they got a piece of paper from us, from the city, from the district that they've been formally been aware of this new district proposal.
And so by next week, by June 3rd is coming up quick June 3rd, we could have an outreach program, a letter out in the mail to those 18 for the people that we haven't hit.
And, and, you know, we've due diligence if that's the right approach.
Um, I I'm just, uh, concerned about the time it would take to, uh, draft a letter and get it sent to everybody.
It's it's, uh, it's a little, I've done this in the past and it's.
Okay.
I'm thinking with, with, um, with Chris Skelly, Haley had put together and Fred has a little bit of, um, uh, text that, that we could kind of call, cause we were talking about the trifold as well.
And Fred seen that, but, but what's going to be in the trifold at something like that outreach could be handed out.
Um, um, could be a good, um, uh, let's get it done.
You know, let's get it done by that day kind of approach.
So with the language that's in Chris Kelly's thing, I think.
to put together a short letter and I'm happy to kind of put that with some of that language and get it out in the next day or two.
One day, just talking about the potential to meet at PorchFest and that we've done a due diligence of stamping those houses with some information, the thought, and we're done.
At least we've done the beginning steps of informing everyone.
Then the second part is more outreach and public meeting.
Okay.
Chris, I can.
Donovan.
I can help with the language for the little folder, whatever.
You have that already between Chris Kelly's writings and our little blurb that.
Is already in the.
Form B's that.
A little narrative, it has to be only two or three paragraphs, so I don't think that's a big deal.
You're thinking about that for that little trifold give out.
Yeah, you know, the pictures that are in Chris Kelly's, he's already got in his report.
Right.
Well, you know, cut and paste some language out of there and off you go.
So Chris Donovan, my question is, is the grandfather's house, do they have a porch band?
Anybody?
What's going to be cute is a button.
They have a family band.
Oh really?
They have a fleet band and they're putting it together.
They're from different parts of the country and they just love.
The narrative here, I don't want to speak too much, but they're doing their own thing there.
And again, this is just be a get together just like the Victorian straw was a chance to maybe pull a couple of people together and rally some resources.
But if any of us could be there at some point to man that table, but I'm happy to kind of do it, but I think it's 1 to 5, or we can make it limited.
But Chris could make a motion, but we can talk about a little bit more to yeah.
Talk about an outreach, but Fred and I could create a trifold in the next couple of days because I haven't basically the artwork for it.
And then just put some verbiage in there.
That's the trifold, but also to create a simple letter saying that this is a proposal and your house is one of the houses that are is being in is in a strict.
Is that something that we think we could, we could try and a get those letters to those nine, but 18 to be, to be, um, and then announce that we're having a little, um, you know, get together at, at grandfather's house.
Is that a possibility?
We can do that.
Um, we want to get together.
We want to have another meeting to approve the language of the trifold and of the letter.
Um, can we do, can we do that?
I'm happy to put some emphasis on trying to get that, that in.
Cause I think we have the bones of that, but just an executive meeting or is that how that's handled as a, as a quick, it would be a full meeting in principle.
Um, But, uh, Um, you know, it could be, this is just a, just a pretty routine just to, for the commission members to officially sign off on the, uh, on the language of the trifle and the letter.
But yeah, can, well, first of all, Fred and Chris, can you guys pull together something for us to approve by this time next week?
Yeah, probably.
Yeah.
Okay.
If you guys want to include me in any of that, let me know.
I work in marketing, so I can help take a look at it.
Oh, yeah, absolutely.
Thank you, Melanie.
Thank you.
Sure.
Yeah.
Okay, well, yeah, let's, you know.
I have like a PowerPoint with like a, you know, it's like a trifold.
It's kind of basic, but just a couple pictures and then either with the guidelines.
Well, I mean, the language is what's important.
The language is more important than the format or the pictures.
But yes, let's, so why don't, okay, so Fred and Chris, why don't you guys put your heads together?
come up with the language for the letter.
I'm sorry.
And think about what should be in the letter too.
And we can approve all that language a week from today.
And meanwhile, I will call city, Dennis, are you still here?
Dennis, can you and Teresa perhaps pull together an address list for the, well, we'll give you the addresses, but can you put together some address labels for the 18 houses
in the proposal?
Yeah, absolutely.
I can add that pretty quickly, so that's easy enough.
Okay.
Chris Bay, did you have the 18 names to give to Kevin?
I don't, but I think we can probably put them together.
I can take charge of getting those names.
Well, let me ask Dennis another question.
Dennis, if I give you the addresses, can you find the names?
Yeah, because the list I have comes through the assessor.
So it literally just click on the address.
It'll generate labels with the program.
Beautiful.
OK.
So I will send you the list of addresses ASAP.
Can I run them down just verbally?
We don't have to be spot on.
But 1 Walnut Street, 6 Manning, 10 Manning.
I don't think you need to do that, Chris.
It's 18.
We don't need to.
I don't know if we added, but we didn't change anything.
It's, it's, it's right in Chris's, uh, it's right in Chris's, uh, thing, Chris Kelly's thing.
And, uh, you know, we have it in other documents as well.
Um, yeah, we agreed on the 18 property sometime ago.
Um, yeah, so I will send the addresses over to.
To Dennis, um, Fred and Chris will put together the language for the
uh for the trifold and the letter letter with with melanie too come on well of course with melody yes yes yes right because you know i'm willing to help out too so throw me in the room yes yes uh charlotte you you want to be on this too sure okay how about you joe um i'm actually going to be away next week um so do you kind of
difficult for me to jump in on that one.
Right, no problem, no problem.
Yeah.
So June 3rd is PorchFest.
I'll make a motion or something, maybe even next week when we talk about this, but to have people there at the table would be nice if we could have some presence there.
Yes, yes, yes.
Gary, are you volunteering, Chris?
I'll volunteer to be there.
Okay, great, that's terrific.
And I'm not saying it would be an open house at grandfather's house at all, but the couple's very sweet and they were interested in this project.
So, um, after that, Chris, what time will it be?
One to five, but doesn't mean that whole time is there, but in this different component, but the whole porch festival is one to five.
There may be a component that's smaller than that, but I'll get back to you.
Okay.
Yeah, from what I understand, every house has a certain time that they'll be doing it.
So people can walk from house to house and hear different bands.
And so usually it's, you know, it'll be like one to three, two to four, you know, some sort of hour, a couple hours in that timeframe.
Which doesn't mean we can't have a window of our own to have a table outside, but they may be scheduled to play at a particular time.
Thank you, Kevin.
Great.
And what about printing the trifolds, Dennis?
What's the, what are the logistics?
Uh, that might be, do you mean, are they like half by 11?
Then you just chop them into thirds.
I'll get a professional.
I think some, you know, like staples can probably do it.
Um, definitely do it.
Yeah.
I sent you a PDF.
Dennis sends you a PDF.
Yeah, send me it, and I'll just see what we can do.
I'm honestly not sure, because some things we can do, some things we just can't.
We don't know.
OK.
Melanie, can I run that by you?
Are you good with the artwork or that stuff?
I can help with the messaging stuff.
I'm not really great with the artwork stuff, but I can help.
Just the format of it.
Yeah, it's the format and stuff.
But if you do want to trifold, even I'm sure even whatever, we can talk about it.
So just send me what you get.
We'll take care of that, Chris Bader.
Thank you.
Oh, this is looking great.
I'm really, I'm really, you know, because I was thinking, oh, geez, can we pull this together by June 3rd?
But apparently we can.
So, yeah.
And then not to take the next step, but it sounds like we'll have our official outreach done for at least the properties, potentially the neighborhood.
Chris Bader, was that a second thing we had to do?
Not only the properties, but the neighborhood.
We'll be sending out the letters to the actual property owners.
We'll be passing out the trifolds at the meeting.
I'm sorry, at the porch fest.
Yeah, we should probably also send them to everybody who lives within 300 feet of any property.
Could we pay for walk him that day, Dennis or is that something we need to put it in the mail.
What, what are you asking.
We may have a little flyer and we want to find people.
Should that be done through the mail system to registered mail?
Or should, could, could we send someone around and put it in, put it in the door?
You know, I think you're fine.
I mean, you know, it's probably.
you know, five to one, seven, the other, you know, it's close enough either.
I mean, whichever, depending on the time you get in the time, how, how soon in advance, because unfortunately the mail has been a little bit slow sometimes.
I mean, I've sort of found when I mail stuff from the city hall, it usually takes about four days to get to people, even going from Medford to Medford.
So the two parts of that is one, we, we want to officially notify the 18.
Do we have to officially notify the next, you know, contiguous.
Okay.
So what I propose is this, we,
um, we notify the actual owners by mail.
Um, we print up the, um, we print up the trifolds and we have, I don't know, you know, a hundred of them at the, uh, PorchFest, something like that.
And, um, uh, and then not necessarily coordinated with PorchFest.
We mail them.
or distribute them by some other means, but that doesn't have to happen by June 3rd to everybody who is within 300 feet of any of the properties.
And we would probably want to change the language of the trifold to reflect the date and time of the public hearing.
We thought the trifold was just kind of a message, like what is a historic district and then a little bit of, you know, the person.
So let's, um, let's hold up.
Maybe we'll, maybe let's, let's hold off, uh, till maybe our next regular meeting, what should go to, to, you know, the probably a hundred or so people that live within 300 feet of one of those properties.
Cause it's a somewhat different message.
Right.
Um,
Yeah, so let's do that.
Is everybody cool with that?
Is that?
Okay, good.
It makes sense.
Yeah.
And we're moving along.
Oh, we're definitely moving along.
This is exciting, actually.
When that's out to the contiguous within 300, then we have a public meeting to deal with?
Right.
So the things that have to happen before the public hearing are,
We want to send out probably a different trifold or maybe a letter with the trifold, you know.
A letter, a letter.
To everybody who lives within 300 feet of any property.
And we want to submit, we want to finish up Chris Kelly's report or we want him to finish it up.
And we want to schedule the public hearing.
But those are all things we don't need to do tonight.
If I could ask Chris Bader, since Melanie and Charlotte want to maybe get involved, the Chris Skelly report is really great, but it probably could use some beef, and that's what we're going to present.
Maybe look at that, Charlotte, with your real estate background.
Enhance the language of it.
I think the language, frankly, could be more persuasive.
And Fred, would the guidelines that you've written, would any of that slide in there with some sense of what either, is this of the guidelines or that it's not as restrictive in that?
So it seems like it's another, the guidelines are different from what Chris Skelly just wrote, correct?
Guidelines are different.
That's correct.
follow all the every district we're trying to sort of blanket the city i wonder if any of that language which fred could go in with chris skelly's report about medford's what we're doing is that make sense or is it two different animals animals
You know, I, I thought that too, when I read his report, whether we should include those guidelines or not, I don't know the answer to that.
Maybe a little bit.
If you could look at that and Charlotte and Melanie too, if you're, um, um, if you're, if you're a real estate, I'm going to have Charlotte's pretty, pretty good at that.
Um, is there anything we could throw in, in, in Chris Kelly's report, either for flowery, um, a question and answer type thing, right.
You can do a Q and a around, um,
around climate questions, requirements and stuff.
You know, everyone always tells me, oh, you're in the historic district.
You tell me what I can do.
I'm like, we're actually pretty lenient to most other cities and towns when you think about it.
We're not nearly as strict as people like Lexington or Concord or even Somerville.
We're pretty lenient and we work with people.
That's been my experience since I've been on this commission anyways.
And I have talked to a lot of people and I think a lot of people are concerned about our historic
homes and land buildings and not being preserved the way they should be preserved.
So I think you can address that.
I'd like to take that line, Melanie.
I think a lot of people are concerned about about a historic.
That's a that's a good one.
And the other line that I remember from Chris Bates, I don't think we've ever said no to anyone.
Yeah.
You know, so I think I think we just I think just having a Q&A and because I think a lot of people
feel like they'll have to spend a lot of money when they want to go refurbish stuff or do things and the materials and other stuff like that.
But I think you can address that in the Q&A instead of say specific.
What does this mean for me if I want to replace something in my house?
You know, you can address that with an answer.
Well, could I ask Melody if there is a Q&A, I believe, on our website that was written 10 years ago?
Yeah.
And it probably needs to be updated because I know some people have taken issue with some of the answers to the question.
So we might need to look at that because I think that needs to be revisited and it could be updated with our new guidelines that we passed and maybe softened up a little bit from what might be in there right now.
Is that true, Chris Bader on our website?
We should probably, there is, so Melanie, there is an FAQ on the website, but we know from experience with homeowners in proposed, so there was an issue some time ago with a house, I'm forgetting the address.
It was close to, it was in South Medford, close to the Whole Foods.
At any rate, the homeowner, it was an 1840s house.
Yes, I looked at that house, I wanted to buy it.
It sold for a million dollars, I think, so a crazy amount of money.
That was like five, 10 years ago, right?
It's the yellow ones on the back on Capon Street, not Capon Street, on Cotting Street.
Talking about that one?
Yeah.
Anyway, the people who own it now took serious issue with the FAQ.
And it was mainly that that turned them off.
to the creation of a single house historic district for their house.
So yeah, we want to revisit the RFAQ based on the guidelines we just approved.
And you know, if you want to collaborate with, you know, have some input.
Take a look and just
look at them and see if I can make it.
If you could, if you could pull one out, Melanie, if you think there's two or three really good ones in there that could be added to, you know, to the Chris Scully's report or something, or we'll call it for that letter.
So the 300 boundary, 300, you know, we'll call it the abutters letter, abutters letter.
Sure, sure.
Okay.
So, yeah, it sounds like we're on the right track here.
the, um, you know, the, the, the letter and the, um, and the trifold should be, this is basically where we're, this is not in preparation for the public hearing, right?
This is, this is just saying, here's a great idea.
Here's something that will really preserve, uh, one of Medford's historic neighborhoods.
Uh, you know,
it's sort of a, it's really marketing, basically, we're, we're, we're, we want to sell people on this idea.
Right.
So what I would say to you, and to Chris Donovan, and Fred and Melanie is and to Charlotte and is, you know, let's make it, we're trying to sell this idea.
So let's not go into
let's not bend over backwards to say what you can and can't do.
We want to sell the idea in the trial.
And we want to be as user friendly as possible in the letter to the owners.
And maybe the letter can just be, we will be scheduling a public hearing in the near future.
uh to uh um to hear your opinions do we want to which which kind of leads to the next point is do we want to are we confident enough that we can get this done that we're we're that we
want to schedule the public hearing now or do we want to wait till the next?
We should probably wait till the next.
Let's wait for PorchFest so people don't think there's something on.
We're still listening.
We're still kind of open.
But let's wait for the PorchFest if we could, Chris.
I think that's a good idea.
I think that's an excellent idea.
Um, anybody else have any comments?
Chris, is there a chance we can go over the, um, um, um, Chris Kelly's report even just quickly, just, just looking at just a little bit of it together.
Um, let's just, let's sure in a minute, let's just make sure that we're, we're cool with the plan of action for putting the trifold together by, uh, by next week, putting the letter together by next week.
And, uh,
Can a reasonable number of people attend a meeting a week from today?
How about you, Charlotte?
I'm pretty sure I can do that.
Same time?
Same time, yeah.
Fred?
Real quick.
I should be able to do that, yeah.
OK, Chris Donovan?
Yes.
OK, Melanie?
Sorry, can you repeat that?
My son interrupted me.
A week from today, same time?
Let me just check my calendar.
Yeah.
That'd be fabulous.
Okay, and Joe, you're going to be busy, right, or out of town?
I'm going to try to make it, but I'm going to be out of town in Tennessee, and I'd have to check with my wife what the itinerary is.
Well, I hear they've got internet there.
It would just be really approving the paperwork and then maybe talking about it.
We're just going to run through the language and say, yeah, this sounds fine.
OK.
Yeah.
So all right.
So that's taken care of.
Let's talk about, do people want to go through?
Well, here's the thing, Chris Donovan, is some people haven't had time to read it yet, right?
Yes.
So why don't we postpone going through that line by line until either next week or to our regular June meeting?
Does that make sense?
Yes.
I'm just flipping through the report right now.
You can see how it's broken into sections and it's really kind of well laid out.
Again, it could be fattened up.
But I want to give people time to think about it and think about what's in there, but also what's not in there, right?
What else needs to go in there?
And I would like Form Bs.
We do have the funds to do Form Bs and we approved that a few meetings ago.
The missing Form Bs, I think there are three of them.
Um, actually, uh, yeah.
And with those foreign bees, Chris, that we, we, we, we have the potential to get, um, Chris Kelly doing them or do we say we have another, what's his name?
John Clemson is doing them and I just need an update from him.
I'll give you, I'll give you guys an update next week.
on what the status of that is.
And that's just more narrative on some of the homes that weren't.
Exactly.
That just means that we have absolutely, you know, I really believe in, I don't know if you guys remember the first Gulf War, but there was an idea bandied about called the Powell Doctrine.
Overwhelming force, right?
So I'm a real believer in the Powell Doctrine and we want to just
be as strong as we can going forward with this idea.
We want to have all the Form Bs.
We want to do as much outreach as possible.
I think the ForgeFest is a fantastic idea.
And so, yeah, let's wait till
till next week or our next regular meeting to discuss the... And Chris Bader, I don't know the timeline of a river fest and not to make this too public, but it does showcase that area.
So maybe as another event, I think it's... Say again, Melody?
I think there's also an Italian fest coming up too, isn't there?
Well, the River Fest, just because it's right there on the water, but for all the... I think the Italian Fest is right there on the water, too.
On the water?
Okay.
It's June 4th at the Continental area.
Oh, same day or the next day?
I think it's the day after.
Fortress is Saturday.
The Italian Fest is... The Italian Festival is... Monday.
Oh, okay.
Let's focus on Porchfest because, for one thing, the owners of Grandfather's House are willing to
I mean, as an example, though, on, on, on that next, if we did have the sort of public meeting coming up, it wouldn't be a bad idea to have a table at, at some of these local events and saying, Hey, one of the latest initiatives in the area.
History.
And if I could just see if there's a request that maybe I'll make a motion that next thing about trying to bring in the historical society, bringing the mayor's office in to help us either with an announcement or.
you know, releasing something together as a, you know, a plan.
I don't know how we do that, but it seems like, you know, it's a citywide thing and not just our organization promoting this.
Let me talk to the mayor about that and see if we can get her on board with
making a push for this.
Understood.
Coach Fest will be a nice thing for us to start our own flag and have something there.
And yeah, yeah, this will be two or three weeks away.
Charlotte's going to be there at the booth, right, Charlotte?
I'm bummed.
I'm not going to be here.
Is it a booth or am I just going to be on the porch?
We're going to have some fun.
Tell me, where do you want me?
We'll sit out there in front for the Victorian stroll.
They had beautiful games out front.
Porch is massive.
It's such a great welcoming environment.
We'll have some fun, so we'll find a place in the sun there.
Yeah.
Are we talking about the grandfather's house?
Grandfather's house will be at PorchFest day, and we'll figure out the times.
That's where the PorchFest will be.
Okay.
Terrific.
Thank you guys for doing this.
And what time will it be?
We'll get back to you at the next meeting next week.
Okay.
Thank you.
make a motion.
Uh, so do we have more to discuss before next week?
I'm good.
Okay.
Melanie.
Melanie, can I just have your email, Melanie?
Um, M M. Thank golly.
My last name.
Mm.
Trigali.
Yeah.
At yahoo.com.
Thank you.
Okay, okay, so I think we're done here.
I think Fred, you know, so the leads on the- Before we do, can I make a motion for $200 for pastries or something for the fest?
Do we have a budget for some pastries?
I think that's fine.
All right.
Do we need to take a vote for that or is it something you could pick up?
I'm happy to do anything.
I don't think we need a vote for this, frankly.
Yeah, but yeah, I will talk to the purchasing and
and see how this is supposed to be built, but yeah, let's... Oh, I know how to do it, exactly.
If I could add the word Colette's Bakery into that.
Colette's Bakery?
I'll tell you what, Chris, just buy the pastries and submit an expense report to me, I will approve it, and you'll get reimbursed from City Hall.
And we'll save a piece for Melanie.
Absolutely.
I like that bakery.
Let's see.
OK, anything else?
All right, so the leads on the letter and the trifold are Fred and Chris.
Please pull in me and, well, any other members that are interested.
If you have a draft, please circulate it.
to Charlotte and me and Joe.
I'll get that up before next week.
And please have something, you know, at least a draft that's sort of press ready by, say, end of day on Wednesday.
Does that sound reasonable?
Yeah, yeah.
If Melody and Charlotte could deal with the letter, the letter, you know.
I'll draft a letter and present a draft for approval.
That's the abutters letter.
Yeah, yeah.
Well, it's not the abutters.
This is just the letter to the owners.
Oh, okay.
And that could be short and sweet, right, Chris?
That could be short and sweet.
And it's going to be.
Because we haven't set the date for the
preliminary hearing.
So what I will do is I would just lay out what they, that we're considering their property for inclusion in a local historic district.
They will be, this is a multi-step process, and I will mention what the steps are.
And, you know, I, and I will just say, you know, we solicit, we will be soliciting your input at every step of the way, including the public hearing.
and it's a celebration of Medford's history.
Yes.
All right, so we have another meeting scheduled next Thursday, right at six o'clock.
Six o'clock, same time, same place.
Okey-doke.
All right.
Okay.
Thank you all.
Thank you, everybody.
Bye.
Thank you.
All right, bye-bye now.
See you later.
Bye-bye.