. .
I'm not speaking. I'm sorry. Yep. Here it is. Maybe you should sit in the center.
Okay, so we have up next is approval of minutes June 3rd. Is there a motion to approve the minutes? Is there a second? Okay, excellent. All those in favor? Aye. Excuse me, counsel. Yes, yes, Mr. Benedetto. Thank you. So these are the April 1st school committee meetings that we're approving?
Right? This is the minutes of June 3rd. Oh, okay. Never mind. It's a motion to approve. It's fine. Yep. Did you get that? Yeah. And you pack it. All right. And so up next is approval of bills, transfer of funds, approval of payrolls. Motion to approve. Do I have a question? Is there a second? A question? Okay, Mr. Benedetto. Thank you. As usual. So, on page 2 of 15.
About almost halfway down, Erzner, first name Eric, $107.82. It says pending classification. So that is a special fund program. So there is not a classification for that particular fund, but it is for school-wide expenditures. I can get you what specifically was reimbursed for that particular item. OK.
In my next question that was actually I'm sorry that that was for Eric Eisen that was reimbursement for the ethics bowl that he had chaperoned Okay on a particular funding
Yeah, we just don't usually see that pending classification notice. OK, so the next one is on page 8 of 15. And it might be the second grouping of second packet. It says legal services for $3,000 more than halfway down.
Judith Impatori? Yes, that's under the IDEA grant. And we couldn't use in-house legal services? It's specific for special education. Okay.
That is all I have. Wonderful. Okay, great. Hall in whose second? Okay, is there a second? Second. Mr. Benedetto. Okay, great. And we do the roll call vote. Roll call vote, please. Member Di Benedetto. Yes. Member Kretz. Yes. Member Stone. Yes. Member Gero. Yes.
next up is report of secretaries and I do have a okay so we're going to move on to report of committees so we had a committee of the whole and we just evaluated the superintendent and
And the mayor's going to do it when she comes back. OK, that's right. OK, great. So we're going to hold off on that one. Next is Special Education Subcommittee. Erin DiBenedetto. Thank you. So we had a Special Education Subcommittee meeting on May 28 of 2019. And we talked further about the two issues, two items that we have been working on throughout the school year. The first is disability awareness program. And the second is out of school time programming for all students.
So, in it, we had many people in attendance, committee members, Paulette Vander Kloot, Paul Rousseau, we had the CPAC coordinators, co-chairs rather, and we talked a little bit about the new PD program that was given to district teachers where disability awareness was infused with the existing curriculum.
And Teachers Wrote Inclusive Curriculum in an Impactful Presentation was given by Melanie McLaughlin. For the first of these six classes, approximately 45 teachers attended this programming. It went extremely well and was very well received by
the professionals in our district. We went further on to talk about our OST, which is something I call it, is out of school time programming. That would be before and after school programming, summer programming, and camps that happen.
Inclusive and welcoming wording was added to the summer fun camp and before and after school handbooks. The summer fun camp staff are hired and ready to go and inclusive training will occur prior to the first week of camp. Before and after school programs were not fully staffed at the end of this year.
They reached out to returning college students coming back home and tried to fill the gaps with those students. Enrollment for next year, for the after school,
Program is there is a long wait list at multiple schools inclusive training will begin Be given to all of those new team members prior to the beginning of the school year and we ended this meeting with the goodbye celebration for Kathy Medaglio and thanking her for all her years of service to the method public school community and
She's been a wonderful director of student services, and we've been very lucky to have her serving our students in our community for all these years. And she's sitting here this evening, so again, I want to thank her. That's the report. OK. Motion to accept. Do I have a second? Yes. Second. Sure, absolutely.
Okay, and so I have a report from the Rules Subcommittee. We had two meetings. One was on June 13th and the other one was on June 19th. The purpose of our meetings was to update the rules and regulations of the Memphis School Committee. Everyone has in their packets a copy of the old document
It was either from 2004 or older. We're really not sure about the historical date. And you have a copy of the updated 2019 document. And we went through and we updated chapters 1 through 10. So we broke it up into two separate meetings. On the June 13th, we discussed chapters 1 to 6.
In June 19, we discussed chapters 7 to 10, and we made a motion to accept the changes that were put ahead in the documents. You'll see throughout the entire document, we removed words such as chairman, replaced it with chairperson, and words
him, his, or her were replaced with gender-free words. Also, you will see a new section at the bottom of the documents, and thank you to Mr. Russo for coming up with this great idea. It is the policy information, such as first adopted date, last amended date, last renewed date, renewed frequency, next renewal, and version number, so that we can easily identify what
the age of the document and determine like when is it going to need to be updated the next date. And I want to just thank all the committee members for coming to the meetings. We did spend several hours in the meetings going through the very old language and updating it to
you know, 2019 language. Some of it was very old. And we also reached out to several different administrators. Diane Caldwell assisted. Christine Patterson assisted. Let's see, Headmaster DeLever, Principal Fallon, Supervisor of Nurses Tony Ray, and, you know, emailing, just going back and forth.
Thank you to Dr. Edward Vincent. She was a great asset to the meeting as well. And my colleagues, thank you as well. Thank you all for your hard work and efforts. And I hope everybody had a chance to review the documents. And Erin, did you have a question? I have actually two questions regarding this document. Okay.
on page three, towards the bottom, section six. It says, any Method resident in attendance may be given permission to speak once at the school committee meetings regarding any item on the agenda for up to three minutes on any one item. It just makes it sound like a resident can only come to the mic and speak once throughout the whole meeting. The wording of that. May I? Yes, go ahead. So that is a reference only to the
There's an item on the agenda and you want to say something. This isn't the regular community participation. You can come to each item if you want to speak on.
five of the items on the agenda. You'd be able to come up five times, yeah. Great, just looking for clarification there. Okay. And my second question isn't on the next page, four out of 15, section eight. Section eight, okay. Group committee members who wish to place items on the agenda will provide written notice to the chairperson by Monday noon prior to the scheduled meeting or at the discretion of the chairperson based on extenuating circumstances.
So I have a question. Does a chairperson get to decline any item brought forward by a member to be put on the agenda? Because that happened to me last year. I wanted an item added to the agenda and the chairperson executed their right not to put it on the agenda. And I would like that addressed in this policy. Mr. Russo? Yes. So this is actually, other than the date, this is current policy.
And because it also earlier states we're following Robert's rules newly revised, if that happens, and it's happened to me as well, then that can be at the next regularly scheduled meeting. Then a member can simply ask that it be put on the agenda anyways for the following meeting. And then if as long as four members say, yes, we want that on the agenda, then the chair loses the right to say no effectively. So the chair does have the right to not put it on.
but we can override at the next official meeting. So, I mean, that's sort of the way it's been. I'm not sure we've ever done that. I would like to see a change where the chairperson does not have the right to put a member's item on the agenda, only because as elected officials, we're here to voice for the community, and I think that a chairperson
having that override really prevents you from doing your due diligence as a school committee member. So I am requesting that that be added to this. If I may? I mean, our charter says Robert's Rules newly revised, and that gives the chair that authority. I don't think we can do a policy that overrides the charter.
That's, I mean, we can write anything we want here, but that doesn't mean it's enforceable, and that's sort of my issue.
We do have that if there is like a stated emergency that would require that that the chair refuses to recognize point of clarification But but you're not saying an item not on the agenda can be discussed
Well, in terms of an emergency situation, so we do have the authority via open meeting laws to discuss those issues. If the chair refuses to put that emergency item on the agenda, we can force that issue to be recognized under open meeting law as long as there's a super majority and we wouldn't violate any open meeting clause if it's an emergency situation. I just think the word emergency
I just can't foresee the chairperson not putting it on the agenda if there's an actual emergency. Nor could I. But we do have that authority as a body. The emergency can't be every person gets to decide what's an emergency, and that I'm a little concerned about. Just because I think it's important and we need to talk about it doesn't make it an emergency. A supermajority would have to agree that it is an emergency.
All right, well, I can just, I accept that that's the rule. I also feel like it's a little bit of censorship as a, that one person from our committee gets to decide whether or not something is discussed on any given week. So, I object to that, but I'm happy with moving forward with this at this point.
Yes. So is there a motion to accept the report? Yes, I make a motion to accept the report. Is there a second? Second. Mr. Ochoa. Okay, thank you. All in favor? Aye. And is there anybody here for community participation? No? Okay. Okay, so report from superintendent.
As you are aware, Medford Public Schools ended classes on Thursday, June 13th.
On Monday, June 17th, my team and I engaged in a three-day retreat with all school administrators. The interactive retreat continued until Wednesday, June 19th, and was held at the Bistro 489. We discussed many topics including, but not limited to, the social-emotional health of our students, leadership and professional development, mentorship of new educators,
events scheduling across the district, after school programming and space, technology updates in the district, and mobile communication apps.
Medford High School assistant principal, Gail Trainor, was presented with the newly inaugurated Mustang Administrator Unsung Hero Award for her outstanding work, not only as an assistant principal, but also for her work as coordinator for the Credit for Life Financial Literacy Fair, and her meticulous planning and organization of the recent Medford High School, Medford Vocational School graduation ceremony.
We were excited that our incoming assistant superintendent, Dr. Peter Cushing, also joined us during the retreat. Administrators will continue their work over the summer, the work that was started at the retreat, in preparation for the new school year. And we will have a opening of school administrative meeting in August for all administrators, again, for us to work and plan for the school year that's coming.
Medford Public Schools is going to be quite busy over the summer. Summer school began today, as well as our annual summer fun day camp. Some of Medford's recreation programs are being held in the district, as well as special education and EL summer programs. The vocational side of the house hosted their CTE camp for middle schoolers last week, and over 40 students participated.
Many athletic camps are also being hosted by the Medford High School basketball, volleyball, and soccer programs. Mustang Girls softball team had a good run in the MIAA softball playoffs, earning a bye in the first round, beating the Woburn Tanners in the second round, and unfortunately, losing to Central Catholic in the third round.
The team finished with a 19-3 record. Congratulations to Coach Dempsey, Coach Paggs, and the girls on a fantastic season.
Additionally, Coach Dempsey notified me that Captain Brenna Forbes will be named to both the Boston Globe and the Boston Heralds, all scholastic softball teams. It is not often that a high school athlete is selected by both of Boston newspapers. A National Honor Society student, Brianna will be attending Colby College in the fall and is planning to play both hockey and softball there.
We congratulate her and her family, and as many of you know, her mother, Rayanne, is a Medford High School girls hockey coach. Tristan Howard, he competed nationally in the 200 meters last weekend. Unfortunately, he was disqualified for stepping out of bounds. Had he stayed in bounds, he would have finished 18th in the nation. We still applaud him for a fantastic year and look forward to his senior year in the fall.
Athletic Director Bob Maloney and Headmaster DeLeva welcomed a new girls basketball coach at Medford High School. Molly Waite, an educator in Melrose, was chosen as the new head coach. She has experience as both a player at Westfield State University and as a coach at many different levels. We welcome Coach Wyatt to the Mustang family.
Last Saturday, the top two winners from the Andrews Middle School 7th grade science fair were asked to present their work at the MIT Museum for visitors and guests. The students, Eric Brown, Matthew Harris, and Sarah Braverman, attended with their teacher, Eric Prylison, and were excited to be able to discuss their projects. Mr. Prylison connected with the museum last year, and the museum decided to partner with the Andrews in this way.
Some of you were able to join with us as Medford High School's Gay-Straight Alliance, GSA, dedicated the pride flag along with a plaque that reads, Love Wins, in the main lobby of the school. If you noticed it in last Thursday's Globe, the GSA was highlighted for their participation in Boston's 2019 Pride Parade. We applaud Nicole Shalafo and Emily Simpson and all the students for their outstanding work.
We have spoken a lot about the opportunity for the middle school students to work together, and this year, Learn Something, Make Something in the library was introduced to students in the Andrews and McGlynn Middle School Libraries. The MPS Middle School Libraries and Medford Public Library successfully partnered to offer a series of STEAM workshops to middle school students during the year. All workshops were held after school in the school library about every other week, alternating between the two schools.
All middle school students were invited to sign up. The workshops provided a nice bridge between books and hands-on learning and had students see the library as a place for active learning and critical thinking. The Medford Public Schools would like to thank the Medford Public Library, the Medford Arts Council, and the Massachusetts Cultural Council for their support of this wonderful project. We can't wait to see what they will do next year. Thank you.
Thank you very much madam superintendent member Mr.. Gero motion to take papers number three out of order, please on the motion for suspension of the rules to take a paper out of order Is there a second seconded by mr. Russo all those in favor? All those opposed motion passes item 3 recognition of Kiwanis Club literacy project miss Caldwell
Good evening again. First of all, this isn't just a literacy project. I'd like to welcome our Kiwanians that are here this evening. There's a whole bunch of them.
This report is in recognition of the incredible year-long support to all of the students and to the staff of Medford. Throughout the year, the Kiwanis Club worked with our staff and students about becoming better citizens and making positive contributions to their community.
The list below provides you with some of the many activities the Kiwanis Club is involved with in our schools. The Builders Club at both the Andrews and the McGlynn Middle Schools help our kids with fundraising so that they can give back to the less fortunate. One of the fundraisers helped to support the Medford Food Bank.
The Key Club is the oldest service program for high school students. It is a student-led organization whose goal is to encourage leadership through serving others. Under the leadership of Mrs. Melissa Solomon this year, students had the opportunity to earn community service hours for their participation.
students forged strong friendships with each other the key club enriched students lives through a greater sense of social concerns and Improved the community of Medford as a whole But the Kiwanis Club does more it supports our center for citizenship and social responsibility otherwise known as CCSR as well as Medford high school athletics
football, band, hockey, and the culinary arts program. Additionally, the Kiwanis Club supports the Medford High School Alumni Association and has sponsored the MHS Up All Night Junior Prom.
The Literacy Project is something that's very, very close to my heart, as you all know. It provides summer reading books to our first and third grade students. We've been doing this for a long time, and I consider myself an adopted Kiwanian. You are, you are.
So this was an idea that was brought to us in Medford Public Schools many, many years ago for some of our kiddos who don't have books to read during the summer. So the Kiwanis orders books for grade 1 and books for grade 3 in every single one of our elementary schools.
as well as our private parochial schools as well. And when you see these kids open up their bags and pull out these books, the smile on their faces is just incredible. And they already want to start reading, and then they look at their books and say, oh, wait a minute, I read, this is a girl's book, maybe I should give this to my friend. And they want to swap right away. But we tell them they have to wait until they get back to their classroom.
So, our thanks to all of the Kiwanis members and what they do for the City of Medford, but most importantly, what they do for our children. So, Ms. Kelly Catalo is now the President of the Kiwanis Club. We would like to present you with a Certificate of Appreciation.
the Medford Public Schools is proud to recognize the Kiwanis Club with sincere appreciation for their dedication to the students of Medford. Mayor Stephanie Muccini-Burke, Chairman,
Oh, chairman, it says. We need to change that. Chairperson. Chairperson. We just did all our rules changes. I know, I know. Didn't make it to the certificate. Kathy Kritz, vice chairperson. We got that one right. Erin DiBenedetto, Mia Mustone, secretary. Dr. Maurice Edouard Vincent, superintendent. Michael Ruggiero, Paul Russo, and Paulette van der Kloof. Very good.
Privilege at being at some of your book giveaways and the kids faces are just like they're so excited and so elated and all that you do for our community from your road races to Everything that you do is just outstanding and we so adore having you in our community and everything you bring to it So thank you all the Kwanians that again tonight I know councillor Carviello would have been here if he could have he's in a budget hearing at City Hall But I know he would not have missed this for the world. So congratulations
So on behalf of our Kiwanis family, we want to thank you for giving us the opportunity to partner with you on all these great things for our children, because it creates one great community in Medford. I'm very proud of how much our club has grown in numbers.
and in spirit this year, and the many things that we've been able to do. And this was a night that needed to be shared with the whole family. So we hope that we didn't bring too many. No, no. I love it. It's awesome. And we want to acknowledge Representative Paul Donato, member of the Kiwanis, who's also here tonight. So thanks for joining. Thank you, Paul. Very good. Thank you.
recommendation to approve mass general cannabis study to miss Ray
Good evening. We've been fortunate to have Dr. Randy Schuster here twice at our school committee meetings. First to present some up-to-date information about
adolescent marijuana use, as well as the impact on the developing brain. And second, to provide information about the research study that she's conducting on marijuana abstinence. Dr. Schuster has partnered with several Massachusetts school districts, and her data is demonstrating many positive outcomes from marijuana abstinence.
As a district, we've used the SBIRT model to open conversations about substance use, to identify students who are engaging in risky behaviors, provide education and support, and make appropriate referrals. And Dr. Schuster's study will expand upon this support and assist counselors, nurses, and parents in providing assistance to our students.
We plan to use SBIRT screening as the model, which mandates that we ask students about their marijuana use. A brief voluntary survey will be conducted with all high school students to determine who would be interested in participating in the study. At that time, enrollment in the study will require student and parent consent through the Mass General Hospital Institutional Review Board process.
Confidentiality will be maintained throughout the duration of the study unless the interviewer deems that the student is harmful to himself or others. So it's my recommendation and supported by the high school administrative staff that we approve Dr. Schuster's study at Medford High School beginning the fall of 2019. I make a motion to accept. I second. I have a question. There's a motion on the floor for acceptance of this and a second by Ms. Kratz. Mr. Russo has a question.
Yes, so I know when this was presented, we were considering going to middle school as well. I'm curious why we're not including middle schoolers. Dr. Seuss, I think I'll have to defer to you on that one.
The short answer is I will go wherever you say it's OK for me to go. I spoke with one of the principals on the way out today, and he said the doors were open. We have the staff to work in middle schools and high schools. We are going to be in multiple middle schools across the state in the fall.
It is my belief that the younger we can start this conversation, the better. So I would be wholeheartedly in favor of rolling out in both middle schools and high schools, in the middle schools and the high school in the fall. But if it's the preference of the committee to start in year one in the high school and then reevaluate in year two, I'm open to that as well. But as I said in the book. Shall I just make an amendment?
Actually, I just first want to ask Ms. Ray if she has any reservations or any reason.
Okay, well then I would like to amend this to include the middle school. Second. Motion to amend as seconded by Ms. DiBenedetto. On the main motion as amended, Mr. Ruggiero. Two questions as well. Thank you. The first question I have was your mix of the opt-in versus the opt-out model that you have. So the original screening, students are just going to have the survey if they want to fill it out or not. Is that an option?
But if they get included in the study, it requires both consent of the student and the parent. Is that still the model that we're using? Absolutely. Great. And the second question I had is, you mentioned before that it would be possible to include other questions, a couple of other questions. It would be great if we could have a question also on vaping and a question on maybe activity levels, including like diabetes and like sugary drink consumption.
So our survey, as it stands right now, and I believe it was in some of the materials that I gave you a few weeks ago, we have a lot of questions on vaping in there. I think that's something that we really need to be thinking about in tandem with marijuana use. So we are capturing that extensively at a school-wide level. And I'm happy to add an additional question about activity level. Yeah, it would be nice if we could have a question about sugary drink consumption as well, because that is a really rising health cost, as you noted. Yep, and that is information that we collect at detail.
when students are enrolled in the study. So that's certainly information that already I know that we can deliver back. But the screener, the school-wide screener is certainly amenable. Yeah, I don't know if this requires an amendment. And I also don't want to jeopardize the scientific value by including every single question under the sun. But if it doesn't actually jeopardize the scientific value of your study, I would prefer questions about obesity and sugary drink consumption and activity levels to also be included
Perhaps Ms. Ray could work on them. We can definitely work together. I think we'd have to discuss how that would link together in terms of this study and whether it's, you know. Of course. But I don't want to invalidate any work that. Of course. That's the most important. I mean, I understand. I don't want you to jeopardize the scientific value of what you're doing by expanding out the scope. I appreciate that. And what I can say is I'm certainly open to it. I don't think it would jeopardize the scientific scope of the study whatsoever.
The potential rate-limiting step on my part will be the MGH and Harvard Medical School IRB. They need to see that all questions are directly related to the scientific goals of the study, and they don't want us taking advantage of that opt-out process. So barring that they say no to that, I'm perfectly open to it. I mean, I don't think this requires an amendment, but if you could look into that for us, I'd really appreciate it. May I just ask the question, though? Yeah. What would you see as the link
between those questions and this study? Well, I would imagine, I mean, I'm speculating, I don't have the scientific data in front of me, but I would imagine that children that tend to be less active and also have a poorer dietary environment
also have a higher likelihood to use marijuana. I don't know if I have any evidence of that, but it would seem at least sort of, you know, you imagine sort of the person smoking pot, watching TV, eating Doritos. I mean, that could be a cliche, or perhaps there's some scientific truth to that fact. I don't know. So one of the things that we're collecting that you'll be interested in that is a
important outcome of the part of the project where we require parental consent. So once they actually enroll in the study, as we look at when an adolescent stops using marijuana, what happens to their activity level, and
So those are things that we're directly linking to changes in marijuana use and can certainly look into adding in at the school level. Yeah, the reason why I mention it is I've had a couple of parents now talk to me about, you know, their child was involved in middle school sports and they were very athletic and then the vaping and the drug use came into their lives and all of that stopped. So, I mean, I would be curious to see whether that correlation actually is valid or if it's just sort of like word on the street what I hear.
Thank you, Doctor. There is a motion on the floor to approve Dr. Randy Schuster's marijuana abstinence study at Medford High School and Medford Middle Schools for the 19-20 year. Roll call vote, please. 7 in the affirmative, 0 in the negative. Motion passes.
Recommendation to approve no school choice district. Dr. Edward Vincent. Is it something traditionally we have chosen not to? Midford is. Do we need a report?
No. Is there a motion? Motion by Mr. Russo. Seconded by Ms. Vanden Heuvel. Roll call vote please. Member DiBenedetto. Yes. Member Kretz. Yes. Member Stone. Yes. Member Ruggiero. Yes. Member Russo. Yes. Member Vanden Heuvel. Yes. Member Mayber. Yes. Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative. Motion passes. Thank you very much. Recommendation to approve school committee meeting dates the school year 1920. Motion to approve.
There's a motion on the floor to approve by Mr. Ruggiero, seconded by Ms. Van de Kloet. Roll call vote, please. Member DiBenedetto. Yes. Member Kretz. Yes. Member Musto. Yes. Member Ruggiero. Yes. Member Russo. Yes. Member Van de Kloet. Yes. Mayor Burke. Yes. 7 in the affirmative, 0 in the negative. Could we also just put a note to advertise the budget hearing somewhere in our calendar so it's on our front and center in our minds. Thank you very much. OK, we have. Free breakfast, lunch feasibility. Do you want to go back to your?
Committee of the whole superintendents evaluation earlier this evening Wait a minute. We have one more item before we go back report on feasibility of universal free breakfast using provision to miss Patterson Thank you
I'd like to start by saying I don't always deliver bad news with this report. The last meeting of the school year. So, again, thanks to this committee and some crunch time research. The Food Service Department, Ms. Jewel Bradley, and myself and other entities worked very diligently to pull together information to look at the feasibility and possibility of Provision 2, which is
free breakfast for all schools. Currently, breakfast is being served at three mandated breakfast sites, which are the Columbus, the McGlynn Elementary, and the McGlynn Middle School. Utilizing the guidelines from the Food Research and Action Center, FRAC, communications with state departments, and engaging with outside resources in a short time frame, we were able to offer the following information.
We reached out to the Massachusetts School Nutrition Association Board and their member, Mr. Robert Shaheen, and conducted a site visit for the purpose of identifying streamlined breakfast delivery methods that would encourage participation for breakfast at all locations. Mr. Shaheen has been in school food service many years, and he is an advocate for school meals at the Beacon Hill and Washington, D.C.
serving on many boards within his SNA role. Mr. Shaheen observed the breakfast program at the Roberts, and he offered ideas, potential costs, and recommended food items that could assist Medford in considering a free breakfast program. Upon his visit, he complimented the kitchen on its cleanliness and based his assessment at the end of his visit by suggesting a pilot program to confirm if free breakfast could pay for itself.
The conference call on June 20th was also conducted with Education Specialist at the Department of Ed, Kevin Dawson, along with myself and Ms. Jewel Bradley. He indicated that the program is a four-year commitment, with year one being the base year to determine participation levels district-wide. The enrollment can be included
as part of the annual food service application and the process through the DESE portal is very simplistic in regard to accessing this Provision 2 breakfast for all the schools. Mr. Dawson also stated that the best option would be to conduct a short-term pilot program to determine if participation levels were there to keep the program running. And if costs were excessive and or participation rates did not justify the expenses, that we could opt out with the notification to the Department of Ed.
Further calculation scenarios were explored. However, there are so many variables with food costs, labor rates to address a large-scale breakfast program. Honing in on that profit and loss scenario was very difficult. So the expected level of staffing at each building that's not currently serving the mandated breakfast would be two to three more daily food service members in the morning to prepare and serve the meals at roughly $600 per week per building just for the labor costs.
But given our enthusiasm to feed the children of Medford and with the recommendation of experts in the field, partnership with Jewel Bradley, our food service director, I offer the following recommendation. That we adopt provision two under a full-scale free breakfast pilot program during the first quarter of the school year, the months of September, October, November of 2019. And upon the third month, we review the participation reimbursement expense levels to conclude if the program is viable to continue.
report will be provided at the first school committee in December of 2019 and if this was your vote we would do a full-scale Advertisement informing all of the families in Medford that come day one of the new school year All students would be able to have free breakfast hot and cold options at every school building Mr. Benedetto, then Mr. Russo, then Mr. Legere
Thank you for your work on this is this the same program as breakfast after the bell or is that a different program? So breakfast is breakfast So there are many different ways to deliver breakfast and again all breakfast has been being served in all of our school buildings this is just a mechanism to provide more participation and say I
It's free under provision two. So the district is committing to free breakfast for all, which in turn is hopeful that all the students would take advantage of that and participate in a free breakfast knowing that sometimes it's a busy schedule in the morning, sometimes children don't have a hot breakfast meal, and it is the most important meal of the day. And if we can provide that in a provision two free category, we would be serving so many families.
Do we look into the Breakfast After the Bell and the grant opportunity of $10,000 per school that signs up for the Breakfast After the Bell program? So that's a different component that's not part of this, and that's something specific. I know, I'm asking if you looked at both programs and made an informed decision between the two. We wouldn't be able to participate if we waited for that grant opportunity. So this is an option to be able to utilize and run a pilot program.
without having to wait and really see what that would entail. So a $10,000 investment may not be enough and that's what we will really find out by running this pilot program for the first three months, which are usually the most active months of a school year. No, I'm happy that you're presenting us with an option. I just wanted to make sure that we were taking
Every opportunity given to us when a private group approached a committee member with an opportunity to write the grants for us, for us to receive $10,000 per school to do a startup. I just wanted to make sure we looked at that as well as this program and picked the right program that we can sustain long-term. And if we're just picking one and not looking at all options, I want to make sure that all students are fed for indefinitely, not just a pilot program.
So this is really a public item. We're not engaging private sectors for this particular. It's a non-profit programming that helps many school districts throughout the Commonwealth of Massachusetts to provide at no cost to them, and they don't gain anything. It's a public service that they provide.
And they do it in the most needy of areas throughout the state of Massachusetts. And they graciously offered to help MedFed write the grant, actually write them for us. And I just want to make sure that we're looking at every option available to us so that we have the correct program that we can sustain throughout the whole state.
The future of Medford Public Schools, I just want to feed hungry kids, but I want to do it in a way that it doesn't have to stop in December because it's costing us too much money. I just want to make sure we do our due diligence and do it once, do it right, and make sure we did our homework. $10,000 would be the start-up cost.
Could I make a motion? Mr. Russo's next. Thank you. It's nice that you're not delivering bad news or that we have to argue about this. I would just like to make a, well, let me back up a second. So I think that the committee should have to vote for the opt out to take place. It should not be an administrative decision.
It really needs to be programmatic, because the food service program has to be in the black. It cannot operate in a deficit. That's by not only state law, but that's federal. We will lose our funding. So we cannot just function in a deficit in that regard. OK. I can accept that. But the McGlynn Elementary has about a 22% participation. They have free breakfast now. And the Columbus has a 93% participation.
And it's my understanding of revision to the name of the game here is participation. And the only reason that there's a 71% difference in participation is because at Columbus it's after the bell. So I'm not really even comfortable wasting three months of time if we're not making it after the bell at the elementary schools. Because there's no reason to believe that the McGlynn students are suddenly going to start eating when they've been able to. So I mean.
I know it's a lot of work to go to After the Bell breakfast, but we're not doing this just to feel good like we checked a box.
No, and the plan with food service is that this would be a full on real process to encourage students to come in and eat a hot breakfast. So that's the real push. We are going to make it, because again, the numbers aren't there to warrant additional staffing, there isn't additional staffing at some of the buildings. So if we commit to doing a full breakfast, a full hot meal,
additional options and really roll out the red carpet, if you will, on the breakfast program and get that excitement from day one, that's our hope that we would gather that participation level in a new scope and a new scale that hasn't been done so before. And really, again, reach out to the parents in early communications throughout the summer indicating your child will eat free.
beginning the first day of school under this provision, too. And in terms of after the bill, that is a much more challenging program to implement because we're talking about schedules, we're talking about classroom areas and getting the particulars in place. Obviously, the Columbus has been doing it for many, many years, so their building is
Working seamlessly. But if I may, free breakfast that requires that you're actually there before school starts, which is what we're talking about, right? I mean, you can go to any elementary school and watch the kids being dropped off one minute before the bell. Not two kids, dozens of them. And also, what about when the bus just shows up just at the last minute? None of these scenarios will enable a kid to eat.
if they're not after the bell. I think the partnership would have to be with principals, that if a bus is late, that they would offer 5 minutes, 5-10 minutes additional for students to go through the line in a breakfast format, just like they do for additional lunch time if there was something that occurred during the day. They offer additional bell service to account and adjust for
something that might take place. If there's an extended fire drill or something of sorts during the day that cuts into their lunchtime, they are given additional time through the principal's scheduling. So, that would be the hope that we would be communicating with principals and be able to put that in place before the start of school this coming fall.
But it's not just the elementary so again like I think that that's important to recognize that the high schoolers are not Eating a breakfast. So this is a big push to get high schoolers to eat a meal and I we know for certain that high schoolers are here well before the bell and and have that opportunity to
you know, not only is it a socializing event, but if they can go get a free meal and they know it's a hot meal, and they like what they're eating, the whole hope is that they will come in and be encouraged to eat that breakfast meal every day. So I just have one more question. So if we, at the end of the three months, opt out because it is fiscally totally impossible, does this opt out prevent us from next year saying we're going to do after the ballot and we're going to try again?
We can do it all over again next year if it doesn't work. That's good. Thank you. Mr. Aguero. So thank you very much for rushing out this report. I know that we all asked you to expedite it and with all the other budgetary work that you had. I really appreciate it because as I mentioned before as a former educator, I know what it's like when kids show up hungry and I've seen the effects. I've taught at both kinds of schools.
But I do share Member Russo's reservations about not doing an after the bell program. When kids have the opportunity, if mom and dad are running late, that kid doesn't eat. And one of the issues that we talked about at the superintendent review was making sure we have a consistent program.
throughout the entire system. I guess the way I feel about it is that, you know, if you're a child in poverty, it doesn't matter whether you go to the Columbus or the McGlynn. I just want to make sure that kid's fed. So I would like to suggest under this pilot, since we're running a pilot, I would like to have a consistent after the bail program.
That would be what we test, not sort of we try this, we try this, we try this. I want to see what happens when the entire district has an after the bell program. And if we have something like 90% participation, then we would know that we have an issue.
seeking a second on that or has anyone else had a motion? So we have time and learning that we have to do. This is mandated by federal and state law that we have to do. With the Columbus Elementary School, they have been doing this for a very long time.
And I'm the first one to say I want every child to have breakfast. I really do. There was a point in time that we had a huge rodent problem at the McGlynn Elementary School. And Michael, I don't even know if you were on the school committee at that time. It cost us thousands and thousands of dollars to replace the books and the materials that the teachers lost. The time and learning that was lost with the kids having to go to the auditorium because they couldn't be in their rooms.
So it wasn't that the McGlynn Elementary School didn't want the kids to have breakfast. It was a rodent problem that we had. I think we need buy-in from our principals as well. I think we need to talk about this. I think every principal wants their child to eat. And if you have them come in, whether it's before or after the bell, then I think that as long as the kids have the opportunity, I think we should move forward with what Christine is suggesting. Okay, there's a motion for approval.
I guess it comes to a question of what we are capable as a community.
And I believe, and I understand, it's like one more thing that member Ruggiero has thrown at the principals. But on this particular issue, I do believe it has a significant impact on educational standards. And it will be seen throughout the entire school system. So I would, if none of my, no one wishes to second this motion, that's fine. But I would like to make a motion that we do a universal after the bell program for breakfast. That's the one we pilot. And if it doesn't work,
If we can't get it to work by November, then we can regroup and say, you know, it just didn't happen at the McGlynn because of rodents. So if I can offer some feedback from the food service side. As much as that would be ideal in all the greater scheme.
In the context of being able to do a pilot program, again, a pilot program is something you try for a brief amount of time and you put everything into it that you can. Our food service department is not prepared to do an after the bell. There's different components. There are travel items that are needed to carry the breakfast. It's not a hot meal necessarily. It's varying items of what can be provided in an after the bell scenario.
We are trying to do a full-scale, broad-based breakfast program, really having hot meal options, really having additional components for all of the different fresh fruits, fresh vegetables, fresh milk and cereal that's part of the daily components anyway.
but in order to do that we also have to train our food service folks at these various buildings. Now they're used to and understand the meaning of morning prep and delivery of a meal and clean up from that to prepare for the lunch service. In terms of a
model that is breakfast after the bell, that's a significant different model that would require more training. And now that the school is out, we won't have any opportunity to engage with our food service staff in order to do that. So this was the hope, to be able to pilot a program that would really engage and get the interest of not only our food service department, whose main
goal is to feed the children of Medford, but also to really offer varying items for the breakfast menu selection to engage the students and get their own buy-in for breakfast and why they would want to come to school and eat breakfast. Mr. Russo. Yes, so I guess
My issue is with a pilot, and I understand the need to stay in the black, but the idea that one day we're serving all of the kids free breakfast, and then the next day, which I realize will happen over a break, but the next day kids will come to school who will not have heard that starting on January 3rd or whatever, you no longer get breakfast for free. That doesn't even sound like something that we could
implement short of doing exactly the lunch shaming policy that we adopted. No, you can't have that, because you don't have any money. I mean, so I just worry that doing a pilot, I get it, why we want to do this. But if there's a chance that we would actually turn it off, I can't wrap my head around that, frankly. So I really do think the committee should have to approve turning it off.
And if you come to us and say we need to turn it off because we're running a deficit of $10,000 a week or whatever, I think the committee should be the folks to say we can't afford it. We aren't going to make up the money from somewhere else or whatever. I just don't think it should be an administrative decision that suddenly kids that were getting free breakfast and we're going to advertise the heck out of it so everybody knows.
And then suddenly they come to school and they don't get free breakfast. That's just, you know, I grew up without breakfast every single day in my childhood. And the entire idea of that, I mean, I can't even imagine what that would be like. And sure, many kids are going to eat free breakfast, have breakfast at home too, but not all of them. So I'm not okay with approving this if we don't approve the termination of the
So in this proposal, there was no indication that it was an administrative review, and that's why I specified you would be presented with the findings in early December. So it would be a vote of the committee, but I would hope that there would be recognition if there's the levels that don't speak to continuing a program.
There's a motion on the floor for approval. I believe that there's someone in the community that would like to speak on this issue.
Hi, I'm Melanie McLaughlin, Alston Street, Medford Mass. As a community member, that was the first time that I heard the statistic that you mentioned, Paul, around the Columbus school program getting, what did you say, 70% participation? 93%. 93% and the McGlynn was 22? I believe it's 22.
And so as we're thinking, and that was just, I gasped out loud because I was really shocked by that. And also as a child who went hungry as a little girl as well, I really empathize with that in our community. And as we're thinking about equity in our district, I really want us to think about why that is happening, right? So why is the Columbus Elementary School having 90-something percent participation and the McGlynn is having whatever percent, 22% participation? And how are we feeding all of Medford students? And I know that it's not an easy answer and I know that
You know, Christine's done a lot of work, and you folks have done a lot of work as well, but there's got to be some kind of a compromise around making sure that all of our children are being fed. And in a way that, you know, whether it's after the bell or before the bell or however it is, but we have to increase that participation at all the schools. And also, I didn't know about the rodent issue at the McGlynn's, which is really concerning, to say the least. So how do we embrace all of our elementary schools to make sure that all of our children are fed? Because as we all know, you can't concentrate on your school
if you're not fed. And so I just wanted to put that forward as a community member. Thank you several years ago, it doesn't happen. Um,
So, I would think that it seems to me that there is a leap of faith here, to some extent, by going with this. Because we have the statistics between two of our schools, and someone answered about a bus being late.
Well, I'm sure hoping that the principal who's meeting that bus that is late is the caring individual who we know that they are and who will usher that it's not a, you know, all of a sudden breakfast is going to close and the door is closed and there's no chance. When I was a guidance counselor over in Everett, there was a child who consistently came late to school and we knew had no food.
And I want to tell you, we always managed to get that child food by going down to the kitchen, by getting help, and we had no breakfast program at that time set up for that. But there are caring individuals in our buildings. I am sure that there are other people in our buildings who want to make this work.
And I'm betting on that. So I'm going to bet on that and vote for approval of this. And then see, we might have kinks. We might have to work it out. We might have to revisit. But I'm at least willing to try it. So that's where I'll come down tonight. Thank you.
Very good. There is a motion on the floor. Ms. Mostow, did you want to speak? Just shortly. I want to thank Ms. Patterson and the superintendent, because we have been talking about breakfast in the schools for three and a half years, and this is the first time that a compromise, it's not what our wish list is, but it's a beginning, and it can expand, and we can grow it, and the word is getting out there. So I truly appreciate your compromise right here. So I vote also to approve this report of universal free breakfast.
There is a motion on the floor for approval of free breakfast by Mr. Russo, seconded by Ms. Mustone. Roll call vote, please. Member DiBenedetto? Yes. Member Kretz? Yes. Member Mustone? Yes. Member Ruggiero? Yes. Member Russo? Yes. Member Vander Kloot? Yes. Mayor Burke? Yes. Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative. The motion passes. Thank you, Christine, for all your work.
Motion to take a paper out of order, ma'am. We do have two more resolutions. School committee resolution be resolved that the Medford School Committee expresses sincere condolences to the family of Rosemary Nicholson. Ms. Nicholson was a longtime educator and elementary school principal in Medford.
Be it resolved that the Medford School Committee expresses sincere condolences to the family of Joseph Grandy. Mr. Grandy was a former vocational teacher at Medford Vocational Technical High School and a former director and coach of North Metro Little League. He was also the grandfather of Brooke's school teacher at Camille Fargo. You could all rise for a moment of silence on the passing of these two Medford alum.
motion to take committee of the whole superintendent's evaluation paper that was tabled earlier this evening from the table. Is there a motion by Ms. Van de Kloot, seconded by Mr. Russo? All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion passes. Earlier this evening we met in the conference room to an open meeting to discuss the superintendent's progress this year and to evaluate her in compliance with DESE. Overall
she had a unanimous vote of proficient in all of the four standards. Some, there were different pieces to this thing, some were over-proficient, some were at-proficient, there was nothing less than proficient. And I think that the school committee just wants to state for the record how extremely pleased we are
with you at the helm, how the public and the students have responded to you at the helm. It's been very, very positive. And we look forward to it even getting better and better. And I know some items popped up that we feel the first year really, you can't even evaluate someone on this, but what you do with the data you obtain, how you make changes, and how you get buy-in, because we know you're such a positive voice and force.
And it takes time, it takes time for everything to settle out. So we're just really thrilled we will be filing with Desi I believe tomorrow morning after our vote once it's solidified to file our proficient status in all four disciplines.
Mayor Burke, well I'll speak to this for just a moment. It's indeed wonderful to see how well Superintendent Maurice-Edouard Vincent has done this year. The fact that she got unanimous support and that we all recognize that this has been a very strong first year for her and she's got such potential for growing from where she's at.
It's truly been a great year to be able to work with her and be able to, for all of us to recognize this tonight. Very good. Is there a motion on the floor? For approval? Yes. We have something we have to do before the end, just with the budget? No, this is just for her evaluation. This isn't to dismiss.
Christine's very concerned, so that's why I wanted to make sure. Right, we haven't approved the budget yet. Yeah, no, I realize that. Is there a motion on the floor to file with DESE the proficiency status and all four standards for the superintendent of schools? So motion to approve, Mr. Russo, seconded by Ms. Vander Kloot. Roll call vote, please, for our records. Member DiVenedetto? Yes. Member Kretz? Yes. Member Stone? Yes. Member Rosero? Yes. Member Russo? Yes. Member Vander Kloot? Yes. Mayor Burke?
Yes, and vote of 7 in the affirmative, 0 in the negative. The motion passes. Thank you very much. Earlier this evening we also had a committee of the whole in regards to the school department budget for the school year 19-20. It was motioned out for approval of the budget as stated. We've had many meetings over the course of the last several months.
Tonight was the culmination to discuss some of the items that have been presented versus what actually ended up in the final budget. We had three motions, if I can find my paperwork, three motions that were taken earlier in the Committee of the Whole, that a meeting be taken place with the Vocational Director Fallon, Mr. DeLiva, and the Superintendent before school starts regarding physical education for vocational students in regards to the scheduling.
Also that an adaptive SPED training program, PD, be initiated for physical ed teachers for the start of the school year. And lastly, that a checklist be developed for renters. So for anyone that is supervising a building while renters are in it, to do a walkthrough before the renter comes in and after the renter leaves to make sure everything is in the same condition. And that a checklist be developed by Mr. McLaughlin of Building and Grounds. Those were the three items that we motioned out.
take to the floor. On the motion to adopt the committee report by Ms. Mustone, seconded by Ms. Kretz, all those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Motion passes. On the budget. It's not on the agenda. Excuse me? Motion to approve. Motion to approve the budget. Yes. As stated in our budget book. There's a motion to approve by Ms. Kretz and seconded by Mr. Ruggiero. Roll call vote please. Do you have to sever?
you need to go on the record for yes I mean go on the record that I will not be voting on the paraprofessionals as my daughter-in-law is in that unit there's a motion on the end occlude will not be voting on the paraprofessional portion of this budget due to a potential conflict of interest and mr. Benedetto likewise substitute on the substitute because of a potential conflict of interest
Roll call vote, please. Member DiVenedetto. Yes. Member Kretz. Yes. Member McStone. Yes. Member Ruggiero. Yes. Member Rousseau. Yes. Member Vanden Heuvel. Yes. Mayor Burke. Yes. 7 in the affirmative, 0 in the negative. The motion passes. Thank you very much. Thank you, Ms. Patterson, for all of your hard work, your diligence. Thank you. Congratulations, Madam Superintendent, on your first budget.
Okay, and now we do have one other item on our agenda. This is not enough room to move these papers around. Negotiations and legal matters. We do have Mr. Greenspan who would like to discuss a negotiation item with us.
In executive session, is there a motion? Motion by Mr. Russo, seconded by Ms. Vander Kloot to go into executive session to discuss negotiation and legal matters. Roll call vote, please. Member DiVenedetto. Yes. Member Kretz. Yes. Member Stone. Yes. Member Ruggiero. Yes. Member Russo. Yes. Member Vander Kloot. Yes. Mayor Byrne. Yes. 7 in the affirmative, 0 in the negative. We will now enter executive session. We will open up executive session and leave from there. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
you