23416 Committee of the Whole meeting Tuesday, October 3rd, 2023 at 6 p.m. is called to order. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Vice President Behrs. Present. Councilor Kerrio. Present. Councilor Collins. Councilor Night. Councilor Hill. Present. Councilor Sang.
Present. For present three absent, the meeting is called to order. There will be a meeting of the Medford City Council Committee of the Whole on Tuesday, October 3rd, 2023, at 6 p.m. in the Medford City Council Chamber on the second floor of Medford City Hall and via Zoom. The purpose of this meeting is to discuss paper 23-416, Rodent Issues in the City. The council has invited public health director, Marianne O'Connor, to attend this meeting. For further information, aids, and accommodations, contact the city clerk at 781-393-2425
Sincerely yours, Nicole Morrell, Council President. As the meeting notice stated, this is something that's been called for a few times. We've had a few meetings in the past on this as well, but as it's an ever-changing situation, I'm going to pay for Councilor Scarpelli to meet once more. So Councilor Scarpelli, I don't know if you want to start or...
that we've heard this over and over again. And I know with the continued efforts of our director, we still see that there's a huge issue with the rat infestation across this community. And just having this meeting right now to really
really get the word out to the residents of what we're doing, what paths we're taking, and just updating everyone. And then after the director speaks, I think that there are some amendments and resolutions to move forward with as we try to navigate this. It seems like an ongoing and ongoing issue.
So thank you. Thank you, Councilor Kelly. Director O'Connor, I will hand it over to you. I know you had shared that there were some updates or looking at other departments the way that they can help in this. So I will turn it over to you for any updates you may have or just kind of the current state of addressing this issue. Thank you and good evening. Is it possible for me to share my screen? Yep, you should be able to right now. Okay, I'll try to do that. Put together a little
presentation just to start the discussion. So I can do this, right? Okay, so can you see that? Not yet. We're not seeing take over the screen at all just yet. Okay.
You see that? Now we're seeing that you've started sharing, but we're not seeing it just, there we go, now we can see it. Awesome, thank goodness. Okay, so if I can get the slideshow. There we go, is that better?
Yep, we can see it. Yeah, perfect. Okay, so I just put this together. I know that's not a mouse, but I just thought.
A little much right now. So I just wanted to let you know, give you a little background, right? So this is not just obviously a Medfit problem. This is an urban area problem that most of us Board of Health Directors like to talk about all the time and discuss ideas and ways that we're dealing with it. But we've been dealing with this since obviously for several years now, right? So in late 2020, we introduced the Clean Up, Seal Up initiative, which was really focused on educating
homeowners and businesses and renters about you know what they could do as far as being compliant with some of our regulations, and also, you know, preventing road infestations on their properties. It was a really big push around education.
And also at that time we began baiting source and other public properties we weren't dealing with private residential properties at that time. We did see a lot of success with that and that that has continued in 2021. The council approved our rodent control ordinance to introduce further efforts, and that required all construction and demolition projects.
dumpster permit holders, food establishments, haulers, and all street opening permits to submit what's called an integrated pest management or an IPM plan, which details prevention methods that they're going to be taking. So all of the demolition and construction projects are required to initiate these prevention measures at least two weeks prior to the project and to continue throughout the project and weeks after, if necessary.
And then in August of 22, we further stepped up our programming, and we partnered with a pest control company to help us mitigate rodent issues on residential properties using their borrower X treatments, which is basically a carbon dioxide into rodent burrows, which basically suffocates them. We did not go with the baiting or the
Odenticide, because at that time there, you know, we feel that that's not the appropriate measures to be taking, especially, you know, when we know that there are other animals like such as that unfortunate incident. So we stayed away from the odenticide on residential properties, but we are doing the borrower X treatments for those who have borrows on their properties.
The rodent ordinance really had a huge impact, we think, and while we're still reviewing and looking at ways to improve, we now review all building projects through CitizenServe. All projects are sent to the health department for review, and we make sure that anyone that meets the requirements of the ordinance, we ensure that their educated pest management plan is put in place throughout the duration of the project.
We also permit all dumpsters, permanent dumpsters and temporary dumpsters. The ordinance requires permanent dumpsters submit IPMs to the Board of Health as well, prior to their permanent renewal. And again, that's an effort to make sure that dumpsters are maintained appropriately, that they're clean, that they're plugged, that they're also that they have an IPM plan in place to ensure that the rodents are kept at bay.
We've always required food establishments to have pest management, but the again the ordinance requires them to submit their IPM which is a full plan it's not just like a pest control report. It's a full plan on how they, they plan to mitigate issues in the on their establishments.
So to date, since January, we've the Board of Health has received and reviewed 462 IP implants. And we are still looking for compliance from several others. And, again, you know, fines will ensue if if folks do not comply. But we've been pretty good at getting compliance for most of our establishments.
So again, complaints and inspections to date from January 2023, we've received about 213 complaints of those, those are residential and commercial properties, 153 complaints have been closed.
They've been inspected, and if needed, our pest control company has gone out and done borrower RX. We do not do borrower RX on commercial properties, only residential properties. If it's a commercial property, we order them to get their own pest control management company in there.
And 52 is still in process. That means they've been inspected, they've been either referred to the pest control company, or we're in process of getting compliance with the homeowners or the business. There's a little bit of a spike there because in August alone, which was our highest month, we did receive 70 complaints. October and September have been a little bit better. So we're still playing catch up on some of those complaints.
We also do GIS mapping of all of our complaints with the help of our folks in the engineering department. They've been great. So we try to use that to identify hotspots. So we see where there's a cluster of issues or complaints. We're able to go into those neighborhoods and areas and see what the contributing factors might be, whether it's a food source, water source, harborage, whether it's residential, commercial, dumpster related.
food establishment related. And then we'll do a fly campaign in those neighborhoods where we see problems identified. Just again, trying to educate folks that bird feeders, feeding the wildlife, inappropriate composting, trash barrels that have holes, anything that can be a water or a food source or a hot bridge. We're trying to educate folks to understand that those are contributing factors to our issues.
And we've done a really beefed up, increased enforcement of our dumpsters and looking at residential food and water sources.
So our next steps, we are currently undergoing a thorough review of how to improve our processes and maybe some improvements we can make even to the Voting Control Ordinance and to our program.
We're looking at additional options we did a survey of surrounding communities. Again, this is not just a method issue we're all like a lot of most urban communities are dealing with this increased rodent issue. So we did do a survey of neighboring communities to see if they were doing anything different that we weren't doing or that we could do. For the most part, everyone's trying to do the same thing as far as residential and commercial property education, and
trying to seek compliance, and most other communities have also partnered with a pest control company. Some are using different methods that we may start to investigate and look at using going forward, because it seems like if you do multiple kind of abatement issues, that might help a little bit more.
We also do have interdepartmental committee committee with DPW engineering, building and planning and development occasions.
just to see how we all can contribute and some good ideas came out of our last meeting that we're going to set to formulate into a plan, maybe looking for additional like flyers right now the IPM is only asked for a permanent dumpsters, but we have a lot of temporary dumpster folks permits that we do.
So maybe giving education and apply it to our temporary dumpster holders on do's and don'ts and what can go in that dumpster and what shouldn't go in that dumpster. Looking at our parks to really kind of investigate what's going on there, maybe additional signage, reminding people about, you know, trash and litter and how to pick up. Looking at maybe possibly a multi-stage installation of
different barrels instead of the open top barrels, trying to move to a closed top barrel that rodents are unable to get into and feed.
maybe requiring IPMs or permits maybe for the for composting so we know where the composting is at and then make sure that you know I know the city's moving towards a formal composting program and those that program does include rodent proof containers, but not all folks do that so really working with those folks who want to compost and how to do it right.
Also looking at our culverts and overflows, again, as areas of water sources and harborages for rodents, really starting an inspection program around those areas.
And, you know, in beefing up our communications and website information as well. We are continuing our residential education efforts on food and water sources. Unfortunately, you have a lot of residents who
really find joy in feeding the birds and the wildlife, but unfortunately that is a huge contributing factor to the problem. So we are trying to educate our residents on the problems that are associated with bird feeding and feeding the wildlife, as well as, again, improper composting, unkept gardens, you know, making sure that fruit and vegetables and
are picked up and kept up. Unfortunately, we do find that sometimes it's difficult to get compliance and for people to understand. And so unfortunately, that does mean that Board of Health has to issue citations and fines when compliance isn't obtained.
We are continuing our neighborhood inspections and again addressing city properties. I know the DPW just went through a huge cleanup and seal up process and repaved their area due to a rodent infestation. So we are seriously looking at our parks and city properties as well, make sure cleaning up our own home. So I guess with that, I'll just,
The we had our pest control company out today in the neighborhoods. And, you know, the report that I got back was that about is to the front and to the rear of this home have chickens chickens are not allowed right now in method.
The area around the shed must be cleaned up, removed at the breeze. The property to the rear has a good size yard waste compost abutting the yard, this compost has active rats around the shed the vegetation needs to be cut up and cleared up.
and removal of all bird feeders. So, and the chicken coop across the street was a contributing factor to the problem. So, I guess, you know, measures can and are being taken to address the rodent issue.
But really, in order for it to be a success, we need everyone's cooperation. There's only so much the city can do. And no matter what we do, if food and water sources are still there, harbors are still there, our efforts are going to be made. So I guess it's just also a plea to folks to really cooperate and understand how they can contribute and help be good neighbors and do the right thing.
That's just to open up the discussion and I will stop sharing now. I'm happy to answer any questions. Thank you, Director O'Connor. Thank you. Director O'Connor, thanks for being here tonight. I know that this is not an easy situation and I know that it's something that's plagued not just Medford but
It seems like all urban and urban rim communities, especially, um. And you know, there was a lot of great points you made, and I think that's that the plan looks good. Um, on a PowerPoint.
But I think that we need an emergency plan put in place where we treat this as the issue that it is right now. And it's good when the plan's in place and it's read, and I appreciate your work on that, but I'll be completely honest. I've talked to people from South Medford, Wellington area, the Heights, West Medford, North Medford. And the common question I've asked
because you brought it up a few times today, and I think I agree with you wholeheartedly 1,000%. There's a huge disconnect on when you're saying that we have to do this together, because from the complaints that I've received, the common denominator is that none of these people have gotten any information
about any plan or any assistance or understanding of what they can do in their neighborhoods, myself included. I mean, I'd like to know from my council members, I've lived in Medford my whole life. I haven't received one thing, identifying a rodent issue or how we can identify or support or help the community or help the city in making sure that we're doing our part.
you know, like I said, when we talked about this years ago, we saw in the community we worked in, everybody, all the departments, very similar to what you're going through, it's impossible for what you have to do in your department with your staff to do what has to get done to make sure that everybody's in compliance.
So I think this has to be a buy-in from everybody. And I think it starts from the communications department and putting together a plan that it informs all of our Method residents. I don't think we've been informed. I don't, all we hear, you know, we hear when there are complaints, but after the complaints are no more, we don't hear any follow through. We don't, we don't hear any plans, you know, the ones that,
what I can't appreciate the people that have said they called your office. You've worked magic by getting your team out there and the pest control team out there. And it says a lot in what you're trying to do to do your part. But I think we have to do a better part, a better piece of this community in working together because this is a serious issue.
We all know. I mean, the composting situation we're moving forward, I know that Director Hunt was here and told us about how these containers are rodent-proof and they can't get into it. I understand that. But what I'm hearing from neighbor communities that do do composting, it's not the fact that the barrel is foolproof or rodent-proof. It's the person not taking care of that
that barrel to make sure that they're doing their part. And it's funny because I've had some in one community that I've talked to, they said, well, the people that are composting, they feel it. Why should they? Why should it be?
you know, why should they not help the rodents? It doesn't have to be closed. It's going to be spread anyway. So you hear some outrageous comments. So I just, I think there's a lot to unravel here. There's a lot of layers here that I think we need to take as a city council, as an administration and a community, we need to start taking this really seriously because it's starting to get, I'm not even saying starting, it's bad. I mean, we know it.
You know, like I said, when you're hearing neighbors from the heights calling that there's a rat infestation in an area that's all ledge, that's telling you something. When the rats are leaving one area to go to a place where there's nothing, we're going to be in trouble. And the reason why I say we're going to be in trouble, you know what happens when the colder weather comes. Where do these rodents go? They don't move to Florida.
they're gonna try to find the warmest place. And what's scary is residential, it's business establishments, it's schools, it's city facilities. And I think that we as a team have to find a way to really rally together and try to put something into action. I know that you made some, the PowerPoint showed that you're working together with this department, that department, this department. I think that we should really do more. And I think that
I'd like to hear from my fellow colleagues because I think it's something that, again, in no way do I want to make this clear.
In no way I'm pointing a finger or saying this is your fault, Director O'Connor. I think you're doing a great job. In the past, I think that people take what we're saying as personal attacks. These are not personal attacks. This is one city council saying, how can we as a team, the community, the city council, the administration,
your office, the DPW, the engineering department, the community development, everybody, how do we all work together to make sure that we start to get ahead of this or at least educate our neighbors on what to expect? Because I will be honest with you, I think that's my only true complaint with this whole process right now. I'm starting from myself and the people I've talked to, no one has received any information
about a rodent concern, a rodent issue and how to prepare or what they can do as their part. No one has. So I think that's the first line of defense. So again, I appreciate your time. And I think that this is one of my recommendations. One of my motions is going to be that we form a committee
or an emergency team that deals directly with someone from your office, from DPW, from the mayor's office, from the city council, that we work together to build a team right now to attack this issue that's only going to get worse. So thank you. Thank you, Councilor Carvajal. Thank you, Madam President. Thank you, Mary.
for being here this evening. You know, this isn't an issue that's germane to one part of the city. I mean, we're hearing it, as Councillor Capelli said, we're hearing it from every part of the community that's here.
We're always doing community meetings for things that are much less important to this. Maybe it's time that we do a community meeting in each section of the city at one of the schools to, like Councilor Scarapelli said, to teach people how to address the problem and see what they can do. I mean, we get 911 calls for everything that's not important. This is a serious issue, and this is something that should be addressed by our administration.
I drive around, and I see dumpsters. I think I've called you a few times on them, and you of the code inspectors have been great coming to take care of it. But I see the dumpsters at these apartment buildings, restaurants, and they were overflowing because they're not doing their part in having these dumpsters emptied on a regular basis. I'm getting calls from
Riverside Avenue across from the Senior Center. That building over there, people are telling me rats are running around the halls.
and they're seeing them at their doors. I don't know, I say again, no one's pointing the finger at you, but it's something that we have to start getting ahead of. We have to start educating the people in how to stop this. I mean, I don't know if, is it the abundance of rain we've had this year that have brought them out in droves? Is it more people doing their own gardens?
I mean, every morning I come out of my house and in my driveway, I see a half a dozen tomatoes all eaten. Are they from the rats or the squirrels or rabbits? I don't know. I don't know where they're coming from, but every morning I'm picking them up. So I think education is the most important thing. And like I say, similar to what we used to do with the police meetings at every different school.
Let's start the same thing over here once a month, go to different schools in different areas of the city, and have a meeting in the evening that people can come over and address their concerns, and let's educate them on how to stop this.
Thank you. Thank you, Director Connor for presenting. Thank you to my fellow colleagues for speaking. I very much agree with those points. I think it's this is an issue that I hear from residents all across the city a lot about, particularly
Um in in the hot spots. I'm sure you've identified that Councilor Scarpelli mentioned. Um, I guess I just have some more specific questions. Um, that kind of go back to what you were presenting. Um, you mentioned that, um. In your review, the survey of different cities around us, um, that we are cities all more or less to the same things. I'm curious what.
What are the differences between our approach and the approaches of our neighboring cities? And do you think that those differences are creating any, I think, different effect, given that Medford tends to be less well-funded than other communities? It's funny when you talk to these cities.
They still have the same issues, right? So they may have tried different approaches. Some are successful, some not so successful. I think you've heard of the rodent birth control. Some cities have tried to adopt that. Other cities that we've talked to have said it's really not helpful because it's only for the females and they have to feed all the time. And so you get different opinions there, which is why we're really trying to investigate these options.
Um, there's also, you know, the shock box option that people are using that we're looking into and sorry about that.
Again, we hear success stories and then we hear different stories. But we are hearing a little bit more success from folks on the shock boxes. They have GIS mapping in them. They help you identify hotspots quicker and kind of point you to where the harbors may be. So that's something we're looking at. But other than that, there's really not a lot of difference. It's educating the residents like you're talking about.
and partnering with private pest control companies.
That's a really helpful response. And I guess that leads into the second question I wanted to ask. With things like shock boxes that we are kind of seeing more success towards, I know you're still investigating it. Would that be something that your department would have money for right now? Or is that something that we'd have to increase funding to the BOH for? And I guess the question that I wanted to,
Asked to link to that was what would you do if the boh had more money and more resources? we still have resources left and obviously if if I needed more I would um, I would make that recommendation, um going forward, um, but we still still have resources left and um Could could trial I guess the pilot to see if if we have any success. Um going with that with that approach um as well, so
But again, it's a lot to do with like solid waste storage like we're talking about whether it be public parks or public places or dumpsters or restaurants it's, you know, it's it again, like, no matter what you do on those abatement.
Trials, I guess, if the solid waste is still an issue, the food is still there. The averages is still there. They're not going to go to the shop boxes. They don't have to, right? They're going to have plenty to eat wherever they want. So, I guess that's, that's really, really the issue.
With something like solid waste in places where we might have more control over as a city, would you recommend, given if we have the money, would you recommend that we switch out trash barrels to models that are more protected? That's something I've been talking with the DPW about.
You know, it would be a long term plan to be able to do that, but certainly an op box to start with. I would definitely open barrels or, you know, just a food source. So if we had closed top, you know, we don't necessarily have to go with the, you know, the big belly, expensive solar barrels, just closed, enclosed barrels, I think would make a big difference.
Thank you for that. I am also curious about, you know, when your department was reviewing what we've been doing as a city, the history of our road and control efforts, was there anything that you identified that hasn't really been working? Any techniques, methods, ordinances that, parts of ordinances that you thought that your department has found not to be as successful?
So we're kind of a look at the ordinance now and seeing just that like, where can we make some improvements and I hope to come forward with those very soon.
And we have tried public education. I know a few years ago, and we're talking about doing that again this year, is putting some education materials in the water bills, for example, or again, trying to fly in neighborhoods and put door hangers and that type of thing around and mailings. Certainly beef up the website info, but it is there on the website if people want to find it.
So I guess, and a couple of years ago too, and that's still on the website as well. So Galvin Murphy is the owner and president of Yankee Pest Control. He is a real expert, if you will, in rodent control.
And he did do a presentation, and we taped it. We offered an open forum to the community. I think we had three people show up. But it is taped, and it is available on the website as well. And it gives you a lot of really great information. We could push that back out again.
Um, but yeah, it's hard to, you know, people are busy and it's hard to get them out. So that's, uh, I appreciate that, but yeah, but it's tough to hold forums and then you don't have people show up. So, although there is a lot of interest obviously in this topic now, so we may get more of our response.
I'm definitely appreciative of all the efforts that your department's been taking to increase communication. And I'm also really appreciative of how self-reflective you guys are being by identifying things that aren't working as well and actively trying to change it. I am curious as to the public education campaign.
What have we been doing with regards to the accessibility of it? So in terms of, I know you guys are doing the water bills, trying to update the website. Have we been trying to translate that material into different languages? I don't know what neighborhoods you all have identified as hotspots. I certainly hear a lot from South Medford, from Wellington.
those are neighborhoods with a lot of people who don't speak English as a first language and I just was wondering what are our efforts to ensure that that message is really getting across to everyone that we talk to.
Great point. Yes, so we have our team of liaisons now who can do translations for us and we're in the process of trying to get some of our information. We use pictograms, pictures a lot too, so it's easier for folks to see when we talk about seal up and clean up, we're actually, it's a picture diagram as to do's and don'ts, x's and y's.
You know, so it's a little bit easier to identify what we're planning on putting out there. But yeah, certainly we could do a lot more with the translations. Thanks. Thank you for your work. Thank you. Thank you, Madam President. Thank you, Marianne. Thank you to my fellow counselors for your comments. Marianne, could you just remind me how much our annual contracts are for rodent control?
Um, so we had $60,000. 60,000. Okay, yeah, I appreciate that. And I appreciate when you said you'd come for additional funding. Not to say that this neighboring community of Somerville has their road problem under control because I know they don't, but they're spending from what I can tell in their city budget.
almost $160,000 plus a year, so at least twice what we're spending. Are there things that your office could do if there was additional funding appropriated for rodent control?
Well, yeah, well, there's always additional things we can do with more resources. But right now, you know, we do have a vacancy in the department as well. And we're working really hard to fill that. I think every health department in the state has a vacancy at this point. But so it's kind of hard to find to find folks, but we do have a couple of
pretty great qualified applicants that we're looking at now and hopefully our vacancy will be filled pretty soon. So that certainly will go a long way as well. We're kind of operating on two thirds right now. So that is in the budget that is there. And once that's solved, I think, you know, having additional manpower is going to be really helpful for going after these complaints and establishments.
To kind of take it to the next level on this issue, what would your top priority be? Would it be adding another staff person or would it be expanding existing contracts that we have with pest control companies?
I think it would actually, like you said, go more towards getting compliance and education out there. Because again, if we don't address the issues of food sources and water sources and harborages, if people don't understand how they're contributing to the problem, that includes businesses. Believe me, I'm not just talking residents. I'm talking about commercial establishments as well.
you know, finding finding the dumpsters that aren't permanent, which we've been because of these, you know, big push we've had this last year. There are a lot of businesses out there with dumpsters that aren't even permanent, that we've been stumbling upon. So, you know, I mean, just really a real big push on on enforcement education, I guess would be would be the way to go. Got it. And, you know,
As someone who's worked in communications consulting, I can think of a few different ways that could go, but, you know, a significant investment, one-time investment, or ideally ongoing investment where you could send out mail to everyone.
That's maybe a little flasher than what's end up and ends up in the water bills and maybe some online advertising and some other ways that the city really doesn't use right now to reach people could be really effective. So I know that's not your, your, you know, your staff wouldn't be doing that work. But I think, you know, bringing someone on board or working with the existing team to do something like that would be
a bigger investment than what we're able to do just by kind of adding this on to existing communications that the city's putting out. So thank you, everyone. Thank you, Vice Chair Behrs. Thank you. To go full circle, I think that, again, I think that this isn't a Department of Health issue. I think this is a community issue. But again, I'm going to reiterate, it's not the messages that we're trying to send out, without blaming anyone,
it's not getting out there. So I like I said the beginning, I think that I would motion that we, um, call for an emergency road and team that would focus on, uh,
I think Councilor Newton brings up a great point about communication issues right now. I think Council saying brings up a great point. Um with the different language barriers and, um, the information not getting out there to some residents because they just aren't getting it in their language and the other piece. I'm going to say it again. People that
is that they haven't heard anything. They haven't been informed at all. So I can understand the frustration that we had a community meeting to talk about rodents, but I'm a city councilor and I really didn't feel or understand that there was this type of a meeting going on and I'm informed. So I think we need to call for a meeting immediately
because again, we're going to kick this can down the street again. And because we've done this a couple of months ago, a couple of months ago, we need to see some action where at least the education piece is put out there. I don't think it's, you know, I don't think when you're talking funding, I really don't think this is low hanging fruit. If we use the departments that are being paid to do their job, which is communication, I think that, you know,
My God, everybody and their mother knew that we had a road race. Everybody, everybody in the country knew we had a road race. Okay, everybody, everybody.
But I've talked to 10 people just in the last week about rodent issues, and they knew nothing about any plan in place, any system in place and how to prevent anything. And as a city councilor who's living in Medford, whose brother, who's one of those people that complained, that lives in North Medford that has a rodent problem, they've never received any information. So we have to do better. And so I put this in a motion that we call for a meeting, and if we have to,
The next meeting, I'll call for the communications director to come to this council with the team of someone from the health department, DPW, the office of community development, and the engineering department, the teams that have been involved
and get them to the table in front of this microphone so people can understand and we can get the ball rolling on this issue. Listen, I know it's a very busy time of year. I know there's, you know, people have a lot more serious issues that they got to be dealing with and initiatives. But I think if we don't do something
quickly. And like I said, I don't think it's a lot of money. I don't think it's going to take a mastermind plan to put together. I think you have a plan in place, Director O'Connor, that explains and can help start the process. It's just not getting out there. And it's not your job as the Director of Health
to do that. We have teams of communication people in the main office here that we can reach out. So as a city councilor, Madam President, that's what I'm asking for. An immediate plan in place with these departments in place with the communications director or a liaison from that department that can share the information that's already there. It's already
We already have it, making sure that it's in proper, the languages that we need to be distributed to the different nationalities and multiple speakers in this community and get the word out so we can start the education process rolling.
because that's only the first piece. We know that there's a long way to go and it's only going to get worse. It's only going to get worse. So I appreciate your time, but that's in a form of a motion. Thank you, Madam President. So just to clarify your motion, is it to get a communications plan or to get a team together? Okay. So to get a team together, that's in place that has all the information needed that that director O'Connor presented.
and work together with the communications team to devise a plan to get the information to educate our community. So we need an education plan.
And if it's something that the city council has to get involved with and vote for whatever we need, I'm all for it. Again, this isn't the Board of Health's issue, this isn't communications issue, this isn't DPW's issue, this is all of our issues. And we gotta figure out a way to, I can't even say get ahead of it, because we're so far behind right now, it's tough to get ahead, but we gotta get the ball rolling. People have to start knowing what to do and educate themselves, because a lot of these complaints I'm getting,
They're very simple answers. They just don't know who to talk to and when. I know that some of the people that have called have said that the health department has been very, very respectful, very, very responsive, and they're doing everything they can. But again, it doesn't start and stop there. So again, for sake of redundancy, Madam President, hopefully I made my point this time. Yes, you did. Mr. Clark, could you read back what you have just to make sure?
Yeah. I cobbled this together for several things that Councilor Scarpelli said, and I'm trying to make sure we have this correct. Councilor Scarpelli moved to form an emergency road team that includes people from Public Health, DPW, the Office of Community Development, the Engineering Department, the Mayor's Office, and the Council, and can focus on communication issues and has all the information needed to communicate this issue or? To have the Communications Department devise a plan
and educational plan and multi-languages to stop the process of education of rodent issues. Thank you. Thank you. Do you just want to swap that to PDS for the Office of Community Development? I have PDS on that. Oh, okay. I think you said Office of Community Development. I think maybe... Yeah, I said Office, yeah. So I could say PDS. Is there an Office of Community Development? I know it's the same thing, but just for...
Thank you. And then before we take that, I know we have folks here. Is there anyone, any members of the public who wanted to speak on this issue? On the rodents? Just name and address for the record, please. And yeah, there you go. Hi, Victor Pisani, 144 Willis Ave. I just want to, I'm sitting here listening to Councilor Scarbelli. I think I agree with the consensus, I think, of the council.
And I just want to say, as you were talking, I was thinking to myself, simple. I mean, you all are, well, many of you are running for re-election. You send out these nice high-gloss postcards, high-gloss postcards that go out to everybody in the city. We could do the same thing. A nice color picture of a rodent or a rat with some simple phrasing in multiple languages.
do you have rats in five different languages, turn it over on the back, there's the website that the director was talking about, URL, phone number, if you have an issue, if you need information, that way we start driving people to a source, a website that could be updated with current information. I also heard the director talk about
the fact that all the hotspots in the city are geo-coded or GIS-coded, that's fantastic. I didn't know that. You could put that address, that URL, right on the postcard so people actually could log in and see, oh, jeez, I live in a hotspot. Let me go figure out what's happening. So I guess I agree with everything that's been stated. Thank you all for your action on this.
Madam President, I'd like to nominate this resident as part of the team. You made a lot of sense. Thank you. You're hired. We can talk after. Thank you. And Director O'Connor, I do just have one question. When you were talking about inspecting the neighborhoods, is that something that is based off of calls in that area? Or is there areas that are frequently kind of, you know, visually checked out?
So it's based on the number of calls, the number of complaints, then we look at the mapping. When we do the GIS mapping, we can see, you know, year to year, if there's a continuing issue in one particular neighborhood, then, you know, that kind of makes us alert that there's something going on there. And, or if it just happens to be in this one year, you know, a high number of calls from one particular area, so. Okay, great, thank you. Any further discussion from the council?
Any other members of the public wish to speak? Do I have a motion? Oh, we didn't vote on that, you're right. So on the motion, we have Councilor Scarpelli's motion. So on the motion of Councilor Scarpelli, seconded by Councilor Carviello. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Motion passes.
And then I have from Councilor Caravello a motion to adjourn, seconded by Councilor Scarpelli. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion passes, meeting is adjourned. Thank you so much, Director O'Connor. Thank you.