You know, I'd like to jump into the meeting and get going, because it looks like it's a full load. I looked at them. I counted them up. There are 32 cases. We have 29 one-day requests and three, you know, one change of manager, change of officer.
I think we should get cracking. So let's jump into it. And I see, Gary, you put two hours for a Zoom allotment. So if anybody's not on, they can always catch up as we move along. So is that all right, Bobby? Ben, you ready? Ready. OK, good.
So, as always, we need to do some housekeeping items first. We need to take a look at the minutes from the last meeting, just kind of review them. And I'd need a motion to accept the minutes into the record, the legal record. I was able to go over them. They all look good to me.
Yeah, there's no issues there. How about yourself, Ben? Yeah, I was able to review them as well, and they look good. And I would make a motion to approve them, if that's all right, if that's agreeable to you, Bob. Yeah, I know. I, too, agree. I reviewed them. They're spot on. Very nice, Daria. Great work. So, Bobby, are you going to second the motion? Yep, I'll second the motion.
All right, very good. All in favor of accepting the minutes, say aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. All right.
So we got that out of the way. As I was saying, for everybody that's attending, there is a full load. As I was saying, there are 32 cases, 29 are one-day licenses. What I'd like to do is I'd like to bat out of order. I do this occasionally. I guess it's chairman's prerogative. But I want to take care of the 1359 associates, Simmeliner and Wegmans first.
And then we can tackle the 29 one-day requests. Ben, Bobby, you think that's wise to get those out of the way first? Yeah. Yeah, that's fine with me. All right, cool. All right. So let's jump into the 1359 associates first. Who do we have on the Zoom representing 1359 associates?
My name is Chris Watson. I'm the president of the 1359 Associates. Thank you, Chris. Thank you. Chris, do you mind? Oh, I'm sorry, Jack. I'm sorry, I'm here as well as the manager that will be taking place.
Okay, and so I see the amendment for the change of manager application. Can you see we, you know, we, with all these forms and documents, we always check for completeness. The 3 commissioners were not.
so we don't, you know, if we see something in there that gets by us, but we're really looking for completeness. But also, if you don't mind, if you could tell us a little about the change of manager, I believe it's John Malcolm. Could you give us a little background or history on Mr. Malcolm? Yeah, I've been a bartender off and on for the 30, 40 years now. I worked in a bunch of different establishments throughout Somerville and Boston.
I was a member of the 1359 for many years, stepped away to raise my children. I came back as a member and a worker a little over a year ago. And at that point, John Frazier, the bar manager, was ready to step down. He's getting on in years, and it was a lot for him. So Chris had asked me if I'd like to step in and take the position, and I happily agreed to do so.
Very good, very good. You know, I'm kind of scrolling through, I see the Cory check, I see your record of birth. I don't have any questions. Bobby, Ben, anything of concern for this change of manager request? My experience,
Sorry about it. No, no, go ahead, Ben. I just said, bartending experience? Yeah, I started bartending back in 1987 at a bar in Somerville and I stayed basically in Somerville for most of my bartending career and I spent a little bit of time at Faneuil Hall.
Oh, that's really that's really I've been away from the business for a good 6 or 8 years as far as working. Yeah, but I've been with 3059 for a little over a year now. Okay. Okay. All right. That's that's good. That's good. Jack. That's Verizon. Correct. Right. If I'm reading this correctly. Correct. I retired from Verizon about 3 years ago. Nice. Okay.
Bobby, anything on your mind, any questions, concerns? I've looked, I see the application, I see the Corey check, I see the entity. Anything come to mind that we've kind of missed or overlooked? No, everything looks good to me, Mr. Chairman. I don't have an issue with this. Okay. Yeah, I thought the same thing. The necessary paperwork are there.
If one of two of you want to make a motion to accept and move forward the change of manager for 1359 Associates, I'm all ears. I can accept and make a motion for the change of manager at the 1359 Associates at 42 Alfred Street in Medford.
Thank you, Bobby. The name they want to say the name john no oh. i'm sorry. The proposed manager john john Malcolm jack yeah okay yep john Malcolm i'm sorry. yeah and i'll second that motion no issues on my end.
Okay, very good. Thank you, Bobby. Thank you, Ben. All in favor of accepting the change in manager for 1359 Associates say aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. You're all set. Jack, Chris, thank you very much. We try to make it as painless as possible. It's been awesome. Thank you very much. All right. Good luck. Take your time, people. Bye. Bye.
How do I close out? How do I close out? If you tap your screen, there should be a leave button up top. Yeah. Okay. Sorry. Okay. All right. Let's tackle Semolina.
Hi, good afternoon, everyone. I'm attorney Mara Sheehan working with Semolina Kitchen, CJ Inc. And we're here because there was a hearing February 21st and the ABCC came back with an RNA letter. So it had a couple of items that we have corrected. So the first one was there is no more pledge of stock in the transaction. It's a pure promissory note.
And that's exactly what they wanted. The name of the new stockholder director was corrected. It's Bruno de Oliveira Barbosa. A few places it was off there. We have corrected the formatting as well as the query request, the entity vote.
And on the last item, working with Rose Egan at ABCC, there was an option to add a director. So Bruno de Oliveira is also petitioning to add as a director and shareholder. So I think the packet is complete and I would request that you recommend this favorably to the ABCC.
Yeah, attorney, I thank you. You checked off all the boxes there, and you have C, exhibits 2A, 2C. I thank you. You made it very simple to follow all the way through. Just about the change in director, Bobby Bend, is that something that can be piggybacked off the top of this, or do you think they have to come back for a change of director?
May I add that I submitted a revised application and ABCC indicated that this was acceptable because he had been part of the petition for transfer of stock February 21st and so they felt comfortable with that. Okay. Okay. All right. We can do the both at once, right?
Yeah, yeah, I think I think that's okay. We get the change of director. We could make it just conditioned upon maybe sees. Okay. You know, when they when they review the final package. Yes. Okay. Okay. And can we just clarify that? So that's a change of director on top of the sale.
Yes, the issuance of stock, a transfer of stock, purchase of stock, and all of the stock documents are included within the packet. And that was previously approved by you, not ABCC yet. Yeah, we just, there is some formatting questions. But yeah, it looks. Okay. Looks good to me now. Yeah. Very good, then. Thank you.
Yeah, I don't see any. We need to take a vote. Let me just kind of look through. Before we do, Mr. Chairman, I just had a question on the change of director. It didn't appear to be on the original one. Did we get an edited copy with the change of director checked off on that box with us?
Yes, you did. You did. You sent an edited one to Daria? Yes. That's fine. Okay. Yeah, because I didn't, for some reason, I didn't see it in here. I'm seeing through the three versions of it. It was revised three times, so I'm wondering if- Okay. Director, exhibit seven. Yes. Yeah. Okay. That's fine. Good. Thank you.
Bobby, Ben, you wanna make a motion? Bobby, do you wanna do this one? Yeah, I can do it. I'll make a motion to accept the changes in the edits of the previous change of manager and change of, I believe it was interest, stock interest, transfer of stock
And for the Semolina license, trying to get a location. I don't have everything in front of me. 572 Boston Ave, Medford. It was for the issuance slash transfer stock, new stockholder, and change of director.
Yeah, okay. Everything else looks fine to me. All of the stuff that the ABCC investigator was requesting, I spent a lot of time going over it, going into all the stuff that she was looking for. I was able to find everything and everything had been done by the attorney, so I don't have a problem with this at all. Very good, very good. Good work, counselor. Okay, and I'll second that motion.
by Commissioner Delfano. Okay. All in favor of moving the Semolina request forward to ABCC, say aye. Aye. Very good. Council, you're all set. Thank you very much. Thank you for addressing those items on the RNA. We appreciate it and best of luck. Thank you very much. Good luck. Thanks, Mark.
Let's jump into the third one, Wegmans. Who do we have? Attorney Devlin, are you there? Who's representing Wegmans? Good afternoon, Chairman Elizabeth Pisano from Upton, Connell, and Devlin. I'm calling in for Attorney Devlin this afternoon. Thank you. Thank you.
Can you give us an overview? I see that Danny Wegman and Colleen Wegman, I see they're moving around. I see there's a strong core now. Wegman's there. But give us an overview of what's transpiring, please, if you don't mind, counselor. Sure. So Wegman's is just changing their officers at the corporate level.
Steven Arsiel is retired and he's being removed and replaced by Aaron Hines as a secretary. Matthew Daylor is going to be added as a director. And Nicole Wegman has also been added as a senior VP and director of the parent company. So there are a couple of changes in the corporate structure, but there are no changes to the
to the restaurant space or the package store area. Everything is going to remain exactly the same, operations exactly the same. It's just a corporate change. Thank you for that counselor. Also just one thing to know, we realized that we were missing one page of the ABCC application.
Matthew Daler was inadvertently left off of section six of the proposed officer. So if you don't mind, I'm just going to send you an amended page that you can just remove and replace before you send it to the ABCC.
Hey, not only that, but, you know, I noticed that the Corey applications and then we're supposed to provide proof of citizenship. And I think I think we were missing some.
I believe we were missing, like if we match up the proof of citizenship with the Corey records, they don't match up. I think we're, we might be two or three short. Is that what you're referring to, counselor? No, the ABCC only requires a majority. So you don't need to show everyone's proof of US citizenship, just only the amount that shows the majority.
Okay, so the proof of citizenship doesn't have to match up with the CORI applications? No. Okay. That's correct. Okay. All right. That was the only thing that jumped out at me when I reviewed the package. I just wasn't sure whether those two... Again, we're not lawyers, but our job is to make sure the package is complete. So when it gets to ABCC, they don't go, what are they, morons down there?
No, but that's why I'm going to send you an amended page just for you to replace. We made one mistake and need to just add somebody in there. He's in the description. You have his query of all of his information. His name was just left off of page two. All right. Cool. Thank you. It sounds like you're way ahead of us. Okay. I didn't have any questions. Bobby, Ben, anything come to mind? I have a simple question. There's these two packages.
Yes. And what is the difference on it? I'm just trying to make sure. So one of them is for, there's two separate licenses. One of them is for the on-premise license and the other one is for the on-premise package store license. So they're just two different ones. Yeah. You have to change both. No, you're right. You're right. That's why there's these two. They look so similar. Okay. I know. They look the exact same. Yeah. Okay. That makes sense.
The only thing that I saw with these were the certificate of compliance for the Department of Unemployment Assistance. They're both expired and they're only good for like 30 days when you get these. So if you can possibly just grab an updated one for both the licenses,
that's required, I'm just looking at one of them here, one of the licenses, but if you can.
I don't have a problem okaying this with the expired DUA thing. It's just that once you get it, just send a copy so we can update our records. Yep, definitely. The ABCC typically takes them up to 90 days, even though the expiration date isn't 30, they usually accept it within 90 days. But we have requested this from our client just in case ABCC doesn't get to it, you know, before June to review. So as soon as we get updated ones, we're happy to send it to your board. Great, thank you.
Very good. Bobby, Ben, you want to make a motion to move this forward? Yeah, I can. I can make a motion.
What's that? I'm sorry. Go ahead. Okay. Okay. After reviewing both of those applications, um, I'll make a motion to approve the application for the change of officer or the package store and the second application for the change of officer for the restaurant at Wegmans. Um,
Wigman's, Massachusetts. 3850 Misty Valley Parkway. Yeah, 3850 Misty Valley Parkway. And I second that motion. Thank you, Ben. Thank you, Bobby. All in favor, accept in the change of officers. Motion, say aye. Aye. Aye. Council, you're all set. Thank you. Thank you. All right. Take care. Thanks. Have a good one. All right.
Okay. I think they're, if I added correctly, there are 29 one-day license requests. I don't think I see that many. Unless I missed some of them. No, I think Alan is counting like how many we got from Medford Brewing and how many we got from Winter Hill Brewing. Yeah.
Well, maybe I'm just counting. Insurance. Insurance. Oh, that too. Yes, yes, yep. Yeah, seven and seven from what I can see. Sorry. Yeah. Okay. So, I guess let's jump to the one-day licenses. Do we have... Mr. Bailey, are you on with us? I'm here, Robert Holdredge, representing Winter Hill Brewing.
Okay, thank you. So if you don't mind, just kind of give us an overview. We're very familiar with the entity and you guys run a nice shop. You have your tip certified bartenders. You guys run a great operation. Just kind of give us an overview of what's happening and what the requests are for, if you don't mind. So I think there was seven dates he requested. Do you want me to list them all?
Yeah, so we can just kind of get them on to public record. I know it's not sure if you don't mind. So June 6, June 27, July 25, August 1, August 15, and October 3 and 17.
That's right. Yeah. And so, yeah, like 4 to 8 p.m. I mean, generally we wrap up a little earlier than 8 p.m. as business dictates, but, you know, we have two TIPS certified employees, wristbanding everyone, IDing everyone. I think this is our third or fourth year doing this, so. Okay. Tell me,
You know, I was going through the insurance policy, and I don't know if I'm missing something. It looked like you had policy dates, but it looked like August 15th.
was missing from one of the master policies, or is there another policy I'm not aware of? I see all the dates, you know, the 26th, the 25th, July 20th, but I don't see something for August 15th. Am I just missing it? No, you was missing, Mr. Chairman. I found the same thing. Okay. Okay, I'll have to get my partner on that. He kind of handles all the insurance stuff, but I'll make note of that.
Yeah, it's an easy fix. Like I said, we're very familiar with the operation where we see that the event's going to be down at the condom shell. But I guess we could make this, I'm just kind of thinking out loud, if we could just approve this with the condition that the insurance gets, the event on August 15th get added to the insurance coverage. Sure, yeah, we'll get right on it. Okay.
Then, Bobby, do you want to make a motion? We got one other issue that I can spot too, Mr. Commissioner. I didn't notice it till just now when this gentleman reviewed the dates. The 6-27 date is on page two of his documentation with the layout of the condon shell along with the other dates.
The actual application is for 6-25. I'm just wondering what the correct date is, 6-25 or 6-27. Our paperwork says 6-25. Well, 6-25 is a Tuesday, so it has to be 6-27, right? The farmers market's on Thursdays. That's correct. Right. OK, so we can correct that and make it 6-27. That is the correct date.
Okay, that yeah, so I think you just you update the policy, because it's also 625 on the policy, so you just update the policy with all the correct dates. Okay, okay well with the additional date, and then you can correct that date. Yeah, so the 27th has got to be in there, and then August 15th has got to be in there. Okay, I'll have them fix that today.
And Gary, you can, if you wouldn't mind, you just update our copy of the one day license, just change it to the 27. So we know for our records. Yes, we'll do. Thank you. As always, great job by you guys. The pictures, the layout, everything's perfect. Thank you. Thanks for having us again.
So let's make a motion to move forward with the, what is it, seven? One, two, three, seven of them? Yeah. Yeah. Where it is correct is on that packet, you guys. That's a nice packet you gave us. That's actually, all the dates are right there, I think. Yep. So that's what I was looking at. I didn't catch that they were off on the other one.
No, you're right. You're right. 2725. You're right. You're right. But yeah, I can make a motion or Bob. I'll make the motion if you like. I'll make a motion to approve the seven one day licenses with a contingent upon a correction from a
with the new insurance coverage page, inserting the date for August 15th, 2024, which is missing, and also correcting the date on the insurance coverage page from June 25th to June 27th, 2024. And the dates we are approving are June 6th,
June 27th, July 25th, August 1st, August 15th, October 3rd, October 17th for a beer garden at the Condon show for the Winter Hill Growing Company. Very good. Very good. Thank you for the motion. Thank you for the second, Ben. All in favor of moving forward with a one-day license request for Winter Hill, say aye.
Hi. Very good. You're all set. Thank you very much. Thank you very much. You're welcome. Good luck. Good luck. Thanks. That's it here at the Bear Garden. Want to do Medford Pride Day? We'll jump to that one. That Medford Brewery. Let me see here. How many are Medford Brewery? There's seven.
Oh, OK. Next seven, OK. Yeah. So actually, before we do start, I actually have another quick question for you all. We are doing a, we did it last year, where we're sponsoring the Dave McGill for a Run Medford run. And so we're sponsoring their beer garden.
and I haven't included it on one of the permit applications, because my memory is a bit fuddled. As it's not a paid thing, we're basically just donating this product through them. Do I need to get a one-day permit for that as well? Are you going to be charging for the bid? No, it's all a giveaway.
Well, it's open to the public and it's a paid admission. Is there a paid admission to run the race? Yes. And is it on public property? I think, and I may be wrong because I move it around, I think they might be ending it at City Hall. I'm not sure. Okay. And is this a non-profit as well?
Uh, I, those are the questions that might make a difference if it's an idea. Sorry, I don't mean to interrupt, but I believe they are nonprofit. Okay. I think Dave said something to me last year stating that they're nonprofit. I mean, I'm happy to throw this stuff in and I can get you the CLI and stuff anyway, just for good measure, but I don't have it on me. It was just a,
Yeah, I guess I'd like to err on the cautious side and say, yeah, you'll have to request one day just to cover ourselves. I guess, Bobby, maybe this is something we can look into so we'll be ready for it next year when you pose the question again. I mean, basically, other than insurance, there'd probably be no cost to Nick other than the product they're donating, obviously.
and the money that you'd be putting out for insurance, everything else. I mean, there's no charge. They're not charging for the alcohol. So I don't really think there's an issue. We can issue a one-day license. There's no charge where it's a nonprofit. So it's kind of like, why not get it? Yes. CYA, and we're good. Right, because it's out in public. Yeah, just in case. Just in case.
My gut is that you would get it because whether you're donating or charging it, to us it's like if we're looking out for the liquor consumption around the city, I think it's the exact same kind of thing for us. We would just as well have it.
Okay, can I make your second slightly dodgy request, which feel free to say no, stop it, Nick. Can I add that to my list and then send you all the paperwork tomorrow so I don't have to bother you again so soon with a few of my things? I mean, if that's not cool, there's no worries. I can just put them to another agenda. For just that one?
Oh, it's not until September the 27th, 28th. We got plenty of time. Yeah, we got plenty of time. We'll be back. I mean, we take, you know, traditionally or historically, we take the summer off, but we'll be back in September, definitely. Yeah, you can submit it September, whatever the third Wednesday is in September, up until then, you know? Yeah, sure. Yeah, no, it wasn't just to lighten loads somewhere, but yeah, I can do that.
Also, just kind of why we do have another meeting in June. Right. Yeah. Yeah. July and August. Yeah. July and August will take off. Yeah.
Actually, just before I do, Carol, slightly entertaining for me was that, Bobbie, you weren't mentioned, but literally last week, Alan, I was chatting with Melinda, who was missing you from the bank, and Ben, Tom Dorsey was singing your praises to me the other day as well.
So it's just a world of the small things. But no mention about you, Bobby. I'm sorry, mate. I've been a good boy this week, I guess. He's all right. It's a small world. Yeah, it is. It's a small city. Oh, yes, it is.
OK, so I think that the tweets added in. And I think we're good now. Any other questions, concerns from anyone on this? We just have four for the show. If you want, maybe we can look over the four or approve the four all at once. And then the other three are different locations. So we might have to do them one at a time.
Yeah, that's the concert, correct? Those were the dates for the concert? Yes, yeah, the Farmers Market concert. So same place as usual, same thing. We'll do the signs. And yes, and the same thing actually with, I think I put one in for the, it's the same sort of thing for the pizza festival. Is that, did I include that one? Yeah, the Italian, yes, yes. I think we, yeah.
which, as far as I know, that's also being put on pretty much by the Farmer's Market gang, so we'll go in the same spot for that as well. All right, is that the Italian Festival June 2nd you're referring to, Nick? No, that's different. I don't know. No, I think it might be different, actually. It's different, yeah. OK, I'm mixing them up. All right. My bad. Sorry. Yeah, I haven't managed to corner that one yet.
Let's see. Yeah, no, that one's different. Yeah, that's coming up later today. Okay, so we're going to add the concert ones. What is it, September 12th? Well, June 20th, July 18th, and September 12th. Those are the three for the concert dates.
Okay. September 12th, yes. And there's a jazz festival too, right? 824, same location? Yeah, jazz festival, same location, which is on 824. Yeah. And we can kind of throw those all on the same one, if you like, Mr. Chairman, that they're all on the same location. Yeah, it's all the same location. It's all the same vendor. Absolutely. Okay. Yeah, I'm looking over it. It looks fine.
Yeah, you always do a good job, Nick. There's never any issues with your stuff. We asked you to get signs and cordon it off and you did all that. All your insurances is all up to date. We've got copies of everything for each event. So all looks good to me as well. Good, good. So make a motion. Yeah. The dates. So we'll just do the common shell one first.
Yeah, I think that'll be easiest. Okay, I'll make a motion to approve the one day licenses for Medford Brewing Company. And the following dates, this is for the farmers market concerts. This is for June 20th, July 18th, September 12th. Am I missing a date? Yeah, no, I guess 24th.
That was for the Jazz Festival. Okay. And August 24th. Very good. Thank you, Ben. I'll second that motion. All right. So all in favor of approving the one day licenses for the concert series, say aye. Aye. Aye. Nick, that's all set. And then we're going to do the, did we do the seven, the other seven? Did we do that? I'm getting kind of confused here.
Yeah, we got three more for Nick. We already did the seven for winter health. We need to, we have to do the other three. Okay. And those are the community event that dug a park. It looks like we got another community event that the members credit union in the square and another one for pride and method pride and city hall. That's right. All right.
I'm good with you. I see the dates. We have the insurance. We know the event. I'm good. I don't have any questions on this. Yeah. You guys want to do them separate with the different locations? Bang them on one at a time? Daria, that's all right with you. A little extra writing.
That's fine, yeah. Okay. So let's do, we'll take the three separately then. Okay. I'll, if you want, Ben, I'll lead off with the first one. Yeah. It's a one day license where you're going to, that the Method Growing Company is applying for, which is a community event at Duggar Park. And that's on the date of,
June 22nd and June 23rd is a rain date. I think we, if this is gonna be the same as last year, I believe we have a sketch on file for that. Other than that, the insurance we have. So yes, I make a motion to grant this one day license. Yeah, I think I got a picture as well on the folder.
But I guess you can email it all, but it'd be great. Yeah. I think I said to Daria, I'm not sure. I sent her so much stuff. I'm amazed how she can keep up with it all. Get that right. Seconded. Good. Thank you. All in favor, accepting the one day license for the Medford Pride Day on May 31st, say aye. Aye. Aye.
This is a different one. This is Duggar Park community event. All in favor accepting the one day license for the event at Duggar Park, June 22nd with the rain date of June 23, say aye. Aye. Aye. Very good. Sorry about the confusion, everyone.
That's all right. We're overwhelmed today, I think. I know I'm all frazzled between the dog barking and everything else.
So then the other one is the pride event. Is that the last one? No, there's two more. Yeah, the next one would be the pride event, Ben. That's May 31st. Yeah, so I can make a motion to accept the one-day license for Medford Brewing for the pride event, which is from 4 to 7 p.m. on May 31st. And I'll second the motion.
Thank you for the motion. Thank you for the second. All in favor accepting the one day license say aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. That one's all set. And then the last one. I'll make a motion to grant the one day license for a community event to Medford Brewing Company on June 15th and rain date June 16th.
and that is for community events at the 29 High Street, Members Plus Credit Union, Parapark. Yeah, called Circle the Square, correct? Yep. Yeah, I don't see it in here, the name of it, but yeah, I guess it's a community event.
I think that's it. Yeah. Okay. Seconded. All right. Very good. All in favor of moving forward and accepting the one-day license for the June 15th community day, a.k.a. Circle the Square, say aye. Aye. Very good. All set. I think we're okay with all of them now.
Wonderful. And then I'll resend the West Medford Studios garden map thingy. It's the same as last year, but I'll send it on to Dario as well later. OK. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you, Nick. Thanks, guys. All right. Thanks. To the farmer's market, I think that we is house bear brewing in Stormalone cider. I think we
we jumped away from when we were talking about the farmer's market. Let's address house beer brewing. Who do we have attending for house beer brewing? Hi, it's me. It's Karl Hirschfeld, one of the owners. Hello. Thank you. Good afternoon.
So tell us a little about yourself. Tell us a little about House Beer Brewing LLC, please. Sure. We've been doing the Medford Farmers Market now since 2021. We make mead and cider. And actually, the Medford Market's one of the better markets for us. I'd say it's one of our top three. So it's always enjoyable doing that. Venue down there is great at the Condon Shells. So we're looking forward to get back there again this year. Nice. Nice.
Since we are all TIP certified and responsible servers, I'm kind of reading through the application. And you guys do samples? Yes, we do. Yeah. Is it usually somebody, a woman who comes in, the other owner who represents? Beth, yeah. Beth usually sits in for these meetings. Yeah.
she's always been very informative. Yeah. Great. So can I ask one question for the, for the chair, of course, you might guys, you, you folks sample as well as sell. And when we say sell, does that mean, um, for on premise consumption there at the market as well as
to take product home? No, it's just for taking product home. Just for taking product home. So it's a sample and then you buy a sealed container. Yeah, exactly. Okay. That's what I had thought, but I just wanted to double check. Yeah, right. A little bit difference in terms of how you go about things. Yeah, exactly. Exactly. I looked over the application and I only found a minor
A little minor glitch on page one. The first thing before box number one is the year. It says 2023. I think that should be 2024 for this season. If you guys can, we can even correct that on our end just so we know. Maybe you guys can reprint the page. Yeah, and send it through to you.
Yeah, in the top right. Good catch. I didn't even see that. I saw the dates down. I saw the June 6, 24 to 11, 24, 24. Good catch, Bobby. Eagle eyes. Oh, yeah. Yeah, we'll just send that on to Dario when we have it. Please. Sure. Yeah. Everything else seemed to look OK to me.
You know, I actually found a couple of things and I highlighted them on my computer, but it wouldn't let me save it highlighted for some reason. I think because of the email. I don't know what it was, but I think that was the only one I found on this one. Okay. Yeah. Yeah. We got the drawing. Everything is great. Very detailed. All good. Very good.
Well, let's yeah. Ben, anything? No, no, it's good. Right. The detail. We have the picture and everything. So I'm good to go. So we'll just we'll just make a motion to approve this application to sell to sell at the metric farmers market.
This is for how to spare brewing. Sorry, Ben. It's mead and cider, correct? Correct. Yeah. Okay. Yeah. Sorry, Ben. Mead and cider. Yeah, I see. Yeah. Okay. Okay. Mead and cider. Yeah. Per the dates listed.
Okay, on this application and the picture where and how it's going to happen on this application. Okay, I'll second that motion. Thank you for the motion, Ben. All in favor of accepting the request license to sell at the farmers market say aye. Aye. Good.
Okay, you're all set. No rain. That's what we hope for. Thank you very much. Come down and visit us. All right. Thank you. Take care. Thank you, Carl. Bye-bye. Very good. Let's do a storm alone cider. Shannon, are you with us?
So Shannon isn't here. I'm Catherine Zonghetti. I'm one of the reps for Storm Along Cider and I'm the one that goes to the markets.
Tell us a little about what's going on, what you're doing. Just give us a good overview. Absolutely. Shannon Edgar is the founder and owner. He's very talented and makes wonderful hard cider. But yes, we've been at the Medford Farmers Market for a few years now. This will be our third. Like Carl was saying, we also love it. It's always a successful market and love the location and always
Wonderful customers, so we are looking forward to, you know, sampling and selling at the farmers market again for the 2024 season. Nice, nice. And same question, you know, they sample and if they like, they buy and then they go. Okay. Exactly. Sometimes I wonder if we should request that to be put in the, you know, in some of the narratives.
But it's a different, it would be a different license, right? Yeah, yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Because we give one day, because it would, this would turn into a beer fest. Because it's like we give one days for, you know, the brewers. And then we give these guys different license to sell. Yeah. Yeah. Anyway. It's almost an identical application.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. We actually alternate with how spare brewing. So we'll be the opposite Thursdays. Same. Same. 24, 24 rather than never mind. Yeah, they had that one, right? I don't have any questions. My fellow commissioners, anything? No, I can make the motion if you like.
Yeah, please. Make a motion to grant a farmer's winery license to sell at the farmer's market to the Stormalong Brewery for the dates of June 13th through October 31st at the 21st
2501 Mystic Valley Parkway method, Condon-Shell area. Very good. I'll second the motion. Thank you for the motion. Thank you for the second. All in favor of accepting the application, buy a farmer winery for a license to sell at the farmer's market, say aye. Aye. Aye.
Passes. Catherine, again, no rain. We have our first cross, no rain. Thank you. Appreciate it. Good luck. Bye. Thanks again. Bye-bye. You're welcome. Ben, Bobby, have we missed anybody? I think we have everything covered. We got that Italian festival.
Yeah, on June 2nd. By the board. June 6th. Thank you. Seiji, are you with us? Yes, I am. How are you? Good, good. Thank you. Thank you for waiting. Thank you for coming on. Of course. Tell us a little about the event. Is this the same one that was held last year?
Yes, it is. Okay. Yeah, so it's good overview of the event, please. Yeah, Danny, do you want to take that? Yes. Yes, thank you. So what the event is, is the Feast of the Republic. It's
basically the 4th of July for Italy. It's when Italy became a republic after World War II. It is celebrated every year on June 2nd, or the weekend of June 2nd, whatever falls on a Sunday. Historically, the event was in Boston, and it was celebrated for many years in Waterfront Park, and a couple years ago,
The committee had approached me and had asked me for my help, because I actually chair a much larger event, the Fisherman's Feast of Boston. And I told them I would help them, but they would have to move this event to my city. I'm a resident of Medford, and we really didn't have any Italian festivals or anything promoting our Italian culture.
You know, I told them I would get involved and they jumped right in. We had the event last year. Unfortunately, it rained, but Medford Rec was nice enough to help us out and get us indoors. And the event was still very, very successful, even though it rained. So we're looking forward to being able to do it again this year, only doing it outside. Very good. Thank you, Dan. Thank you.
I remember it last year, I brought my son by there and it was fine. It was inside and it was where the Y is, right? Yeah. We made the best of it. We still had some food vendors that roughed it out outside and it worked out well. There's a lot of people though, so outside will be great. Yeah.
I, I see the 1 day license request diary. Is there something I'm missing? Do we have the insurance for it? Or do we have a little diagram or a layout of. Of where the events taking place didn't have any have those 2 items been submitted. So, the, the.
The layout I submitted to diary a little earlier, uh, right before the meeting, actually, uh, it's the same layout that we used last year. We're going to be right adjacent to the show. There's going to be a cordoned off area. Um, you know, roped off clearly roped off area for the alcohol. Um, and it is not to leave that area obviously. Um, and as far as the insurance rider, I'm waiting literally for an email right now. Um,
from my insurance, from our insurance company, with the coverage, which I also can get to Daria, which she can forward it to you, I'd say within the hour. Terrific. Terrific, Dan. Thank you. This drawing is the back of the pizza box one from last year. Yes. I remember that. It's pretty good, right? It was.
You got the straight line in the box. You can follow. Yeah. Maybe next year when we can see a little better after this successful year, I can actually, you know what, I have to create one for, for the food vendors anyways. So I'm actually, I'll, I'll get a Google earth one and get that out to you before the, you know, within a week or before the event. Yeah. Yeah.
I have one question. You folks realize that this is wine and malt only, not all alcohol, correct? Only because in order to have an all alcohol, you have to be a nonprofit. And it's not a nonprofit event. So it's just going to be wine and malt. And then Sage, you're with the Ford.
Yes, I am. OK. And so you guys are doing this event. You guys are providing the tip certified bartender and everything. Yes, correct. I am tip certified. I will be present doing all that good stuff. OK. And are you guys setting up the section where the alcohol is going to be distributed?
Yeah, correct. We're going to have it sectioned off. So and we'll have signs put up no alcohol outside these premises. So they'll stay within that section. So no alcohol will leave that area. Yeah. Yeah, you know, really what it is, you still want people wandering off, you know, like with a drink in their hand, just so it stays contained. So okay. Okay, good. I think we, we picked up the little nuances in there.
Anything else, Bobby, Ben, anything else jump out at you? No, everything looks great to me. Okay. Daniel, you're aware of the nonprofit versus the corporation rules, correct? Yes, correct. I just want to make sure. Okay. Yeah, we went through the same last year. It's literally just, like you said, wine and malt. Okay, good.
Alright, so Bobby and Ben, if you want to make a motion.
Yeah, I can do it. All right, so I'll make a motion to accept the application for the one-day license. This is for the Italian festival, which is going to be on June 2nd from 11 AM to 2 PM. This is going to be held at the Condon Shell in Medford. The entity running it, Mystic Dining LLC, Ford Tavern, this is for the alcohol.
Yeah, following the depiction we see there, the plan we see there, and then subject to Dan getting us insurance. Very good. I second it. All right. Very good. Thank you for the motion. Thank you for the second. All in favor of accepting the one-day license for the Italian Festival June 2nd with the conditions
Commissioner Ben, lay down, say aye. Aye. Aye. Very good. OK, it's a go. Again, no rain. No rain. No rain. Come down and have a glass of vino with us, will you? Will do. All right. Thank you, guys. Take care. Thank you. You're welcome. Good luck. All right. Thanks. OK.
Have we got everybody? Have we missed anything? Yes. So we have one more from Alvaro for Alta Cuba. I sent it, I think, 1220-ish. Oh, OK. Yeah. So as you guys got the email that I forwarded from the mayor,
stating pretty much KP law told us that it's up to the city how we want to approach a lot of dining with liquor.
And the mayor is, of course, in support of outdoor dining room liquor. So it's up to us on how we want to handle it. That's why I was trying to get you guys' input before. And Alvaro has been asking me about it for some time. So I wanted to get him on to just get it done for him if we just want to continue to do with the way we've done it for the past couple of years.
So yeah, because we also have Oasis that has reached out. But I did call Oasis, but I didn't hear back. And I'm not in the office today. So maybe he did call me back. I'm not sure. Well, my only concern is as long as it's a dedicated area,
As long as it's a dedicated space to serve, I think I would be fine with that. I'm happy that the mayor is all for it to keep the city moving and the city being vibrant. Anything, Bobby, Ben, anything jump out at you? Any concerns or additions to making sure the serving area is sectioned off?
There's no drawing of it, right? Alvaro? I can't hear you. You're on mute, Alvaro. Can you hear me now? Yes. Well, I sent the print how it will be set up.
And it's basically what we use the same way as what we did in the notch previous years. And then in two years in a row, we were able to get alcohol. In this case, we're asking also part of the drawing is to have some on the sidewalk because it's a wider sidewalk. But that's pretty much all on the outdoor. So I don't know if there is anything that needs to be required to keep the people more enclosed.
Yeah, yeah, did you actually send it? So no, I mean, I was thinking about it, because you have to knock and that's a notch. And then that's all good. I mean, really, I'm just speaking for myself. I have no problem with it. Obviously, you're doing a great job at that restaurant. It's a very successful restaurant. So I have no problem with it. But assuming all the other boards in the city, OK, I'm sure you have to sort of submit some kind of plan to them.
Yes, that is correct. So everybody still has to go through outdoor dining commission.
And part of it, so PDS is a part of it, building, fire, engineering. So everybody does work together still. It's just we're waiting on the alcohol part. And as you guys know, they just approved it May, like the first week of May, the state. So we don't. We.
We've been approved, and I have the permit. But if we don't get approved for people can drink outside, it makes no sense for us financially to actually do it. So that's what we're waiting in order to actually build and do what we want to do in front of the place. But until then, we're just going to be pending. Yeah.
Yeah, no, I get that. Actually, I was going to say, I think of the great American Bear Hall where there was nothing there. There was nothing there, but we said, OK, as long as the conditions that the city puts down, I think we'd be fine. So in this case, Navarro, you're saying that the city's already looked at your plans and they're fine with it.
I kind of echo Ben's sentiment that I'm fine with the two. Anything to keep the city vibrant as long as we're minimizing the risk to the owner and the city, I'm good with this. How about you, Bobby? Yeah, I did some research on this and I really dug into those.
emails that Daria sent us about the new ABCC rules and the governor signing that this is going to be up to the local licensing authority. It made it an act making appropriations for fiscal year 2024. And what it is is
Basically in a nutshell, it's the same exact thing as we've been doing since COVID in 2020. The city has got its own rules that the licensee has to abide by. The only difference is the ABCC come up with a new form, which I'm trying to put my hands on. It's a licensing authority certification form
One pager, and any licensee in the city can fill this out. It's no charge. They've added an additional box to the top with all the boxes, change of office, ownership, interest, change of manager. They put outdoor only alteration of premise. That needs to be checked. And you need to put the licensee's information in with a complete description of the license premise, inside and outside.
And as soon as they do that, we approve it. And as long as they're abiding by the outdoor dining commission regulations, we're good. They can have outdoor alcohol just like they've had the past three years. Only the ABCC doesn't get involved in it. It's strictly turned over to us now.
The only thing Daria has to do is once these forms are filled out, they have, she has to send it through the portal to the ABCC to inform them of who is doing alcohol outdoors. And this is going to continue from this point forward every year. Um, you know, every year you'll just have to fill out this form. It's the licensing authority certification form and
That's giving our approval to allow you to sell alcohol outdoors as long as you're complying with the Outdoor Dining Commission rules. There's probably going to be an easy way to do it or a hard way to do it. The hard way to do it would have you fill out these forms and bring it before us to approve each and every one of them. The easy way to do it, and I was going to suggest to my fellow commissioners,
is that we had just adopt the ABCC and governor's new ruling. And basically all that does is we can make it citywide that when Daria receives one of these forms, she can grant the outdoor dining license as long as the licensee has complied with the outdoor dining commission rules.
So each one doesn't have to come to us. We're just gonna approve it on a blanket type approval that anybody that fills out this form is good to go as long as they're complying with the Outdoor Dining Commission rules. That's the way I think it'd be the easiest. That sounds much easier. Yeah. It's like adopting a new law or whatever, you know, it's just, because obviously,
These, they can't, everybody can't get all their forms in and then have to wait until the end of our meeting in June. It's just gonna be too crazy. It wouldn't be able to work. So if we just say, anybody that wants it or inquires about it, or wants to do alcohol outside, fill out the licensing authority certification form, and you got it, as long as you're compliant.
So I don't know how you guys feel about it. Yeah, no, I think it's efficient. It's clean. I like it. I like it. It's smart. Dario, does that work for you? I mean, would that also make it a little more streamlined for you as well? Yeah, that's fine. And you're talking about that form that I usually fill out, correct? The local licensing decree?
It was the form that was attached to those documents from the ABCC regarding the outdoor dining and the cocktails to go. That's the one that they want you to return a copy to them once it's completed. It's basically, it has one, two, three boxes along besides all the
things on the top that you change your license type, change it, transfer a license, whatever you want to do. But it's got to be outdoor only alteration of premise has got to be checked off. The applicant's information, it's just their licensee, DBA, street address, manager, type, class, and category. And then they've got to put a complete description of the premise indoor and outdoor. The box below it
It says local licensing authority information. Advertised, yes or no. They don't have to advertise. So it's just a no. Just check off the box, no. About as notified, no. Because they already have their alcohol license. And then date approved by the LLA, if all their paperwork is in order and they present this application to you, that's the date it's approved. Because it's, you know,
We're approving all of these as long as they're in compliance with the outdoor diving commission. Right. How long it would take that? I'm sorry? Because how long it will take this process? I called the ABCC prior and then we couldn't get an answer from them. The explanation they gave me is once they go into the authorities, it will be like basically the previous years.
And on the previous year, I remember I never submitted any, once I have an approval of the inside of the space, now I have to do a description of the inside and outside, even though that I'm only doing alteration of the outside because I never had it. It's just to see how, on the timeframe, how long it would take me to actually do this.
Well, let me ask you a question. Are you approved for the outdoor dining commission already? Do you have compliance? Yeah. I just say that I have a permit already in place. The only thing is that we don't do the build out. It's because if we are not OK to sell alcohol, it makes no sense for us financially to do it. So that's the only reason we haven't done it. Right. No, that's correct.
And if the commission approves, Mr. Chairman, he can come to city hall today and pick up his form, fill it out, and he's good to go tomorrow. Three more. Avaro, get that form filled. My thought is, since you've already meet the criteria for the city, we're OK with that. Just complete that form, get it back to us.
And I think you're good to go, unless I'm missing something. Bobby, Ben, am I missing something? He's already been approved by the city. Yeah, the city's OK with it. Yeah, we're good with it. So just an FYI, the mayor just said it's up to the Liquor Commission on how we want to handle it, if we want to do a bonus notification or whatever. So just passing it along, just a messenger.
Yeah, I mean, if there's no need for a butters notification, why put the licensee for that? Yeah, and that's that's what I think. So we did that before we do. Well, we have to do it when there's.
When there's an official alteration of premises, right, we do have to do it. When Medford Brewing had to do it. But just my two cents in, you guys don't need my input, but just my chain of thought on this is that we're only doing this from April 1st to October 1st, I believe, is the season of outdoor dining. So it's not, you know, where you do it at all the time.
I just don't know if we should be doing this case by case because some places, Alvaro's place is not in residential, it's just business area, but some are more in residential area, so I don't know. I don't know. My thought on that, Daria, is it wasn't required for the past four years since COVID. So according to the ABCC,
And in the email from the governor's office, it's to follow the 2022 rule, I believe it says, that was put out from the governor. On April 7, 2022, the ABCC approved guidelines for outdoor alcoholic beverage service areas. And that's what we've been following.
And it doesn't require a notification. You're 100% right if they're doing an alteration of premises, absolutely it needs it. But for this, no, it doesn't need it. So that's why in those boxes, advertise, no. About a notify, no. And then, you know, we're good to go. I mean, he can come today and pick up this form from you
or you can email it to him, he can fill it out and bring it to you. As soon as he brings it to you, there's no charge, he's good to go. Yeah, I can send it to Omar because I'm not, I'm out till Monday. Okay. I mean, if you want, I can email him one, do you want to, well, that's right, you know, I mean. Yeah, email would be great. I can email it to you, fill it out and email it back to Daria and you're good. Yeah, he'll be all set.
And then if she's got to fill out a little something when she gets back from vacation, that's fine. You know, we can do it. That is as long as it's okay with my fellow commissioners. I like to, like I said, it's clean, it's smart, it's efficient. You're right, Bobby, we're kind of following the rules from COVID 2020 going forward. So I'm good with that. Just as long as he completes that form and gets it back to us so we have it for record.
I think we should be fine. Yeah, and you know, you feel bad for these fellows too because they've already lost a month and a half. This is usually April first, you know, and I don't know whether the governor dragged their feet on it or what happened, but you know, all these restaurants in the whole state lost a month, you know. Yeah, so. Just let them do it. Yeah. Okay, thank you.
Yeah, so time is of the essence, Alvaro. Get that form, get it back to us. And like I said, best of luck. Alvaro, do you want to give me your email address and I'll send it to you? I'm sending it to him, Bobby. I'm doing it. Oh, you are? OK. I didn't know. OK. OK. Well, thank you all. Thank you very much. You're welcome, Alvaro. Good luck. Thank you. Daria, anything else?
Do we have to put this in a form of a motion, the way we're handling it, or no? I think so, just to have it there in minutes and officially that you guys discussed this and this is the way you want to handle it. I think that would be a good idea. Yeah, I know. That way it's on record that we discussed it and we voted on it. So Bobby, if you don't mind making that, I know you explained it very well, if you mind giving us a little narrative again and we can vote on it.
Yeah, I'll make the motion. I'll make the motion from this point forward, May 15, 2024. We are to follow the guidelines of the ABCC for outdoor only alteration of premise licenses on an annual basis.
from, Daria, I think you said April 1st to October 31st. I believe, yeah, I can check the dates with the outdoor dining people. Yep, that's fine. For those dates, pending the licensee is in full compliance with the Outdoor Dining Commission,
and a licensing authority certification form has been completed and turned in to the local licensing authority. There will be automatic approval if that is the case. I think I didn't leave anything out. I think I got it. Can we reference to CUBA here? Yeah. Can we reference to CUBA specifically though?
It's for any licensee. This is just in general. Any licensee. Then if he submits that, then we can OK it then. Is that what you're saying? As soon as we receive this license application,
then he's good to go. All right. So that's what that's OK. So, yeah, we're getting the motion and then we'll vote on the motion. And now it's the record. And then he'll get the stuff to us later on. So I'll second that motion that Bob said. OK, one further thing, you think that we should put some language in there that upon proof of outdoor dining commission
compliance, this license will be granted. Because anybody can come to us and say, yeah, remote that they said I could do it now. You know, I'll just give you this farm and I'll start selling the liquor. Well, we don't know if he's been officially approved because
We have to see some paperwork from somebody. It's a two-part verification. We need the form, and then we need the outdoor dining commission to approve this. Yes. They must have some kind of certificate or something. To that effect, that it's a two-part process?
Yeah, because I think, um, as I remember from last year, the final signature comes from, it comes back to us from Planned Development Sustainability and that the mayor signed. So I believe that I need to see that too before we issue the license. I'm sorry, go ahead, Dana. No, no, no, I'm sorry. I was just going to say I can work with Planned Development Sustainability so they can let me know whenever
or let's say AltaCoopa is approved, then I can automatically say, look, okay, once you fill this form out, you will be approved because you'll work by the commission. I just want to get the motion and get our interpretation of the process on record before any requests come in. Okay. Okay, cool. So we're all set. We second that we approved it.
Yeah, all in favor of accepting the motion, say aye. Aye. Good, good, good. Thank you, Ben. Thank you, Bobby, for putting that in writing. Now, Daria, is there anything more or are we caught up? We're caught up, I believe.
OK, we we all know about the new alcohol, outdoor dining, alcohol to go, right? We're all good with that. And basically it's it's right in the email. So, you know, there's nothing new on that. And there was a question brought up on liquor, liqueur and cordial licenses. Oh, yeah.
Basically, you know, I did a little digging into that too, as well. And it's basically if it's an existing beer and wine that wants to get a liqueur and cordial as well, they have to do a change of category on the licensing authority certification form. And the only thing I'm not sure of is where they're only required with malt and wine to have
19 seating capacity, I would assume that rule carries even with liqueur and cordials, because it's not a distilled spirit. I mean, I even looked up the definition of a distilled spirit, and liqueur or cordial is basically something that's blended with a distilled spirit. So they can't sell vodka or gin or rum or bourbon, but they can sell
you know, like B&B or Galliano or whatever, other cordial, Cointreau or Grand Marnier, whatever. I, you know, so I, myself personally, if someone should bring this forward to us and they've already got the beer and wine, yeah, it's 19 seating. If it's a brand new license that wants beer, wine and cordials, yeah, it's 19 seating. That's the way I feel about it.
I don't know how you guys feel about it. You know, beer and wine, they only needed 19 for that. So if you want beer, wine, and cordial, which is another category, it should still apply, in my opinion, to the 19 seating.
Yeah, yeah. You know, this sounds vaguely familiar that we discussed this a long time ago. And I think it came out that your opinion, Bobby, I think was the same one as our prior chair. As long as they had malt and wine and whatever the minimum seating was at that time, he was okay. And I think where the precedent's already been there, I think we should stick with it.
Yeah, yeah, I think, I agree, I agree. But somebody that has an existing license, they have to do a change of category. Change of category, sure. Yeah, if not, just apply for a new bearing line with cordials. With cordials, yeah. Other than that, I think that's the only other thing I had. Yeah, okay. How do you feel on it, Ben? Yeah, I was just thinking,
The definite, the, sorry, what are the cordial definition is technically? Oh yeah, let me show you what it is. I got it here, I wrote it down. Let's see. Like it's just a type of. Yeah, it's in chapter 138, section one definition. Like a fruity. It's a liquor or cordial.
All alcoholic beverages manufactured or produced by mixing or redistilling neutral spirits, brandy, gin, or other distilled spirits with or over fruits, flowers, plants, cured juices, therefrom or other natural flavoring materials or with extracts derived from infusions.
percolations or maceration of such materials and containing no less than two and one half percent of sugar by weight. Yeah, that's a liquor. So our opinion was it's like wine, sort of like a wine. No, it's like a sweet, yeah, weed alcoholic beverage. It's higher in proof than a wine.
Not like a hard, whiskey, a bourbon, a rye. Yeah, that's what I started keeping in mind or whatever with one of the craft beer, a craft beer that has a higher alcohol content. Right. Yeah. But you can't sell a distilled spirit, which is just a gin or a vodka or whatever. Yeah. You know what I mean?
It's got to be something like, I imagine that, well, I've attempted to make lemon cello myself, and it's basically alcohol with sugar and lemon rind. You don't use the actual lemon juice. But those are exactly what I read. You know, there's the sugar. It's got an abundant amount of sugar in it.
And it's got the flavoring of the rind of the lemon. So, you know, it falls into the category of liqueur and cordial because it's mixed with either vodka or straight alcohol and water, you know. So, I mean, that's kind of where it is. It's a fine line. There's some cordials out there that are, you know, 80 proof. I mean. Yeah, sure.
All right, it was just a definition thing. No, I mean, I'm in agreement with what you both say about it. I really am in agreement with that. And being kind of a guy looking for something to do every once in a while, I did a little revision, a very slight revision on the one day license application. It just made it a little more user friendly and
I had a chat with Gary about the fees, because it seems like there's no set way of paying for these licenses, and there's no way of really keeping track of who paid, who didn't pay, or whatever. So part of the application is, you know, in Method License Commission, one-day liquor license requirements, one through eight, you know, it says we can, or one through seven, we can add in the number eight,
It says fee, dollar sign, payables, the city of Medford, pay due on day of application. So they apply for the license, attach a check for $60. We don't have to worry about it. And then it says, number nine, the next one, licensee must notify license commission if event is canceled. Because I guess a couple of times events have been canceled and you don't get your money back.
I don't think, but you should have a credit. You know, Allen has seven or eight one day licenses a year and the other rain, they couldn't have it, blah, blah, blah. They had to cancel it. Okay, well, we'll just credit you a $60 payment or whatever, you know, just trying to keep track of it. And at the very top, the date of event, the license, I just put right below it, rain date, if any. So that way there, you're giving the person the opportunity to have a legitimate rain date
And this license is still good for that date if the original date wasn't used.
Can we kind of table that and let's talk about that at the end of the June meeting and buy it, you know? I like tweaks, why not put it right there in writing so everyone sees what's expected or what they can expect. Yeah, and I can email it to you guys so they can look it over. I'll email you guys and pull it apart, pick it apart, see what you think is good, not good, whatever. I mean, it seems reasonable.
Yeah, I mean, it's just, you know, anything we can do to lighten the load for Daria would be good too, you know, because she's got enough to do that she doesn't have to go chasing people for money. Okay, good. All right. All right, so if we're, Daria, we're all set, then I'll make a motion to adjourn. It's 2.31, according to my time. Can we get a second?
A second. Very good. Thank you. Bobby. All right. Well, good to see everybody. I thank you all for your help and your participation. And like I said, we'll we'll revisit what you are referring to Bobby at the June meeting and then we're we're off July and August. Good.