April 15th, 2013 is a day no one will ever forget.
It was a day of horror and sorrow, but it also inspired a unified community and pride for our city.
April 16th was not your average game day for the Medford High varsity softball team.
With yesterday's events fresh in their mind, one woman's story touched a girl's heart, and that was Crystal Campbell.
Crystal was a Medford High alum.
And a former softball player.
So the team thought that it was only fitting to dedicate the rest of their season to her.
Four softball seasons later, Medford High Softball continues to support Crystal.
Through tournaments and selling Medford Strong t-shirts.
And their proceeds go to the Crystal Campbell Scholarship Fund.
From then on, Medford Softball has done all in their power to carry on Crystal's legacy.
I will visit the Crystal Campbell Peace Garden and say a prayer.
This garden is a fitting tribute to Crystal, Sunflower, Martin, Baseball Bro, Lindsey, Brooks, and Sean Badge.
In the days, weeks, and years following the horrific events, these families, first responders, and survivors have demonstrated pure strength by their actions and words.
I will attend the Boston Marathon to support the many runners who are trying to make a difference.
We've been doing this for four years, the Medford Strong Motorcycle Run.
It was right by the Peace Garden.
I'm going to make a difference in the Medford community by working with young adults every day to make Medford High School the best school.
I'm going to make a difference by supporting my students to be successful.
I will make a difference by making everyone around me smile.
I'm going to make a difference by praying for those in need.
I'm going to celebrate One Medford Day by honoring the victims of the Boston Marathon, particularly Crystal Campbell.
Purchase a Medford Strong t-shirt to support the Crystal Campbell Scholarship Fund.
I'm going to make a difference by doing random acts of kindness and making sure all the students at Medford High graduate.
Take a moment of silence in honor of the Boston Marathon victims.
is I will get to know students, get to know as many students as I can, and support them and learn about them.
We will take a moment of silence to honor the Boston Marathon victims.
Take a moment of silence in honor of the Boston Marathon victims.
Make a donation to the Crystal Campbell Fund, and I challenge you to do the same thing.
I'm going to make a difference by attending the softball tournament in the name of Crystal Campbell.
Mustangs on three.
One, two, three.
Mustangs!
A big part of Crystal's life was Medford High School and the activities that she participated in with the band and softball.
We are Medford Strong.
We love you, Crystal!