So yeah, okay, it is 1145 so we can begin. I know Nicole has a 12 o'clock appointment.
We have a Parks and Recreation Linkage Trust Committee meeting October 6, 2023 at 1145 a.m. The Parks and Recreation Linkage Trust Committee will hold a public meeting Friday the 6th via Zoom. Our agenda is as follows. Approval of up to $608,090 in linkage funds to go towards cost of design, permitting, and bidding for the implementation of phase two of the Carr Park
vision plan, request from planning development sustainability, approval of meeting minutes from October 27th, and then the second agenda item is the approval of the minutes from October 27, 2022. So, I will turn it over to you, Alicia and Amanda, just to give us a brief overview of what's going on and what the money is needed for.
Certainly. So as you all know, phase one of Gar Park is fully funded, is designed, is going into construction. We're in fact having a groundbreaking next week.
We have also received grant money for phase two of Car Park. That is many millions of dollars. Amanda could give us an exact number. One of those grants we've known about but we're still not able to publicly announce. It's a second land and water grant from the federal government.
That one's a million, there's a million and a half from the DOE, and then there's match money from ARPA to make up all the matches that we need for all of that.
Those monies, land and water grant and ARPA, sorry, and DOE are not available until January, although we are actually, we've moved into the contracting process for them. So however, in order to meet the timelines of this project, we really need to be doing community outreach and the design and construction documents for phase two now. Honestly, we should have started already.
Therefore, there's a request here to pay for the design consultant and preliminary work in order so that when the grant money is available, we'll be able to bid it out and use the grant money for construction.
To be clear, there is not as much our linkage money in the account as we put on the agenda. What we wanted to do was to just give you an upper number because Amanda and with Bob's help has been going through the linkage accounts to understand how much money is definitely available.
for allocating to this project. So at this meeting, we're actually gonna ask you to vote on a different number. The number we're asking for is $294,131. That is the amount that Bob and Amanda have looked at, and Bob, correct me if I'm wrong, is available in the Parks and Rec Linkage Trust.
As an aside, there are a number of other small accounts in the Parks and Rec linkage for projects that were approved between 2016 and 2019 that we believe the accounts could be closed out and the money returned to the trust.
We think that dollar amount is going to be on the order of $18,000. It could be a little higher once Amanda does a little bit more digging. But we believe that Bob has informed us that releasing that money to the trust needs to be a vote. We think we actually have to have a separate meeting where we've put it on the agenda so that it's publicly advertised before you release that money. Okay.
So at that point, the number would no longer be zero again. But we also, I always have a but, Park has some small, we know we're gonna need some change orders and that they would be under $20,000 worth of work. So what we're hoping to do is have a solid number on Gillis change orders, have a solid knowledge of how much is,
we're releasing back to the trust, and then have one meeting where we ask you to release those small accounts and allocate a little bit more to Gillis. So I just wanted you to know that that was also going on, but we weren't ready with those numbers today. But we really need to get started with the car park work, design work. Okay, and just so I'm clear from the chair,
Bob, there is at least $294,131 in that account, or is that the exact number in the account? $294, well, that account has received $620,041 in revenue this year, so the actual number available right now is $294,715.
Oh, say that again. Your audio is a little off for me. They gave me a new laptop computer that's supposed to solve all my problems and it doesn't work. I sent everybody a PDF of the latest update today. But yeah, 294,759 projects that Amanda
forward it to me, but I do believe we need to vote to close total 17, 977.52. And then at some point, we have to figure out why there's a deficit in one of these things, 1.23, but I think it's probably just a misposed that I can get rid of, so we're gonna have to build on that. Let's see that. It's the third project from the bottom, a short nine grand.
And then any of these other little projects that, you know, the little balances left, if we could get rid of those two, that'd be great. I'd like to clean things up that way. But yes, we can vote on 284,131.50 right now. That's what's left. So that's it, Morel. Do you have any questions? Just about,
Director Hunt, do you anticipate we'll be coming, I mean, other than the small amounts in that additional vote you talked about, do you anticipate there'll be further linkage requests for the car park project?
We would love to come in with further linkage requests to help pay for the rest of the design and consulting fee. The number that was in the agenda is what we're actually going to need. But what we also are trying to do is what are the projects that are going to be paying linkage. We have two projects that we definitely know are going to be paying linkage, but they're not only residential projects pay parks and rec.
So we have two projects that are not paying parks and rec that are coming in soon. We actually need to go look at the 40B as that's when that applies for its building permit, they need to pay linkage.
And I need to settle how much of that is going into Parks and Rec because the ZBA negotiated with them and is not charging them the full amount. They're giving them some deductions. So we need to figure out how much of that will go into the Parks and Rec's fund. Okay, and then I guess my question is, so just after this like $608,000 number, do you think in future phases, just out of curiosity,
there'll be a request for that project for linkage? So this isn't asking for the full 600,000? Yeah, but you said you would like that. We would like that if we had it available. The difference between the 294 and the 600,000 number, we're still going to need to work with the mayor to figure out where that's coming from and how that works out in
the ARPA money, the grant money, the rest of it, but this number will get us started until we have access to the grant funds. Okay, understood. And then the project to see it bid out. So there is a chance that the grant numbers aren't exactly right, so maybe the design money can go into the grants, and maybe we won't have enough, depends what happens when we go out to bid. Okay, thank you.
So I would. Yeah, I would motion to approve the amount that 291, if someone could read back the amount because I don't have it in front of me. Yep. So motion to approve as amended to make it read 294,131.50. Yes. I remember by President Morrell, seconded by CFO Dickinson. I'll do a roll call vote. President Morrell? Yes.
you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. CFO Dickinson. Yes. And myself. Yes, that's 3 in the affirmative 0 in the The motion as amended has been approved. So thank you all for your time and PDS Amanda and Alicia, thank you for all your hard work on this will. Figure out the rest of the night in the coming weeks, right. We can put those minutes on the next meeting. If you want
Did those get sent to us, or I don't know if I saw them, or? I did send them out, and they were in the meeting invite, but we can definitely move them to a subsequent meeting. Yeah, that would be great. Motion to table. Second. Motion to table the minutes from October 2022, by President Morrell, seconded by Director Dickinson. I'll call that roll. President Morrell? Yes. Director Dickinson?
the meeting minutes from October 22nd to have been tabled to our next meeting and then we'll also use
We'll try and give you more notice. We appreciate you doing this quickly for us so that we could get this project moving. I think we'll have a little bit more flexibility with our timing for this next group, the next meeting. Great. Great. Thank you so much. Thank you, President Morrell. Sorry you had to do it driving. We appreciate your time. No worries. I'm stopping now at least. So I guess motion to adjourn?
motion to adjourn by President Morrell, seconded by Director Dickinson. Motion for approval to adjourn. Moral call vote, President Morrell? Yeah. Director Dickinson? Yes. And yes for me too, so that's three in the affirmative, motion is adjourned. Have a wonderful weekend, everybody. And Amanda, you took those minutes or do you want me to type them up? I'll take them, yeah. Awesome, thank you. Thanks, have a great weekend, everybody.