[SPEAKER_01]: Good evening, everyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: The 38th regular meeting of Medford City Council.
[SPEAKER_01]: Madam Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, Councilor Bears.
[SPEAKER_01]: Present.
[SPEAKER_04]: Councilor Falco.
[SPEAKER_04]: Vice President Knight.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you unmute, Councilor Knight?
[SPEAKER_04]: Vice President Knight, okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_01]: Present.
[SPEAKER_04]: Councilor Morell.
[SPEAKER_00]: Present.
[SPEAKER_04]: Councilor Schapelle.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's here.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's on Zoom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seven present.
[SPEAKER_02]: I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America, and to the Republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all.
[SPEAKER_01]: All right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reports of committees.
[SPEAKER_01]: November 9th, 21611, Committee of the Whole report.
[SPEAKER_01]: This was... What was that about?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Motion to accept the November 9th Committee of the Whole report.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the motion by Councilor Bears, seconded by Councilor Morell and Madam Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Bears?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Bailão?
[SPEAKER_03]: Vice President Knight?
[SPEAKER_01]: He's muted, I don't know why we can't unmute him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Shane, can you unmute Councilor Knight and Councilor Scarpelli?
[SPEAKER_01]: All right.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm unmuted, Mr. President.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: 7 affirmative motion passes.
[SPEAKER_01]: 21600 and 21601 November 10th committee of the whole motion to accept the minutes of
[SPEAKER_01]: of those two meetings.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the motion by, on the motion by Councilor Morell, seconded by?
[SPEAKER_01]: Second.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seconded by Councilor Bears.
[SPEAKER_01]: Madam Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_04]: Councilor Bears.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Councilor Falco.
[SPEAKER_04]: President Knight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, President Knight.
[SPEAKER_04]: Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Councilor Morell.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
Councilor Falco.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, I move the affirmative, motion passes.
[SPEAKER_01]: 21618, November 16th, Committee of the Whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the motion to accept the report.
[SPEAKER_01]: Motion by Councilor Behr, seconded by.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right here, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the CPA, but the fire station.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seconded by Councilor Falco.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Madam Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says yes also.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So in the affirmative motion passes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Public participation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does anyone want to speak in public participation?
[SPEAKER_01]: Good evening.
[SPEAKER_01]: Name and address of the record please.
[SPEAKER_02]: I wanna speak about the traffic concerns that we had at the intersection of Carding West, North, and Auburn Street.
[SPEAKER_02]: The city traffic engineer has done two designs, and I have taken those designs around the neighborhood.
[SPEAKER_02]: I've showed them to over 200 residents.
[SPEAKER_02]: The residents that have seen this say both, they reject both of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: They said that the cause is not being addressed.
[SPEAKER_02]: The cause of all these traffic problems stem from Route 16.
[SPEAKER_01]: What?
[SPEAKER_02]: Route 16 is the source of all these traffic violations.
[SPEAKER_02]: The Auburn's, the Cotting Street residents say that the residents, drivers are going down the wrong way.
[SPEAKER_02]: But there's also wrong way drivers on West Street, on Norton Ave, on Marshall Street.
[SPEAKER_02]: So this is what I'm hearing from residents.
[SPEAKER_02]: So they say, you're gonna close off Cotting Street.
[SPEAKER_02]: What about Norton Ave, West Street, Marshall Street?
[SPEAKER_02]: You're gonna close those off too?
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not solving any problems by the designs that we have presented to us thus far.
[SPEAKER_02]: I have called the mayor's office and I told the mayor I want to meet with her in person because I want to relay to her what I'm hearing from the residents.
[SPEAKER_02]: She's going to get back to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: I talked to her before Thanksgiving.
[SPEAKER_02]: She's going to get back to me after Thanksgiving.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I'm hoping that we can arrange for an in-person meeting at the site.
[SPEAKER_02]: that I can explain the concerns of these over 200 residents that I've spoken to.
[SPEAKER_02]: And we're not gonna have a huge meeting there because it would just be too cumbersome, but I can, I'm just gonna have- You can do it on a Saturday morning again.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, I don't wanna have a big to-do.
[SPEAKER_02]: I just wanna have a quiet little thing so that she can observe.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm gonna have one resident from each one of the streets who sees what happened on their streets there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it would be a public meeting.
[SPEAKER_01]: So anyone who wanted to attend could come.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we'd have to advertise it.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I want to see her instead of meeting in her office.
[SPEAKER_02]: I could explain all this to her in office, but I think for her to see it in person would, I'm not expecting all the Councilors to be there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It sounds like a meeting between the mayor and the council.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm just updating the council on what's transpired since,
[SPEAKER_02]: The traffic design was made and the traffic commission meeting was held.
[SPEAKER_02]: The traffic commission meeting, I was the only one that showed up because I hounded Todd when the meeting was gonna be.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was not advertised.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was the only resident that showed up that said that they were opposed to the designs that were presented.
[SPEAKER_02]: So the traffic commission decided to postpone any decision on the designs until the next meeting.
[SPEAKER_02]: And they said that they were gonna advertise it, whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: But again, I'm gonna back up here.
[SPEAKER_02]: The real crux of the problem is Route 16.
[SPEAKER_02]: Back about 10 years ago when they first did the study for the Green Line, back then they put a meter across the road right near Boston Ave.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then there were 12,000 cars a day that crossed Route 16.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know what it is today.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the traffic that goes down Route 16, for the most part, is pass-through traffic.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not local traffic because the locals avoid it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I know that it's a state road, so the city would have to negotiate with the state, but there was green space to the side of the road.
[SPEAKER_02]: If they had to widen the road, you would not be displacing people or taking any eminent domain.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's already state land there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I think it would go a long way to improve the neighborhood situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you could just have the flow through traffic leave on Route 16 without trying to take detours through the side streets.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I just wanted to update the council on what's transpired in the last two or three weeks.
[SPEAKER_02]: All right, I don't expect you to respond to anything here because I have a calling to the mayor here.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm gonna be meeting with the mayor at some point to update her and see where we can go.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you could let us know when you're meeting with the mayor is at the same, if anyone wants to attend.
[SPEAKER_02]: she'll come to the site, but we're not moving on.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you could let us know, we'd be, whoever wants to attend, we'd be happy to attend.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it may be during the week when it's probably not convenient for all of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm around during the day.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if you want, I can come.
[SPEAKER_02]: All right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's just an update.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you very much for coming.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hey, any further business?
[SPEAKER_01]: Records.
[SPEAKER_01]: The records.
[SPEAKER_01]: Records of the meeting of November 9th.
[SPEAKER_01]: We'll pass to Councilor Falco.
[SPEAKER_01]: Councilor Falco, how did you find those records?
[SPEAKER_02]: I read the records.
[SPEAKER_02]: They appear to be in order and I move approval.
[SPEAKER_01]: Second.
[SPEAKER_01]: The motion by Councilor Falco, seconded by Councilor Bears.
[SPEAKER_01]: Madam Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Bears.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Falco.
[SPEAKER_01]: Vice President Mack.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Councilor Gabbard.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same in the affirmative motion passes records of the meeting of the 16th.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're past the vice president night vice president night.
[SPEAKER_01]: How did you find those records.
[SPEAKER_01]: The reader says.
[SPEAKER_01]: Council night would like to table that the records second, seconded by Council of Mayor's men and please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says yes also.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: 70 affirmative motion passes the records.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The table, the Nova 60 records of number 23rd were passed the council of marks Councilor Marks.
[SPEAKER_01]: How did you find those records?
[SPEAKER_01]: On the motion by Councilor Marksley, table those records.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seconded by?
[SPEAKER_01]: Second.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seconded by Councilor Falco.
[SPEAKER_01]: Madam Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm in the affirmative.
[SPEAKER_01]: Motion passes.
[SPEAKER_01]: table.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any further business?
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a, I don't have the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you know what time the event starts here tomorrow?
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's an event, the holiday extravaganza.
[SPEAKER_01]: Starts at six, I think six o'clock.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might be five.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe five, I think five o'clock.
[SPEAKER_01]: We have a community board meeting at six.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: On Zoom, correct?
[SPEAKER_01]: On Zoom, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And
[SPEAKER_01]: We will be having a committee of the whole being to talk about the taxes, you know, the tax classification hearing that we normally have before the end of the year.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I think we're doing that on the 14th, because it has to be done by the 21st.
[SPEAKER_01]: All right, so motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_01]: Motion by Councilor Bears, seconded by Vice President Knight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Madam Clerk, please call the roll.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, he said he says yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, affirmative.
[SPEAKER_01]: Motion passes meeting adjourned.