Good evening, everyone. The 38th regular meeting of Memphis City Council. Madam Clerk, please call the roll. Okay, Councilor Beers. Present. Councilor Falco. Present. Vice President Knight. He's here. Can you unmute, Councilor Knight? Vice President Knight, okay. Councilor Mox. Present. Councilor Morrell. Present. Councilor Schapelle. He's here.
He's on Zoom. Present. Seven present. I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America, and to the Republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all. All right.
Reports of committees. November 9th, 21611, Committee of the Whole report. This was... What was that about? Yeah. Motion to accept the November 9th Committee of the Whole report.
On the motion by Councilor Behrs, seconded by Councilor Morrell and Madam Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Behrs? Yes. Councilor Bailão? Yes. Vice President Knight? He's muted, I don't know why we can't unmute him. Shane, can you unmute Councilor Knight and Councilor Scarpelli?
All right. I'm unmuted, Mr. President. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. 7 affirmative motion passes. 21600 and 21601 November 10th committee of the whole motion to accept the minutes of
of those two meetings. On the motion by, on the motion by Councilor Morrell, seconded by? Second. Seconded by Councilor Behrs. Madam Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Behrs. Yes. Councilor Falco. Yes. President Knight. Yes, President Knight. Councilor Mox. Yes. Councilor Morrell. Yes. Councilor Fevella. Yes. Yes, I move the affirmative, motion passes.
21618, November 16th, Committee of the Whole. On the motion to accept the report. Motion by Councilor Behr, seconded by. Right here, yeah. It's the CPA, but the fire station. Seconded by Councilor Falco. Yes. Madam Clerk, please call the roll.
Yes. Yes. He says yes. Yes. Yes. He says yes also. Yes. So in the affirmative motion passes. Public participation. Does anyone want to speak in public participation? Good evening. Name and address of the record please.
I wanna speak about the traffic concerns that we had at the intersection of Carding West, North, and Auburn Street. The city traffic engineer has done two designs, and I have taken those designs around the neighborhood. I've showed them to over 200 residents. The residents that have seen this say both, they reject both of them.
They said that the cause is not being addressed. The cause of all these traffic problems stem from Route 16. What? Route 16 is the source of all these traffic violations.
The Auburn's, the Cotting Street residents say that the residents, drivers are going down the wrong way. But there's also wrong way drivers on West Street, on Norton Ave, on Marshall Street. So this is what I'm hearing from residents. So they say, you're gonna close off Cotting Street. What about Norton Ave, West Street, Marshall Street? You're gonna close those off too? You're not solving any problems by the designs that we have presented to us thus far.
I have called the mayor's office and I told the mayor I want to meet with her in person because I want to relay to her what I'm hearing from the residents. She's going to get back to me. I talked to her before Thanksgiving. She's going to get back to me after Thanksgiving. So I'm hoping that we can arrange for an in-person meeting at the site.
that I can explain the concerns of these over 200 residents that I've spoken to. And we're not gonna have a huge meeting there because it would just be too cumbersome, but I can, I'm just gonna have- You can do it on a Saturday morning again. No, no, I don't wanna have a big to-do. I just wanna have a quiet little thing so that she can observe. I'm gonna have one resident from each one of the streets who sees what happened on their streets there.
And it would be a public meeting. So anyone who wanted to attend could come. So we'd have to advertise it. No, I want to see her instead of meeting in her office. I could explain all this to her in office, but I think for her to see it in person would, I'm not expecting all the counselors to be there. It sounds like a meeting between the mayor and the council. That's fine. I'm just updating the council on what's transpired since,
The traffic design was made and the traffic commission meeting was held. The traffic commission meeting, I was the only one that showed up because I hounded Todd when the meeting was gonna be. It was not advertised. I was the only resident that showed up that said that they were opposed to the designs that were presented. So the traffic commission decided to postpone any decision on the designs until the next meeting. And they said that they were gonna advertise it, whatever.
But again, I'm gonna back up here. The real crux of the problem is Route 16. Back about 10 years ago when they first did the study for the Green Line, back then they put a meter across the road right near Boston Ave. Then there were 12,000 cars a day that crossed Route 16. I don't know what it is today. But the traffic that goes down Route 16, for the most part, is pass-through traffic. It's not local traffic because the locals avoid it.
And I know that it's a state road, so the city would have to negotiate with the state, but there was green space to the side of the road. If they had to widen the road, you would not be displacing people or taking any eminent domain. It's already state land there. And I think it would go a long way to improve the neighborhood situation. If you could just have the flow through traffic leave on Route 16 without trying to take detours through the side streets.
So I just wanted to update the council on what's transpired in the last two or three weeks. All right, I don't expect you to respond to anything here because I have a calling to the mayor here. I'm gonna be meeting with the mayor at some point to update her and see where we can go. If you could let us know when you're meeting with the mayor is at the same, if anyone wants to attend.
she'll come to the site, but we're not moving on. I don't know. If you could let us know, we'd be, whoever wants to attend, we'd be happy to attend. Well, it may be during the week when it's probably not convenient for all of you. I'm around during the day. So if you want, I can come. All right. Okay. Well, that's just an update. Thank you very much for coming. Thank you. Hey, any further business? Records. The records. Records of the meeting of November 9th.
We'll pass to Councilor Falco. Councilor Falco, how did you find those records? I read the records. They appear to be in order and I move approval. Second. The motion by Councilor Falco, seconded by Councilor Behrs. Madam Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Behrs. Yes. Councilor Falco. Yes. Vice President Mack. Yes. Councilor Gabbard. Yes.
Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Same in the affirmative motion passes records of the meeting of the 16th. We're past the vice president night vice president night. How did you find those records. The reader says. Council night would like to table that the records second, seconded by Council of Mayor's men and please call the roll.
Yes. He says yes. Yes. He says yes also. Yes. 70 affirmative motion passes the records. Yeah. The table, the Nova 60 records of number 23rd were passed the council of marks council marks. How did you find those records?
On the motion by Councilor Moxley, table those records. Seconded by? Second. Seconded by Councilor Falco. Madam Clerk, please call the roll. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. I'm in the affirmative. Motion passes.
table. Any further business? There is a, I don't have the time. Do you know what time the event starts here tomorrow? I'm sorry. There's an event, the holiday extravaganza. Starts at six, I think six o'clock. It might be five. Maybe five, I think five o'clock. We have a community board meeting at six. Right. Yes. On Zoom, correct? On Zoom, yes. Because the, yeah. Yes. And
We will be having a committee of the whole being to talk about the taxes, you know, the tax classification hearing that we normally have before the end of the year. So I think we're doing that on the 14th, because it has to be done by the 21st. All right, so motion to adjourn. Motion by Councilor Behrs, seconded by Vice President Knight. Madam Clerk, please call the roll.
Yes. Yes. Yes, he said he says yes. Yes. Yes. Yes, affirmative. Motion passes meeting adjourned.