Thank you for being with us this evening. Sorry for the delay. I am going to get the meeting started.
Welcome to tonight's meeting of the Method Community Development Board. I'll call the meeting to order. We're going to begin with obligatory procedural matters. I'm going to read the actual public hearing notice, the remote hearing notice. This hearing of the Method Community Development Board is being conducted via remote means. However, accommodations for in-person participation to view the meeting and provide comments is being made available in room 201 of City Hall.
and recording of this meeting will be made available on the Metro Community Media website, metrotv.org. A reminder that given the remote nature of this meeting tonight, all votes from the board will be made by roll call. Actually, I just wanna back that one up with the city, and ask the city regarding the Room 201 of City Hall. Is that still applicable for this evening? Yes, Madam Chair, and Teresa is coming to you live from Room 201. Okay, awesome.
Please know that the project materials for all projects before the board can be viewed on the city's website, medfordma.org. You can click on current city board filings. You can also find a link in the chat. Danielle, can you actually, I'm going to do roll call attendance after the city introduces anyone on the staff. Yeah, so I just added the current filings to the chat.
Myself, Daniel Evans, senior planner. Our director, Alicia Hunt. Teresa Japan is helping out tonight in room 201. She is the Community Preservation Act manager. And this is not her job, but she's helping out, which we appreciate. And I believe that is all of us. Oh, we also have a graduate student intern, Gabe Weinstein,
will be taking minutes tonight. Awesome. Thank you, Daniel. Okay, I'm going to go back to roll call. I just wanted to give an extra minute, just in case there was one other board member that was joining us. Peter Kautz. Here. And I'm just going to double check for Ari Fishman.
Pam Marianski. Here. Sally Akiki. Present. And myself, Jackie McPherson. I am present. So the first item for this evening is approval not required. It's an A&R plan for review for 970 Felsway. I'm going to, before I invite the proponent to present their plans for 970 Felsway, I would ask if the city can give us a synopsis on this.
Yes, Madam Chair. 970 Felsway is the site of a recently approved comprehensive permit location. And despite a comprehensive permit where the ZBA does everything, the Community Development Board still needs to approve the ANR, which is approval not required to
I'll let Patrick noon from Davis companies explain, but there's some division of a lot from the existing use but he'll, he'll explain all that. But that's what the project is here it's all approved, it's just a formality to create the new lot.
Thank you. Okay, so I will invite to present the plans for 970 Fellsway. If you can please give them screen sharing abilities, make them co-host whoever's presenting. Yes, that would be me. Thank you. I will start sharing now.
Can everyone see my screen?
Great. So I will be brief. Thank you again for hearing us this evening. So just following up on what Danielle was saying, we have been through the comprehensive permit hearing process with the ZBA, recently concluded that process. We are following up now here with this A&R plan submission for endorsement.
What you see on the screen here is an aerial view of the building and the site as it exists today. Just giving a picture of what the existing conditions are as the site exists today, it is currently one lot.
As we have gone through this comprehensive permit process, the stated intention has been from the start to separate the existing parcel into two parcels, whereby there will be a residential development on one parcel and then the existing extra storage space
building will remain on the other parcel. Just following up to the formal A&R plans, so these are the plans that have been submitted and filed with the Community Development Board for endorsement that identify the separation between the two parcels identified on the screen here as lot two and lot three. These have been certified by our surveyor Feldman
and are here for formal endorsement. So that is the end of the formal presentation that I have to give this evening. Thank you very much. Can you tell me what the frontage actually, what were the dimensions again?
Um, what are the dimension? So the project of fronts, myrtle street and fells way.
I don't have the formal application up in front of me, just referring to the plans here. So this is 336 feet, roughly, along Myrtle Street here, and then another 25 feet, roughly, along Myrtle Street at the corner between Myrtle and Felsway, and then there is
I don't want to quote the wrong information for you, just doing this live and on the fly. I'm sure we have it on the application that was submitted, which I, again, do not have in front of me for what that formal dimension is, but I can follow up if that's a question that needs answered at this current time.
Thank you. Part of, I just have to make sure they satisfy the minimum funds requirements and that there's vital access to the lots. Planner Evans, are you able to provide that information? Hold on a second. I'm just trying to troubleshoot a document issue. Sorry, Jackie, could you ask a question again?
What was it that you were looking for? What is the minimum frontage? 50 feet. It's 50. Okay. My document has 35. And so I'm a little- I think that's from the wrong planning, the wrong district. Okay. Right. I thought that all, yes, it's a commercial. It would be 50 feet. This has 50 feet. Okay. My apologies. I just wanted to say thank you.
I'm going to open it up to the board for questions while I continue to look forward to something. Does anyone have questions? Peter Kautz? Yes, I don't know if, I'm not sure who to direct this question at specifically.
Uh, I just want to kind of, I guess, understand the process and what it is, what it is, and is not the. The proponent and the city are asking the board to do.
Did you have a specific generally? So an approval not required is where you have one lot that you're dividing into more than one lot or two lots that you're joining together. And as long as there is appropriate frontage on a legal way, then the board has to say yes.
there there isn't any discretion and it doesn't matter what the buildings are on the lots it doesn't matter what the zoning is of the lots like none of that is required that is why the the procedure is called an approval not required. One time I saw this board deny one because the
place where the the property met a road was the very end of a dead end there was only about 10 feet and then they were like we'll make space for a fire truck to turn around and basically that was there wasn't appropriate frontage for the second lot on a legal way but as long as there's appropriate frontage the zoning board is just confirming that yes there is
access. And so this very clearly has frontage on the new parcel on two streets and on the remaining parcel on Felsway. Okay, that's fine. I just was unfamiliar with the process and was trying to figure out what the criteria we should be looking for were.
The questions are, yeah, do the lots front on a right of way? Do the lots satisfy minimum frontage? And then is vital access provided? Some of the neighboring cities actually don't go through this process because they've opted out of subdivision control law, where, for example, in Somerville, the planning director just signs this. It doesn't go to their planning board.
Yeah, and based on the fact that there is at least 50 feet, I'm going to actually just move it along and ask for a motion to endorse the plan as proven not required. Do I have a motion? I second the motion. I second. I, Peter, second. I'm going to do a roll call. Peter Kautz? Aye. Pam Ariansky? Aye.
Sally and Kiki? Aye. And myself, Jackie McPherson, I'm an aye. Thank you so much for being here with us tonight. Thank you very much. You too. The 2nd item on our agenda tonight is 400 minutes to GAV, special permits, site plan review.
So the applicant is requesting a continuance to a date, July 17, 2024, which is the date certain. That's when they want to finalize the requested revisions. So I am going to ask the board for a motion to continue the public hearing for 400 Mystic Ave to July 17, 2024. So moved. And a second. Second.
Roll call, Peter Kautz. Aye. Pam Mariansky. Aye. Sally Akiki. Aye. And myself, Jackie McPherson. I'm an aye. Our third item this evening is 360 Salem Street, which is ZBA case A-24-14. It was a public hearing on June 27, 20. There will be a June, there was a public hearing scheduled for tomorrow, June 27, 2024.
The applicant has submitted a letter to withdraw their special permit application from the CBA. Since there is no longer an active application for city board to review in its advisory role, the matter is also withdrawn from CDB and there will be no discussion of public comment. Item four, approval of minutes. I'm going to ask for a motion to approve the minutes for May 15th, 2024.
I said emotion. A second. I Peter second. Roll call Peter cows. Hi, Pam Marianski. I'm selling a kiki. Hi, myself, Jack McPherson. I'm an eye.
Before adjournment, I want to ask if the board or the city has any other items for discussion. Madam chair, we have someone in the audience is having difficulty hearing. I believe they logged out and back in because they're
I saw that after they sent the message they logged out and now that phone number is back in. So, okay, I'm having a hard time running the zoom and also following. So I missed that. So if everyone is all set and if the individual missed the announcement that 360 Salem Street
it's being withdrawn from the zoning board, and so there's not an application for this board to review and make recommendations on, and therefore there's not an item that they can discuss. And any general discussion, it's not on the agenda, so that would be a violation of open meeting law. So it may be an agenda item in the future, but it is,
not going to be heard. And with that, if there's no other items from the board or the city,
And if we feel confident that all members have heard the announcement in regards to item three, 360 Salem Street, not being heard, since it was withdrawn, I will ask for a motion to adjourn. Having no other items. A motion. A second. Second.
Is that Pam? Yes. Roll call. Peter Klaus? Aye. Pam Marianski? Aye. Sally Akiki? Aye. And myself, Jackie McPherson. Thank you everyone for coming tonight. We will reconvene on July 17th. Have a good evening. Thank you.