[SPEAKER_00]: Hi, this is Anna Callahan with a post-campaign update.
[SPEAKER_00]: By the end of my campaign, I had started to think a lot about what I wanted to do if I were elected.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when I lost on election night, I realized that all of the things I was the most excited about, engaging new people in the political process, building the movement that we need in order to pass a Green New Deal, Medicare for All, a criminal justice overhaul, and housing for everyone here in Massachusetts, that all of those things were things that I didn't need to be a state rep to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can do them right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: There has never been a more important moment in our country.
[SPEAKER_00]: between the presidential elections and an ongoing pandemic leaving 40 million people unemployed, with a climate crisis and the racism in our society and our criminal justice system.
[SPEAKER_00]: We need to step up our game to make the political process work for us.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I agree with AOC when she talks about what we need to be doing right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: She says we have to bring new people into the political process.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I think her words were that we have to do that in every pocket of this country between now and the November elections to save our democracy and even after the elections as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I couldn't agree more.
[SPEAKER_00]: I had the great privilege of being able to spend every day engaging people in state politics.
[SPEAKER_00]: And wow, I really miss it.
[SPEAKER_00]: loved it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I loved walking outdoors.
[SPEAKER_00]: I loved meeting new people.
[SPEAKER_00]: I loved hearing what matters to people, what issues people care about, and how it affects their lives.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I really miss dreaming big about what we could have if we all worked together and if our government worked for us.
[SPEAKER_00]: So my team and I will be engaging people in the political process right now through conversations about the upcoming election on November 3rd.
[SPEAKER_00]: We are going to be knocking on doors.
[SPEAKER_00]: We are going to be hosting Zoom meetings.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm most excited about going on walk and talks in the different parts of the district so that we can meet people where they are.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I hope that you'll join us.
[SPEAKER_00]: I really believe that if we build a movement here in this, one of the most progressive districts in one of the most progressive states in the country, that that is the way we can move our issues forward.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I look forward to seeing you soon.