Hi, my name is Melanie Tringali, and I'm a candidate for Medford City Council. A homeowner and taxpayer, my husband James Murdoch and I live on 4th Street with our four children, Michaela, Emily, Jackie, and my son Jacob, who is a junior at Medford High.
Both of my parents were born and raised here and graduated from Medford High School. My father, Salvatore J. Tringali, grew up in South Medford, and my mother, Lorraine Mifflin, grew up on the hillside. I am a UMass Amherst graduate and have over 20 years of business experience in operations and marketing, working for both for-profit and non-profit organizations.
For more than 20 years, I've volunteered with organizations throughout Medford. I served on the Medford Family Network Advisory Board, was co-chair of the PTO for what was then the Columbus School, served on the Historic District Commission, and organized annual park cleanups. Today, I'm a board member of the Rotary Club, an organization that provides community service to our cities and schools, providing college scholarships, neighborhood improvements, and other initiatives such as Thanksgiving and Christmas baskets.
Why am I running? For too long, I've seen our elected officials focus more on ideology and national issues rather than the local challenges right in front of us. My goal is to bring the focus back to Medford to strengthen our communities, support our residents, and address the issues that affect our daily lives. We need to bring common sense back to the city council, the kind that strengthens our neighborhoods, improves city services, and respects the character and history of our community.
As a councilwoman, there are many things I will work on, but let me highlight my top priorities. One, I will always stand up to protect our neighborhoods in historic squares. Blanket rezoning that favors high density would forever change the look and feel of our community.
Instead, we need thoughtful, balanced planning that focuses on revitalizing our commercial areas and main corridors, bringing new life to our business districts, expanding our tax base, and supporting responsible growth that benefits residents. With more than 1,100 new apartment units already in the pipeline, there is no need to expand residential zoning. Mevitt can grow and thrive without sacrificing the character and charm of our neighborhoods.
Two, our streets and sidewalks remain in poor condition. Potholes, uneven walkways, and crumbling pavement make daily life difficult for too many residents, specifically our seniors and physically challenged. Despite budget overrides and staffing changes, little progress has been made. Safe sidewalks, well-maintained streets, and reliable city facilities aren't optional. They're basic city services. We must repair what's broken now while also investing in long-term maintenance plans.
Three, our police officers, firefighters, and emergency personnel put their lives on the line every day. They deserve full staffing, safe facilities, and modern equipment to do their jobs effectively. Public safety must come first in our city budget. We need to prioritize the health and safety of those who protect us and ensure our neighborhoods remain safe for everyone.
Four, for the fourth year in a row, Medford has carried unusually high levels of free cash reserves, a sign that we need better financial planning and accountability. I will push for line-item budgets, transparent reporting, and a financial process that shows where every tax dollar goes. We also need to diversify our revenue by encouraging commercial growth, reducing over-reliance on residential taxpayers, and ensuring we're investing in projects that deliver real value for our community. And five,
We need traffic patterns that ease congestion, not create it. Lane reductions, narrowed streets, and scattered pylons strewn across the city have only made driving more frustrating and stressful. It's time to bring common sense to our traffic planning. Any changes, whether it's a lane adjustment, signal timing, or street redesigns, should be well-planned and backed by real studies and data, not rushed experiments.
At the same time, we must ensure clear, well-marked crosswalks and safe intersections so that walkers, cyclists and drivers can all move safely and confidently through our city. Medford residents deserve a transportation plan that works for everyone.
Together, these priorities strengthen the foundation of our community and help make Medford the special place that it is. I'll bring to City Hall an independent, fair-minded voice focused on what works for Medford, not on partisanship or politics. My decisions will always be guided by what's best for the residents and neighborhoods. In closing, Medford deserves a City Council that puts Medford first.
I look forward to earning your support, your trust, and the opportunity to serve you and our city on November 4th. I respectfully ask for one of your seven votes for City Council. Thank you.