[SPEAKER_04]: All right, good afternoon, everybody, and welcome to the June meeting of the Medford Board of Health.
[SPEAKER_02]: The meeting, it's 1234 p.m.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, this meeting is being held by Zoom only.
[SPEAKER_04]: Dr. Platowicz, would you like to open the meeting, please?
[SPEAKER_05]: The meeting is officially open.
[SPEAKER_05]: First is the review of the minutes that were mailed to everybody from the last meeting.
[SPEAKER_04]: So I know Jenny had emailed me a couple of changes just to her name.
[SPEAKER_04]: She's not Jennifer.
[SPEAKER_04]: She's Jenny.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sorry, I apologize, Jenny, for that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then a couple of other minor changes.
[SPEAKER_04]: about her working in Medicaid ACO space for the past five years.
[SPEAKER_04]: So we will make those revisions.
[SPEAKER_04]: Other than those revisions, everybody else get a chance to review the minutes?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Good to me.
[SPEAKER_05]: Motion to approve.
[SPEAKER_04]: Second.
[SPEAKER_04]: Moved by Dr. Polanowicz, seconded by Kathy.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: All in favor?
[SPEAKER_04]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_04]: All right, so we'll make those revisions and send those back out to everybody.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't see anyone here from communications, but I'll send them out back down to Emma as well, so she can post them for us.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, so.
[SPEAKER_04]: What we're gonna try to do today, and hopefully we'll accomplish a lot, if not most of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So we're looking, actually, this came about, and Kit Collins has joined us on the Zoom today, and Kit, these are our board members, Dr. David Flatowicz, Kathy Chabonier, and Jenny Vital.
[SPEAKER_04]: Kit is our city councilor who's been working with the city council on
[SPEAKER_04]: updating the city's solid waste ordinance and that has to do a lot with the haulers and they're adding the recycling requirement as well as other revisions to the ordinance and once we started going through the ordinance
[SPEAKER_04]: It was apparent that we wanted our haulers regulation and our permitting process for haulers to obviously match up with the ordinance requirements and changes.
[SPEAKER_04]: So Kit was gracious enough to go through this with me a couple of weeks ago.
[SPEAKER_04]: And we did see a lot of revisions that need to be made
[SPEAKER_04]: And a lot of them just need to be made anyways, because I think the last time this regulation was looked at was in 2009.
[SPEAKER_04]: So language has to be updated and definitions have to be revised.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then our permitting process, we want to mirror what the requirements are with the new city ordinance.
[SPEAKER_04]: So I think I sent you all regulation five and six.
[SPEAKER_04]: So you could go kind of follow along with me on this.
[SPEAKER_04]: And we'll just go through it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then once we approve the changes as we go, what I'll do is update the regulation, send it all out to you, and we can probably vote to approve the revisions and the revised regulation at our September meeting, if that makes sense.
[SPEAKER_04]: But we'll see how it goes today, see how far we get.
[SPEAKER_04]: So first off,
[SPEAKER_04]: We need to really include the word recyclables in and throughout the regulation, because right now we just have solid waste removal septic awful medical waste.
[SPEAKER_04]: grease rendering, transportation, and dumpster permitting and operations.
[SPEAKER_04]: So really nowhere in our regulation right now is the word recyclables.
[SPEAKER_04]: So actually just putting it right at the top on the title of the regulation after solid waste, it would be solid waste and recyclables.
[SPEAKER_04]: That being said, we need to add the word recyclables to our definitions.
[SPEAKER_04]: So our list of definitions,
[SPEAKER_04]: stats and would be going on page two if we went in alphabetical order, and we can use the definition that's now currently being used in the ordinance.
[SPEAKER_04]: So the definition as in the ordinance which we would be adding is recyclables shall mean, that's not an easy word to say.
[SPEAKER_04]: Recyclables shall mean a material that is banned from disposal in the Commonwealth of Massachusetts pursuant to 310 CMI 19.017, waste bins, mixed paper, cardboard, glass, metal and plastic containers are priority materials of this regulation.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that is the definition of recyclables that we'll be taking away from the ordinance and using in our regulation as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: Also, the ordinance does mention and point out mercury disposal prohibition.
[SPEAKER_04]: We have hazardous waste as a definition in our list, but we don't call out specifically mercury.
[SPEAKER_04]: So because that is going to be part of the new permitting process as well, we're going to add the mercury disposal prohibition definition as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: Another big discrepancy, kid if you're able if you want to join if you have an opinion.
[SPEAKER_04]: I kind of decided.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you look on page two of our regulation solid waste or waste definition.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's quite lengthy and encompassing, but I have a feeling that it's.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's aged out a bit and has probably been updated sense and the ordinance City Council solid waste definition is much smaller, and I think more succinct.
[SPEAKER_04]: So there's that again.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you have opinions and you want to keep really calling out specifics like we currently do, let me know.
[SPEAKER_04]: But right now in the ordinance, solid waste shall mean useless, unwanted, or discarded non-recyclable solid and liquid wastes, excluding items restricted from disposal in Massachusetts, as defined by table 310 CMI 19.01.
[SPEAKER_04]: 7.3 of Massachusetts Solid Waste Regulations, 310 CMI, 19.017.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, Kit, I know you and I talked about looking at the CMI so you could see if there were differences, but I think that this definition has been updated within the last 15 years so that if we just
[SPEAKER_04]: go with the solid waste definition as prescribed in the ordinance, I think we'd be covering.
[SPEAKER_04]: What I can do in the meantime is certainly make sure that that's the case, but I think we'll be covering all of the solid waste definitions as currently held by the state as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: Does that make sense to people?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is there a reason anyone would want to use, to stick with the current definition and the regulation as we have it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Thoughts?
[SPEAKER_06]: Seems very wordy, what's there now.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, I think so.
[SPEAKER_04]: So I'll just clarify 100% that what we want covered with all these things that are currently listed are in that all one and comes in 310 CMI 19.017.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, one difficulty, if you get too detailed and then list 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, I would then think if something's not listed where you would detail listing things, then that's
[SPEAKER_05]: would be okay to dispose of.
[SPEAKER_05]: So that's why, you know, I'd be all inclusive, but I'd be careful to listen 10 examples of what you consider solid waste because someone's going to say, well, this is the 11th and it's not on there.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you know, you would have put it on there if you wanted to call it solid waste.
[SPEAKER_05]: So it's not.
[SPEAKER_05]: So that's why I move against something that's very verbose and 10 things, because if something that's not on there, someone's going to assume it's not.
[SPEAKER_05]: covered when it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, you raised your hand.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah, thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_07]: And thank you all for having me here.
[SPEAKER_07]: I just wanted to, I don't want to take up very much of your time, but just because me and Director O'Connor have been talking about this one-on-one and in City Council meetings over several months, just to provide a little more context, you know, for other folks in the room, you know, these definitions and the updates to the solid waste ordinance in general.
[SPEAKER_07]: was based on like a best practices template from the MassDEP.
[SPEAKER_07]: That was kind of the origin of the document that we've been working off within the city council.
[SPEAKER_07]: And exactly to that point that you just made, Dr.
[SPEAKER_07]: Plasevich, you know, I think that the point here is to simplify, to have it point to sort of like longer lasting definitions at the state level.
[SPEAKER_07]: So it's not something that has to be continually updated and enumerated to make sure it's comprehensive, but just sort of provide a bigger umbrella.
[SPEAKER_07]: So, thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, so that's that makes a lot of sense to consolidate and go on the latest best practice as definitions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we will remove, basically removing A to I, as well as including a new definition.
[SPEAKER_02]: All right.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then we will be adding recyclables to the list here as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: So moving on to 5.4 general again, you know, we have the basically the title of the regulation and
[SPEAKER_04]: wherever we see that now, we're going to have to add the word recyclables to it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So again, I think we mentioned several, a couple of times here, actually three times within this one paragraph, solid waste, septic, awful, medical waste, resendering.
[SPEAKER_04]: So in all of those sentences, we'll be adding solid waste and recyclables to those sentences.
[SPEAKER_04]: The permitting procedure has to change up a bit as well, because there are some other requirements for the ordinance that we're going to have to add to our permitting procedure.
[SPEAKER_04]: And again, we have a twice solid waste septic offload medical waste.
[SPEAKER_04]: So we will be adding recyclables twice to that 5.5A.
[SPEAKER_04]: And also, where it says the City of Medford shall obtain a permit from the Board of Health, we're gonna add shall obtain and or annually renew, because that kind of was blaring, that that's not here now.
[SPEAKER_04]: Annually renew a permit from the Board of Health.
[SPEAKER_04]: All persons collecting and transporting amendments in the City of Medford shall obtain
[SPEAKER_03]: and or annually renew a permit from the Board of Health.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then under B are our requirements as they currently stand for the permit, the application form, the application fee, proof of property and liability insurance, a list of residential, municipal, and commercial industrial customer service by collection,
[SPEAKER_04]: I know in the ordinance they asked for the number, so we could adjust that as well, but I think getting a list is getting a number.
[SPEAKER_04]: Description of the collection vehicles, make model registration, name of the company appearing, and that we have the right to require all collection vehicles which are permitted in the city to have fixed on them, any markings identifying a permit holder.
[SPEAKER_04]: In addition,
[SPEAKER_04]: The new ordinance, or the proposed ordinance, I should say, asks that the permit application include a statement that the private hauler understands and complies with the Massachusetts Waste Ban and Mercury Disposal Prohibition.
[SPEAKER_04]: So we will be putting that statement or signature on the application form.
[SPEAKER_04]: Also, the ordinance, the annual permit renewal,
[SPEAKER_04]: says the application must indicate any changes from the original permit, including any change in solid waste or recyclable facilities used.
[SPEAKER_04]: We do ask for that list every year, and must be signed by the business owner.
[SPEAKER_04]: Currently, we say signed by the owner, manager, or agent.
[SPEAKER_04]: So we can adjust that as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: It also says that the renewal must be accompanied by the following information or a completed annual solid waste and recyclables reporting form.
[SPEAKER_04]: So in lieu of the recyclables reporting form, they have a list of what would be required and it's A through E.
[SPEAKER_04]: So we will include those requirements and they basically, I'll summarize a little bit.
[SPEAKER_04]: They are asking for the total tons of solid waste collected and the total tons of recyclable collected for processing from residential customers, generators within the city and the previous year, calendar year or 12 month period.
[SPEAKER_04]: In the case where the permitted hauler estimates the tonnage of a specific load for disposal of recycling, the permitted hauler shall use an industry standard table designated by the Commissioner of Public Works and provide the estimated tonnage to the city.
[SPEAKER_04]: So we will work on getting that and again revise the requirements in our permit application.
[SPEAKER_04]: Also ask for the average number of customers, both residential and
[SPEAKER_04]: Commercial, it asks for the names, which we do already have commercial customers.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then copies of any waste be in violation letters or notices received by the permitted hauler during the prior year that refer to loads collected within the city of Medford.
[SPEAKER_04]: So we would add that requirement onto our permitting process.
[SPEAKER_04]: and also failure to provide a complete and accurate annual solid waste and recycles reporting form may be grounds for denial of a permit to operate within the city of Medford.
[SPEAKER_04]: So those basically will be added to our regulation.
[SPEAKER_03]: I believe everything else matches
[SPEAKER_03]: As far as, as far as fees, operational procedures, violations.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that's all, that's majority, it was really regulation five.
[SPEAKER_04]: Regulation six, Dempster,
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a little easier.
[SPEAKER_04]: The dumpster permit itself will be less cumbersome as far as the changes go.
[SPEAKER_04]: On regulation six, it's again really adding just the title of recyclables and the definition, adding the definition of recyclables to regulation six, which is the dumpster regulation.
[SPEAKER_04]: And also changing that solid waste definition as well, because that same definition is in Regulation 6 as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: So we'll be amending that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then again, adding not just to the definitions, but also under 6.4 general, adding
[SPEAKER_03]: the collection and transportation of solid waste and our recyclables.
[SPEAKER_03]: Anybody else see anywhere else where they think
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, the only other thing while we're here on this too, with regulations, thanks to the dumpster regulation, is in light of the, we need to update this anyways, with the rodent ordinance requirements for integrated pest management plans to be submitted with dumpster applications.
[SPEAKER_04]: so that we know that they're being looked at and taken care of well and helping us.
[SPEAKER_04]: control of our rodent problems here in Medford.
[SPEAKER_04]: So I would want to at this time, since we're revising anyways, to go ahead and add the rodent ordinance language to the dumpster regulation, including that requirement for IPM and integrated pest management plan from their licensed pest management company submitted when they get their dumpster permit.
[SPEAKER_02]: along with the field.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we'll update that while we're doing this, if that makes sense.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, so I guess the best way to do this is just to make sure we have approval on that data writing that you're all in agreement with what we just covered.
[SPEAKER_04]: Does anybody have any comments?
[SPEAKER_04]: Want to make any other suggestions or changes?
[SPEAKER_04]: Do we just want to vote to accept the changes as proposed for Regulation 5 and Regulation 6?
[SPEAKER_05]: I have a quick question.
[SPEAKER_05]: With the biotech laboratory boom going on, how does that waste, medical waste, is that going to flow into this or is that separate?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so we include medical waste if they're
[SPEAKER_04]: disposing or picking up or hauling away medical waste that's included within this regulation.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, good, good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mary Ann, do we need to, should the integrated pest management plan also be included in the, is it regulation five or is it just needed for the dumpster?
[SPEAKER_04]: At this point, it's just for the dumpster.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Regulation 5, I don't... I know Regulation 5 touches on the permit for the dumpster.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, let's see.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you... You're right.
[SPEAKER_01]: I thought I saw it in there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe it would go under 5.9 dumpster management.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if it's captured under regulation six, which is really all about dumpster regulations, getting the permits that are necessary, then I think we should be covered.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, certainly doesn't hurt to have it in two places.
[SPEAKER_04]: So you're right on the 5.9 is dumpster management.
[SPEAKER_04]: We certainly could put it in there.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, I think it certainly could be put in there as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: Permanent dumpsters.
[SPEAKER_04]: permit both permanent dumpsters and temporary dumpsters.
[SPEAKER_04]: But we're not requiring IPMs for temporary dumpsters.
[SPEAKER_04]: So we can pull out the fact on the dumpster management that permanent dumpsters requirement of the IPM.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's a great catch.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Jenny.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, I'm good with the changes you've proposed.
[SPEAKER_04]: All right, can we take a, can I have a motion to approve changes as proposed?
[SPEAKER_04]: to Regulation 5 and Regulation 6?
[SPEAKER_05]: Motion to approve.
[SPEAKER_05]: Motion as proposed, 5 and 6.
[SPEAKER_05]: Plattowitz says yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you, Dr. Plattowitz.
[SPEAKER_04]: Do I have a second?
[SPEAKER_04]: Second, Kathy says yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you, Kathy.
[SPEAKER_04]: OK, all in favor.
[SPEAKER_04]: Jenny?
[SPEAKER_01]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_01]: Aye, yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Kathy Chabonet?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: And Dr. David Plattowitz?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, and what's in the boxes behind you?
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, COVID tests.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_04]: We have plenty of COVID tests left.
[SPEAKER_04]: If anybody's in need of a COVID test, please feel free.
[SPEAKER_04]: I have, this is just one wall.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hopefully we won't have to use them anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, but people are paying for them now.
[SPEAKER_04]: So we do, we're giving them away free.
[SPEAKER_04]: So if anyone's in need, certainly feel free.
[SPEAKER_04]: I know.
[SPEAKER_04]: So I'm, I'm using my new camera and microphone for the first time.
[SPEAKER_04]: And now I realized I must actually clean my office.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, you're busy.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's a good sign.
[SPEAKER_05]: It was clean enough.
[SPEAKER_05]: It was on your desk.
[SPEAKER_05]: We'd be worried.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't think, um, I have any other business, but so I guess what we'll try to do is get these all together.
[SPEAKER_04]: Um,
[SPEAKER_04]: I know Millie will be helping me do that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then we'll provide you with the updated regulations for our final vote adoption in September, once we go through them and make sure that everybody's feels that they're complete.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I can also share a copy with Councilor Collins.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that way, if we have any changes, we can deal with those in September as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you, Councilor Collins.
[SPEAKER_04]: All right.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't think I have any other business.
[SPEAKER_04]: So we will not be meeting in August.
[SPEAKER_04]: We're going to be taking the month of August off.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so our next meeting will be on September 19th.
[SPEAKER_04]: Amazing.
[SPEAKER_04]: Do I have a motion to adjourn?
[SPEAKER_05]: Motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you, Dr. Plattowitz.
[SPEAKER_04]: Second?
[SPEAKER_04]: Second, Kathy Chavadio.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you, Kathy.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, all in favor, Jenny Vital?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Kathy Chabudier?
[SPEAKER_04]: And Dr. Platt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_04]: All right, enjoy August and see you in September.
[SPEAKER_01]: Enjoy the rest of the summer.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Take care.