[SPEAKER_01]: Rowdy, it's a field of eight, but really it's a tail of two.
[SPEAKER_01]: McIntosh and Ledecky.
[SPEAKER_02]: More than a race, Jason.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is a generational showdown against the greatest female swimmer in history.
[SPEAKER_03]: On the right, and this teenage phenom on the left.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're going to see this signature tempo of Ledecky going out.
[SPEAKER_03]: Will she push Summer McIntosh to a limit that she's just not used to?
[SPEAKER_03]: But McIntosh has shown so much poise.
[SPEAKER_03]: here in Singapore.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you don't, like you said, you talked about Pallister underneath Ledecky.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is a great field.
[SPEAKER_03]: Might be the best 800 field in history.
[SPEAKER_03]: Five of the eight fastest swimmers ever in this race, including Pallister, who's the third fastest behind Ledecky and McIntosh.
[SPEAKER_01]: So they are off and moving here in the 800 free.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Ledecky,
[SPEAKER_01]: In lane one, McIntosh just above her in lane three, Pallister below her in lane five.
[SPEAKER_01]: The American champion and the Canadian challenger.
[SPEAKER_01]: For more on Summer McIntosh, let's go to Nicole Auerbach.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well guys, we've talked all week about summer trying to win these five gold medals here in Singapore, but this is the new addition to the program and the biggest challenge.
[SPEAKER_00]: The one we've been most excited for her coach.
[SPEAKER_00]: Frederick knew told me that this she thinks he thinks she can be the one to end Katie's reign in this event and stop her from winning a 7th world title in the 800 free now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Summer wasn't as explicit, but she had told me that she has prioritized the 800 in her training above everything else, which is kind of scary to think about when you consider how well she's performed at all of these other events, Rowdy.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and you're so right, Nicole.
[SPEAKER_03]: She's got these events, but she's been fearless.
[SPEAKER_03]: And she's got this incredible aerobic base she has built over the last six months.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then you've got the experience
[SPEAKER_03]: of Katie Ledecky and knowing what she's done this year.
[SPEAKER_03]: She just broke the world record a couple of months ago.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you know, it's just so many great things coming together in this race.
[SPEAKER_03]: I really believe unless something really wacky happens with Katie, I think this whole way is going to be just like what you're seeing here with Katie and Summer starting to extend that lead a little bit on Pallister.
[SPEAKER_01]: As Nicole talked about, Summer McIntosh adding the 800 to her program this year.
[SPEAKER_01]: Remember, Rowdy, she swam it at the Tokyo Olympics as a 14-year-old finished 11th, but it wasn't a priority in recent years.
[SPEAKER_01]: But she talked about, it's not definitely my favorite event, but I'm good at it, so maybe I'll grow to like it again, and certainly,
[SPEAKER_01]: the ability to come to these worlds and maybe potentially become the first woman to win five solo individual golds at one worlds to match Michael Phelps was an opportunity for her to add it to her resume and man she's excels.
[SPEAKER_03]: She is pushing the pace.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whatever happens she's going to make Summer McIntosh earn this first 400.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't mean that Katie's not going to hurt.
[SPEAKER_03]: But trust me, she's going to go, I'm going to make you feel this first 400.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're both, well, Ledecky's under three minutes at the 300.
[SPEAKER_03]: He's about a half second ahead of that world record pace.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pallister kind of hanging in there as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: I can't imagine Pallister being able to
[SPEAKER_03]: keep pace on this just wicked.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, this pace is just wicked, Jason.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, and Summer can't let her go.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, she's got to say, you know, I can't let her get a body link from me.
[SPEAKER_03]: I got to hang in there with her and then just hope and pray that aerobic pace I built will get me through this next 400.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, Summer McIntosh got out of the water after having what you could term a casual 800 free in the prelims.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ledecky was not in her heat.
[SPEAKER_01]: And she came out of the water, Rowdy, and was asked about her race and said it was kind of boring.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing boring about what's going on right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And she's tracking with the six-time world champion, Pallister of Australia, right there as well, just past the halfway point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Boy, you know.
[SPEAKER_03]: Boy, that was fast pace, Jason.
[SPEAKER_03]: Her world record pace, 4.017.
[SPEAKER_03]: She's about 6 tenths ahead of that.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's eerie how similar their splits are when it comes to the two best times ever.
[SPEAKER_03]: McIntosh was 4.011 when she went 8.05.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right there, she was 4.013.
[SPEAKER_03]: The next two, 200, they're exactly the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just eerie.
[SPEAKER_03]: The only thing I... I'm just trying to look at these 50 splits.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know... I know I get calls about, quit talking about the clock, but the splits tell you so much.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ledecky out to Glitter, that previous 50, but that 50 was about a tenth faster for Summer McIntyre.
[SPEAKER_03]: So now 14 one hundredths of a second.
[SPEAKER_03]: Separates him and look at Pallister!
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, who asked her to join this party?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it looked like a table for two, and now you might have to bring an extra chair and make this a setting for three, because Pallister is hanging right there, at least for now.
[SPEAKER_01]: This trio looking spectacular here in this 800 free final.
[SPEAKER_03]: I like Summer McIntosh, the way she's looking right now, though, Jason.
[SPEAKER_03]: She still looks smooth.
[SPEAKER_03]: She's not fighting that water at all.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is watching an experienced,
[SPEAKER_03]: Legacy-making swim by Katie Ledecky, colliding with this wall-rising brilliance from Summer McIntosh, and for that matter, Pallister.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I just can't imagine Pallister hanging in there these last 200 meters.
[SPEAKER_03]: It is really a great race for Lani Pallister right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Ledecky has never lost this race at the World Championships.
[SPEAKER_01]: This woman, six times, won all six.
[SPEAKER_01]: She hadn't lost in 800 at all in well over a decade, and at a lower level meet last year in Orlando, McIntosh was able to best Ledecky in this race, but both
[SPEAKER_01]: at various points of their training, getting ready for the Olympics last summer in Paris.
[SPEAKER_01]: But here at the biggest meet of the year, it's those two going head to head with Pallister sticking in the mix as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: I like McIntosh.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know why.
[SPEAKER_03]: I just get the feeling she hasn't shown everything yet.
[SPEAKER_03]: She's so good coming home.
[SPEAKER_03]: We saw her almost break the world record in the 200 butterfly and 100 meters left to go.
[SPEAKER_03]: Stroke for stroke, this race does not disappoint in any way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the head-to-head showdown becoming a three-headed monster, at least for a while.
[SPEAKER_01]: But Ledecky and McIntosh maybe trying to get some separation against Lonnie Pollister, who is not out of it yet.
[SPEAKER_01]: The American ahead of the Canadian as they head for home here in the 800 free final.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ledecky out-splitter there by four-tenths of a second.
[SPEAKER_03]: And now she's increasing that pitfall.
[SPEAKER_03]: And look at Ledecky go.
[SPEAKER_01]: Look at Ledecky go.
[SPEAKER_01]: The champion and the challengers.
[SPEAKER_01]: McIntosh is fading.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pallister is surging.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ledecky trying to hold on to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Katie Ledecky racing her way into history with another 800 free title.
[SPEAKER_01]: A seven time champion of this event.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first ever in world championship history.
[SPEAKER_01]: Long live the queen of the 800 frame.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you have anticipation of what you hope something can be.
[SPEAKER_01]: That feels like it delivered more than we could have even expected.
[SPEAKER_03]: And just like that, the legend grows, man.
[SPEAKER_03]: She turned back that challenge.
[SPEAKER_03]: And she reminded, I hope she reminds every single person on the planet that knows anything about swimming,
[SPEAKER_03]: that she is the gold standard.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is the greatest... Think about that, Jason.
[SPEAKER_03]: The greatest female swimmer in the history of the sport.
[SPEAKER_03]: And we go back to 1896.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean... It's... I mean, I can't begin to tell you how many people... There's her coach, Anthony Nesting.
[SPEAKER_03]: I can't believe, my phone blew up the last 24 hours.
[SPEAKER_03]: McIntosh is taking her, McIntosh is taking her.
[SPEAKER_03]: Didn't quite have it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I thought she looked great going into the 700.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh boy, she fell off that last 100.
[SPEAKER_03]: And she is not happy.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh boy.
[SPEAKER_03]: Side by side.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ledecky on the right.
[SPEAKER_03]: And this is where I thought that, you know, Summer out split Katie on that 50 right there, Jason, by about 4 tenths.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I thought, wow, she's just building to this 100.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's what made me believe it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But boy, why do I question the heart of a champion?
[SPEAKER_03]: Why do I do that?
[SPEAKER_03]: I am just some big idiot.
[SPEAKER_03]: And watch this final turn there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Look at the way she comes off.
[SPEAKER_03]: Look at that dolphin kick.
[SPEAKER_03]: Four dolphin kicks coming off that wall.
[SPEAKER_03]: And give Ronnie Pallister a lot of credit.
[SPEAKER_03]: She goes her best time by three seconds and beats McIntosh.
[SPEAKER_03]: And look at Team USA.
[SPEAKER_03]: They've been ridden hard this week.
[SPEAKER_03]: A lot of comments happening.
[SPEAKER_01]: Katie, baby, Katie.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for someone that has that quiet confidence and doesn't often show a ton of emotion post-race, that is a raucous celebration for Ledecky, Anthony Neste, and the rest of the coaching staff.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mom and dad!
[SPEAKER_03]: Mary Jen!
[SPEAKER_01]: Summer McIntosh.
[SPEAKER_03]: She's not done, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Already three goals for her here but Ledecky gets another her 30th world medal all time second only to Michael Phelps.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a twenty third world title only Phelps is more of those with twenty six.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's an 18th individual world title in swimming.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody has more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ledecky with a championship record.
[SPEAKER_01]: Palliser with an oceanic record, taking silver.
[SPEAKER_01]: McIntosh with bronze.