[SPEAKER_00]: Hi, I'm Justin Tseng, and I'm proud to serve as your city councilor in the city I've always called home.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm the son of immigrants who came to Medford chasing the American dream.
[SPEAKER_00]: My parents stretched every dollar and raised me paycheck to paycheck, but it was our public schools, our neighbors, and this community that gave us everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: For the past four years, I've worked to give back and to pay it forward.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now as national politicians gamble with our economy and threaten our neighbors,
[SPEAKER_00]: Medford needs steady hands and bold leadership.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll always stand up for you because Medford stood up for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And over the past four years, we haven't just made progress, we've made history.
[SPEAKER_00]: While some leaders are busy banning books and turning neighbors against each other, we're building a city that welcomes everyone and works for all of us.
[SPEAKER_00]: We've made record investments in our schools and passed laws to protect our neighbors and our freedoms.
[SPEAKER_00]: While politicians in Washington and on Beacon Hill continue to cater to big money interests and leave us priced out and left behind, we're passing once-in-a-lifetime reforms to make housing more affordable, spur local business growth, and lead the fight against climate change right here at home.
[SPEAKER_00]: Life is rocky enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Our job is to smooth the path.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're fixing roads and sidewalks that haven't been touched in decades.
[SPEAKER_00]: We brought back bus routes that families rely on because getting to work, school, or the doctor shouldn't depend on owning a car.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we're making City Hall more transparent and accessible so residents have a seat at the table.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when national leaders fail us, Medford steps up.
[SPEAKER_00]: We prove that by leading with heart, with vision, and with the courage to do what's right, we can achieve results for all of us.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the job's not done yet.
[SPEAKER_00]: More than ever, we need leaders who know this community, and who show up and listen day in and day out.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I'm running for re-election.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's keep building a Medford that works for you, me, and our neighbors down the street.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's keep moving Medford forward together.