I am Julie Morrow and I teach cosmetology.
Some of the highlights of our shop is being able to work on people.
Having actually live clients come into the shop and being able to do nails here and skin services for them.
I'm Danelle and I'm a junior in cosmetology.
I was interested in nail art and hair color.
and do nail art with the correction tools.
The teachers are very nice.
I just really like doing hair and making people feel good about themselves.
After high school, I plan on doing cosmetology and getting my license.
I joined this shop because I knew I wanted to open a salon.
My favorite project we've done has to be the Halloween too, but I love that we get to work on each other.
My plan after high school is to pursue aesthetics, like facials, makeup, stuff like that.
Some of the opportunities are being a hair stylist.
You could actually be a makeup artist.
You could go on to work in the field of making the products or selling the products.
Also, there's extension schools where you could go to learn how to do hair extensions.
And also, there's additional schooling for advanced aesthetics and barbering.