[SPEAKER_01]: So the next speaker we have is going to be Susan Eldridge.
[SPEAKER_01]: Susan is a lifelong resident of Somerville, almost lifelong.
[SPEAKER_01]: She's a member of Our Evolution Somerville, a great grassroots organization that helps elect a lot of people to the current Somerville City Council.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through their work in both elections and policy, Somerville recently passed the strongest living wage ordinance in the country.
[SPEAKER_01]: It also passed a great housing policy, like a transfer fee, like condom conversion ordinance, and the Somerville Community Land Trust.
[SPEAKER_01]: Susan is actively engaged in the Tufts PILOT program, which is, PILOT is for payment in lieu of taxes, basically trying to get Tufts to just pay their fair share to both Somerville and Medford.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, without any further ado, Susan.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anna, she's just fantastic.
[SPEAKER_00]: Working with her on the Our Revolution group in Somerville.
[SPEAKER_00]: And she's just so committed, and like someone said, she's kind, and she's always willing to help.
[SPEAKER_00]: She's so patient, and I've just really enjoyed working with her a lot.
[SPEAKER_00]: I look forward to working with her in the future and getting her elected as a state rep because I know she's going to represent all the things that we care about, affordable housing, Medicaid for all, Greenland and Yale, so all those different levels that we definitely need.