The phone, the phone is ringing The phone will be right there The phone, the phone is ringing The phone, the phone is ringing
The report is here.
Hi, I'm Lydia Ryan with Mustang News Channel 15 and we're here at the game opener for Medford Mustangs varsity football team and I'm here with my co-host Nick Kenniston. Nick, how are they looking tonight? Well, the Mustang team looks pretty good. The offense has been working hard all through the summer. I actually went to a couple of the practices and they learned a lot of new different stuff and it looks pretty good.
How do you think the offense will do tonight, although they didn't do that great in their last game? Well, you know, I think it's all about execution. You know, they worked on techniques all throughout practice this week, and I think that, you know, you can scheme all you want, but it's basically just about execution. Hi, I'm Lydia Ryan, and I'm here with Christian Gotti. Christian, how are you feeling tonight? Pretty good, Lydia. Alright. Why'd you come out tonight to the football game? To support the team and watch the game. Is there anyone in particular you're supporting tonight?
Well, I think Aaron Sealy's going to have a big game tonight. Oh, he is. I bet he is. So did you hear about Corey's injury? How do you feel about that? Well, he's a really good player, so it might affect the team. You think it will hurt the team? It could. How do you think Belmont's going to do tonight? Well, I haven't heard very good things about them, so. You don't know? I don't know. Let's hope for the best, though. Yep. All right. Thank you, Christian. Thanks. And here they come. Wow, looking marvelous, right through the banner.
Aaron Seeley, captain. And Myles Oliver, wide receiver. There's a kickoff and we are underway. Taken by number three, Aaron Seeley. And he's running, he's running. Oh, he's going, he's going! Oh, he's going, he's going! He's going for the touchdown! Touchdown!
Ben Antoine under center, takes a snap, read option left, double pass and it's dropped. Incomplete, but tackled by number 31. We still have the ball. Oh, and he's running, number three, Aaron Seely, right through, oh he sprints to the middle, oh a fake, oh and he's down.
Because I have an idea for a video. Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State! Go State
Wow, catch made by Miles Oliver. Wow, and another one for Medford which puts us in the lead 14 to 9 in the third. Coach Nascimento is the head coach and he's one of the best coaches here.
Antoine back in the shotgun. Goes back to pass. Can't seem to find her. Person runs right through and gets to the about 25th yard line. I'm Cheyenne and I'm here with the Mustang Report and we are still here at the football game and I am here with... Andre, Pia Paul, Cotton's mom. So how do you think he's doing so far? Oh great, I believe it's a great game and I'm looking forward for the game to end and we wish that we won this game.
So right now we're 14 to 9. Do you think we're going to keep this lead? Oh, we should. We should go more than 14. I think we should go like 29. I agree. That's a good number. All right. Thank you.
Hi, I'm Lydia Ryan and we're here at halftime at the opener MHS varsity football game with MHS leading 14 to 9. I'm here with Hallie Farrell and Lacey Ryan and Hallie is going to tell us the joke of the game. Hallie, to you.
Well, since it's a football game, I thought I'd tell a football joke. So, why did the football coach go to the bank? Why? To get his quarterback. Oh, my God. What a great football joke. That is truly inspirational. That was great. And, Lacey, how do you feel about that joke? Does that make you laugh? Yeah.
Hi, I'm Hallie and I'm here with Aidan and Dominic. What grade are you guys in? Sixth. Sixth grade. What school do you guys go to? Andrews. Andrews Middle School. Is this your first football game? No. Yeah, for high school. Are you guys excited? Yeah. Do you think Medford will win? Yeah. I hope so. I think they will too.
Are you guys going to come to any other games this season? Probably. Oh, you will? Well, thank you. I'm Hallie Powell. Back in the shotgun where he's been all night. With the ball running right through, makes a quick break to the right, running straight on the line. Six Belmont guys on him. Oh, my God. And tackle down at the 8 yard line. Ball.
We are still running it through. Oh, toss to number 31 on the outside. Oh, he dives into the end zone for a touchdown for Medford. Hi, I'm Gabby Martinez here for MHS TV. And right now, I'm with... Scott Andrew. Brandon Shaloney. And Paul D'Orio. So guys, how do you think the band's doing right now? Well, as you know, the band's job is to get the crowd hyped up for the game. And as you can see, we're pretty hyped up.
I gotta agree, I think they're improving more and more every day. I think they're like the Drake and the Future album that's being released at midnight. Yeah, I think the band's doing great. They got great rhythm. They're number one in the state and number one in all our hearts. Oh yeah. Okay, thank you guys. Back to you.
Doing really good this game, hopefully they'll pull out a win. Number 8, throw to number 9.
Well, she breaks a tackle. Oh, he breaks. Oh, he pushes through. He pushes through. And a touchdown by Medford! Score of the game was 31-28 Belmont. Nick, how did you feel about this game? Well, it was pretty spectacular up until the end. You know, both teams fought pretty hard and continued to play very well. They definitely improved from last game. And it was an intense and specular game from last time. And it was so close all around. But good job, Medford. Good job.
I don't hear you, Jimmy.
6, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30
What?
I just wanna celebrate I just wanna celebrate I just wanna celebrate I just wanna celebrate
Yeah, don't break it.
4 goals?