[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you for teaching me letter sound.
[SPEAKER_05]: So she helps us a lot when we need help for our homework.
[SPEAKER_05]: So my second grade teacher is the best because she let us eat outside.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you for helping me and thank you for helping me do work but not exactly tell me what to do.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'd have to give a huge thanks to Coach Rowan.
[SPEAKER_05]: He's helped me stay active this whole year and just made gym more fun.
[SPEAKER_05]: I want to say thank you to my fifth grade teacher for being funny and a good teacher and being British at it.
[SPEAKER_05]: My ELA teacher makes me laugh.
[SPEAKER_05]: My math teacher helps me feel challenged.
[SPEAKER_05]: I feel really close to my ELA teacher.
[SPEAKER_04]: All of my 6th grade teachers are very kind and caring and make my day better.
[SPEAKER_05]: My ELA teacher, my science teacher helped me feel welcome.
[SPEAKER_05]: My ELA teacher takes stress out of class.
[SPEAKER_05]: All the 6th grade teachers make the day fun and stress free.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm grateful for my ELA teacher because she always finds a way to make the students laugh.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm grateful for my wellness teacher because she's the GOAT.
[SPEAKER_04]: My science teacher always has a good attitude towards our class and is good at explaining things.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm thankful for my math teacher because she always has a good attitude and she makes math fun.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm grateful for my teachers.
[SPEAKER_04]: What I appreciate about my teachers is that they really care about us and want us to succeed.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm thankful for my teachers for helping me through the days, even though I have bad days, they're always there to uplift me.
[SPEAKER_03]: and look out for me.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if you need to talk to somebody, they're always there to talk to you.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're always open to listen to anything.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're always there to help you out.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you're struggling in class or whatever, they're always there to help you.
[SPEAKER_03]: They'll tell you what you need to do right or wrong, like what you're doing right or wrong.
[SPEAKER_03]: and yeah, just always ask them.
[SPEAKER_03]: I really appreciate my teachers.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm super thankful for my chemistry teacher for helping me and all of the students in her class to understand the assignment in a way that we could all understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just want to say thank you to all my teachers who helped me out when I'm struggling on tests and quizzes and just figuring out everything and all the hard work they do for us.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would just like to say thank you because like whenever I'm struggling they're always there like after school and they're flexible as always.
[SPEAKER_01]: Their schedules are always really flexible and everything, so I'd just like to say thank you for helping me out in that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: I just want to say thank you to all the teachers here at Medford High for showing support to their students and making sure they understand the material and they're really looking out for them in the classrooms and that they have a safe and real community.