Council to the thirty-fifth regular meeting of the Memphis City Council, November 9th, 2021. Will the city clerk please call the roll? Okay, Councilor Bears. Present. Councilor Falcone. Present. Vice President Knight. Present. Councilor Huff. Present. Councilor Morrell. Present. Councilor Scapelli. Here.
seven. Yes. So present zero. I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America and to the Republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all.
Motion to order is a resolution to 1610 water by President Gabrielle, the result of it that city council come in to congratulate you, Frank Hilbert you for 23 years of 23 years as chief and 39 years in the play department when it's upcoming your time.
Thank you, Mr. President, as you all know, Chief Gilbert, he will be retiring at the end of the month there. And I just wanted to recognize him for his 26 years of being being the chief of the city of Baffin and 39 years with our fire department. And I also like to recognize that the mayor was appointed john Freeman, excuse me, john
is our new chief and I want to welcome him as the new chief but I just want to talk about the chief for a few minutes. Again, he's been a dedicated employee for almost 40 years. He's overseen by department that said, you know, we've had building concerns everything and they'll do some difficult times here and
want to commend him for his work that he's done over the years and I think he's done his best to try to keep the buildings up as the best he could with the, with the budget that he had so I just wanted to commend him for that. And I'd like to maybe have him come here maybe next week to receive a citation from our city council chair recognizes Councilmarks.
Thank you, Mr. President. I want to thank President Caviello for putting this on the agenda. We all know this day was coming, Mr. President.
uh, Chief Gil Birdy served as chief for, as was mentioned, 26 years. Um, he led the fire department through some good and bad times. Mr President, my only hope was that we could be talking about a brand new fire headquarters and revitalized fire stations throughout the community. Unfortunately,
That is not the case, Mr. President. So I'd like to thank Chief Gilberti for his many years of dedicated service to the residents of this community and the property of this community, and congratulate Deputy Chief John Friedman, Mr. President, who, in my opinion, will do a tremendous job in that role. He is well-liked by his colleagues, Mr. President,
He is someone that really fights for his fellow firefighters. And I know he's interested, like the rest of us, about moving forward with getting a new headquarters, revamping our stations, and also, Mr. President, getting the training tower, which was promised to our firefighters back several years ago. So thank you, Mr. President.
Chair recognizes Councilor Fevella. Thank you, Mr. President. I thank President Carriello for bringing this forward tonight. I also want to thank Chief Gilberti for his many years of service and commitment to our community. Wish him well in his retirement and also congratulate Deputy Chief Freeman on his new position, his new role and wish him well. Thank you. Chair recognizes Councilor Scarpelli.
Thank you, Mr. President. Thank you, Mr. President, bring this forward. Chief has been a rock here in the community for so many years and now I can publicly say my dream is to, when I grow up, is to be like Chief Gilberti, hoping to get hair plugs, lose some weight and go to the tanning beds and
And we could say this publicly now, can we please get the new chief Friedman. I know, I know, Chief Gilbert he had his, his, his city vehicle, which had the right the side to look really close. It's a fire chief.
So I wanna get a nice big sign so everybody knows who our fire chief is. No, but seriously, we appreciate all the hard work he's done. I know it's not easy. You can't make everybody happy 100% of the time. And I think chief had that balance to make sure that his department worked for the best interests of our community. And we appreciate that. So thank you.
Chair recognizes Council Member Morrell. Thank you, Vice President. I just want to echo my colleagues. I obviously didn't have the pleasure to work alongside the chief as long as everyone else did, but I thank him for his decades of service to the city, the residents, his firefighters. I think in the short time I have had,
been able to work with him and whether it's meetings here or events, he's always welcoming kind and available and that's really just an asset to everyone in the city. And I also echo my council colleagues in congratulating Deputy Chief Friedman on his elevation. Thank you, Mr. President. Similar to Councilor Morrell I think
you know, working with Chief Gilberti these past two years, he's been incredibly open, communicative, trying to let us know the needs of the department within the constraints that, you know, any department head is under. But I think even more than that, the chief has been the chief more than 80% of my life. And he's still here. And I'm still here. He's still here. And, you know, I'll always remember, we had a
weird electrical fire in one of our walls. And I always remember the fire department coming down this quick, you know, very promptly getting an address, saving our home from what I'm sure would have been a disaster. And I, you know, can't say enough about everything that our fire department does to keep our community safe. So I think that's a testament to the chief and to deputy chief Friedman. And I look forward to working with deputy chief Friedman when he becomes a chief. Thank you.
If I may, from the chair, Chief Gilberti has become someone I've grown to admire. I've always been
very impressed with the way that he's handled the budget. And I think that in his retirement he should hold classes for the current department heads on how to answer questions at a budget session. Chief Gilberti I think has the most direct responses out of any of our department heads here in the community. Three words or less usually most of his answers are yes, no, maybe, I don't know. He's been great. He's been great to work with. And he's going to be sorely missed. He brings a lot of institutional knowledge to the table.
His expertise in financing and firefighting is something that's unparalleled. And I do wish him the best of luck in his retirement here in Massachusetts and down in sunny Florida. And I also know with great faith that the city of Medford's in good hands with John Friedman behind the helm. So with that being said, on the motion of Councilor Caviello, seconded by. Second. As amended by Councilor Caviello. All those in favor. Aye. Opposed.
The eyes have it. Show it's a motion. Motion by council this take papers in the hands of the clerk. Second, because the cover yellow. All those in favor. I opposed. I just have it under suspension in Council November 9 2021 Council paper 21615 on set by offered by counselor.
Caravello, be it resolved the Memphis City Council receive an answer regarding the paving of South Street and Prescott Street Council Carville. Thank you, Mr. President, Mr President done. As you know, we've been struggling with this ever source project for going on four or five years now.
And with the paving so I think many of us have been. I think we, we went a little bit dodging the manhole covers all over Mr gab we got that paved. Now, we're still dodging manhole covers on South Street. The neighbors have received a letter that this street was supposed to have been paid a month ago. As of today there's still no paving.
I think, as we all know, as the weather gets colder, the asphalt plants will be closing down soon. So are we going to wait until the asphalt plant closes down and we buy asphalt of serious standard, just the kind they use to do patchwork, or is this going to get done in a reasonable amount of time?
Again, we have one of the neighbors here that lives on South Street, and they say, these neighbors have been promised this for going on a while now. They say they were a month overdue. Would you like to? No. OK. Well, I'll say, again, we'd like to get an update in when this pavement is going to get done on South Street. Never mind. And if you go to Prescott Street, they've dug up streets over there with trenches, and they didn't even patch them.
They filled them in with dirt. Again, we're gonna wait till the plane closes, and we're gonna be using the winter mix that lasts about a month, and then it's gone again. I mean, there's not even anybody down there working anymore on Prescott Street. In fact, I had a call to the engineer last week, because during all that rain, there was a hole that you can drive your car fell into.
So again, these are projects that, this Eversource project is never gonna end, ever. I mean, it's just going, and you say, now that, I mean, they're still digging in front of the police station now every night, and you're seeing plates and plates, and now we're getting the complaints from the neighbors as the plates have moved down on that end now. I say, I would think at some point, we need to get Eversource in here,
and figure out where they're going. I mean, they're going a couple of feet a day. This project isn't going anywhere. We're probably another two years away from this project getting done. So I would make a motion that we have a community of the whole meeting with the Eversource officials, whether it be, I think it's Robin Collins, she's the project manager.
to get somebody in here at the committee hall to discuss where the project is going and have the engineer reach out to the people doing the work on Prescott Street by the school. Get your hand out of his back, Zach.
Sounded better the second time. So I'll make that motion, Mr. President. What's the corporation? Is that McCabe that's down there on Prescott? I don't know who's doing Prescott Street, but I haven't seen them down there in a bit. I think it is McCabe. I'm not sure. But again, they've dug trenches there, and all they do is fill them in with gravel. And they're coming up now.
Chair recognizes Council Members. Thank you, Mr. President. I want to thank President Caviello for putting this on the agenda. You know, when we talk about Eversource, I think no one can refute that Winthrop Street was heavily impacted by all the construction over the last several years. And another street that comes to mind is Salt Street.
South Street has really borne the brunt of not only ever source but other projects, Mr President, over the last several years, and they.
deserve some peace and quiet on that street. So the quicker they can pave that area and give these residents a break, I'm all in support of that, Mr. President. So I would hope the administration gets a wind of this and immediately acts, Mr. President, before, as President Caviello mentioned, before the weather gets too inclement for any type of road pavements. Thank you, Mr. President. Councilor Scarpelli. Thank you, Mr. President.
Again, who have we invited? I miss that, Mr. President. For the Committee of the Whole meeting, we want, what departments are we asking, requesting again? I would say we'd have the project manager from Episodes come down along with our city engineer and DPW. And maybe our city solicitor to find out what our legal ramifications are. As I say, this project's gonna be going on for another two more years at the pace they're going, if not longer.
Stop it.
There you go. Probably in the chimney.
Okay, if we can't to go back to that I think that it's important I'm going to hop on this until we find some sort of resolution I think it's important that we have a clerk of the works. That's really reporting back to the city when we talk about these, these huge, huge inconvenience
wrote the roadwork that's going on again. If we have someone there on site every day something's going to get done something's going to be reported to the right people because there's definitely a disconnect, and I think that who's paying the price up and down Winthrop Street not the South Street and no council mark said it but
You know this, it's no different than the rattling of the plates, you know, it's, I've talked to a few neighbors in Winchester, and I said geez I said do you have the same concerns with the rattle and plates, and they say no that was one of the first initiatives I talked to them about making sure that every time they drop those plates. It was an enough of a buffer to make sure that didn't happen.
But you travel and traverse right over the line. And it seems like the slap in the face keeps coming back with these huge companies like Eversource and National Grid. So I appreciate the welcome. I think we need every department there that's possible. And we need to make sure that we have a watchdog moving forward that's representing the city to make sure that
Everything that that person will say from Eversource is held accountable, because if you remember the first meeting we had at Eversource, remember everyone? The gentleman came up and he had a plan, and this is great, they're gonna put door signs, and everybody, this is my cell phone number, people call me, remember how great that was? I have yet to hear from that, that man disappeared. It was a figment of our imagination, because there has been no communication, no support from Eversource. And again,
We know we had no power control to allow them in. We heard that a thousand times, but we also heard that we would get the support and the people would have, somebody would hear a voice that when something needed to be done. And I'm just so disappointed. I'll say this to the end. This is what we hear every day, roads, sidewalks, and a lot has to do with our,
our partnerships with Eversource and National Grid. So I'm pretty disgusted. I appreciate Council President bringing this forward. Thank you. Chair recognizes Councilor Peco. Thank you, Mr. President. I also want to thank Council President Capriolo for bringing this resolution forward. I know I've been on the Council for six years and pretty much this started six years ago and it still drags on today.
And this needs to be addressed, this is absolutely these are quality of life issues that need to be addressed in every single day the residents are residents throughout the community are impacted, but especially the residents that live. In and along that route of where the constructions taking place, I mean, if you take a look at the construction in surrounding communities it's been definitely been managed differently than it's been managed here.
And I definitely would agree with President Cabrillo. There needs to be a meeting, Committee of the Whole meeting sooner than later on this. And I would ask that when the meeting is held or when it's scheduled, if we could send a robo-call to everyone that lives on this route. The residents need to be involved in this and the questions should be addressed. I think everyone wants to know when is this finally going to be finished?
The other source project is gonna last my tenure on the council. I mean, really, it's ridiculous. It's been going on for six years now. That's just unacceptable. It needs to be addressed. It needs to be managed. I don't think it's being managed properly. And I would ask that all of the residents along the route be notified of this meeting so they can have their questions answered. And if we could schedule this as soon as possible, I greatly appreciate it. Thank you.
Chair, Mr. Councilor Baez. Thank you, Mr. President. And I'll be as quick as I can on this, but I just want to drive home the point. When we're talking about the plates, when we're talking about the paving schedule, we're talking about any of this. There were plates 300 yards up the street a year ago, and we said, can you make them not be so loud that people can't sleep at night? It's recurring. You know, we are going back. It's a recurring problem. I think Clerk of the Works is one potential answer here. And I'm totally supportive of that. But at this point,
when we're asking them to do something over and over again, they go and do it. And then the next time they go out to do something similar and they don't follow that instruction again, I just want to ask you in the form of an amendment, is there any sort of recourse we have with the department of public utilities, either for additional accountability on oversight from their end on projects like these are specifically on the ever source project. And is there any compensation that the city's entitled to considering the impact that this has had
and what I would call the negligence of the contractor working for this company. Because basically I think to Councilor Scarpelli's point, it doesn't feel like a very public to me, not so public utilities in my opinion. These companies are just running roughshod and they're not accountable to the public. So if there's some recourse either through additional accountability that the state can come down, I think it's an addition to whatever we can do as a city in the long run to get these projects working. And to be honest, I think
you know, I'm sure that we're not entitled to compensation, but I'd at least like to ask because I think we deserve it. Thank you. Yes. And, um, you know, if you look at like the big, big, for example, you know, they had performance standards, right? Where they said, if you don't meet these benchmarks, then you're going to pay us money. Um, I think it might be time for us to start looking at the contracts that we're offering and, uh, seeing if that's an option. They don't pay utility companies. We went through that with the state, with the fast 14 project, with the bridge, they will not pay. Right.
I won't give any. On the motion by Councilor Caviello, as amended by Councilor Caviello, Councilor Falco, Councilor Scarpelli, and Councilor Baez. All those in favor? Aye. Opposed? The ayes have it.
Council paper 21613 offered by Councilor Mox, be it resolved that a moment of silence be held to lifelong resident Robert Amari on his recent passing. Councilor Mox. Thank you, Mr. President. What a life Mr. Amari led. He was a lifelong Meffitt resident. He was a graduate of Meffitt High School. He was the captain of the varsity football team at Meffitt High School.
He was enlisted in the U.S. Army, achieving the rank of corporal, and was decorated for service in the Korean War.
Robert was a plumber by trade, and he also enjoyed a long career with the MBTA as a mechanics and maintenance supervisor. He was a devoted husband, father, grandfather, brother, and friend to many, Mr. President. He is survived by his wife, Frances, a sweetheart of a woman, his children, Joanne, Robert,
Lisa, and Johnny Amari. Everyone knows Johnny Amari as the mayor of South Method, and he truly is the mayor of South Method, if you know Johnny. But, you know, the Amaris are just a staple of this community, have been here for many decades, and they will be, Robert will be sorely missed, Mr. President.
I would ask that we dedicate this meeting in his honor, Robert Amari from Stearns Ave, Mr. President. Thank you. Oh, on the motion of Council Marks, seconded by Vice President Knight. All in favor. Please rise for a moment of silence.
21614 of my vice president, I'd be a strong result and let me see council and send the defense to say congratulations.
to Ralph and Loretta Evangelista on the momentous celebration of their 60th wedding anniversary. Vice President May. Mr. President, yes, thank you very much. Just this past week, Ralph and Loretta celebrated their 60th wedding anniversary. Many of us know Ralph and Loretta from being around the community, raising two lovely daughters, Lisa Evangelista and Julia Evangelista. Many of us know Lisa from her work in the mayor's office and from her work
up in the public schools. She's been dedicated to our community for close to 40 years. But that is nothing compared to the dedication that Ralph and Loretta have shown each other for the past 60, Mr. President. They're the cutest couple you'll ever see, two peas in a pod that you'll see go everywhere together. And it's great to see that they've been able to celebrate this momentous occasion. So with that being said, I'd ask my council colleagues to join me in congratulating them. Thank you.
And if I could speak, I've known Ralph and Loretta many, many years, two great daughters, two great people, good friends of mine, and I wanna wish them congratulations, 60 years of marriage. So, Council Member Falco. Thank you, Council Member Knight for bringing this forward. I just wanna wish the evangelist is a very happy anniversary and many more years to come.
Congratulations. Thank you. So on the motion by Vice President Knight, seconded by Councilor Falco, all those in favor. Aye. Motion passes. 2-1-6-1-6 offered by Vice President Knight, be it so resolved to seek counsel for the moment of silence and recognition of the sacrifices made by veterans.
in honor of Veterans Day. Vice President Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much. As we're all aware, this Thursday is Veterans Day, 11-11. And it's also the, I believe, 246th birthday of the United States Marine Corps, if I'm not mistaken. But with that being said, Mr. President, Medford has a very strong veterans population. There's almost 2,000 veterans that reside in this community that at one point in their lives signed the dotted line and said, I'm going to do more for my country. I'm going to do more.
And these individuals sacrifice they spent time away from their family they put themselves in harm's way. And some of them are fortunate to come back. And those are the people that we honor here on Veterans Day, Mr. President, all those who have served. So with that being said, I'd ask my council colleagues to support me in this resolution. I'd also like to offer that I've had conversations with Michael Durham.
down the veterans office I bumped into him just the other day at the Mets donuts where he was making a purchase of 300 donuts to distribute to veterans mentioned veterans on Veterans Day. So with that being said was the president that for those veterans that are interested that please visit the veterans services website for more information but it will be a celebration Thursday coming out of the veterans service office on Iraq veterans with donuts from the Mets. Thank you.
Any further discussion? So on the motion by Vice President Knight, seconded by? Seconded by Councilor Spelko. All in favor? Aye. All opposed? Motion passes. Motion to revert back to regular business.
Do we have anything else to discuss this evening? 2, 1, 5, 4, 3, if I'm not mistaken, I think that was the redistricting.
Yeah, that's right. These were the on-site meetings on the 30th we did. So on the 21513, Committee of the Whole report, as I said, this was the outdoor meeting. We're waiting for reports from the administration and the traffic engineer for north carding in that area. So on the motion by Councilor Behrs, seconded by Councilor Marks. All those in favor? Aye. Motion passes. 21593, October 30th, Committee of the Whole report.
This was the committee of the whole report in regards to Brooks and Irving Street. Second on the motion by Vice President Light, seconded by Councilor Behrs. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion passes. Please let me take a moment to congratulate the candidates on the reelection. And I wanna congratulate our two new councilors, Councilor Tang and Councilor Collins.
I look forward to seeing them here in the next couple of weeks to join in. And thank you for all the candidates who took the time out to run for the job and I think we all know what a daunting task that is, you know, to be in the campaign. And I just want to send good wishes out to everybody.
In common custom, we've always invited the newly elected councils to come down and sit in the well behind the rail to observe as we lead into