hello kids today we are going to read sight words for grade four example when what wheel where girl two with teacher elshi are you ready let's start
when when what what wheel wheel where where girl girl dare
Their. Too. Too. Many. Many. When. What. Wheel. Where. Girl. Their. Too.
Many. People. People. First. First. Where. Where. Went. Went. With. With.
or, or use, use whiched, whiched people, first where, went with, or
Use. Which. Bean. Bean. Number. Number. Broader. Broader. Hundred. Hundred. Why.
Why. Who. Who. Your. Your. One. One. Been. Number. Broader. Hundred.
Why. Who. Your. One. Each. Each. This. This. Ward. Ward. Into.
Into Toward Toward First First Water Water Please Please Each This Word
Into Toward First Water Please Only Only Great Great Move Move Father
Father. Follow. Follow. Find. Find. Study. Study. At. At. Only. Great.
Move. Father. Follow. Find. Study. Add. Question. Question. Any. Any. Because. Because.
Beautiful Beautiful Again Again Sentence Sentence Different Different Picture Picture Learn
Learn. Question. Any. Because. Beautiful. Again. Sentence. Different. Picture. Learn. Learn. Around.
Around. Work. Work. Das. Das. Very. Very. Large. Large. Pull. Pull.
Through. Through. Learn. Around. Work. Thus. Very. Large. Pull. Through. Even. Even. Answer.
Answer. World. World. Open. Open. High. High. Sorry. Sorry. Leave. Leave.
Earth, earth. Even, answer. World, open. High, story. Live, earth. Bought, bought.
until until carry carry being being group group though though between
between present present bought unseal carry being group though between present
Favorite Favorite Always Always Paper Paper Children Children Example Example Without
Without. Together. Together. Are. Are. Favorite. Always. Paper. Children. Example. Without. Together.
Are. Under. Under. Watched. Watched. Every. Every. I. I. Often. Often.
Night. Night. Later. Later. Almost. Almost. Under. Watched. Every. Eye. Often. Night. Later.
Almost. Once. Once. Mater. Mater. Really. Really. Could. Could. Talk. Talk.
Also. Also. Eerily. Eerily. Jump. Jump. Once. Motter. Really. Could. Thought. Also.
Early Jump Soon Soon Found Found Drink Drink Important Important Eight
Eight. Family. Family. Across. Across. Sign. Sign. Soon. Found. Drink. Important. Eight.
Family. Across. Sign. Listen. Listen. Write. Write. Know. Know. About. About.
sometime sometime second second enough enough young young listen write know
About Sometime Second Enough Young Next Next Caller Caller Hold Hold Ride
Ride Laugh Laugh Done Done Put Put Grow Grow Next Collar Hold
Ride Laugh Done Put Grow Kind Kind Shall Shall Walk Walk Think
Think. Well. Well. Only. Only. Use. Use. Which. Which. Kind. Shall.
walk think well only use which Thank you! Once again, this is teacher Roshi and please don't forget to click like, share and subscribe to this channel Bye-bye! See you again!