I came to dance, dance, dance, dance I hit the floor cause that's my plans, plans, plans, plans I'm wearing all my favorite brands, brands, brands, brands Give me some space for both my hands, hands, hands, hands You, you, cause it goes on
I throw my hands up in the air sometimes, saying ayo, gotta let go
I came to move
Move, move, move, get out the way of me and my crew, crew, crew, crew I'm in the club so I'm gonna do, do, do, do just what the fool came here to do
I throw my hands up in the air sometimes, saying ayo, gotta let go
We gon' light it up like it's dynamite Cause I told you once, now I told you twice
I just want it all. I'm gonna put my hands in the air. Hands in the air. Put your hands in the air. I throw my hands up in the air sometimes, saying ayo, gotta let it go.
Baby, let's go Cause we gon' rock this club We gon' go all night We gon' light it up Like it's dynamite Cause I told you once Now I told you twice We gon' light it up Like it's dynamite Dance, dance, dance, dance I hit the floor cause that's my plans, plans, plans, plans I'm wearing all my fans
Give me some space for both my hands, hands, hands, hands You, you, cause it goes on and on and on And it goes on and on and on, yeah I throw my hands up in the air sometimes Saying ayo, gotta let go
I came to move, move, move
Get out the way of me and my crew, crew, crew, crew I'm in the club so I'm gonna do, do, do, do
I throw my hands up in the air sometimes, saying ayo, gotta let go
I'm gonna take it all right I'm gonna be the last one
I just want it all I'm gonna put my hands in the air Hands in the air Put your hands in the air I throw my hands up in the air sometimes Sayin' ayo, got an ayo
Baby let's go Cause we gon' rock this club We gon' go all night We gon' light it up Like it's dynamite Cause I told you once Now I told you twice We gon' light it up Like it's dynamite