[SPEAKER_06]: Good evening, everyone.
[SPEAKER_06]: Hi, Bob.
[SPEAKER_06]: Go ahead and call the meeting to order.
[SPEAKER_06]: This is a meeting of the City of Medford's Cannabis Advisory Committee.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I will call the roll for attendance.
[SPEAKER_06]: Chief Buckley.
[SPEAKER_07]: Present.
[SPEAKER_06]: Marianne O'Connor.
[SPEAKER_06]: Here.
[SPEAKER_06]: Neil Osborne.
[SPEAKER_06]: present and here.
[SPEAKER_06]: Bob Dickinson here.
[SPEAKER_06]: Great.
[SPEAKER_06]: We have two items on our agenda this evening.
[SPEAKER_06]: The first being a detailed review of kindly cannabis deliveries application for a location
[SPEAKER_06]: at 86 Swan Street, and thank you all for getting your scores in on time.
[SPEAKER_06]: We were able to tally those, so we'll show you the scores, accept any conversation on that application.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then we also have a presentation from EnRoute Delivery, which is a new application for you all to consider for preliminary review.
[SPEAKER_09]: Recording in progress.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thanks, Teresa.
[SPEAKER_06]: So with that, any questions before we jump into the review of Kindly Cannabis Deliveries application?
[SPEAKER_06]: I know that Kindly is on.
[SPEAKER_06]: I see Lisa.
[SPEAKER_06]: Hi, Lisa.
[SPEAKER_06]: If you have any follow-up questions, just as a reminder,
[SPEAKER_06]: Once this review has been conducted by you all and the application has been scored, we are making a recommendation to the mayor to consider during her review for a host community agreement.
[SPEAKER_06]: And as we've done in the past,
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm happy to write up the memo and include any comments that the committee has for the mayor's consideration.
[SPEAKER_06]: Along with the memo, we'll provide the application and the scoring sheet.
[SPEAKER_06]: Here is a summary of the scores.
[SPEAKER_06]: Nothing unusual.
[SPEAKER_06]: For those that are keeping track at home, the overall score is a little lower just because we only have four out of five CAC members at the moment.
[SPEAKER_06]: The building commissioner seat has not been filled.
[SPEAKER_06]: Are there any questions or comments from the committee members?
[SPEAKER_06]: I know it's hard to digest this.
[SPEAKER_06]: As I mentioned, the purpose of the scoring sheet is to pass along to the mayor for purposes of comparing applications.
[SPEAKER_06]: But I'll open it up to questions or comments.
[SPEAKER_05]: Just want to say hello to everybody.
[SPEAKER_06]: Hi, Bo.
[SPEAKER_06]: Do you mind introducing yourself?
[SPEAKER_05]: No.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hello, everyone.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm Bowie Berthold.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm the co-founder of Paper Crane Cannabis and Kindly Delivery.
[SPEAKER_05]: And we're just excited to see what our score is here and hopefully start moving this forward.
[SPEAKER_05]: If there's any questions from anybody, feel free just to go ahead and throw them out.
[SPEAKER_05]: I don't see Lisa or I don't know if Lisa and Ed are planning on being here, but I'm happy to answer any questions anybody has.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thanks, boy.
[SPEAKER_06]: I think they are here.
[SPEAKER_06]: Oh, OK.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, we'll open it up to the committee members.
[SPEAKER_04]: I guess Victor, my only question would be the impact of not having, right, one of the members here as far as their scoring goes and how that's going to be kind of weighed as when you're comparing the other scores.
[SPEAKER_04]: Is that going to have to be somehow weighed?
[SPEAKER_05]: So yeah, we're missing basically scores from one person.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's right, am I right?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: Right, it's a five member committee and one of the seats isn't currently filled.
[SPEAKER_06]: So yeah, it's a good question, Marianne.
[SPEAKER_06]: I think that in our memo, it's fair to call that out to the mayor just so she's aware of that.
[SPEAKER_06]: And if it's the building commissioner, I suppose if there are any,
[SPEAKER_06]: specific questions she has to that expertise, there are folks on staff that she can consult.
[SPEAKER_06]: Or if she preferred to get some additional input from the CAC, that would be her prerogative as well.
[SPEAKER_06]: But yeah, it's a little unprecedented because we haven't faced this before in other reviews.
[SPEAKER_06]: I guess I don't have a great answer to your question, except that it's something we should acknowledge as we're passing this along.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: Well, I would accept a recommendation if that's where there are no further questions.
[SPEAKER_08]: So I guess I'll start us off.
[SPEAKER_08]: So I would recommend that we move this application on to or pass it on to the mayor for her review.
[SPEAKER_09]: I second that motion.
Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: Chief Buckley?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Bob Dickinson?
[SPEAKER_06]: Marianne O'Connor?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Neil Osborne?
[SPEAKER_06]: All right.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you very much for
[SPEAKER_06]: your attention to this.
[SPEAKER_06]: For the paper crane, kindly delivery crew, thanks for joining us this evening.
[SPEAKER_06]: And we'll pull together the packet of information for the mayor and we'll let you know once it's forwarded along to her.
[SPEAKER_06]: From now on, you'll be communicating through the mayor's office and I'd be happy to connect you with the folks there.
[SPEAKER_05]: All right.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you, everybody.
[SPEAKER_05]: Appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, everyone.
[SPEAKER_10]: Good luck, well done.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you so much, appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_06]: Next up, we have a presentation from the folks at EnRoute related to their application for a delivery only license.
[SPEAKER_06]: Who is here from Enroute?
[SPEAKER_02]: Hi, this is Brian.
[SPEAKER_02]: Brian Keith, I'm here.
[SPEAKER_06]: Hi, Brian.
[SPEAKER_03]: Joanne Keith is also here.
[SPEAKER_06]: Hi, Joanne.
[SPEAKER_06]: Do you have a deck presentation?
[SPEAKER_06]: I do.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can share my screen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Salman Chowdhury, also one of the owners here.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm still disabled from screen sharing.
[SPEAKER_06]: Teresa, are you driving?
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_10]: Brian, I just made you a co-host.
[SPEAKER_10]: Got it.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm in.
[SPEAKER_06]: Just so everyone's
[SPEAKER_06]: aware of where this application stands.
[SPEAKER_06]: We have received what we consider a complete application.
[SPEAKER_06]: There were a couple items missing, but the EnRoute team has provided those.
[SPEAKER_06]: And after the presentation tonight, if it's acceptable to the committee, you can vote to allow them to proceed with a community meeting.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's the next step in the application process.
[SPEAKER_06]: At that point, we will post the application on the city's website for public review and work with Enroute to post the meeting and communicate that with the public.
[SPEAKER_02]: So Brian, with that, take it away.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And one minor correction, it's Enroute, it's French.
[SPEAKER_06]: Gosh, I'm so sorry.
[SPEAKER_02]: No problem.
[SPEAKER_06]: I've been pronouncing it for months now.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's good we had this meeting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Good afternoon, Director Schrader and members of the Cannabis Advisory Committee.
[SPEAKER_02]: My name is Brian Keith, one of the principals at En Route Home Delivery.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm joined today by my fellow founders, Joanne, Rokia, and Solomon.
[SPEAKER_02]: Today, we will be discussing our proposal for a cannabis delivery operator license for en route home delivery to be cited at 151 Mystic Ave in Medford, Mass.
[SPEAKER_02]: Our mission statement speaks to who we are and is a true expression of our values.
[SPEAKER_02]: En route's mission is to build a community conscious adult use cannabis business that engages, serves and benefits communities of color and other disadvantaged communities through financial success and social responsibility.
[SPEAKER_02]: En Route Home Delivery Medford is 100% minority owned and majority women owned.
[SPEAKER_02]: Our team members are the, our team are members of the City of Boston Equity Program, as well as the State of Massachusetts Social Equity Program administered by the Cannabis Control Commission.
[SPEAKER_02]: We are excited about our proposal in Medford because when we join a community, we truly become active members of the community.
[SPEAKER_02]: Joanne is a chair of the Ward 8 Democratic Committee in Boston, member of the Massport CAC, and a member of a Patient and Family Advisory Committee for a local NICU.
[SPEAKER_02]: Rokia is a member of Roslindale Main Streets in Boston.
[SPEAKER_02]: Solomon is a member of the Central Square Business Association, as well as Roxbury Main Streets Organization.
[SPEAKER_02]: I hold a position of chair of the board of trustees for a local charter school.
[SPEAKER_02]: a member of the Roxbury Main Streets Board as well, a member of the UUUM Board in Roxbury, and until recently, I handled aircraft logistics for a Massachusetts-based private jet company.
[SPEAKER_02]: Salman and Rokia Chowdhury are a husband and wife team with more than 22 years of local business and ownership experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Their portfolio includes Shanti, three full-service Indian restaurants in Dorchester, Roslindale, and Kendall Square, the Dudley Cafe, a coffee shop in Roxbury's Newbeen Square,
[SPEAKER_02]: and 250 plus real estate developments and investments.
[SPEAKER_02]: Shanti Express, a fourth Indian restaurant, is a delivery-only kitchen concept, not dissimilar from our proposal this evening.
[SPEAKER_02]: Together, we have 20 years as small business owners, 30 years as community advocates, 16 years in fleet logistics, expertise in areas of retail operations, luxury marketing, and regulated industries, and five plus years of planning and research in local cannabis space
[SPEAKER_02]: And we're in the final stages of opening a cannabis retail establishment at 331 Newberry Street.
[SPEAKER_02]: We have had the pleasure of working through both the City of Boston licensing and permitting and zoning process for our adult use cannabis establishment approved on Newberry Street.
[SPEAKER_02]: We are nearly complete with the CCC process at this location and are awaiting approval of our final license.
[SPEAKER_02]: You will see on this slide before and after images of the initial state of our facility, truly creating a cannabis boutique in the retail heart of the City of Boston.
[SPEAKER_02]: And to be clear, the bottom images are the images of the before and the after are the top images, not the other way around.
[SPEAKER_02]: These next images display our family-friendly participation in Open Newberry over the past six Sundays.
[SPEAKER_02]: Open Newberry is an event where the entirety of Newberry Street is closed to vehicular traffic and becomes a pedestrian way.
[SPEAKER_02]: This past Sunday, we invited Girl Paul Creamery, a Black-owned ice cream shop from Boston's Dorchester neighborhood,
[SPEAKER_02]: to hand out complimentary ice cream to passersby.
[SPEAKER_02]: We are excited to, of course, compensate Grifoil Creamery for their work, but also give them the exposure to the foot traffic and disposable income found on Newbury Street.
[SPEAKER_02]: Uplifting small businesses is integral to everything we do.
[SPEAKER_02]: A delivery operator is a business that receives wholesale cannabis from licensed marijuana cultivators and marijuana product manufacturers.
[SPEAKER_02]: The wholesale product is stored in a secure vault at 151 Mystic Avenue until it's securely transferred from the vault to one of En-Route's three secure all-electric vehicles for delivery to customers.
[SPEAKER_02]: Here, you'll be able to see a sketch of our proposed interior layout.
[SPEAKER_02]: This shows very small on our screen, so after the presentation, if there is interest, we can revisit this slide and make it bigger.
[SPEAKER_02]: Regarding delivery, En Route delivers to customers who are 21 years of age or older at their home residence or to licensed marijuana operators.
[SPEAKER_02]: Deliveries to dorms, government housing, hotels, or similar are strictly prohibited.
[SPEAKER_02]: To ensure that all requirements for delivery are met, prior to placing an order for delivery, all customers are required to pre-register and submit proof of age and residence verification.
[SPEAKER_02]: Age is verified again on camera at time of delivery.
[SPEAKER_02]: All delivery vehicles will be staffed with at least two employees, and during delivery, the vehicles will not be left alone at any time.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is important to note that there is absolutely no public component to this operation.
[SPEAKER_02]: There will be no registers on site nor will there be any customers or members of the public coming into the facility at any time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Our last delivery must be in the customer's hands by 9 p.m.
[SPEAKER_02]: or it will be delivered the following day.
[SPEAKER_02]: We will be a fully self-contained site.
[SPEAKER_02]: As a transportation business, we'll be looking closely at how best to optimize delivery schedules around peak commuter times.
[SPEAKER_02]: There will be no delivery vehicles allowed to park alongside the street.
[SPEAKER_02]: and we will be employing GPS technology to track all vehicles, ensuring vans safe entry into and out of the facility.
[SPEAKER_02]: Centrally located, EnRoute will have the ability to deliver with speed across the city of Medford and to surrounding communities.
[SPEAKER_02]: Our hours of operations, as you can see, are 10 a.m.
[SPEAKER_02]: to 9 p.m.
[SPEAKER_09]: Apologies for the dog.
[SPEAKER_02]: 40 state certified employees, including 12 delivery drivers and 28 warehouse staff, dispatch, security, with a preference to local BIPOC and veteran and LGBTQ individuals.
[SPEAKER_02]: We plan on creating 40 jobs at En Route Medford with a preference for Medford residents.
[SPEAKER_02]: Our hope is that we are hiring in such a local manner that our employees will have the opportunity to walk to work.
[SPEAKER_02]: We estimate a payroll budget that will see employees averaging a salary of $75,000, well above what is considered a living wage.
[SPEAKER_02]: Employees will have access to full medical, dental, and vision benefits, including 401k.
[SPEAKER_02]: Additionally, we have created a profit sharing program that employees will have access to based on the success of the location.
[SPEAKER_02]: We will encourage employee growth and will promote skills that will be transferable beyond the cannabis industry.
[SPEAKER_02]: We will touch on this again later in the presentation,
[SPEAKER_02]: but it is important for us to note that we have signed a labor peace agreement with UFCW Local 1445 to ensure that employee voice is always paramount.
[SPEAKER_02]: As mentioned previously, we will use a small to midsize fleet of three all electric.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do I need to let anybody in the room or is someone else able to do that?
[SPEAKER_02]: I just saw someone jump in the room.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, great, perfect, thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: As mentioned previously, we will use a small to mid-sized fleet of three all-electric vehicles.
[SPEAKER_02]: We are excited to bring an all-electric cannabis delivery fleet to Medford, which means zero exhaust and emissions, and zero engine noises, which ensures we are always respectful to our neighbors.
[SPEAKER_02]: Each vehicle used to deliver product will be outfitted with the highest standards of security, including a mobile vault system, GPS tracking, and a two-person crew.
[SPEAKER_02]: The vehicle is never left alone with product inside.
[SPEAKER_02]: Each vehicle will have an estimated range of up to 250 to 300 miles on a single charge.
[SPEAKER_02]: A fleet and asset management software platform will ensure efficient usage.
[SPEAKER_02]: En route, we will offer parking on site for all delivery vehicles and 15 employee parking spaces.
[SPEAKER_02]: We thought it was important to show you the types of vehicle we will be operating.
[SPEAKER_09]: So you can see the BrightJob Xevo 400 right there.
[SPEAKER_02]: As this is a warehouse model, our security protocols will be focused on ensuring only employees have access to the site and that we run an efficient operation with the minimum impact to the surrounding community.
[SPEAKER_02]: With continued dialogue with surrounding neighbors, neighborhood associations, and the Medford police, we will add state-of-the-art security cameras to ensure the security of the site.
[SPEAKER_02]: All cameras will be shared live and in real time with Medford police should they wish access.
[SPEAKER_02]: At our Newberry Street adult use facility, all doors are access controlled
[SPEAKER_02]: We have 65 cameras, 58 interior, seven exterior, and all systems are redundant.
[SPEAKER_02]: With all the security, it is also important for us to note that our facility does not appear to be a prison or some other type of institutional facility.
[SPEAKER_02]: We will maintain the existing facade and we'll ensure that our operation blends into the fabric of the neighborhood.
[SPEAKER_02]: On this slide, you will see a five-year projection of revenues for en route given a certain number of inputs.
[SPEAKER_02]: We have used the capacity model, which we feel will be more efficient and lead to less vehicles on the roads on a continuous basis.
[SPEAKER_02]: This slide also shows the projected HCA payments to the city of Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm confident there are questions on this slide, so we can absolutely circle back during Q&A.
[SPEAKER_02]: As we are a business that does not see customers in person or on site, we will create a good neighbor pledge, which will be signed by all employees.
[SPEAKER_02]: This pledge will ensure that all employees are held accountable and fully respect the community that has invited our operations.
[SPEAKER_02]: The pledge will state that employees will not smoke cigarettes in public areas, will not loiter, will keep noise to a minimum, and will not park illegally.
[SPEAKER_02]: We will work with residents and the city to add to this pledge.
[SPEAKER_02]: Failure to adhere to this pledge will be considered an offense worthy of termination.
[SPEAKER_02]: In addition to the zero to 3% discretionary impact tax, which will be directed to the city of Medford as defined in our HCA,
[SPEAKER_02]: We plan to work with the city of Medford to fund a grant program.
[SPEAKER_02]: This program will be administered by a board of residents, business owners, and nonprofit leaders from the Medford community who will determine what worthy causes will receive the funds.
[SPEAKER_02]: Our profit sharing program is unique to En Route and our sister company Rooted In.
[SPEAKER_02]: We will profit share with our employees based on company success.
[SPEAKER_02]: As you can see, employees are important to us and ensuring they can afford to live, work, play, and own in our communities is very important.
[SPEAKER_02]: We've created an employee home buyer program, which you can see detailed on the screen.
[SPEAKER_02]: There will be an effort to monitor health impacts on the neighborhood.
[SPEAKER_02]: And as parents ourselves, we will monitor any impact our presence may have on the local youth population.
[SPEAKER_02]: We'll work with the Medford Health Department on ways to combat the burden of hard drugs and opiate abuse.
[SPEAKER_02]: In consultation with the Medford Health Department, the mayor's office, and local healthcare leaders,
[SPEAKER_02]: will develop a fund which will be directed to increase positive outcomes to those working to recover from substance abuse disorder.
[SPEAKER_02]: Diversity planning.
[SPEAKER_02]: En Route Medford is 100% person of color owned and 50% of its structure is social equity.
[SPEAKER_02]: We've created a very unique investor model.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was first established at our Newberry Street location, which saw 55 of our
[SPEAKER_02]: excuse me, 53 of our 55 investors being people of color and 47% of our investors being women.
[SPEAKER_02]: We wanted to ensure that our investor model was approachable to all.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it's not a $50,000 investment.
[SPEAKER_02]: It actually starts at $1,200 with as much as $100,000.
[SPEAKER_02]: This model allows us to not only benefit ourselves and our employees through the operation of this business, but also it allows us to create generational wealth.
[SPEAKER_02]: specifically generational wealth in communities of color.
[SPEAKER_02]: Additionally, you can see the hiring construction as well as how we plan to work with growers with a preference to BIPOC and veteran growers in Massachusetts.
[SPEAKER_02]: We've engaged in meaningful conversations with abutters, neighbors, businesses, community leaders, as well as Medford-based stakeholders, and have garnered nearly 50 letters of support.
[SPEAKER_02]: As mentioned previously, we've proudly signed a labor peace agreement with UFCW Local 1445.
[SPEAKER_02]: They are the Massachusetts union that represents cannabis workers statewide.
[SPEAKER_02]: We've also engaged with a local chapter of a national civil rights organization.
[SPEAKER_02]: And here you can see our difference.
[SPEAKER_02]: Starting with our mission as our guide, our greatest differentiator is our investment team and our approach to building generational wealth for communities of color.
[SPEAKER_02]: We want to bring cannabis businesses to our community that are owned and operated by residents of color.
[SPEAKER_02]: We have deployed a unique investment model, which works to give disenfranchised communities a seat at the table at the ground floor of this burgeoning industry.
[SPEAKER_02]: As far as hiring, we'll hire members of the local community with a focus on those with past candidates and fractions.
[SPEAKER_02]: 5% of location equity will be set aside for employees and a profit share, which we have gone into.
[SPEAKER_02]: We pledge to be good neighbors, give back through grants and monitor and remedy any adverse health impacts.
[SPEAKER_02]: With that, I'd like to thank you for your time, and I look forward to your questions.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you, Brian and the en route team for that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And as mentioned, happy to bring up anything that requires additional detail or anything that needs to be zoomed in.
[SPEAKER_08]: OK, I'll start again.
[SPEAKER_08]: Assuming that you were to be given the green light to
[SPEAKER_08]: work from Medford, how soon could be up and running?
[SPEAKER_02]: Our goal is to be operational by winter of 2023.
[SPEAKER_02]: We've gained a lot of experience learning the state's process and just understanding the construction process.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is a relatively unique construction process, not unique to construction, but there are certain things that cannabis requires as far as security and protocols and things of that nature.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we've gained a lot of that experience on Newberry Street, we started Newberry Street in January of 2021, and we expect to be open, either late November, early December.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we think that, you know, given our experience knowledge, we can do better than that two year mark with this facility.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, Brian.
[SPEAKER_04]: Can you talk to me a little bit more about your employee training and the system you're going to use for age verification, both, you know, the initial sale and delivery?
[SPEAKER_04]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: So with regards to age verification, the customers will initially upload
[SPEAKER_02]: their IDs onto a portal online when they are initially placing their order.
[SPEAKER_02]: That way we're checking IDs, obviously it's not an official check, but we're checking IDs, giving it a tertiary scan to ensure that the individual is 21, to ensure that the address that we're delivering to is an address that we can legally deliver to because there are restrictions on delivery.
[SPEAKER_02]: Once our drivers are on site, they will have
[SPEAKER_02]: ID scanners that offer passport quality checks of those IDs to ensure that they are the individuals who they say they are and that it is a valid ID.
[SPEAKER_02]: For if this is what we do in our dispensary, it also probably happen less.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if there is someone with an out of state, excuse me, foreign ID, we would ask for a second form of identification as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: That'll probably happen less because we will see a lot of tourists in person.
[SPEAKER_02]: But for delivery, it's typically going to be the individual that resides at that residence.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if there is someone from out of state that's visiting, you know, we wouldn't, as long as they can provide a second form of identification, we would allow them to make that purchase.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then as far as training, all employees must go through a minimum of eight hours of standardized training from the state.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then we will provide our own internal training as far as customer service, you know, securing themselves, securing the product and things of that nature.
[SPEAKER_02]: Training is actually very important to us at our Newberry Street site.
[SPEAKER_02]: We actually set aside about 300 square feet specifically for training space.
[SPEAKER_02]: We don't have a big facility, but we wanted to make sure that we had the ability to
[SPEAKER_02]: train our employees, and we anticipate doing something very similar in Medford to ensure that, you know, when we are ready to put someone on the road or even individuals who are working in our warehouse, there's a standard level of service and a standard level of training that everyone has.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thanks.
[SPEAKER_04]: Could you speak to the surrounding communities?
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, what's the area that you're planning on having deliveries to?
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, what's your expansion?
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: So the way the rules work at the state level is that as a delivery operator, we're only allowed to deliver to communities who have approved cannabis in their municipality.
[SPEAKER_02]: Um, so for us, we expect to start small and start with, um, a catchment area that is Medford only.
[SPEAKER_02]: Um, then we anticipate, you know, as we grow, um, and as we bring on additional vehicles and additional personnel, um, that we would grow into the communities that surround Medford who have, um, allowed for cannabis delivery.
[SPEAKER_02]: Um, there's only so far that you can go, um, because, you know, there's only
[SPEAKER_02]: so much product that you can have in the vehicle at a time, plus there's a point where it becomes inefficient to go out so far.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I would say we would probably go one or two communities beyond Medford, and then we would revisit to determine if it makes sense to go further than that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And will your vehicles be have signage on them or are they just going to be like I saw the vehicles you showed said the onboard or whatever would you have vehicles be identifiable are they just going to be.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, so the rules state that all vehicles have to be completely nondescript the the pictures that you saw were promotional pictures for that vehicle so it actually said the.
[SPEAKER_02]: name of the company that manufactures it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Our vehicles would be completely nondescript, likely white or black vehicles, something that just looks like any other delivery vehicle on the street.
[SPEAKER_04]: Great.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, appreciate that.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think that's all I have.
[SPEAKER_04]: I was interested in the grant fund program.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then you talked about, you know, helping to fund folks but recovering from substance use disorders, those two separate things that you're talking about.
[SPEAKER_02]: Those are two separate.
[SPEAKER_02]: Those are two separate items so the substance abuse disorder is one, because we recognize that, you know, but I'm in Boston, right now and I'm in Roxbury it's a huge problem, you know, down where I am.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's separate.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's completely separate.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's something that we would fund separately to the grant program.
[SPEAKER_02]: We anticipate the grant program would fund things like, you know, back to school backpack programs and, you know, things that support youth and other things that are needed in the Medford area.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you, Brian.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_07]: Hi Brian, Chief Buckley, thanks for the presentation, well done.
[SPEAKER_07]: Question, you say you have a retail establishment opening in Boston.
[SPEAKER_07]: Do you or your team have any other, I'd like to hear about your experience in the marijuana industry outside of just, do you have any current experience or investment and involvement in other regulated marijuana industry?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, the industry is very new.
[SPEAKER_02]: Um, we don't, uh, we don't have specific, um, marijuana experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Most locals, um, you know, true locals, um, to Massachusetts won't have marijuana experience because marijuana has only been legal on the recreational side for about four years and about six or seven years on the medical side.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you know, my background is not cannabis.
[SPEAKER_02]: My background is private aviation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Um, that being said.
[SPEAKER_02]: Salman and Rokia do come with a background of regulated industries.
[SPEAKER_02]: They, you know, are former owners of lounges.
[SPEAKER_02]: So they, you know, and they also own the restaurant.
[SPEAKER_02]: So they, you know, deal with alcohol.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I think alcohol is the closest thing right now to cannabis.
[SPEAKER_02]: So as it pertains to experience, we don't have
[SPEAKER_02]: direct experience, but I think as a group, we do have parallel experience to the industry.
[SPEAKER_02]: The way the regs were written was very similar to how the alcohol and liquor regulations are written, obviously with more specifics towards the plant and cannabis and things like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's a lot, it is more strict.
[SPEAKER_02]: The cannabis regs are more strict than alcohol, but we do have, I would call it parallel experience.
[SPEAKER_07]: I thank you for the answer.
[SPEAKER_07]: And again, I don't, I don't mean to apply that.
[SPEAKER_07]: I think it's a negative.
[SPEAKER_07]: I just wanted to see if there did exist, uh, experience out there, but thank you.
[SPEAKER_09]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_06]: Any further questions from the committee?
[SPEAKER_06]: I'm good.
[SPEAKER_06]: Great.
[SPEAKER_06]: As I mentioned, the next step for en route is to hold a community meeting.
[SPEAKER_06]: It is at the committee's discretion.
[SPEAKER_06]: So as we've done in the past, we'll entertain a motion.
[SPEAKER_06]: I do see a hand up.
[SPEAKER_06]: Go ahead, Gabriel.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, this is Gabriel Camacho.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am the political director for United Food and Commercial Workers, Local 1445.
[SPEAKER_00]: Local 1445 represents approximately 12,000 essential workers throughout the Commonwealth of Massachusetts.
[SPEAKER_00]: You probably know us by the friendly faces of workers at Stop and Shop, Macy's, and more recently at Cannabis Dispensaries.
[SPEAKER_00]: UFCW nationally represents tens of thousands of cannabis workers throughout the nation from seed to sale.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here in Massachusetts, local 1445 represents a thousand of cannabis workers in agriculture, production, processing, packaging, delivery, and in medical and adult recreational dispensaries.
[SPEAKER_00]: Our union is in strong support for Enroute Home Delivery Service.
[SPEAKER_00]: In addition to being an equity applicant, Enroute has committed to hiring affected residents by the War on Drugs, and that usually means people of color.
[SPEAKER_00]: Enroute and UFCW Local 1445 has entered into a partnership with a labor peace agreement
[SPEAKER_00]: otherwise known as an LPA.
[SPEAKER_00]: Simply put, an LPA is an agreement between a union and an employer where the company agrees to remain neutral during an organizing drive and the union agrees not to engage in any job actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: In this way, employees will decide to unionize or not without undue influence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Additionally,
[SPEAKER_00]: Our union, and this is very important for us, strongly believes that racial equity must have an economic stability as its backbone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although the cannabis industry in the state has surpassed $3 billion in gross revenues last year, the Attorney General's office has fined cannabis companies hundreds of thousands of dollars for violations of state labor laws.
[SPEAKER_00]: This would never happen with a union contract.
[SPEAKER_00]: Indeed, our collective bargaining agreements, not only contain better wages and benefits in the canvas industry, but also equally as important in non economic matters such as non discrimination clauses upward mobility that respect seniority and shop floor.
[SPEAKER_00]: union representation.
[SPEAKER_00]: We also know that en route is equally committed to racial justice in the cannabis industry, and indeed, in all aspects of social and economic justice.
[SPEAKER_00]: UFCW Local 1445 strongly urges the Cannabis Advisory Committee of Medford to support En Route for their delivery license in Medford.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_07]: Well, I'll make a motion to allow en route to move forward to conduct a community meeting.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'll second that motion.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'll call the roll on that.
[SPEAKER_06]: Neil Osborne?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Bob Dickinson?
[SPEAKER_06]: Chief Buckley?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Mary Ann O'Connor?
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_06]: Brian, as you probably already know, there's some guidance that was established for the community meeting.
[SPEAKER_06]: If you have any questions about that, please contact us.
[SPEAKER_06]: And I think you will be anyway to check schedules and make sure we're not conflicting dates.
[SPEAKER_06]: So Teresa is your point person.
[SPEAKER_02]: Great.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_02]: I really appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_06]: With that, scheduling of the next meeting is the next agenda item, but we'll wait for, we don't have any other business at the moment, so we'll wait for Enroute to conduct their meeting and we'll send the information out to you all for consideration and scoring.
[SPEAKER_06]: And then I'm happy to open it up to public participation at this point.
[SPEAKER_06]: If anyone has any questions, please feel free to raise your hand.
[SPEAKER_06]: I would like to mention, I'm glad that
[SPEAKER_06]: Lisa is still on the call, and Bo, and I should have mentioned this earlier, we did receive an email from a neighbor, kindly, Joe Albano, Joseph Limousine, with some comments for consideration by the mayor as she reviews their application.
[SPEAKER_06]: and mostly related to storing of cars and parking for employees.
[SPEAKER_06]: So he submitted a number of questions.
[SPEAKER_06]: Also notes that the entrance to Kindly will be on James Street, which has no sidewalks.
[SPEAKER_06]: The roadways in bad condition.
[SPEAKER_06]: And the businesses and employees of Mystic Ave, Swan Street and Union are parking on James Street and Route 16 behind the DPW building.
[SPEAKER_06]: This has created challenges for the businesses in this area.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I'll be sure to forward that along to the mayor along with their application.
[SPEAKER_07]: Victor, can you send that to all of us also?
[SPEAKER_10]: Yes, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_06]: Alrighty, any other questions or comments?
[SPEAKER_03]: Hi, I'm Emily and I just have a more general question as to why
[SPEAKER_03]: particularly cannabis companies in order to open in the Medford area have to go in front of a council for a proposal to open?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Hi, Emily.
[SPEAKER_06]: Good question.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's by local ordinance.
[SPEAKER_06]: So the city council established an ordinance for review of marijuana applications and the licensing of these entities.
[SPEAKER_06]: by ordinance, this is the first step in the process.
[SPEAKER_06]: We have posted the ordinances on our city website under the Department of Planning, Development, Sustainability.
[SPEAKER_06]: You'll find a tab for the Cannabis Advisory Committee and the ordinances are listed there.
[SPEAKER_06]: They're also on the city's Muni Code website if you'd like to review them.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, I'll accept the motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_10]: Motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_10]: Second.
[SPEAKER_06]: Bob Dickinson.
[SPEAKER_06]: Let's adjourn.
[SPEAKER_06]: Marianne O'Connor.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Chief Buckley.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Neil Osborne.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Great, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_06]: Have a nice evening.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thanks, everyone.