All right, the March 29th meeting of the Medford Bicycle Advisory Commission will come to order.
I think Dennis has some verbiage for us.
Thank you.
Unfortunately, I just switched, but I've got it here.
I always have it up, and I always forget exactly what tab it's on.
Here we go.
On July 16, 2022, Governor Baker signed into law an act relative to extending certain state of emergency accommodations, which, among other things, extends the expiration provisions pertaining to the Open Meeting Law to March 31, 2023.
Specifically, this extension allows public bodies to continue holding meetings remotely without a quorum of the public body physically present at a meeting location and to provide adequate alternative access to remote meetings.
The act does not make any new changes to the open meeting law other than extending the expiration date of the temporary provisions regarding remote meetings from 2022 to March 31st, 2023.
Speaking of which, since now that you mentioned it, what happens after March 31st, 2023?
At this moment.
So the bill I guess I'm not fully conversant in the ways of state asked by both the House and the Senate and it's on the governor's desk waiting for signature.
Okay, so.
PB, John Gerstle, COB, he's the one who's going to do it.
I mean, the anticipation is that, I mean, you all are pretty good at that.
Your meeting isn't for another month.
So this has happened.
Three times in the last three years that they push it to the very, very end.
And.
It's nerve wracking when you have meetings that are in the beginning of the month, as I also do.
So we.
But so for going forward, yeah, everything should be fine.
I don't know specifics of the timing, how long, I've heard two years, which would be lovely and not have us to think about this for a bit, but for right now, we all should be fine and continue meeting in this fashion.
Great, thank you.
In that case, will the secretary call the roll?
Jared Powell.
Present.
Bruce Cook.
I'm present here.
Emily O'Brien.
Here.
B. Dan Fairchild.
Ernie Meunier.
I see you, Ernie.
Say that you're here.
You're muted.
He's here.
Yes.
Taking that as present.
Doug Packer.
I do not see.
Has anyone heard from Doug recently?
I know he kind of comes and goes, but just curious.
Gaston Fiore, is he still part of the commission?
As far as I know.
Okay.
Sorry.
I had an old list that also had Peter on it, and I was like, wait a minute.
Daniel Nazimuller, present, and Rebecca Wright, who I do not see here.
We also have some visitors.
Lily, do you want to start and then we'll get the others?
Hi, everyone.
I'm Lily.
I'm a student at Tufts and also an intern in the Department of Engineering and Department of Planning.
Great.
Thank you.
Noam?
Hi, everyone.
Noam Reveni.
I'm a resident.
I live in West Medford, and I've been corresponding with Daniel about joining the commission.
Also, I submitted my paperwork to the city a couple of months ago when that correspondence kicked off.
So nice to join you all.
Great, thanks for coming.
Janine?
Hi, I'm Janine, and I'm a student at Tufts as well.
Caitlin?
Hi, I'm Caitlin.
I'm a Medford resident interested in better bike infrastructure.
Great.
MCM Government Access, do you want to introduce yourself since you're here?
I'll take that as a no.
That's the channel.
I think that's the channel.
That's the TV.
They're showing us over the.
Oh, I see.
So there's not actually, I wasn't sure if there was actually a person.
No, it's, I mean, there's someone in there who's actually plugging in, but they're doing all the TV stuff.
Okay.
But they don't actually, they don't actually need to introduce themselves.
So actually, if I can just jump in, as we were speaking, I literally just got forwarded that the governor has signed it.
So,
for two more years.
I don't know exactly when it happened, but it just got sent to me as we were talking.
I'm glad we have her here.
I guess her ears were burning or something.
Great.
Announcements.
What have we got?
Um, I've got a couple of things here.
Go ahead.
Maybe some of them probably overlap with yours.
Maybe Emily just remind about circle the square.
That's June 17th.
I'm sorry Emily.
Do we register for that already?
Um, I think somebody else did.
I did not, but somebody else had the information and was going to.
I think that was the.
That was my understanding.
If we aren't, then we should, and I can do it.
Yeah, I think that's a good idea.
I get the emails about it, but I don't think I was the one who submitted that, so if we haven't, we probably should.
Yeah.
Okay, so that's Circled Square, June 17th, fun event.
We've attended plenty of times.
The other one was
bike helmets, which I don't know if Pat was going to be able to jump on today.
He did say he would jump in, but if you want to give the quick announcement version of it, and then we'll... Sure.
Well, you all remember
through a project was a KidSafe, Breakheart, White, and Gluck, the local law firm that distributes bike helmets to various organizations and things for free around Massachusetts for them to distribute.
They're doing that again this year.
That was usually Pat Bibbins' project that he often spearheaded.
So they're looking to give us 70 helmets again this year, either in May or June.
So we basically just need to say yes to that, I think, and set up a person to kind of spearhead that, which usually just means helping coordinate with Kevin Bailey over at the rec center or the rec department since he'll, he can usually store them for us until we get an event for distributing them.
And we can think about a distribution event or events as well for later this year.
While we're at it, should we just quickly make a motion to accept those?
And then is there somebody who wants to take on coordinating with that, Ernie?
We should tell them what the size distribution should be.
If it's 70, who's decided what they're going to be?
I think that's a good question.
I think they did.
But if you have feedback about
What sizes tend to be more in demand or that we need more of.
I can pass that along.
I forget Doug had that.
And I don't remember what he thought the distribution was, but it did get a little skewed by the end with an excess of a certain size.
Is it usually small as they get left over?
I'm guessing that as well, that we want to,
and reformulate the distribution on that.
Hi, Pat.
Do you remember what the helmet size distribution should be?
Oh, Pat's here.
Good.
Hi, Pat.
Well, in that case, we might as well just have Pat say what you needed to say about helmets, which we were just talking about.
Ah, great.
Yeah, sorry.
I tried to log in before, and I couldn't get in.
But Dan, thanks for sending that invite.
PB, John Gerstle, COB – He, Him, His.:
: So we're yeah where you put.
: Part of the the helmet topic are you discussing at the moment.
We got as far as saying that it exists and that we should approve to accept more helmets and then Ernie mentioned that he thought that we should check on what size distribution, we should ask for.
All right.
So yeah.
So a little background on this.
For the past quite a few years, Breakstone, Hoyt, and Gluck, a law firm that has a program called Project KidSafe, has donated about probably like six dozen helmets to us each spring.
And we've, in the probably last three or four years, we've done a distribution in collaboration with the REC program down at Tufts Park.
And that's been very well received, very successful, very well organized.
And that's something that in the past I had coordinated, but now that I've stepped down from the commission, I would very much like to hand it off to somebody else who might have an interest in it.
And I can certainly assist in either day of, or just providing advice and background on how the whole thing has been done in the past.
Um, yeah, so size breakdown, I, it's not on the top of my head.
I know that like very often we seem to run out of the small helmets.
Um, I think we, we can probably request, uh, some things, but they do come in like cartons of a couple dozen.
So usually breaks down to, uh, like by the carton.
Um, so maybe like, uh,
It might, I feel like two, maybe like two cartons of smalls, one of mediums and two of larges or two mediums, one large, something like that might be a good breakdown.
Well, someone said we were getting 70, which would be only like one carton of each, I guess.
Yeah, they typically come like two, two dozen, two carton.
It kind of depends on the size, but it's usually been about five.
But let's see, that's five dozen, so like six, between 60 and 70 helmets.
And that's in the past, uh, that's like been like a pretty good match.
Like when we do an event is we usually end up with like a dozen or two leftover.
Um, so that's, uh, that that's kind of what I would expect that it would be offerings this season.
We have any leftover from previous events at this point or we managed to.
Okay.
We do not.
We were very efficient on, on, on kids' heads.
Good.
Does somebody want to take on coordinating that?
I would be willing to step in and help coordinate that.
Yeah, and I think, like, with the rec department, they will, we could, depending on how you want to do it, they could
likely do a lot of the distribution.
We don't necessarily have to do an event.
They have, you know, maybe something that they could like give out to kids in the programs over the course of the season.
So there are lots of ways it could be done.
That's great.
We'll certainly have the square and we'll probably be at the farmer's market at some point.
And we'll, I mean, we'll have, we'll have events
Even if we don't schedule.
Another one.
The other one.
The other thing is.
There's Ellery is putting together a bike to school day and then in the spring and then another one in the fall.
So these are probably not quite high school student size, because high school kids kind of have grown up size heads, but but the middle school and elementary school kids.
This could this could that could also be an opportunity to distribute some of these.
Yeah, I mean definitely if we're going to have a... then we should be able to hand out helmets to anyone who doesn't have one already.
Yeah, I mean, and this is, I know that the bike to school day that, well, we'll get to that as another agenda item, but the bike to school day that Ellery organized the last time was really fairly impromptu.
It'll be a little less so this time because it's planned longer in advance.
The main part of it is just organizing caravans
From different parts of the city to the various schools.
And in this case, it'll be to hopefully to all of the schools, not just to the middle school in the elementary school that are right next to each other in that one spot.
But so we may need to coordinate with with Ellery or with other people at especially the elementary schools to do this.
I had.
tried several ways to get some additional coordination with students or teachers at the high school and didn't really manage to come up with anybody who wanted to
take on anything in particular.
They all like the idea and they all want somebody else to do it basically.
So I don't have a great, I don't really have a great contact at the high school, but I think if it's part of a larger, it'll be part of Bay State Bike Month and I think that's like a national bike to school day, something like that.
So it'll be part of that and we'll do our best to get it publicized and announced at the high school as well as the other places.
But, which I guess is the update about that, which is also on the agenda.
That's Wednesday, May 4th.
While we're on that, well, we'll come back to that, I guess, because we still need to deal with the helmets.
So do we need to double check on which sizes ran out earliest or latest before getting back to them?
Or Daniel, do you want to get in touch with Pat and get this underway?
Yeah, I'll get in touch with
Any info on the sizes that ran out the fastest?
I remember being the one who gave away the last few helmets, but that's probably, that's a small representative sample.
So I'm not sure what that would look like.
Ernie?
I think we'll be pretty safe in ordering or asking for a distribution of 25 large, 25 medium, and 20 small.
That may work out to be just about right.
Yeah, Pat, I think so too.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think so.
And the main important thing is just like giving Sarah over at Project Kids Safe a contact person.
So Daniel, if you're doing that, that kind of solves the immediate problem.
there are lots of ways to structure things from there.
So that's all good.
Pat, I thought you said that the smalls ran out first?
It's hard to say.
My experience is like we often seem to run out of small helmets.
Maybe just get the same number of each.
Yeah, it's kind of an imprecise science.
This just said the recording stopped when Dennis left.
Oh, that's interesting.
He transferred.
He made me host.
So let me see if I can start this again, although it'll probably record to the wrong place.
Hopefully, as long as it's there, as long as it's somewhere, then it's good.
Recording in progress.
I'll get it where it needs to go.
Sorry about that, folks.
No worries.
OK, so do we need a motion to continue with that or are we good to go?
I don't I think we're I think we're OK to go if everybody's everybody's happy.
Okay, other announcements.
Yeah, so I had one thing I wanted to let the group know, I was approached by former Mayor Mike McGlynn, and he set up a meeting with myself, Emily john pre auto and jack Engelbert who is, I think the head of criterion developers.
And basically it was just to provide advice regarding a development that's going in at the former KISS 108 site on Mystic Valley Parkway.
That's right kind of in the corner of the Wellington T Station parking lot.
It's kind of where that funky modernish glass building and a couple antennae are located.
And that's going to be redeveloped.
At least the plan is to have them redevelop it to residential with some small retail, and they were just seeking advice, basically community input and one of the areas was.
regarding bicycle infrastructure, what they can do to help out the path that is going to be put in to help complete the Wellington Greenway, as well as other issues like access and parking, amenities for workers at the retail, amenities for the residents and so forth.
And I just want to let everybody know that Emily and I attended that meeting and provided our opinions based on our experience with the group and generally with the bicycling community.
So there's not really anything going on yet I don't even know if the project has yet been approved.
This is not the air rights possible project over the Wellington T station parking lot, but they did allude to it and we wanted to make sure that any, any things they do.
how do I want to say it, that they will coordinate well with any possible things that happen on the air rights as well.
So they're aware of it.
They're very, how would you say, Emily?
I think they were very interested in doing the right thing, basically.
They were interested.
They were receptive.
They wanted to make sure that the things that we thought that the things that they were trying to do in terms of bike access were the right things and were going to make things really work.
They wanted to make sure that whatever pathways they build connect to the other pathways so that you can get from one side to the other and access the building from the path as well as from the parking lot.
All the things that we want to see.
Yeah, we basically talked about mostly about access and.
wayfinding and stuff like that.
So for example, making sure you can get from Mystic Valley Parkway, whether you're on the bike lane or on the sidewalk, making sure that you can get from the trails up easily, that you don't have situations where you see something desirable, but have no clue how to get there.
You know, that happens so often where you'll be on a bike path and you see this great beer garden up on the cliff, right?
And you're like, okay, how do I get there?
And there's no clue, so you don't go.
Right.
Yeah.
Or you're in the Wellington parking lot and you see the bike path.
And you don't know how to get there.
Right.
Exactly.
Yeah.
So anyhow, I thought it was an interesting meeting.
I'm glad, I'm glad Mike McGlynn helped set it up.
And John Friato was there.
He's a great ally for paths and pedestrian access and bike access and all that stuff.
So I think it was interesting that the developer is reaching out, you know, and trying to get the ducks in a row before
You know how these things are always a little bit contentious.
So I thought that was a great move on their part to solicit information before they get too far down the path.
Yeah, I guess one other addition to that is I also took a bunch of photos of the bike path access getting from the one side of Route 16 over to the River's Edge area and kind of just the lack of signage that makes it that much more difficult even just to use the existing facilities.
And of course, this really is a DCR issue.
It's not them.
This is not on the developers property at all, but they abut it and they may have more reasons to be talking to DCR about access from Route 16 or MassDOT.
And they
They may be able to make more noise about that kind of thing than we can.
So, so I did send John Priattle a document with a list of photos and descriptions of here is the locations where it would be nice to have a sign telling you how to get where you're going, because
The thing that you need to get to is not actually in view at this spot.
And I can share that document with the group.
It's probably not anything anybody doesn't know.
And it's not a Medford Road.
But the city puts up those wayfinding signs on DCR roads.
Some of them.
And I think, I mean, I would also like to see DCR take a- I mean, I like to see DCR do lots of things, but I don't expect them to do anything.
So like, if we can get the city wayfinding signs put up.
So I can also share that page that I put together.
It's kind of, at the moment, it's a little bit quick and dirty because I just wanted to
It was sort of I had some extra time unexpectedly so I snapped some pictures and I put it together quick.
But I can also send it to the group.
And if it's something that Medford could put up some signs that would be great.
You know, in some cases they should go on the same sign posts that already have road signs on them, and that might not be.
that might not be a Medford signpost.
I don't know if they can just add another sign to that same post or not, if it's not there.
So- Like they put them up on, like, there's a wayfinding sign, you know, like at the crosswalk across Route 16.
I mean, I know, I don't mean like the printed Coroplast ones.
But like, why not?
Like.
Well, I know, but I think this, you know, I don't, in this case, like we really are talking, we're not talking about like giving you some bonus information.
Like this really is, this really is like a road sign and it should look like a road sign.
I mean, this is, you know, the Coroplast things, those are nice and I'm glad we have them, but this is, this needs, this needs real reflective metal signs.
Because I'd rather any signs than like, you know.
Yeah, but if it's, I mean, but again, the issue in this kind of place especially, if you put those zip-tied choroplast things up like that, they would not even be visible from where you need to see them.
Like it would, it just, you wouldn't, it wouldn't even, it wouldn't even do the job.
Yeah.
It would have the same problem that we already have.
In any case,
Um, we can, if we want to, if we want to discuss that further, we certainly can, or we can add that to another meeting.
This is, I mean, this is also, I put up, I put this together with this places that are only most immediately close to this site that they're talking about building this new development.
Um, but I can off the top of my head to think of,
eight other places where I could do the same exact thing.
Maybe we should, maybe that's a thing we should do.
We certainly have talked about it.
And this is a, you know, we all know this is an ongoing issue with all of these pathways.
And that could be something we could put together a working group to do, or we could, you know, each take a junction and do it.
So, I'd be happy to do some I biked through, I biked through there, about two hours ago, and there again you know next week, like, pretty early.
Well, if we, I mean if we want to put together a working group.
to start dealing with putting together recommendations for signage for some of these places, I think that would be great.
B. Dan, you and I could meet at some point and maybe just pick the locations that need it.
Even in this one area, this is what I did basically deals with
essentially one intersection.
And there are so many others that go on this list.
But I think that would be an incredibly cheap way to improve the usability of all the pathways that we have.
So B-Dan, let's get together sometime in the next month and do that.
Sounds good.
I also wanted to just add, before I forget, I didn't mention that John Pruodl is the main principal with the Rivers Edge development, in case people didn't know what that name was when I mentioned it.
In order of, I guess, protocol here, we still need to approve the minutes from January.
Oh, thank you.
Do we have a movement to approve the minutes from January?
Or from February.
You mean from our last meeting?
From our last meeting.
Which was actually the first week in March.
Yeah, sorry.
Second?
All in favor?
Aye.
Okay, minutes approved.
Thank you, Daniel.
Do we have any other announcements?
I'll take that as a no.
The next thing on the agenda, I wanted to make sure that we thank Amy Ingalls for all her hard work.
I thought that she was finished at the end of the month, and then I looked back at the email more closely, and she's finished already and not here.
But I still would like to thank her anyway.
And then we can write to her and tell her that we did.
I'd like to make a motion that we write such a letter to her to thank her.
Seconded.
And just sign it for her.
Great.
All in favor?
Aye.
Great.
I will write a letter thanking Amy.
And I'm really glad that we've had the time with her that we have.
She's been a big help and great to have such a great ally.
And I don't want to say I hope they replace her soon because of course you can't replace Amy, but I hope that her position is filled again soon and that we have an equally good person coming soon.
Next up, Winter Street.
Does anyone- I'm just pleased there's one possible announcement, which this was sent to the list, but there is a public forum on the Transform Medford Square tomorrow.
And it's not entirely clear to me what the biking.
Aspects of that will be, but certainly the Clippership connector will go right through it, so there might be some relevant things.
Well, that's that certainly is a good thing for us to know, and I mean Medford Square is certainly certainly could stand to be easier to bike through so.
I would definitely encourage all of us to attend that if you possibly can,
speak up in favor.
Thank you.
Next Winthrop Street updates.
I think this we're looking for Lily and you might as well.
We have additional infrastructure updates later on, but you might as well give us whatever you've got all at once.
Sure, happy to do it.
So the Winthrop Street, so the next phase of the Winthrop Street bike lanes was proposed at the last traffic commission meeting.
It was, I think it went generally okay.
There were a couple of criticisms and questions about a couple of key areas.
One of the main areas of focus was the Winthrop Circle itself and then whether all of the current sort of slip lanes and right turn lanes need to
be maintained and so.
There were a few questions there.
There were a couple of other concerns about parking, which is kind of typical.
So where things stand now, Amy, before she left, kind of made a few tweaks to the original plan.
And Todd has also kind of made a couple of changes.
And my understanding is that we're going to try to propose really essentially the same plan with maybe a couple little changes at the next traffic commission meeting.
So Todd and I are working on coming up with some new graphics and kind of seeing sort of how that goes.
So we will be doing that and hopefully the whole thing can get connected.
Shall I go ahead and just kind of give you the update on the rest of the updates?
Oh, yeah.
Sorry, Willie.
Could you share those updates with us before the traffic commission meeting?
Sure, I'll have to check with Todd, but I think we should be able to do that.
Okay, that'd be great.
Yeah, thank you.
Oh my gosh, the lights just went out.
I'm here in city hall and I think I'm the last person here and the lights are motion sensitive.
Anyway.
As far as other infrastructure updates, let's see.
The main and most exciting thing is that it's now going to be construction season again.
That's typically April to October.
We're going to have Eversource paint basically everything that's already been approved by traffic commission.
Phase 1 of Winthrop Street, which I think currently has just temporary markings, Mystic Ave, which Amy and I actually marked some of that in the fall, and also South Street.
And we also have, let's see, Main Street and George Street and College Ave.
There were some bike lanes that were already approved.
There's the need to be painted.
And this one I'm not familiar with, but evidently a portion of Salem Street, maybe there was a bike lane.
So that's on the list that Todd gave me.
I remember that being approved.
I didn't realize that was ever sourced that was going to paint it.
I think this might be the city painting that particular part.
But again, this season.
And then let's see, of course, blue bikes.
So this season, we're hoping to install four stations kind of concentrated in the eastern portion of the city.
So trying to fill in some of the gaps.
Oh, sorry.
Go ahead, Jared.
Oh no, I'm sorry I had a question about some of the bike lanes you you mentioned before.
Sure, go for it.
I recall that.
I think the plan was for George St between College and Maine involved repaving like the right most.
6 feet or something of that street on the South side.
Is that still in the works or something that's going to happen before the painting?
Or is that no longer happening?
That's a great question.
Todd did not mention it, but that definitely rings a bell, so I'll make a note to just ask him to clarify the kind of order of operations there, because I'm actually not sure.
OK, great, thank you.
But it would seem that that would make sense to kind of repay first before bothering to put paint down.
Yeah, although the north side is also pretty bad.
Yeah, that's true.
It got worse over the winter.
Yeah.
We're also working as an aside sort of the, there is a backlog of pothole requests and I am, I do have access now to see click fix.
So I'm trying to kind of coordinate the most dangerous ones from the list that you guys provided and we'll do everything we can to kind of bump them to the top of the list.
So there's, there's kind of a bit of a backlog right now, but we see them coming in.
I know that it's, I know that it seems like it's really, I don't like to make a pain of myself about every single individual pothole, but it is, there are some out there right now that are like imminently likely to get somebody hurt.
There's at least three on Boston Avenue between College Avenue and Ball Square coming down the hill.
And those are ones that those I mentioned, those have been, there's been requests going back six weeks.
There's like 10 requests on CTAs for that area.
And it's particularly bad because you come down the hill and there's the one giant hole that's in a rough area.
So it's fairly clear and everybody steers around it.
And the impatient person behind you kind of lets you steer around it.
But then they're like, okay, I let you pass that pothole, now get out of my way.
But then there's another one.
And it's not in a big roughed up patch.
So it's sort of, it would be,
It's all too easy to imagine somebody missing the second one.
Or not missing the second one as the case may be.
But it's, you know, it's definitely one of those things that it's been a long time and it's pretty urgent.
Definitely.
And we do appreciate hearing about these because, you know, it's funny, I actually ride that particular stretch of road all the time.
And I know there's one that I think has been there for at least two years that's just gotten bigger.
So it's kind of one of those, yeah, it's a big problem.
Like, how do I ride this every day?
And still it's like part of the landscape now, but that's not acceptable.
So yeah.
And I also, you know, I hope that we can eventually, um, you know, if there's a thing on C click fix and multiple and somebody says, this is a danger to cyclists, this is going to get somebody hurt.
You know, I would like it to not require.
One of us who knows the right person to contact to be the way that it gets fixed.
You know, we don't necessarily go on every single road in Medford every week.
There's a small number of us.
We go to places that we go.
We get around a lot, but there might well be places where there's a really dangerous pothole that none of us thought to say anything about, but somebody did put it up on C-Click Fix.
So hopefully.
Hopefully that can happen a little faster, at least for the ones that are really dangerous.
So but yeah, I do keep reporting them.
It does make a difference and we keep track of all of these things.
Like there's a sort of internal spreadsheet that Amy started that kind of keeps a running list of ongoing concerns.
So we kind of know where to target our interventions.
Great, thank you.
Did you have other?
Where you finished with updates are you still sure I'm going to have.
Yeah, I think there's, let's see, I think the last thing I wanted to mention was the blue bikes expansion.
So, the next sort of phase of that will include four stations kind of mostly kind of geared towards the eastern part.
of the city we have some kind of provisional locations but nothing has been finalized but really they're meant to kind of connect the three existing stations with the one that is at Wellington station so to kind of fill in that gap.
And then later, and these are this would be a I think it's our mass gaming commission grants.
And then later in the season we hope to follow up with three more stations using the Community Connections grant and for those we have they're kind of sprinkled around but we do hope to sort of expand to the west to start to like make movements towards West Medford and kind of
fill in there.
And we're still, I think there's like a bit of a hang up with the ones we're arranging through Tufts since they're a private sponsor.
And I think there's some contract issues there, but we're hoping that those can come online in a sort of synergy with the others so that we have this like outward expansion to kind of keep the network moving.
Sarah Silver, PB – she, her, hers): And I think I probably the last update is the bike plan update so we're still kind of working on that there's a at this point there's like a pretty final draft that just really needs to be reviewed and approved by you know.
DPW and like whoever is higher up at the city that can kind of sign off on this.
But my goal, one of the things I've been working on is to kind of create a public input map and to kind of create some engagement materials to kind of start setting up some outreach.
So once we're ready to kind of push this out publicly, we'll have some ways to engage with folks, folks who bike and folks who don't.
And so in subsequent months, you know, in coming months, I'll probably be engaging more with you guys for ideas and help on how to really reach people about this.
That's great.
Thank you.
We're really excited about that.
I know we ask this every time, but do you know anything about the Clippership Connector?
I'm afraid I don't, but the minute that I do and the minute we have anything official, I will send you guys an email because it's probably the number one question that I get.
Yeah, I'm sure.
It's the number one question we get.
Anytime we have a stand anywhere, people just come up to me and go, wait a second, what is that happening?
And we're like, yeah, well, we wish we knew too.
Yeah, run into, stop at a red light and there's another cyclist.
Oh, you've got a bike helmet, Lon.
Do you know anything about the Clippership Connector?
I'm glad people are talking about it.
Yeah.
But we hope to have it shovels in the ground soon.
Well, we hope so too.
Thank you.
All right.
One more thing.
I didn't want to forget this, but Amy's job has just been posted, so hopefully we'll start getting some good applications for traffic engineers with experience in bike and pedestrian planning.
That's great.
Fingers crossed.
Awesome.
And let's see, bike to school day.
I think I mostly covered that.
But Wednesday, May 4th.
And I hope that we don't need to be too concerned about this yet, but I hope that lots of y'all will be.
available to help lead caravans from various places to various places.
It's going to more schools now, so from more places.
So that means it probably will need more ride leaders to coordinate more groups.
The one in the fall, we had basically four caravans and they each had kind of a couple different stops.
And this time we'll have more destinations with
at least as many and possibly more starting places.
So we'll definitely need the volunteers then, Jared.
Sorry, when is that, the bike to school day?
Wednesday, May 4th.
The 4th is a Thursday.
It is, or May 3rd then.
There was some back and forth in the email.
So it is whatever the Wednesday is.
I think I may have read it and misread and mistyped because there were some corrections in the email that I was copying it from.
Gotcha.
If I'm available, I'd like I'd like to help with that.
Yeah, look forward to hearing a bit more about it.
And looks like Pat has just said his goodbyes.
Thanks, Pat.
Now that he's gone, he can't hear us.
So yeah, so that's Bike to School Day.
And if you're also interested in helping to get the word out about that, you can also get in touch with Ellery Klein.
I think everybody here knows who that is, but if you don't, get in touch with me.
Next up, bike lights.
Ernie?
Ernie has disappeared.
Jared?
Wait, I'm sorry.
I feel like I keep dragging us back to previous things.
But the bike to school day, I'm wondering is there more we can do on that, essentially?
It feels like that would be something that
Yeah, I mean, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I,
One thing that I think we could do if we had those contacts and if we had interested people at the schools who were interested kids, one thing that could be a good pre-event is to have a Sunday ride that goes from all these various points to the schools.
You know, a Sunday, Sunday morning, mid morning, midday ride that you know a loop around Medford and you can start and stop it wherever you want.
That shows you how to how to get to school when it's not
a school day and you're not on a school schedule and that could be a fun thing to do.
Maybe kind of demystify the whole idea, show people that it's actually not very far.
Trying to get kids to go to school on a Sunday might be a little... Oh, and they don't actually have to go in.
They can just, you know, ride by and wave and be like, ha ha, I don't have to go there today.
Yeah, I guess, I guess I'm thinking maybe, you know, I can reach out to Ellery about this, but I guess I'd like official bike commission sanctioning for us to maybe do more to help her with the planning and participate and advertise and market and whatnot.
Yeah, that we could contact the principals and get in touch with the PTOs who might be helpful, depending upon what their bent is on having their kids bike to school.
a lot of work.
I'm not saying that I can do all that, but you know, it's one avenue that we could get a little bit of publicity going and maybe they could make it a school event as well as this outside event that's occurring and get us involved.
It would help the parents understand that, you know, we're here to help.
It would maybe demystify, like you said, the way to do this and just get some hype about it.
So that's one idea that we could possibly do to get more involved in this.
Well, I don't mind doing some of that.
I don't necessarily want to commit to doing all of it.
But I can certainly start by trying to do that at the high school.
I have contacted some other groups and students at the high school who kind of liked the idea but didn't actually want to do particularly much on their own.
So that's another avenue to try.
But if somebody else wants to do the same at one of the other schools or multiple of the other schools, there aren't that many.
I can approach the Brooks School.
That's something I can take on.
If maybe we can get some other people to commit to the other five school, well, with five in the high school.
There's two elementary, one middle, and one high, right?
There's, I'll enumerate them, the Roberts, what used to be the Columbus, is that a Sagamore school now?
Missituck.
That's right, Missituck.
The Misitech, the Roberts, the McGlynn School, which is also part of the McGlynn Middle School, the Andrews Middle School, and I already mentioned the Brooks, and then the high school.
I think that's all.
And maybe there could be some additional buildings that are still used.
I don't know if the Tufts School is still used at this point, but that was one that in the past had been used.
And there was also a smaller school building
up in Fulton Heights that I think may have been redeveloped.
But again, I'm not certain of that.
So those are some ideas that we could look into.
Certainly the main schools, for sure.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's great.
Does some does anybody else want to tell you what I'll take?
I'll take that on to recruit other people to get in touch.
OK, I'll do the Brooks and then I'll snag other people to OK with the other schools.
I can reach out to Ellery as well and see what legwork she's done already for some of that stuff.
Maybe not sure what she what she hasn't done.
Ernie?
Maybe I should segue here to the bike lights thing.
Bruce, if you're gonna spearhead that, I'd like to get maybe a couple dozen bike lights kits to you or Ellery for that event, as she had distributed some last year.
Not too many, I got, I think, half of them back, but I think a couple dozen is probably a good idea.
All these kids going to school should be properly lit
It's the perfect opportunity to get lights on bikes rather than just hand them out to them loosely.
And if I could take that opportunity to segue to the chairperson.
So let's do this backwards.
I am going to be out of state the second week of April into the third.
And then back for only three days and then taking a bucket list trip to Croatia for three weeks.
So I'm going to miss the next meeting.
But it, the, there was some nice
I think opportunities to feed the bike lights distribution this spring in a cogent format.
So I've got a hundred lights distributed to the five schools last week and the week before and telling them that they would, for the spring use, telling them that there would be a big push in late May for the summer.
when I get back and we'll be able to resume this.
In the meantime, the last shipment for this fiscal year ending this June arrived.
So there are 240 light kits there, some of which have been given out as that 100, but it leaves about 200 or so
to give out in late May for the summer season.
I have not been able to come up with other sponsors, but decided to double dip.
And so contacted Brookline Bank again and couldn't get them up to $1,000, but I got them to renew their $500
contribution of last year, and I'm hoping it's going to be a recurring contribution.
I'm hoping that in the meantime, maybe, well, not in time for this bike to school thing, but certainly by late May, they will get me more swag.
Maybe it's those wonderful yellow highlighter pens they provided last year, so that their contribution will be reciprocated by sending parents and kids their swag in late May.
conclude the bike lights program for this fiscal year, at which point I will collect receipts and hope to get repaid by the city, oh, within six, seven years.
That's the way it's going.
Because part of, if you're ever doing this for any other events and you're seeking contributions,
organizations require that checks be made out to the city.
So you have to turn them over to the city and then hope to be reimbursed.
And I guess it's going to work out in the long run.
So that's what's going to happen in late May, I will be back and
will help do a major 200-light distribution to the five schools to cover the summer.
And depending on what happens this summer, we'll revisit this topic in, I guess, an August meeting, again, to see what needs will be for the fall, depending upon how this goes.
Now that I'm about to be remunerated for 2022, I feel like this should continue without too much risk to my pocketbook, which is, you know, down about $3,000 with this.
I don't see a lot of kids running around with the bike lights, but they are on bikes.
Principal and vice principals that I saw last week at the schools were grateful and saying, oh, yes, thank you.
It's a week, you know, we want more, etc.
I didn't get to talk about an adjunct program with bike helmets.
Because considering, you know, my accident last August.
I'm sort of the
a principal show and tell guy for a survivor with a cracked helmet for that in the future.
But I'm sort of not up to it.
I'm still in PT to be able to walk correctly.
I haven't been on a bike since August.
So I'm just going to, for now, continue the bike light program and see how things go this summer.
So I won't see you at the next meeting, but I will see you in May.
And maybe in the meantime, if I need some help distributing these lights, I'll be in contact by email.
So I think that's what I have.
Great.
Thank you for doing all that, Ernie.
That's really great.
Do you know if the school principals have a stash so that if there's a kid who
You know, it's, they're going home, so that if a kid is going home later and they go, oh crap, I forgot my light today, or oh, my light battery is dead.
I don't know quite where they put these or whether they have little raffles going on, or they tell all the teachers who know kids who ride bikes, et cetera.
They managed to use them up.
And, um,
that's well and good.
On a small technical note, the shipment arrived a couple weeks ago and it was only half the size of normal and I thought the rest of it was lost in the shipping.
near Singapore, but it turns out they got smart and put two lights in one box.
They cut their packaging in half in their shipping, which is very smart.
So the bike lights kit is a little bit smaller looking and with different graphics from the city, as you'll see, because we don't have that lovely four color.
Medford community card anymore.
Those are all used those are history.
Those are used up, but they have something similar with decent graph, you know, I'll just show you 10 seconds.
So here.
So the bike light kit now has two lights in one box, including two straps and two charger.
You know, we're not getting skimped.
Room for decals and for possible swag, like a pen or something.
On the back, this is what the city has.
And it can fold up, it's a big card.
It can fold up into two ways.
You guys wanna vote on which you think is better?
One of them has the word, it's important that it has Medford on it to know what this is.
One of them says Medford twice and invites you to look past the overlap two messages.
And the other one is, you know, unified prose, also with a picture of a kid on a bike.
So these are the two ways to fold the insert that's provided by the city.
I like seeing the picture of a kid on a bike.
This one?
Yeah.
Okay.
I kind of like this one because it invites you to peek behind the fold and actually read what's being said.
But I don't have a strong preference.
We could do half of each and let people pick the one that appeals to them more.
I could just fold them in the dark and they come out the way they come out.
Okay.
Thank you.
That's brilliant, Vivian.
I like that.
All right, so that's it.
They look a little smaller, simpler bags, but smarter than to cut their postage in half.
But someone asked, when are they going to charge us more?
Well, this was their way of economizing.
Yeah, now it takes you one less step to put everything into the bag.
So that's even better.
It's actually a little harder because I'm using a smaller bag and the cardboard just, you know what it is.
Okay, thank you, folks.
Well, thank you.
Thank you for doing all that.
That's, that's really great.
Next, I think this is our last item for the day, is new member recruitment.
They have had the notice up on the city website for a while, and I just hadn't heard anything.
So I got in touch with Lisa Coliani yesterday or the day before, and she sent me some resumes that they've gotten, but she didn't send me any cover letters or anything else.
So it's sort of a random list of resumes.
And then she also said, oh, and we're going to make sure we announce it next week.
So I guess that means she's expecting to have some other applications next week.
And I will also get back in touch with her and say, did these people send anything other than their resume, since that doesn't, for our purposes, that's nice, but it's not necessarily that
Most of what's on a resume is not that relevant.
So I'd like to get a little bit more and I'm sure they have it and it just didn't come through in the same files or something like that.
So that's where we are.
If there's
And we have a fair number of available slots, but we do have, there are some applicants too, so I don't think we're gonna be, I don't think we're gonna be like struggling to, either struggling to fill our spaces or hopefully we'll, you know, we'll be able to take the ones that we want.
I think the last time, because we didn't feel that it was appropriate to,
Discuss all the applications live in a meeting and we are not allowed to discuss things like that.
Anywhere else?
I think Jared.
Looked through all of the one all of the applications and made his recommendations.
And that's what happened.
Is that right, Jared?
Yep, yep, that's right.
So unless somebody tells me differently, I assume that I will do that this time.
I will say thank you to Noah for showing up, basically showing up to half the battle.
Yeah.
So that's appreciated.
Yeah, definitely.
Definitely.
Yeah, happy to make it.
Yeah.
To your point, Emily, I think we should make it, should be standardized that we pass judgment on any applicant so that we can't
we're never put in a position of just accepting what a mayor wants to throw at us through their vetting, which was the last time when Jared was the chair at the time, and he did pass judgment and he did make recommendations.
It wasn't just they weren't just throwing somebody that is that pro forma is or is that just because that's how it happened.
Don't we rate the candidates to our
Well, we didn't, it was, we can't, we can't deliberate when we're not in a public, we can't deliberate not in a public meeting.
Yeah, I heard what you said.
We didn't want to air everything in a public meeting, so.
In theory, we could go into executive session.
I'm not quite sure how that works with the government access and
elsewhere, I mean, whatever, but yeah, that would be an executive session kind of thing to discuss personnel, which, you know, this would be about.
On the other hand, if we just provide individual vetting and, or if the chair provides vetting and recommendations, that's probably as accurate as we need to be anyway, it'd be my guess.
Yeah, I think so.
But if anyone has
input or things that you think are particularly important, you know, certainly let me know.
Noam, since you're here, if you want to say anything about your particular interests or what, you know, why you decided to show up tonight, we're happy that you're here.
Oh, definitely.
Well, certainly it was suggested, you know, this is happening, and I have an interest overall, but
I've lived in Medford for more than 10 years now and in the region for more than half my life.
So I've been commuting by bike that entire time and kind of take a look at things from that perspective or sort of see that being a really vital aspect of a vibrant Medford is the ability to get around safely.
So aside from that, I also am like an avid recreational cyclist and enjoy going on a lot of rides
making the most of what Massachusetts has to offer as well.
So I see both sides of it there.
And as a parent with a kid in the school district, I also have concerns there.
And I know it was sort of joked about earlier, but I too am keen on knowing what's going on with the Clippership Connector and how it will resolve kind of the missing link for my six-year-old's future commute to middle school.
It does seem like a really critical link.
And then with all of the development that is going on in the city,
and all of the RFPs and things, and what's happening very quickly brings, I think, a further kind of interest of mine in ensuring that there's sort of equitable access to safe non-vehicle or non-motorized vehicle modes of getting around our kind of really small city at the end of the day.
You can get across Medford a lot quicker on a bike and then connect to other communities really quickly.
and get to downtown Boston if you need to.
So that's also an aspect of the city that perhaps could be better marketed if we had better infrastructure to support it.
So I guess that's my kind of ad hoc speech.
But let me know if there's any questions.
other things that you guys are interested in.
We have a tradition of allowing people who aren't yet members to volunteer to help us out.
So if you don't mind, maybe I can tap you for whatever school your children are or child is attending.
Yeah, definitely.
You don't need to tell me about that now.
We can we can chat offline, but perhaps if you would send what's the best way to get your contact information, maybe send to
Jared, who's our secretary, and then he can send it to me.
Daniel is the secretary.
Oh, I'm sorry, Daniel is.
Yeah, I think Daniel has my contact info.
Sorry.
From an earlier thread, but I'm a parent at the Brooks, but I'm happy to assist and also, you know, participate physically in parades and whatnot.
So, yeah, Daniel, if you don't mind connecting us, I'm all yours.
That's great.
And actually that goes for other visitors here too.
We've always, we welcome any volunteer help whether you're a member of the commission or not whether you have any intention of becoming a member or not.
We really appreciate the help, and that goes for things like Circle the Square or any of the events that we do.
I know that, I think, Caitlin, you've been at a number of our meetings by now, so you've kind of seen what's going on here, too.
So anybody is always welcome to step up and help, and especially with something like Bike to School Day, where we will need a bunch of ride leaders from a bunch of places.
And probably more than more than we have bodies of our own.
So that's, that's really helpful.
Since we are doing this, Caitlin or Janine, do you have anything to add, since you're here?
I do not, thank you.
Well, thank you.
Does anyone else have anything?
I think this is the end of our agenda for today.
Am I missing anything?
Emily, I'm sorry I stepped away for a moment.
Small kids, but the the timing of the applications for joining the NBAC that that's just an open ended thing.
Or were you closing that?
I am not.
So I contacted Lisa about it and she said, oh, and I'm going to make sure to announce it next week.
And I wasn't entirely clear on where that was, but it was also next week and after this meeting.
Sorry, announce what exactly?
that we're accepting applications.
So I don't entirely.
A re-announcement then, right?
It's already on the.
It's already up there.
It's been up there for a while.
Yeah.
And so I contacted her to say, hey, what's going on with this?
So I will get back in touch with her and say, we do have some applicants now.
And by all means, keep announcing.
But maybe we should.
Maybe we should pick some and pick some and be done.
I mean, I don't, I also, maybe this is another thing we could discuss.
I don't have a, I don't see a particular reason why we couldn't accept new members on a rolling basis.
If people resign on a rolling basis, attrition happens at the rate that it happens.
I don't, you know, maybe it's more work for somebody in the mayor's office to appoint new commission members to things.
But as far as I'm concerned, I don't see any reason why we couldn't just keep it open
you know, whenever, and when we start losing some, then we can add more.
Yeah, I'm in full agreement with that.
And if that means our commission size has a large beta from small to maybe perhaps very large, that's okay.
Over a long period of time, I think the rolling admissions makes a whole lot of sense.
Yeah, I mean, we have, you know, since we'll tend to like wait till we get down to a certain amount and then start looking for some new people, we end up getting fairly small.
And then all of a sudden we're pretty big again, and we have a bunch of new people.
So maybe it does make sense to do.
It's probably worth checking with the mayor just to see what she wants to do about that.
It sounds like a good idea to just touch base with her to see the, you know, her thoughts on it.
Yeah.
Okay.
So I will check in with that.
and see what they say.
Yeah, I was going to say last time around, I remember us kind of approaching it from the perspective of like every year we just needed to kind of re-up and re-announce openings and things just to make sure that we, you know, dealt with the attrition and whatnot.
Yeah.
And it has been, I guess, about a year, right?
Yeah, I think it's been around that.
Yeah.
So I think the main thing we want to do if we're doing rolling is to sort of make it clear to people what the schedule is for us examining or, or recommending, or, you know, the mayor, you know, just like, so people aren't like submitting an application and then being like, well, I have no idea when this is going to be acted on or not.
And then eight months later, somebody is like, Oh, remember that?
You're appointed.
Yeah.
Without getting too formal about it we could try to aim for some kind of quarterly publicity marker.
or invitation or blast so that people know that it's not an annual thing.
And that'll smooth out the ripples, the big ripple.
Well, I'll contact the, I will write back and see what they say about doing kind of filling openings on a more rolling basis or on a more frequent basis.
The other thing is we can always, which I think we do, but maybe we can say this more loudly and in more places,
There's anyone who wants to attend our meetings is always welcome.
And you're always welcome to speak up and say your piece and propose something you want to do.
Contact us to get it on the agenda if there's something you have in mind.
You can't formally vote on something if you're not a commissioner, but everything else you can still participate in, you can still do.
And we're happy to have that.
We're happy for people to do that.
And as far as voting on things goes, I'm not sure that we've ever not been unanimous anyway.
So for all practical purposes, come and join us and speak up.
And we want to hear from you.
So we can also make sure that we say that every chance we get.
It's an exciting place to be.
Oh, yeah.
Do we have anything else?
I'll repost some of my social media messages about participation and joining the NBAC as well.
I know that did trigger a handful of applications, at least.
Yeah, and if you do that, I will, if you post something, then I will definitely share it and spread it.
I never thought of this before.
Should I include a little insert in the bike lights kits to the parents, custodians?
Can't hurt.
Yeah, I hadn't thought of that, but that might be a good way, of course, to get a parent involved.
Yeah.
Even if it's just come to our meetings, say your piece, speak up, be heard.
Like I think just at minimum, just like
The bicycle commission exists and typically meets, you know, if you're interested in biking in Medford, come for meetings.
Yeah, like.
Yeah.
I'll work on that for the late May.
Big, big distribution.
Good.
Yeah, that's great.
Okay.
Thanks.
All right.
Move to adjourn.
Seconded.
All in favor.
Aye.
All right, thank you, everybody.
Have a good night.