This one is heavy Hi guys, Anatoly here, 32kg gym up here And it's new part of video where I pretend to be a cleaner in the gym.
So let's just change the uniform and
guys i'm pretty sure you will enjoy this video let's get started i'm sorry this is for arms is it okay we will do like one by one just one set it's okay no worries about this like we'll be like one by one i will be fast guys i will be fast my dream is same big arms
Is it okay like, sorry, next set we'll do together?
You and me?
Yeah, like same time.
I don't know the technique.
Sorry, guys.
Just one question.
Why do you use fake weights?
Plates not plates.
I mean like this is the plastic Guys is it?
Okay.
I will do with you I don't know like usually I didn't count like weights.
I just do it like I
The bar?
Like this?
I don't want to say to anyone, but I just see it looks like... I mean... There is like water or plastic?
Just try it yourself.
Like this?
But what if dumbbell will break the... No, no, no, not too far.
What's happening guys?
What's serious?
What they give me permission to do?
Nothing beats a jetty holiday.
I'm like even music.
Nice.
I'm ready, like, YouTube.
Yeah?
Okay.
Something like... I don't know, like... Honestly, like, just for me, it looks like... Like, not that real.
I don't know, like... Let me just hold them up, I will try.
Okay?
I usually do this lift, like this one.
So, like this, and then like... What do you mean?
You mean like, this is the... Just hold them up, please.
No, this is the real.
You're joking or not, but can I do this hand, please?
Guys, it's okay, because you look at me like... I'll be just one hand and then I'll go.
But if you hurt yourself, we are not responsible.
Hurt what?
If you want her back.
It's already broken.
Okay, bro.
Careful, huh?
is heavy but you tell me this one I mean this is like real or this is like a regular industrial map guys
Who is this warm-up?
This is your friend?
Or warm-up is someone?
No, no, it's fine.
It's fine.
Yeah!
For back what?
You mean with the fake weights, something happen at his back?
I'm gonna lift quick.
Just a moment, sorry.
Sorry, sorry.
Guys, just one sec.
What I'm talking about like see it's like jumping this is like jumping
with two pieces is much easier like this is correct or I'm real but the weight is not real but it feels like not that heavy like I don't know what do you mean like this what I show you like this technique
I do it at home, yes.
This is prank, yes?
You use like fake weights and... No, I'm not cheating.
You put me with the mob of 50 people.
50?
Guys, it's like regular map.
You are like joking like on a prank here or something.
Guys.
I'll do like this one.
This is like good.
If you want, you can try with the map as well.
Yeah, just try it.
They give me this map and they tell me, like, it's heavy, but you're gonna get stronger.
Who is this joke?
I have today, like, a really hard day, that's why I'm not laughing, but it's funny, nice, guys.
It's nice.
I will take it, it's okay.
That's why sometimes I have to do some exercise.
Like this, the same exercise.
if you need any help if you need any help here guys just let me know I mean I don't think like I'm just I know it's not
I cannot be like, guys, see like, this is like jumping.
Have a good workout.
Just like regular, like day.
I'm just like mapping.
I really appreciate trainer.
Thank you very much.
A year ago we did a social experiment.
We gathered 700 people from all over the world and the next 4 weeks all of them followed a training periodization method and a high collagen diet.
This was just 3 workouts per week, maximum 1-1.5 hour per session.
And after 30 days the results shocked even myself.
I even felt like it's fake to be able to do this in 30 days.
But I got all of the proofs in pictures and even the videos before and after.
And this was the Anatoly Challenge.
Guys, please, don't do all of these basic arms or calves workout.
You just get a pump, look at the mirror, looks nice.
But then 40 minutes after your workout, you look the same.
The rules is very simple.
Do only things which gets you closer to the progress.
Adjust the load, I mean your training periodization now.
Avoid overtraining, it's a really big problem in the industry.
And please, do exercises which really shock your body and increase, of course, your hormones and anabolism.
That's what, guys, honestly, I am personally doing to be Anatoly.
And more than 45,000 people already tried this.
And the results speak for themselves right now, right here on the screen.
Guys, I'm really proud to say that the link to join my training program will be in the description below.
So see you in the gym, be smart and stay strong.
See you.
Abs.
Sorry How much sets guys you have here?
3 sets Biceps For biceps?
Looking great man Do you have a trainer or something like this?
If you want like I will be like your trainer
I'm just joking.
Is it okay if I do it with you?
Why are you laughing?
No, no, don't worry.
If you want to try, then try.
I will join because you have three more sets and they're like... Yeah, yeah, if you want to try.
Yeah?
Okay.
Okay, I'll just clean here a little bit.
Can you like maybe show me some like technique or... So you want to go there?
That side?
Where?
The leg weight?
You don't understand me.
If I want the same biceps like yours, I should do the same weight or... You can do it.
but if i'll do like bait like i will be same like a girl looks like sometimes i'm doing exercising something like this but like i don't know i'm doing like like this i mean the real thing that's what i'm asking like can you just hold it
Why are you like... This is what I'm talking about.
I'm doing like this always, like, for biceps, like this.
You can hold it.
I am, like, never been with a girl, like, too close.
It's always here some men and, like, you are here like flowers.
I'm sorry for this.
Like, by the chance, maybe I will show you something better for the apps.
I know some exercises, like, very good.
Okay, guys, I will be just fast.
You don't believe, like... But I do like... I do like...
Great.
I have like super set.
So is it like something like this or... Or I should take something like heavier.
I don't like now.
Doctor from my home country, he tells me like this is not good.
This is some problem like...
place I'm doing this exercise like this like this one this is much much better for her yes you mean I should take something bigger or can you give me them up please
What?
What happened?
Okay, this is like three by three.
My trainer told me this.
You mean still lightweight?
Sorry guys, if something went wrong.
Okay, I will come then.
Trainer?
This is my trainer, Samantha.
I mean, try it.
You can try it.
This is like Samantha.
200 grams, I don't know.
Are you sure?
Try it.
You're joking, right?
But you like laughing.
By the way, this is my girlfriend.
She's my trainer's girlfriend and in general, this is my love.
Like this?
I don't know, like, every day they give me this map five years ago.
If you need, like, any cleaning, just let me know.
And enjoy.
Enjoy, guys.
You are nice.
Thank you.
I will just take this.
I should do bigger, yes.
Thank you.
Yes, if you need any help or something, just let me know.
Okay.
Any apps for Kappa?
Yeah.
So guys, hope you enjoyed this video, don't forget about likes, don't forget about comments, and of course, don't forget to subscribe to that channel, because our goal is 10 millions, and hope we will make it this year.
And guys, when we will make 100,000 likes on this video, by the way, I will upload new part with the heaviest map and with a big weight, so don't forget about the likes, and see you in the next video.
Let's go!