Welcome to the 8th edition of the Mustang Report. We'll be showing you highlights of the boys' soccer game. We will be visiting the Mustang Mall. We're going to be talking to Senor Scorker about his D.C. trip.
make sure to come to The Hollow by Agatha Christie.
Woo! Yeah! Yeah! Yeah!
I got chills. I got chills everywhere. It's Rozzy in her.
I want to be here to recognize the great achievements Ashley has been involved in in her career here at the high school. She's certainly been a leader that has pulled a lot of people together. She has helped to blaze trails for kids who will come after and people who see what a great team that we've had for the last few years up here would want to get involved.
Hi, I'm Cheyenne Payne and I'm here with the Mustang Report. I'm here in the main lobby here to interview Mr. Dennis Robinson. So, first question, what are your responsibilities here at MHS? Well, my responsibility is basically security for the building, but I also act like its host. This is a large building, people can get lost, so I'm able to give them directions as to where they need to go. How do you like your job and why?
I like my job because it's greeting people. I'm a person who likes to talk to people from different walks of life, different subjects, and I get to do that while I'm here. What about your favorite sandwich? My favorite sandwich would be chicken salad or tuna salad, not peanut butter and jelly though. I eat it at home, but I just don't eat it in public because Mr.
Dempsey and I have a controversy over peanut butter and jelly sandwich being a child fare but not the mature fare. Hi, I'm Katrina Rasche and I am here with Renee Stoudy, our faculty football expert. And we are going to be talking about the Eric Rezani faculty football game happening next Friday, November 20th at 6.30 p.m. I will be saying some of the participants' names and Renee, you will be saying the first thing that comes to your head. So the truth. The truth, yes, the truth.
So, Mr. Wilson. Oh, he used to be in the I.F.L. and then he left the I.F.L. to play in our faculty football games here at M.H.S. Mr. Rudowsky. He was an amazing quarterback. He played for the University of Alabama and he was offered the group at Packers, but no, we got him instead. Mr. Tucci. What would you do if you were up against Mr. Tucci? If I was up against Mr. Tucci, I would probably run the other way. Yeah, me too. Dr. Perrella.
Dr. P, let's see, he was, he was a lot of things. He played soccer, he coached football in college at University of Alabama also. So he coached our players. Now he's playing with them. Dr. Perella has had a football trainer for the past few weeks and he's doing really well. By few weeks, you mean few months in this. How about Ms. Glasser? Ms. Glasser will watch out for that one. This is gonna be a force to be reckoned with.
How about Ms. Bowler? Ms. Bowler, I heard she tackles students in the main office. That's where she gets her practice for tackling. What are you guys most excited for about this faculty football game? I would have to say to see Mr. Drozdowski going down-ski. I'm most excited about seeing Eric Ferrazani in the stands. You know, cheering us on as a faculty, rooting us on, having a good time, and raising some money for awesome cars and an awesome family. And we very much look forward to seeing Eric.
and also compete against each other as a faculty. How into it all the teachers are going to get? There's some pretty good rivalries going on. Well, I enjoy watching Mr. Drozdowski suffer. You know, he suffers in a very Shakespearean way. It's dramatic, but it's also powerful. And I can see the fear, the anger, the depression in his face, and for some reason that really
kind of interests me. So I guess I'm most interested in seeing how Drowski deals with another loss. Breaking news! It has just been informed to us that there is going to be a draft next Tuesday night. So none of the teams are going to be the same. Watch out Medford High.