Hey Medford, I just want to jump on here and have a quick conversation with you like I did last week about my candidacy and why this campaign is unique.
One of the best questions I've been getting on the campaign trail is what makes you unique.
Why should I vote for you for school committee?
Well, before I answer that question, I want you to know that I love both collaborating and the creative outcomes that are possible when you are working with a diverse team.
And there's lots of strengths and a wide range of skills and experiences
in the incumbents and the other candidates running for school committee.
What I bring that is unique is that I am the only candidate with the lived experience of being a recent graduate who understands the challenges of being the diversity in the room.
I am attuned to what's happening in the halls, on the buses, on the athletic fields, on the river, in the parking lots, and even in the bathrooms of the Medford schools, including as a person of color.
I also, as a community liaison for the city of Medford, in the midst of the pandemic, have had direct experience gathering and listening to immigrants and communities of color about their hopes and their dreams, their wants and their needs.
I know their experience personally.
I'm the candidate who has worked one-on-one with at-risk youth in the Boston public school system.
I had the privilege of working as their advocate and their mentor when serving as a City Year AmeriCorps member.
And I am the candidate who researched the impact of subconscious bias in the classroom for my senior thesis as a political science major.
Finally, I am and have always been a social justice advocate who's called to public service now and for the long haul.
I want to serve our city as a member of the Medford School Committee because representation does truly matter.
I ask for your support and your vote this coming November 7th.
If you would like to learn more about our platform, talk to me directly, or help with the campaign in any way, please check out our website at electaaronolopate.com and join us at one of our upcoming campaign events.
Thank you so much.