Hello, my name is Nick Tucci, and I'm the principal of the John J. McGlynn Middle School.
Back in the spring of 2018, I proudly accepted the position of principal at the McGlynn Middle School.
And ever since, I've been honored to be a part of a school that has a rich tradition of nurturing young people to reach their full potential as learners through a philosophy of the education of the whole child.
As the principal of the school, I very much enjoyed the role as the educational leader of the McGlynn Middle School community while working with such a talented and diverse group of students.
I've also relished the opportunity to work with the talented and dedicated staff at the McGlynn to offer the best possible education to our students.
I'm a proud product of the city of Medford, having graduated from Medford High School.
I possess a master's degree in educational psychology and a bachelor's degree in history from the University of Connecticut.
Over the course of the past 17 years, I have served as a principal, assistant principal, teacher, varsity coach, and club advisor at several schools.
These opportunities and awesome responsibilities have enabled me to grow as an educator.
The most important things that you need to know about me as a school leader are as follows.
First, I genuinely care deeply about the students of Medford.
I will work diligently to establish relationships with students.
Second, I respect and value the work that teachers do in the classroom every day.
A teacher's impact in the life of a student is profound and powerful.
Third, I stand up for what I believe is right.
And finally, I will lead by example and trust that my strong dedication and positive attitude will exude to the point where it reflects in others.
Now, the McGlynn Middle School offers a full complement of academic course offerings.
For instance, students will attend core academic courses, such as mathematics, English language arts, science, and social studies.
Students are also afforded the opportunity to explore unified arts classes throughout the school year, such as engineering, art, general music, computer applications, physical education, wellness, and guidance.
Students may also select to take one of the following world language classes, French, Spanish, or Italian.
Students may also like to have band or orchestra built into their schedule to enable them the opportunity to develop and showcase their musical talents.
One of my biggest suggestions for a student entering into the McGlynn Middle School is to get involved into the life of the school by joining an after school club, activity, or sport.
In fact, the AMS and MMS share clubs, activities, and sports.
And on Tuesdays, Wednesdays, and Thursdays, we offer a full complement of clubs and activities after school, such as chess club, art club, GSA, volleyball club, yearbook club, CCSR, drama club, culture and diversity club, and a relatively new Tufts University partnership, where students are bused onto the Tufts University campus for STEM, art, and tutoring opportunities a few times each week.
In addition to the full complement of clubs and activities that we offer, we offer middle school sports where we compete in the Greater Boston League against the likes of Malden, Everett, Revere, Chelsea, and Somerville.
Please know that as a student at the McGlynn Middle School, you'll be coming to a community of learners where you will be supported and challenged to strive toward your goals and grow as a learner and as a person.
Thanks for listening, and go Mustangs.