Hello, everyone, and welcome to Medford Happenings, a show far and about the city of Medford. I am John Petrella. And the purpose of this program is to give Medford citizens facts and information to help you make informed choices. And today, I want to welcome a special guest, Tricia Schiappelli,
who is a candidate for our Meffitt City Council. And I wanna really thank you, Tricia, for joining us today. You've been on the show before. And I also wanna thank you for running for City Council.
Thank you. You may owe me one for that. Yes, we appreciate it. We really do. But thank you so much for having me back. I always enjoy the show, and I'm happy to be here. We enjoy having you here. All right, we're going to get right into the questions like we always do. We'll start by just giving our audience some background information about yourself. Who's Tricia Ciappelli?
Well, I originally moved to Massachusetts in 1998 to complete my MBA at Simmons University in their Graduate School of Management. I graduated in 2001. I have 20 plus years experience as a commercial lender.
in the banking industry. I work with CEOs and CFOs of companies with revenues in the size of $10 million to $60 million. I help them acquire debt, refinance existing debt, purchase their real estate, whatever they may need. I also help them with their cash cycles in their business so that they can get paid faster, hang on to their money a little bit longer, and then make their payments in a faster, more secure environment. So I am currently a Medford resident.
And I moved here in 2009. I lived at Station Landing first for just a little over four years. And I really loved that development with the access to the T and just being so close to so many things. And then in 2013, I actually bought my home. So I actually enjoy the house. It's a Victorian.
Yeah, Method's a good place to live. And you also, some good qualifications I want to point out to run for city council. Thank you. A lot of good stuff. Thank you. All right.
You know, can you give us a few reasons why you're running for a seat on the city council? And maybe throw in a few concerns you might have, like why you're running and what would your concerns be? Yeah, sure. So I am running for city council because, first of all, I live in the city.
And I think it has a tremendous amount of potential and opportunity given its proximity to Boston, Cambridge, and access to the 93. Unfortunately, I believe it's my opinion that it's being horribly mismanaged. And that is something that if elected to the city council, I would really want to change and improve
And as you know, the first debacle I became involved in was the methadone dispensary. That was my wake up moment if you will. I have to your point what are my concerns, I have a very long list of concerns to be
honest. And the first one is my concern is if we stay on this trajectory and we don't have some drastic changes sooner rather than later, that we may hit a point where there's a point of no return. And I believe that we are in a current downward spiral and we need to correct that as soon as possible. It is going to be a heavy lift.
absolutely, given the current circumstances and the six years of the current administration and city council, who in my opinion have really done nothing except raise our taxes. Of course, they must think we're all blind and that because we can't see that nothing is being done in the city. With our tax money, our roads and sidewalks and water are still not fixed.
in desperate need of repair. However, they have managed to throw the city into a complete chaos with this radical rezoning that they pulled out of thin air and decided to thrust onto the community.
Good concerns. And I, you know, I think a lot of people agree with you. Just, I really do. I think that's a lot of people agree with you on that. All right, Trish, can you give us some solutions for the concerns you brought up? Absolutely. And I'm going to start at the top with the mayor, which I think is where the buck stops. And while she is running unopposed, which I find shocking to say the least,
If she has any interest in saving her reputation and her legacy as the mayor of Medford, I believe she needs to do three very difficult things immediately. The first thing is she needs to deny the city council their request for additional funds for the zoning studies.
The second thing is she needs to fire consulting. They are lacking in experience for the project of this size and the location. They were not the right decision for the project in the beginning. The largest project they have done is out in a smaller town past 128.
And an example of why I think they really need to be fired and we shouldn't be giving them any more money is at a recent presentation at city council when questioned about some of the streets in the homes that were going to be changed with this zoning, they admitted that they hadn't driven
by the actual addresses or walked through any of the neighborhoods to really understand the lot size and the types of houses their planning is going to affect with this radical rezoning, but rather they chose to rely on Google Maps. Seriously? That's what we're paying for? I just was really kind of shocked by that.
Then the third thing, the mayor absolutely needs to immediately, because it is so long overdue, I believe, in my opinion, she needs to fire Alicia Hunt immediately today for her pandering to developers. It's really inconscionable and that's just a period, full stop. So once those three things have been done on the city side to really help
reflect and make some changes that we can all live with. She has a chance to resume herself with the city of Medford. And then the next thing that needs to happen is it falls to the actual citizens in the city, the good people that live here, the people that vote, the people that want to help and do their part in saving the city and their respective neighborhoods. And it is really very simple.
The voters need to vote out every single Our Revolution city councilor, full stop, period. And I'm going to repeat that, and they may need to write it down. The voters need to vote out every single Our Revolution city councilor if they want to take back their city and have a decent city with neighborhoods that they can live in and enjoy and have a say in. Full stop, no questions.
So who do they vote for? The voters then need to pick independent candidates who will listen to them and put Medford first, not be all involved in a national agenda and with things that aren't even pertaining to us. And you have to be careful because not all of those saying that they're independents are true independents.
A couple are questionable because they really don't want to take a hard line. And this is an election about a hard line. You take a position, you pick a hill, you live and die on it. And that's what this city needs.
And so one of my favorite sayings is the definition of crazy is doing the same thing over and expecting different results. We have been doing the same thing over for six years and expecting different results, and we have not gotten any. So once there is a turnover,
Then we can roll up our sleeves and really the hard work can begin and we must review rezoning and decide what gets changed. We must demand a forensic audit and demand 21st century standards for how we are reporting our finances.
and how we show the taxpayers of this city exactly where their taxpayer dollars are being spent. Right now, accountable and transparent with this administration is really just a word salad. I looked at our budget. It consists of three lines. It consists of revenue, expenses, deficit or surplus.
It's ridiculous. Yep. Right. Annual reports are really not much better and don't provide a lot of additional information. I actually reached out to our CPA audit firm in Woburn and more than once and crickets, of course.
So, we need to really work together and partner with each department in the city and hold people accountable for the people's tax dollars. And that isn't as difficult as it sounds. We need to understand where surplus and deficits are coming from so that we can stop the gaps. Otherwise, we just continue to rob Peter to pay Paul.
We need to fix our roads desperately. We need to fix our sidewalks. We need to get the lead out of our water system. We need to fix our schools. The scores are abhorrent. And I think I would like to see an ethics guideline added in there for city councilors.
Okay. So I think that's important so that we're all playing by the same rules no matter what position you're in. That's important to me. And finally, the people of Medford need to know that every Tuesday night there will be a city council meeting that is consistency is the key. They can come home, turn on their TV or log in online and we will be there in chamber
every Tuesday night to discuss and update them on all of the items that we are in the process of working through. These marathon meetings until midnight or later, because they only meet every other week because that is what is convenient for them, really isn't working. The citizens of this city have jobs, they have kids, they have a life to live.
Also, it will get rid of all these side meetings behind closed doors, I believe. If we go to meetings every week, the citizens of this city will have the right to hear the facts and the figures and hear the presentation of the pros and cons between their city council members and better understand the concepts of how it will affect them as we move through the discussion of the facts and the figures and research prior to an item being moved to a vote so that they will feel a little more comfortable
hopefully with the decisions being made. Of course we would still always have open comments and they would have the right to ask questions and maybe we could delve through it a little bit better. But I really feel like they've been kept out of the loop and no one has the time and the wherewithal to go look everything up and read through 16 pages. That's our job. Then we're going to boil it down and give it to the citizens of Medford so that they can understand what's going on as is their right.
Thank you. I mean, the citizens deserve that, too. Absolutely. Lots of talk about zoning and method. Do you think voters were misled when promised affordable housing through zoning changes? And, you know, we might as well. What is your position on zoning?
Well, so I think that, yes, they were misled, but I think that my position on zoning is that we absolutely must improve our city. I think as you drive around, it has the potential to be a beautiful city, but right now it looks tired and dirty. We have to be thoughtful about any zoning that we do and look at the zoning as a total number and how it's going to be affected with the city with
our resources such as zoning and sewer and things like that, we already had the DPW leader come in and say, you have to give me a number, you have to give me a number. So they can't give them a number, they're just adding, throwing people at it. At some point we're going to end up like other cities were with brownouts and sewage running down your streets, sewage backup during horrible storms.
So I actually think that the city of Medford is at a crossroads right now. We have the luxury to design a thoughtful city where people want to live and one that will drive visitors from contiguous cities to come here and spend dollars and enjoy some time. The zoning decisions that we make now will define us as a city going forward for many, many years. And we will either be like Somerville, where so many people say, oh, gosh, I lived there. It used to be great. It isn't anymore. You're jam-packed. It's miserable.
They don't want to live in Somerville. People are starting to move out of Cambridge. Or we choose to be smart and manage growth responsibly, where we can keep green spaces, have homes available for people through every season of their life and what they need. And in which case, we would be more like Belmont, Winchester, possibly even Melrose. I would like to see us take that direction and have smart growth, not just throw in density.
But to even imply, as our revolution city councilor Matt Leming did, that gone are the days of a single family house,
is really just ludicrous. I think people will always have a need for a single family home and want to choose that as their option of a place to live. They suffer from the delusion that all growth is good growth, and as we know in business and finance, that isn't necessarily the case. Growth that is too fast actually drives up costs and takes a toll on the existing situation and the existing assets, and you can actually put
the company, or in this case the city, in a deficit position if not monitored and managed appropriately. I've seen it happen firsthand. So interesting legal fact that I've done some research, I've talked to a couple of attorneys in preparing for this, and zoning laws are in place to protect the property owners
not for the city to use and change as they see fit in a desperate cry for additional tax dollars. Zoning laws initially were established so that you can buy property and not worry that one day you will wake up to a 10-story building next door to your house or a factory.
In fact, zoning ordinances have a valid legal interest in protecting the character of the neighborhood, not destroying the character of the neighborhood. And this gets back to the taking of land that we had had a conversation about a while ago.
When you buy a home, you are entitled to certain rights. And that right is that you have a say in the neighborhood that you live in. And the laws are very clear. And there are actually two Supreme Court cases, one in 1926 and one in 1928, that actually involved Cambridge, where a zoning ordinance had depleted the plaintiff's property value, and the Supreme Court overturned it.
So I feel if we continue down this road and things get as bad as some projections think that they could be with what they want to do, there is going to be a plethora of lawsuits. So get ready.
So Medford is just really just waking up to the truth about what is going on in the city. And my concern right now is for West Medford because I'm worried that they will now get lulled into a false sense of security with the zoning being delayed to March 2026 only to one day wake up and realize
exactly the ugly scenario that Salem Street is in and the reality, and that is that our sneaky Our Revolution City Councilor Matt Lemming in the dead of the night around 11 p.m. after the Community Development Board had agreed to the request of the homeowners and we had a completely different neighborhood negotiated, Councilor Matt Lemming reversed the request to the original zoning and all six of Our Revolution Councilors voted for it.
Again, don't be fooled, West Medford. If reelected, this city council will do the same thing to you. Don't let it happen. There is another saying I like to say. People show you who they are and you better believe them. And they've shown me on several occasions. Radical rezoning must stop, period.
That was a great, not a good answer, that was a great answer. It's the truth. I appreciate it. It is the truth. And there's so many things that people in the city don't know, and I think unless you live in the Salem Street corridor, you really don't understand what happened to us. I think people have to go back. And how egregious it was. They have to go back and know what zoning was designed to do. It was designed to protect the property owners. Absolutely.
for the city council. And those cases, to this day, have never been overturned. They never will be. Why would they be? Great answer, Tricia. So, let's get on. How would you approach getting economic growth started and, you know, growing Meffitt's tax base?
So I would focus on making the city more business-friendly. I hear we're not really that friendly to businesses. And I would make a target list of companies that our city and residents would like to have in Medford and companies that maybe are not available to the contiguous cities that we have that would then drive visitors to our city to see certain things and then
increase bottom line we need to increase our commercial tax base. The homeowners really just can't continue to take the hit for that because our administration doesn't know how to attract or negotiate with certain
certain entities and I feel like you know the Budweiser campus is a perfect example of something that took place and we should have been working with the owners of that and I feel like some of the leadership could have gone there and said thank you so much for you know
being here all these years and leasing and I understand Budweiser has had to move out because of their, but what can you do to help us and we understand that it's around price and you could even cut a side deal with them.
I mean, right now we're losing 600,000, but if you said to them, listen, I understand price is important, but if somebody comes in with a million three and they're a few hundred thousand dollars short, let's go with the lesser and we'll pay you back 200,000 a year.
year for three or four years to make up that difference in that sale price, and we're still $400,000 or $500,000 ahead in tax revenue, versus just giving it to the MBTA and then saying, oh, you know, we're losing, we're at a deficit for $600,000 a year. And things like that are done all the time. I know they are. And I call it they've lost the odd of negotiation. That's what I call it. Well, yeah, that is definitely something I would have advised one of my clients to do.
Absolutely. Yeah. Don't let that. If you really want that building, don't let it go. Go in and try to negotiate. What's the worst they're going to say is absolutely not. Yeah. Okay. So you're back to square one, but at least you try. At least you can say to the good people of Medford, I tried to save us $400,000 to $600,000 in tax revenue, and here's what I did, and they refused to do it. Looks a lot better. Good people of Medford hear you loud and clear. All right. We're going to move on. I got to ask this question. This came out of nowhere, but what's your opinion
You know, on the Method City Council, they're looking to divest from certain, you know, business entities. Right. Yeah. I sat through that whole torture show the other night. Yeah, that was, yeah. It was a torture show. I thought it was laughable and a complete waste of time. Four hours of nonsense and four hours of my life that I'll never get back. And they insist on focusing their attention and prioritizing things that are not local and
things that are happening thousands of miles away. And I could see if everything was glorious here in Medford, and our roads were fixed, and our sidewalks were perfect, and the birds were humming, and everything was beautiful, and our parkways were perfectly planted, not with weeds and overgrowth.
But I think they did it for a reason. I think there was a strategy behind it. And I think it was a much-needed diversion for them so that people can focus on something other than their inept management of the city and their failure at the rezoning, given what's been transpiring.
And as they've already confirmed, like three and a half hours into the meeting, I believe it was, they said, oh, well, by the way, we already knew from the investment company they had let us know that we really didn't have an exorbitant amount of percentage that is out of our guideline in those companies anyway.
Oh, my God. Are you kidding me? They wasted all that time. You could have just changed the agenda. You could have made the announcement and said we wanted to save everyone's time. But no, they didn't. And so what I thought was fascinating is that they actually allowed people from other cities, Malden and Somerville, to come up. I've never heard of that before or seen that. And that's really, in my opinion, shouldn't be allowed.
My greater concern at the end of that whole debacle is for our large Jewish population who just a few weeks ago spoke at a city council meeting and tried to impress on them and explain to them that they feel scared in Medford and they're uncomfortable in Medford with the things that are happening and the anti-Semitism that's going on. And they made it perfectly clear at that meeting, their message was received loud and clear, they just
don't care. Yeah, obviously. It's sad to say, but that's the message. All right. Since you're on a roll, let's look into another question.
You know, what do you think Council President Beers, he had a video response prior to the meeting, you know, to the meeting on the mayor's request to slow down zoning changes. What did you get from that? What did you, I mean, what do you think about it? Well, I thought it, I thought it was odd.
First of all, coming from him because he's been, you know, so rah-rah zoning. And then I thought, yeah, you know, that's actually a pretty good stunt to pass the blame on to the mayor because that's really kind of the overarching theme that I picked up.
And as we know, the truth is the city council really has had full control of this whole process all along. Now, is it incumbent upon the mayor to maybe have frequent check-ins, weekly, quarterly reports? Was that done? I don't know. But certainly when they had an opportunity to listen to the residents and do the right thing, they didn't.
What I think is more interesting is that they don't seem to be able to have a mea culpa moment. You know, you're right. We're sorry. We shouldn't have done this. We should have listened to the residents. You know, an apology, in my opinion, is owed to the Salem Street residents. And I think what's really more interesting is that it doesn't appear that he actually crafted that whole message himself.
As I found out later, the speech that he gave was verbatim to a memo that the mayor had written herself to the city councilors with regard to her thoughts on the zoning a day or two earlier. In fact, her memo is actually posted out on the web, and anyone can view it and confirm this fact. So it's public information, so it isn't like I'm not. But again, it's just a waste of time, and not to mention another meeting violation.
Yeah, I hear you. Yeah. Interesting. Yeah. All right. As we move on, you know, another important thing. How would you improve the management of city finances? What do you see needing to be done there?
So nothing short of a complete forensic audit for at least the past three years would suffice for me. A new city council would never want to take over the funds and the books without having an accurate financial picture of where they currently are. And while it is true, we are already audited. It is someone that is state approved. It's somebody that we've used for 15 years. And I often find vendors, when you have them come in
for assignments such as this, in that length of time, they tend to become complacent. It's just, you know, dollars in, dollars out. This is what you want. Of course, I don't know if maybe that's because our side doesn't ask for more. I'm not in those meetings. I don't know.
A fresh set of eyes with some new ideas to help us clean things up would be terrific and money well spent, I believe. I also hope that an RFP would get us a larger accounting firm that specializes in forensic accounting and can give us some financial guidance and benchmarks to reach for the years as we grow. Nice. Very nice.
One more thing on that. So with regard to that and anything else that takes place, I think one of the things I would like to do is also I like the idea of putting advisory boards together with industry experts for certain tasks that can give us guidance in their respective areas. Businesses do it all the time. There are CEO forums that certain CEOs join
to help solve problems that they experience with other CEOs. And it isn't uncommon when businesses are in a huge growth pattern, they put advisory boards together. And it isn't something that you do every week. They wouldn't be at every meeting. But if we have a problem, and certainly something with planning, you would pull some really big, big, big developers in, like Suffolk and CTA Construction. And I know those guys.
You come in and you go, hey, are we doing this right? Are we looking at this right? What do you recommend? And even if you have two of them, you're going to get one maybe that has a different idea than the other one, right? So then you can choose. And so I just feel like even for finances and certain things, you need to be putting those things together to give the best city their biggest bang for their buck. And what you're doing basically is you're having experts experience. Absolutely. And that's what's missing. And I think that's great. You have experts.
I know what I know, but you really, you have to be smart enough to know what you don't know, right? Absolutely. Yep. Yep. Very nice. Um, uh, one of my things, uh, that I always think about, you know, what, what would you consider, uh, would you consider updating the city's financing and accounting procedures?
Well, I mean, I don't know what they're currently using now. I just know what the finished product looks like. So I would say absolutely. And a new audit team would be a part of that. They would probably, you know, I would look to someone that deals strictly with municipalities and they would probably be able to make some recommendations and then we would have them come in and we would, you know,
figure out which software is the best for us, given our size and maybe the growth that we're anticipating over the next 10 years. And then, you know, maybe pick the top two or three, and we would take it from there with an RFP and definitely update in, you know, software tailored for municipalities. And we need to work closer with the part and partner with each of the departments to better understand their needs and help them accurately budget.
As well as monitor the process through the year, right? So, you know, what do you need? Why do you need it? Have an honest conversation around that. Try to get them what they need. You know, the first couple years may be a little dicey. Some may run into deficit and you may need to put a line item that you lent money from this department over to this department and then you pay it back at the end of the year or you look at did you really need that money in the first place.
You kind of balance things out as you go along. But within two years, you should be able to have a good handle on what your projections for that year are and not be as in an upheaval as what I think we are. And I think it's also important that there's a proper expense approval put into place.
with regard to credit cards and with regard to what they're spent on, and regard to dollar limits and who has that dollar limit, you know, so maybe the person that is the manager of that department can approve, and I'm just making this up, up to $1,000, anything over $1,000, it has to go somewhere else, and then once you get into $5,000, it has to go to a third person. And so everybody is on board with that money being spent.
They understand why it's being spent. They understand if there is a need right now that it has to be spent, or could it wait. And I think the citizens are owed the financial reporting that shows them exactly how their tax dollars are being spent and where. And if not, who approved these expenses that they don't like, right? And then have a conversation around that. The President Exactly. Exactly. What is your opinion?
seven and a half million dollars in overrides in their passage. What's your opinion on that? How do you feel about that?
I think the passage of the override is disgraceful. I think that as we all know, the votes, and you had someone else on here that can speak to this, but the votes were counted behind closed doors and in an election office where you could peek through a window if you were lucky and not even that.
with our revolution city councilor Matt Lemming holding guard outside. And I know people who tried to go inside and were not allowed. The whole thing is suspect and very shady. And I know from talking to many people in the city, I can count on my two hands the number of people who actually voted for it.
I think what's so sad is they, again, were lied to by this Our Revolution city councilor. They built this big program that you could go in and you could log in your house value and blah, blah, blah. I kept trying to tell people that calculator is not accurate. It is not going to be $45 a month.
I will guarantee you that because they haven't taken into, nor can they, the new assessments that are going to hit in January before that tax override is added on top of the assessment.
You know, for whatever reason, I think some people got that. It's interesting. Today I was talking to someone else and she said I was out there talking to a woman and she thought that 7.5% override was for the high school. So I mean, I think there's just really this misinformation out there that people really don't understand or know.
what that seven and a half percent was, and I think they understand now, as they've gotten their tax bill, that the calculators weren't right. They certainly do understand. They understand that. But, yeah. So, anyway. No doubt about that, yeah. And so based on some of the things that we've seen posted recently in our politics page, I understand the Department of Justice is actually investigating the whole state of Massachusetts with voter information. Yes, they are.
After we have a handle on our finance and we understand where we truly are, I'd like to overturn the override in some fashion. I'm actually working on that and thinking about several different things and trying to figure out if there's a legal way to do that. And if so, what do we do? What's the easiest to do for the people? So anyway, more to come on that.
You know, that's a great answer. We talked about some pretty serious stuff tonight. I appreciate it. No, we really did. I'm exhausted. We get into some good stuff. Very interesting. Very interesting. So now let's let's do one that's I guess it's it's easier. Ask this for everybody. OK, as we're coming to a close. So what are you least?
and most favorite things for you to do in Medford.
Oh, a fun question. OK, great. So my least favorite thing to do in Medford is drive around and hit potholes all the time with my car. And then deal with the bike lane. I'm going to end up with a hood ornament someday. If there was ever anybody in there, I would probably have them as a hood ornament. But there's never anyone in there, thankfully. But it seems like.
No one's in them, they're a pain in the neck, and all they do is make traffic worse that's already bad. And then another genius idea by the administration to just put bike lanes in regardless of whether the people want them. My favorite thing is I love our library. I love going to the library and perusing some books. I check out books there.
I enjoy just spending a few quiet hours there. Everyone is very helpful and super nice, and it's just an enjoyable time when I get to go there. I agree with you on the driving, and I especially agree with you on the library, because it is incredible what's available. And they have some nice events there as well. Oh, they have great events, and I don't think enough people in the city
know what's going on up there, take advantage of it. I mean, we had them on the show. We plan on having them again. Oh, that's great. Because I think it's great to promote them. Absolutely. That's a gem in Method. Absolutely. It really is. And the people are great. It's something. I enjoy it up there, too.
Okay, so this is the very last question. It's the most important question. Someone wants to get in touch with Tricia Schiapelli. Okay.
Well, if they haven't heard enough already and they want more opinions from me, they can e-mail me at Trish for Medford at gmail.com. So Trish, T-R-I-S-H, the number for Medford at gmail.com. Or text me. I have a phone number set up specifically for this at 617-620-7845.
Again, that's 617-620-7845. Thank you so much, Tricia. Thank you for having me. I enjoyed it. Well, it is that time again, so I want to really thank Tricia Schiappelli for joining us on Method Happenings.
And second, and most importantly, for being a candidate for our Method City Council. I think that's great. I also want to take a minute to thank everyone who has been watching the show. I guess we're getting popular out there. And I want to thank you for your feedback. I always say whether positive and negative,
We're getting a lot of positives. It makes us feel good about what we're doing, that we're appreciated. And if you would like to share a comment, if you're a candidate for any city office,
Anything. Any candidate, you're more than welcome to join us on Method Happenings. If you're opening a new business, you have an existing business you want to promote, if you represent an organization with an upcoming event, would like to appear on a future show, you can contact us at johnpatrella55 at gmail.com.
And you will be able to see replays of this show on Metfed Community Media Monday, Wednesdays, and Fridays. I'm sorry, Monday, Wednesdays, and Fridays at 6 p.m. or 7 p.m. On YouTube, you can join us at Metfed Happenings. And on Facebook, you can check us out. And we have a really great website. And I want to thank you.
All of us want to thank you. It's got a tremendous response from the people of Medford. And that's MedfordHappenings.com. I'm going to say that again. MedfordHappenings.com. It's a great website. Take a look. For the Medford Happenings team, Margaret, Bruce, Marco, Paul, I'm John Petrella. And remember, stay informed. Thank you all.
Ta-da!