Hi, everybody.
Are we recording?
Thank you, Mr. Pippicelli.
The 12th regular meeting of the Members School Committee will come to order.
Executive session is at 5 p.m.
and regular meeting will be as close to 6 p.m.
as possible.
This was in the Howard Memorial Chambers, Medford City Hall, and via remote participation.
The meeting is being recorded.
The meeting can be viewed live on the Medford Public Schools YouTube channel through Medford Community Media, on your local cable channel, Comcast 9, 8, or 22, and Verizon Channel 43, 45, or 47.
Participants can call or log in by using the following Zoom link, 913-4944-0286 is the meeting ID.
Member Rousseau, if you could please call the roll.
Here.
Member Mastroboni.
Member Olopade.
Here.
Member Parks.
Member Rheinfeld.
Present.
Member Rousseau present.
Mayor Langel-Kern.
Present.
Seven present, zero absent.
I don't see our student reps here today.
I know they were here the last meeting when we changed to Zoom, so we'll welcome them when they get here.
If you can all please rise to salute the flag.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America and to the republic for which it stands, one nation under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all.
We have executive session upon a motion to enter executive session pursuant to general laws 30A, section 21A.
Executive session.
to conduct a strategy session on the basis that an open meeting may have a detrimental effect on the bargaining positions of the Medford School Committee.
Specifically, the Medford School Committee will convene an executive session to discuss collective bargaining.
with the Massachusetts Teachers Association regarding a teacher grievance, and the Chair so declares, and pursuant to General Laws 30A, Section A3, to conduct a strategy session on the basis that an open meeting may have a detrimental effect on the bargaining positions of the Medford School Committee.
Specifically, the Medford School Committee will convene an executive session to discuss collective bargaining
with the Teamsters Local 25 regarding an administrative grievance and the chair so declares and executive session pursuant to Chapter 30A Section 21-2 to conduct strategy in preparation for non-union personnel or contract negotiations with non-union personnel specifically but not limited to the Assistant Superintendent of Academics and Instructions, Chief Operations Officer, the Director of Student Services and Assistant Superintendent of Student Services and the Director of Human Resources.
We will convene back in session as close to six as possible.
Is there a motion to enter executive session?
By Member Reinfeldt, seconded by Member Mastroboni.
All those in favor, please call the roll, please.
Member Graham?
Yes.
Member Mastroboni?
Member Olopade?
Yes.
Member Parks?
Member Reinfeldt?
Yes.
Member Rossell?
Mayor Longo?
Yes.
Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative.
Motion to enter executive session has been approved.
Alrighty.
Welcome everybody.
Welcome to our student representatives.
Thank you for being here.
Thank you for your patience.
We ran a bit over in our executive session, so we're going to go quick through our consent agenda, and then we'll get right to our Mustang moment.
We have approval of bill and payrolls, approval of donations, $100 impact church donation to the McGlynn Library, approval of meeting minutes from our regular meeting on May 18th, 2026.
Is there a motion for approval?
I move the approval.
I, member Olopade, seconded by member Reinfeld.
All those in favor?
Aye.
All those opposed?
paper passes.
We do not have any reports of subcommittees, and we have a number of reports from our superintendent.
So I'm going to turn it over to you, Dr. Galluzzi, to start us off with our Mustang moment.
Hello, good evening, my favorite part of the school committee agenda.
We have three Mustang moments tonight, and what a wonderful display of community in the chambers.
I'm so glad everyone was here to join us tonight.
The first Mustang moment we're going to hear from, I'm gonna call up Director of Arts, Suzanne Fee, and she's gonna frame a little bit of this acknowledgement this evening.
Good evening.
I think Will is going to play a little video while I talk about why we're here tonight.
Tonight we're proud to recognize a student whose dedication to the arts has made a lasting impact on countless young artists throughout our community.
First established in 2009 by the Medford Art Center, the Medford Children's Art Showcase has become a cherished tradition, celebrating the creativity and talents of students from across our district.
For years, this event has provided thousands of students with the opportunity to see their artwork professionally displayed, recognized, and celebrated.
What makes this accomplishment even more remarkable is that it represents three generations of commitments to the arts.
In 2011, Jen Desotels, who is Christine's mom and a wonderful computer teacher here at Medford High School, took over this project from MAC.
It was then carried forward by Christine's sister, Julie, who revived and expanded the event in 2021.
When Julie graduated, she entrusted this important work to her younger sister, Christine, who embraced the responsibility and continued the tradition with the same passion, care, and dedication.
Behind the scenes, Christine has coordinated artwork from schools across the district, individually matted and labeled hundreds of pieces, organized reception events for families, and worked closely with educators and community partners to ensure that every young artist feels valued and celebrated.
Because of her efforts, thousands of students have experienced the pride of seeing their work displayed publicly and have been encouraged to continue exploring their creativity.
She has not only preserved a beloved community tradition, but she strengthened it for future generations.
For her exceptional leadership, commitment to the arts, and service to the students of Medford, it's my honor to present this award to Christine Desautels.
In the fall, Christine will be heading to the University of Maine to study marine biology.
We wish her all the best as she heads into this next exciting chapter of her life.
And I'm going to invite Christine to come up and be celebrated and also just share a few words about her feelings about the experience.
The point of the Medford Children's Art Showcase is to make students of every grade and basically every single student in the district understand that they are an artist because they have made art.
A lot of other art showcases are about celebrating like maybe their best art or their, it's like a competition and they like rank them or something.
And part of the point of this is that if you have done, if you've made the piece and you completed it and you put it all together and brought this idea to life in your own special way, then you deserve to be celebrated and you deserve to,
feel pride for your accomplishment and for your peace.
So every year we do grades three and seven.
So they're kind of the middle grades and they
If we keep it at the same grades every year, then we will eventually hopefully get every single student who passes through.
And we try and get one piece from every student from every school.
Sometimes we don't have a certain school because they have their own art showcase going on.
Sometimes they just run out of time to get something to us.
But the goal is to make sure that they
know that their art is important and they should keep making it.
So we also, we have like little stickers that say I'm an artist so that they are noted as the ones being part of this showcase and we send them each an individualized invitation that says your art is being displayed, come and see it.
And it's become a bit of a fixture at Rivers Edge where we display it and we've had like
people who live in the building above it come by as we're setting up and they're like, oh, I love this show.
It's like so cute.
It's great to see all of the different ranges of interpretations of the same prompt.
So like there'll be a self-portrait and some people do it landscape, some do it vertical, some add all sorts of flourishes and others keep it really simple.
And
Everybody gets to walk around and see the different ranges of ability and be inspired to keep going and keep developing their skills.
And Christine has been interested in finding a student who wants to carry on this work.
So spread the word in the community if anyone wants to carry on the tradition to reach out to me.
And hopefully we can make this continue and keep the Desotels family tradition going and the Medford Public Schools tradition going.
So I want to thank Christine and also her mom and her sister, who I wish I could go back in time and give you guys an award as well.
But I hope Christine will share it with you.
Thank you.
Next I would like to, we're going to acknowledge esports, and so I'd like to call up our athletic director, Mr. O'Leary, and I'm not quite sure if any of the coaches are here.
Okay, go ahead.
Good evening, thank you for having us.
Like Superintendent Galussi said, this is a wonderful night whenever athletics is in front of you for the Mustang moment.
And you've all heard of a dynasty, and as Will pointed out to me when I walked in, we have our very own dynasty here in Medford.
We have a three-time state champion Mario Kart team here tonight from our eSports team.
I'm going to introduce coach Lindsay Rabla and coach Tyler McCready, and they're going to introduce the students.
So if you come forward.
All right, we brought the trophies with us as props, but that will get set right there.
So I just want to briefly introduce the seasons that we've had over the past year.
We were here last year as an esports team after having won our first state championship.
in spring of 2025.
And of course, no team has an expectation that that success will continue over time.
But we had a very successful fall season going 7-1 in the regular season and then going on to win the state championships at Endicott College.
And then we had a very successful spring season going undefeated in the regular season and then going on to win the state championships at Sutton High School.
We additionally had an invitation to compete at the Council of New England Secondary School Principals Associations.
esports regional championships where we defeated another team before falling to Rhode Island's Mario Kart team.
And we also competed in the Play Versus Cup, falling short there.
But nevertheless, we've had a fantastic season.
And that is entirely due to the effort of these wonderful students that we have, who I'm going to go ahead and introduce.
So I have them in order up here.
First, we have Justin Lara.
Echo Valdez-Melgar, Jalen Richardson, Juan Tapia, and Nobi Ashihara.
All right, I guess, could everyone give them a round of applause for their fantastic work these past couple of years?
Do you want us to pose for pictures?
Yes.
Absolutely.
OK.
Let's be symmetrical.
You've got to go on the inside.
You've got to go on the inside?
Yes, OK.
Oh, excited.
OK.
Okay, three times a charm.
Last Mustang moment for this evening is I'm going to invite Dr. Chiesa to come up.
She's going to frame some humanities acknowledgements through the humanities department.
Good evening.
I am so excited to be here to celebrate some of our humanities Mustang, and I'm calling it moments, but I know I'll try to be
as succinct as we can be.
We do have a lot of different honorees, and on our slideshow we have the Geography Bee tonight, the Teen Perspectives on Immigration Contest, the Scholastic Writing Awards, the Ethics Bowl, the Mock Trial, and the Model UN.
You can see as the
We move through two more slides.
We do have a lot of students to honor, so I just wanna tell the students they're gonna come up.
Their advisor, if they're here, is gonna share a little bit of information about the achievement or the student.
And if all the students can just stay until we're all done so we can take a picture, I think that was the plan.
And we do have certificates, but we will pass them out at a later date because we do wanna make sure we honor and
give a little time if you have any questions about anything.
So I'm gonna start with the first event, which was the Middle School Geography Bee.
I don't know if the students were able to come tonight.
I know it's really busy this time of year, but we have Elliot Kaminsky, Stefano Lazara, and Janie Schwartz.
If they're here, I would love to come join me so I'm not alone up here.
I will just share briefly that they participated in the Geography Middle School Bee and answered a series of questions related to physical, cultural, economic, as well as political geography.
And from the slideshow, you can see our winners.
I'm so happy that you're here, and I'm not alone up here.
A huge thank you to Mr. McCarthy, Mr. Zizzo, and the other seventh grade teachers as well.
And we are going to give you a big congratulations.
So thank you.
Do we have any questions?
Any geographical questions we want to test him on?
Anything?
What was the question that won it for you?
Do you remember?
No.
OK.
Good job.
Congratulations.
Thank you so much.
We also just wanted to call out that Elliot Kaminsky has won it twice, two years in a row, which is awesome.
So we just wanted to have a special slide dedicated to that as well.
And then we're going to move to our next
This one's a contest, so Teen Perspectives on Immigration Contest, and I am going to turn it over to one of our winners.
You can see all the names on the slide there.
We have Resna Basnet, Valentina Burke, Lila Graham, and Sarah Carboni all winning the achievement, and I'm gonna turn it over to them so that they can share a little bit more about it.
Thank you.
Hi there.
So the Immigration Learning Center runs the teen perspectives contest for short essays and art pieces and students can enter their piece for a chance to win up to $300 in prize money.
I think a few people from Medford won some awards and a lot of other kids participated and had really
amazing works that were put into it.
And it's for Malden and Medford and Everett public schools, I believe.
And this year the prompt was how immigration benefits your community.
So it was a really cool opportunity to explore that theme.
And there's a lot of really interesting pieces that people put into it.
Okay, we're moving right along.
So we have our Scholastic Writing Awards, which you may recall we have presented individually before, so I'm gonna go as quickly as I can with that.
I'm excited to announce that we had two Silver Key recipients this year, which is huge.
We have Tristan Igano and Griffin Lynch Wood, and they're gonna come up and share a little bit more about their essay and short story that got them the Silver Key Award.
So I'm gonna ask them to join.
Come on up.
And also, Mr. Ambrose is here to support his student, so we welcome him and all of his hard work.
Hi, guys.
My name is Griffin Wood.
I'm coming from Miss Sanford's 10th grade English class.
I'm so glad to be here.
My poem was called The Loudest Bird.
And it was a satire piece about social media and how people often post, or in this case, tweet, using birds as a metaphor, their certain messages and their opinions, often without thinking about how it will affect others or make other people feel.
And I just thought that it was important to sort of highlight that sort of issue in society and use this contest as a kind of a
opportunity to get that sort of thing out there.
So, thank you.
Hi, I'm Tristan Ngano, and I've been writing since probably about fourth or fifth grade.
And I wrote a short story that's kind of like, it's very dark.
It's like there's this guy, and he kind of has this twisted sense of what's right and what's wrong.
And I always find that very fascinating when characters in books or shows have that.
It's just always a very interesting thing.
So I wanted to write my own story about that.
I just want to share how proud we all are of both of the students.
Previous winners of Silver Keys include John Updike, Sylvia Plath, and Stephen King.
So Griffin and Tristan are in very good company of bright, futurist writers.
We'll add that Miss Sanford wanted to be here too, but she just had her third baby.
So she is with us in spirit, probably watching.
So congratulations.
All right, we're moving right along.
We're gonna move next to our mock trial competition, and I'm gonna invite Ms.
Dineyu to come up.
She can read the names and explain a little bit more and have a few students speak to it.
Ms.
Dineyu?
And if the students are here, if they wanna join us, that would be wonderful.
Great, yeah.
I knew the names.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Okay.
Okay, so a little bit about the mock trial competition team in Medford.
It is one of the longest running student activities at the school, and this year the students traveled around to various courtrooms around the Commonwealth, and they viewed civil and criminal proceedings, not just to learn about the justice system, which is obviously a big part of the class, called trial practice skills, but also to prepare for their competition season.
And they honed their public speaking and their advocacy skills, which have become so important right now at this time.
And they gave excellent performances in three trials against neighboring schools.
I am tremendously proud of these students.
And some of them will be continuing on as seniors, taking the class to compete with me again next year.
Our team received many compliments this year from judges around the Commonwealth about their courtroom decorum.
and their knowledge of the rules of evidence, which can be very challenging even for licensed attorneys to learn and to harness.
This year, we're not really sure what happened, but we didn't make the yearbook.
So the graphic design class printed this beautiful picture.
Each kid is going to receive this.
Okay, this would have been our yearbook picture.
They're gonna receive this, it's on cardstock as a memento.
It has the whole group and we hope that they'll keep it and they'll remember this time and they'll use these public speaking and advocacy skills for years to come.
I have two students, Carly and Jack, who would like to say a few words about their experiences.
Before that, let's go ahead and read the names of the whole team.
So some of our seniors have graduated and they're not here this evening because of various commitments, but Jacob Assetta, Moesha Bernard, Rohan Gupta, he's here this evening with us, John Lucas, Sarvesh Maharjan, Laura Musawi, Lucy Rodriguez, Nelson Ruan, Carly Sensaba, she'll also be saying a few words, Sophia Shah, and Polixeni Ververis.
Okay, I'm gonna turn it over to the students.
Hi, I'm Carly Sunspot.
I'm a recently graduated Medford High student who was a part of the recent mock trial.
I just want to share that this was a really cool experience because most of the mock trial teams we went against were just clubs that met some days in the week, but we got to see each other every day during second period.
I've always been kind of shy with public speaking, and I think that being a witness in all three of the trials really has helped me come out of my shell and work on my public speaking.
And I just want to give a quick shout out to Ms.
Dineo, who has really taught us about really important things about the law, especially in Massachusetts, that I'll need in the future.
And now I'm going to pass this over to Jack.
Thank you.
I'll keep it quick.
Carly really hit on all the points.
Mock trial has helped a lot with public speaking, but also being able to read and comprehend information really quickly.
With mock trial, a lot of it wasn't just being able to stand up and argue.
It was also being able to synthesize information from bits of passages or things like that.
So that was a really valuable skill.
So yeah, that's about it.
Thank you, Ms.
Dineo.
And thank you, all of you.
Wonderful, thank you.
Next up.
I'm still here.
Moving on, we have two left.
We are going to celebrate our Ethics Bowl team, which is run by Mr. Esner.
So I'm going to invite Mr. Esner to come up, along with, I believe, one student is able to join.
I just want to share, I'll let Mr. Esner read the names, but we're excited to continue our partnership with Tufts University and continue to work with the Ethics Bowl team.
And without further ado, they're here.
Hi, good evening.
So the Ethics Bowl program at Medford High, we've been doing it for about 12 years now, I want to say.
It's a great program.
It has the kids engaged in an array of skills, both critical thinking, speaking, writing, argumentation.
It operates both as a club, so kids can come and take part and join in the conversations, but then it's also a competitive side where kids are kind of locked in and then go to competition and compete.
So, I'm not going to go too much into detail because I think Victor is going to speak to kind of how it operates and the value of it.
But I just wanted to speak to the participants this year.
We had Raul Gonzalez, Rohan, who's here, Rohan Gupta, Nikhil Manekkar, Victor Mendez, Julia Sarantonio, and James Sloan, who is a senior graduating and heading off to Wesleyan, I think.
He's going to Wesleyan.
So, anyway, I'll turn it over to Victor.
Thank you.
Hi, everyone.
Hope you're all doing well.
I just wanted to explain to you guys what Ethicsful really is.
And you guys might know that it is a debate-styled club.
But what really distinguishes us is our approach and our emphasis.
We tend to focus on exploring the ethical landscape of each case, because we're given 15 real-world situations.
And we're given the chance to really
dive into them throughout the school year, and then compete against some of the most, like, a lot of the really prestigious private schools in the Northeast at Tufts.
It was really great this year.
We competed against BB&N, Phillips Andover, and other very good schools.
And I just think it's very rare to find a club that is so collaborative, yet still manages to compete with some of these really hard-hitting teams.
And I think in a time that is so polarizing, it is so
important to not just choose one side, to really understand the nuance in between every situation.
And I just wanted to say for Ethics Bowl, one of my biggest regrets or one of my only regrets is not joining sooner.
I think that it really could have given me so many more opportunities if we've competed harder.
And I'm very excited to try again next year.
And I hope we make it to finals and maybe we'll make it to nationals.
Thank you.
I want to move on to our last set of awards.
I also want to thank all of the school committee for their generosity.
You have supported many of these teams in the past, including the Ethics Bowl.
So we do appreciate that and your commitment to the students.
I also want to thank Mr. Bowen Flynn and Ms.
Sanford, who helped support the humanities department in many different ways.
We end with, last but not least, our model United Nations, and I'm going to ask Mr. Brophy to come up and speak a little bit more.
You will see we've had numerous conferences as well as numerous awards that I know that they're all excited to share with you, so thank you.
Good evening.
I just want to speak a little bit about Model UN, and then I have some students talking about it.
The club is fairly new.
We've been doing this.
I've been doing it for three or four years, and we've gone from doing two or three conferences a year, we did seven this year, and now our students are winning awards at almost every conference they go to, and I can see their growth from sophomore to junior year, speaking, being more confident, able to write their position papers, and now they're going toe-to-toe with big model UN programs, private schools, and bringing home the big awards.
So I'm gonna have a couple of our students, Topper, Fowler,
Aaron Greenberg talk a little bit more about the club.
Yeah.
Hello, I'm Aaron Greenberg.
I'm the Secretary of Model UN.
And I'm Topper Fowler.
I'm the Secretary General, or at least the President of Model UN.
So Model United Nations is an after-school club where students engage in discussions with other students.
Students split up into several committee sessions to discuss different topics that could be real or fictional scenarios.
They represent an entity that fits the topic, such as historical figures like George Washington, or a nation such as the United States.
Students will collaborate towards a solution based on their beliefs.
At Medford High, club members meet weekly on Mondays in our advisor, Mr. Brophy's room.
to conduct committee simulation, reflect on conferences, and write position papers to prepare for future committees.
In conferences, members address the problems presented to them and seek out a resolution to fix these issues.
Throughout the 2025-2026 school year, Medford's Model United Nations Club has attended seven conferences, two of which being multi-day conferences where students spent three days fully immersed in the experience of a United Nations delegate away from home.
At these conferences, Medford High School has won numerous awards, including Verbal Commendations, Best Position Paper, Outstanding Delegate, and Best Delegate.
These awards do not just look good on paper.
Winning awards involves dedication in three key qualities, penmanship, public speaking, and cooperation with others.
As demonstrated through many awards, Medford High mastered these qualities through hard work and perseverance.
So I would just like to take a brief moment to recognize the students here and my co-advisor.
And Jen Gates can't be here tonight.
But our students who are assembled here have won awards.
So Ryan Godley, Griffin Lynch, Christina Yosegly, Topper Fowler, Sophie Hook, Jadenville, Andrew Hong.
One more slide.
Tess McMorrell.
Alachi Yeager, Cassidy Collins have all won awards.
Thank you.
Do we have time for a quick picture?
Why don't we do this group first and we'll do the rest in another group because this is a large one.
th th th
Thank you.
Congratulations.
Dr. King is in the restroom already.
Yeah, I have time.
th th th
th th
One more.
Thanks, everybody.
Congratulations.
Next up, we have the recognition of CPAC retirements.
I'm going to turn it over to Dr. Suzanne Galluzzi, our superintendent, and Ms.
Joan Bowen, director of student services.
Thank you very much.
This is a very special recognition.
Director Bowen is going to speak in just a few minutes, but I just want to say that we are here to acknowledge the phenomenal CPAC executive board members, and I do want to just thank them for a decade of dedicated service to families, to students,
for creating that bridge between home and school.
And without your efforts, a lot of people may not have felt supported.
So I truly appreciate all of the support and dedication and guidance that you've been able to provide a lot of families.
And so on behalf of Medford Public Schools, thank you very much.
And I know Director Bowen is going to get into a little specifics.
This is a little lengthy.
So good evening, everyone.
Tonight, we have the honor of recognizing and celebrating four extraordinary executive board members of our CPAC, which is our Special Education Parent Advisory Council.
whose dedication, leadership, and advocacy have made a meaningful difference in the lives of students, families, and our entire school district.
What makes their contributions especially inspiring is that their commitment to CPAC began long before they served on the executive board.
They became involved because they genuinely cared about creating better opportunities for students with disabilities and supporting families throughout their educational journey.
Over the past 10 years, they have generously given their time, energy, and expertise to CPAC.
They organized and hosted countless events, both in person and via Zoom, responded to parents seeking guidance and support, and consistently made themselves available whenever families needed them, all while balancing careers, family responsibilities, and their own busy lives.
Their dedication has truly been remarkable.
One of their greatest accomplishments has been helping to build a strong and collaborative partnership between CPAC and the district.
Together they fostered a relationship grounded in trust, problem solving, and a shared commitment in supporting students and families.
Whenever concerns or questions arose, they approached each situation with compassion, thoughtfulness, and a genuine desire to work together toward positive solutions.
The strength of this partnership was recognized during a coordinated program review by the Massachusetts Department of Elementary and Secondary Education.
The district received a commendable rating, which is the highest you can receive, and reviewers noted that they had rarely seen a CPAC and school district work together so effectively.
That recognition reflects the culture of collaboration these individuals helped create.
Their impact exceeds far beyond meetings and advocacy.
They understood that meaningful progress happens when people come together, and through the work on the Universal Safety Committee and the creation of monthly admin meetings, they helped establish opportunities for families and school leaders to listen, learn, and collaborate in ways that benefited students.
They have also been instrumental in advancing some of the district's most meaningful initiatives, including adaptive physical education and unified sports.
helping to create more inclusive opportunities for students of all abilities.
Through these efforts, they ensured that families felt not only heard, but valued as essential partners in the educational process.
Perhaps the most lasting contribution in their commitment is promoting acceptance, understanding, and belonging.
They championed the development of a disability awareness curriculum and they were instrumental in bringing Best Buddies to our high school.
Thanks to their dedication, the program has flourished and we are excited to see it expand to the middle school in the fall.
While we will certainly miss their leadership, the programs they help build, the partnerships they strengthen, and the lives they touch will continue to benefit for our community in many years to come.
On behalf of our school community, thank you for your vision, your advocacy, your kindness, and your unwavering commitment to make a difference.
We are deeply grateful for all that you have done.
So please join me in congratulating and honoring the CPAC Executive Board, who will be retiring in June.
Co-chairs Tanya Sullivan and Alex Larick.
We have Secretary Anne Herzog-Rousseau, who couldn't make it tonight, as well as Jamil Anne Johnson, who is our treasurer, and she was not able to make it tonight.
But we just want to celebrate them as a beginning on their new chapter.
We wish them much happiness, fulfillment, and many wonderful adventures in the years ahead.
Thank you.
Oh, you're so sweet.
This is just a little token to say thank you.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
I was going to do a little speech, but Joan pretty much covered everything, so there will be no speech.
But we do want to thank you, Joan.
You've been, obviously, a pleasure to work with, as has the school committee, and Superintendent Galussi, and Mayor Lungo Kern.
So we just want to thank you all.
And we're still around, so if you need us, we're here.
We're officially retired, I guess.
Yeah, in June.
Thank you very much.
We appreciate it.
Don't go very far.
Picture time?
Don't give it, well, before a picture, I think the mayor has something to acknowledge you as well.
Yes, I too wanna just thank you for everything you've done for students and families.
10 years is a really long time to be doing what you're doing, and I do get the emails, so I see all the Zoom meetings that you're having and supports that you've been able to provide so many, and we just really greatly appreciate all you've done for our community.
I just have a citation that I'd like to give you.
I'm sure Dr. Galuzzi might want to take a picture with you as well, but just in recognition of your contributions to CPAC and expertise supporting students and families signed on my behalf from the city of Medford.
Thank you.
th th th
Turn it back over to Dr. Suzanne B. Galussi, our superintendent, for recognition of Medford Public Schools retirements and employee anniversaries.
Yes this is like a bittersweet recognition right now.
So we have many first I'm going to acknowledge our retirees.
We have several retirees.
I am going to call them by name and by role.
Some are here tonight.
And so I would ask if you could.
come forward.
We will give you an opportunity if you want to say something.
No pressure.
And then we will do a picture.
But this year marks the end of a career for many people, but we want to just make sure that we say thank you for your
unwavering dedication to the students and the families and the community of Medford Public Schools.
Thank you for the tireless hours that you have put and poured into your students.
You leave a lasting impression and I want you to know that we greatly appreciate everything that you have done.
Teaching is one of those jobs that it fills your bucket.
But it's also very tiring and very draining because you give so much of yourself into your students.
So everything that people have done, I just want to say thank you from the bottom of my heart for doing what you have done for these past several years, some of you decades, on behalf of the students and the families.
So I'm just going to start reading the names now of retirees.
We have Michael Allen, teacher at the Brooks.
James Amarena, special education teacher at the high school.
Patricia Brandl, science teacher at the high school.
Diane Cabral, cafeteria manager.
Richard Cormio, vocational, well, electrical teacher at the high school.
Maria Dorsey, library teacher at the high school.
Paul DeMeo, teacher at the Andrews.
James Garrity, teacher at the Roberts.
Kelly Malloy, computer teacher at the Roberts.
Lola Mastracchi, special education teacher at the Andrews.
Edward McAveney, custodian at the high school.
Joanne McKay, teacher at the Roberts.
Stephanie Mickley, accounts payable, Medford High School.
Maria Michelli, kindergarten teacher at the Brooks.
Alexa Mays, after school group leader at the Brooks.
Round of applause first.
Good evening.
I had to write this down because I was going to have a slideshow, but Lisa said I couldn't do that.
Mr. Cormier, can I just interrupt one moment?
I'm so sorry.
Yeah, that's fine.
I forgot a name.
I had it on the other list.
It didn't transfer over.
My deepest, deepest apologies, Gina Coppola, paraprofessional, Andrews Elementary.
Gina, in my mind, you weren't leaving.
My apologies, Gina.
You're on the other list.
I'll say your name twice.
Mr. Cormier, go ahead.
I'm sorry.
Thank you.
Please remember to bring up, no this is the wrong one, sorry.
Okay.
Good evening and thank you for this opportunity to speak tonight.
My journey at MVTHS, the voc began in September of 1971 when I entered the school as a freshman.
I didn't know then that 36 years later I would return to teach in the very room that started my career as an electrician.
Now, here I am at the end of a 19-year career that saw the voc grow from a school struggling to survive, where students were looked down upon as not being smart enough for college, to where it is today, a school of choice rather than a last option.
Many have asked me what I like about my job, and that's pretty easy.
Watching a student come in with a dream and leave with a career that I have had the honor of being a part of is the greatest and most rewarding feeling.
being a part of the total re-imaging of the school with my colleagues and their students, projects like the bistro, the robotics and engineering space, and most recently, the new plumbing shop that will open next year, transforming a dark and dingy section of the girls' locker room into a vibrant workspace built by the students for the students.
Point of irony?
My first homeroom in 1971 was V220, right across the hall from the plumbing shop.
So I'm going to start and end my career here in the same spot.
I'd like to thank Bill Mahoney, Roy Bellson, and Tom Ritchie for giving me this opportunity.
And I want to thank Heidi, who held my jaw when I caught a little cancer there back in 2013.
Chad, I want to thank you also for listening and guiding us and letting us do our own thing.
And to you, Medford, thank you for allowing me the honor of teaching your students.
And of course, I have to thank my wife and my family.
This doesn't happen without their support.
And you know, I'm a pretty lucky guy.
So what's next?
Well, in September, we're going to go to Germany.
I'm going to the wedding of the man who gave my stem cells, who saved my life.
And then the only other thing that I'm sure of is that I'm going to be spending a lot of time with those eight humans who call me Papa.
This has been a hell of a ride.
Thank you very much.
OK.
Thank you.
So I'm going to wrap up my career in numbers.
34 years, four superintendents, six principals, four schools, up to 700 students, hundreds of families, hundreds of colleagues.
But one teacher with the hope
to make an impact on my students.
I want to thank my family and all of you.
Thank you.
Hi.
Good evening.
Thank you very much for inviting us for this honor.
I wasn't going to speak because I'm
like some of my students are afraid to speak in front of crowds.
But at any rate, I just want to say how much, as a special education teacher, I've felt privileged to work with students who sometimes struggled.
I've worked at the Curtis Tufts School, as well as Medford High School, for the past 24 years.
And I just feel that the special ed department has helped so many students, and hopefully I've had something to do with that.
Just very brief, not my whole biography, but my personal story.
Not to talk Mr. Cormier, but I was a senior in 1970.
and graduated in 1971 in the first graduating class at the new Medford High School.
My wife, Denise, my three sons, my mother, my mother-in-law, my sister, my brother-in-law are all Medford graduates.
So I started in business world for the first half of my life, and then I decided what I wanted to be when I grew up, so I became a teacher.
in 2001, and so I've kind of gone full circle as a Mustang student and employee.
Thank you for listening.
Hi, I'm Lola Mastracchi, and I've taught at the Andrews Middle School.
I want to say what an honor and a privilege it's been to teach the students of Medford for the past 40 years, and only in Medford.
And I, too, am a Mustang, and I will always be a Mustang.
I thank you all very much.
And yes, I'm Gina Cappella.
Many of you know me, but I want to thank everybody, school committee, citizens of Medford, my bosses who are out over there, and the special ed department, because it has been my life and my honor to be with these children.
And I thank you, Madam Mayor, and you, Suzanne, who's known me for a long time, Dr. Galussi,
Dr. Case left, but all right, I want to thank her.
Joan Bowen, my biggest member, mentor.
That's you.
And everybody else that I worked with at Medford Public Schools.
I'm not done though, Paul.
You know me.
I'll be back day in and day out just to do something, either if it's volunteering or whatever.
I thank you all for the opportunity to have your children.
And they are the best kids.
I always say Medford gives too much.
I love them all.
Thank you so much.
We'll do a picture.
Did anybody else want to say anything?
OK.
All the retirees, let's come do a picture, please.
Thank you very much.
Medford Public Schools and Tufts University are here to honor.
One more acknowledgment before we move on.
I'm going to list the names of our employees that have given years of dedication to Medford Public Schools.
I'm going to list teachers and staff members that have given 25 years, 30 plus years, and 40 years to Medford Public Schools.
I'm just going to ask for them to stand up.
like citations, people that aren't here will make sure that they get to them.
But 25 years in Medford Public Schools this year, John Bissell Jr., Doug Bowen Flynn, Jonathan Brown, Holly Casabon,
James Dickens, Kathleen Ellis, Michelle Farkson, Nancy Gersick, Jacqueline Harvey, Sean Lally, Mike Lazaro, Joseph Ouellette, Andre Pierre-Paul, Stephanie Roach, Lucille Shedd, Jonathan Wilson.
Could you please stand?
30 years, Adeline Laney Cahill, Michael Coates, Robert Ferrante, Debra Notaro, Diane Serbanian, Lynn Travers, Lauren McCarthy.
40 years of service, Marie Cunningham and Anne Patton.
Could I just quickly have you come up here for a photo, please?
I'll turn it over to you anyway.
Medford Public Schools and Tufts University honor Marie Cassidy, founder of the Medford Family Network, Dr. Suzanne Begalusi, superintendent, and Mr. Rocco DiRico, associate vice president of government and community relations at Tufts University.
Thank you.
I'm just going to say a little brief, if that's OK, Mr. DiRico.
I mean, where do we begin to talk about Marie Cassidy and the impact she's made on the Medford community since 1993?
So it's impossible to sum up into words what Marie Cassidy means to the city of Medford and to Medford families.
we could try.
She's been the driving force to the Medford Family Network.
She started the program and has just with persistence, grit, love, and dedication has just poured her entire self into the program as well as the Medford community and for that many Medford families have felt that support
through the resources, the guidance, the training, and the materials that you've been able to provide to families for decades.
So I know that we're not going to necessarily say goodbye to Marie.
I don't think that that's possible.
But I do want to, on behalf of Medford Public Schools, thank you for everything you've done for our families and for our students.
Your impact is profound, and it is seen, visible, and felt.
So thank you.
Thank you Mayor Lungo-Kern, Dr. Galluzzi, and the members of the Medford School Committee.
My name is Rocco DiRico.
I'm the Associate Vice President of Government Community Relations at Tufts University.
At Tufts, we often talk about the importance of civic engagement and we value our partnerships and collaborations with the city, Medford public schools, and local nonprofit organizations.
We treasure our partnership with the Medford Family Network.
And as Dr. Galluzzi was saying, for over three decades, that iconic purple door has been a beacon for everyone in the community.
And for so many families, over 400 Tufts families call Medford home, and many of those families have benefited from the programs at the Medford Family Network, including my own.
And when we think about the heart and soul of the network, we think of Marie Cassidy.
She is a fixture at the Medford Family Network, but she's also been a fixture at Tufts University.
She's at Tufts Community Day every year.
She has served on our Tisch College Community Research Board.
She is an alumni, technically, because she received an honorary degree from Tufts as well.
So today, on behalf of President Sunil Kumar and Tufts University, and in honor of Marie Cassidy, Tufts University would like to announce a $50,000 donation to the Medford Family Network.
Oh my God, this is absolutely incredible.
How do I begin?
How do I say anything?
You know, I'm just out to song, you know that.
Good evening, school committee and everyone, how are you?
Great, great.
We all are here tonight because I think we got it right.
Good evening school committee and everyone.
How are you?
Great, great.
Thank you so, so much.
I do not know where to begin.
This is unbelievable.
It has been more than a joy and an honor for me to have this role.
I have been privileged every single day of my life.
I really have.
The good, the bad, and the ugly.
Every moment of it.
I look to our families and the star of this story is the story.
the story of our families, of our members, of our struggles, of their struggles, and the winning of those struggles, and the getting through it, and the picking themselves up year after year, because we have an amazing staff, three of whom are here with me this evening.
If you could please raise your wonderful hands.
Irina Shumway is here, Brenda Kennedy is here, and Cindy Selbig.
I have an amazing team.
And they represent with me decades of work.
I think we have like thousands of years of staff time when you pull it all together.
It's been an amazing, amazing time.
And this Medford School Committee and the Medford Public Schools have been opened up with welcome arms to us year after year.
When we didn't have a place to be, all the schools, the elementary schools, of which there were 11 by the time, at that time if you may remember,
opened up their arms to us and let the Medford Family Network have a place there.
And then we opened up our arms at Medford High School in 2003 and we're able to be a really permanent place in the school, in the city.
I don't know how to thank all of you enough to thank the city enough.
Every organization, every business has opened up their arms to us.
Tufts University, what an honor it has been to be with you and all of your students.
I had taught scholars for many, many years, and they were amazing, and implemented programs that live to this day at the Medford Family Network.
The focus group helped us set up every September.
We just had a wonderful working relationship right at Tufts University.
The students came out and worked with our students, with our families, putting on some athletic programs.
So I cannot thank everyone enough.
As I do, it's 33 years, and I keep saying I'm only 29, so I don't know how that happened.
But it's been an absolute honor, and I will always have this wonderful, wonderful memory.
Thank you so very much.
Marie?
Yes.
Thank you so much.
Don't go far.
Oh, hold on, Marie.
Marie, Marie, Marie, you need to come back.
Ms.
Cassidy, you need to come back.
On behalf of school committee and the district, we also have a recognition of your retirement that Irina will present to you that was specifically made by our students in our CTE shops.
Oh, my goodness.
Ms.
Malone, the two shops are
Carpentry and metal fab.
It's our logo, our common logo.
A friend to know, a place to grow.
I made that up 33 years ago.
Medford Feeling Network, Marie Cassidy, founder, established in 1993.
This is beautiful.
Oh my god, I love this.
Thank you, thank you, thank you.
Thank you for everything that you've done.
We appreciate it.
Loved it.
We're going to do a picture, of course.
It's the last one of the night, so we're going to bring it home.
OK, bring it home.
Why don't we?
There's a recommendation to approve the donation to the Medford Family Network from Tufts University of $50,000.
So if we could maybe just take a roll call vote on that.
You didn't bring a big check, Rocco, so we could take a picture with you two?
OK.
Fair.
We appreciate the donation.
It will go to good use.
Motion to approve by Member Reinfeldt, seconded by Member Graham.
Member Graham.
Member Mastroboni.
Yes.
Member Olopade.
Member Parks.
Yes.
Member Reinfeldt.
Member Rousseau.
Absolutely.
Member Mayor Langel-Kern.
Yes.
Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative.
We will accept that donation.
Thank you very much.
Thank you very, very much.
Thank you.
Why don't we bring a view of Marie and then maybe Rocco.
You can grab one, get one in one after and with Marie and we can publicize it.
th th th
Marie, it's your month.
I mean, you're Citizen of the Year, Retirement Teddy Bear Picnic, Retirement Party this week, School Committee.
It's all about you.
Congratulations.
Well deserved.
Um, thank you.
And we're gonna get to a little business.
So we have a recommendation from Dr Suzanne Galusi, our superintendent to approve amended school year 26 27 MPS district calendar.
Thank you.
I think I'm, Mr. Pippis, oh, thank you.
I don't have my Zoom on, so hopefully it's displaying.
I just wanted to, I came before you to give you an update regarding next year's calendar.
This first slide that displays what was discussed just are the highlights in the last presentation around some of the challenges for school year 26-27 calendar as Labor Day is very late this year.
It is September 7th, so that means that teachers report on Monday, August 31st for two days of professional development and students grades 1 through 12 plus do not start until Wednesday, September 2nd.
And then Friday is a no school day, an observance of Labor Day per the collective bargaining agreement with teachers, making the last day of school set for June 23rd.
That is without the five snow days that the Department of Education has us factor in, in case we need them.
And as we reflect on this year, we needed four of those five days, thus moving the last day of school date up by four days.
If we go to the next slide, part of the work that the district has done in partnership and collaboration with the Teachers Union was to talk about the challenges that arose around Good Friday and that it wasn't as simple as to say that
We would recognize Good Friday as a school day off because per the five days that the Department of Education requires you to put in for snow days brings us exactly up to June 30th.
So there was no wiggle room.
I did present to this body and the community about the challenges and the data that the Good Friday Day provided to the district and the community.
and reflected on our staff not being a true representation of the community population.
And therefore, a lot of our staff members celebrate Good Friday.
The work that we've done with the Teachers Union to get to an understanding is as follows.
So Good Friday, which is March 26th, will now be a district-wide day off.
School will be closed.
It'll be a day off for students and staff.
And then the previously planned March 2nd professional development day will now become a full school day.
for students, teachers, and staff.
And what we are doing with the time that was allotted on that professional development day is it is being divided up amongst the four remaining professional development days.
And so that each of those four days, there are two before students start in August.
one on the election day in November and then one on the Tuesday following Martin Luther King weekend.
Those four professional development days will now go until four p.m.
for staff.
This was the recommendation and proposal of the teachers union and in collaboration with our district team felt that it was a wonderful solution to the challenge that we have for next school year.
We love additional professional development time and adding that to an existing professional development day really allows a lot of breath and opportunity for the
what we are going to have the teachers engage in, especially the two days in August as we're getting ready to kick off the year.
That is the agreement that both sides came to in a memorandum of understanding.
And then the only additional piece that I want to call out, that is a change since the last time that I presented to this body, is a slight date change for Eid al-Fitr is now moved.
Mr. Pippicelli, is that March or May?
Okay, just making sure I had the correct month.
Previously we had it on March 10th, but it was brought to our attention due to the shift in the moon cycle that it is actually March 9th.
And so we made that change on the calendar that you have as part of your packet.
And I'm happy to answer any questions that you may have.
Motion for approval or anybody have any questions?
Member Graham.
And the district for the creative work.
And and make a note that this does.
Unevenly acknowledge religious holidays for this next year, and I just want to.
Make sure that the community understands that this is a
sort of an extraordinary calendar situation that we find ourselves in and that we would be revisiting and we would be coming back to our policy the year after this.
So this is indeed a one time event or maybe it happens every I don't know seven years or something.
I'm sure there's some it will happen again sometimes
in the future but you know I just want people to know that it's our full intention to observe our policy and the religious holidays that it lays out in future years.
Thank you member Graham.
So building on what member Graham said, I just want to make special recognition of Eid al-Adha, which is Monday the 17th.
That is now an in-school day and I want to make extra sure we are being sensitive there.
around that observation and understanding that that is an important day for many in our community.
We have school and I think recognizing that is really important.
That is the one holiday that isn't on a weekend or a day off now.
And I do not want this to be singling out our Muslim community members in this.
in not in having school on this day.
And I know we've had some challenges in the past ensuring that this is a no tests, no exams.
It's in May.
It's a tough time.
And I really want to build that awareness in the district.
I don't love that we were not able to give it off along with others.
I understand the challenges of staff, but I just I want to acknowledge that.
and how that lands.
I understand how extenuating these circumstances are, and I appreciate the work and the thoughtfulness that went into negotiating all of the pieces.
Calendars are far more complicated than I was expecting.
But just to recognize that this is a day that is in our policy, and this is kind of the one day where we are going to school against that policy.
So registering that.
Thank you, Member Reinfeldt.
Is there a motion to just quickly comment?
Yep, Dr. Galussi and then Ryan, our student rep would like to say a few words.
Okay, no, I appreciate the sentiment and the reminder.
The district has been doing a lot of planning and have engaged in a lot of conversation in the planning for next year.
We're actually dedicating some of our administrative retreat to that, but we're trying to
be proactive and make sure that some of the oversight that happened this year does not happen again.
So I thank you for that reminder.
Sorry about that, oh my god.
You said that Tuesday at the MLK Day is a professional development day, and I was just wondering, do the students not have school that day, or do we still have school?
Yes, there's no school that day, because it's a professional development day for the staff.
All right, just to make that clear.
Thank you, Ryan.
Is there a motion on the floor?
Member Graham, seconded by Member Lopate.
All those in favor?
Aye.
All those opposed?
New school calendar has been accepted.
Yay!
Last for superintendent reports is a recommendation to approve updated Medford Public Schools handbook.
Dr. Galussi.
Thank you very much.
So, I do believe that members have received copies.
I made sure that, well, first I will say that when I first presented this, it was tabled with feedback from this body for things to update, edit, and align.
And so, that work has been done.
And what I'm going to do this evening is
review what those updates and alignments were.
I know that you are equipped with the updates and recommendations from the previous school committee meeting on this, which is in May 18th.
Those remain still intact in terms of proposed changes.
And this evening, I'm going to talk about the updates.
So for this evening, the updates from the May 18th
All of the handbooks across the district have been updated so that the way school committee is represented is aligned.
All names and roles are listed as applicable and a link to the school committee tab on the Medford Public Schools website has been provided so that people can learn more about the school committee and know the channels to reach out if people want to communicate.
The second piece was elementary recess.
There was not necessarily an alignment that was needed here, but I think it's important to just recognize that Medford Public Schools believes that recess is an essential component for a child's physical, social, and emotional development and will not be withheld as disciplinary measure for anything other than direct logical consequence for an unsafe body.
That commitment is seen structurally in all four elementary handbooks across three distinct policies slash practices.
One is in the discipline code, which speaks specifically around practices for students' well-being and times when there may be an unsafe body and students may need to take time out to self-regulate.
The other one is under recess expectations where it is explicitly stated that the handbook protects recess and it may not be removed for consequences unless it's an unsafe body.
And then also in homework expectations where the handbooks specifically say that
Recess is not to be used for academic penalties, especially for homework.
Incompletion of homework will not result in the loss of recess.
And then I did say this at the last meeting, but I do think it's very important.
All four elementary schools are responsive classroom schools.
And so this is part of the tenets of responsive classroom, very much tied to logical consequences so that students are able to make connections between their behaviors
and consequences.
But I did have meetings with the elementary principals in order to review this and just remind what our expectations are around recess and the use of recess.
So if there's any further questions on that I'm happy to answer.
The next part was the Cori statement that Dr. Kroll put in her handbook and it is now within all of the handbooks so that regardless of the school, this statement that explains to caregivers how they complete a Cori is now part of all handbooks.
The other piece was around secondary attendance, specifically the middle schools, as there was not clear alignment for both schools.
And so there were a couple meetings had between myself and Principal Tucci and Principal Skane, and a lot of discussion to make sure that we're adding the clarity that was seen at the high school around the time that constitutes what a full day of school means and what does not
like what would equal an absence.
So in other words, students need to be present for three hours and 15 minutes in order for that day to be counted as a full day.
And at the end of this work,
Principal Skane pretty much aligned to the language that was in the McGlynn Middle School around attendance practices and language within the handbook.
I don't think I need to read all of them, all of that language, because it's pretty lengthy, unless you would like me to.
And then after...
this attendance piece, there was the academic dishonesty panel.
Oh, do you want me to pause, Mr. Russo?
Member Russo?
Thank you.
I know when we had met, we had talked about if recess is taken away, that there would be a, is this in here?
That we would, that each school would be logging exactly
that this has happened and that it will be collected by you and all the gory details.
I don't think this belongs in this, but I think it would be important to note it.
I also noticed that under the discipline code section, recess is still listed as one of the lots of building activities, assemblies, intramurals, field trips, extracurricular activities, and recess is still there.
So I'm not sure what changed.
No, because all of the four elementary schools were aligned.
there wasn't really a change in language.
So this piece under the, I would say that there's some repetitive nature to this.
So the discipline code and the recess expectations both are there for when students are exhibiting an unsafe body.
And sometimes that can happen during recess, and I would say that that's part of the recess expectations.
So sometimes when students are outside and engaged in recess, if they have an unsafe body,
They may need to remove themselves from play so that they can calm down, regulate.
is sometimes there are moments where a student is exhibiting unsafe behavior prior to recess and they're just not at a state where they're ready to be with their class as they're going to recess.
And so they may need to stay inside until they're able to regulate their body and then be able to join the class outside.
That all makes complete sense to me, but a serious conduct violation
refers the student to the office, appropriate disciplinary action will be determined by an administrator.
So if a student calls a teacher the F word, what is to prevent the administrator from determining that the loss of recess is an appropriate disciplinary action?
That isn't a logical consequence and I, not that I think it's okay if our students are doing that, I want to be clear, but it just, this is wide open for interpretation and I'm really still very uncomfortable that there is nothing in here that doesn't prevent one administrator from deciding that all kinds of things are reasons to take recess away.
and another administrator follows the intent, I think, that everybody sort of is on the same page with.
But if recess is just going to be listed there as something that can be a disciplinary consequence based on the opinion of an administrator and it has nothing to do with unsafe bodies, there's no mention of unsafe bodies here, I'm still uncomfortable with that as being the policy to approve this.
I can take it back to the elementary principals.
I have no problem adding the word unsafe.
I just wouldn't want to remove the school leader's autonomy in some of these situations where it very clearly may warrant that students are not safe to go to recess, which would fall under the discipline code, in my opinion.
I have no problem maybe adding a footnote or a parenthesis, but I don't want to remove that completely because all of this just has so many shades of gray.
It's not a concrete situation, and so to remove it completely I think may also hinder in some
problem solving capacity for school leaders.
I think I would be okay with it literally being in here the way it is.
We also added an administrative burden.
Something needs to be written up explaining why recess was taken away, perhaps sent home to the parent, as well as sent to the main office, to your office, for you to understand not once a year that there's an administrator who's taking recess away all the time.
Like, that's not helpful for the kid at the end of the year for you to find out that there's an administrator who has a very different understanding than the other administrators.
I mean, we all know that they're all coming to work with all the best intentions.
They're all individuals though and they're not working together in the same building and they can't see each other's, you know, learning from each other in a professional learning community is important but like,
our principals and assistant principals have an incredible amount of stuff to deal with on a daily basis.
So, I mean, I feel like there needs to be some way for you to know quickly, I mean, what if it's just a new administrator?
Like, that they do not understand that in Medford, taking recess away is not acceptable under most circumstances.
So,
if that can end up in here as well, because I think parents also need to know there's an expectation, because Facebook is the way we get it resolved now.
Facebook is how.
After nine years of school committee, Facebook is how I had found out that yes, there's some place where recess is still being taken away for things that the parents, at least, don't believe is appropriate.
And there's no teachers and there's no administrators having a dialogue on Facebook about what the behavior was and there shouldn't be.
So it's all very one-sided.
And I don't think the parents necessarily have the, the caregivers have the information they need.
to know this nuance.
And I don't want the school committee getting monthly reports of this.
I want you, because I know where you stand on this.
to be able to quickly respond when there is in fact a variance from what your expectations are of administrators.
And I want parents to know or caregivers to know that that's a real thing that's happening.
Because Facebook is just really
It's bad for the community.
It's bad for the sense of what Medford Public Schools represents.
It also puts those of us that get tagged in a really awful place because we can't find anything out about what actually happened and why it was taken away and because we don't have access to student information.
And I'm sure you don't enjoy
this topic coming up over and over again, year after year.
No, but I would say, I do appreciate data.
I have not heard of recess being taken away, and I'm not on... Right.
I think there's been four cases at least this year where it's become a Facebook topic.
And it's not that the caregivers are blowing anything out of perspective, they're not there,
and we're not there and the teachers and the administration aren't in that Facebook group and shouldn't be.
So, but it has a really, it has a pile on effect.
Oh yeah, this has been a problem forever and this is, we keep trying to fix it and the school committee says we fixed it and then it's like, you know, the next school year starts and it's again.
But, you know, as a school committee member, I don't know, is it again or is it like a kid was experiencing unsafe body at recess and they had to have, you know, some, I don't even think of it as consequences, just like an intervention in some way versus like, and I think that gets mixed up also because caregivers were students.
It gets mixed up with the, you know, I looked funny at a teacher when I was a kid and I didn't have recess for a week or I didn't do my homework so I couldn't have recess.
Those are things that aren't happening in Medford as far as I know and shouldn't be happening.
But caregivers all were students and we all have our memories that we bring to these things when they, the fire gets lit on Facebook.
And it's just bad for the district.
It's just not a good look.
So figuring out how to keep it from becoming an issue that ends up making people go to Facebook, especially now that Facebook allows anonymous posts, which drives me crazy.
But thank you.
Member Reinfeld?
So on that, what I would just love to see is that value statement that you just read.
I would like to see that in the handbook.
That clarifies what the conditions would be for that.
I thought it was a really good encapsulation of where we stand on recess.
And I see your argument for saying that this is, if the serious conduct violation is violence and physical...
invasion of another student's space during unstructured time.
I just think the value statement can make that clear and maybe resolve some of this without having to necessarily delete this.
I will say I've heard more reports of threats of recess being taken away or a few pieces being shaved off of recess.
And I don't know, one of the things that drives me nuts is threats that cannot be, like if you say you're gonna do something, that consequence needs to happen.
I've heard more incidents of,
threatening to take recess away and knowing that that's, is it a thing?
Is it not a thing?
So I think the value statement would clarify this for me.
I'm happy to add that in and I thank you for that additional data point.
I'll make sure I cover that with the principals.
So is that a motion as amended?
I think we're not done going through the changes.
I also had a couple of questions about the attendance.
I don't know if that's now or later.
Okay.
I will just note that major religious holidays is listed twice and I'm wondering if the second as a excused absences for major religious holidays and other reasons for absence may also include major religious holidays and I didn't know if that was supposed to be minor or if it was just repeated.
That's a consistency thing.
I think it's just repeated.
I'll bring that up.
And then I wanted to clarify it's a physician statement may be required so it is not necessarily required for when a student has a cold and the parent says student is going to be absent.
This is definitely a point question I get asked by parents.
Do I really need to get a doctor's note for
meeting some of these symptoms that are on the list, the very extensive list of don't send your children to school if these symptoms are here, and that the policy and the practice in this handbook is around repeated illness, chronic illness, some kind of acknowledgment that this is an extended medical circumstance rather than we are staying home because we are potentially contagious in this moment.
Yes.
And so I think
Because once students move, especially when you get to high school, and some of the unexcused absences really can impact your grade or your attendance, it is
It will be excused if there is a medical note explaining the reason for students to be home.
It's not that there isn't trust there.
It's just when the parent calls, if this is extending beyond a day or two and it's consecutive, then it is best to get a doctor's note.
But that one time, it can be the parents.
Yes.
They don't have to pony up for a co-payment.
If they don't have health insurance.
Yes.
No.
Very valid.
That's really.
Yes.
I appreciate that.
Thank you.
And they could always reach out to director Silva who has the relationship and the contact with Dr. Sabia because sometimes he will for your point about if families don't have health insurance or don't have a regular doctor.
That is why we have him here in the
school district and people can use that access if needed.
This is maybe a little bit off topic, but is that the sort of thing that having a larger teen health space in the high school would help with?
Potentially.
Okay.
All right.
My other questions are things you haven't presented yet, so I'll let that happen.
OK, so I'll move on?
Yeah.
OK.
So the academic dishonesty panel.
I think the bigger piece here, again, was the clarification statement that's at the front, not necessarily changes in the process, though there are some pieces at the bottom.
So this statement here about the academic dishonesty panel states that when academic dishonesty is suspected, teachers first address the concern privately with students to allow the students to clarify the situation.
If confirmed, the incident is logged in school brains, parents are notified, and progressive developmentally appropriate consequences are applied.
If the teacher and student disagree on the determination of academic dishonesty or the resulting consequences, the matter can be referred to the academic honesty panel.
This panel is composed of the principal or a designee,
A teacher and the student.
This panel functions as a formal appeals process to review documentation, hear perspectives, and make a definitive recorded determination to resolve the dispute.
So then the rest of the already approved.
Part of the academic dishonesty panel that is part of the AI policy talks about what that process is, talks about the consequence for the first offense, and then consequences for subsequent offenses.
And then there are additional notes that speak about repeated offenses and offenses that are tied to, like, for example, leadership roles or the honor society.
And then there is the purpose, the composition, and then student participation in the panel.
And there was discussion around
student participation and confidentiality so that if the student is part of this panel, but depending on the particular case that may go before the panel, there may not be student representation on that panel other than the student itself for confidentiality purposes.
Mm-hmm.
Thank you.
My question last time was around which teacher and which student.
The new text in the beginning seems to be a teacher, not necessarily the teacher involved in the dispute, but the student who was involved in the dispute.
Am I reading that correctly?
Yes.
OK.
Because that is not necessarily clear in panel composition, so I think it
Could the teacher on the panel be the teacher involved in the dispute, or is that not, or is it, it must be an outside teacher?
Do we have, have we laid that out?
I don't have that clarification.
Okay.
I would have to ask that question.
Yeah.
That, cause that was the clarification I was looking for is, is somebody evaluating their own judgment or is it necessarily someone who has not seen that, this content before?
I can have the conversation and bring it back, but I would assume it is a different educator that's not part of the initial.
Yeah.
That's how I read it in the opening text.
And yeah, I think we're just looking at definite articles and indefinite articles.
I know.
I'm happy for a language suggestion.
In my conversations with secondary leaders, this was very much
that the original policy already laid out what the first offense would be, what the second offense would be.
I think that's really clear.
I just want to know what teacher is evaluating it.
Well, in the conversations I had, this was very much to be used for appeal, review.
So is it the teacher and the student sitting down with the principal or their designee?
Is that the panel, or is there an outside?
No.
No, so it's an outside body.
No, because that's part of the initial, we're going to deal with this internally, confidentially between the student and the family and the teacher.
If we're invoking the panel, the principal may remain or the principal may decide a designee.
So maybe the assistant principal is more appropriate in this case and it would be a different teacher.
But there are not outside, so a different, so a teacher not involved in the initial disagreement.
That would be my suggested language.
Okay.
I'm just going to type that.
But the student on the panel is part of the panel or is just in the room?
The discussion for that based on confidentiality was said student.
Okay.
I think there... So there aren't other students reviewing a student's work?
No.
Okay.
I don't think that would necessarily be appropriate for confidentiality reasons.
I think as long as we clarify that it is a different teacher.
I'm not involved.
I'm willing to see how this plays out.
Yeah.
Yes.
A teacher not involved in the initial.
I think we're calling it a disagreement not a dispute.
Right.
Yes.
I can add that in.
Thank you.
Should I go on, or are there any other questions to this one?
Students?
Not on this one.
I had a couple of AI questions, but that's not new.
Student reps, yeah?
May I ask, why should it be a different teacher?
I'm sorry, what?
Why should it be a different teacher than the one that is not in the dispute?
So in the discussions, the panel would be,
The panel would be used when the disagreement can't be resolved at that initial original, with the original party.
So that would involve the teacher and the principal, maybe the caregiver or the parents, the student.
And so this would just be neutral, unbiased kind of perspective to hear the review and both sides.
Does that make sense?
Yes, thank you.
Thank you.
Should I keep going?
Yes, please.
OK.
And then the other pieces were around bus expectations.
So there are two pieces of bus expectations.
First is elementary schools.
There was great alignment.
There was always alignment around the elementary schools.
There were a few pieces missing that we felt would be important for families to be aware of, and some language that existed in the middle school bus expectations that was felt would be appropriate to bring over to the elementary bus expectations, and that was around
just making sure parents know the appropriate place to go for information, who the contact people are, statements around the bus.
over general expectations around the bus being an extension of the school day and therefore the same expectations that students have around their behavior and conduct while they're in school still applies to while they're on the bus.
Areas of that is around
Use of technology, remaining in their seats, how they're treating their peers, harassment, things around graffiti, things around their language.
So just to make sure that it's very clear for students and families what the expectations are when students ride the bus.
The other piece is we did, in this iteration of the handbook, did specifically name Eastern Bus.
I don't know if families think that Medford Public Schools owns their buses, but just to be clear who our vendor is and that Eastern Bus, as our vendor, does have surveillance within their buses, video and audio recording.
And so we wanted to make sure that that was part
of the handbook so that it's very clear for caregivers that that is part of Eastern bus, busing.
And then we left in some of the list of expectations and then just put in here the email address to transportation just to make sure it was all aligned with the email address and the phone number so caregivers knew exactly
how to contact Ina Williams, our transportation supervisor.
I'm not sure if you want me to go to middle school.
I could just really briefly say, middle school, the language really remained the same except adding in the extension of the day
expectations from school to transport to and from as well as the surveillance language so that it's very clear for our middle school families that Eastern buses are equipped with surveillance.
And those are the updates to transportation.
So with the extension of the school day connotation in the student handbook, does that mean students can't use their phones on the bus?
Correct.
I find that to be a little unfair because if you're walking home or driving home, I feel like you get to use your phone.
So if you're walking, so that means I feel like if we put that into the buses, we would also have to kind of allow it to walking home and driving.
And I feel like that's kind of,
makes an unequal opportunity for the use of technology.
Do you understand what I mean?
I do.
I 100% know what you mean.
I think the difficulty is, and remember, Ryan, right now I'm talking about elementary and middle school, so I'm not talking about high school.
The difficulty is for in school,
Cell phones are often away.
They're not used while you're in school on the school bus.
I understand where you're coming from but unfortunately what happens sometimes is inappropriate use of the cell phone which could be that we have found that sometimes there's inappropriate use of what people are viewing.
inappropriate use of taking pictures or taking videos of other students without their permission.
And so I understand that this might be really upsetting for some students to hear, but it provides a layer of safety for everybody.
on that short ride home.
And then once they're home, the caregivers can decide how the phones are being used.
But it really provides just a clear expectation for all students about what their experience on the bus is going to be.
I have a suggestion.
How about discipline the certain student that is using the technology inappropriately and let all the other well-behaved students get that kind of reward.
And how about disciplining the certain student and maybe banning the student
from the bus or having them sit next to the driver and the driver monitors the situation.
Yeah, just an idea.
I understand that, and that's a great idea.
Unfortunately, it's not necessarily attainable on every single bus.
for elementary and middle school.
We're trying really hard to put monitors on buses that would be helpful to have an additional adult on the bus.
But some buses, it's just the bus driver.
And so it's really hard to know where that consequence would need to lay.
And sometimes what we also want to do is lessen any sort of like,
group mentality that could be targeted.
I have another question.
Why is this for the elementary and middle schools and not for the high school?
I'm just wondering.
That's a great question, Ryan.
So the majority of the high school busing is the MBTA.
And so that is not necessarily part of the extension here of Medford Public Schools.
So that is difficult for us.
We have expectations, but it's difficult for us to, it's even more difficult for us to monitor that.
Why is it difficult if it's running, if, so the bus makes a trip only for the high school students.
So I'm wondering why is that difficult?
Well, maybe I should know this, but sitting here right now, I'm not quite sure if MBTA has surveillance.
Like, I'm not quite sure if there's video or audio recording on an MBTA bus.
Or, yes, or if they would give us access to that recording.
And we have that with Eastern Bus.
All right.
Thank you, Dr. Golosi.
Thank you, Ryan.
And that's it for updates on this part.
So you have two, our updates from May 18, and then
this evening's updates and I do have notes of language that I will update regarding who's in attendance for a panel review, the duplicate of major religious holidays, and the addition of the elementary recess statement.
Member Parks.
Is it possible?
I know some of our schools have assigned seats and some don't.
Is that something that might be in one of these policies or is that not something that would be?
Sometimes I struggle a little bit between that fine balance between alignment and autonomy.
And yes, we could probably be maybe a little bit more aligned than we currently are.
Most of the schools, one of the things that I did talk to the principals about is a lot of the schools will have, I guess for lack of a better word, developmental seating so that the older kids are sitting in the bus.
fifth graders all the way up to kindergarten, and it goes that way.
And if there are siblings, then the older siblings have to sit in the front with their younger sibling and not vice versa.
But maybe with the absence of one school, assigned seating is usually a consequence.
for a student that is not following the bus expectations and need a specific seat so that they are within either two things, removed from some peers that they're having difficulty with and or in eyesight of the bus driver or near the monitor if it is a bus that has a monitor.
That's typically how it goes.
Again, I'm happy to have that conversation but there is a.
There is a slight autonomy piece.
I think we know alignment is critical.
And it helps, but we also have four schools that are so different.
And even if we just look at enrollment on the bus, some of our schools don't have the sheer number of students that ride the bus as other schools do.
So I hate to kind of make a blanket statement around
seat assignments that may be really hindering one school versus the other where right now it's kind of used as a consequence.
But I'm happy to revisit that if it doesn't go well.
I would just like to
motion to put a line in the A.I.
guidance that A.I.
tool educators should not use A.I.
tools to provide feedback or assign grades.
We had just to be very clear that A.I.
should not be grading
people's work, and this can go in the educational staff section, but I realize that the educational staff section is not in the McGlynn Middle School handbook.
It is in the Andrews and the high school.
but the McGlynn Middle only has the student use of AI.
I think there's, we've discussed many times in this committee that there's going to be a space to review the AI policy in general, but I think we need a clarification about grading in these handbooks that are going out next year, just because we did see some confusion around that in this school year.
Okay, so I'll make sure that section is added to the McGuinn medal and that's added.
And to be clear, this can go, we have the line educators use of generative AI should not be used as a, it should be used as a tool to support to the teaching and learning environment, but does not to be solely relied upon in place of educator review and judgment.
Grading is sort of covered there, but I think an explicit line that these tools are not to be used to provide direct feedback or assign grades to students.
Thank you for specifically calling that out.
It's page 27 in Andrews 47 in Medford High School and as noted not in the McGlynn.
That's a member I feel that's good for you.
Ryan.
So does that mean teachers can or cannot use AI to create lessons?
Member Reinfeld?
Those guidelines outline how teachers can use in lesson planning, preparing assessments.
The guidelines go through that.
It is just the grading that I want, that needs to change.
So the teachers can use AI just in a certain way, right?
Yes.
All right.
Thank you for cleaning that up.
Any motions or further questions?
Member Rousseau?
Motion to table to the next meeting until we see the recess update.
Sorry.
Motion to table by Member Rousseau.
Second.
Seconded by Member Olopade.
All those in favor?
Aye.
All those opposed?
Motion is tabled to see the revised edits.
Member Graham.
Ask my colleagues who provided a lot of feedback to maybe check in with the superintendent before the next meeting so that
Yeah, we can actually get it done in our last meeting.
Thank you.
Sounds good.
I'm fine with everything you said.
I just don't want to do it again.
We do not have any presentations of advisory council or presentations of the public.
We do have two resolutions.
No continued business with new business.
2026-12 offered
Member Reinfeldt and Member Rousseau, this is an update to policy JJH student travel.
Would you like me to turn it over to you for a quick update?
Motion?
Member Graham?
I said motion to waive the reading.
Motion seconded by Member Rousseau.
All those in favor?
Aye.
All those opposed?
Member Reinfeldt and Member Rousseau, would you like to?
Member Reinfeldt.
It is not the state law, but it is our policy to approve field trips.
We have discovered that occasionally when people have
suddenly qualify for a national competition and have to go out of state between meetings, we don't have a procedure for approving that.
So this attempts to put that in place without adding excess meetings.
The only reason we would meet about that would be if there were something controversial and we needed to actively discuss it.
Motion to approve.
Yes, and if in between readings, if we can make sure Attorney Greenspan reviewed this, I don't know.
I just want to make sure we don't have to be BCC'd to not violate open meeting law.
Motion for approval, seconded.
Roll call.
Member Graham.
Yes.
Member Mastrobonni.
Member Olopade.
Yes.
Member Parks.
Member Rheinfeld.
Yes.
Member Rossell.
Yes, seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative.
First reading is approved.
It will be run by Attorney Greenspan on exactly how to email us.
And then we'll take our third reading next time.
2026-13, resolution to establish a special education reserve fund for Medford.
Whereas the Medford Public School District
Thank you.
Motion to waive the reading by Member Graham, seconded by Member Reinfeld.
All those in favor?
Aye.
All those opposed?
The reading is waived.
If somebody could give an explanation.
I'll turn it over to you, Member Parks, as it's your resolution, if you don't mind.
Okay.
So this resolution is to establish a special ed reserve fund for Medford, which I learned about
when I was attending the charting the course training when I first started this role and basically it allows us to
put aside up to 2% of our total annual expenditures into a reserve fund, an interest bearing fund that can be used for unanticipated or unbudgeted costs of special ed services and programming out of district tuition for students.
special education transportation services and recovery high school program tuition.
And given that we have consistently seen fluctuating costs year over year and students move in mid year requiring these services.
And that has not been budgeted for at the beginning of the year.
This fund would be able to help offset those costs as it grows.
And so this resolution is to help with that.
Motion to approve by Member Reinfeldt, seconded by Member Graham.
All those in favor?
Aye.
Oh, wait, there is one correction, though, actually, in it.
Before the roll is called, Member Rousseau.
Thank you.
I'd like to amend 3E.
The current language is, current language is, any other permissible revenue, I'm sorry, 3E, other extraordinary expenses related to special education staffing, evaluation and assessment services.
What I would like to say is extraordinary expenses related to special education staffing, evaluation and assessment services that were not anticipated in the current fiscal year's operating budget provided that any such expense funded through the reserve shall be incorporated into the district's annual operating budget in the subsequent fiscal year and may not be funded through the reserve in consecutive fiscal years.
My concern is that we will
treat this like we do with other slush funds if you will revolving accounts and I don't if this year we need a new teacher because we have some new needs we absolutely that's the purpose of this next year.
Because we don't have enough money in the budget, that is not a use for this fund.
So looking at the law, the law doesn't say anything about this.
We literally could just fund our special ed department through this fund, which would be crazy.
And I want to make sure that whatever we do, we're making it clear that this is for this year only.
So that's my amendment.
The expenditure is just for that certain year?
So it's not for year over year cost is what you're saying.
I'm saying if you, you know, we have a student moves in and has a very specific special need and requires a certain kind of staff member and we hire them and the student is here next year too, that fund is not paying for next year.
That is an operating budget.
Yes, it's not an ongoing operating cost that we continue to take from.
Yes.
has to get into the budget no matter what on earth that means.
Which is my understanding of the intent of this, but it does feel like a little bit of an open door for maybe around 10 years.
No, that is the intent of it.
And that was also sort of the intent of putting in, maintaining a minimum balance in this fund so that A, there would be something that continuously collects interest in the account, but also to prevent it from drawing it down completely.
once we get it to that minimum place.
And if you accept it as a friendly amendment, then we don't have to... Yes.
Okay.
Member Reinfeld.
Sorry, this is procedural.
Since I made the motion, do I need to accept it, or can Member Parks accept?
I will, if Member Parks is comfortable, I accept this as part of the motion.
There is one correction, though.
It's I'm going to city council on June 23rd and not June 9th, as it says.
I will accept that amendment as well.
What was the date?
Sorry.
June 23rd.
OK.
And I think we probably need a roll call vote.
Who first and seconded that?
Sorry.
I first.
Roll call as amended.
Thank you.
Second.
Member Graham.
Yes.
Member Mastroboni.
Member Olopade.
Yes.
Member Parkes.
Member Reinfeldt.
Yes.
Member Rousseau.
Mayor Legault-Kern.
Yes.
Seven in the affirmative, zero in the negative.
Paper passes.
No reports requested.
Condolences.
The members of the Medford School Committee expressed their sincerest condolences to the family of Maureen Hennigan, who was a dedicated member of the Medford Public Schools for 28 years, most recently at the Andrews Middle School.
This loss is deeply felt across our entire district.
Maureen's former husband, William Hennigan, and her grandchildren are members of the Missittuck School community.
If we all may rise for a moment of silence, please.
Our next regular meeting is June 15th, next Monday at 5 p.m.
executive 530 executive session.
We got to figure that out and 6 p.m.
meeting 5 here in the Alden Memorial Chambers and in addition to Zoom.
Is there a motion to adjourn?
By member Reinfeld, seconded by member Graham.
All those in