you
My dad's always at Everett, my mom's at work. If you walk into the study hall five seconds late to where you're supposed to go, you're just throwing up.
I'm Victoria here with Mr. Glucy, the coach of the girls lacrosse team. Hi, Mr. Glucy. How are you? Hi, Victoria. How are you? I'm great. I'm good, thanks. So Mr. Glucy, can you tell me a little bit about the season so far? Yeah, sure. This season is definitely like a rebuilding year. We graduated 12 seniors last year. So we are taking our lumps, for lack of a better term. We're working really hard. Great group of girls. They come with a great attitude. And we're kind of learning on the fly. So wins are few and far between, but we're definitely getting better every day.
Well, I know you had a nice game against Malden yesterday. Can you tell me a little bit about that? Yeah, sure. We beat Malden, I think it was 12 to 2, 14 to 2, something along those lines. Games like that are tough, lopsided victories like that. It was nice to get everybody in, everybody played. So many people contributed. Vic Paris had five goals. Brie Forcier had three or four goals. I mean, girls, it's nice to see. And those are some of our younger players, Vic's a sophomore.
Breeza Jr. Defense looked great. Both goalies played, Madison Daugherty and Patty McLean, both looked great in cage. So we have a lot of building blocks and we took steps towards that yesterday. It's just, it's tough sometimes. So one thing we've been really fortunate, we have a junior captain this year, Ailish Fallon. She's doing a tremendous job. She really gets the girls motivated. You know, we only have four seniors on the team, Hannah O'Brien, Joe McCarthy, Alex Joba, and Katie Covino.
It's tough with a lot of younger girls and not a lot of older girls. I just want to give hats off to Eilish doing a really nice job keeping us together and keeping us motivated through this tough season. Good job Eilish. Well good luck for the rest of your season. I hope you get some more wins. I do too. Thanks for all that you do. Mustang Report is awesome. Thank you. You're welcome. The answer to last week's Mustang Report question of the week is, let's go crazy.
Hola, would you believe what Senora Lepore did in Australia? Hi there, I'm Mr. Wilson, a math teacher at Medford High School and advisor to the Key Club. So, what is your role in the blood drive?
Well, I have organized the blood drive here with the help of my key clubbers and so that entailed getting in touch with the Red Cross and getting them here to Medford High School today and setting up all these tables that you can see if you pan around the room and getting these nurses here and
making sure we have people to help, to sign people in. Okay, over to your left over there, you can see we have a sign-in table. Some people are waiting to have their blood drawn right now. And some people are having their blood drawn as we speak. And then these people here are just having a snack while they kind of wait to not feel so lightheaded before they can go back to class.
How many people have participated in the blood drive? We had roughly 60 people sign up for the blood drive. And our goal was to accumulate 40 units of blood overall. Because sometimes, even if you want to donate, there's some reason or another that you might not be able to. So that's why we have more people than we really are looking to get sign up. So we had about 60 sign up. I'm Victoria here with Mr. Richards, who's participating in Buzz Off Cancer on June 5th.
So Mr. Richards, can you tell me a little bit about it? The Buzz Off for Kids is a fundraiser to all the proceeds go to Kids for Cancer. It's held at Gillette Stadium. Everyone goes there that's participating, and they buzz their heads as their way of showing their support for these kids with cancer. Our site, you can donate at buzzforkids.org.
And we're team HEMO, H-E-E-M-O. There's a few other teachers from the city. HEMO was a student at the McGlynn School. He lost his battle with cancer. His family still goes to the Memphis Public Schools. I have two of his sisters that come to our summer camp. And one of his sisters participates with us. She buzzes her head also.
But it's a great charity, it's a great event. Some Patriots players show up. Last year, Rob Gronkowski buzzed his head with everybody. So, you know, it's just something that we're trying to do to give back to this charity. That sounds great. Thank you, Mr. Richards, and good luck. Thanks.