And we're back with the Mustang Report. Before I go, I want to say one thing. I get the opportunity to announce the graduation speaker for next year, for this year, actually, 2016. It was a very, very close vote. The difference was two votes. I had to recount it three times. The graduation speaker for this year, I'd like him to come down here, is Mr. Michael Skorka.
Ha ha ha!
The money that you have donated today will go back to the children living in public schools and we appreciate it.
Dashing through the snow In a one-horse open sleigh O'er the fields we go Laughing all the way The bells on bobtail ring They make our spirits bright What fun it is to ride And sing a sleighing song tonight Jingle bells, jingle bells Jingle all the way Oh, what fun it is to ride In a one-horse open sleigh Jingle bells, jingle bells
What fun it is to ride in a one-horse open sleigh!
A day or two ago, I thought I'd take a ride, And soon Miss Fanny Bright was seated by my side. The horse was lean and lank, Miss Fortune seemed his lot, He got into a drifted bank and wee-wee got upside.
Jingle bells, jingle bells, jingle all the way. Oh what fun it is to ride in a one horse open sleigh. Jingle bells, jingle bells, jingle all the way. Oh what fun it is to ride in a one horse open sleigh.
It's the most wonderful time of the year
With the kids jingle-belling and everyone telling you be of good cheer It's the most wonderful time of the year It's the hap-happiest season of all
With those holiday greetings and gay happy meetings when friends come to call, it's the happiest season of all. There'll be parties for hosting, marshmallows for toasting, and caroling out in the snow. There'll be scary ghost stories and tales of the glories of Christmas as well.
It's the most wonderful time of the year. There'll be much to see. 5, 4, 3, 2, 1.
Seniors! Whoa, right here! Oh my god, we're like totals!
on the left and you have down the right. No, running. They're trying to get open. Okay, so I'll look for that. So what about like blocking? I'm blocking. Okay, so you guys got to be like a tight link because they're coming right in the camera.
Oh say can you see, by the dawn's early light, what so proudly.
1, 2, 3, Green Team! That makes sense to me.
I think it's going really well, much better than last year. So I think we have him already. Game's over. Game's over. Good luck, Mr. Murdoch.
That's a nice crowd. Worth every penny. Worth every penny. Hey, watch the D now. Watch the D.
Yeah!
I think both sides did their homework on each other. They prepared defensively.
Right now it's pretty tough to move the ball down the field on either side, so it seems like it's whoever has the ball last may win the game. We'll see. A little sore. I think the last time I played flag football was about 40 years ago.
Right back, right back, right back, right back. Go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go,
Up, up, up, up! Yeah!
How are you? I'm here with Jackie Dempsey at the second annual Air Force 95 football game. And Jackie Dempsey just got the second touchdown, I was going to say home run, for the great team. How do you feel? You know, I'm pretty excited. We've got this amazing quarterback, stellar defense. Go Jackie!
I got it! I got it! I got it! I got it! I got it! I got it!
Oh, you are good.
So Mr. Michels, this is your first flag football game, faculty flag football game, how are you feeling? Pretty tired right now, I'm not going to lie to you, I'm in bad shape, but it's a pretty fun experience, it's awesome. How did it feel when you got that first touchdown for your team? I was nervous I was going to drop it, I was wide open, but luckily I caught it, it felt pretty good to get on the board. Well hopefully you get some more, and good luck tonight. Thank you very much, thank you.
The teams are just so good that there's no winner.
is the day when we will do battle with them, where the Mustangs will show their Mustang pride, their Mustang spirit, where they will dig a little deeper to make sure that they come out victorious against all odds!
7, 1, 9, 4.
There'll be scary ghost stories and tales of the glories of Christmases long, long ago