If you're taking your T7 soon, whether it's in just a few weeks or in a few months and you're a little bit scared or maybe a lot scared of the science section, this video is for you.
In this video, we're gonna be going over the most realistic and aligned free T7 practice test.
We're gonna be answering questions on chemistry, A&P, scientific reasoning, and biology.
This is the most legit free test that you're going to find.
We also offer a reading, math, and English test.
You can sign up to take those tests using the link in the description below.
Make sure that you grab a pen and a piece of paper.
because not only am I going to be explaining to you why the correct answers are correct, I'm going to be explaining to you why they're incorrect.
So before we dive on in, I do want to remind you that if you're taking your TEAS exam, taking a practice test is the best thing for you to do, especially in the very beginning.
The number one mistake that we see students make
people find out that they have to take this test and they just start studying random stuff and they have no idea what's actually on the test, how in-depth or not in-depth the test is, and people get really stressed out and they get really overwhelmed or they just straight-up study the wrong thing.
So taking a practice test is
and figuring out what is actually on the test, what is not on the test, what do I know, what do I not know, that allows you to be able to gauge how ready you are for each section of the exam, and it'll allow you to also gauge what it is you need to study.
So thank you for being here.
You're doing the right thing by taking a TEAS practice test.
So without further ado, let's get on into it.
Okay, so let's dive right on into our first question, which looks like it's going to be on A and P. A patient presents with excessive bruising, excessive bleeding, and slow wound healing.
Which of the following does the patient's blood test reveal?
A low platelet count, high antibody count, high red blood cell count, or low white blood cell count?
the right answer is going to be A, low platelet count.
So let's talk about why the correct answer is low platelet count.
So as you probably remember, platelets are tiny cell fragments in the blood that help form clots to stop bleeding.
So in this question,
when someone is experiencing excessive bruising, excessive bleeding, and slow wound healing, that's because their blood is not clotting as well as it should be, which would indicate low platelet count.
So this is a great question to get the test started with because you will definitely see questions like this.
So it's not always a matter of knowing your vocabulary words and memorizing
This is a great example of why it's important to understand context.
Let's go to our next question.
Blood oxygen levels are most likely low when blood does which of the following?
Leaves the aorta, fills the right atrium, reaches the body's tissues, or flows through the arteries?
The right answer here is fills the right atrium.
So the right atrium is one of the four chambers of the heart and it's where blood returns from the body after it has delivered oxygen to the tissues.
So the blood is now lower in oxygen because it has already been used by the body cells.
So when the blood fills up the right atrium, it's carrying less oxygen and is on its way to the lungs to pick up more.
So let's talk about why the other answers are incorrect, leaving the aorta.
So the aorta is the largest artery in the body, and it carries oxygen-rich blood directly from the heart to the rest of the body.
And blood in the aorta has just come from the lungs where it was just reoxygenated, so now it is high and oxygen not low.
reaches the body's tissue.
So this is incorrect because when blood reaches the body tissues, it is delivering oxygen to them.
This means that it is still high in oxygen when it arrives at the tissues.
It only becomes low in oxygen after it has delivered the oxygen and is on its way back to the heart.
And lastly, flows through the arteries.
So arteries generally carry oxygen-rich blood from the heart to the different parts of the body.
The only exception to this is the pulmonary arteries, which carry oxygen-poor blood from the heart to the lungs.
However, in general, blood flowing through the arteries is usually high in oxygen.
An intracellular chemical signal can be produced in the cell membrane.
Once it is produced, it goes to which of the following?
A, to a different cell.
B, to another part of the same cell.
C, to a region right outside of the cell.
Or D, to an area with high ion concentration.
The correct answer to this is B, to another part of the same cell.
So an intracellular chemical signal is a signal which is produced inside of a cell.
That's what the intra part means.
And what it does is it communicates information within that same cell.
So when this signal is created, usually that happens inside of the cell membrane, it travels to another part within the same cell to carry out specific functions.
An example of a function might be something like activating enzymes.
All in all, intracellular signals are designed to act within the same cell where they are produced and traveling to different areas of that cell to carry out their task.
All of these other answer options here are talking about intercellular signals, which would mean that the signal would have to leave the cell or go to unrelated areas.
Which of the following enzymes breaks down proteins?
Is it A, amylase, B, lactase, C, pepsin, or D, suocrase?
So this is a great question because on the TEAS exam, you're going to have questions that come up on
macromolecules kind of in two different ways.
So you're going to see questions like this where it's really related to A and P, specifically the gastrointestinal system.
And then you're also going to see questions about macromolecules
asked of you in more of the sense of a biology question.
So it's really important that you really understand your macromolecules, also known as your biomolecules, really well through and through, because there's a good chance that you're gonna be asked an A and P as well as a biology question about them.
So in this case, the correct answer is C, pepsin.
So the reason that pepsin is the correct answer is because pepsin is an enzyme that is specifically helps break down proteins into smaller pieces, making it easier for the body to digest them.
Pepsin is produced in the stomach where it works best in the acidic environment to start protein digestion.
Let's talk about why the other three are incorrect.
So amylase is the enzyme that breaks down starches, meaning complex carbohydrates into simple sugars,
It basically doesn't have anything to do with proteins at all.
Lactase.
Lactase is an enzyme that breaks down lactose, that's the sugar found in milk, into simpler sugars.
So lactase works on lactose, not proteins, that's why it's incorrect.
And lastly, sucrose is an enzyme that breaks down sucrose, which is basically table sugar, into simpler sugars, which are
for example, like glucose.
Therefore, petsin is the right answer because it's the only enzyme, at least on this list, that breaks down proteins.
The diffusion of nutrients through the walls of the digestive system is critical to homeostasis in the body.
The majority of this diffusion takes place in which of the following areas of the digestive system?
The large intestine, the colon, the liver,
or the small intestine?
The correct answer here is the small intestine.
Okay, so the small intestine is where the majority of nutrient absorption takes place in the digestive system.
The walls inside of the small intestine are lined with tiny structures called villi and microvilli, and that increases the surface area, making it highly efficient at absorbing nutrients and passing them into the bloodstream.
This is obviously essential for homeostasis as the body needs these nutrients to function properly.
Well, let's talk about why the other options are incorrect.
large intestine.
The large intestine mainly absorbs water and some minerals, but it does not play a major role in absorbing nutrients from food.
By the time food reaches the large intestine, most of the nutrients have already been absorbed.
The colon is part of the large intestine and has a similar role in absorbing water and minerals.
It helps to form solid waste, but it's not involved in the significant absorption of nutrients.
And lastly, the liver does not absorb any nutrients from the digestive system.
Instead, it processes and it stores nutrients after they have been absorbed by the small intestine.
So the small intestine is the primary site for nutrient absorption in the body, while the large intestine, colon, and liver have very different functions in the digestive system and they do not absorb nutrients.
As soon as this invader enters the body, the body initiates immunological responses.
Which of the following is the name of this invader?
Is it A, foreign particles, B, pathogen, C, toxin, or D, vaccine?
The correct answer is B, pathogen.
So a pathogen is a harmful microorganism.
This can be anything such as a virus, a bacteria, or a fungus, and a pathogen can cause disease.
So when a pathogen enters the body, it triggers an immune response because the body is recognizing it as a threat.
On the TEAS exam, you're going to want to make sure that you study microorganisms.
You're going to want to make sure that you understand different types of transmissions of diseases, immunity responses, as well as you're going to want to have a really good understanding of the different types of microorganisms, the harmful kinds like a pathogen, and also the beneficial kind.
Which of the following muscles do circulating hormones stimulate?
Extension, flexor, skeletal, or smooth?
Okay, the answer for this question is D, smooth muscles.
Okay, so smooth muscles
are found in places like the walls of the blood vessels, the digestive tract, as well as the bladder.
And they respond to circulating hormones in the body, which can cause them to contract or relax to help control processes like blood flow, digestion, as well as waste elimination.
These muscles work automatically, meaning involuntarily, and are directly affected by hormones.
The other three answer choices are incorrect, so let's talk about why.
So extension is a type of movement, it's not a type of muscle.
Flexors are a type of muscle that causes bending at the joints, like when you bend your elbow.
Flexor muscles are usually skeletal muscles that are controlled by the nervous system, not by hormones.
And then skeletal muscles are the muscles attached to the bones that control voluntary movements like walking or
picking up a piece of apple pie.
These muscles are controlled by nerve signals rather than by hormones.
If this practice test is making you feel like you definitely have some studying to do in the science section, just know that you are not alone.
And that is exactly why the T7 online course exists.
The T7 online course helps you relearn and freshen up your knowledge about everything that we've seen so far on the science topics, that's A&P, chemistry, scientific reasoning, and biology.
In addition, the T7 online course goes over everything you need to know for reading, English, and math.
You're gonna have way more than just practice questions.
You're also going to find flashcards, educational video lessons, and interactive study modules.
and get everything you need to pass your TEAS exam with Smart Addition Academy's T7 online course.
Check it out at www.smartadditionacademy.com.
Okay, so this is our first question on scientific reasoning.
You are going to have eight scored scientific reasoning questions.
When you take your real TEAS exam, scientific reasoning is anything like designing an experiment,
scientific method, inductive, deductive, reasoning, as well as things like conversions and scientific measurements.
So which of the following actions contribute to minimizing bias when selecting a sample for an experiment?
Selecting participants based on personal beliefs, using convenience sampling methods, ensuring that the sample represents the population of interest,
choosing participants from a single geographic location.
Okay so the correct answer for this is going to be C, ensuring that the sample represents the population of interest.
So with this question, it's asking you about eliminating bias.
So when you're conducting an experiment, it's important that you have a sample that accurately represents the larger population in which you are studying.
This helps ensure that the findings are reliable and they can be applied to the whole population, not just a specific group like question D talking about a specific geographic area.
By selecting a representative sample, you minimize bias, meaning your results are going to be more fair and accurate.
If a person smells something sweet, which of the following forms of information is this initially perceived as in the nervous system?
Cognitive, integrative, motor, or sensory?
The correct answer is sensory.
So when a person smells something sweet, the information is first picked up by the sensory receptors in the nose.
And these receptors send signals to the brain about the smell.
which is an example of sensory information.
Sensory information can be defined as data gathered from the senses like smell, taste, touch, hearing, and sight.
Here's why the other answers are not correct.
So a cognitive process includes things like thinking, reasoning, and understanding.
Recognizing and thinking about a smell might come later, but the initial detection of the sweet smell is sensory.
It's not cognitive.
Your integrative processes, they happen when the brain combines sensory information with other information to make sense of it.
But since we're talking about the initial perception of the sweet smell is purely sensory, the integrative aspect of it would happen after the sensory data is received.
And motor information involves movement, like moving your muscles to walk or grab something sweet.
Smelling something is not related to movement, so it does not involve motor information.
While hiking, a person is startled after encountering a bear.
Her palms get sweaty and her heart starts racing.
Which of the following parts of her nervous system was directly stimulated?
Central, parasympathetic, somatic, or sympathetic?
The answer is D, sympathetic.
So the sympathetic nervous system is part of the anatomic nervous system and it is responsible for that fight or flight response that we are all so familiar with.
So when a person is encountering something scary or stressful like a bear on a hike, the sympathetic nervous system would be activated causing physical changes such as sweaty palms and a racing heart.
These reactions are basically preparing the body to either fight the bear or flee from the danger of the bear.
So central nervous system would be incorrect because the CNS consists of the brain and the spinal cord.
And while the CNS processes the information and sends the signals, the physical reactions like the sweaty palms and the racing heart are controlled by the anatomic nervous system, not in the CNS directly.
The parasympathetic nervous system is the rest and digest system, which just helps the body relax and return to a normal state after a stressful event.
So in this case, it would slow down the heart rate and calm the body down.
The somnomic nervous system controls involuntary movements like moving muscles to walk or pick up something, but it doesn't control the anatomic or automatic reactions like sweating and heart rate changes in response to stress.
Which of the following types of tissues include cells of the immune system and of the blood?
Connective, epithelial, muscles, or neural?
The answer is A, connective.
Connective tissue is a broad category of tissue that includes several types of cells including cells of the immune system like white blood cells and cells of the blood like red and white blood cells.
So blood is considered a type of connective tissue because it connects and it transports essential substances throughout the body.
So epithelial tissue covers the surfaces of the body.
This is things like the lining of the organs or the skin.
It acts as a protective barrier, but does not contain immune or blood cells.
Muscle tissue is responsible for movement, and it is made up of muscle cells.
And neural tissues make up the brain, the spinal cord, and of course, the nerves.
It's involved in transmitting nerve signals, but it does not include blood or immune cells.
So that's why connective tissue is the correct answer.
Which of the following correctly describes homeostasis?
A functional system of the body, blood flow to every cell in the body, a relatively constant environment within the body, or neural pathways that have integrated into the body.
The correct answer is C, a relatively constant environment within the body.
So homeostasis refers to the body's ability to maintain a stable internal environment despite changes in the external environment.
So this can include things like keeping the body temperature regulated, blood pressure, and pH levels within a narrow and optimal
range for proper functioning.
The body uses feedback mechanisms to regulate these processes and ensures that everything stays in balance.
When you take your TEAS exam, not only should you expect to answer questions for each of the systems within the A and P questions, you'll definitely be presented on questions on homeostasis.
So make sure that you have a really good understanding of homeostasis.
So fertilization, which is the fusing of one sperm and an ovum, results in which of the following?
Embryo, fetus, an infant, or a zygote?
The correct answer here is a zygote.
So fertilization occurs when a sperm cell from the male fuses with an ovum,
also known as an egg from a female.
This union forms a single cell called a zygote.
The zygote contains all of the genetic material needed to develop into a new organism.
It is basically the very first stage after fertilization.
So an embryo, a fetus, and an infant will all happen after that, after the zygote is formed.
They're basically just later stages of development.
Which of the following are included in the male reproductive system?
The penis and the epididymis, the vas deferens and uterus, the penis and the fallopian tubes, the penis, scrotum, and cervix.
The answer is A, the penis and the epididymis.
So the penis and the epididymis are both inside of the male reproductive system, which are the organs responsible for producing and delivering sperm for reproduction purposes.
The penis is the external organ used for sexual intercourse and the delivery of sperm, while the epididymis is a coiled tube
located behind the testes where sperm mature and are stored.
Technically, the scrotum and the vas deferens are also part of the reproductive system.
However, the uterus and the cervix are part of the female reproductive system.
So those answers are incorrect.
Which phenomenon begins with red blood cells releasing oxygen to the other cells in the body?
Is it air conduction, cellular respiration, internal respiration, or pulmonary ventilation?
So the correct answer here is C, internal respiration.
Before we talk about why internal respiration is the correct answer, I do wanna make a point that on your TEAS exam, you should be prepared to study cellular respiration, cellular reproduction are all things that you should study as they may show up on the biology questions of your exam.
So internal respiration is the process where oxygen is released from the red blood cells into the tissues and the cells of the body.
this occurs in the capillaries where oxygen moves from the blood to the cells and carbon dioxide moves from the cells into the blood to be carried away for exhalation.
This is a crucial part of how the body gets oxygen to the cells and removes waste gases.
So air conduction refers to the movement of air through the respiratory system such as like through the nose and through the trachea
but it does not directly involve the exchange of oxygen between blood and the body cells.
Cellular respiration is the process by which cells use oxygen to produce energy, also known as ATP, and release carbohydrate as a waste product.
But this process happens inside of cells, and it's not really about the release of oxygen from red blood cells like this question is asking.
And pulmonary ventilation
is the process of basically breathing in or inhaling and breathing out.
And it involves the movement of air into and out of the lungs, but it does not directly involve the exchange of gases between the blood and the body tissue.
So that is why internal respiration is correct because it is the exchange of gases like oxygen between the blood and the body's cells.
The correct answer is D, the cardiovascular system.
So hemopoiethesis is the process by which blood cells, such as red blood cells, are produced and it occurs in the bone marrow of the skeletal system.
So once these blood cells are produced, they enter the bloodstream, which is then part of the cardiovascular system.
The blood cells are then transported throughout the body via blood vessels, playing crucial roles in oxygen transport, immune defense, and clotting.
The other systems such as the urinary, digestive, and muscular system, they just don't play a direct role in the production or the transportation of blood cells.
So the urethra is the final structure through which urine travels to exit the body.
When it's time to urinate, the urine moves from the bladder through the urethra and then it is expelled from the body.
Why did it take many years for the cell theory to be developed?
Advancements in microscopy took place slowly.
Cells were difficult to isolate for experimental analysis.
Researchers believed a cell formed from pre-existing cells.
Or scientists already proved that cells were essential for life.
Okay, the correct answer here is advancements in microscopy took place slowly.
And before I dive a little deeper into why this is the correct answer, I do also want to say that this is cell theory as well as microscopy is going to be something that you should expect at least one to two questions on, on your exam.
It's really important to understand
pretty much everything there is to know about cells from a biology subject matter context.
So cell type, cell function, plant cell versus animal cell, cellular respiration, and cellular reproduction as I mentioned earlier.
In addition, you want to know
microscopy in terms of the different types of popular microscopes that you would use in a scientific lab setting.
And you also want to know things like the different types of like glass containers, different types of scales and things like that.
And you want to understand the advantages and different that you want to understand the advantages as well as the disadvantages of different types of microscopes.
So as a refresher,
The cell theory states that all the things are made up of cells and that cells are the basic unit of structure and function in living things.
But it took a really long time for this idea to develop because microscopy technology, which is the tools you use to actually see the cells, it really took a while to improve and develop over time.
Early microscopes were not powerful enough to observe the small details of cells and scientists really could not make accurate
conclusions about cells until the microscopes got better.
Which term describes complex carbohydrate molecules consisting of numerous monosaccharide units?
Is it monomers, diosaccharides, polysaccharides, or oligosaccharides?
So this is one of those questions
that I was alluding to in the beginning of the video when we first had that question about enzymes that help digest proteins.
And I was saying that it's really important to have a good understanding of macromolecules because you will see questions on it kind of in an A and P context.
And then you're going to see questions on macromolecules in more of a biology context, which is going to be just a little bit more detailed than what you would see in an A and P setting.
This is a prime example of that.
And the correct answer here is polysaccharides.
So polysaccharides is a complex carbohydrate made up of many monosaccharide units, which is basically what this question is asking.
Monosaccharide is a simple sugar and it's linked together.
Polysaccharides can be very large molecules and include substances like starch, glycerin, and cellulose, which are important for energy storage and structural support in organisms.
So let's talk about why the other options are not correct here.
So a monomer is a single molecule that can bind to other molecules to form a polymer.
In this case, the monosaccharides are the monomers that make up larger carbohydrates, but monomers by themselves are not complex carbohydrates, which is specifically described in this question.
So if you said answer choice A, I can understand why.
A diosaccharide is a carbohydrate composed of two monosaccharide units.
This question specifically asked for several or many
So that is why this question, that is why this answer isn't correct.
Oligosaccharides are carbohydrates made up of a few monosaccharides, usually somewhere between like three and 10.
And so while they are larger than diacycrites, they are not as large or as complex as polysaccharides, which have many more of those units.
Polysaccharides are large, complex carbohydrates made up of many monosaccharide units.
They have more than any of the other options listed on here, which is why polysaccharides is the correct answer.
Which of the following organelles is not separated from the cytoplasm due to the presence of its own membrane?
The mitochondrion, the nucleus, the ribosome,
the vacuole.
So the correct answer here is C, the bribosome.
So the question is asking organelles is not separated from the cytoplasm due to the presence of its own membrane.
So
As a refresher, the ribosomes are a small structure in cells that make proteins.
What makes them unique is that they do not have a membrane around them.
This means that they are directly in the cytoplasm, which is the jelly-like substance that fills the cell.
I'm gonna add a picture of it here so you can see it.
So let's talk about the other answer choices here.
So the mitochondrion
is the part of the cell that makes the energy.
It actually has a double membrane, which means it has two layers of membrane and that separates it from the cytoplasm.
Then we've got the nucleus, which holds all of the cell's DNA.
The nucleus is surrounded by nuclear membrane, which separates it from the cytoplasm.
And then lastly we've got the vacuole,
which is the storage organelles within the cells and they hold things like water and nutrients and they have a membrane around them to keep their contents separate from the cytoplasm.
So that is why the ribosome is correct because it's the only organelle of these answer choices that does not have a membrane and it is the only one that is directly in the cytoplasm.
Which of the following is a primary use of microscopy in healthcare?
Another microscope question.
Administering treatments for chronic diseases, diagnosing infections, performing surgical procedures, or prescribing medications?
Okay, the correct answer is B, diagnosing infections.
So microscopy is a crucial tool in healthcare because it allows medical professionals to examine tiny organisms, things like bacteria and viruses up close or any cells that might be abnormal, that might be causing an infection or a disease.
So by using a microscope, doctors can identify pathogens in samples such as from blood or urine or tissues, which helps them diagnose infections as well as other conditions or diseases.
In a DNA double helix, adaline is a nucleotide base that pairs with which of the following?
The correct answer here is thymine.
Okay, so in a DNA double helix, the nucleotide bases pair up in a very specific way to form the structure of the DNA molecule.
And the base pairing follows essentially these rules.
So we've got adaline always pairs with thymine.
That's our correct answer.
And then we have cytosine always pairs with guanine.
And this is because of the very specific chemical bonds that form between the bases.
Specifically, adaline and thymine form two hydrogen bonds with each other and
and cytosine and guanine form three hydrogen bonds.
So this complementary base pairing is crucial for DNA replication and maintaining the structure of genetic code.
And so when you are studying for your cheese exam, you should definitely be prepared to see questions just like this.
You're going to be asked questions on genetics and DNA, and you're also going to
potentially see questions on Punnett Square.
So brush up on your information regarding genetics and DNA.
A patient's medication prescription is for 75 milligrams of a drug.
If the tablets come in 25 milligram doses, which of the following indicates how many tablets should the patient take?
One, two, three, or four.
Well, the answer here is three tablets because three times 25 would equal 75 milligram.
Which of the following is the primary advantage of using a light microscope?
It provides higher resolution and magnification than electron microscopes.
It allows for the observation of live microorganisms in real time.
It can visualize viruses and subcellular organelles.
It is more complex and expensive than electron microscopes.
So the answer here is B. It allows for the observation of live microorganisms in real time.
Don't say I didn't tell you that you would
have questions on microscopes.
So you definitely want to make sure that you know light microscopes as well as electron microscopes.
So the primary advantage of a light microscope is that it is easier to use, it's more affordable, and it allows for the observation of live specimen.
In contrast, an electron microscope offers much higher magnification and resolution and it allows for a super detailed examination of structures, but it's really more of like at a molecular
or an anatomic level, and it requires specimens to be non-living and often prepared in very specific ways.
So that is why light microscopes are awesome.
Which of the following ions from a base react with hydrogen ions in a neutralization reaction?
Okay, the answer is going to be B, hydroxide.
So in a neutralization reaction, a base reacts with an acid to produce water and a salt.
The key to this reaction is the interaction between hydroxide ions from the base and the hydrogen ions from the acid.
So the,
Hydroxic ions from the base react with the hydrogen ions from the acid to form water, which then neutralizes the solution.
Which of the following is classified as a type of acid-base reaction that produces a salt?
Combination, decomposition, hydrolysis, or neutralization?
So the answer here is neutralization.
So in a neutralization reaction, an acid reacts with a base to produce a salt and water.
So for example, when a hydrochloric acid reacts with sodium hydroxide, it forms sodium chloride, which is a salt and a water.
This is the classic acid-base reaction that produces as a salt as a product.
This is the classic
acid-base reaction that produces a salt as a product.
So let's touch upon why the other options are not correct.
So a combination reaction involves two or more substances combining to form a single product, but it doesn't specifically produce a salt from an acid and a base.
A decomposition reaction involves a single compound breaking down into two or more simpler substances.
This is not an acid-base reaction and it does not produce a salt.
And lastly, hydrolysis involves the breakdown of a compound by water simply to form ions or molecules.
It is not an acid-base reaction and it does not produce a salt.
In addition to your A&P questions, your scientific reasoning questions, and your biology questions, as you see here, you are going to be tested on your chemistry, knowledge, and comprehension, which seems scary for a lot of people, especially if you just have not taken a chemistry class as recently as maybe you took your A&P classes.
So for the chemistry questions on the TEAS exam, you're gonna need to know things like acids and bases,
trends of the periodic table, the types of chemical reactions, the type of chemical bonds, you're gonna need to know about chemical solutions, formulas, and equations, things like calculating moles, molarity, molality, and things like that.
So if it's been a hot minute and chemistry scares you or really just preparing for the TEAS in general scares you and seems overwhelming,
I highly recommend that you check out our TEAS online course.
It has everything that you need to study in one single place for your TEAS exam, not only for science, but also for reading, English, and math.
But specifically, students love our science study materials because it's really short and sweet and simple to understand study lessons, but they also include lots of videos, lots of PDFs, as well as interactive practice questions and flashcards, so people
really find those beneficial, especially visual learners or people that are on the go.
So definitely check out the TEAS online course, open up a new tab right now and go to www.smartadditionacademy.com.
Okay, let's get into the next question now.
Which of the following methods helps to eliminate bias in an experiment?
So the correct answer here is a random assignment of participants to experimental groups.
So this is our second question on eliminating bias and random assignment of participants to experimental groups is gonna be the best way to eliminate bias because you want the results to be as
easy to replicate as possible and straying away from using people because of a personal preference or specific age groups or a specific environment or geographic location like the previous question had asked.
The more random, the better for eliminating bias and the more you eliminate bias, the easier it is to replicate your experiment
So which of the following types of bond forms between nitrogen and oxygen and why?
The correct answer here is covalent because electrons are shared.
So a covalent bond forms when two atoms share electrons in order to fill their outer electron shells.
In the case of nitrogen and oxygen,
both elements need electrons to complete their outer shells so they share electrons to form a stable bond.
This type of bond is called a covalent bond where electrons are shared between the two atoms.
So let's talk about why the other ones are incorrect.
ionic bond because electrons are shared so ionic bonds form when electrons are transferred from one atom to another not shared.
The second one ionic because electrons are transferred so while ionic bonds do involve the transfer of electrons like we just discussed
Nitrogen and oxygen form a covalent bond, not an ionic bond.
They both have similar electronegativity, ability to attract electrons, so they share electrons rather than transferring them.
And lastly, a covalent bond because electrons are transferred.
We've sort of talked about this, but this is incorrect because in a covalent bond, electrons are shared, not transferred.
So when electrons are shared, it forms an ionic bond.
So again, it's really important to know what covalent bonds are, what ionic bonds are, what they do, what they don't do, and just really have a deeper understanding of chemistry on that level.
So again, if you need a refresher on all of these different chemistry topics, be sure to check out the online course.
So which of the following atoms is a cation?
Okay, the correct answer here is D, 82 protons, 125 neutrons, and 78 electrons.
So a cation is an ion that has a positive charge, which means it has more protons than it has electrons.
So when an atom loses electrons, it becomes positively charged because protons, which are positively charged, outnumber the electrons, which are negatively charged.
So with the answer choice D, 82 protons, 125 neutrons, 78 electrons, this atom has 82 protons and 78 electrons, which means that it has four more protons than electrons.
which means it is a positively charged ion or a cation.
The positive charge is because there are more protons than electrons.
A spoonful of sugar is added to a hot cup of coffee.
All of the sugar dissolves.
Which of the following describes the resulting solution?
The correct answer here is unsaturated and homeogenous.
Let's break this correct answer down into two parts.
So a solution is unsaturated when more solute, in this case sugar, can be dissolved in the solvent, which in this case is the tea, at the given temperature.
So since the sugar dissolved completely and no solid sugar remains, there is still potential to dissolve more sugar, assuming the solution is not at its maximum capacity.
So in simple words,
the person making the tea can decide to add even more sugar into the tea, it's not completely saturated.
The second part of this answer is the solution is homogeneous because the sugar completely dissolves in the tea and you cannot see any distinct layers of separation.
So meaning the tea and the sugar have become completely mixed in a uniform fashion at a molecular level.
Once that sugar is in the tea, you really can't take the sugar out of it.
You can add more sugar to it, but you can't take the sugar out of it.
Once it's mixed, it's mixed.
So that is why the correct answer is C.
In the following single replacement reaction, blank replaces blank.
Okay, so the correct answer here is chlorine and iodine.
So in a single replacement reaction, one element replaces another in a compound.
So let's break down this reaction.
The chlorine reacts with the sodium iodine,
The chlorine then displaces the iodine from the sodium iodide, forming sodium chloride and iodine gas.
This means that the chlorine replaces the iodine in the compound.
So let's talk about some of the other answer choices.
So sodium and iodine.
This is incorrect because the sodium does not replace iodine in this reaction.
The sodium does not change or replace anything in the process.
Chlorine and sodium.
So this is incorrect because the chlorine does not replace sodium in this reaction.
The chlorine replaces the iodine and the sodium remains the same.
and then sodium and chlorine.
This is incorrect because the sodium is not replacing the chlorine.
The chlorine is the element that is replacing iodine in the reaction.
What type of reaction is described by the following equation?
And if you're taking this test along with me and you're like, man, this feels like a lot of chemistry all of the sudden, I can definitely understand.
So as a reminder, when you're taking the real TEAS exam, there's gonna be 50 questions.
Some of those are going to be unscored, but you should expect 18 AMP questions, eight chemistry questions, nine biology questions,
and eight scientific reasoning questions that are actually scored.
So sometimes students say, man, my test felt like really heavy one way or the other.
It could be that those extra unscored questions were in one particular topic.
It could be A and P or it could be chemistry or any of the above, but just in case you were feeling like that and thinking like that, that's why, but on the real exam, you will only have eight scored.
chemistry questions.
You may see more than eight questions, but only eight of them will be scored and know when you're taking the real test, they're not going to tell you which are scored and which are not.
Okay, so the answer, the correct answer here is double replacement.
So in a double replacement reaction, two compounds react and their positive and negative ions basically switch places
forming two new compounds.
So let's break down this equation a little bit.
So the zinc bromide and the potassium hydroxide are basically dissolved in water.
The zinc bromide reacts with the potassium hydroxide to form zinc hydroxide, which then becomes a solid.
potassium bromate stays in the solution.
So in this reaction, the zinc and the potassium switch places with the bromine and hydroxide, making it a double replacement reaction.
So let's talk about why the other options are not correct.
So a synthesis reaction occurs when two or more simple substances combine to form a more complex substance.
That's not what's happening here because two compounds are basically breaking apart and forming new compounds.
They're not combining.
A decomposition reaction occurs when a single compound breaks into two or more simpler substances.
And so again, in this reaction, we have two compounds reacting, not one breaking apart.
And then in a single replacement reaction, one element replaces another in a compound.
So for example, if the zinc replaced the potassium, then it would be a single replacement reaction.
However, here, the two compounds are reacting and they're exchanging ions, so it's not a single replacement reaction.
Which of the following best illustrates multiple alleles?
Blood type in humans with A, B, and O alleles.
Height in humans.
two alleles blending together to create a mixed phenotype or genes inherited from two different chromosomes.
Okay, the correct answer here is blood type in humans with A, B, and O alleles.
So the reason why answer A is correct is because
Multiple alleles means that there are more than two possible forms of gene in a population, okay?
Remember when I said earlier that you would definitely need to have a good understanding of genetics and DNA for your TEAS test, so this is a great example question of that knowledge coming up.
So in the case of the human blood type, there are three different alleles in this variation, A, B, and O, that would determine the blood type.
These alleles can combine in various ways to create the blood types we know, such as A, B, AB, and O. So let's talk about really quick why the other ones are incorrect here.
So B, height in humans.
So height can be influenced by many genes working together rather than one gene with multiple alleles.
This is an example of what's called a polygenic trait, which means many genes
which means many genes affect one trait, not a case of multiple alleles like this question is asking.
Two alleles blending together to create a mixed phenotype.
So this is describing an incomplete dominance rather than multiple alleles.
So when we talk about incomplete dominance, what that means is two alleles blend together to make a
mixed phenotype, like red and white flowers creating pink, for example.
Multiple alleles involves more than two choices, like the correct answer, A, B, and O blood types, not just blending.
And lastly, genes inherited from two different chromosomes.
This is not correct because this is completely unrelated to multiple alleles.
Multiple alleles refers to different forms of the same gene.
not genes on separate chromosomes.
Which of the following phase changes will the cohesion between the particles of a substance decrease?
So this is pulling in some of that states of matter and properties of matter information that you should also be aware of when prepping for your TEAS exam.
So we've got condensation, deposition, freezing, and vaporization.
Okay, the correct answer here is D, vaporization.
So vaporization is the phase change that talks about a liquid to a gas.
So an example of this is when water boils and turns into steam.
During this change, the particles move further apart and the cohesion or say like the attraction between them decreases significantly because they are moving more freely and they are no longer tightly connected into a liquid form.
So condensation is incorrect because condensation is the change from a gas to a liquid.
So when steam cools down and then turns back into water.
So in this case, particles are moving closer together, which then increases cohesion rather than decreases it.
When you are refreshing your knowledge on states of matter, properties of matter, one of the things that you're going to want to make sure that you have a really good understanding of is what happens in each of the different stages, specifically when it comes to cohesion.
Are the particles moving quicker?
Are they moving slower?
Are the particles slower and further apart?
Or are they closer together?
Are they more dense?
So you kind of want to have a good understanding of, during each of these phases, what is happening to the particles.
So deposition is not correct because deposition is the change from a gas directly to a solid, something like frost forming on a window.
During deposition, particles come closer together and they form a solid, which then increases cohesion.
So again, knowing what the particles are doing and if it is increasing or decreasing cohesion.
And then lastly, freezing is the phase change from a liquid to a solid.
So when water becomes ice and freezing, particles move closer together and they form a solid structure, again, increasing cohesion instead of decreasing it.
Okay, so you are gonna see just a little tiny bit of math when you are answering the questions on the science section.
This may actually also come up just a little tiny bit on the reading section.
Sometimes there's questions about like say recipes,
there's a question about you know how much time passed between the time that Bob arrived to the party and Stacy left so some of that information will be given to you it's typically pretty simple straightforward math so don't stress out too too much but here we've got kind of a math problem so let's tackle it together a patient's blood pressure is a hundred
40 millimeters of mercury convert this pressure to kilopascals given that 1 mmHg is approximately 0.133 kPa.
So while you're working out the math I do want to remind you that in most cases
conversions are not provided to you.
So when you take the math section, the formulas and the conversions are not provided to you.
You are expected to have them memorized for the most common conversions.
So we're talking things like ounces to cups, cups to gallons, milligrams to grams, kilograms to pounds, like your standard metric conversions.
But when it comes to something like this, that's very specific, like a kilopascal, a kilopascal is not something that they're gonna expect you to have memorized.
So in this case, you're basically just doing a little bit of math to determine what the answer is, given what they have provided you.
So the correct answer here is actually A, 18.62 kilopascals.
So kilopascals, the way you needed to do here was 140,
Multiply that by 0.133.
This information was provided to you.
So when you calculate that with the four function calculator that they will provide to you on the screen, you will see 18.62.
So this math problem is relatively simple.
It's really more so testing your knowledge of how you would calculate it, right?
So it wanted to test you to make sure that you knew
that you just needed to multiply this and that you didn't need to make it more complicated than that.
Okay, so here is another question very similar to the one that we just answered.
In which of the following states of matter are the intermolecular forces between particles in a substance the strongest?
Gas, liquid, plasma, or solid?
Okay, the correct answer here is going to be a solid.
So in a solid, particles are packed very closely together, and they vibrate in a very fixed position.
The intermolecular forces, which basically is a very fancy way of saying forces that hold the particles together, are the strongest in a solid, which is why solids have a fixed shape and volume.
Just remember that solids, they are the densest,
they are the strongest.
They have the strongest molecular force.
And with the plasma, so plasma is very similar to gas.
It has a very high energy state.
The particles are very far apart and they actually almost have no molecular force at all.
Plasmas are actually made of charged particles that move freely, so the intermolecular forces are very very weak.
just like they would be in a gas.
Sequence of amino acids in a gene determines which of the following, the primary structure of a codon, the primary structure of a protein, the primary structure of a nucleotide, or the primary structure of a nucleic acid?
Okay, the correct answer here
is the primary structure of a protein.
So the primary structure of a protein is the specific sequence of anemo acids that are linked together in a chain.
And this sequence is determined by a gene which provides instructions on the order of the anemo acids.
So the primary structure is sort of like a blueprint that determines the shape and the function of a protein.
So let's talk about why the other answers are incorrect.
A codon is a sequence of three nucleotides in an mRNA that codes for a single enema acids.
They are not made of enema acids, they are made of nucleotides.
So the gene sequence determines the codons, which then helps specify the enema acids, but the final product is the protein.
Let's take a look at C. So nucleotides here are the building blocks of DNA and RNA, not proteins.
gene sequence is made up of nucleotides, but it doesn't directly determine the primary structure of a nucleotide.
Instead, what it does is it determines the anemo acid sequence in a protein.
And lastly, we have the primary structure of a nucleic acid.
So nucleic acids are chains of nucleotides, not anemo acids.
Basically, this is meant to
to code for a protein, not to define another nucleic acid's structure.
So the right answer here is the primary structure of a protein, because the gene sequence directly determines the sequence of enema acids, which then would form the protein's primary structure.
Which of the following is true regarding the urinary system?
Select all that apply.
So when you're taking your TEAS exam, version seven does have a few different question types.
For the most part, you're mostly still going to see multiple choice questions, like the ones we've been answering up until now, but you will see sometimes some select all that apply.
You will also see
question types that are fill in the blank, and you will also see ordered response.
There is also another question type called hotspot, where you will be shown an image and you will basically have to click on the image for the correct answer.
You won't see too many of them, just a few.
Okay, so for this particular answer, the correct answers here are, can these help regulate water balance?
Yes.
they regulate levels of electrolytes such as sodium and potassium, also yes, and they eliminate mellabotic waste.
What is not true, kidneys do not make urine, and if you are watching this and you're like, what are you talking about, of course they make urine, they don't.
They don't, and we'll talk about that more in just a moment.
They don't make urine in the sense that you might think that they do.
They don't make urine.
And as a person ages, kidney tissues infiltration capacity increases.
That is also not true.
So let's break this down just a little bit more.
So let's start with the correct answers.
Kidneys help regulate water balance.
So yes, the kidneys control the amount of water in the body by adjusting how much water is reabsorbed or excreted in the urine.
This helps keep a stable water balance, which is essential for maintaining blood pressure and just overall hydration.
Regulates levels of electrolytes such as sodium and potassium.
So yes, kidneys definitely play a role in balancing electrolytes, they filter blood and they adjust the levels of these minerals based on the body's needs, which is crucial for functions like muscle contraction and nerve signaling.
eliminates melobotic waste.
So yes, this is true because the kidneys filter out waste products from the blood such as urea and creatine, which are byproducts of metabolism.
These wastes are then eliminated from the body in urine.
Now before we talk about why the other two answer choices are not correct, I also just want to let you know that on the TEAS exam, there is no such thing as partial credit.
So when you've got a question like this, that is select all that apply, if you selected four instead of three, you're not gonna get like a 50%.
If there was three correct answers and you only selected two of them, you're not getting a 66% on that question.
It simply just will not, it'll just be straight up wrong.
Same with the fill in the blank questions.
If you spell the word wrong, you're not getting that question right.
Kidneys make urine.
So kidneys do play a role in filtering blood and they play a role in forming urine, but they do not actually make urine in the simple sense.
Instead, kidneys filter out wastes and they adjust water and electrolytes, which is then excreted as urine through other parts of the urinary system.
What actually makes urine
are things called nephrons, which is what kidneys are actually made up of.
And as a reminder, nephrons are basically the functional units of the kidneys where all of the process of urine formation occurs.
Each kidneys has about a million nephrons.
And lastly, as a person ages, kidney tissue infiltration capacity increase.
So this is incorrect.
The statement is actually the opposite.
As people age, kidney tissue infiltration capacity tend to decrease, not increase.
Aging can lead to reduced kidney function, which makes it harder for the kidneys to filter blood effectively.
During the aging process, not all hormone levels decrease.
Some actually increase.
Which of the following is a hormone that may increase as a person ages?
Cortisol, insulin, luteinizing, or thyroid?
Okay, the correct answer here is luteinizing.
So the luteinizing hormone is a hormone involved in regulating the reproductive system.
So as people age, particularly during menopause in women, levels of what's called LH often increase because the body tries to stimulate hormone production from the ovaries, which are becoming less responsive.
This increase in LH is a natural part of the aging process in both men and women, though it is typically seen more so in women.
So let's talk about why the other three are incorrect.
So cortisol is a stress hormone that helps regulate metabolism, blood sugar, and immune responses.
And though cortisol levels can fluctuate with age and may be higher during times of stress, hashtag adulting anybody, cortisol generally does not increase just as a result of the normal aging process.
That's just life.
It has nothing to do with aging specifically.
insulin.
So insulin is the hormone that helps regulate blood sugar levels and with age cells in the body may become less sensitive to insulin which can lead to higher blood sugar levels but the actual production of insulin by the pancreas does not typically increase as part of the aging process.
And lastly, the thyroid hormone.
So the thyroid hormone helps control metabolism and their levels typically decrease or they stay about the same with age.
It really just depends.
Some people may develop a thyroid issue as they age, but an increase in the thyroid hormone is not part of the aging process.
A science student needs to measure 50 milliliters of water for an experiment.
Which of the following measuring instruments should the student use?
A 100 milliliter graduated cylinder, a 500 milliliter beaker, a 50 milliliter
volumetric flask or a 250 milliliter Erlenmeyer flask.
So we talked about questions like this in the beginning of the video with some of the things that you're going to need to know regarding those nine scientific reasoning questions.
It goes back to scientific measurements, the scientific method, how to design an experiment, inductive versus deductive reasoning.
So this is an example of that kind of question.
it's important for you to be able to differentiate when you need to measure something in a scientific lab, you know, what is appropriate.
Is a cylinder appropriate?
Is a beaker appropriate?
Or is a flask appropriate?
And there's pros and cons and there's do's and don'ts when measuring for scientific purposes.
So again,
brushing up on that knowledge using something like the T7 online course to brush up on everything related to your scientific and reasoning, your A&P, your chemistry, and your biology is gonna help you out quite a bit.
So the correct answer here is a 100 milliliter graduated cylinder.
So a graduated cylinder is actually specifically designed for measuring liquid volumes accurately, and it is an acceptable device to be used for measuring specifically in scientific settings.
100 milliliter graduated cylinder will have clear markings that will allow the student to measure exactly 50 milliliters of water, making it the best choice for precise measurement.
So let's talk about the other things here.
We've got a beaker, we've got a volumetric flask, and then we have a Erlenmeyer flask.
So let's start with the beaker.
So a beaker is not considered to be as accurate because they have fewer and less precise markings.
It just wouldn't be the appropriate thing to grab.
So let's talk about the volumetric flasks.
Okay, so volumetric flasks are accurate and they are designed to be used in a scientific setting.
However, they're typically used for making solutions rather than measuring out various amounts of a liquid.
And then we've got the 250 milliliter Erlenmeyer flasks.
So Erlenmeyer flasks are actually typically used for mixing or for holding liquids.
They're not used for accurate measurements.
And so they're kind of like beakers in that they just have a few markings, but they're not really designed for precise volume measurement.
So again, the cylinder is the only thing that was listed here as an answer choice.
that is widely accepted for accurate and adjustable measurement, and then all of the other options either lacked precision or they were just not intended to be used for measurements in a scientific setting.
So really important to, again, know the different types of microscopes, know the different kinds of scales, know the different type of glassware.
All of that is going to come up on your TEAS exam.
Which of the following
phases is the cell cycle part of?
Interphase, metaphase, prophase, or telephase?
The correct answer is interphase.
So interphase is the phase of the cell cycle where the cell spends the majority of its time.
So during the interphase, the cell is growing,
performs all of its normal functions and then it prepares for division by duplicating its DNA.
So interphase has three stages as a reminder that is G1 which is growth, you have the S phase which is where the DNA synthesizes, and then G2 is preparation for division.
And interphase is the phase where really all of the essential cell activities happen before actual division begins.
So let's talk about these other phases, what they are and why they're not correct.
So we've got metaphase, which is just one of the stages in mitosis.
This is what is a specific part of cell division, but it's not the entire cell cycle.
In metaphase, chromosomes basically line up in the center of the cell before being separated.
Then we've got prophase.
So prophase is also a stage in mitosis.
But again, it's not the entire cell cycle.
What happens in prophase is that the chromosomes condense, and then the nuclear membrane starts to break down.
But this is, again, it's only one part of cell division.
It's not the cell cycle, which is why it's not correct.
And then telophase is another stage inside of mitosis.
During telophase, the cell finishes dividing its chromosomes and begins to form two new nuclei.
But like the other stages, this is just one step in the cell division, and it's not a separate phase of the entire cell cycle.
In which of the following states of matter do the particles of iron have the lowest amount of cohesion?
Solid iron particles have the lowest amount of cohesion.
Liquid iron particles have the lowest amount of cohesion.
Gaseous iron particles have the lowest amount of cohesion.
Or the particles have the same amount of cohesion in all states of matter.
So this question is very simple.
It sounds harder because it's basically trying to add a false sense of
Difficulty by having you think that iron might be different than anything else.
So iron is no different from water.
So the correct answer here is actually going to be C.
The correct answer is actually going to be C, the gaseous iron particles have the lowest amount of cohesion, and that's because all gas particles have the lowest amount of cohesion.
That's not specific to iron, that's just specific to gas particles.
A person is diagnosed as having acidosis, a condition in which the blood pH is below 7.45.
Which of the following does the doctor most likely conclude?
There is too much carbon dioxide is found in the blood.
Highly oxygenated blood circulates through the body.
A blockage prevents blood from leaving the pulmonary artery or the nasal cavity is having a difficult time clearing particles from the air.
Okay, and so the correct answer here is A, too much carbon dioxide is found in the blood.
So as the question stated, acidosis refers to a condition where the blood becomes too acidic, which means that the blood pH is below 7.45.
So when CO2 combines with water in the blood to form a carbonic acid, which lowers the pH, which then makes the blood more acidic.
So this condition can happen when the body has trouble expelling CO2 through breathing, leading to what's called respiratory acidosis.
So let's talk about why the other three answer choices are incorrect.
So oxygenated blood.
Again, oxygenated blood refers to blood that is rich in oxygen and acidosis is related to an imbalance in CO2 levels, not oxygen levels.
If the blood is highly oxygenated, it would not cause acidosis.
A blockage prevents blood from leaving the pulmonary artery.
So a blockage in the pulmonary artery is actually called a pulmonary embolism, and that would affect blood flow and oxygen level, but it would not cause acidosis.
And then the nasal cavity has a difficult time clearing particles from the air.
So this one is more so related to a respiratory issue, but it wouldn't explain acidosis.
The point where the small and large intestine meet.
The point where the small intestine and large intestine meet is which of the following?
The anus, the appendix, the cecum, or the colon.
The correct answer is the cecum.
So the cecum is the first part of the large intestine, and it is located where the small intestine meets the large intestine.
It's like this pouch-like structure that marks the beginning of the colon, and the small intestine empties its contents into the cecum, which then leads into the rest of the large intestine.
So let's talk about why the other three are incorrect.
So the anus is at the opening at the end of the digestive tract.
I'm going to put a picture here so we can take a look at the entirety of the digestive tract together.
And this is where waste is eliminated from the body.
The appendix is a small tube-like structure that is attached to the cecum, but it is not where the small and large intestine meet.
The colon is the main part of the large intestine but it's further along after the cecum and the colon is divided into several parts including the ascending, the transverse, and the descending.
Also, it's really important as I say those words, this reminds me to remind you that it's important to really have a good understanding of anatomical position and the different planes in the body.
So language like ascending, transverse, descending, lateral, all of those words are really important for you to know as you prepare to take this exam.
So like I was saying, the colon is divided into several parts and the small intestine meets the large intestine
Not at the colon, it's at the cecum.
Which of the following processes involves the addition of water molecules to break down covalent bonds within macromolecules?
The dehydration synthesis, the condensation synthesis, the hydrolysis, or the photosynthesis.
So this is such a great question because I feel like it sounds like a really hard question.
And I feel like it's because it sort of overlaps a lot of different concepts.
So we're talking about macromolecules, we're talking about water molecules, and then we're talking about covalent bonds.
So this just feels like a question loaded with some chemistry and some biology.
So the correct answer here is actually going to be hydrolysis.
And so hydrolysis is the process where water molecules are added to break down covalent bonds within macromolecules, like proteins, fats, carbohydrates, et cetera.
During hydrolysis, the addition of water splits the large molecule into smaller molecules.
So for example, in digestion, enzymes break down food by adding water to split macromolecules, like breaking down
scarch, like breaking down starch into glucose.
So let's talk about these other three answer choices.
Dehydration synthesis, which is also another word for condensation synthesis, which is of course one of our answer choices here, so both of them are the same, is the opposite of hydrolysis.
In dehydration synthesis, also known as condensation synthesis, two smaller molecules combine to form a larger molecule, and then water is then removed, not added.
So this happens, for example, when two anemo acids bond to form a protein, water is released.
And lastly, photosynthesis.
Photosynthesis really has nothing to do with it.
Photosynthesis, of course, is the process by which plants use light energy to convert carbon dioxide and water into glucose and oxygen.
So hydrolysis is the correct answer.
Which of the following liquids typically forms a convex meniscus when placed in a container?
water, mercury, salt water, or alcohol?
The correct answer here is mercury.
So mercury forms a convex meniscus when placed in a container because it has really strong cohesive forces, which basically an attraction between mercury molecules, and it has weak adhesive forces, attraction between mercury and then the container surface.
This causes the mercury to basically stick to itself more than to the sides of the container, which is where that curve happens up.
That's called the convex at all of the edges.
So again, this is something that you're going to see when you study scientific reasoning.
You're going to learn the difference between a convex and a concave meniscus.
It may appear on your test.
Water, saltwater, and alcohol all act like one another when they're placed in a container.
They form what's called a concave meniscus, and that basically means that it curves down at the edges.
What that means is that their adhesive forces with the container surface are stronger than their actual cohesive forces with themselves, with their molecules.
Before we answer the next set of practice questions, I want to give you a reminder that if you've got your T7 exam coming up in just a few weeks or in just a few months, that it's never too late to start studying with an online course.
The online course is intended for you to ditch the boring study guides and to study
using a very simple and easy to understand structured system that's guaranteed to help you pass.
This online course will give you everything that you need to know and to relearn so that you can feel confident not only on test day, but as you get ready to go into your program.
So if you're ready to simplify studying for your T7 exam,
and you don't wanna spend a bunch of money on test prep, know that the T7 online course has your back.
Check it out at www.smartadditionacademy.com.
Which of the following best describes the primary reproductive mechanism of bacterial cells?
Binary fission, sexual reproduction, budding, or sperm formation.
This is a great example of why it's important to not just focus on just memorizing definitions
and really having a good understanding of the content that you are studying.
This question is not only asking you about cellular reproduction, it's also asking you to pull in your knowledge of what you know about microorganisms, in this case, specifically bacteria.
So being able to know a little bit about how bacteria works, knowing how to pull in information on how cellular reproduction work will allow you to answer this question correctly.
So for this question, the correct answer is actually A, binary fission.
So binary fission is the main way that bacteria reproduce.
What happens in binary fission is a bacterial cell copies its DNA, and then it splits in half, creating two identical cells.
This process is a type of asexual reproduction, meaning it does not involve combining DNA from two parents.
It is quick, and it allows for bacteria to multiply rapidly.
though sexual reproduction is not correct because it involves the combination of genetic material from two parents to create an offspring with a mix of both parents' DNA.
Budding is a type of asexual reproduction seen in organisms like yeast.
In budding, a new organism grows off the side of the parent and eventually separates.
In spore formation,
So spore formation is a survival mechanism some bacteria use in harsh conditions to protect themselves, but it's not a primary method of reproduction.
So when it comes to studying microorganisms, you're gonna wanna make sure that you have a very good understanding of things like bacteria, viruses, parasites, fungi, how do they move?
What are their characteristics?
What are some examples of them?
How do they reproduce and things like that?
What kind of diseases do they cause?
Which of the following is an example of polygenic trait?
ABO blood type,
flower color in snapdragons, skin color in humans, or eye color in fruit flags?
So the correct answer is skin color in humans.
So polygenic trait, this basically means it is a trait that is influenced by multiple genes working together and skin color
a polygenic trait.
This combination of genes results in a range of possible skin colors rather than a simple one gene one trait outcome.
Because many genes contribute, polygenic traits like skin color show a wide variety of appearances.
So let's talk about the other three answer choices.
We have
ABO blood type.
The ABO blood type system is controlled by a single gene with multiple alleles.
This is an example of multiple alleles like we discussed earlier in this practice question.
Flower color and snapdragons are determined by a single gene that shows incomplete dominance.
In this case, crossing a red flower plant with a white flower plant would produce pink flowers.
This is an example of incomplete dominance, not polygenic trait.
Eye color in fruit flies is also controlled by a single gene with a simple inheritance pattern, not multiple genes.
The cerebellum helps blank.
The correct answer is B, coordinate body movements.
So the cerebellum is the part of the brain responsible for coordinating voluntary movements.
That's things like balance, posture, and fine motor skills.
It helps make movements smooth and accurate.
So for example, the cerebellum allows us to walk straight or allows us to reach for objects without losing balance.
Body pressure regulation is managed by other systems, specifically the autonomic nervous system and parts of the brains, like the medulla, which help control heart rate and blood pressure.
Breathing mechanics are controlled by the brainstem, specifically, again, the medulla and the pons, which regulate respiratory rate and depth.
Language processing and the interpretation of sounds occurs in areas of the brain that are located in the cerebral cortex and the cerebellum is not involved with language interpretation.
Making coordinating body movements the correct answer.
All right, and then our last question is going to be an A and P question.
The B cells do not directly attack pathogens or infected cells.
Instead, they mark the pathogens for destruction by macrophages and B cells.
They mark the antibodies for destruction by B cells and natural killer cells.
They mark the antibodies for destruction by macrophages and killer T cells.
They mark the pathogens for destruction by macrophages and natural killer cells.
Okay, and the correct answer is D, mark the pathogens for destruction by macrophages and natural killers.
So B cells produce antibodies, which are proteins that bind to specific pathogens like bacterias or viruses.
And by attaching to these pathogens, the antibodies mark them so that other immune cells
macrophages, which basically eat invaders, and natural killer cells, which help destroy infected or harmful cells, can recognize and destroy them.
The B cells don't directly attack, but they rather like tag or identify the pathogen so that the other cells can eliminate it.
So just a few reasons why the other answer choices are not correct.
So B cells, they do not destroy pathogens directly.
Instead, they just produce antibodies.
Macrophages are the ones that handle the actual destruction of the pathogens.
Antibodies are the markers that B cells produce and are not themselves marked for destruction.
Instead, antibodies attach to pathogens, marking the pathogens for destruction.
Okay, and that wraps up our last question.
So if you've stuck in with me throughout this entire video, this entire test, amazing job.