Good evening and welcome everyone to the city of Memphis traffic commission meeting.
Today's Thursday, January 19th, 2023.
The time is 5 0 7 p.m.
Meeting will now come to order.
Uh, Alva, could you call the roll call for the commissioners?
Commissioner McGiven here.
Commissioner Brzezinski here.
If Buckley present recording in progress.
Thank you.
We have one vacancy that's yet to be filled, but this three present commissioners does give us a quorum.
We'll see also present this evening and just looking up we have the secretary of the trash traffic commissioners Alva Erickson, two of my sergeants assigned to the traffic unit Sergeant Larry Rogers and Sergeant Jordan canaba online director of trafficking engineer Todd Blake traffic engineer Amy angles I believe is here.
And I think I missed you when you're.
That's everybody.
Um, the minutes of the December traffic commission, they've already been distributed.
All members.
Uh, have we had a chance to review?
If so, I will take a motion, uh, to accept the minutes of the December traffic motion motion by commissioner Brzezinski seconded by commissioner hunt and, uh, have a roll call vote for the three present commissions.
Uh, commissioner hunt.
Yes.
Commissioner Brzezinski?
Chief Buckley?
Yes.
Motion has approved.
The minutes have been read into the meeting.
New business 2023-01.
The meeting scheduled for 2023.
Normal course of business every January is to list our scheduled traffic commission meetings for the year.
Alba, do we have that list?
I can quickly.
So for the calendar year 2023.
We have tonight's meeting, of course, the February meeting will be February 14, March 14, April 11, May 9, June 13, September 12, October 10.
November 14th and December 12th.
This falls in the traditional pattern where we do not have traffic commissions for July and August unless there is a special need.
And it represents the second Tuesday of the month at 5 p.m.
And I say to the two commissioners, if that's acceptable, we should motion this meeting in order and we can publicly post them.
So I would accept the motion unless somebody has a discussion or concern over those dates.
Chief, I don't have a, has anyone talked to Tim?
I mean, is that an issue for him or Alicia?
I know you all are busy with more city stuff than I am.
That's fine with me.
Um, and yeah, I mean, I don't, I don't know if, if, if Tim has, has an opinion on this, I have not received a negative, um, or any feedback in the negative manner from him.
I actually expected him to be here tonight.
So hopefully he does join in, but, um,
It's pretty standard second Tuesday of every month, anyway, with those months.
Alicia, have you had a chance to talk to Tim?
No, I think that we are expecting them.
I had actually held these times on my calendar just going forward, because this is what I was expecting.
I think that things come up, and if necessary, we'll reschedule them as we've had to.
But it is good to have a standing time.
And this is as good of any of the standing time.
I don't see any reason to change them now.
The intent is to get it out publicly so that, you know, the residents of Medford have an understanding of what we're trying to do and when we're trying to do it for the Traffic Commission.
Again, understanding- Yeah, motion to approve.
Okay, I'm gonna move- Seconded by Commissioner Hunt.
Seconded by Commissioner Brzezinski.
Thank you, Steve.
I'll have a roll call vote, quick.
Commissioner Hunt?
Yes.
Commissioner Brzezinski?
Yes, three nothing, the motion is approved and the schedule will be submitted publicly.
2023-02, for the traffic commission to discuss the issue of absentee landlord permits and or visitor passes.
I'm gonna try to give this a traditional history look to the commission's presence.
While the traffic commission has not ever taken a formal vote on this,
Individuals who own property in Medford but rent it to other residents have historically been granted the right to wait or have some of them have historically received permit to park on the streets of Medford on the residential street where their property belongs and have been granted permit sorry visitor passes Alba
not all occasions, but in several occasions, given to.
And so having, you know, at the end of 2022 and coming into January now, several of the landlords have requested these same permits be extended, but there's no formal rule in the traffic commission.
And I don't know when that practice existed, but I thought we should, as a commission, discuss this and vote whether or not we are accepting of it or not.
I'm going to ask Hal the one more question traditionally.
If the landlord gets the visitor passes, does that mean the resident who actually lives there does not get visitor passes?
No, the resident that lives there has the right to a sticker if they own a vehicle and two visitor passes per household.
So that means the household could potentially get four visitor passes, in theory.
This is a- Yes.
Yeah, okay.
Somewhat problematic to me, but.
So I opened it up for discussion to the commissioners and to what they want to do.
The intent of the traffic commission
My best of my understanding in my last four years as being the commissioners that visitor passes, two of them belong to the household.
And not all landlords request these permit passes but they've been granted to some of them.
I don't, I guess I just, I have so many questions in this.
I really think that the commission should kind of debate this back and forth and see whether or not we have opinions on it.
So I throw it back out to Commissioner Hunt, Commissioner Brzezinski, for your thoughts before we open it up to public input on this.
Commissioner McGibbon just entered.
You'll need to make him a co-host so he can unmute as well.
Excellent.
He is unmuted.
Apologies for my tardiness, I lost track of time in the task.
Commissioner McGibbon, I don't know when you logged on, I missed it, but we're discussing 2023-02, absentee landlord permits if this passes.
So the commission has never formally adopted this as a practice.
The parking division does not
necessarily support it in the sense that it would have to be, in order for them to grant these landlords a parking pass, they would need to have traffic commission approval.
So we have to make a decision on this one way or the other, or actually maybe not, just not address the issue further as table on it, which we have to stop doing on a lot of occasions.
So questions, comments from the commissioners.
I guess, Chief, I would be interested if there are any of those landlords who are here who could sort of explain the rationale.
I could imagine that if you, the term absentee landlord actually strikes me as funny because I usually, that term is usually used to refer to a landlord who's not taking care of their property.
But one could imagine you don't live in the city, you are in fact taking care of your property and you would like to come by frequently
to do repairs and take care of the yard, et cetera, then there is some basis to having and there is some benefit to us encouraging our landlords to be physically present and monitoring their own properties and taking care of them, regardless of whether or not the tenant is home, to give them a permit, the visitor's pass to park there.
And there is actually an argument for that that is quite valid.
And I guess I'd like to make sure I understand that that is the intention of the use.
I can't imagine in my mind why you would need more than one, unless you're trying to make the argument that it's you and you're going to have repair guys there and you need to have that kind of stuff going on as well.
But that's, I think, a bigger, different issue.
that I'd like to, I guess that's, that's where I stand on it.
I can see the potential, like why, why it's not a bad idea.
Um, but if there was a landlord who wanted to speak to it, that would make sure that my assumptions are correct.
Uh, do either the commissioner of business give a commission, but given, uh, would like to defer to public comment.
I can do that first.
I, yeah, I, I kinda, I agree with Alicia again, being
parking being so critical in the city, I don't necessarily agree to four visitor parking, four visitor parking passes, but I could see you're meeting a roofer there, you're meeting an electrician there to repair something, you would have a need for the landlord to park and a contractor, and then anything above that, I think you could probably use your tenant's pass to justify additional people there, or potentially approach parking and ask for maybe something special
grant access to multiple contractors, but not necessarily one plus two, I wouldn't necessarily support again, unless there's some valid arguments to support that.
Why don't we try to have, is there a, someone who wishes to speak to this?
Is there someone present this evening who is a landlord and has received these permit passes and would like to speak to it?
And if you could just raise your hand or wave wildly on camera, we can,
That's Amy.
I want to wait.
Amy, I do see a hand up.
I just wanted to see if we could hear from a landlord first.
Francis Mitchell.
You can unmute your screen and then we can.
First of all, I'm not a landlord, but I just want to say that when people are having work done and the
trucks are here they have a sign on the trucks and when they if the people go by who give out tickets see that there's they don't they don't give any tickets because they understand that they're doing work in the house so I don't understand why it is even necessary to do that
Thank you for the comments, and it does incorporate the individual themselves coming to the property so it's happened to me many times.
I'm just, thank you.
Anyone else any other landlord property owners comment questions.
Let's see any so let me, Amy angles.
Yeah, I just wanted to say, I just had a little sidebar with Lily Worth, who's our intern that's working with us in traffic and transportation and also in planning.
I asked her to do some digging to see what some other cities and towns nearby might be doing as far as visitor passes are concerned.
I myself live in Brookline and I learned about their visitor pass system recently.
They're kind of notorious for being quite strict, but now I understand the process and and I think it could be useful to see what you know what else is done, what might work for us.
Peter Wallace had a handout.
Thank you.
Peter Wallace, did you have a hand up a comment.
I'm just going to have to unmute you.
There you go.
It was actually not related to this specific thing.
It's about visitor passes, but I was going to ask that at the end.
OK, well, thank you.
I will get to you.
I want to just kind of keep on comment.
So seeing no landlords present.
It's just two screens, you have to go back.
Okay.
Anyone else wishing to speak, you know, or someone who has experienced this or has experience with this process?
I guess I push it back to the commissioners.
If it's something that we think, I mean, there's multiple ways we could do this.
We could grant the landlord one permit as it relates to their property.
I don't see a need to have more than I think I like the idea of keeping a traditional to visitor passes per household.
But that's just my opinion at this point to take a vote on it but I had one person who.
husband has a car, the wife has a car, and she would request two permits, one for each of their cars, but nothing for visitor passes because they could use the tenant's visitor pass, because they will know in advance when the work is going to be done, even if they're not there, they can make that visitor pass available.
Alba, do you know historically how many of these passes are out there?
Sorry if I'm speaking low.
I don't think there's a lot.
Okay.
I have probably 10, 20 maybe at the most.
The other thing I guess we could do is in line with what Amy has suggested is maybe do some research for what other communities.
Some of them has a program for landlords.
They pay like $25 for the permit for the year.
But it is attached, it goes with the car.
Okay, so I throw it back to the commissioners.
There was, you know, there's obviously some sympathy for the subject matter to the commissioners.
I don't know if there's enough understood about the process for one of the commissioners to offer a motion and or a thought on how to handle this moving forward as the chair can't really offer a motion.
I put it back in your hands.
I have a question.
But do we know how many landlords are not in in the city.
And the reason I ask it because you know, obviously we're going to run into capacity issues at some point, and we're doing this.
And I know that's kind of street by street but, you know, I think I agree with my fellow commissioners that have spoken up on this.
You know one permit for the landlord themselves makes sense.
I think, too, I think was just made this point, having the.
visitor passes that the actual tenants use be used for any contractors and things like that.
In my mind, this is just, you know, someone owns a building, they should be able to park legally near the building to access it.
But we don't, I don't think we need to have more than the amount of visitor passes that we're already giving to that property.
So that's my opinion on it.
But I'd also be interested in knowing how many of these do we have and what do our neighbors do that are similarly dense?
OK, understood.
I get that.
I guess this is going to require a lot more research than it probably should have been done before it got on the agenda.
Chief, I'm willing to hear public comment because that may also inform our research.
Yep, just check to that.
Okay, we do have two.
Maria, we're gonna ask you to unmute here.
Hi, yes, good evening.
My name is Marie.
And thank you.
Thanks for having the meeting.
We all my husband and I own it.
We're Medford residents long term, almost 40 years.
We do have a two family house on a busy street, Bowen Ave.
And we've always been granted visitor passes.
As landlords, we are responsible for all the repairs, contract workers,
We do a lot of the work ourselves.
My husband's pretty handy, but we need to be able to park in front of the house without worrying about getting ticketed.
Luckily with the little snowstorm we had this week, our tenants, some of our tenants were not at work and they were able to shovel the driveway and the sidewalk for us, but that may not always be the case.
So whether myself or my husband go over there, we're required to get rid of the snow within a certain amount of time.
We need to be able to park in front of the house and we pay taxes on it.
We maintain it.
We've had it for quite some time and it's an older house and sometimes things go wrong.
We don't feel like we should impose on our tenants
Well, one set of tenants don't have, actually from what we understand, none of the tenants have visitor passes.
They just didn't feel like they needed them.
There is a good size driveway and therefore cars take up the driveway.
So I think we really should be granted at least one visitor pass.
I mean, it's nice if you have contractors or a realtor come over,
if they can park on the street again without risking getting a ticket, I think that's the right way to go.
We're not going to be taking up parking every day, you know, all year round.
It's not that frequent, but when we do, we need to be, you know, we can't interrupt our tenants who work full time.
And, you know, I don't want to be bothering them to,
Well, as I said, they don't even have the visitor passes right now.
So that's, that's all that's I've had some nice conversations with Alba.
She's been very, very helpful.
So I would, I would, does a great job.
Yes.
She's lovely.
Absolutely.
Thank you very much for the comments and helping us to understand the issue as it relates to landlords.
Okay.
Thank you, Alex.
Welcome.
Hi.
So we actually made a survey regarding the next issue, hopefully on the agenda about the resident permitting party parking within a quarter mile of GLX.
Half mile.
Half mile of GLX, yes.
But on that survey, something interesting came up about the guest passes, even though I didn't ask anything about it.
which was that people were saying, oh, we wish we could get visitor passes, but they were evidently not aware of the fact that they could.
That's all I can tell.
I have nothing to do with it otherwise, but I just noticed that when I looked at what people were writing about the proposal and what feedback they were giving.
Okay, thank you.
I appreciate the comments.
Thanks for the participation.
Yeah, I'll just know that I'm like looking at the website right now and it says you can get guest passes only but they could they only work for two weeks while you're waiting for a new vehicle registration is what it says.
So that's the website just kind of I think makes it look like you can't even get them.
Okay.
We'll look into that one.
Thank you.
Uh, the comments, uh, so seeing no other further public, sorry, we have two pages, um, public comment, uh, commissioners, uh, based on what you've heard thoughts.
I I'd be willing to make a motion for a, uh, owner parking spotted in one visitor.
Um, you know, I think in the instances where.
you need more than one parking spot, I think we could probably make accommodations, but just to keep the item moving, I'd be willing to make that motion.
Okay, so just to be clear, so the motion by Commissioner Brzezinski is for landlords to receive one resident permit parking and one visitor pass.
That's correct.
I'll second that motion.
Seconded by Commissioner McGibbon.
Roll call vote.
Commissioner McGiven?
Yes.
Commissioner Hunt?
Commissioner Brzezinski?
Yes.
Chief Buckley?
Four to nothing.
The motion passes.
We'll put together.
And if there is anyone interested in this, it takes us like a day to get this all up and running.
So I would give us just a few days to make sure it's worth the weekend looming on us.
2023-03 permit parking variances for Kelly, Scanlon, and Andrew Leap, 91 Bristol Road, Somerville, for MedFed.
The variance has been previously issued to this residence, but it was never, it's never been memorialized, and now that we have two different
uh, or a internal agent, uh, division department handling these, uh, we want to memorialize, uh, some of these non, um, uh, traditional park invariances that have never been sort of written down and fallen so that the parking department can, um, issue permit pocket.
So I'm going to let, um, if they ask, uh, Kelly Scanlon, I believe I saw a present.
I'm going to let you present, uh, the history of, uh, the petition for the commissioners.
Welcome and thank you.
Good thing.
Thank you for your time.
So yes, my husband, Andrew Leap and I moved here about a year and a half ago.
We were told there was gonna be a bit of an issue with parking as on Bristol Road, our apartment is in the only residential building on the street that is technically listed as Somerville.
The rest of the residential,
homes are Medford addresses.
And as such, all of the permit parking on our street is Medford parking.
The only parking available on Bristol Road is metered for Somerville.
So we've kind of had issues over the past year and a half since we've been here.
you know, going back and forth with Park Medford around, you know, our address.
And, you know, the exception, they argue that we should be able to park just in front of our house, but even on the tree that is directly in front of our front door, it says Medford parking.
So there is no place for us to park in an unmetered space.
Okay, thank you.
And I think that makes sense.
And traditionally you've had this variance that was granted by the traffic commission, but again, for some reason it's not written down.
And one of the things I want the commissioners to know, and I did some research on this, as it comes to that piece of property that we're trying to put up on the screen, is it's a really unique piece of property.
The majority of that street, except the very end is all in Medford.
Ms.
Scanlon's residential home, it's like the front door, that whole stairwell, the sidewalk, the street, is in the city of Medford.
The majority of the rest of the house is in Somerville.
The line cuts right through that.
And so historically, the residents have been granted a permit to park there.
I'll ask Ms.
Scanlon, can you comment with visitor passes granted to you?
Can you hear me, Ms.
Scanlon, can you unmute?
Sorry, I muted myself and then couldn't unmute again.
Yes, that's correct.
So we've been able to argue in the past that we required an exception to be able to park on our street and we've successfully been able to get parking permits for both of our cars.
Okay, thank you.
Um, to the commissioners.
And what about visitor passes?
I would assume you would need them as well.
And that driveway next to you.
That's not, is that your driveway?
Technically it's the properties driveway, but the truck you see is, um, I believe it's our landlords and the Jeep is, uh, it's in use by, um, by the,
apartment one, we're in apartment two, so we don't have any off street parking available to us.
As for visitor passes when we first moved in, we were told that the previous tenant had
kept or thrown away their visitor passes.
And as it was still in the middle of the year and we were unable to return that visitor pass or they were unable to provide it to us, we didn't have access to visitor passes.
And honestly, the last time we were just happy that we were able to get permit passes and we didn't want to make too big of a fuss.
But it sounds like that there was an understanding that there were visitor passes allocated to your apartment.
But you just personally did not have them.
That's correct.
Yeah, it's just helpful for us to understand sort of what's historically been done because the records, some are better than others.
Sure.
We're getting there.
Yeah.
And obviously it seems obvious to me that this is one of the very weird they're all we I'm aware that there are a number of properties we haven't put it up on the screen but I've looked at the map where the city line runs through people's private properties it's it's all over the city, it's hilarious when you don't have to personally deal with it and then it's frustrating as all get out.
So I think we should just approve them as if they lived in Medford with the Medford address for parking.
I'd be happy to hear from my fellow commissioners before I make a motion, but I'm bored.
I agree.
Commissioner McGivens is in agreement.
Commissioner Brzezinski, any comments, questions?
No, I think in this instance, I'd be OK with supporting that.
All right, so I'll turn it back to Commissioner Hunt.
Seeing no other public comment, is your motion going to include visitor passes?
Yeah, I think they should.
Honestly, it's just a weird city boundary that their address is not in Medford.
They should have the rights of anybody else who lives on that street.
In fact, I assume that we make them shovel that sidewalk or their landlord.
Yeah, just because the bedroom is in Somerville.
That's why it has the address in Somerville.
My office that I'm sitting in is in Medford.
It's an arbitrary rule.
It doesn't make any sense for a house with a property, a boundary line through it.
So we should be treating this like you live in Medford because your frontage is in Medford.
And that's where you park, that's when you shovel, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
Okay, on the motion of Commissioner Hunt to allow a variance for resident permit parking plus two visitor passes for 91 Bristol Road, seconded by?
Seconded by Commissioner McGibbon.
Roll call vote please.
Commissioner McGibbon.
Yes.
Commissioner Hunt.
Commissioner Brzezinski.
Yes.
Motion passes to nothing.
Thank you for your participation and your assistance in getting us through this.
We will notify the pocket department and you should be all set.
Wonderful.
Thank you.
2023-04 on petition Gaston Street.
Snow emergency parking assigned to odd side only between Racket and Taft Street.
I don't have the petitioner's name.
How would you know who the actual petitioner is?
And if they are present, raise your hand.
don't know how to raise your hand in this chat, just go to the chat room and try and send us a message or wave.
So we know I'm Nancy Burgess is raising is waving.
Okay.
Yep.
Nancy, welcome.
Thank you.
Good evening, everyone.
Mike Richard and I who's over there are in some other neighbors who are petitioning
for parking, snow parking, emergency parking on the odd side of the street.
If you'd let me read my notes, because I'm nervous.
Don't be nervous.
Please read from your notes.
We would respectfully like to petition the City of Medford for parking on the odd side of the street.
during snow emergencies, like always.
Currently the other end of Gadsden Street already has that.
They're not as hilly as us.
So, and we've been meaning to do this for many years.
The reason we're doing it is like I said, it's hilly and the other side of the street on the even side, everybody has a driveway, multiple car driveways,
Um, so they can fit several cars in their driveway.
Our side has, some houses have no driveways because we're hilly and we're up.
Some cars have, some houses have one car garage that's very small.
Um, so we can also have more parking space on our side because we can block the driveways that we really can't get into or the garage.
Um, so
Sorry.
Also, if we have to park on the even side this year, because of the change in the how you want us to park the direction of the flow of traffic.
HAB-Masyn Moyer.:
: Our end of the street.
We're on the we're on the higher end.
I'm at 85 and and down towards bracket street, but it inclines up, but it also HAB-Masyn Moyer.:
: Kind of HAB-Masyn Moyer.:
: Leans down towards the even side so
We've lived here many years and we've had cars that have been parked on that side of the street.
When people come around the corner and try to go up, they slide into our cars that are parked there.
So that's always been a problem.
So now that we're gonna have to go this way, I just feel like now we're gonna be sliding backwards into cars behind us as well.
So we would just like to petition that we have more parking on our side,
And the other side of the street has driveways with multiple car driveways in them, so they can park in their driveways.
I think there's only a couple of houses that have no driveways, but everybody on that side mostly does.
And most of the side doesn't have one, or they have a one car, small little garage.
Like I can't even fit in my garage, so.
I can definitely park in front of it.
And I'm nervous, I'm sorry.
So I know some people are unable to attend tonight.
They're working.
So we're just petitioning.
And I don't know if Mike would like to say something as well.
What's that?
I don't even know.
That's not our side of Galveston.
That's down towards... Yeah, bracket.
Yeah.
So, up there.
Which house are you?
I'm down further, a little bit further.
No, that's Brackett.
Turn the other way.
That's the other end of Gadsden that has street parking on that side already.
We're up this way.
Yes.
Okay, while he figures that out, there was, for the commissioners, there was a petition circulated for the residents, and it looks like, I mean, we're talking about the low numbers, so from like seven Gaston all the way through.
Like 90, 80 something, yeah.
90, yeah, 90 something, and just going quickly counting.
42 houses, there's 21 on each side.
42 houses and we have 32 signatures in support of the petitioner.
So before, I mean, I'm sure there's a number of people and I'm sure there are a number of people willing to speak on this subject matter.
The commissioners have any questions of the petitioners so we can have an answer for ourselves before we open it up to public.
I have a question.
This is Tim.
Is this, the agenda item says between Brackett and Taft, but I thought I heard, and my understanding is that Brackett, Gaston Street is like this the whole way.
So one side is high with retaining walls and not many driveways and stairs, then the other side is relatively flat with driveways.
So I guess I just want a clarification.
Are we talking about all of Gaston Street or just this one section between Brackett and Taft?
What we're talking about is just this section, but I believe what the petitioner told us is, and Sajan, you were not there, the rest of Brackett, I mean, the rest of Gaston Street already has this in play.
Oh, okay, got it, all right.
Tim, I believe from Fulton to Brackett is already in place.
This is from Brackett to Taft.
Okay, I would be in support of this.
I mean, it does make sense for reasons stated by the resident.
The other commissioners have any questions for a while before I, I, I just, I go ahead honestly I would defer to Tim as the DPW commissioner and the fact that it's his staff that has to deal with where the vehicles are parked and how that all works.
I would just want to ensure that is through this process, we're.
I think to the signs on the other end say something, it's just one thing that will happen is you know somebody sells a house somebody else moves in.
We advertise no parking emergency even side this year, how did the new people know it feels something that would be very important to somehow clear to people.
It is listed on the website, all the exceptions.
There's a bunch of them.
And then as far as the operations of it, the plow drivers are really just going to plow the drivable portion.
So, and that's what I was just looking at.
I don't think it's gonna affect geometry of how operations happen.
So they're just gonna clear the side of the street that doesn't have cars on it and have a path wide enough for travel.
So I was looking at that, it doesn't seem like
there's any benefit to swapping one side to the other for polling operations on this particular stretch.
So Tim, there's no benefit to having like, and I guess why is this now an issue?
I don't know how long it's been this way, but there's no benefit to having a portion of the road one side, a portion of the road the other side.
Not from a prime perspective, but from an equity perspective and get, you know, providing relief, because sometimes it's burdensome to have to cross the street during snowstorms.
So I think the genesis of this is basically to swap responsibilities back and forth in neighborhoods.
We're just going to plow the path through.
That makes sense.
I see a few hands up.
I'm sorry Commissioner, just one last thing and then we have there's, I think I've accounted 42 houses on that street, and we have 30, we only have 32 in support of this.
I got in front of me, just those 42 houses in that section 32 signatures in several the, I shouldn't say several, the other 123456789.
It should be an easy 10, right?
Not home.
There's actually a few more that are not home.
Okay.
And all the residential number just skips.
That's all I had.
All right.
So let me open it up to public comment, but let me first hear from those in favor of the petition.
So if you're in favor of the petition, please raise your hand.
wave in front, and I'll just gonna turn to you, Saj, if you just wanna call them out and open them up.
Yes, I just lost Gary.
Gary and Kathy, you guys were raising your hand.
No, you're not in favor.
Okay.
Okay, that's fine.
Molly and David, we're gonna ask you to unmute.
Hello, can you hear me?
Yes.
Yes, welcome and thank you.
Thank you so much for holding this conversation.
My partner, David, and I live at 96 Gaston Street.
So we are on the even side of the road.
We've lived here since, oh goodness, 2003.
So 10 years now.
The way that it currently works is the parking is odd every other year and even every other year.
So we're having the odd side parking, you know, half the time.
As a resident on the even side, I don't think it makes much of a difference to us, as pointed out by Nancy, excellently presented, by the way, Nancy.
You know, half the time it's on that side anyway.
It doesn't affect us.
We have our own, our driveways.
I would love to see this pass because it would make the quality of life higher for our neighbors.
You know, the folks that we live near, we love them.
We do want them to be more comfortable and we're already, you know,
living with having the parking on the odd side half the time, why not make it all the time?
Thank you for your comments and for your participation in the process.
Next, Michael Richard.
Yes, I live down at the very end.
Can you hear me?
Yes.
Yes, I live at the very beginning of, between the beginning of Brackett towards Gaston.
and I live on that hill Nancy was explaining in two and it's an optical illusion hill.
When you're parked, I've been here for 35 years and when you're parked going uphill, then the way the traffic flows, if you don't have a four wheel drive vehicle, you're not getting out of that spot.
So, uh, for the last 30 years, we've been parking going down the hill, which is a lot easier to get out of and not get stuck.
So, um,
and that's one of the reasons.
And the other reason is like she said, the houses on that side of the street all have at least two car driveways that can be utilized for them.
And also getting in and out of the driveway, if they park on the even side and somebody's in that driveway, it gives them, and there's snow piled up on the other side of the street, it's awful hard for them to get in and out of their driveway.
There's telephone poles and everything else.
that come into play.
So like Nancy said, we've been talking about this for a few years now, and now we've finally been putting it together.
And it seems like more than 75% of the people on the street are in favor of this petition.
So that's about all I have to say.
It would make everything more comfortable for everybody, that's for sure.
Understood.
Thank you for your comments and for your participation.
Much appreciated.
Um, Gary and Kathy, we're going to ask you on mute.
We have other people.
We're just going along.
Okay.
My name is Silvania Silva.
I leave at 56 guests on the street.
I signed the petition favor, but I understood wrong.
I was, which is very narrow in my driveway.
If I tried to get out of it, then it's known that sign.
I can't get out because the cars, the other side.
So it's narrow for him over there, I understand.
But for us over here, it's too many trucks.
People don't need here, it's too many trucks and it's very narrow.
So I don't agree with that.
I will say the same thing too.
I'm at 60 Gaston Street.
I'm next to Silvani.
And if you have trucks of snow across the street, it's murder to get out of there.
And basically makes the driveways unusable.
So more people are going to have to park on the street.
I'm Kathy Floyd, because that's going to make access in and out.
All right.
Sorry.
I just want to keep it to in favor only and then give those who are not in favor an opportunity.
So please raise your hand if you're in favor of the petition so we can hear this in a clear and concise way.
Otherwise, we're going to be here all night long.
And I don't want to get this into an argument.
So if you're in favor of the petition, raise your hand and we will
allow you to speak and then we will get to those.
I wish to speak against the petition.
Paul, we're going to ask you.
Paul, welcome.
Hi, how are you?
Um, I live, I live at 25 Gaston and I've been here for 65 years in until Nancy just mentioned it.
I agree with her.
I've, I've slid into that other side of this.
street across from her house and across from Mike's house.
I've actually done that trying to get up the street.
And I also looked, there's on the even side, there's 17, there's actually 41 homes on the street.
There's 42 lots, but only 41 homes.
One's an empty lot.
There's 17 homes out of the 20 on the even side that have at least two parking spots and more off street.
On the odd side, we have zero.
is there are no homes with more than two spots on the odd side.
And on the even side, I think there's only one that has no off-street parking, but it's at the very end where Taft is, and they're across the street from an odd house that actually has two spots on Taft.
So they don't park in front of their house.
So they have plenty of spots on the other side.
So most of the homes on our side, on the odd side,
There's two that don't have any parking, but I agree with Nancy and Mike that there's more places to park on our side than there are on the even.
So when people on our side during winter and it's even parking, sometimes it's really a pain because there's actually less spots to park because they all have driveways.
So it makes it more difficult.
So I'm in support of making it odd side only.
because it just seems like it would be better for everybody on the street if we did that.
So I'm in favor.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments and your participation.
Do you have anyone else?
I know you have multiple screens.
I think I see you're on mute.
Hi, my name is Ellen.
I live at 35 Gaston Street.
Welcome.
Thank you.
I agree with the petition.
When we come home on in the snow storm we come by or taft and come down the hill, because we're in the in a Dale, it's hills and dales on our street.
So we're on a Dale.
And if we parked across the street.
We would be trying to get uphill.
So that's what we deal with in the winter.
But this year, now that we need to park in the proper direction, you're stuck trying to get uphill to go towards Taft.
If we're on our side, then we can just roll down a little bit and go towards Brackett Street.
And we all have to leave by Brackett in a storm.
and you would slide to the left into the even side of the street if you're trying to get down the hill to bracket to go home to get away from home.
So I agree with the petition.
Thank you for your comments and your participation.
All right.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Anybody else?
Raise your hand.
Check the screen.
The other residents in favor.
Okay, I'll open the floor to anyone who wishes to speak against the petition.
Raise your hand.
Joan.
Just have to unmute.
Welcome.
Can you hear me?
Yes, we can.
Welcome.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
And appreciate all of the input into this.
And I have thought about this petition for a long time.
and I'm very concerned over some of these issues.
And to be very brief, I'll put it in seven points.
One is plowing.
I live near Gary, Kathy, and Sylvania at 55 Gaston Street.
It is the narrowest neck of the street, and I could reach out my arm to touch cars on the other side.
and with snow and snow banks and cars, it makes it almost impossible to get in and out of a driveway.
Also, I'm gonna skip most of the other six and go to the seven.
We have people in homes with multiple family members and each of those members have cars and trucks.
And if you think they're on the even side and that they can park all their cars and trucks in the driveway, please think again.
There are at least four cars or trucks that are already parked on Gaston Street.
They live down the street from where we are on the upper end.
And they take spaces from the residents near our homes in order to park.
That's a big issue here and there have been conflicts on the street as a result of this.
I've been on the street too for decades.
I'm 78 years old and the odd even alternate side has worked for decades.
I appreciate the comments and the input that people have given
for parking on the odd side and what their issues are.
I respect that.
But also on the other side, you also have to respect our issues.
When there is plowing on this street, if it's going to be on the odd side that people are parked, then the snowplow blade has to go towards the even side.
And all the people on the even side are going to have these large snowbank walls to have to deal with.
And when they're ice, that's even worse.
And the people on the odd side that have bumper to bumper cars and trucks all along like a domino line need to practically shovel or snowblow out into the middle of the street before we can get out.
We are taxpayers too.
And we have a right to access in and out of our homes.
And I think that Paul mentioned we have at least two spaces.
Paul, I disagree with you.
I was talking about neighbors down the street that are parking near us.
They park in front of my house.
So there's a parking space that is missing for nearby neighbors that live near me.
Safety issues is a concern here.
For years, I've seen this street even getting narrower and narrower with all the big, why don't everybody on Gaston Street need big trucks?
Police, fire, ambulance, and city vehicles have trouble getting through.
If there are cars on the street, snow banks, I have witnessed that.
I have been abused verbally by neighbors that have blocked DPW trucks from going by because they can't get by.
What would happen if, say, a family member of yours
had an emergency and went by a wide boxed ambulance and that ambulance couldn't get by on the street.
What about space grabs?
Have you ever thought of that?
These families that have multiple cars living on the even side of the street, where are they going to go when the parking bin is odd only they're going to space grab other residents that live on the odd side of the street.
I have witnessed it personally.
And there have been arguments and conflict on this street, as a result of it.
And some of the people who are far the odd side, their family members have had this trouble in the past.
They will just pull in.
these other people to cleared out spaces just for themselves when residents that have parked on the odd side have shoveled and cleared out those spaces.
We have to look at the deeper infrastructure of all of this and not just say, hey, odd, even.
There's more to it than that.
You have to look more deeply into it.
And what about the enforcement of this law of odd and even?
How will it be enforced?
What if somebody space grabs?
They don't belong in front of somebody's home.
Similar communities.
Have we looked at similar communities that have put this into place where odd or even would be a permanent snow parking restriction?
I looked up online that Quincy and Haverhill have tried this and
Maybe we should look into that.
I mean, I'm not saying that, you know, go ahead if you wish, but maybe there should be a little bit of a study on this so that we have a better perspective on where we're coming from and where we are going.
There has to be, I'll tell you a little insert, in the Haverhill, the mayor of Haverhill during February of 22, they had a plowing problem with this odd and even
a plan in place.
And the plows could not, it was on the even side.
Everybody had a park on the even side that was permanent.
The snow plows came down and they weren't able to do the whole even side.
So the next day
They went back and all of the people who were correctly and legally parked on the even side had to move over to the odd side so the snow plows could finish their work.
There has to be flexibility in this.
It can't be just etched in stone.
There are going to be circumstances throughout the years where things are going to have to remain flexible.
And I myself have been a victim.
Yes, victimized by driveway entries and exits.
out of my own driveway with bumper and bumper cars on the odd side of the driveway, as well as abutting my own driveway.
Talking about law and enforcement.
All right, it's impossible in the winter, I know, for three feet distance from a driveway.
I understand that, but they are overlapping a driveway.
What's going to happen if all of the cars have to park on the odd side of the driveway?
Don't you think they're going to squeeze in to any space they can, even if it is overlapping the driveway?
And then what happens to the resident in their home who's trying to get out to go to work?
John, I appreciate the comments and your participation.
That was a deep look into the issue.
There's two questions you asked.
I just want to make sure I answer them for you first.
One, enforcement is done by the Medford Police Department.
And two, while historically there are people in the city who still use that or adhere to the concept of spacecrafts,
The Medford police does not condone it.
The DPW does not condone it.
And we cannot allow those things to happen as it moves forward.
So, but I really, really do appreciate your comments on this.
Anyone else against the petition?
Chief, can you just explain for me?
I think that the term space grab, I've heard of space savers and that's the thing you put in the space to save it.
And my understanding is we don't allow that in Medford.
Correct.
That's the interpretation.
The resident meant people were grabbing the space she had shoveled out.
And that's what she was objecting to, that she wasn't able to save the space.
Well, we could refer back to her for comment, but either way, I mean, I get it.
I mean, it puts the city and the police department in a very difficult position to have to say,
I mean, it's public streets, public parking, residents have the right to park.
We can never sit there and say, you have an entitlement to park in the street, even if you shovel it up.
I mean, I think neighborhoods resolve those issues sometimes themselves, but if you involve the police, we only have one option.
It's public street and public parking.
So, and I think either way would be handled by the police department in the same manner.
Thank you.
Anyone else wishing to speak against the petition?
I have to slide down.
This is Sheila.
Sheila, I'm going to ask you to unmute.
Sheila, welcome.
Sheila, just got unmuted on your phone.
So I agree with Joan.
I think it's not fair to the residents on the even side that it should be on each side each year.
It should change every year.
And then the even side residents have to contend with the snow being piled up on their side, and I just don't think it's fair to the residents on the even side of the street.
Well, I'm in opposition of it as well.
Sheila, thank you for your participation in your comments.
Anyone else should speak against it?
Gary.
Just got on mute guys.
I mean, Kathy.
I'm going to ask you to unmute and then you can unmute it.
Hi, I get it.
Uh, I just want to, I just want to say that, um, I think that Joan put it extremely well.
There is real problems at this part of the street because of how narrow it is and how many trucks and cars and stuff like that, that are on this part of the street.
And one of the things too.
One of the things too it's actually very interesting because you're actually having two different parts of the street that are arguing one thing.
in a different part of the street that's arguing something else.
And I know that they have brought, I know they've brought the police up here before because we have people with out of state plates that are parking here overnight and they don't do anything about it.
And I don't even think that's legal to do.
I mean, so my question would be who's actually enforcing the parking?
That is the Medford Police Department.
I think you need to have a conversation with the Medford Police Department as to why they don't enforce it.
I don't know.
Specifically just parking in general?
No, they're parking overnight on the street.
They leave it overnight on the street and the plates are from New Hampshire.
All right, Chief, can I address this?
Please, Sergeant.
I spoke to the owner of that truck in question.
He's claiming that he does not stay here.
Well, then I would send a police cruiser up around here to check it.
And it's not just a... Sir, this is not a forum for argument.
You brought an issue up.
I need to have my traffic sergeant address it.
Thank you.
Chief, I spoke to the owner of that truck.
He said he lives in New Hampshire.
He visits his girlfriend now and then.
He does not live at 70 Gaston Street, and therefore he is not required to register his place in Massachusetts.
I spoke to him, I believe it was last Sunday.
Okay.
So it's Gary and Kathy, and I'll just leave it this way.
I will have my traffic sergeant reach out to you.
In some sense, this isn't exactly pertained to what we're discussing here, the odd even parking issues, but you do have an argument and a legitimate concern that if there are cars that are parking on the street, it's not.
So I'll have the traffic sergeants reach out to you separately so we don't take up time on the commission meeting to handle that as it relates to the police department.
Is there anyone else wishing to speak in opposition?
I think somebody someone else with you.
Yep.
Go ahead.
We'll open it up.
There you go.
Welcome again.
Hi, it's Kathy Floyd.
I can't all of the additional cars and trucks and everything affects the parking.
No, yep.
I'm just trying to recognize whether or not it's a snow emergency or whether it's it's not in there is a car that is parking with the answer plates.
Okay, understood.
Anyone else wishing to speak in opposition?
Seeing none, could we, can you flip the second page?
Sorry about that.
Anyone else?
We didn't see anyone there, okay.
Turn it back to the commissioners for comments or questions.
I have a question.
Just to clarify, what are we doing now?
It's one year odd, one year even?
Correct, yes.
Okay.
Yep.
And who makes these initial determinations on what side of the street?
should be parking.
So the long-standing traffic commission process is the winter starts in say 2022 like this year it is even side parking the winter starts next year and say 2023 it's odd side parking that has been in play for in my entire 25 years career and it's during snow emergencies Sergeant Rogers said 40 years so but in this situation equity issues
In situations where you create safety hazards as a result of the choices.
I mean, is there another group, maybe Tim's group who weighs in on like, uh, the one gentleman mentioned that when traffic or when snow plowings on one direction going to.
Uh, bracket street, I think he mentioned becomes like a safety hazard.
Are there some situations where the odd even really doesn't work because you create safety issues when you switch it?
So, yeah, so it's a good question.
I can't think of one offhand with that's currently in that play and I know that's one of the arguments being made to us before us tonight but I can't think of one offhand that's made to it.
There are some locations in the city, where we choose one side, every single year and that's generally because there's like a park across the street.
and a certain street might have a public park across the street and residents park in front of their house year round.
Um, that, that seems to be the, probably the biggest exception to this rule.
Otherwise it is odd even across the city.
Yeah.
Uh, you know, I think this is a prime example of equity and I don't necessarily know that there's unanimity on what
the street needs.
So absent some sort of safety issue that's created when traffic is one way or another, which I don't necessarily think this committee is in a position to rule on, I think that's more of a public's work, not to give Tim more things to do, but to evaluate that there are true safety issues that come when the parking is on one side versus the other.
You know, unfortunately in this city, what you deal with is exactly what you're dealing with.
Streets are narrow, there are way too many cars.
So switching this to one side of the street, I don't think solves the problem.
Again, absent the safety issue, which in that case, I don't think it's our position to actually rule on that, so.
Thank you, Commissioner Brzezinski.
Commissioner McGibbon, Commissioner Hunt?
Yeah, I get a couple of things, I guess.
It was brought up and I am aware of this there's more parking spaces on the odd side than the even side that that's a factor here, and I would say Steve it's more of a operational challenges, when it comes to where to put snow and how to push it.
And I think a couple of the residents on both sides that brought that up.
So we try not to plow into the vehicles if we don't have to, we do try to remove and clear the snow, so push it to a place, as opposed to just pile up the wind rose inside.
You know, but we're, we're limited because of the narrow streets.
So, you know,
Also, what has been said a couple times it's really about equity that's where this policy comes from.
What is interesting in this situation is the difference of the sides of the street, where the houses are higher on one side with no off street parking or very little off street parking and then the other side, less parking spaces on street and more off street.
So that makes this a little, little interesting.
As, as well as the idea that 32 of the homes signed a petition that would like this.
So I kind of have a couple questions.
One is, do we know how many more parking spaces are on the odd side versus the even side?
And then my next question is, do we know the reason why the other portion of Gaston Street was granted this variance, I guess you could call it?
I, we do not have the answer to either one of those questions.
And I suggest it probably would.
Wouldn't be difficult to obtain them, but we're not going to get that.
Okay.
Commissioner Hunt.
Yeah.
I guess I come down to.
if this would be easy if all the residents were in favor.
Given that there are some who are strongly opposed, I feel like then it really comes down to safety and operations.
And if this was coming from originally from Tim's office, like look, this would make a huge operational difference, then that would make a big deal.
I think that if there is any
information on such or who would give information on the safety issue because I am concerned about the cars that slide and stuff and that it's worse and it gets worse.
And I do want to just actually point out one thing that I picked up on that residents pointed out that's changed here.
And what's changed is that
They, part of this road is relatively steep and they've made it very clear that it is, if not safe, they don't feel comfortable driving down in one direction or up in one direction.
They have trouble in ice and snow.
I also live in Fulton Heights, so I'm familiar with other, I'm not familiar with this street specific issue, but there are streets, my own, that I will only exit in one direction during snow events.
because of exactly this, you'll slide into the intersection if you go down it.
So we do have streets that are like this, I know it.
But the key thing that's changed here is that in Medford, traditionally, nobody has ever cared which side of the street you park in on facing in which direction.
And that is actually something that our current traffic department has stated is a safety issue, that if you park on the wrong side, facing the wrong way on the side of the road, that that's a safety issue.
and therefore they feel very strongly about ticketing for it.
And that is new this year.
And if that's in fact causing people to now have to park in a way that then means that they're not feeling safe and they're having to slide down the hill or they can't, sorry, I didn't quite follow which years it's a problem in which direction, but it was my understanding from the way that the residents discussed this,
the odd side of the street parking or the even side would alleviate that issue, allow you to be facing in the direction you're going to slide and not be sliding backwards down the hill if you were to park over there.
And that it sounded to me maybe, I don't know if we need to confirm this or not, that in previous years, people just parked on the even side or parked on the side of the correct side of the street and if necessary, pointed their car in the direction that they felt was safest for sliding down the hill, not the way that's legally required.
And that actually.
It's something that changed.
Why is it an issue this year and it never was before?
And I think that we should actually consider that, that the enforcement of the rule of parking in the correct direction may have actually increased the dangerousness of parking on that street, on that side of the street during snow events.
I feel that that's what I was hearing.
And that makes me a little concerned about this.
I do feel like, well, we could do more research, we could get some safety numbers, we could get some information on accident reports or whatever.
If people even mention accidents, I mean, I certainly don't report it every time I slide into the intersection of Fulton Street, because I've gone the wrong way.
But if I hit another car, hopefully I would.
On the other hand, we're at the start of the month that is one of the snowiest months of the year and this is when it's going to be a problem is during February I'm very sorry that we were not talking about this in May or November, and would feel like we had more time to think about it.
We should to address your first couple questions there.
If we were to like table is to a date certain, I could also ask.
my crews if there are issues on this particular stretch and if there are operation and safety issues on this stretch.
I don't think there is, but getting their perspective may be helpful in this particular situation.
So, and I would say that I think it's always been a rule to park in the direction of travel.
I think it just hasn't been enforced.
So, I mean, all those rule followers have been parking in the direction of travel.
I understand it hasn't been enforced, but... I wasn't aware that it was a law until it came up this year.
Yeah, definitely is.
So... I have a quick question.
If you have an issue where your group is the better group to evaluate a situation for safety or ease,
Can the community make petitions to your group to evaluate?
Because what I'm getting to is I really don't want to table this.
But I love the idea of your group looking at this and deciding, look, for safety factors or ease of pushing snow, it's better for us to look at this.
Because I'm afraid this issue will go with the rest of tabled items and die a slow, painful death.
But at the same time, I don't want the community to think like we're giving up on the issue.
In this situation, given the split, even though it's 32-42, it's not unanimous.
I like the equity factor.
I will support the motion, but I don't want the issue to be lost if there are safety concerns with what's going on.
Yeah, that's a good but I don't necessarily like tabling things either.
Things get tabled for different reasons but we can table to a date certain, so everybody that's here.
Here's I say that, and it's on the agenda.
Next time we meet if that's next month.
The timing isn't that great, as Alicia mentioned, but again, we want to make this decision correctly.
I understood understood that 32 out of 41 want it.
but we don't want to make a decision that is wrong.
I think it was Nancy who spoke against it.
Her most salient point to me, really, out of all of her excellent points, was the one that we should look into this deeply, because this is a decision that will impact operations, could impact safety, and is something that sticks.
I think I totally agree, but is it is there is there a way to petition your group directly to take a look at it versus it coming through us first because I think.
this issue sounds like if there are safety concerns and or logistical concerns, it should have been to your group to begin with before it came to us.
So you said- The answer is yes, and they could just do that.
It doesn't have to be a petition.
It can just be a group of residents that want to ask me a question basically, and I can come back with an answer.
I think a lot of these things over the years have been hashed out, which is why we have a list of exceptions to the odd even rule.
We do.
And that has been a result of things like operations, safety,
where the snow goes there's a park on one side, etc etc.
So, you know, over time, that that's been what what has happened so I think, absolutely.
Is this the wrong form.
But this would be the forum that makes that or the commission that makes that that formal decision right.
But certainly the DPW would be the advisor from an operation and safety standpoint.
So, I would like to table this to the next meeting, where I can get feedback from my crew, bring that information back to this meeting.
There's very well could be something I'm not thinking of.
that at the end of the street where it meets tap, there's a railing and some stairs, most likely we pile snow in that area.
So an operational issue could be that one side of the street or the other is favorable for where we put snow.
It seems like it would be better to have cars on the odd side for that, so we could push snow into a place at the end of the street.
But at the same time, is it a big deal?
I don't drive a plow.
I'd want to talk to the plow drivers.
Is there a way, though, like when you come back next month, like you could have a recommendation on what we should do versus like, here are the pros.
I'd love to know what your group says, like, look, we should switch it.
Or look, there's no benefit one way or another.
Just so in next month when we come to this, we won't have as much discussion about it.
We'll have a clear understanding from your group.
Again, the safety concerns that Alicia points out, which I really focus on, if we table it, I'll support a tabling if we can get some idea
That next month, I'll have a clear cut answer from your group as to what's the best course.
What I can promise is if if there's something that we're not thinking of that I can.
flag and advise on.
I don't think I can advise one way or the other.
I think the place where we begin is a place of equity, odd, even side.
And we have information, some of that information that is persuasive.
Most of the residents want it on odd.
And the questions that are still on the table are, are there major operational issues here?
Are there major safety issues here?
And, you know,
Do we want to remove the equity piece in the interest of those other issues.
Another big one to me I think is the number of spaces.
And when you look at the street itself.
It, you know, there's more spaces on the outside so there's more places for people to park.
And another question I'm hoping we could have answer to in this timeframe is, why did the other section of Gaston get this exception?
And, you know, does that reason extend to this side?
It is an unusual street where I think it's been described, the house is up on one side, level on the other side with driveway.
So it is unusual.
So I think it's worthy of taking a deeper look into it as one of the residents said.
All right.
Thank you.
So we have a motion to table for Commissioner McGiven.
I just offer, you know, from the chair's perspective that, uh, as a voting member, I'd be hot pressed to break the equity issue here.
We've been practicing this in the city of Memphis for a long time and it has been, um, it has been successful.
And I just will also remind you that I would really, uh,
I really would like us to look at this and the issue of safety, as in multiple facets because of it.
We have other streets who have hills, we could be opening up an issue where residents just decide they want to take it upon themselves and start voting every street one side or the other and I, I do not think the Traffic Commission.
should break its sort of tradition of providing equity on either side, who gets plotted and who doesn't.
And so I just offer that as a suggestion, but we do have a motion to table.
Do I have a second?
Chief, I just want to actually clarify something.
And it's the use of the word equity, because equity means giving people what they need to be able to succeed in the situation.
Equality means treating everyone equally.
Equality.
What we are talking about is equality.
Everybody gets their own side, their own turn at doing it.
Equity would be giving them what they actually need to be successful, which would mean treating each street independently the way it needs to be treated, which in fact might actually mean the side with more spots is the one that people park on.
We throw that term around and we're talking about treating everybody equally here.
Okay, motion.
Okay, so thank you.
So we have a motion to table for commission we're giving, and to look at the safety issues in the, in the parking areas.
Do I have a second, just correction to date, sir.
Well, it will be the February traffic commission meeting.
Yes, correct.
I have that written down.
Yeah, most of the table to the February traffic commission meeting.
I'll second that.
I could hit by Commissioner.
Commissioner McGiven?
Yes.
Commissioner Hunt?
Commissioner Brzezinski?
Yes.
Yes for nothing.
The motion has been tabled with the understanding that the DPW will conduct some research into the matter.
And I also pledged that the traffic commission will dig out the reasons and the date of when the other end of Gaston street was the bonafide.
Does anybody, would anybody have any information on reported like accidents, accidents?
Could we get that information as well?
I can get you a list of accidents.
Yes.
I think it would be helpful.
And frankly, if you're able to circulate this data in advance, that might be easier for the commission members to review it.
Yep.
We can do that.
Thanks.
I'm just making a note here.
I apologize for the silence.
Yeah.
Just to follow up on Alicia's point, anything that speaks to the safety or the logistics of changing it.
I think that'd be the best information to have.
I'll find out what I can.
Thanks, Sam.
Excellent.
All right.
2023-05, request from Bridget O'Donohue, 6th Alston Court for permit parking variance and visitor passes for Alston Street.
Let me pull this map up just to kind of show.
Is the petitioner present?
And if so, I'll ask you to unmute yourself.
What's the name again?
Sorry.
Bridget O'Donohue.
Raise your hand just so we can, there's a couple of people on there.
If you can make a message in the chat, Bridget O'Donohue, we're not seeing you on the name table.
Are you perhaps using a different name?
Nothing, interesting.
The history of this is that,
Can you just pull the map up just just so the conditions understand before we make a decision on what to do with it.
Austin court is a very small driveway driveway essentially but I'm going to try to show it to you here.
And correct me if I'm wrong with this is one again that has had a historic variance.
been granted, but it was never memorialized.
The parking department doesn't have a record of the traffic commission approving it, and the intent was for the petitioner to present her argument for parking pass and parking visitor passes, which she has historically had one
Yeah.
And if you can just look at the, you can see how small Austin, Austin courted trying to get you guys that this is the view here.
Chief, just to be clear, that says Austin Terrace.
Is it the same or don't you look at that road?
You look at the road sign, I think it says Austin Terrace, she in the back.
oddly when I look on Google Maps Austin court and Austin terrace seem to be on either side of Austin street from each other, but when you look at it from Street View one looks like it's just a driveway.
The one that Street View tries to claim is all just in court.
Yeah, I.
The Alston, actually, no, it has a street sign next to that driveway there.
This is it, guys.
Right there, yeah.
Sorry.
Yep.
So the house or the resident can, I don't know if we can try and get, it's never gonna even let you down there.
The Google car can't get out.
Well, I don't think it needs to present much.
There is a residence down there.
It does not really have the ability to park on that driveway.
A driveway because should our roadway I mean it looks like a driveway but it's technically a roadway, and, you know,
fire ambulances, police cars, if somebody's parking there, we cannot get through.
I think traditionally that has been the reason for this to have been granted to the residents and they've had it for many, many years.
Again, this is, it's not something that we've declined in the past, but it is never been, it has never been memorialized and we need to, we need to consider this.
One other,
point is that that Austin court is a private way.
And same sort of argument we've had in the past.
How do we provide variances onto public ways or private way residents?
But I think this one's sort of obvious, right?
If that's where they have to park and they can't get down to that house, it's
Chief what I can't tell it from the images if you could just clarify it sounds like you're, you're your staff maybe more familiar.
It appears that there's one single family house down there with a car in front of it, but I'm starting to suspect that maybe it's a multi unit building or maybe it's.
And is there parking down there, like, this is all this is again what why we really need the petitioner here.
The family has lived there since 1965, and they lived there with their elderly parents.
So at least from the petition request from Ms.
O'Donohue, it appears to be a single family home.
I just can't.
I can try and zoom out a little bit, if that helps.
I guess I just want to understand, right, if somebody lives at the end of a private way and they have private parking down there, they don't need
Why are they asking for street parking, on the other hand, that I'm making a lot of assumptions here.
yeah.
I guess that's why we need.
The notified they indicated they would be here.
Looks like there's two houses at the end.
I think that might have access on the other side.
Historically, when the petitioner is not here, we table it for one month and then remove it.
The motion to table it and let them know that they have to come explain what's going on.
I mean, if they really can't come, they could send us a detailed letter explaining it.
Okay, we'll do and they had agreed to come.
So I mean, I always list that up there, but let's just look one more time and make sure that there's no one present here.
And then we're going to take a vote.
Well, actually we have a motion to table, so I can't do anything, but take the motion to table motion to table by commissioner hunt.
Do I have a second?
Alicia, would you modify just to make it a date certain?
Motion to table just one month.
Yes, motion to table for one month.
Second.
Seconded by Commissioner Brzezinski on the motion to table for one month.
Alva, roll call vote.
Commissioner McGibbon.
I think Tim quit.
Yes or no.
Yes.
Yes, for the nothing the motions approved table for one month, let's just reach out to them, make sure that 2023 606 proposed fee waiving for senior residents obtaining visitor passes without the purchase of resident parking permit, and this was presented.
requested of the commission from the mayor.
I think if I could speak quickly on this matter.
Currently seniors, senior residents do not pay a fee, it's been waived.
for, let me just read it.
I respectfully request and recommend that your body consider the following change to the fee structure of obtaining visitor parking passes.
It is the opinion of this office that visitor parking passes for seniors should not carry a fee as that is penalizing senior residents who do not operate a motor vehicle.
Currently senior residents over 65 years of age who have not purchased a resident parking permit are subjected to a $5 fee for each of the two visitor passes they are allotted as a resident of Medford.
Seniors who are purchasing a resident parking permit receive two visitor passes free of charge.
Thank you for your kind attention to this matter.
Cecily Briana Lungo-Kern, Mayor, City of Medford.
So to put this quite frankly, if you are a resident and you own a car,
you receive a resident permit and two visitor passes free of charge.
However, if you are a senior and you do not own a vehicle, and you wish to have two visitor passes which you are entitled to, you have to pay $5 per
permit to per visitor pass.
So the request from the mayor's office for the traffic commission to review that since the intent several years ago, I think it was in 2019, we changed and made senior parking free was to sort of address this issue to this.
So I opened up to the commissioners for questions.
It's hopefully seems straightforward as I presented it.
And if I confused you, I apologize.
Question, do we have any input on how many people like how many people are affected by this, like how many people are paying this $5 fee.
He's all like it seems like a budget issue I don't necessarily know us a waving fees is what the city needs right now but you know the mayor's in charge of the budget.
I believe so we've dealt with this only a handful of times since we passed this in 2019.
And so I think it's a very small number.
And as I said, if they had a vehicle, it would cost them no money any, you know, it would, it would just be free.
So it's, I guess it's being presented as a
as an issue of fairness, so to say.
But we, I mean, Alba, I'm trying to think back since 2019 when we passed this, it's only like a very small handful of times that the question's been posed to us.
Yeah, but I do not have the numbers, Commissioner Brzezinski, as to how many it is, but I can, just from experience, I'm betting you that it is a very small number.
And just one last point, just to be clear what you just said, this $5 fee was put in place by the Traffic Commission back in 2019, is that?
but I heard no.
In 2019, what was petitioned was for senior residents who own a vehicle to pay a fee to obtain a resident permit parking.
When they obtained that resident permit parking, two free visitor passes come with that.
In 2019, it wasn't specifically addressed the matter of what if you don't own a vehicle?
And so a resident of, say 30 year old resident,
who doesn't have a vehicle is still entitled to visitor passes, but they have to pay a fee.
And who sets the fees for parking permits?
Who determines $10, $5, no charge?
Right, all fees are set by the city council and I was privy to a conversation with the mayor about this and we did believe that it may also, it might also have to go to the city council, but that this board definitely needed to vote as well on it.
And that was part, right?
Am I confusing two items, Chief?
No, I think you're pretty much on target.
Generally, there's always a level of redundancy in what we do as far as city government.
When we were in the meeting, what we were discussing is that there is one category in our fee system for visitor permits, period, and that fee is $5 per permit, so $2.10 per two.
In order for the city council
to actually vote for senior permits to be free, we actually have to vote and create a category for senior visitor permits.
And if we create the category for senior visitor permits, and perhaps with the advice that this is so that they could be at a less expensive or a different rate than regular visitor permits, then the council could vote that they would be free.
Otherwise, there's only one category and the Council can't create the new category because the categorization is under the purview of the Traffic Commission.
I like the idea.
I don't know if Alicia can put exactly what she said in a motion, but I would support that.
Right.
So the motion would be to create a category for senior visitor permits with the recommendation that they should be free.
I like all of that.
If the council decided that it was our purview, the rate, then fine.
We've just voted it to be free.
And if not, then we have not overstepped.
I like that.
I like the recommendation aspect.
So if that's an official motion, I'll second that.
I will say that my thought process on this is that
I like to encourage that people can have visitors, that particularly seniors could have people come visit them, that they may need aids and assistance, or they may just need family or friends to come, and they should have visitor passes.
And the idea, and I will question our fee structure to no end with the amount that we charge for parking permits, but on the other hand, if the parking permits for seniors are free, then their visitor passes should be free.
That's sort of my perspective.
That's my perspective on it.
Okay.
So let me just be clear.
If I have it on the motion of the commissioner, create a category for senior resident visitor passes with the recommendation that they should be free.
Um, essentially an attempt to match the, um, senior resident permit market.
Does that sound right?
Yes.
Thank you.
Do we need to take, um, public comments on this at all?
I haven't seen anybody.
That's good, while we have the motion before I notify the second.
Does anyone here wish to speak publicly on this?
I almost got caught up in myself there.
Anyone wishing to speak public comment, raise your hand.
Okay, seeing none, I will go back to the motion and I have a second by Commissioner Brzezinski.
I'll go roll call vote.
Commissioner McGibbon?
Yes.
Commissioner Hunt?
Commissioner Brzezinski.
Yes.
Chief Buckley.
A vote of four to nothing.
The motion is approved.
This is just for visitor passes.
Yes, correct.
2023 dash zero seven request for 23 spaces in the upper city hall lot on clipper ship drive be deemed mixed use spaces for commuter and paid parking.
I was led to believe that director Morrison would be here tonight to discuss this.
Did she have her, did she see what she wrote out here before I, and I don't know if director Blake is, is, has the ability to comment on this, the request to the traffic commission from the market director, Miss Morrison says, I request that the city make 23 spaces in the upper city hall lot on clipper ship drive be deemed mixed use spaces.
for commuter and paid parking.
Please see the enclosed drawing outlining the spaces in the request.
I also request that the current signage be moved to cover the 23 parking spaces in this request.
Um, and she sent it to the director Blake.
Do you have, um, I know you've been involved in this and might be a little bit unfair, but if you can speak to it.
Yeah.
Um, so this is a lot we're talking about.
It's a city hall lot.
That's between Clippership drive and I 93.
Some people say behind the Hyatt.
So it's this lot right here.
So I believe Faye was recommending that the spaces in this back edge along this greenery here and then there's a few right along this parcel here.
So those 23 would be allocated right now.
The signage shows this entire area.
I think the revised is just this back area, at least at this point.
see if I can get a better view for you all.
So it would be this back area here along this fence, and I think there's about three or four of them right here.
Currently that's a municipal lot so what is it just paid parking right now.
Chief, we received some email, I received emails from some residents about this.
And it was my understanding that these sign this lot is signed commuter parking.
I've seen the signs say commuter parking.
And that this January, when a couple of residents approached the parking office to get commuter parking permits to park in this lot and then take the bus to Boston, they were told that we don't issue commuter parking permits for this lot, that she has no record of it, and that the signs must be wrong.
She didn't know where the signs came from.
That was my understanding of the conversation and what was related to us to me via email.
And so that this is not necessarily that we're changing what's here from some perspective, but rather affirming that we agree this lot could be used for commuter parking.
Yeah, so my recollection is that, yeah, so all of the existing signage here does say commuter permit only or paid apart.
in this sign here, I know it's hard to read in the street view, but that sign exists on that pole and all the rest of the poles that go towards the left on this image.
So yeah, there used to be an off street parking commission that dealt with parking lots.
So we believe that this particular restriction allowing commuter permit and pay for park existed
when that commission existed prior to 2014.
So the traffic commission didn't necessarily have records of the approval, but this is an attempt to reaffirm the use of this parking lot in the same way.
But Faye did include a graphic that explicitly asked for 23 spaces versus the entire lot to be used for commuter permits and asking for the signs to be revised as such if the board approved that.
The resident did say she was going to try to come today.
But I think she wasn't sure if she was able to attend, but I think she sent an official record of her support to Alva Erickson.
I do have that, Todd.
We have that document.
Let's just see.
Is there a petitioner present and or anyone who would like to speak to the subject matter?
Seeing none, so anyone who wishes to speak against the subject matter of the petition.
Okay.
Seeing none, uh, director Blake.
So what I'm hearing is that this is actually marked or signed for commuter and pay already.
but the parking department doesn't have a record of it being such and we are trying to affirm that slightly different.
We wanna specifically mark out 23 spaces and for that, correct?
This is a little bit confusing to me if it's already marked.
That was according to the communication I got from Faye and I believe she sent to Alva.
I'm just reading off of that.
And can you clarify for us that there was no, cause I was in a conversation with her in a meeting with her where she, where this was discussed, but it wasn't, I do remember her saying that she wanted a specific number.
So she had a specific number of permits to issue so that there weren't more permits than there were spots, but I wasn't clear why they were reducing the number from the full lot.
Other than the fact that I am aware that there are a number of city staff that need to park in that lot for when our lot overflows at city hall.
But I don't know, did anybody have any further information on that?
If I just make a comment, if the commission is taking into consideration, the church at the end of the parking lot, I believe, uses this whole lot.
I believe it's Saturday, if I'm not mistaken.
I think you're right.
I believe it's on Saturday.
Whether it could be Saturday center excluded or whatever, but this parking lot does fill up.
when that church is having services.
Do they have any agreement with the city to use it not as a paid lot?
Because it's always been a paid lot.
I mean, I would respect it if they had an agreement with us, but that gives them that.
What church is it, Larry?
What church is it?
Isn't it Vita Real?
And they're in the old Springstead building.
The old spring stepped up.
It's a Spanish church.
Okay.
Let's, uh, thank you, Sasha, but let's just kind of, let's figure this first part out.
Um, Chief, I believe that it's important that we have commuter parking, that Medford residents can drive down out of particularly Fulton Heights and take the bus into Boston.
Um, so that they don't have to drive all the way in or to one of the teas.
Um, it makes sense.
I know there are some small number of residents who have a long history of using this lot to take the bus into Boston.
And I like that, I applaud that.
Yeah, I do know that there's, I've heard there's eight to 10 residents who actively used it as a communal lot.
And I believe the intent of this 23 number is sort of, it's a map out area, but it also is to try to
encourage others to use it.
And so I, I think I was just originally confused of the fact that it's already signed that way, but a phase looking for some sort of affirmation from the traffic commission that we do want this here and we do agree with it.
Then I, you know, absolutely.
I think we should take a vote on this and to approve that that as a commuter and paid mixed a lot of spaces, but
If you're making a motion Commissioner hunt or does other commissioners have a question.
Go ahead.
I have a question for Tim.
All right.
So that whole lot is not all the city's lot.
Todd, do we know if those 23 spaces are all in the city portion of the lot versus the hotel portion of the lot.
If they are.
Yeah, so, um, thanks to Alicia's plan development sustainability department, they had
survey done of those parking lots as part of the RFP process.
And that helped identify what's exactly ours and theirs.
So the entire area of favor poses within our jurisdiction.
Yeah.
Thank you.
All right.
I would support this.
Commissioner Brzezinski.
Let me see if I'm on mute.
Do we have clarification?
I mean, if we support this, do we now have clarification that there is an office that people can go to, to get a commuter permit?
Yes, correct.
And that's one thing that the director is supporting.
She would be supplying them.
She's looking for a specific number that she can vote as it relates to this lot.
And it would, as I understand it, make business a little bit easier for them in the parking department and clarify the rule.
I would make a motion to support the request for the 23 spaces.
Second.
On the motion of Commissioner Brzezinski to support the request for 23 spaces in the Upper City Hall lot on Clippership Drive so that they may be deemed mixed use spaces for commuter and paid parking seconded by Commissioner McGiven.
Now the roll call vote.
Commissioner McGiven.
Yes.
Commissioner Hunt.
Commissioner Brzezinski.
Yes.
Chief Buckley?
Yes, on the vote of four to nothing, the motion of the petition is approved and the petition passes.
2023-08, Paula Bernazani, 291 to 293 Riverside Avenue.
Permit parking variance for Carolina Street along with two visitor passes.
This is a similar issue where the resident has been granted
a variance for the past several years, and it just has never been memorialized in writing under the Traffic Commission, and there is no evidence to support her variance with the parking department.
And so the petitioner is back before the Traffic Commission to seek the variance.
Are you present?
Is the petitioner present?
Yes.
If you could unmute yourself.
Welcome, and the floor is yours.
Steve Garnizzani.
So we haven't had a anything memorialized, as you say, but we actually did find a letter from 2007
It shows the number, it was from Leo Sacco, the police chief at the time, and it was the variance number when we presented was 2007-57.
And although we never got anything from it, we have not had a problem ever getting the variants, you know, for the parking tickets and the visitors passes.
There is no parking on Riverside Ave.
So there's just nowhere else to go.
Understood.
Thank you.
And how many years have you had it?
So you had it at least since 2000.
2007 is the date we have on this paperwork from the city.
And I know your current petition is asking for visitor passes, but were you granted visitor passes back from this whole time?
Yes, we have a number that permit number 43901.
We've had that for all the permits we've gotten in the past, had that number when we went through Park Medford.
Okay.
And Alva was part of the 2007 petition.
Alva's been part of the petition since 1959.
And I'm not joking about that either.
That's accurate.
Actually, Paula's lived here since she was born.
So she's been around for a long time too.
OK.
So thank you for enlightening us there.
But commissioners, before I open up to public comment, any questions, concerns as it relates to this?
HAB-Charlotte Pitts, Moderator, Speaker 1.: So i'll jump on this one, and in general rule, I feel like there's no reason for us to be changing things, especially if we feel like it's you know.
HAB-Charlotte Pitts, Moderator, Speaker 1.: This is the way it's been I have had the belief that if, once we grant a variance for permit parking it should at least the very least run with the ownership of the House and not need to be renewed.
I mean, obviously you need to renew your parking permit every year everybody does, but the variance to this board shouldn't need to be renewed.
And I'm of the oppression and understanding that the parking department is in agreement with that now it's just that they don't have this list of the.
So yeah, we did go there, but they didn't have something formal from this traffic commission and they wouldn't give us the visitors nor would they give us a permit.
So, okay, excellent.
Thank you.
Uh, commissioner given commissioner Brzezinski, any thoughts, questions?
Is there the only thing I have, is there anybody opposed to what they're asking for?
All right, if we're just if we're fixing paperwork, I'm all for it.
So what if there's anybody against it, I'd love to hear it should be given any quick comments before I open up to public to see.
I would generally, I have the same opinion as I think both of my, uh, the other commission members.
Um, I am curious how many units are in the building.
It looks like there's two units and a pretty significant driveway.
Again, though, this is, it sounds like a paperwork issue.
Um, so just for my own information, though, could I ask the residents how many units are, are, and do you actually use that entire driveway?
You just got unmuted.
It's a it's a two family house and we just we basically just use it for family members and visitors, but we do use it.
And then so you have more need for parking, hence the Carolina Street.
Yes.
Yeah, because we have our kids and our grandkids and when they come over we need more parking.
And we want to encourage them to visit us.
Yeah, because we're seniors too.
All right.
Thank you.
All right, is there anyone here wishing to speak in favor of the petition?
Raise your hand, wave wildly.
Seeing none, anyone wishing to speak in opposition of the petition?
Seeing none, I direct it back to the commissioners.
Motion to support the request.
On the motion of Commissioner Brzezinski to approve a parking variance for 291, 293 Riverside Ave and two visitor passes, seconded by.
Sorry, I'll second that.
By Commissioner Hunt, I'll have a roll call, please.
Commissioner McGibbon.
Yes.
Commissioner Brzezinski.
Chief Buckley.
Yes.
On a vote of four to nothing, the motion is approved and the petition passes.
I thank you both for your participation, your comments in helping us work our way through this.
Just give us a day or two to get all the information typed up and over to the director of parking and you should be all set.
No issues.
Thank you.
Good night.
2023-09, establish a school zone on Winthrop Street for Medford High School in both directions, southbound at approximately Lorain Road, northbound at approximately Victory Park Playground Entrance Area.
Director Blake, the floor is yours.
Hi, thank you for seeing this.
proposal.
So basically the state used to restrict school zones to just elementary schools but they recently changed the rulings in their guidance regarding that.
So they're now allowing high schools to be considered for school zones.
So the transportation division is proposing to have the school zone on Winthrop Street near Medford High.
It would be approximately a quarter mile in length and run approximately from Victory Park to about Lorain Road in both directions.
The city is also applying for free equipment that would, if awarded, we would get free equipment from the state to install a school zone flasher with radar feedback sign in each approach.
And as part of that application process, it's required to have a school zone approved in place through the local regulating body.
So we think it's an improvement that will help safety
for the children in the area, especially since it's a large number of high school students that cross Winthrop to get to the MBTA buses.
And there's been some crash history over the years there.
Some pedestrians and cyclists as well as vehicle crashes.
The pedestrians, two of them in the past decade caused incapacity and injuries.
So we really think this is important and hope that you'll pass it.
I appreciate your comment.
Um, and, and director Blake, just for those not really familiar school zone, it's just the regulation of speed in that zone.
It will not, um, is there any other, um, uh, factors that would come into play?
There's no loss of, um, parking spaces.
There's no narrowing of lanes.
There's no, nothing else traditionally would be changed.
Yeah, nothing else changed.
Um, and yeah, so, so Medford, thank you for.
Asking that question she's Medford's speed limit is 25 miles an hour unless otherwise posted school zones allow us to reduce that speed to 20 versus 25.
And it's because they're providing the equipment that would be a flash, it would be when when it's flashing.
If you don't have the flashing equipment usually have to specify either times or when children are present.
Understood.
Any questions from the commissioners.
Uh, isn't there, there's a school sign in front of the, um, the Jewish school now all the way up.
Is it not already a school zone?
Hopefully he's looking at not frozen.
If you look at, um, yeah, it does have a sign in the vicinity of the temple.
And then if you go all the way up, if you go all the way up past the high school near Lorain, I think past or near Lorain, there's already a school sign.
So I'm just wondering if, are we duplicative?
We need it legally recorded is that the problem that it doesn't.
I guess, thank you for bringing up commissioners presents key so as we know, there have been some cases in the city.
That some signs were put up possibly without regulation so either it's already in place, or if if it was done in that case with a sign without regulation, this would just reaffirm that school zone.
and it would capture both the high school and the temple area as well as the daycare that's in the temple area as well.
Is the intention of the city that new school zone signs would go up in this area?
So yeah, with that grant available, the intention is to put a flashing assembly in the school zone so that
The state of Massachusetts is offering grants to cities and towns because of the change to the high school, knowing that a lot of communities will want that.
So it's an opportunity.
So we do intend, if we receive that grant, to put up a flashing system, which is an assembly of flashing lights, a radar feedback sign, and a sign all in one post.
It looks more like a signal post than a sign, which exists there today.
So yes, I would
Basically, we're asking to formally approve it, whether it was approved or not, because then we can provide the paperwork to prove that it's been formally approved as part of that grant process.
Thank you.
I do understand the need for legal paperwork.
I'm in favor of it.
I will say that my children used to bicycle to the school.
I am aware that the new
bike lanes that we approved are in that there is a group of parents who are talking about organizing a bike to school day for Medford High School, by the way, if anybody wants more information, let me know, I'll connect you to them.
And so I'm definitely in favor of this.
I apologize, I might have missed the beginning.
Is that a motion to approve?
Sure.
Okay, on the emotion of Commissioner hunt to approve a school zone on one three feet from method high school in both directions southbound and approximately Lorraine road in North on an approximately victory Park, seconded by second, second by Commissioner given our roll call vote.
Do we need to ask if there's any comments on it?
Yes, I keep forgetting.
I keep looking at other paperwork to get ahead of myself.
I want to go home.
Prior to any public comments, does anyone wish to speak in favor of the school zone in the petition on Wentworth Street?
Seeing none, does anyone wish to speak against the petition?
public comment, seeing none, I refer back to the motion on the floor to approve the school zone and winter street for Methodist in both directions, southbound at approximately Lorain Northbound and approximately Victory Park.
I'll have a roll call vote.
Commissioner McGibbon?
Yes.
Commissioner Hunt?
Commissioner Brzezinski?
Yes.
Chief Buckley.
Yes, on a 40 nothing vote the motion passes in 2023-09 has been approved.
That's the end of new business, and I believe I'm going to turn the floor over to Commissioner Brzezinski who has
last month's tables 2022-49 for the January meeting.
Commissioner Krzyzewski, if you wish to take this up, I remind you that we have to take a vote to remove it from table items.
And so I refer to you if you wish to discuss that tonight.
I would, I'd like to get it over with.
I mean, we promised a month for more people to join, not counting us, including us, there are 18 people still on this call.
So I'd like to just, you know,
Motion to bring it up for a vote so we can move it off the table of items.
Understood.
On the motion of Commissioner Brzezinski to pull 2022-49 from table items, do I have a second?
Sure.
Seconded by Commissioner Hunt.
Need a quick roll call vote, Alba?
Commissioner McGibbon?
Yes.
Commissioner Brzezinski?
Chief Buckley?
Yes.
On a four to nothing vote, the motion is approved.
We will be taking up 2022-49 expansion of the pilot residential permit parking opt out program.
All city public streets are proposed to become resident permit parking only 24 hours a day, six days a week, excluding Sundays and holidays.
Exceptions include
along non-residential uses where two-hour parking will be allowed from 8 a.m.
to 8 p.m.
without a residential permit.
Changes only apply to areas currently unrestricted, i.e.
changes do not apply to existing no parking areas, short-term parking areas, meet or pay to park areas,
loading zones, accessible parking spaces, existing resident permit parking areas, et cetera.
If approved, residents can choose to opt out by completing a petition to remove resident permit parking from their streets.
So that is the petition as was presented.
And I will defer in one second to Commissioner Brzezinski, but I believe the issue was we wanted to see, we wanted to make sure we advertise, put it out there and see the people who were
in favor of this and opposed to this would be present for this month's meeting to make a final vote.
Commissioner Brzezinski, any thoughts or comments for us before we move forward to public participation?
I don't think so.
I think I've been pretty clear about my stance against this.
And I tabled it for a month just to allow public comment.
So I'll defer to my fellow commissioners if they have anything to say, and to Todd, and then open it up to the community to let us know their thoughts.
Commissioner Hunt, any questions, comments before we open up to public?
No, I'm prepared to hear from the public.
Commissioner McGibbon.
I'm prepared to hear from the public as well as the police.
If we've experienced any issues since the opening of the station, I think we've been open for, I don't know, a number of weeks now.
I can answer that before I would defer to Director Blake, but there are no additional, I mean, my traffic statute said no additional impacts on parking areas in the area.
And I don't believe any complaints either.
Neither.
Commissioner Blake, since this is somewhat, I don't know, was presented by you last time.
Do you have any comments before we open it up to public comment?
I don't think so.
I think a lot of the issues in the presentation was covered,
beforehand.
So in the interest of time, just maybe let's hear from the public, see if there's any more to be said, or questions I could answer maybe.
Yep.
Thank you.
Okay, so now we'll open up to public participation.
If you're wishing to speak in favor of the expanding the pilot residential permit parking opt out program.
In favor, please raise your hand or make yourself known to speak.
Okay, seeing none at this time, I will defer.
If you wish to speak in opposition of 2022-49, the expansion of the pilot residential permit parking opt-out program, please raise your hand and we will get to you one at a time.
Go ahead, just one phone.
Dan Craven to Sasha on mute.
Good afternoon, can everybody hear me?
Yes, thank you and welcome.
Thank you.
I live on maple, which is within the transit district be but outside of the half mile radius.
My front door maple I was not a big street my front door is point nine walking miles from the Medford Tufts T stop.
It's a small one way single sided parking only street.
There's roughly 20 street parking spaces on the entire street, roughly 35 housing units, so it is difficult to park normally.
And specifically, the station has been open for a month.
I have not noticed any change in the parking at all, uh, as it relates to commuters, um, during the day when people are at work, does half the streets wide open.
Uh, so people are not commuting into maple have parking that cars and walking 0.9 miles to the, to the train, just not happening.
Um, and I would like to echo other residents sentiment on the negative impact of.
visitors and I think maple lab has a specific set of challenges in regards to that because it is single side of the street parking only and there are more houses and units than there are physical parking spaces especially as it relates to street by street parking permits that would severely negatively impact the residents of maple avenue and even if we opt out
we will lose the ability to park on South Street, Summit Street, and Curtis Street, which currently, every once in a while, depending on what time you get home from work, you have to park on South Street and walk up.
And it's always been a thing that we've done.
Packing is typically ample on that section of South Street between Curtis and and maple lab.
So I think I would like to echo the sentiment of one of the residents from last month's meeting that this is a solution in search of a problem it's the commuting aspect of the Green Line extension has not extended down to maple Avenue.
And the opt out program specifically would severely negatively impact my street on top of, I believe, the entire neighborhood, which is why you've already had multiple streets in the area opt out.
And that's my biggest issue.
We have always had the ability to opt in if the need arises.
And I would just ask and implore this commission to just leave us the ability to do that.
and vote no on this.
Thank you.
Thank you very much for your comments and your participation.
Alex, we're going to go with you.
Just ask you unmute.
Hello.
Hi.
Welcome again.
So yeah, we've been here last month and we waited for a month to see if the commission or director Blake would do any
any public outreach and we didn't see any, so we made a survey and we asked residents on what they think about this proposal since it's a sweeping proposal and it will concern many people.
If we could screen share, we could show you some brief graphs and results.
If not, I can just say it in percentages.
Why don't you give it a source in percentages first and we'll see where we want to go from there.
Thank you.
So first of all, I asked a bunch of questions about the awareness.
65% were personally unaware of the proposal and 94% thought that there wasn't enough public outreach.
Of people who were
of people who were answering the questions about parking and how impacted their neighborhoods were.
Most people could find parking all the time.
Some people could find parking sometimes, but generally, the absolute majority of people could find parking most of the time.
I'll note that the visualization shows how this is split between people who own houses on the street versus don't own houses and people who were affected by the date, but who are in the proposal or not.
Thank you.
I can send you all of this data.
I can send you all of the data that I collected.
It was about 130 people who answered from the city.
And about 80 of those were from the streets that are affected.
I linked the streets that are affected to the survey.
And generally, it shows that only 5% of people want to switch
to resident permit parking opt-out system, and at the same time, want a street-by-street permit parking system.
The zone permit parking system was way more popular, and there were also some proposals for citywide parking system, but it doesn't seem like many people want street-by-street parking system.
Of 80 people, only about 12 really wanted street-by-street parking system.
So I guess that's all from me.
No, actually I also read the report of the commission.
What was it called?
The report that Director Blake cited and I got a bit confused because it seems like the report actually recommends zone parking system and they were actually recommending moving away from the street by street parking system.
some quotes from it if you would like to see them, but that's my take on it.
That would be the Parking Policy and Enforcement Commission.
And I do believe all of us have read that, but I mean, I'll defer to other commissioners if they would like to hear either the quotes and or reference back to your charts, but I think you presented the statistics, you know, well enough for us to understand.
Let's move on to Melissa and then we can go back.
Commissioners wanna hear more from what was presented.
Melissa, just unmute.
Hi, my name's Melissa.
I live over on Main Street, kind of by Alexander's and Bob's in South Medford.
I just wanted to comment on putting the permits all around South Medford, kind of just echoing what Dan was saying earlier.
Me and my roommates haven't seen any change in the parking situation here since the Green Line extension has opened.
We've always had plenty of parking in the area without the need for a permit.
And I know me and my roommates would like to keep it as it is as residents can apply for a street to opt into permit parking, opposed to having to opt out if the half mile radius was put into place.
I know there are some other concerns I saw in the chat.
I believe his name was Peter Wallace.
He mentioned that the visitors pass is only good for two days.
I know some of us may have visitors for longer, family members, dog sitters, other things like that, babysitters.
which can be a concern.
I know my residence personally and a lot of residences on Main Street don't have driveways, so parking on the street is our only option.
I know for me, it's one of the reasons why I chose to rent on Main Street because I knew there wasn't going to be permits because I wanted to avoid that.
Looking into the future with renting in the future would be something I would take into consideration as well.
But that's my stance and as well as some of my roommates who are here with me tonight.
Thank you.
I truly appreciate the comments and your participation in the process.
Anyone else wishing to speak in opposition to the petition?
Seeing none, I defer back to the commissioners.
I prefer to leave Commissioner Krasinski for last because it's his sort of motion to kind of wrap up.
But Commissioner McGiven, Commissioner Hunt, any comments or questions about the process?
Sure.
Yeah, I have a couple.
So the thing that really stands out for me is finding a problem for the solution.
So I feel like
PB, Harmon Zuckerman.
PB – David Ensign – he, him, his PB, Harmon Zuckerman.
PB – David Ensign – he, him, his
We were having all kinds of issues with commuters parking on the streets that we're talking about.
I would have a very much a different opinion on this.
So anyway, that's what I have to say at the moment.
And I would also like to thank the residents for doing some survey work there and providing us some information, but I believe my position is regardless of that information, but I certainly do appreciate it.
And I just took a quick viewing of some of those graphs.
So I know you put some work into it.
Thank you.
Thank you, Commissioner Hutt.
Yeah, I guess I feel like one thing I do want to clarify, if there are some boards, I staff, I work with a lot of boards in this city, that if something comes before them and it fails, then there's a period of time before it can be brought back.
And that is usually in the rules or regulations of the board or it's in the
enabling statute of the board and I don't think that we have any rule like that.
And I say that because if there were, you know, it just was a slow ramp up and there was a point where in a couple of months in a month or two, somebody was like we need this, please reconsider, they could bring it back.
On the other hand, I also, I do think that this is a problem and may be problem or may become a problem for some individual streets, in which case those streets always have the opportunity to bring us their specific road.
The one thing that stands out for me is that we heard from residents of one street who felt they could never get the support of their fellow residents because it was all renters and absentee landlords and that that was a problem for them.
And that was the one street that felt like they couldn't get that support.
I think that streets that need this could come to us as a case-by-case basis to discuss the situation.
But I can't imagine imposing this on the entire area when there isn't a clear need for it.
Permit parking is a pain in the ass, it's a pain.
PB, Harmon Zuckerman.
PB, David Ensign ---- He's live.
Sorry, it's late.
So, I think the resident who actually who had that problem with the short street would would like to address this they haven't yet spoken on the issue tonight.
Chief I don't know how you want to.
Who's I know I see a couple of people, Francis, just want to make note.
Obviously there's a chat message from Nicolette and Alicia.
They are seconding that.
So we can go back to them and ask them to speak, but we can go with Francis first.
Let's go to Francis.
I chat speak for themselves.
So I didn't think it was on the record.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
I guess I was the one who wrote that letter.
We only have six houses on our side of Edison Avenue.
Edison Avenue runs from Tesla to Edison, and then there's a line.
It's not a through street.
It's not a through street, but there is a fence.
And the other side of Edison runs from Capon to the fence.
That side of Edison is all owned by Tufts University, and it is a private way.
Our side of Edison runs from Tesla to the fence, six houses.
Four of the houses are students.
And the landlords do not live in Medford.
And the,
Student houses, the four houses have a capacity for eight students.
And because it's supposedly a private way, many of the students allow their friends to park here.
And there's nothing we can do about it.
You come home to park and there's no parking because somebody is parked who doesn't even live here and they use it during breaks and whatever.
No, I think we understand the point you're bringing about.
Yeah, I'd like to make an additional point, which is that because we live on a corner lot,
with Tesla running down one side.
In the past, we could have our guests park on Tesla, but because of the Green Line extension, signs have gone up saying resident parking only, resident permit parking only.
So there is no safe place for our guests to park, like when my book group comes and several cars.
And so we've actually been in touch with Alva
Fran and I, who co-own a two family and we each live in one of the units, we would like to get resident parking permits, a variance for that, so that we can also get visitor passes and not have to worry about our guests getting tickets.
And also, so.
Okay.
When we first moved here, the police actually did ticket
We moved here in 1989.
And when there was a problem, the police actually did ticket people on Edison Ave.
It wasn't designated as a private way from Tesla to the gate.
And all of a sudden, it's designated as a private way, but was never really
Yes, and in the pilot opt-out program, it shows the first half of Edison, the one we live on, is marked blue, which says, a public street without resident permit parking.
Public street without resident permit parking.
It's sort of ambiguous.
And we also sent Alva a picture many years ago, one of our neighbors,
asked for a variance, and we did get one from Chief Sacco at that time.
So it has been done in the past.
But because of the change, because of the Green Line extension and all the houses now having so many students in them, our parking situation has gotten very difficult.
And especially, we worry when guests come.
OK.
So your variance issue will have to be addressed separately.
would have to, I will speak with Alva, Alva and I will kind of speak tomorrow and reach out to you as it relates to that.
We have to address the permit parking program in total now, the petition.
So,
I'm thinking I might want to say something else, but thank you.
Thank you for your participation and your comments on that.
Do we have anyone else here we should speak against before?
I mean, I know we did this.
Dan, I think just still has his hand up, but I know we did this.
And do you want to speak again, Dan?
Oh, no.
Yep, OK.
Yeah, I would just like to say that I, as a commissioner, Alicia Hunt was saying that
affected there was a resident that was concerned about the renters on the street.
I myself am a renter, and I think to echo what Melissa was saying, renters may not have access to a driveway at all, even if the driveway physically exists on a property.
Landlords will absolutely tell you, hey, as part of your lease, you don't have rights to park in the driveway.
And so in the interest of equality,
with taking renters and owners into account.
I think that's just worth noting that, you know, it goes on both sides and parking is an issue in the city of Medford and it's it's part of living in the city.
And I feel for Francis and the residents of Edison have
But I remain committed to the idea that Edison Ave is a single issue and the opt out program is entirely separate and that we have always had the ability to opt in if we need it.
And I think that's important.
Thank you.
Thank you very much for your comments and participation.
Okay, so back to the commission.
First off, thank you, Chairman Buckley, Commissioner Hunt and Commissioner Brzezinski and Commissioner McGibbon for allowing me to speak tonight.
I'll try to be as brief as I can.
And I want to tell you something, I'm more nervous than Mrs. Burgess was, to be honest with you.
My name is Tony Viola.
I'm the manager of Harvard and Maine LLC, which owns the property at 379 Main Street.
It's on the corner of Harvard and Maine.
and our building houses, among other things, a yoga studio known as the Corner Studio, which has been in business for more than 10 years in that location.
Rockland Trust ATM, I think you know the building.
Two residential units as well.
And I know this is gonna sound trite, but I wanna thank you guys for your time.
for your dedication, for your commitment to getting this right.
And I know the work that your commission does is extremely difficult and often very, very much underappreciated.
You gotta know back a few decades ago, while I was living in the town of Boston, I had the privilege of serving on that town's parking and traffic commission for several years.
So I had some experience, although limited in terms of parking issues.
The last, forgive me for coming late to the party.
This is the first time I've been live with you, but to get a flavor of what was going on in the city with respect to the parking regulations and proposals,
I spent a lot of time meeting with business owners on Main Street.
I got to spend some time with Director Blake and with Ms.
Erickson, who opened their doors to me, and they were extremely helpful.
And thank you, Alva, and thank you, Todd, for being so patient with me.
My honest belief was there would be a public outcry for the passage of this
article of this proposal this evening, but there seems to be everyone here that wants to speak against it.
I can't begin to speak about how the impact is on the residential streets.
I can only speak to how it might have been on Main Street.
And given, it seems to be with the direction that the commission is going, I can refrain from going into specifics with regard to Main Street.
I'm a big proponent of
creating zone parking, didn't think that this was necessary to go in that direction.
And I was concerned about some of the flavor as it would relate to parking on Main Street, specifically the business community.
So let's put that in the back burner for the time being, because if this comes up again, I can work with Todd and with the commission, if that'd be the proper stance at that point in time.
But suffice to say, I'm disappointed that we're not, that I'm not able to give you all the detail, but I think it's going in the direction conceivably that I think is the best for the city at this point in time.
We've only been 30 days into, you know, GLE extension being open, and there's not that outcry at this point in time.
As Commissioner McGiven said, this might be just a solution looking for a problem to create.
I think by postponing it at this point in time might make sense for the community, and certainly I would love to be involved if this comes back on the table again.
And there are some proposals that we've thought about amongst the business community that conceivably that we'd like to bring forth to you with regard to permit parking for businesses in light of the recent changes or the resident permit parking on Wareham on Yale Street.
Thank you so much for taking the time for me.
I appreciate your words and your comments.
Thank you.
Anyone left?
Nicolette?
Hi, everyone.
How are you?
Are you welcome?
Thank you.
I am just wanting to add a super short point.
I live about one block down on Main Street from the Green Line extension.
And I think given that the line was supposed to open for, I mean, I know,
It was delayed for months and months and months and then it became a year and so on because public construction as it does.
But I guess with that, I would think by now with it being open for five weeks, if there was going to be a surplus of people parking, especially on Main Street, especially one block away from it, that would have happened already.
Like I said, I'm on Main Street and there's more than enough parking for me when I come home every day for my commute.
And I haven't found an issue with it yet.
So for what it's worth, I just wanted to add that in.
I really appreciate your participation and your comments.
Thank you for it.
Thank you.
To the commissioners, and at this point, I think unless Commissioner McGiven wants to add or change anything and Commissioner Hunt wants to change anything, I would direct it towards Commissioner Brzezinski.
I want to unleash his point.
I don't want to be lost.
Is there a restriction on this being brought?
I don't want this to be pushed out forever just because of a rule, but do we have a rule that if something is denied that it has to stay off for X amount?
There is no written rule as far as the timeframe.
Okay.
As you're aware, we are working on traffic commission rules and regulations and it would be in there, but it doesn't exist right now.
That's helpful to know, because I think it is fair to say that if somebody were to just say, bring it back next month, but with no evidence of anything changing, the commission wouldn't be inclined to change their mind.
On the other hand, if there was some overwhelming evidence of change, something changed, then I think we are all very open-minded people here.
Is that fair to say?
I agree with that.
Go ahead, Alicia.
I was gonna throw in a side comment, Mr. Viola, that we have, my office has staff person who specifically works with businesses.
If you're not on the email list, and I'll say this to the public for anybody, we have an email list specifically for business owners in the city, where we reach out on issues of interest to business owners.
If you're not on it, feel free to send me an email or to my office at ocd.medford-ma.gov, because it is really hard to figure out who all the
the business owners and property owners are to get the business owners and the big commercial landlords on that list.
So I just wanted to add that in there.
But I think, Steve, did you want to make a motion or?
I appreciate all the work that's been done.
And I truly appreciate community involvement.
I mean, you'll find with working with me, I, I think the more the community is involved in things, the better.
Um, I like the idea that if this does become problematic, we're not handcuffed to not bring it back up.
But, um, I think the motion is to put the property in the program.
Is that right?
Chief?
I just want to, I mean,
I, you know, I think Todd's request was to put the property in the in the program or put the streets in the program and I just you know motion to deny the request, I just want to make sure I'm making the right motion.
Yeah, it's a good question how we want to vote to to vote a subject down, we can either just clearly vote.
Uh, no on the matter or but if your motion I guess is to, um, is to make that clear that your motion is to deny 2022 49 a year's vote would deny the petition.
The way I read what it's written, it's a motion to expand the pilot residential permit parking opt out program.
Correct.
This would be the half mile though.
The quarter miles already been approved.
This would be the half mile.
Yep.
I think the right motion to deny proposal.
or the commissioners could take a vote, a motion, could file a motion to deny 2022-49.
Is that what you just did, Tim?
Is that what you're saying?
Yeah, I was just saying that the wording of it is a proposal.
So if it's a proposal, accept the proposal or deny.
So if the motion is to deny the proposal, then a yes vote means that it doesn't happen.
Right.
I agree with Tim.
It looks as if we're having to, if we, if we're not in support of this, we need to deny the motion.
OK, so I agree with Tim.
If Tim's not willing to make the motion, I'll make the motion.
If not, I'll second his motion.
OK, I didn't know if you did it.
All right, well, the motion has not been made yet, so why don't you just jump forward?
Motion to deny 2022-49.
I'll second.
Commissioner Brzezinski to deny petition 2022-49, seconded by Commissioner McGiven.
I'll have a roll call vote.
Commissioner McGiven?
Yes.
Commissioner Hunt?
Commissioner Brzezinski?
Yes.
Chief Buckley.
Yes, on a vote of four to nothing the motion passes in 2022 dash 49 has been denied.
I just want to very quickly go on record that in front of the commissioners and the public was still left nothing.
In denying this motion, it does not change the current program of opting in for a residential street.
And I think all the commissioners have said that clearly, but I wanted to make it a last point to be clear that any individual street could still opt into the program.
And this is only to the expansion, the half mile.
One thing off the table item.
Motion to adjourn.
Hold on, hold on.
He directed it.
I think there was also one question from a resident, and I'm under the impression that he may have been directed to the Traffic Commission with his question.
I think it was, yes, Mr. Wallace, because it seems to me it would be an appropriate question for the parking department, but for some reason, coming here.
Is Mr. Wallace present?
Yeah, he is.
Peter, if you could just unmute.
There we go.
Yes, so I went to the parking commission when I got my visitor passes and they told me to call you and I spoke with the secretary about this.
The new visitor parking permit specifically says
that you cannot use the permit for more than two consecutive days in a one week period.
And that was different last year it said you can't be in the same parking spot for two days and you just have to move your car.
So I'm curious if you've guests like family staying for more than two days, they won't be able to use this visitor pass and what is the alternative?
It's an interesting question, but I don't think we've ever changed.
It's always been two days.
I can share.
I have a picture of the parking pass for reference, but yeah, it's a new line in there.
It also says only one permit is valid per vehicle per week.
Those are just two line items that are different this year than last year.
So when that language was approved to go on the visitor parking permit, we wrote
or the parking department put down there exactly what the rules of the traffic commission are as it relates to visitor passing parking permits.
Um, yeah, visitor passing permits.
So the question of no more than two days in any one week, except for Sundays, uh, has been a historic, um, rule for the traffic commission.
And it's been in place for a while.
I don't really recall offhand how it was written.
Um,
in the last permit, because that was put together by Park Medfin.
And here, this is the city putting it down.
And they are, in one sense, just writing down what the rule is.
What was the other point?
Other than that, is the only one permit is valid per vehicle.
Well, that one, I think, makes sense.
It's the first.
So last year, I just had family members move their car every 48 hours.
But this means if a guest, let's say a family member comes for a week, they can't park at our, where do they park?
We don't have any public parking around any of our residential streets.
After two days, we have to tell them to leave.
This is an excellent question.
So there's a tiny, I have a tiny bit of background on this.
It's some information that came to me from the parking department recently.
She let us know that apparently people had been selling Medford visitor permits and for a lot of money, which is part of why things were, she's gotten really strict about some of this and that people have been seriously abusing them, right?
And you have your car here, and I'm not saying you would do this like what you are asking is a legitimate difficult question.
But this is why some of the things have gotten stricter that a resident would get a parking permit for their car, and then they would get a visitor pass for their car, and then they would sell it to somebody else who doesn't want to register their car in Medford, who wants to register their car in, you know, wherever they're some other community and maybe New Hampshire which is notorious for having cheap car registration.
And then they would then use that visitor's permit and move their car frequently and get away with using the visitor parking permit instead of registering their car in Medford.
And that was the kind of stuff that apparently was getting pretty rampant.
And apparently, particularly among students, they were seeing visitor parking permits.
And this is some of where this all came from.
I'd actually be really interested to find out how do other communities handle this.
And I do know that Lily is interested in doing more research for us and on some of these parking permit questions.
Because this is an excellent.
you know, I don't know what to tell you other than we, you know, actually, maybe we should clarify this.
If he was near one of our parks, because we have parks, everybody in Medford lives within 10 minutes walking of a park.
And so my question is, and I know that we don't require permit parking at the parks.
Now I've just elaborated to the public a huge loophole in our parking rules.
He could park at, you know, the Tufts Park parking lot or something, right?
Yeah, well, I think we have our limitations.
So I mean, I think what you're presenting is a valid question.
The problem
as chair that I have is I know that that is the rule as written.
And I don't think we as traffic commissioners tonight based on what we heard can even rule on that and change.
So I suggest that, I know you've said you've reached out to Alba and maybe send your contact information and we can do a little bit of research on this.
But that is a, as I said, that's the rule and it's not, it wasn't a mistake and it wasn't added by this,
parking department this year, that is the historic role how it has been so let us do some research into this let's let's take some time to kind of delve into that question it is a unique question but as Commissioner hunts point, I think that rule exists.
to prevent some abuses of these visitor permit parkings.
So I'm just going to beg a little bit of your indulgence to let us do a little bit of research on this and try to get back to you while recognizing that it is a valid question.
I know director Blake has his hand raised.
Would you like to speak on this?
Yeah, just briefly.
I just say that I am aware of the way other communities handle it.
And basically it's
management, it's handled by management within the park department.
Usually there's different ways to go about doing it, but there's ways to handle parties like Superbowl parties when you have 10, 12 people instead of two people, there's ways to handle family visiting for a week.
It's usually a management way of dealing with it.
Yeah, and to that point we have, and it was one of the things in my mind, but I didn't want to really go down that, or take that direction for public discussion yet, but we have, you know, we have the ability to make certain
exceptions in certain situations.
So I'll just defer back if you could just be slightly more patient with us and kind of give us some time to look into this and kind of debate it a little bit further because it definitely is a rule for the city.
There was a reason for the rule, but you present a unique argument.
So reach out to Alba by email.
It's not just to make sure one more time that I can have your contact information.
She could forward it.
Other than that, Alva keeps telling me.
So we have an item tabled.
It's a tabled, yeah.
We have a tabled item, 2020.
That's right there, 2022-66.
This was on the agenda last month.
And we didn't take it up.
There was a list of streets who wanted to opt out and one of them was Spencer Road.
We didn't take it up because we didn't have the petition before us.
And it turns out that they had presented it to the wrong location and we weren't able to debate the issue in time for the agenda.
But in order for us to take this up and discuss it, I would need a commissioner to be willing to take it off of table items for discussion.
We're still off the table.
Oh, we're still off the table.
That's good for Albert.
Keeping me in mind.
So 2022-66 says opt out petition from Spencer Road.
Outer transit resident parking area, GLX permit parking.
So Spencer Road.
It's not on.
It's not on here.
Todd, can you just help me out for one quick second we dispense a road lie in this the quarter mile of a half mile.
It's a quarter, it's like on the upper northwest corner of the quarter mile.
All right, so it's part of the part area that was already approved.
Yeah.
Okay, so they are part of the rest, they are part of the resident permit parking program because they were included in our quarter mile.
petition that this traffic commission approved and they are now seeking to be opted out.
Do we have the petition before us?
No, I don't have it.
I bet that's the petitions that, that, um, I mean, she did and they're all, they're all filed away from last month.
And the petition was in order and the, the, the, all the residents, do you remember the residents, the number of residents?
It's only about four.
There's only like four houses there, right?
Yeah, it's not a big street.
So I'm sorry, I'm having a conversation with Alva.
It's probably not fair to not direct this publicly, but Spencer is a very small street and it's her understanding that the majority of the residents have petitioned this board to opt them out.
So I turned to the commission to see if they would be willing to address this issue this evening.
How many people have signed the petition?
I see seven houses.
Can we get the petition?
No, I'm believing that there was either four or six people that signed that.
I'm concerned that we don't have it in front of us to... No, I don't have that.
I couldn't find it.
Yes.
One quick second.
Sorry.
Was there some thought that it had come to my office?
It went the wrong place.
No, I don't believe so.
It was, I believe the December meeting.
We didn't have that petition.
in this office when the meeting was being conducted.
After the meeting was over, the chief had to check his mailbox, and it was in his mailbox where it was in the wrong place.
So we did not realize it was in the building.
when it was.
So your motion was to vote on all those streets that opted out with the petitions in hand and to exclude Spencer Road until the petition is received and then take a vote on it at that time.
which will be this coming meeting because the petition was in the building at the December meeting.
So that went forward to table business for the January meeting.
Just going through my record of last month.
All right, well, I'm actually, I can get it.
I can contact the lady because she did make copies.
All right, we're not even, I think as chair, we can't address this without the petition.
So I take it back.
We do not need to bring this up as tabled items because, and there's plenty of time to deal with this.
There's no reason to rush to judgment on this one.
It's not a crisis situation.
Did they already have the signs go up?
No.
Oh, I don't believe there's any posting.
Yeah.
I don't think they've got a street yet.
And if commissioner McGiven could probably hold off on that one, we would probably save him a lot of time and effort.
So do you think, do you think, do you think we can be ready to discuss it next month?
Um, yeah, a hundred percent.
I make a motion to move it up, make a motion to make it the first or, you know, first issue to, to review.
We can do that on the motion of Commissioner Brzezinski.
I mean, if it's our fault that, not our, not you, not our, if it's our fault, for lack of a better word, that we're not ready to hear this tonight, and we should be, then I'd motion to try to move this up toward the front.
I would accept that.
We put the agenda together.
We should have the petition with it.
So I will accept the motion of Commissioner Brzezinski 2022-66.
The opt-out petition from Spencer Road will be taking up as the first item on the agenda for February traffic commission.
Do I have a second?
Sure, second.
Seconded by Commissioner Hunt.
Alba, roll call vote.
Commissioner McGibbon?
Yes.
Commissioner Hunt?
Commissioner Brzezinski?
Yes, exactly.
Yes, on a four to nothing vote.
The motion is approved on the agenda next month to rest.
Can you just make sure just to make a note just to send us everything you can, or do you have just so we can review it address it expeditiously.
easy enough.
Thank you.
I appreciate getting stuff as much in advance, as you have it just because then, rather than waiting for everything at once, that way I can look at the things as they come in and, and if I don't have time at the last minute.
And at least I saw some of it.
We can do a better job and get it done.
With that, I don't think there's anything else anybody
have anything else they feel need to be brought up?
Just my motion to adjourn.
You weren't allowed to take that, was that?
On the motion of Commissioner McGibbon to adjourn, do I have a second?
Second.
Seconded by Commissioner Hunt.
Alva, roll call vote.
Commissioner McGibbon?
Yes, please.
Commissioner Hunt?
Yes.
Commissioner Pruszynski?
As much as I would love to see the city hall doesn't stay all night.
Yes, I've been here since 630.
It's good to say I'm not trying to just stay there all night.
And the chief is a yes I thank you all for your time and efforts in these meetings as usual welcome to 2023 and.
I do have a plan in the works with Commissioner Brzezinski to start working on a lot of these tabled items.
So I appreciate him stepping forward on that.
So we can get some research into them and maybe this year we'll clear up all our tabled items.
So thank you all.
Appreciate it.
Have a good night.
Alva, thank you.
Saj, thank you.
Thank you guys.
Good night, everyone.
Good night.