Here with Kittyja, with trivia on air. Random subjects, choose questions for five amateur kids who answer questions based on a topic. With our five contestants who will be joining us for season one. We have Asya, Sophia, Marie, Ryan, Slater.
We will see you folks shortly. But until then, goodbye. Welcome to episode one of Trivia on Air. Today our contestants are... Asia. Ryan. Marie. Alright folks, today's topic is cats. Now let the game begin!
All right, question number one. Asya, what gender do calico cats only come in? I do not understand.
Well, anyways, Marie, the question was, what gender do Calico cats only come in? So what is the answer to that, Marie? Female. Correct! You got it right! Now, Ryan, what do cats sense with? This is question number two.
I think they sense with their whiskers. Yes, you got it correct! Now, Asya, what does it mean if cats rub their paws on the ground? It means they sense their territory. Great job, you got it correct! Now, Marie, what flavors can cats not taste?
D-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-E-N-
I'm not sure. Oranges? Yes! You got it correct! Now, Asya, this is a couple more questions coming up, but I think you can get this right. How many cats live in the United States? Ten thousand. That is wrong!
The correct answer was 88 million cats live in the United States. But better luck next time. Anyways, Marie, this is the last question after the break. So, how many kittens are in an average litter?
I'm not sure, three to four? You got that correct! Alright folks, we'll see you after the break.
Do you like clean? Do you like affordable? Well then come on down and buy Animal 10 Plus Dyson. It has lots of tubes to suck up all your pet's fur, and it can be bought at Bed Bath and Beyond, Kmart, and Target. Goodbye. All right, folks. Now, we have gone after the break, so I think it's time
to give y'all some more questions. Do all your bids, and we shall come back momentarily. All right, folks, now to up the stakes. We're entering a new contestant. Enter Slater. All right, to start us off, Slater. This is our first question that was after the break.
What is the greatest cat breed? A mancoon? Yes, you got that correct! Now, Ryan. How many years of a cat's life equals 15 years of a human's life?
Ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne
You weren't supposed to say that. How many years of a cat's life equals 15 years of a human's life? Dee-nee-nee-nee. One year later. Yes, you got that correct! All right, Marie. How old was the oldest cat? Dee-nee-nee-nee-nee-nee-nee-nee-nee-nee-nee-nee-nee-nee-nee.
38. You got that correct, Marie! Now, Slater. What is a female cat often called? Ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne
Now, we are getting out our new set of questions. Same topic. Ryan, come forward. What does Catnip do to cats? Ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne. Does it make them go crazy? Yes, you got that correct!
Thank you. Now, Asya, come forward. Yes, sirree. Why do cats sleep so much? Because they're often lazy and confused about their existence. You got that wrong. Now, Ryan.
What is a group of cats called? De ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne ne
This is another one of our questions. This is the second-to-last question. So, why do cats like boxes? Because they feel like it protects them? Yeah, you got that correct! Great job, Marie.
Thank you, piano guy. All right, Slater. You'll finish off our last question. Why do cats loaf? Nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee nee
Better luck next time, kiddo. Anyways, now we have one more ad before we end this episode. Be sure to check out the next one, though. Buy Kellogg's Frosted Flakes now, available at Target and Costco and all of your local grocery stores, unless they don't know what the 21st century is made of.
Anyway, just please buy this box. It'll make your life better. Also, it doesn't have any gelatin in it, so that's good. Bye! Alright. So, the winner is...
We will see you in a couple seconds when you click that next episode because we assume you are a good person