Good evening, everyone. I'm Sergeant Canava, Sergeant Rogers, and Alva is here. The Chief is on his way back, and he will hopefully be here shortly if he can, depending on traffic. And I'd just like to obviously start on Tuesday, October 10th. There's a Traffic Commission meeting, and we'll start with a roll call. Alva. Commissioner McGibbon? Here. Commissioner Hunt? Here. Commissioner Brzezinski? Here.
Chief Buckley. He's absent, but he's present for me. Sergeant Canava, designated chairperson. All right. Foranathan. Also in attendance. And also in attendance is Sergeant Rogers. Todd Blake. Todd Blake is also here as well. Approval minutes for last meeting.
Let's go. September 12th. September 12th, so that'll be previous minutes and they're all set. Motion to approve. Motion for- Second. Second, okay. Tim, sorry, it was Commissioner McGiven and then seconded by Commissioner Hunt. Yep. Commissioner McGiven? Yes. Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski?
We are moving forward. I don't think we have anything from the table.
So I will ask you to unmute. Hello. Hey, how are you? Good. Good. Commissioners, before you speak, I did go down last week. I believe I spoke to her son-in-law. What's her name? Helena? Daniel Armstrong.
is moving in with her daughter and she's requesting a handicapped space outside due to her disabilities.
So I was just, thank you. I was just calling up the location to look at it. I don't know if Director Blake wants to share it to everybody. Because my first question when there's a handicapped placard request is always, is there a driveway and can you use it? There is a driveway to the right. They felt that it'd be with their breathing issues to right in front of the front door and the stairs.
I'm trying to pull it up now, sorry. It looks like an additional step then from the driveway. So let's see a little bit more about that. It seems like a more difficult journey from out in front of the house to the front door and from the driveway to the front door. My husband is also disabled and has a hand clap placket.
So then that's also the issue. So is there one currently there now as well, or you're just saying as a handicap placard, he doesn't have, there's not a sign there. There's not a sign there. I've never had a sign for him, but I park him right next, he parks in that spot right there at the end of the driveway in whatever.
I also have, yeah, so that is why we tried to get the one in front of the house. And this is both their parking, correct? That right side is their parking. I'm not sure of the handicap sign on Choro at all.
I believe there is one on the end. Yeah, look, Tom. I thought I saw one on the other side. There's one on the right-hand side at the beginning towards Summer. Okay. Is Toro one-way street?
Yes, it is. That was my impression from seeing all the cars parked in the same direction, but I didn't want to... It's the only one way going towards South Street. Do we have any other requests for handicapped spaces on Toro Ave that we know about? I don't have any on this thing, but...
John, you don't know of any, do you? I just want to make sure that, because two on this one seems reasonable. I'm not aware, no. There's only one handicapped request today. All we have is this one. Yeah, but there's one further back. Yeah, but he's saying if any other than that, this one is not.
And the other thing that we want to make sure that you're aware, as the resident, if we put up a handicapped sign, they're not specific to you. Anybody with a handicapped placard can use it. There seems to be some history and miscommunication about that in the city, but you should be aware that anybody with a handicapped placard can use that spot. Okay.
Well, my thing of it is, is if I have to hold it for my mother, I'll throw my car there and then throw she'll pull out and then go around. The problem is, is Torah as you know, doesn't matter how many spots, whatever I have children, I have whatever he like I had to park my mother's car on man, like a street over yesterday, because there was no parking.
And then I had to run around as I was working with my phone, get her car, pull it up in front of my car. And I don't work from home all the time. And that was the issue.
It's just that these are not reserved spots for people. Okay. And that's like they're still public, all the spots are still public parking, but it would be limited. If there was anybody ever parked in there without a handicap placard, you can certainly call the parking department or the police to ticket them because that is really not allowed.
have any other thoughts on this? We have to take that whole strip from the telephone pole, I guess from driveway to driveway, will that be allocated to the spot? I was wondering if it's busy at night, if there are spots open on Toro, are we displacing a car someplace else?
It's probably just one car can sit there. Okay. Yeah, it looks like it's about 26 feet, so I'd say one car, especially when you factor in the two or three feet from a driveway at a time. Yeah, you're looking at- And they own a handicapped placard, and they have a neighbor up the road that also owns one, so it makes sense to have a couple here, so I'm okay with this. Agreed. All right. Motion to approve.
Second. Motion. Okay, Alicia Hunt and seconded by Commissioner Brzezinski. Roll call out. Commissioner McGibbon. Yes. Commissioner Hunt. Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski. Yes. Sergeant Canaba. Yes. Okay, four nothing. That passes.
It's Constantino, just the sign department will obviously work on that and I'll be in contact with you with two to three weeks. Perfect. Thank you so much. Thank you. Thank you. God, what a day.
Another happy customer. Here we go. All right, moving forward. 2023-441 request for a three-way stop. Bowen, Dexter, and Todd, if you want to speak on this. I know that we've had some collisions here, and I know you were kind of bringing this up. Then Sergeant Rogers would probably second.
Yeah, thank you, Sergeant Tanaka. There were some crash history here, and so Bow Street is a two-way street from, as most of you know, from Maine to Maine, but it extends from here, 1,800 feet, towards Albion, this end,
So it's a two-way street, currently has stop signs on both street approaches. But Dexter, which is a one-way street from Joseph to Magoon Square, Somerville, Broadway, Medford Street, is a one-way, currently does not have stop control. And a lot of drivers seem to be approaching it thinking it's all way,
And then there's some incidents occurring there. So it's kind of unclear, it seems, to the driving public, which is the major and which is the minor street. And functionally, they're about equal. If anything, both streets are longer, but they both collect traffic from neighboring local roads. So that combined with the crash history, I think it's a good candidate for an all-way stop.
So that's why we're bringing it for you. I don't know if Sergeant Rogers had anything to add. Coming up, Bo, as you approach Dexter, the stop sign is fairly back on Bo. So you basically have to stop and then slowly proceed out and to look down Dexter Street to see if anyone's coming. And we've had some serious accidents there. Yeah, so this direction. Yeah. Yeah.
So again, to someone driving on both sides, would you consider putting it on for Dexter? Can you swing back around to the other side? Because I think on the right. Yeah, definitely on the right. Yeah. OK. Yeah, so I mean, it's a one-way street, so we could have a stop on both sides, but it would likely be right on this top. Yeah, I was going to say that would be the more preferred one, because that tree I know on the left side, obviously not really blind. Unfortunately, I mean,
So stop bar has to be minimum 4 feet back from the crosswalk. So the stop line itself is going to be back here. But that's a function of where the ramps are located right now. Maybe there could be a long-term project to move the ramps closer, although with the catch phase it'll be difficult to improve the sightline in this direction.
But just by having the stop in all directions, they'll stop and then hopefully proceed with caution slower, and then they'll be able to see each other when they get out to this area here. I think the two collisions that I've been here, the speed was 100%. I think one was a motorcyclist. And one was brakes. Yeah, one. Yeah, so I know that. If they're posting the sign on Dexter, what is that, a westerly direction?
but it would be an all way. I know. Yes, but we're posting it. Westbound. Yeah, south westbound, yeah, westbound. So we're also doing, just to let the commissioner know, we're also doing other things to try to improve safety here. We recently striped shoulder lines to kind of guide people around the corners and give it appearance of a smaller intersection so it doesn't seem so wide open.
So we are doing other things, but we felt that the hallway stop could help as well. Is this one on the complete streets list, Todd? Good question. It is not on the top 20 list. I'd have to check to see if it was on the supplemental list. But it's not on the top 20, no.
I know he's definitely a good candidate change wise so slopes a little bit so but this item is for tonight is a stop sign right to make it a three-way stop always correct yeah motion to approve okay second was final sighting by Broadway Blake and it's a three-way street yeah
Okay. I have one question. I mean, I approve this, but will the sign say stop always? Yeah, once you have all direction, in this case, it's three versus four, but once you have all way, you're supposed to add the tab underneath that says all way. So we'll do that. They have the tab that says four way and all way, always good for a situation like this when it's...
the three directions that can approach. But then at least it alerts the driver that every direction is stopping. Okay. Thank you, Tom. Or else drivers might come up to it and stop waiting for the other person to go thinking they have the right way. Okay. So motion to approve by Commissioner McGiven and second by Commissioner Hunt. We'll call Eva. Commissioner McGiven? Yes.
Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski? Yes. Sergeant Canaba? Yes. Or nothing. This passes. Okay, moving on to 2023-42. Andy, sign for Maine and Yale, Maine and Laramie.
And Todd, are you going to speak or is Frances here? I don't think Frances is here, so I'll speak on this. So Frances and I were looking, I don't know if she got a request or just she was proactively looking at accessible spaces in business districts, but she and I walked this area and determined that
there was a lack of accessible spaces in this area on the street, especially on the west side. On the east side, there's two already, one here, one down here. On the west side, it's none on this block or this block. She had recommended to the end spot at main near Wareham.
And it's a good candidate for that block just because there's no one behind it or in front of them, because the crosswalk and the 20-foot corner rule. Is that there on the right there? Yeah. Yeah, obviously, you can see here with the pizza shop there, it probably currently gets used a lot by customers. But this versus a mid-block space here that would be more difficult to get in and out, this was seen as the location. So Todd, just one thing. Sorry before you keep going. Yeah.
a lot of issues that we have had with this crosswalk and this parking area here is that for delivery trucks for the liquor store and the pizza shop and they kind of pull and they take up a lot of that area in the crosswalk area so we've spoken to them multiple times about this but they really make it really difficult for
This crosswalk area here, because they're not just a small box truck. They're, they're. Really decent size truck, so we definitely. That's 1 of the issues we've been having over there. Yeah, and this handicap sign, if you put it there, I mean, they're definitely not going to park in that.
Yeah, for this particular item, we weren't recommending daylighting this, although I think that's what you may be getting at. But when, as part of the parking department's replacement project to take out this kiosk and put meters in, engineering marked the potential spaces here, and we started from the driveway back here, and we were able, by doing that, we're able to
free up some area here with no parking, just the way the math worked out with the spaces. It wasn't long enough to be a space. That was going to be a problem. Yeah, that was going to be a, yeah, when the meter projects went in, that was going to try to clean that up. But for this particular, that's a good point because we're trying to do that everywhere. Even over here, same thing. Once we delineate these spaces with Ls and Ts,
we were able to have a hatched area before the crosswalk when that meter project comes in, and the space is striped, because that's within the 20-foot wall anyways on that side. So for this particular thing, Francis Warren was asking for accessible space here. And then the other location, excellent.
So these angled spaces that are in front of Oasis and other businesses, there was an area at the ends that was being utilized but not striped. So we officially striped another space here, then added a hatched area that leads to the ramp, the corner there. So essentially asking for this last space to be
This space right here to the right of the tree to be accessible space. And then there's a hatched area. So they'd get out and go up the ramp. So that was the other space. Just so the commission knows, it's not part of this agenda item, but to be thoughtful of the overall area to see if we're not taking too many. Francis and I were looking at,
the Yale Street lot to see by locating spaces closer to where people want to go on Main Street, maybe we could reduce the number that's in this lot. It seems excessive right now. I think there's three spots in there now. There may actually be four or more in here already. Basically, the idea is that Francis was saying if we locate it close into the businesses on Main Street where they want to go because it's a shorter distance,
then if we add those two and we're displacing non-accessible spaces, maybe we could relieve that in this lot by taking away an accessible space or two, if it's excessive. Because there's a standard for parking loss of percentage, so we were going to double check that, but that was what we were thinking. Because the users, I mean, if you're someone with needs, you wouldn't just say park here and walk.
wheel all the way down to the businesses if there was a space that was more convenient at the businesses. So that was the idea behind the requests. So at this time she's only asked for approval of these two and then we'd come back to you once we revisit this lot and see if we could reduce some of the ones that maybe aren't necessary. This was two there and I think there's
one or two in that corner as well, and one here. Basically, the idea was to trade, to swap out, but for now, we wanted to make sure we got those ones on the street. Do we need to paint it blue to be compliant? On street, we don't have to paint them. We usually sign them, but I know in certain business districts, we paint them, like near the library in Medford Square areas, just so they stand out a little more.
This one on streets that's heading is a little unusual to sense that most on streets is parallel, not heading. So this one, it would probably make sense. I would say at the very least have the symbol in the middle. Instead of painting the whole thing blue, you could kind of do the box with the
Yeah, a little birdie told me one time that we had to paint them blue, but I don't think that's the case. Yeah, I don't think so. It's just, yeah, in parking lots, it's more traditional, but on the street, it's not as sweet. Closest we can get, this is right in the corner. There's an out-of-coat, but ramp right there. So has anybody talked to any of the businesses about it?
I have not, I couldn't say if Francis has. We didn't at the time when we did our site visit. We only converted one space. We added one space and we're converting Word. Right. The first one is right in front of the pizza shop and I just get the impression that those pizza shops tend to really rely on the quick in, quick out spot in front of them.
I have a feeling that if we make that a handicapped spot, we're going to see a lot of people park in it, run into the pizza shop, treat it like a five-minute parking spot. I hope not, but I wonder if the pizza shop there is going to have an opinion in the matter and say, why couldn't you put it up the block a little or over there? Those are great questions. Existing-wise,
There is one here existing that's opposite side of the street, that last end space there. And then there's one on the opposite side of the street right here. But yeah, those are good. We looked at the other end, like potentially this space here where the red car is. Ultimately, we thought that other one was more desirable. It was at that end where a lot of the handicapped
the accessible spaces at that end, so there's a lack on this end, so keeping it from the far end. Tom, what about where that maroon sumo row is? I guess part of the question there is, is there a preference or a recommendation that they should go at the end of blocks rather than in the middle of a block? I feel like I always see them at the end of blocks.
It's I think Stephen requested this in the past in a different agenda, which was a good request. Like, it's just easier to drive in and out of it versus back and in back and out. But there's no requirement per se, like, even this one next to a driveway. One of these two spaces would be less of a.
less of a potential challenge for someone, we don't know exactly what their needs would be, but to back into this space versus to use the same space. I was going to say that because you have the driveway, they can just basically pull. Yeah, you can look at this one or this one even. That one right there. You just drive away. This context, that's what we're having the meeting for.
I think in general, I can't speak for Francis 100%, but in general, the idea is just to get an accessible space in these areas where the businesses are to get someone that may want to use these businesses closer to the front door versus the U.S. supply. Best spaces. That's the rule of thumb with handicapped spaces. You want to give the best spaces.
Great. But I guess I'm also thinking that we don't know if they're going to the Taylor, the pet clinic, the liquor store, the pizza shop, which is why I'm wondering if the one in front of the oil company is actually better because there's no way that people are parking there to go into that oil company and they're quick. That's not the same kind of business. That oil company is not depending on that in and out business.
And then if the tailors, they're close, they're near, like, they're near a lot of those businesses. I just want to sort of, in lieu of talking to the businesses, thinking about how they're going to perceive it. I mean, I think with our friends being here, I think, I think should be happy, you know, if the commission decides to do this space instead of the other one, I think it would satisfy the need.
And Todd, I have a question, but I don't think you can answer it. Maybe you can. Are there any businesses around here that would be especially attractive to handicapped or disabled folks? There's a salon right across the street. A barber shop, a salon. The DeVito's barbershop right there where the gray car is.
Yeah, this one. I mean, it's hard to say because accessible people could visit any number of businesses, right? Yeah, anything that stood out is sometimes. There's just a lot of pedestrian traffic. Businesses with higher levels of pedestrian traffic. You can argue that it's a place. The other night on Main at Harvard.
That's a great point. And actually, now that you mentioned that, Tim, that was one of the reasons why France is like this, because not only it's on a string of businesses, but it's near the crosswalk in case they were visiting a business on that side. So, in that case, again, it's not a rule, but keeping it at this end, this crosswalk, or the other end, the other crosswalk versus mid-block, but it's all within reason.
I think if you go to the right, there's another salon there at the car. Uh, which direction here? Other, just the other side. Yeah. Oh, yeah. At the corner right here. Yeah. So once you get them on a foot traffic, I'm sure. Yeah. And they have the bus stop and the no partner corner and yes. So that one has this space here. They do have to cross the street, but it's, um, that's really cool. So, you know, you try to do what you can to space them out.
Maine and Alexander, he's talking about Maine and Harvard. I don't think you'd want it there, it's right on top of the next one. I like it where there's a cruise. No, I'm going to have to tell the public.
I mean, you could always, obviously it's up to the commission, you could always approve the one you're confident about now and then, you know, take some time to speak to the business or us get back to you with what we're going to get back to the non-accessible folks in the lot as a trade potential. I mean, I really like putting one down at that end of, and I see what you're saying about the opposite end of the street. Like if you have this zoomed out that you have right now. Yeah. Can you, are you able to just point to where the existing ones are?
Yes, so the existing one right here, the corner of main and right, and right here. So they were both on the east side of the street on the northern block and none on the west or east southern block of the square.
sitting in the lots over here, obviously closest to the northwest side. On a second, what Commissioner Hunt said, the one at the Bocelli's and at the Harvard, closest to Harvard, and we have the most issues with people running into a quick store and parking in there. So to her point,
With it being in front of the pizza shop, we're probably going to have issues with people running in and, you know, we're, we're coming up to them and we're saying, you're in a handicapped spot. Here's a, you know, they receive a ticket and they're like, I was only there for a minute. Well, that doesn't matter.
But we have a lot of issues with that spot at Main and Harvard where Bocelli's is closest to Harvard because it's not painted, they don't see the sign. I've even had people tell me that it's not a legal handicapped spot because it's not situated with enough space. I said, well, it absolutely is a legal handicapped spot.
I'm going off track here, but to her point, I think the only reason I say that at the other spot in front of the oil company would be a little more convenient. I agree with you, Sergeant. The oil place does seem like a good compromise in an area that's not utilized the way you're describing it.
Right, I guess what I would think is that it's very convenient to all the stores on that block. And we're not asking, we're not tempting people to then abuse the spot and use it when they're not handicapped. So it actually increases the probability that the site, the spot would be available for people.
Yeah and timing wise I would say it's good for y'all in my opinion to pick before the meters go and then Faye and the parking folks will know which spot to not put the meter. Yes please. If we're comfortable making this the spot in front of the oil company
I think that I'd be comfortable approving that today. I do see the argument about being close to the crosswalks. Keep going up. People should get the best spot. On the other hand, we don't know where they're going, to which of these businesses, and we know people going into a pizza shop are going to abuse it. Keep going up where you wanted it. Sound logic.
see right there with that white car. If we put it there in the spot where the pizza guy, you would think he wouldn't park his own car there. The best spot for a handicap is to pull in and pull out. Put it there in front of Moreno's Barbershop. This pizza car actually illustrates
Once we stripe it from meters, this will very clearly be one space, not two. Right now it looks like they may squeeze two in, but it's within the 20 foot rule. I mean, I'm definitely okay with the spot even further back where the white car is also, but, um, probably oil company in front and, and even with pavement in front of the Moreno's barbershop. Do you think, um, Moreno's barbershop is going to lose their mind over it? I mean,
I mean, people don't run in and out of a barbershop, right? No. I don't know, how long are they there? 20 minutes, a half hour? When we measured out the meter Ls and T spaces from the driveway back near the tailor to here, you end up with less than the space in front of Marina, which we were going to recommend to daylight and hatch. Then if we did a handicap here, it would probably be more in front of the liquor store.
in terms of alignment. And then I'll have to back out and pull up. That's like the last space. Because say when we did the math for the L's and T's, there might have been like 15 feet or something left over, which is not enough for each car. So you will effectively daylight that without it needing to be a regulatory thing. Correct, yeah. So the last L space would be more in front of the brick building. Yeah.
versus the Greybill Moreno. I think if we daylight it and then put a handicapped spot there and take almost what is essentially two spots from them, that's a lot. Practically, it's going to feel that way. Yeah. Maybe for that regard, it may make sense to do the oil area just because then it's
breaking up the spacing of the perceived loss of spaces. Because again, even this is going to feel like a loss because this is within 20 feet so that the space here is going to be striped, more aligned with 399 doorway. Okay. Open to the public.
commissioners, I don't know if you want to approve on both. If you want to do the one on the Yale Street side, I'm open to either suggestion. What was the address of that oil company? We can just say it's approved at that address.
I like the other space too. I mean, a motion to approve both spaces if we have an address for the one that's in front of the oil company, it sounds like. I don't know if we talk to anybody in the public about this. Is there anybody to speak upon it here? Sorry, Commissioner McGiven, I didn't. That's all right. I don't know if there's somebody that is on here. If, Todd, if you had mentioned it to some of the business owners and they may be here to speak about it as well.
I'm not sure. I'm having trouble reading the number on that. Is it 339? I think it's 389. When I go from above, it says 389. I think your point is, if there are any members of the public who would like to speak on this, they should raise their hands or somehow indicate they would like to speak. In the chat, or as Commissioner Schatz said. I'm seeing none.
We found a good spot. What number was the oil company? Is it 389 or is it 380? What's the name of it? Harlada? Harlada. It says 387 Main Street on here.
is a lot of oil companies says 387 okay I mean if we went out there and it's 389 is that an issue I think we know what the intention is you feel looks like a nine to me that's the next
We Googled it, and when you Google it, it says 387 Main Street. It might be a dash, yeah, because his house is above. Oh, it could be, like A or B. Bedford Pet Clinic is 391, so. Okay. I think we could put it in. Let's fix the control. We're gonna get it, it's in our CAD, one second, and we'll be able to do the exact.
Is that, that house is attached to the same building, isn't it? We can always say the southernmost space between Harvard and that first driveway there. I think we understand what spot we're looking for. I think if it was approved, then if we went out there and it's 389 or 387-389, I think
that would suffice in that way. It's going to be 387. We can just say the southwest corner of Main and Harvard. It's 387 on our cap, so that's what's coming up as well. Yeah, the end space. So that one and the one on the bank north of Harvard, the end of the bank. Correct. I know I was kind of interrupting the information we were given before you were making a motion.
That's okay. It was good to see if anybody here has anything to say about it. Maine and Yale and Maine in front of 387. I believe Commissioner McGiven made a motion. Anybody would like to second it? I'll second it. Great. We put it in there.
the Yale Street end of lot, and then we put in southern most spot in front of 387 for the driveway is what we have in there. So Commissioner McGiven and seconded by Commissioner Hunt and roll call. Commissioner McGiven? Yes. Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski?
I will say yes, I just want to encourage us again as we go forward on these projects, please talk to these neighboring businesses before we change the parking. So, but yes, I vote.
I will just on commissioners in his comment. I've had a vacancy for many months in my office economic development planner that works with small businesses. If that position was filled I would have volunteered that that person go out and talk to the businesses. But I don't have the staffing until I can get that position filled.
to do that. Yeah, it's unfortunate. Hopefully, I mean, I mean, hell, I'm happy to go talk to these businesses. I think these are important things, you know, that I'm sure there are many citizens who would love to help Todd and his group. I mean, but the same issue we had in on on High Street, when we started talking about taking parking spots and designated them for sidelines of handicap, it's just I think it's important to
I'm just wondering if you could talk to these neighboring businesses about the changes because you may never know there could have been a business that would have really welcomed a handicap parking spot in front of their location and that may have been the desired location. But I just encourage us to talk to these neighboring businesses a little bit more than we do.
Definitely agree with that. I think we'll probably, we'll sure hear from them when they do go up, but hopefully it's with positive feedback. There might be a process changed with the traffic commission and how we want to do things, which means it might be like a rule that we got to vote on or something. We should run it by the chief because these things land on the agenda. And maybe there's some pre-agenda work that could happen. I don't know how it happens. I'm just bubbling it to the surface.
It was on my list today that we really need to revisit the draft traffic commission rules. I mean, there's rules and regulations for how this board operates and there's the citywide rules. And we really need to get those, the drafts in our hands so we can review them because it's going to take us weeks or months to review them. So we can get started on that.
I think there's a meeting about that this Friday that's on my calendar. Probably two out of four of us will go. I had suggested that we could hold a meeting of the Traffic Commission during business hours to just talk about rules and regulations, so. Okay. I also, I'm not saying I disagree with us going to the businesses, but
I don't know what business is going to say, hey, I'd like a handicapped spot in front of my business to take away a spot. Yeah. No, Julian, on that point, too, I'm taking all this in. I don't think communication is key, but there are not necessarily this particular item, but other items, there's safety involved. And basically, it's, in my opinion, some of the keys are more of an FYI, just a courtesy,
Because sometimes if you approach folks at a corner house or near a crosswalk that needs to be daylight, it could give them a sense of whether it should be approved or not. And it's more just letting them know, because in some cases, it's safety-related. I definitely agree with that. I mean, yeah. I mean, there are some instances where on the safety, especially the sightline items, I think it's more about, hey, we're doing it because, hey, what do you think about this? But parking in that area of town, it's
So that is so valued in that area. There's so much traffic down there and with parking. And so I just always encourage us to talk to these neighboring businesses. And if we citizens need to get involved to help each other, there are plenty of us out here who are willing to kind of help facilitate the interaction between citizens and the government.
Yeah, I think it would have to be a notice process because I don't think there's a lot of decision power with the people that have frontage there. It all lies with us, but we can at least notify them, give them advance notice. If it happened in front of my house, if all of a sudden there was a handicapped parking space right in front of my house, I'd be like, what? But if I got a 60-day notice or a 30-day notice or I was told about this meeting, then I'm going to be ready for it.
The other thing is that when our staff do go out and talk to businesses, there is a difficulty in finding the right person to talk to. Sometimes it actually takes stopping by and leaving a message for the manager and leaving another message for the manager. Sometimes you're lucky and that person is there, but it can take a couple of visits to get the timing right.
Yeah, but in my world, the legal world, I think the effort is probably what matters the most. And so, you know, hey, we came by twice to talk to you, and we could never find you. We left a number, left a message. I think that kind of shows how important this issue is to them, which is not. So this is my only thing. Again, in a town where parking is premium, I just always encourage us to talk to these neighboring businesses if we're going to change things up.
It's a great point, Steve, especially. That's why Francis and I were thinking, can we give some spaces back in the Yale Street lot for people with able-bodied that could walk the half block, you know? OK. Great. Moving on, 2023-43. Daylight request for no parking north side of High Street, 20 feet east of existing crosswalk at 190 High Street.
Todd. Yeah, this this I'll be quick to this one. This is very similar to the others on high street. It's this side of the street to sell side in front of the region. C one 90 is already signed as no parking between signs. So it's the north side. If you could see my cursor 20 feet prior to this crosswalk here, which would daylight so that people aren't coming out from behind a parked car. I do have photos of
that way it will look like. If I could, quickly for all of you. Before Todd gets those up, I mean, this is a crosswalk.
I know Sergeant Rogers and I have definitely dealt with parking issues of them coming within inches of parking within that crosswalk. It's happened for a long time, and it's pretty dark. It's not very well lit when nighttime comes around. So them sneaking out is really Russian roulette when they need to get to the bus stop on either side here. If you can see this image,
So this, before the approval, we drafted some dash markings and cones momentarily to show how it impacts the safety. And we also have the street sign. So this space on the right here near the stone wall and staircase is the one we're asking for, that 20 feet. So yeah, I was told that there was actually possibly a fatality at this crosswalk years ago.
But I, that's, yeah. That might be fake news, Todd, I don't know. Is there driveways on these houses right here? Driveways for these houses? Majority of them have a smaller driveway. Some of them have a lot. This particular house, I don't believe so.
Theirs is around the back. Yeah, they have a shared driveway. I know the owner, so it's a shared driveway. All right. We're going from three down to two spaces now in that section of curb? It looks like it, yes.
That's a block that has a lot of handicapped parking on it, but that's because of that apartment building, right? Parking is such in a demand here. This is where we always had trouble with the Grace Church driveway and people trying to pull out of it. It looked like there had been some markings done next to the driveway. I'd seen that. Yeah, some hatching right here. Yeah, because people were parking so close to the driveway, people couldn't see to get out of the driveway.
Yeah, I just want to point out that there is no parking already in front of the awning here. So there's a sign here, no parking between signs, and a sign here. So basically, this gray pickup truck is in violation right here. That's existing, so we're just kind of replicating it.
Wait, so there's already no parking there? Now I just got myself. Yes, on the Regency side, there's already no parking. Sorry. Oh, this is doing it. So we're going here opposite the Regency. This is what I was requesting right now, because this is already technically restricted where this pickup truck is. So this says no parking between signs.
What we would do, what we're requesting here is no parking here at crosswalk 20 feet from this side. So I'll go back to the photo. So this is the one we have before you tonight right here. This one on the right, if you can see my cursor, near the stone wall. The one on the left is already restricted.
coming from the circles already restricted. How long have those cones been there, Todd? It's a good question. A couple of weeks. Anyone complaining? They've already moved on. There are some, yeah. But they're complaining about the Regency side, which is already restricted, which is not an item because it's already restricted and signed as such. So like that pickup truck that was in the image,
they constantly violate the no parking to do pickup drop-offs or what have you. So, they've been moving those cones on that side, but nobody's complained to me about the opposite side. Usually on the Regency side, they park like a U-Haul truck when they're moving in and out. And that's what we get a call for would be a U-Haul truck that's parked in that area and they're
it's usually somebody moving in or out that week. Yeah, it's on the agenda because the Regency didn't, I don't believe, reach out to Alva for requesting this, but my recommendation was that if they want to pick up drop-off at a short-term parking for whatever needs they may be for the Regency, I would recommend it be proposed as a different restriction before
then no parking restriction or after the crosswalk and not utilize the current posted no parking because that actually could have to come to us for that, right? Yeah, that's why I wasn't necessarily speaking to it, but that's what some folks have been complaining about. There have been pedestrian conflicts here with the vehicles? Todd had mentioned that there was a fatality here.
I'm sure of that. Sergeant Rogers may know about it in the past 11 years. I don't recall it. But for pedestrian issues, the issue that we're having is they usually will avoid this crosswalk because the cars park so close. Yeah, but they're going up the next one, correct? They're usually just, instead of crossing here, they'll just go to the one that's a rotary one.
So site line is definitely there. Lots of different places. So I mean, I'm in favor of these in general. So I'm going to motion to approve this. Todd, the email that I had gotten and sent to you, I didn't process it was this location. In my mind, it was around the other side where we had put in the
the bike lanes, but the email was specifically about the cones being here, and she wanted to be able to use that space as a drop-off pickup location. So what the resident was saying to me in email, and I didn't even realize this was on the traffic commission, I don't know if she did. Well, because what I'm asking for tonight is opposite the regency. Right, the opposite side. What they're complaining about is the existing restriction that's been there for years.
Well, she was saying that this is the only place they can access the elevators without using any stairs, which is probably why there are two handicapped spots right here. They've explained that to me as well. She was saying they use that as an active drop-off pickup, but it's daylighted for the crosswalk.
Yeah, well, back then when they had those signs and restriction, it was probably for the purpose they wanted. They just didn't... They used the wrong signs. Yeah, and also the crosswalk is likely located where it is because of the efficiency. Like it lines up with basically their front door. Otherwise, there would be usually no need to put a crosswalk there. There's one at the church or up near powerhouse and there's one at the circle. So like... Yeah.
Yeah normally if there was a pickup drop off if I were to do from scratch it would be after the crosswalk so the front of the daylight and then after you could but right now there's a handicapped space but that side of the street was not on the agenda tonight. Oh that's fine I just didn't realize that that's what that we were talking this was the same location.
But I did have a solution for them. I recommend it for safety. You can keep the daylighting on that side and then put a pickup drop off or 15 minute, whatever they want before or after the no parking or crosswalk. But then the accessible spaces located nearby might have to shift a little bit. So I had a solution, but they also have a big private parking lot in the back. But again, it's not with the elevator apparently when a toll doesn't go all the way down to that level.
Right. It's also there's only one spot per resident. So they don't really have pickup drop off in there is my understanding. Well, it's big, but it's only it's not as it's only that big because the number of units in there. If that one's that one's not on the agenda this time. Great. The daylight for this one. So let's Yeah, I guess I'm okay with daylighting that.
I know that there's a lot of demand for parking in that area. I'm perplexed as to what people use, excuse me, that crosswalk, where are they going? Usually, they're either going into the Regency or they're going to both bus stops on either side. The bus stops? I was just trying to figure out if you're leaving the Regency, what's across the street there?
For the rest of the commission members that, you know, weren't involved in the email, the original request to improve the safety of this crosswalk is from a resident of the regency and several other regency. So there's basically comments from, you know, within the regency about both things, safety of the crosswalk and pick-up drop-offs. Anyways, just to give some context. I've got a motion on the table. Yep. So Tim has motioned it. Alicia seconded it. Alicia seconded it. Roll call, Alba. Commissioner McGibbon?
Yes. Commissioner Hunt? Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski? Yes. Sergeant Canaba? Yes. 4-0 passed. Moving on to 2023-44, request for permanent parking variance for Ross Street from 372 Riverside Avenue. It's from Sarah, and I am not going to pronounce your last name correctly, so I apologize.
I'm going to ask you to unmute and you can speak on behalf of us. Hi. Can you guys hear me? Yes. How are you?
I'm good. So as I spoke to Alva, I have been a resident at 372 Riverside Ave for almost 12 years now. I've almost always parked two of my cars on Roth Street. And recently, it's been the left side of Roth Street has been issued to permit parking only. And I,
I believe I had obtained a permit in the past, but I don't believe you guys have anything in your system for it, which I'm not sure how that must have happened.
But as of now, when I do park my cars, I sometimes get tickets. And I understand I am not a corner house, but a couple of things I want you guys to know is my driveway only takes three cars. And I am like the only driveway on Riverside Ave between Ross Street and Spring Street that doesn't have a parking lot in the back, only has a driveway.
And I live in a two-family home. My family has three cars. The other family has three cars. Generally, they are the ones that park inside, and we are left to park on Roth Street. And like I said, this hasn't been an issue in the past up until you guys issued it as permit parking only. Yeah, that's also all I have to say.
I'm gonna share the screen so you guys can have an idea. Can you guys see that? So I can bring you guys to Ross Street. Obviously this is the resident.
Driveways to the right? Yes. Yep. Got a better view, I think. And it might be wrong. We've got them in the past, correct? Yes, I believe I was issued one for one of my trucks in the past. So wait, I just wanted to clarify something. Are these trucks or cars? Is this, sorry, I don't have the agenda in front of me. It was open.
It's a, it's a residential truck. Look, it's a, it's a car. Okay. There was something on our agenda about a commercial vehicle as well. So this is a, this is where I found my agenda. Sorry. How's the capacity of Ross street. It sounds like this has been done in the past. Wasn't an issue. Sorry. Yeah.
say it's lightly parked on, but I'm coming over to it now, sorry. Usually has a decent amount of spots on this. It's on one side of that, no homes, it's just the fence up there. Yeah, this side is usually, there's no homes here, so it usually has plenty of room coming forward. And we made it a permit parking. Yeah, when did we make this permit parking? I don't remember.
Either do I. I'm not sure it is, but let me look at my list. We usually don't post an area where there are no homes for permit parking. Permit parking is in front of residences only. Yeah, there is on this side, yeah.
but I'm not sure there's any on the left side. That's the house side, that's the side. I'm not sure there's any on the side. It's not on the left side, going out to the left. On the left, Ross Street, but there's none on the left side here. Right.
That's where most of the variance is limited. Parking by permit only. I see that on the right side now when I zoom in. It just says no dumping, and there's nothing on the left side for permit parking. If you go down where it goes 90 degrees to the left, there's one at the corner. Go the other way. The other way. Go the other way. The other way. Keep going. Keep going. Go all the way down in that house to the right. Go to the right.
No, yeah, with the red door right there. Yeah, that's in front of the house. Yeah, yeah, it may be interpreted to be the whole street by traffic enforcement. Yeah, no, it's not.
Is there an arrow on that? Yeah, I guess I'm wondering if traffic enforcement is assuming that because there are some signs on this street, the whole street is permit parking only. I guess I can imagine that if the commercial building there, the big brick one, if that was occupied, then maybe there might be overflow from that building, but that building is not currently in use.
Sorry, it's in front of some, we've been discussing with the owners some potential renovations there. I mean, correct me if I'm wrong and I may be, but I thought if we had a sign for no, for permit parking or any sign that we have, I thought it had to be within
like 20 feet of each other. So there's not a sign for this entire stretch. And we're going to assume that somebody that parks all the way up here is going to, there's not a parking that's probably 150 yards away from any other no permit parking site. So the petitioner is putting in the text that there is a new sign on the left side, not on street view, but right now, if you go up there.
It's not on street view though. It's too recent. So there's an, so Sarah, how do you, sorry, how do you pronounce your name? No, you're right, Sarah is correct. Sarah, so you're saying there's a new permit parking sign that's gone up? Yes, I believe it was pretty recently gone up there. I also have a picture of it if you guys want me to provide it here or something.
It may have been a mistake. We've had a couple of mistakes like that recently. Unintentional mistake. Would it be, we could let her share her screen or she could email it to me. I could definitely email it. No problem. Does that change anything? If that sign is not supposed to be there, then do we not need to grant a variance? Right, like, because I guess.
I was just going to ask the same thing Tim did, because Riverside, the street that the house is above, doesn't have parking. And usually in those cases, you do grant variances to the side street nearby. I'm confident that there's plenty of parking in Ross and a motion to grant the variance. The potential snafu with the sign, we can correct. But I think Ross Street is listed on the list. So we may have just filled the gap in with the sign.
Motion to approve by Commissioner McKibbin. I'll second that. Seconded by Commissioner Brzezinski. And Alba, roll call. Commissioner McKibbin. Yes. Commissioner Hunt. Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski. Yes. Sergeant Canaba. Yes. Or nothing. That passes. Obviously,
I don't know if that's going to happen. Sarah just give us. Some months. Well, uh. Presently. Fay is not issuing him. Well, she gets an updated list. We will give an updated list and. Just just give us till a couple weeks and you can go down
We just say in the meantime, we believe she should be able to park on the right side of the road against the commercial, that they shouldn't be issuing tickets for that. If they do issue a ticket and she's on that side of the street, does she have any recourse? She can appeal it, but we've had issues with whether or not that's going to be appealed because other miscommunications.
What about the permit parking sign that she's posted there? We'll look and see if the sign's there. I agree with Alicia. I don't remember any record of approving permit parking for that side of the street because there are no homes and it's not typical action that we would do. All right, if that sign is there, I'll see if DPW Tim can get rid of it as soon as possible. Well,
I'm wondering how it got there because we don't just put them up willy-nilly so we could have been replacing one that we thought we really just don't we unless we get an order from the travel commission we don't put up new signs so that's why a resident doing it is it a city sign or is it just i'll check the sign tomorrow let's look at it let's look at it we can confirm it we should also look at the um vote to make raw street permit parking to see if there was any um
You know, usually it's the full street, so then the whole street gets signed. So, we'd have to say something different in the motion. Okay. I will check, I will go back to the original passage, and there might be something listed in that. Yeah, we've got it saved as well.
Okay. Good enough. Moving on 2023-45 request for commercial vehicle variance for Jeff Edwards for 47 Logan Ave and I did see him on here so. Jeff, I'm just gonna ask you to unmute. Hey Jeff, good evening.
Jeff, we can't hear you if you're speaking. You are unmuted, but we can't hear your audio. Before he, I will say that she just emailed me the picture of the sign. I'm going to send it over to you, Tim. It says parking by permit only both sides of street.
So, there may have been some confusion about what the appropriate signage is at this location. Can you guys hear me now? Yes. Yeah, we got you now. Yep. All right, thank you. So, yeah, if you'd like to speak on behalf of the commission to why the commercial vehicle variants you'd like to add for your, if it's business van or some, it's unmarked business van or un,
It's an unlettered pickup truck that I have rights to use as personal use for. It's a company vehicle. It is my only vehicle and I need it five days a week for work. The street I live on is not permit restriction and it's pretty wide open. I haven't had an issue so far.
And I did send the letter from the company stating that it is for personal use as well. And you don't have a driveway to park it in? There is a driveway at the house, but it is not for my use. It's for the first floor.
Todd, can you pull this up for the map? I can't, sorry. It's 47 Logan Avenue. Well, I think I got it now actually. No, it's not letting me, just won't let me drag onto it. I think I got it now, sorry. It should be...
Which side are you on? It's on this opposite side of the park. So up a little that go up past that. Right here? Yeah, it's in front of that van. That, yeah, that one. This house? Yeah, the three level. You're saying this parking is not to be used by the downstairs residents? Correct.
And this isn't the van? No, no, it's a black pickup that's unlettered. It just has commercial plates. Right, and so the issue is that we don't allow overnight parking by commercial plates and we need a commercial permit policy and procedure. So did we decide that, do we have one?
Are we even able to do this and enforce it? Can they get it into their system if we approve it? So that's kind of why I reached out is because I got a ticket for facing the wrong direction. And in the notes, it said no commercial vehicles. And so I reached out to the city and they said that they couldn't take it based on the notes. So I was able to appeal it, but I just didn't want this to be an ongoing issue.
which it would be. Well, the wrong direction is regardless of commercial. Oh, I was faced the right direction. I took a picture of it. So wait, they gave you a ticket for their rationale was because you don't have commercial plates, but they don't have that as one of the boxes on the ticket. No, the violation said wrong direction.
So they gave you a ticket for the wrong direction for commercial vehicle, or did they give you a ticket for wrong direction because you're parked in the wrong direction? I was parked in the correct direction in the notes. I took a picture of it one second. I can pull it up on my phone.
because it just so happens that the lettered vehicle, which is not yours, is correct parked in the direction of the street. Yeah, well, that's that's not me. I wasn't living there at the time. The violation says wrong direction. And in the bottom notes, it says no commercial vehicles. Midnight to 6 a.m. But there is an exception. You have granted some. Yes. We have granted.
On this specific type, we have granted variances. Just so the commissioners know, on the very low side, I get 30 complaints a week on commercial vehicles. And it's probably more like 75. It's all over the city. Why? What is that issue? They're ratting out their neighbors. It's usually a neighbor.
issues overnight commercial overnight. Yeah, yeah. Okay. Um, this request here is not for a I'm just saying, we've got to look into this at some point.
because it's gone crazy. Yeah, I agree. My question is, as far as this request goes, this isn't for a permanent street. This is just for a waiver, basically, of overnight parking in the city. That's correct. Which we have given.
Yeah, I mean, was there an issue with the parking enforcement system in this or not? Is the way they will take it a reflection of their deficiencies in the system? We have the same system as the parking department, so I don't understand why they wouldn't be able to. All we need to do is look up a plate, ABC123, and if it has a
have a motion to approve the permit or a commercial vehicle, we can issue a ticket for that. There's no issue. I feel like I'm the one making all the first motions today, but that's okay. I have a motion to approve. Motion by Commissioner McGibbon, seconded by? I'll second it. Seconded by Commissioner Hunt. Roll call, Elma. Commissioner McGibbon? Yes, indeed. Commissioner Hunt? Yes.
Yes. Sergeant Canava. Yes. Pass for nothing. Mr. Edwards, obviously we will notify our department on our end with the commercial vehicle variance that hopefully we can add it into the system with your license plate. And I will try and speak with Faye over at the parking department to have that as added as well. So just give us a
a week here and we'll hopefully have that done. I do have the plate number in his request too. I'll get that and I will work on that. Is your email over or cell phone so I can get in contact with you? I have it here. Great. I will contact you as soon as possible. Thank you very much. Have a nice night.
I'm going to ask one question on the previous request for Sarah on 372 Riverside Ave. It was approved. She mentioned she has three vehicles. What are we approving for one vehicle or are we approving all three of them? We understood it to be one vehicle. One vehicle? Yes. Yes. Okay. Thank you.
and no visitor passes. Sorry, there was no mention of visitor passes. Nope, no visitor passes, just the one. No visitor passes. Great. Thank you. I did forward the picture, Tim, to you that says no parking on either side of the street. Okay. Or permit parking both sides of the street.
and it's a brand, it's very clearly a new sign. Yeah, we'll find out what's going on. Thank you. Okay. Well, I think that is all we have for new business unless commissioners have anything they'd like to bring up. Someone else should make the motion to adjourn.
you're going what are they calling in hearts rainbow or whatever it is another table no I don't play hearts but anyway if I may Alva I had requested to revisit an existing item to clarify something for for yes I did Francis for Francis sorry
Oh, I was keeping handicapped sign up at the Boston Avenue GLX. Yes, housekeeping. It's an old item 2022 dash 35, which it was going to be consulting with me for exact positioning. So we've done that with Francis and we want to come back to the commission to make sure it met with what they expected. The chief was looking at this when I received it.
I don't know if he had questions pertaining to this. I mean, I can say what the situation is to the commission members. Basically, in 2022-35, you guys had approved, the commission had approved a ride share pickup drop-off zone and HP sign, but it didn't specify how many spaces of HP, so it was kind of assumed one, but when Francis and I
Francis is the diversity inclusion and deals with a lot of accessibility folks. When we went out there to visit, this is what we determined, this graphic that's on the screen, that we actually want two accessible spaces near the GLX station. And I have a note on the approved minutes that Commissioner Brzezinski had a caveat to not put it between two other zones. So that's what we've done here. So there's nothing behind the blue.
the accessible spaces. In front is a pull-off for the ride vehicle, so the green would be the ride share. It was already approved and it was kind of left up exact positioning to me, so I wanted to clarify that we're asking for two handicaps, but it's still one zone, not boxed in. Hopefully that was okay. This actually came up recently in another context, having
accessible spaces close to the Green Line station. Have you not heard the noise that people wanted more handicapped spots near the Green Line station? Yeah, it was mentioned at the mayoral debate. I feel like I heard it before that. It's been a long-standing request. As you can see in this street, all the images on Google are still outdated with the construction. We're finally able to sort it out over there, so this is what we're recommending.
So we just wanted to kind of close the loop with you all, because it didn't really say a single HP space, but again, given the need in Francis.2 would make sense. It's still one zone, two spaces long. If it's okay with everyone. I mean, I have a question. If it's not a handicapped parking space, what else is that going to be?
It is a handicap workspace, I'm just saying it's not a single, I'm saying it's a zone, and it could fit two. So the question isn't whether making it shorter, it's just like, can we call it two spots? Yeah, it was just unclear in the previous minutes if it was a singular handicap accessible space or a zone. So I'm trying to clarify that's all, that we're doing two, that's what we want to do.
So it's the two spaces, blue space here. Currently, it's unrestricted in this block. After construction, there's no signs there whatsoever. Right. I mean, I'm okay with it. My impression is that it's not like this is going to be some other kind of parking. It's not like this is going to be eight-hour commuter parking right there anyhow. So we might as well have it be two handicapped spots. I use this station a good bit. I noticed that the T people park in most of these spots.
as it is, so I think this is incredibly beneficial to allow someone else other than, I don't even know what they throw on their dashboard to designate that they're authorized to park where they park, but. Yeah, Steve, as you said that, when I was out with DPW Mark in this, we did see some of the T employees there with the vests and the windshield, and then the parking department actually, by chance,
walked by as well. And they looked it up and they're feeding, they're paying that fee all day long. So that, cause in this particular stretch, this is one stretch in the city where it's more than two hours. It's, I think it's unlimited or 10 hour. So they basically pay all day long. At least they're paying. I always thought they were kind of throwing something on their dashboard and not paying anything. Yeah. Um,
So we were about to sign it. The reason why we came back to you is because we wanted to make sure it met the intents that you all wanted. And because the sign department is going to put poles in the ground, and we don't want to do it incorrectly. If you're looking for a motion, I'd support that. But I think it's fine. I don't see where else you could put it.
The chair can ask for objections if the clarification is wrong, and if any of us object, we can revote it, but I don't see a need to if none of us object. Yeah, I'm fine with it. So I'm not sure, do we even need to do another motion for this if it's already been approved? No, I think you as the chair can just ask if any of the members object. Any of the members object? No. No.
All right, we're good. Thank you. Frances will be happy. Thank you for entertaining that last question. I have a question. Go ahead, Alicia. Can I make one thing? We had tabled 2023-33 from last week about a change of permit parking from Strathmore Road to Bow Street from Sydney Goldberg. Did she make it tonight? Or he make it tonight?
Goldberg, if you are here, either raise your hand or type into the chat. I just have two other people here on here, so I'm not sure. Did anybody reach out to them? Since there are only two left, we could unmute if one of those two are trying to speak. Yeah, P. Anthony and iPad, what are you guys here for?
You guys would like to unmute, then iPad, and then P Hanson, if you guys are here for that then. You don't have to speak, but. We're going to wrap up if you're not going to speak. That's a problem. We'll fix it.
I'm sorry, we're not Francis, whoever you look for. We just wanted some answers in the chat, if possible. Yeah, if you'd like to ask them, you're more than happy, but the chat isn't recorded. Oh, okay. So in the chat, I mentioned about the crosswalk in front of the police station.
It's the corner of South Street and Main Street to cross Main Street. Could it be monitored by the police because it's very dangerous to try to cross there because cars basically ignore you. Yeah. Are you saying coming from South Street towards the other end of the police station on Main Street or are you coming from the other side?
Yeah, so if you're coming down South Street and then you want to cross the street, like in front of the police station, so you can get over to the square. They go faster, basically, and they don't want to stop. It's very rare to get one to stop. Yep, right there.
Yeah, we can absolutely monitor that. And is there a specific time of day that this is more? I can take your information and talk offline about this. So if you want to give me your number, I can kind of do this offline too. Sure, that'd be great. It's basically probably in the morning.
Okay, we can definitely do that. And my emails, I can give you my email so you can give me an email and then we can go from there. Okay, thank you so much. It's Jay and then Charlie, C as in Charlie, A as in Alpha, N as in Nancy, N as in Nancy, A as in Alpha, V as in Victor, A as in Alpha at MedfordPolice.com. So Jay Canava at MedfordPolice.com.
Okay, thank you so much. And then the other question was, how far can cars park from a driveway? Three feet. Three feet, each side. Each side, yeah. So we can block, so it was the first thing that you had proved next to us, the handicap on Toro Avenue, with the people next door, and we've
We park in our driveway and we get blocked into our driveway. We can't get in or out. It makes it really hard. If that happens, just call our police at 391-6404 or the emergency line. 395-1212. And we will immediately tell them. Yeah, because they squeezed two cars in front of our house, which is a pretty small area.
If that happens, you just call us immediately and we'll have a cruiser come over there and they'll be able to tow the vehicle. All right, great, thank you. So it's supposed to be three feet. Okay, thank you so much. No problem, have a nice night. Email me with any other questions, please. Okay, thank you, appreciate all your help. All right, Tim. To ask Tim Chard on that handicapped space at Boston Ave. Yep.
Are they posting an additional sign that's a handicap sign? How are the postings going to be? Yeah, we were going to post a sign at either end to mark out like accessible space in between the two signs, but it would be two spaces. I believe we're going to do L's and T's to help identify it as well. Okay, thank you. Okay, Tim, shoot the moon. I got the reference.
Oh, motion to adjourn? Yeah. I have a question that's not quite traffic commission, but it's for the traffic division and Tim. It's a motion on the table. It's about the parking lot this weekend.
I understand you're going to close the Andrews school or the lot between the McGlynn and the Andrews for the Energy Festival on Saturday. Is somebody planning to or able to put signage up in the lot in advance so the dog park people and garden people are aware in advance that the lot will be closed Saturday? DPW, Alicia. DPW does that?
Yeah, yeah, we could do we can do that. We probably need to just check in real quick on on the scope of work for that event. But that's that's the easy 1. I think. I know that Kevin emailed the traffic division about closing the lot for for. Saturday.
Yeah. So I mean, do you want to, we can like put soft horses up on Friday afternoon or something. Is that what you're talking about? What I was hoping is to put some cones in the lot on earlier this week so that people coming to the dog park would know on Wednesday and Thursday that they can't come on that Saturday, the lot will be closed. So they're less angry on Saturday.
have a motion to adjourn. We have a motion to adjourn. We have a motion to adjourn. We have a motion to adjourn. We have a motion to adjourn. We have a motion to adjourn. We have a motion to adjourn. We have a motion to adjourn. We have a motion to adjourn. We have a motion to adjourn. We have a motion to adjourn. We have a motion to adjourn. We have a motion to adjourn. We have a motion to adjourn. We have a motion to adjourn. We have a motion to adjourn. We have a motion to adjourn.
Yes. Commissioner Brzezinski? Yes. Sergeant Canaba? Yes. Thank you, everyone. The meeting is adjourned. Have a safe night and travel safely. Put your cell phones away.