have to try to, you know, bear with me. It's a little tough to top that. Thank you very much. So a couple things. I'm a bit of a talker and so to do not that, I'm gonna have a bit of a little speech just so that I can get to the points that are really important but you also can hear my voice in the same time. I want to start off by saying thank you so so much for coming here to support myself, support Anna. It means the world to me on an individual level and a personal level because to be supported by people in our
community who you don't know directly really is the inspiring work that we need as community members and as people who are engaged in our city. As a younger person I think it was a really difficult decision to do this because it takes a lot of work. It's really tough to kind of put yourself out there every single day to knock on doors, to make phone calls, to go to events, to meet people who may disagree with you ideologically speaking.
But that being said, though, you also learn so much so quickly. I probably learned more in the last three to four months than I probably did in the last probably four years of college in real world experience. And I think that that's, you know, priceless, truly, truly priceless for me as someone who wants to engage in this type of work for my career and the rest of my life. So thank you, truly.
Now, I'm going to pull that out of my speech so you understand where I'm going with this, what my platform is going to be, what I hope to accomplish in the next few years if I am to win on November 7th. With your vote and your help, that'll happen. Hello, my name is... We're going to restart here in a little bit.
My name is Aaron Olopade and I am running for Medford School Committee. My story is a testament to the transformative power of public education and community connections. After arriving in Medford in 2013, I found direction, support, and purpose in the classroom, on the river as a member of the rowing team, and through community service. I was, believe it or not, able to surmise about 500 community hours
by graduation, something that Medford High is very important on graduating. You need to graduate with 60 hours. I was able to push it a little bit, hit that 500 hour mark, so clearly I am very engaged in this type of work because it is something that fulfills me.
By the time I graduated, I became driven and I wanted to lead by example and to work for equity, unity, and progress. Whether it was as a community liaison for the city of Medford, a team captain at Boston College, a legislative aide in the Massachusetts State House, or serving underrepresented youth with City or Boston, I've been dedicated to these values. My studies in political science and social justice and my work with the NAACP just intensified my determination to represent underrepresented
As we stand at the crossroads of tradition and progress, mine is a voice that understands our past and fearlessly envisions our future. I'm a product of the Medford schools, an advocate for our youth, and a representative who has walked the hallways
and felt the community struggles. My experience leads me to a platform with these three priorities. One, a safe and supportive learning environment that produces a quality education. I envision a Medford where students are equipped to handle life's challenges both inside and outside the classroom and can thrive as a whole human. What will I do to address this? I will advocate for budgets, buildings, books, and for all the tools necessary for students and educators to excel in an environment that promotes safety, security, and sustainability.
I will also make sure that the student's well-being is paramount. I will emphasize the importance of mental health resources, tools for social and emotional growth, and programs focused on conflict resolution.
Two, equity inclusion acts as an opportunity. I see the unequal footing that many students stand on and understand how racism and bigotry hinder young Medford minds. I am committed to fostering a learning environment where every student feels valued, understood, and free from discrimination. And I am devoted to ensuring that every student, regardless of their socioeconomic background, has the same opportunities in education. And what am I gonna do to address this?
This means making extracurriculars accessible, paying special attention to the needs of students with disabilities, those from lower income families, and English learners, and advocating for a more diverse teaching staff. I will advocate for educational initiatives that create an equitable and inclusive learning environment, such as integrating curriculum that includes contributions from different backgrounds, cultures, and perspectives. And I will champion an anti-racist, anti-ableist, and inclusive Medford Public Schools ethos. And three.
Support of teachers, educators, and families through community collaboration. What we're doing right here is the first step. That community collaboration is paramount. Recognizing the backbone of our education system, I will use community collaboration, just as this is right here, to uplift and empower the educators and staff of the Medford schools.
I know from personal experience the power of community. Fostering collaboration between our schools, local organizations, and the broader Medford community, we can tackle broader challenges that impact our students. A holistic approach to education means ensuring students are nurtured at school, at home, and throughout the community.
How do I accomplish this? To solidify a passionate and motivated educational workforce, I will work to ensure our staff and educators are fairly compensated, have a healthy work environment and the tools that they need, and their voices are essential in the decision-making. To develop a community-wide commitment to achieve these priorities, I will seek ways to work with our community of parents, students, and our local organizations. I will help to create tools for strengthening these partnerships, such as directories, committees, and an open and safe forum for feedback.
I'm asking for your vote for the Medford School Committee to embrace the idea that every student, every teacher, and every resident of Medford is heard and valued. That dreams and aspirations, just like I had a dream and aspiration when I was younger to do this type of work, are elevated and the vibrant diversity that makes Medford unique is celebrated.
I'm also asking for your financial support because man, it is really, really expensive to do this and everything matters. Everything counts. This is the type of work that we as a community have to do and I can't appreciate, I can't thank you, I can't be more gracious than I am right now in this moment, seeing all of you staring directly at me as I'm asking you for financial support, volunteer support, any type of support, advice, suggestions, however you think to support me and Anna and the work that we're trying to do is