Ben or Bob, any questions on that? Any concerns? Go ahead, Ben. No, no, just clarifying it. So that's one thing. So there's the sort of acoustic performance or talks and lectures. There is trivia. And then there are TVs.
Yeah, there'll be two TVs. I used to run and curate a reading series at the Medford Historical Society for poets, but also I'll probably be reaching out to interesting people in the community like cooks and scientists to do maybe once a month, like a seven to eight or 6.30 to 7.30, meet your neighbors who do interesting things type talk. In terms of music, we're not gonna have drum sets. So it's gonna be quiet.
And in terms of television, I do love the Boston Bruins. And the only other thing is that for major events, like should the Red Sox find themselves in the World Series again, we will have a projection screen on one of the sides that will occasionally be used. But at this point, we haven't worked out our TV contract with Verizon to be able to show anything. So the only thing that would happen between now
probably, you know, New Year's would be maybe a little bit of a holiday singing with an acoustic guitar. We plan on being deferential to our neighbors. And we're also, our current business hours are closed before 10 or closed at 10. So it's, it's not really, we are not opening a rock club. Yeah. Yeah. So it's not going to one in the morning or anything like that. Sure. Not at all. Okay. Yeah. I'm good with that. Yeah.
The question I had, Mr. Commissioner, is that considered two licenses they're going to need, one for entertainment by performers, which is gonna be the acoustical, and one for devices? Or is it just under one? I'm not really sure how this... No, Daria, correct me if I'm wrong, but it's three separate licenses they've applied for, correct?
No, it's all one. It's all one. Okay, they get all one license, but we just check off the ones that they're like using. So, for example, they only apply. What is it Bobby? It'd be just the two $100 fees for this particular license.
Three, because they're applying for performers, patrons, and devices. And devices, right. One for each. So it would be one license that would cover these three categories. Exactly. We give them one license, but it's three different categories. It all falls under that entertainment license. Right. And that explains the three separate sign-offs by all the appropriate department heads for each category.
Okay, good. All right. They just have to pay 300 for this. Yeah. That's what I figured, three different. 100 times three, that's right. Okay, good. Well, very straightforward. I know that was a lot of work getting the department heads in there, but if you guys wanna, if you know other questions, you wanna make a motion, let's get this one off the table.
Yep, I'll make a motion. A lot of work, but now you're all set. So that's great. Good luck with everything. So I'll make a motion to accept the application for the entertainment license for the three separate entertainment license for performers, devices, patrons as laid out here for the Medford Brewing Company.
I'll second that emotion. Very good. Um, uh, since I don't see any, anybody in negative, so let's, uh, uh, the motion is carried all in favor. Say aye. Aye. Very good. So it carries. Thank you, Max. Um, all right. Is anybody left at school? Because I just saw about the six 60, 75 of them marching down the city. Oh, who's left. There are a lot of kids here, but it's, um, yeah, there are a lot of kids who left.
We're trying to put a, we're trying to do the best we can here today. Yeah. Listen to the student voices, but also continue to provide a safe environment and classes, you know, I'm teaching. So we'll see who shows up in eight minutes. Okay. All right, sir. All right. Happy holidays. Take care. Happy holidays.
Okay, let's jump over to the Chili Garden. I see the attorney. First of all, let me just say, attorney, I went through that package. That was a lot of work on your behalf. Everything was perfect. I checked everything, names, everything. So kudos to you for structuring the entire transaction and helping Jen.
with this acquisition. So I do thank you for being part of this. Jen, I wanted to commend you for stepping in and buying the Chili Garden. I mean, that's fantastic. I always judge by chicken wings. So I'll be coming by, once you're up and running, I'm gonna be coming by and ordering chicken wings. So that's how I judge. So tell us, as I said, we're aware of the acquisition, you're purchasing
The restaurant for $250,000 is 200,000 shares. So tell us a little about your background. Tell us a little about what's going on and what are your plans? Your questions are for Jing, right? Yeah, yeah. I'd like to hear from Jing.
her background, what her plans are for the restaurant. Just give us a little background, because we have all the documents. Yeah, we can see the purchase and sales agreement. We can see all the financial take of it. But tell us about what your plans are to get the restaurant going in the square. I think it's your time to respond to the commissioners' questions.
Oh, she's muted. She's muted. You click on the unmute audio.
I can hear what he said. I want to make sure if what he said is my plan. Your experience and your plan. I don't understand what he said. What did he say? 2500 is what? Your experience and your plan. Okay.
Yeah, I work here a long time. So I have plan for sometimes maybe I will plan for make the new delicious food for the neighbor and the customer. You know, here I know the least restaurant.
It's open long times because I work before here. I have some mind for change for the some menu, some give the some restaurant some new, new something, you know, and maybe give some customers new feeling. Yeah, it's very important. So, you know, the time is past the every day. So I want to give some label can
know that to be got to have some change, you know. Very good. The reason I ask is, you know, we have the Chevalier Theater, and there are nights when there are play nights and in the squares crowded and there are people, very hungry patrons all roaming around the square looking to spend their money. And we
You know, our dream, you know, I was on the chamber board for 10 years, and our dream had always been to revitalize the square and make it a destination. And that's why we, you know, we applaud that you're stepping in and taking over the restaurant, buying it, and let's make it bigger and better. Let's make it, you know, help to Medford Square become a destination. So that's kind of my chamber thing. But I'm happy that, as I said, that you,
Let me see. So you, Ms. Wang, and Mr. Zhang are all partnered to buy the establishment, correct? You're at 50%. Ms. Wang is at 25% in stock, and Mr. Zhang is with 25% in stock, if I'm not correct, right? Yeah, yeah.
As we can see, you've taken the proper steps. We've seen the public posting. We've seen the documents. I don't know. I'm pretty good with it. As I said, I read through the P&Ss. I read through the promissory notes. I see what the payments are. Ben or Bobby, did you have any questions or any concerns about the transaction or the acquisition?
No, I know it was a dense packet. I did, you know, looking through it, I did see that you were, you'd been employed there for a long time, TIP certified, what percent owner you'd be. And I'm familiar with the restaurant and I'm glad it's staying in business.
So no, I, the close, sorry, the closing date, is that, has that already happened, the closing, already happened? Closing date is gonna wait until ABCC approved this multiple amendment application. Okay, that was all I was unclear on. Okay, well then that doesn't really affect what I was- Yeah. So I'm good, so- Okay, good, yeah. I don't know if Bobby has anything- Bobby, what about yourself?
It was a big package. I agree. It was a very thick package. Yeah, it was. I went through it pretty much myself. And it all looks, everything looks in order. I mean, the DUA and the DOR, they were all paid to date, which is great.
You know, as far as, I did find one little error, and probably for the lawyer, you might wanna take a look at, on page nine on the financial disclosure, Mr. Zhang was putting in $625,000 for his own money. I think he might've just added an extra zero there.
Yeah, I saw that too. I figured that was just a typo, but you're right. All the figures were totaled. But other than that, I mean, everything else looks great. Is there any need to change the entertainment license there or do they not have one while we're doing this? Should they be applying for a new entertainment license?
So they're not doing any changes for the entertainment aspect of the operation. So it remains the same. There's no application.
biodepending or planned. So this is a straightforward stock transfer. Yeah. And they could, you know, they could always come back for the entertainment. That's, you know, that's pretty easy. There's no, you know, there's no limitation on the entertainment. So, but yeah, that was the, Bobby, that's the same thing that, that caught my attention there with that one. And,
I don't know, I'm pretty good with this. We can see what's happening. Did you have a follow-up question, Bob? No, no, that was it. I mean, everything else looked pretty much in order. And I feel the same way that, you know, it's great. The square needs all the businesses we can get. And from what I hear, it's a very nice restaurant. The food's very good there. And we wish you a lot of luck. I hope things go well for you.
Good, good, good. So let's, if someone would make a motion for, you know, the change in managers, change in stock, let's see, change in manager, change in officers, directors, and managers, and issuance of a transfer of stock, new stockholders. So if we could have a motion for that, that'd be great. Let's see.
I can make a motion. Yeah, sure. You want me, could you do it, Ben? Yeah, I'll make a motion to approve the transfer of stock license via the transfer of ownership for the Chili Garden. Yeah. You know,
as laid out in this meeting right here. So I would make a motion to accept that. Very good. Very good. I'll second the motion. Very good. Thank you for the motion. Thank you for the second. All in favor of accepting the application, say aye. Aye. Aye. Very good.
You're all set. Again, thank you. Thank you, attorney, for all the hard work you've done on this. Again, I see how you structured the purchase and sales agreements, the notes, the gifts, everything. So there was a lot of work, a lot of yeoman's work. So Jen, best of luck. Dari, did you have a question? Were you telling me to slow down? Yes. So I just noticed, I hope this is right. It doesn't have checked off transfer of license.
which this is transfer of license on the application of multiple amendments? This is, if I may, it's not a transfer of license, it's a transfer of the stocks. I gotcha, so the owners are staying the same, right? Okay, okay. Just wanna make sure. Well, the stock is being transferred to the new owners. Gotcha, okay. Right, yeah. Okay, good. All right, so then all in favor of the motion, say aye.
All right, very good. You're all set. You're off and running, Jen. Congratulations. Like I said, I'll be by for chicken wings at the beginning of the year, so. Yeah, welcome. All right. Those are going to be coming off the menu, Alan. That was the name of the change. Yeah, we'll get a new menu. All right. All right, attorney. Take care. Thank you. Good luck. Good luck. Thank you. Good luck.
All right, so Chili Gardens, we're done. Daria, did you get my response on, you had sent me electronic signature document? Yes, and then I went to Ben and then I think it's gonna go to Bobby. Okay, good, good, good.
Yeah, it says it has now been sent to telephone or gmail.com to sign. All right. Is that the is that the one where it says the commission will vote to approve the list of the 2023 liquor license renewals was that the document that no so I sent you the. Yes. All the individual.
Yep. Well, I did it. I tried to do pack all the package stores together, all the clubs together, all the restaurants for alcohol, all. Yes. They're all the same. Just the one that I sent you guys just shows that Carol's didn't renew in Boston. We just didn't renew.
Yeah, that's what I thought it was just just verifying that we saw that those guys did not renew their license. Exactly. So I'm going to send out the package. And then we also have I sent it to you guys yesterday. The estimation of the population. Yeah, that's that's the one I couldn't find. Yeah, I couldn't find that either.
So I didn't send you the actual form because then I noticed because I get this from our HR director because he does the census stuff. I noticed that on the population estimate it says July 1 2021 not July 1 2022.
So, it's two years, so I don't think it's a, I don't think met for is that 62,098. So, I told them, don't rush just try to find this for me and then I'll send it to you guys. Okay, we're gonna prove it that way so I can send it, you know, next week or something. So this was out of my hair.
And then I can do the electronic signature like that as well, because that was easy for you guys, right? That wasn't hard. It was very easy. Very easy. All right. So let's back up a bit. So the retail license renewals. So I put them into different categories. I put them into the all alcohol. I put them all alcohol club, package store, all alcohol, and then wine and malt, and then cordials, wine, malt, and cordials. So thank you. This is great.
we kind of know who the managers are for these. I think to me, these are very helpful that we, as next year goes on, we need to pull, we can pull these out and say, well, okay, you're not the manager that we have on record before. So I think this is very helpful. So I guess we need to make a motion to approve the package, right? Approve the list of 2023 liquor license renewals. So one of you want to make a motion to approve
the package Daria sent us? I have a question. Yeah. So, okay. So right, we have beer and wine, we have restaurants, we have all alcohol package stores, right? So I looked at all of those. So some of them, a lot of them, the manager and then like the printed signature, it is different. And you know, like the hotel, like the hotel that shut down right there, Marriott.
If you just kind of scan through it, you'll see there's like slight differences. Um, I think that matter.
Package stores, a lot of them, the owners were coming in for clubs, same. The people that I spoke to, mostly were all the same people from last year. I know there was a change, a manager for, that we just recently did for Smashburger. So it was a different person who signed for that one. Yeah, so that one's different, I saw that. Yeah, there was a change in the station landing to hotels, because again, that's a different manager that we just approved.
And then the 85 station landing and the 95 station landing. I think that's the month that Ben was in here. Oh, yeah, it was probably I think it was last month. Yeah, that's Maria. That's the one you're talking about. So it's just like and then like Canova, Keith something and the manager is Iliana.
Yeah, or B05, for example, the manager. Yeah, yeah. So does that, are we, are we worried about that? No, no, because, you know, the restaurant manager is not, in some instances, the manager is the owner and
In other instances, they're not. So I don't think that's, it's just, you know, the owner is either in the kitchen cooking if it's a restaurant or out front smoothing with the, you know, the patrons and the managers doing the manager gerial stuff. So I don't see that as a concern or an issue. Bobby, do you think that's something that we should be aware of? I'm not sure. I mean,
I mean, a manager, I don't think necessarily is the owner, correct? In some instances, yes. In some instances, no. Down the bottom, it says title. And that's where they write an owner. I mean, if there's a manager, they just write in manager, right?
Yeah. I think like the paperwork does kind of cover us because the paperwork that we submit, it says it in there. And I feel like businesses need to take responsibility in that to look. It says it there that it has like who needs to sign for it. It can't just be a random person. Yeah. I don't think I can be president or owner. So, yeah, no, I mean, that is that's right. That's that's pretty much what all they are. It just it doesn't always line up. So
No, it was just a question. And I'm glad that that doesn't seem to be an issue, because this would be a lot of work. No, it's a good question, because we don't really know. But I also don't know, because they all come at the same time. I don't really know how to filter all of them and ask. Yeah, I don't know that we would need to, though, because of what Bobby just said. Yeah, OK.
Well, you know, I'm going to have a question right. I was going through them, and I found the L to Cuba consignor and to kill about Medford square and under the.
where they certify and swear on the penalty and perjury, blah, blah, blah. There's four questions. And the fourth question is, the premises are now open for business. Then an exclamation point or parentheses, if not, explain below. And the additional information box below, it's still empty, is- Well, that's funny that you noticed that. They haven't done it for the past-
At least four years. At least four years. Yeah, at least four years. Well, like I said before, when you get old, you got nothing better to do than read stuff. No, that's a good point. I saw that one too, Bob. I was going to ask you about that too. Yeah, it's kind of like, you know, it'd be nice for us to know what their progress is. I mean, people ask me every once in a while, hey, anything about that place? You know what? I like that, Bobby. I like that catch.
David Ensign, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB – He-He Him, PB
So we have something for record. So Bobby's right. So then I decided to go in a different direction or something. So then we have something for record. Yeah, it's completely valid. I mean, if we're here to approve liquor licenses of a restaurant that's just been sitting there boarded up, it's strange to say the least. So it's completely valid, I think, that they give us a... Yeah, I don't think we're being...
You know, out of order or anything yeah.
A point of information, I drove by there a couple of nights ago and I actually saw some lights on for the first time in a long time, like there's some type of activity going on. But I just said to myself, maybe they're getting ready to open. And then when I saw this and it was blank, I'm saying, well, it could be one of two things. Maybe they're going to be open by January 1st of 2023, and that's why nothing was put in there.
Is this document just to swear for the date of?
to 2023, or is it mean if your business, is your business now open, meaning the day you signed it, 11-16-22? I don't know. It's just- I would bet they just signed it and they didn't think about any of that. Yeah, yeah. I doubt they're planning on opening January 1st after that. Yeah, I think you're right, Ben. I think it's just automatic pilot. It's been going for four years now and they just,
Yeah, let's let's push back a little bit, you know, not, you know, we just we just want we want a little clarification to the question for because they are, you know, certifying and swearing under penalty of perjury. Same same owner as to knock or to know. Yeah. So he already did is his to knock to knock application. Yeah.
Darian, I'm sorry, I didn't mean to cause you more work. No, it's fine. So yeah, so he's, you know, he's already done, you know, so we're okaying one of his open businesses. We're asking about his unopened business. Right. That's right. Yeah. We, all right. We just, you know, we're flagging, you know, El Tacuba and we just, we want some clarification on that. That's all.
I mean, either way, I don't think it really makes a difference, no matter what answer he gives, unless he states that he doesn't have any plans on opening, but that wouldn't be the case if he paid for his license for another year, right? Yeah. Yeah. And plus, you know, there's nothing wrong with us asking and he should be able to provide that because if he's not, if he's not open for business, it says, if not explained below. So he does owe us something. So, all right.
So let's okay everything with that one exception. Sounds good to me. Okay. Yeah. So Daria, I'll make a motion to accept the retail license renewals with the exception of Alta Cuba. And the commission has asked for the owner to address question four.
or to revisit question four. So can we get a second? Yeah, I'll second that. Very good. All right. All in favor, say aye. Aye. Aye. Very good. Motion carries.
All right, so the renewals have been accepted with the exception of AltaCuba until we get something in writing explaining or addressing question four. Alan, do you think maybe we should maybe put some sort of an amendment in that if he gets diarrhea, that information contingent upon getting diarrhea, the information, just so it doesn't tie up his renewal? Yeah, I'll amend. Yeah.
before, you know, November 30. So it'll just keep them from having to redo all paperwork and everything again, if somebody takes a look at it and says, hey, you know, you didn't get your renewal in on time. But I don't think they will. That's a good point. So everything just gets passed as long. Yeah.
It gives us something to fill in, in the additional information box. I'm good with that if you guys are good with it. No, I think that's a great idea. So, Jerry, add that to the amendment that as long as he provides us with some information, we'll be fine. We'll locate the license, the renewal. Maybe a satisfactory explanation or some type of information. Yeah.
satisfactory. yeah satisfactory explanation. Okay. Have we covered everything I think we've covered everything now. Anything else. believe so yeah as long as you guys are good with the non renewals so carols and.
the wing stop. Yeah. So Bobby, you should have that now that I've signed off on it. Cause I actually just signed off on it. It went to another email bucket of mine. It was weird, but I have it. And I signed, I just signed off on it. I did receive it and signed off on it. Did you receive it back Daria? Oh, okay. You did a couple of minutes. Okay. Yup. Yeah. A few minutes ago.
So we should be able to. Any new information on deep cuts? No, I stuck my head in the, and I can see people in there working. The auction was completed and now I see people in there and it's a sign that the state sign is gone. And there's a sign that says under renovation. So it looks like they continue to move forward.
Oh, good. That's good. Followed up with me, but I just haven't had the chance to do anything with it. So I think he's waiting for us to do. I don't know, to do what, but to do something. Well, we were, and I apologize, Bobby, I know you took the steps to put together the questions. I, you know, it just got side, you know, with the with the end of the year and everything, it just got
It got sidetracked, but we'll add our questions and we'll get it over to ABCC for their opinions. Yeah, only because I'm sure he wants to move forward with it as soon as possible. He mentioned last month that he was targeting for some time in January, right?
Yeah, but then the seizure happened, and so that might have put him behind, and the auction occurred. But we'll get to it. Like I said, it's just that it's been the end of the year crush for me and the bank. Oh, I can imagine. I can imagine with everyone. It's end of the year is a little
All right, good. Are you guys ready to move forward with it? I haven't mentioned anything or done anything. I just wait, you know, until you get ready. We'll circle back to that. So, all right, Dari, anything else? Just that I'm going to send you guys the
estimation for the population. And this way, if you guys are good with it so we can approve it so I can send the package out. Okay, renewal package. Did you, did you hint at it being 62,000 Did I hear you say that or do was I just that's what he had as of.
That's what it had as of July 1, 2021 population estimates. Yeah, through census. Wow. That moved up a lot. It always... 55 or something? Yeah. And then it was like dancing for a long, long time, 57, 58, 59, somewhere in that neighborhood for a long time. And now it's 62. Wow. Okay.
Yeah, so send that to us when it's available. Yeah, I'm gonna send it to you guys once I get it from Neil. And then so this way we can approve it. Well, you guys can approve it and then we can just, I can send it out and we'll- Okay, good. All right, well, if we're all set, then hearing will be adjourned at 1.39. Good to see you guys. Happy holidays. Hope all your shopping is done.
I hope you weren't subjected to that Patriots game Sunday because I was screaming at them with that bonehead. You know what Myers did where he just they went into rugby mode. You know, I don't think they knew the score. You know, that's what you do when you lose and you got nothing to lose, you know.
Why didn't Mac Jones tackle him? The guy just pushed him over like a little kid. He supported Mac. He grabbed his legs.
That play doesn't work. It doesn't work, that play. Why even try it? It's total desperation, but all you do is fall down. That was it. Then we go into OG. I don't know. It's crazy. I don't know. Alan, I could hear you screaming from my house. Oh my god. I couldn't believe it. I could not believe it. Oh my god. All right. Good to see you guys. Happy holidays. Take care, everyone. Bye, everybody. Bye. Bye-bye.