So basically, Fred, are you happy with the contents of the brochure? Yeah. The only thing my family suggested was creating a link. You know, when you take, I forget what it's called. Oh, sure. A QR code. QR code. To create a QR code. Yes. But then we need to link that.
to a web page, yeah. Yeah. Chris Donovan just wrote back. He says, I'm still under the weather with COVID. I have no energy. Unbelievable what he's going through. So he's still on the unable to perform list, I guess. OK, that's fine. Let's see.
Okay, so let's, why don't we, obviously, I have to put together a webpage. Well, we all do. There has to be a webpage relating to the proposed South Street historic district. I still have to get the new guidelines up on the website.
Yeah. So the website is up, by the way. That's at least a step in the right direction. I did look at it, and yeah, it looks good. It would be nice if we were able to update. It's much, much easier than we do. OK. So basically, all right. So I looked over the thing that Chris Skelly sent me actually more than a month ago.
Dennis, is that you? No, that's me. That's Chris Donovan responding to my text. Oh, sure. Okay. So basically, I would like to shoot for a public hearing in September. That means we have to submit the report
the preliminary report to the Mass Historical Commission by mid-July. How do people feel about that? How do you feel about that, Fred? You think that's good? I think the one that Chris Skelly sent us is fine. There was a lot of information needs to be plugged into that. He had a lot of placeholders for things.
But it certainly seems acceptable to me. We have the map. If we can hand him that information that he can plug in, then I'm OK with moving it. OK, great. What about you, Charlotte? What do you think? I don't think I have what you're talking about. Oh, OK. Well, I can send it to you right away. OK.
Yeah, basically, boy, I'm sorry. Yeah, I'll send that to you right after this meeting. It's pretty long, it's about 30 pages long. But basically, there's all kinds of sections that are actually specified in the Mass Historic Mission Guidelines. And of course, Chris Shelley himself probably wrote those, so he at least knows how to follow the guidelines.
And looking over the report, it looks like it follows the guidelines. Yeah, so I'll send out the latest draft, which, as I say, was from a few months ago, to you guys. Yeah, the one. I'm just trying to find it, Chris, for. It's let me let me have a look here.
LHD report. So is it this one? Let me share my screen if I can. Oh, sure. It's this version, the working draft from April. Yes, that's it. Okay. Yes. It hasn't changed since then. Okay, great. But I'd say it's about 90% there. Yeah.
So this, I think if we can just tighten it up and set it up. And Charlotte, if you could look at it, we talked about this at the last meeting. So I don't, I don't remember any comments that, you know, maybe jazz up the intro a little bit to add it. It's a little dry. I think we said it is pretty dry. The tone is maybe we can have Melanie. Melanie is a marketing person. Maybe she can,
punch up the tone a little bit, make it more rah-rah. Yeah. You can take some of the language we have in our trifold pamphlet if that helps. There you go. Yeah. That's all available to Melanie to do. Right. I want to submit this. Let's work on between the three of us and hopefully Melanie and Joe and Chris,
let's work on, let's just pass this back and forth with some revs, with of course Chris Kelly involved, and get this ready for submission in the middle of next month. Does that sound okay? Yeah, if we can get that, that's great. Okay. We're talking mid-July. Mid-July, correct. So basically, I'd like to have us agree on a
On, you know, a version, well, it's a preliminary report, so it's funny to talk about the final version, but that would be the version we're going to submit to the Historical Commission.
do you want us do you want each picture to have the history of the house? Is that what you're looking for? Oh, it's pretty long. It's okay. As you can see from this. Yeah, I want a brief description of every house. Okay, okay. I don't have the summary sheet and all the rest. All I have are the pictures. So that's online that I can pick it up. I'll mail it to you right after this meeting. All right. Thank you.
But I think does he go he gives all the information in here, you know, for each house, as far as I know. Yeah. But, you know, I mean, talk about look at six Manning Street notes, somewhat somewhat altered, blah, blah, blah. Boy, you know, we want something a little more interesting than that. Don't we? Well, I guess all that. Yeah, we could. It's just from the
the forms that have already been, the Form B that's already prepared for it. Maybe, I don't know if he includes all those in the end of this thing. I forget. He doesn't. He doesn't. I'd like to incorporate a summary of each Form B into the report. Yeah. All right. So maybe we could just do that. It's only whatever, 18 houses. Yeah. Some of them are more interesting than others, so I guess that's- Of course. Yeah.
Yeah. So yeah, I mean, look at the 114 South Street, that's fine, right? Yeah, yeah. And I just want the others to be like that instead of just saying, oh, you know, it's too bad about the vinyl siding.
Well, I'm happy to help with each one. Okay, can you do that, Fred? That'd be great. I'll have Chris send you over the, Chris Skelly send you over the word so you can modify it directly. Well, either that or, yeah, I could just send him a little blurb for word document. And then when you get that together, send it to me also. Yeah. Yes, and to you also, of course, Charlotte. Right. And let's see.
Yeah. We want to get that ready. Let's see if we can get this ready to go in the next, say, three weeks and have a version we can distribute to everybody on the commission, and then we can vote on it at our July meeting. Yeah, that's great. Say, yeah, this is what's going to the mass historical commission. Right.
And I think we need to have all the edits sort of done by Chris Skelly at that point. So he. Yes. Yes. The revision of this one. Right. Right. OK, let's try and get it in a final form in the next three weeks, say. OK. OK, the next step is if we're going to do a public hearing in
at our regular meeting in September. By the way, I took the liberty of booking the main chamber of City Hall for our regular meeting in September. Okay. We can postpone it if we have to or reschedule it, but I just wanted to put a stake in the ground for that.
Let me just check here. That is September 14th. I forgot what it's called, but it's the big auditorium in City Hall. Yeah, great. Okay.
That's for our public hearing of this thing. Correct. That's what I'd like to aim for. Yeah. Let's meet again in August. We also need to send out a mailing, at least to the owners, but I'm thinking we should probably send it out to a butters as well. Do you guys agree, Charlie? I would agree with that, yeah.
I mean, what is is what can I do to help get that out? Well, let's see. OK, so we need a letter. We should probably enclose the brochure that we've been working on. Yeah. And. The letter.
For the owners, the letter should probably be personalized. You live in the King house, which was built approximately blah, blah, blah. Here's a summary of the history of your house. We're considering putting this house in historic district and we'd like your input and there's a public hearing for that on September 14th.
Does that sound reasonable or is that too much work? Right. Chris, I'm looking at the sheet in front of me. It says 54 South Street, 60 South Street. I can take these addresses and look up the name of the people who own it so that we can send them a letter. That would be great. But Dennis and Teresa can do that too. All right. Okay. Right, Dennis? Yes. Yeah. If you just send us the info, we can get that. Okay.
But what you can possibly work on, Charlotte, is the actual... I would like a personal letter to each owner, you know, with maybe a paragraph of info specific to that property. Well, I'll let you guys do that. I'll take care of the mailing of it. Someone else can put it together and I'll try to take care of the mailing. No, no, Dennis and Teresa can take care of the mailing.
Yeah, so we want to make the mailing a big deal. We want to personal, we want to send out letters to all the abutters, and that's anybody within 300 feet of any house. So it's going to be a lot of, that has to be at least 100 properties.
And the ones that, in my opinion, the ones to the owners should be personalized. Right? We can. That's overkill, Fred. Not all the owners live in the property.
I know that. Right. I'm just worried it might be more work. I mean, if Melanie's not here, Joe's not here, Christian's not here. Okay. So maybe that's a little too ambitious. I'm happy to help, but I don't know. No, no. Yeah, yeah. Okay, let's skip that part. So we'll send out the same letter to the owners and the abutters. Does that make sense?
Yeah. If we have an opportunity to introduce a paragraph at the beginning that's personalized, then so be it. Great. But somebody is going to have to do that for the 18 properties, which is a bit of a work. Yeah. So I think you're right, Fred, that's going to be too much work. So why don't we just send out the same letter to everyone? Does that make sense?
Well, that would be more efficient and easier, certainly. And yeah, like likely to happen if we we have a hard time. Well, we we kind of a history of biting off more than we can chew. So, yeah. OK, yeah, let's do that. So I will ask Dennis and Teresa to put together a list of the not just the owners of the. Of the the 18 houses, but
everyone who lives within 300 feet of one of those houses. And I think that's pretty easy to do with the software you have at City Hall, right, Dennis? Yeah, it's pretty straightforward. If I just have the addresses, I just kind of, you basically add in all the addresses, the ones that you want, and then you just say, I want everybody from 300 feet, and it creates the list. Perfect. Yeah, yeah, I thought it could do that. Yeah. And Chris, we already have that list. It's been circulating around, I think,
share together. I'll just send it over to Dennis right after this. Well, maybe tomorrow at this point. Okay. Yeah. Then that letter should go out in mid-August. There has to be a gap of 60 days between the, sorry,
Okay, it has to happen for at least 14 days before the September meeting. So theoretically go out as late as the end of August, but let's aim for the middle of August. Yes, yeah. Because we don't want to screw up on the
on the, you know. Let's plan a week before that, make it the second week in August, just in case something holds us back, we have an extra week to work with. Sure. So if we plan on doing it the second week in August instead of the mid-August. Sure. Sounds great. Yeah, because we've got not less than 60 days from the study report transmittal to Mass Historic and with 14-day written notice to property owners. So I guess we've got to make sure we're
We're hitting these legal requirements for us. Right. No, I agree. Okay. There's a hard deadline of, let's see, 60 days. Let me think about this. Hold on. We have a hard deadline of probably, let's say, July 15th.
for sending the thing to Mass Historical, and that's right after our meeting. Let's just make sure that we do send it on July 14th. Great. If we can do that, then I think we'll meet all the- Then our hard deadline for August is not until
Well, as I say, the end of August, but Charlotte's absolutely right, we should aim for way before that, because that would be a catastrophe if we can't, well, not a catastrophe, but. We're gonna change all of our plans if we don't stick to those dates. Yeah, so let's not do that. Yeah, we don't wanna change, we've had enough changes of plan. Okay.
That is, we don't have a quorum, so we can't vote on anything, but do you guys agree that's a good plan going forward? Yeah, that's the only way we're going to hit this thing if we stick to that schedule. Okay, excellent. Okay, do you guys have anything else? No. We can wrap this up early. Yeah, and hopefully have better turnout at the next meeting. Yes, yes. All right.
Okay. All right. I'll see you guys. All right. Take care. Take care. Thank you for attending.