[SPEAKER_02]: So basically, Fred, are you happy with the contents of the brochure?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: The only thing my family suggested was creating a link.
[SPEAKER_05]: You know, when you take, I forget what it's called.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: A QR code.
[SPEAKER_05]: QR code.
[SPEAKER_05]: To create a QR code.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: But then we need to link that.
[SPEAKER_02]: to a web page, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Chris Donovan just wrote back.
[SPEAKER_05]: He says, I'm still under the weather with COVID.
[SPEAKER_05]: I have no energy.
[SPEAKER_05]: Unbelievable what he's going through.
[SPEAKER_05]: So he's still on the unable to perform list, I guess.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's see.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so let's, why don't we, obviously, I have to put together a webpage.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, we all do.
[SPEAKER_02]: There has to be a webpage relating to the proposed South Street historic district.
[SPEAKER_02]: I still have to get the new guidelines up on the website.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So the website is up, by the way.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's at least a step in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_05]: I did look at it, and yeah, it looks good.
[SPEAKER_05]: It would be nice if we were able to update.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's much, much easier than we do.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: So basically, all right.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I looked over the thing that Chris Skelly sent me actually more than a month ago.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dennis, is that you?
[SPEAKER_05]: No, that's me.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's Chris Donovan responding to my text.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So basically, I would like to shoot for a public hearing in September.
[SPEAKER_02]: That means we have to submit the report
[SPEAKER_02]: the preliminary report to the Mass Historical Commission by mid-July.
[SPEAKER_02]: How do people feel about that?
[SPEAKER_02]: How do you feel about that, Fred?
[SPEAKER_02]: You think that's good?
[SPEAKER_05]: I think the one that Chris Skelly sent us is fine.
[SPEAKER_05]: There was a lot of information needs to be plugged into that.
[SPEAKER_05]: He had a lot of placeholders for things.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it certainly seems acceptable to me.
[SPEAKER_05]: We have the map.
[SPEAKER_05]: If we can hand him that information that he can plug in, then I'm OK with moving it.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK, great.
[SPEAKER_02]: What about you, Charlotte?
[SPEAKER_02]: What do you think?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't think I have what you're talking about.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I can send it to you right away.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, basically, boy, I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I'll send that to you right after this meeting.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's pretty long, it's about 30 pages long.
[SPEAKER_02]: But basically, there's all kinds of sections that are actually specified in the Mass Historic Mission Guidelines.
[SPEAKER_02]: And of course, Chris Shelley himself probably wrote those, so he at least knows how to follow the guidelines.
[SPEAKER_02]: And looking over the report, it looks like it follows the guidelines.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so I'll send out the latest draft, which, as I say, was from a few months ago, to you guys.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, the one.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm just trying to find it, Chris, for.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's let me let me have a look here.
[SPEAKER_05]: LHD report.
[SPEAKER_05]: So is it this one?
[SPEAKER_05]: Let me share my screen if I can.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, sure.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's this version, the working draft from April.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, that's it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: It hasn't changed since then.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, great.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I'd say it's about 90% there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: So this, I think if we can just tighten it up and set it up.
[SPEAKER_05]: And Charlotte, if you could look at it, we talked about this at the last meeting.
[SPEAKER_05]: So I don't, I don't remember any comments that, you know, maybe jazz up the intro a little bit to add it.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's a little dry.
[SPEAKER_05]: I think we said it is pretty dry.
[SPEAKER_02]: The tone is maybe we can have Melanie.
[SPEAKER_02]: Melanie is a marketing person.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe she can,
[SPEAKER_02]: punch up the tone a little bit, make it more rah-rah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: You can take some of the language we have in our trifold pamphlet if that helps.
[SPEAKER_05]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's all available to Melanie to do.
[SPEAKER_05]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: I want to submit this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's work on between the three of us and hopefully Melanie and Joe and Chris,
[SPEAKER_02]: let's work on, let's just pass this back and forth with some revs, with of course Chris Kelly involved, and get this ready for submission in the middle of next month.
[SPEAKER_02]: Does that sound okay?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, if we can get that, that's great.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: We're talking mid-July.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mid-July, correct.
[SPEAKER_02]: So basically, I'd like to have us agree on a
[SPEAKER_02]: On, you know, a version, well, it's a preliminary report, so it's funny to talk about the final version, but that would be the version we're going to submit to the Historical Commission.
[SPEAKER_01]: do you want us do you want each picture to have the history of the house?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that what you're looking for?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, it's pretty long.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: As you can see from this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I want a brief description of every house.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't have the summary sheet and all the rest.
[SPEAKER_01]: All I have are the pictures.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's online that I can pick it up.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll mail it to you right after this meeting.
[SPEAKER_05]: All right.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_05]: But I think does he go he gives all the information in here, you know, for each house, as far as I know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, you know, I mean, talk about look at six Manning Street notes, somewhat somewhat altered, blah, blah, blah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Boy, you know, we want something a little more interesting than that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't we?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, I guess all that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, we could.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's just from the
[SPEAKER_05]: the forms that have already been, the Form B that's already prepared for it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Maybe, I don't know if he includes all those in the end of this thing.
[SPEAKER_05]: I forget.
[SPEAKER_03]: He doesn't.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'd like to incorporate a summary of each Form B into the report.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: All right.
[SPEAKER_05]: So maybe we could just do that.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's only whatever, 18 houses.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Some of them are more interesting than others, so I guess that's- Of course.
[SPEAKER_03]: So yeah, I mean, look at the 114 South Street, that's fine, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I just want the others to be like that instead of just saying, oh, you know, it's too bad about the vinyl siding.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, I'm happy to help with each one.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, can you do that, Fred?
[SPEAKER_03]: That'd be great.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll have Chris send you over the, Chris Skelly send you over the word so you can modify it directly.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, either that or, yeah, I could just send him a little blurb for word document.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then when you get that together, send it to me also.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, and to you also, of course, Charlotte.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: And let's see.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: We want to get that ready.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's see if we can get this ready to go in the next, say, three weeks and have a version we can distribute to everybody on the commission, and then we can vote on it at our July meeting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's great.
[SPEAKER_02]: Say, yeah, this is what's going to the mass historical commission.
[SPEAKER_05]: Right.
[SPEAKER_05]: And I think we need to have all the edits sort of done by Chris Skelly at that point.
[SPEAKER_05]: So he.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: The revision of this one.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK, let's try and get it in a final form in the next three weeks, say.
[SPEAKER_05]: OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK, the next step is if we're going to do a public hearing in
[SPEAKER_02]: at our regular meeting in September.
[SPEAKER_02]: By the way, I took the liberty of booking the main chamber of City Hall for our regular meeting in September.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: We can postpone it if we have to or reschedule it, but I just wanted to put a stake in the ground for that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Let me just check here.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is September 14th.
[SPEAKER_02]: I forgot what it's called, but it's the big auditorium in City Hall.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, great.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's for our public hearing of this thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I'd like to aim for.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's meet again in August.
[SPEAKER_02]: We also need to send out a mailing, at least to the owners, but I'm thinking we should probably send it out to a butters as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do you guys agree, Charlie?
[SPEAKER_02]: I would agree with that, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, what is is what can I do to help get that out?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, let's see.
[SPEAKER_04]: OK, so we need a letter.
[SPEAKER_02]: We should probably enclose the brochure that we've been working on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And.
[SPEAKER_02]: The letter.
[SPEAKER_02]: For the owners, the letter should probably be personalized.
[SPEAKER_02]: You live in the King house, which was built approximately blah, blah, blah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Here's a summary of the history of your house.
[SPEAKER_02]: We're considering putting this house in historic district and we'd like your input and there's a public hearing for that on September 14th.
[SPEAKER_02]: Does that sound reasonable or is that too much work?
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Chris, I'm looking at the sheet in front of me.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says 54 South Street, 60 South Street.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can take these addresses and look up the name of the people who own it so that we can send them a letter.
[SPEAKER_02]: That would be great.
[SPEAKER_02]: But Dennis and Teresa can do that too.
[SPEAKER_04]: All right.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right, Dennis?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you just send us the info, we can get that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what you can possibly work on, Charlotte, is the actual... I would like a personal letter to each owner, you know, with maybe a paragraph of info specific to that property.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I'll let you guys do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll take care of the mailing of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Someone else can put it together and I'll try to take care of the mailing.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, Dennis and Teresa can take care of the mailing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so we want to make the mailing a big deal.
[SPEAKER_02]: We want to personal, we want to send out letters to all the abutters, and that's anybody within 300 feet of any house.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it's going to be a lot of, that has to be at least 100 properties.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the ones that, in my opinion, the ones to the owners should be personalized.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right?
[SPEAKER_01]: We can.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's overkill, Fred.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not all the owners live in the property.
[SPEAKER_02]: I know that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Right.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm just worried it might be more work.
[SPEAKER_05]: I mean, if Melanie's not here, Joe's not here, Christian's not here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So maybe that's a little too ambitious.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm happy to help, but I don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, let's skip that part.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we'll send out the same letter to the owners and the abutters.
[SPEAKER_02]: Does that make sense?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: If we have an opportunity to introduce a paragraph at the beginning that's personalized, then so be it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Great.
[SPEAKER_05]: But somebody is going to have to do that for the 18 properties, which is a bit of a work.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I think you're right, Fred, that's going to be too much work.
[SPEAKER_02]: So why don't we just send out the same letter to everyone?
[SPEAKER_02]: Does that make sense?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, that would be more efficient and easier, certainly.
[SPEAKER_05]: And yeah, like likely to happen if we we have a hard time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, we we kind of a history of biting off more than we can chew.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK, yeah, let's do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I will ask Dennis and Teresa to put together a list of the not just the owners of the.
[SPEAKER_02]: Of the the 18 houses, but
[SPEAKER_02]: everyone who lives within 300 feet of one of those houses.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I think that's pretty easy to do with the software you have at City Hall, right, Dennis?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's pretty straightforward.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I just have the addresses, I just kind of, you basically add in all the addresses, the ones that you want, and then you just say, I want everybody from 300 feet, and it creates the list.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perfect.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, I thought it could do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: And Chris, we already have that list.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's been circulating around, I think,
[SPEAKER_02]: share together.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll just send it over to Dennis right after this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, maybe tomorrow at this point.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then that letter should go out in mid-August.
[SPEAKER_02]: There has to be a gap of 60 days between the, sorry,
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, it has to happen for at least 14 days before the September meeting.
[SPEAKER_02]: So theoretically go out as late as the end of August, but let's aim for the middle of August.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because we don't want to screw up on the
[SPEAKER_02]: on the, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's plan a week before that, make it the second week in August, just in case something holds us back, we have an extra week to work with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if we plan on doing it the second week in August instead of the mid-August.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sounds great.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, because we've got not less than 60 days from the study report transmittal to Mass Historic and with 14-day written notice to property owners.
[SPEAKER_05]: So I guess we've got to make sure we're
[SPEAKER_05]: We're hitting these legal requirements for us.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I agree.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a hard deadline of, let's see, 60 days.
[SPEAKER_04]: Let me think about this.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hold on.
[SPEAKER_04]: We have a hard deadline of probably, let's say, July 15th.
[SPEAKER_02]: for sending the thing to Mass Historical, and that's right after our meeting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's just make sure that we do send it on July 14th.
[SPEAKER_05]: Great.
[SPEAKER_02]: If we can do that, then I think we'll meet all the- Then our hard deadline for August is not until
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, as I say, the end of August, but Charlotte's absolutely right, we should aim for way before that, because that would be a catastrophe if we can't, well, not a catastrophe, but.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're gonna change all of our plans if we don't stick to those dates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so let's not do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, we don't wanna change, we've had enough changes of plan.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is, we don't have a quorum, so we can't vote on anything, but do you guys agree that's a good plan going forward?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, that's the only way we're going to hit this thing if we stick to that schedule.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, excellent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, do you guys have anything else?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: We can wrap this up early.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, and hopefully have better turnout at the next meeting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: All right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: All right.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll see you guys.
[SPEAKER_02]: Take care.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thank you for attending.