It's a limo out front. Hotter styles, every shoe, every color. Yeah, when you're famous, it can be kind of fun. It's really you, but no one ever discovers. Who would have thought that a girl like me would double as a superhero?
The answer to last week's question of the week is that I went up in a balloon in Australia in the outback. And that's a picture, and if you look carefully, you'll see me in the picture right here, all bundled up, because it was really cold. But it was fascinating. The Mustang Report question of the week is, how many concussions have I had?
I'm Victoria here with Mr. Pichelis from McGlynn Middle School, who teaches fifth grade. How are you today? Good, how are you doing? I'm good, thank you. So Mr. Pichelis did the Buzz Off for Cancer last year. Can you tell us a little bit about that? Yeah, so last year we did the Buzz Off for Kids with Cancer at Gillette Stadium. And the purpose of it is to raise money for cancer awareness for young kids. And last year was my first year participating in it.
It was a great event. Rob Gronkowski was there, the spokesperson for the entire organization. Yeah, it was a really fun event. I got to meet a lot of kids and hear a lot of stories. It kind of motivates you to raise money for them and be a part of it. So what is your motivation behind doing Buzz Off for Kids? Well, three years ago we had a student in our school, Himo Adadi, who unfortunately passed away of cancer. He's a third grader.
And over the last couple years, I really got to know his mom and his sisters. They've come to my camps. They go to our school. His youngest sister is currently in fifth grade. They're a good family, and they've been through a lot. I just want to do as much as I can for them. Sorry, my hair is pulling everywhere. So, it's this upcoming June 5th at Gillette, am I correct?
Yeah, so June 5th, coming up at Gillette Stadium will be like our second year participating in it. And we're really trying to spread the word out to the city and get the awareness out there of Team Medford. You know, not just Team McGlynn School, but really Team Medford and trying to get everybody in the city involved. So where can you go if you'd like to donate? So we've sent everything out on the Medford Facebook page. We've had the mayor's blog on it. We've gone to the city council meetings.
There is a link, there's flyers all over the city. If you go on, as I said, the city's Facebook page, there's a link for it that will say BuzzOff Team HEMO, and you click on that link and you can donate any amount of money you want.
We're also looking for people to buzz, you know, we have about six or seven people, some teachers, Mr. Richard from Effort High School, Mr. Cosmith from the Roberts fifth grade, Mr. McKenna from the McGlynn Middle School, so we have a lot of teachers participating and students this year who are coming out to be a part of the event as well. Thank you Mr. Portales, I'm looking forward to seeing how much money you raise. Alright, thanks for taking the time and talking to me. No problem.
Not necessarily glowing depictions, but oftentimes the complexities of their administrations will not necessarily be dealt with. The exhibits here have actually gotten better over the years. When this first opened in 1975, this was basically a shrine to Saint Jack. You have to keep in mind, too, he's murdered in 63. So at the moment he's murdered, he stops being a human being.
Right? And becomes what? A martyr?
So for Amendment 2, I think we can do a great deal of work to increase the amount of business that America does around the world. I'm a respected volunteer at the Republican Centers for both Texas and Arizona. And we're here to filibuster this absurd bill that will be an extreme detriment to our society.
National security I think is a point across the aisle where we can both agree. Both parties would agree. We need to keep this country safe. National security is very important. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye. Aye.
here we are now everything's about to change we face tomorrow as we say goodbye to yesterday
A chapter ending But the story's only just begun A page is turning for everyone So I'm moving on, letting go Holding on to tomorrow I've always got the memories While I'm finding out who I'm gonna be We might be apart But I hope you always know You'll be with me
with me wherever I go. It's time to show the world we've got something to say. A song to sing out loud. We'll never fade away. I know I'll miss you, but we'll meet again someday.
So I'm moving on, letting go, holding on to tomorrow. I've always got the memories while I'm finding out who I'm gonna be.