We welcome Principal Diane Gershow.
Ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and
gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen, ladies and gentlemen,
What are you doing?
Thank you.
always plug hashtag
You guys are going to go to the side.
All the way up to the side.
Okay, so this is the place where we're gonna rotate.
This is our spot right here.
It's awesome.
of the United States of America, and to the Republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all.
Now please stand and remove your hats for the playing of our national anthem.
you
Nice throw.
Let's go, Tesson!
Yeah, Tesson!
Go Reese!
Nice job guys, well done.
Well done, well done.
72, 72.
I'm everywhere.
It is.
Ready.