So we've had no votes, so I think it's distinction without a doubt.
Yes. Just to summarize, people who are recording, we had no action items on the first three items on the agenda. We briefly discussed Cross Street Cemetery and the support for future restoration work there, and we're currently discussing the archaeological presentation with Public Archaeological Laboratory that's going to happen this October to summarize the archaeological dig that took place at Thomas Brooks Park. Any other questions on the presentation?
Hearing none, just an update on the archaeological cap small grant. So we have to call it an archaeological cap we were calling it like a memorial, it can feature interpretive elements that would.
that would include that sort of thing, but we have to call it for the sake of CPC and archaeological cap, which is the protection to the archaeological resource that will be below. They did give us the money for that project, so we will be moving forward with Peter Hedlund as soon as the funding is all set up, which City Council had to approve it, which I don't know whether they did or didn't.
but I'm assuming that they did and Teresa said that if all goes according to plan should be set up sometime in the next week or two. So that will be good to get moving on that and that is just for the design of the cap that's going to go on and protect that and there'll be lots of public input once we have a preliminary design. Questions? Any new business that I missed?
All right, hearing none, I'll go to old business. Properties under demo delay. I don't have any update on 91 Winchester at this point. I don't think there's anything else under delay.
permit and subcommittee. Sorry, can we just, on Winchester, where do we leave things with her? She was going to reach out to CPC and try to get some CPC funding. So I don't know whether she put in for the determination of eligibility. I haven't heard back for the long grant yet, which is due at the end of the month. So I'm just going to go ahead and do it.
So I would love help if people want to help me do it. It's the same basic application, but longer. So maybe I can rodeo some people into helping me. Okay, great. Yeah, I'll help you, Ryan. Okay, I appreciate it. All right, maybe we'll take care of that next week then, because then we'll get that off of our plate.
Okay, great. Don't have anything on permit subcommittee update haven't heard yet if the city's hired a new head of the building department. I'm sure that's coming.
another new head of the building department? Yeah, the current building department head is going to become the head of the building department in Holbrook, which is much closer to where he lives. So we have lost somebody that was really helpful and really good. But I'm sure the next candidate will just be equally as helpful and equally as good. Only because this came up in the minutes and it was
Doug was going to talk with the Dyer building people about what happened to that marquee. I haven't heard any updates on that. I can tell you that they still have not sold all the units there. The developer is still the owner. Just as an FYI, they have not completed the project technically. There's still a few for sale.
We should we should be able to get to them. Yeah, and I think part of the nice letter from KP law that says that it's within reasonable, the building it's partners reasonable efforts to be able to stop a project from completion or final certificates.
is helpful because if they decide to say, hey, we don't want to do this marquee anymore because we're done with the project, then we can say, well, you promised this to get developers to, you know, if they show something on their drawings, they need to deliver on it because that's what we're voting on. You know, not just us, but all the boards. Well, I will say, Ryan, we should check in with the building department because I don't know if they've been issued their CEOs. I mean, they very well could already have them all.
Yeah. So we should check with them first. Sure. I would just shoot an email to Mike. It would just be good to know before we go to them. And I mean, I would hope they would still do it out of, you know, faith, good faith. Yeah. Okay, great. I can do that. Any other questions?
Notice that there's a Denise rotating on there. Is that one of our demo applicants? Yes, I think Denise was representing the property at 69 Court Street. I see a window for them, but they're muted. Oh, there they are. Oh, hi, Denise.
Denise you're muted, hold on, I'm gonna ask you to unmute. There you go. I haven't submitted everything yet. Okay, if you could get that to us as soon as possible, we'll act on it on the next meeting. Yeah, yeah, I was hoping to take care of it last week, and I know things have to be in on Mondays and the week before, and I just didn't get it taken care of, so. Okay. Which property are you associated with? 69 Court Street. Okay, thank you. Okay.
And you're the owner of that? Yes, I am. Okay. Thanks. Okay. Thanks. Yep.
All right, next up CLG annual paperwork, I'm working with Chris Bader to get the last of the paperwork, they have meeting minutes. Apparently they only reviewed two properties last year under their, their bylaw, so that seems a little low but I'm not going to question it. They had no meeting minutes for the meeting so they had to go back and reconstruct they have to approve them.
at next meeting, which I'm hoping to have. And then I just have some final tidying up to do with them. And then we'll have this one year's report done. And then we have to go back and do the following, the previous two fiscal years to come back into compliance with the feds. So this is for certified local government funding, which gives us 10% of the
federal money that comes to Massachusetts has to be passed the CLG community so that puts us in a small pool with a select other few we're almost guaranteed to get the money every year, so this is a very good thing would be very bad for us if we lost the certification. Okay. Thank you Ryan for helping with that.
Not a problem. I am gonna push them a little bit because some very bad things came to light about their meetings and I will be helping them take care of them. So this is a good thing that people are on their case now. So.
Okay, great. Walking port the comments that we put together were sent out and sent to mass historical I don't didn't hear anything from the housing authority I haven't seen the project notification form. I have no idea if we will or won't mass historical will usually issue comment. So, once they send it, so I'm going to assume that they'll move it right along.
They wanted to discuss the findings of the form a but I thought that kind of irrelevant at this point because we've, you know, our comments are different from where their focus is which is their focus is that they're.
harping on the fact that the buildings are outmoded and outdated. And that's, you know, our focus is on historic preservation of the fabric. They're two slightly different things. They collide, but they, you know, MHC is going to issue comments wherever they focus on the preservation aspect of it. And again, we, I think our comments are not asking them to preserve these buildings, we're asking them to just document them and be on their way.
For Thomas Brooks Park, I don't have any other formal update other than we're going to be working on the phase two application that's coming up. And then for survey projects, the consultants are currently working on a temporary side project with us. Mass Historical asked us to spend more money. We said, sure. And so that has gone out the door and we have to spend it by the end of September. So they'll have some product by the end of September.
So that's going right along, and Fulton Heights, they'll return back to Fulton Heights when that project's done. And that's it. So the only thing I have left is the approval of meeting minutes, unless people have any old business that I missed or questions. Approval of meeting? Quickest meeting on record. Yeah, yep. Did anybody have any questions on the meeting minutes?
If not, I'll take a motion to approve. Who said that? Did you say that, Ed? Yeah. And a second? A second. A motion. Kit Nichols second. Okay, I'll go around the room in the order that I see you. Kit? Sorry, yes. And Jen? I'm gonna abstain since I was not at the last meeting.
Okay, that's fine. And Peter? Yes. And Ed? Yes. And Ryan is a yes. So four to zero to one approved. So Ryan, just to be clear, because we had two meeting dates on the calendar for October in case we needed to vote because of the distance of time between
this meeting and since the next meeting would be after Columbus Day. We're not going to have a meeting on the 2nd, is that correct? Then we'll do our meeting on the 16th? Hold on, I'm just counting. Because we have two posted on our website, just FYI. Depends on when they come in. If they come in,
Uh, if they come in this week or next week, we may have to have the meeting because it's before the 30 days. Um, but if not, then any day after the, any day after next Monday puts us into the 30 day window for the, for the 17th, sorry, for the 16th of October.
Okay, so we just need to stay nimble until for another week? Yes. Yep. Okay. Fair warning, as I previously given the vice chairman, I don't expect to be at either October date. Okay. I appreciate you letting me know. Thank you. And I will be out of the country on the second. Okay. Okay.
All right, with the meeting minutes approved, that's it. I'll take a motion to adjourn unless anybody else has anything to discuss. Move to adjourn. Second. And second, non-debatable. Kit? Yes. And Jen? Yes. And Peter? Yes. And Ed? Time for bed. And Ryan? Yes. So approved 5-0.
Thank you all. Thanks everybody.