My buddy Dylan Zahn uses similar bags for his congas.
It's an old school technique of Army, Navy duffel bags.
It's a lot cheaper than proper cases.
Proper cases.
Hey, why don't you make it hot?
Give me the case there.
I'll take it to the gear dump.
Oh, I got it.
If you don't get done and we're ready to start, will there be time for us to make adjustments moving forward?
Yes, definitely.
I don't like to call it intermission because it puts the wrong idea in people's heads, but we do a little break.
He broadcasts on local television.
Wow, okay.
Yeah, that's why.
In the back there with the cameras and so forth.
No, he does it all.
Yeah, well that's his side of the network.
No, it's the guy that volunteers at the station.
That's right.
I like it.
I love it.
I'm editing it right now.
What's going on?
I'm coming to set this.
Oh, OK.
Are you a musician?
Yeah, I'm a guitarist.
That's great.
Drums, and Hillary, and saxophone, and polka.
So Owen is the box.
Hillary means a big box.