[SPEAKER_00]: My buddy Dylan Zahn uses similar bags for his congas.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an old school technique of Army, Navy duffel bags.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a lot cheaper than proper cases.
[SPEAKER_00]: Proper cases.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hey, why don't you make it hot?
[SPEAKER_00]: Give me the case there.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll take it to the gear dump.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I got it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't get done and we're ready to start, will there be time for us to make adjustments moving forward?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, definitely.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't like to call it intermission because it puts the wrong idea in people's heads, but we do a little break.
He broadcasts on local television.
Wow, okay.
Yeah, that's why.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the back there with the cameras and so forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, he does it all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, well that's his side of the network.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's the guy that volunteers at the station.
That's right.
I like it.
I love it.
I'm editing it right now.
What's going on?
I'm coming to set this.
Oh, OK.
Are you a musician?
Yeah, I'm a guitarist.
That's great.
[SPEAKER_00]: Drums, and Hillary, and saxophone, and polka.
[SPEAKER_00]: So Owen is the box.
Hillary means a big box.