[SPEAKER_12]: You wanna, let's kick off, it's 101.
[SPEAKER_02]: And more people are jumping on as well, so.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay, and the AC has been running all day today in the bank, I don't understand, but it finally just kicked off, so.
[SPEAKER_12]: All right, so let's jump in.
[SPEAKER_12]: I thank everyone for attending today.
[SPEAKER_12]: We're gonna do some housekeeping things before we jump into the actual meetings.
[SPEAKER_12]: The first item on the agenda is to approve the September 21st License Commission meeting minutes that Daria prepared.
[SPEAKER_12]: Daria, thank you for doing this.
[SPEAKER_12]: My only thing is, I think I had asked if it could be reflected in the minutes that I had tasked you to research
[SPEAKER_12]: what other communities are doing, whether they have any limitations or restrictions on restaurant bar stools.
[SPEAKER_12]: So I think we should get that into the minutes.
[SPEAKER_12]: So if council or the mayor's inquiring about whether we're doing our due diligence, it's reflected in the minutes.
[SPEAKER_12]: So if you don't mind, if you could add that in as number six, that would be great.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, we just had it on the minutes from the summertime, too.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's why I didn't add it in there.
[SPEAKER_12]: But yeah, it's an ongoing thing.
[SPEAKER_12]: I, like I said, I am concerned, especially if I'm
[SPEAKER_12]: The great American bear haul I think is that the name of the place that's supposed to be coming next year that's supposed to be breaking ground in the summer and, and that's going to be a giant undertaking a big place and, and like I said it looked like from looking at the plans that look like it was around 20,000 square feet.
[SPEAKER_12]: If I'm, if I'm doing the math right but.
[SPEAKER_12]: But it'll be a big place.
[SPEAKER_12]: And I know they're going to be concerned about our 25 maximum stools because that formula wouldn't work.
[SPEAKER_12]: But if you could look into it, and then the commission will take it under advisement and see if we can tweak or put some levels in there, that would be great.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I reached out to Malden and Summerville.
[SPEAKER_02]: I heard back from Malden, I believe, yesterday.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he's the person, uh, the liquor license commissioner secretary said that it's done through the building commissioner.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I'm reaching out to the building commissioner to find out that information summary will never go back to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I'll reach out to them again.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I'm working on it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just terrific.
[SPEAKER_02]: It takes time to get back to me.
[SPEAKER_12]: So, yeah, no, thank you for your help with that.
[SPEAKER_12]: I, um, you know, we should.
[SPEAKER_12]: You know, I don't know how old that other rule is, but I want to say it's probably at least 20 years old.
[SPEAKER_12]: So it might be time to tweak all that and get it into the 21st century.
[SPEAKER_12]: So Bob, Ben, any comments on the minutes?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, I just wasn't there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: I actually wasn't present at that.
[SPEAKER_12]: Oh, that's right.
[SPEAKER_12]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: Bob, anything?
[SPEAKER_11]: No, it looks fine to me, Alan.
[SPEAKER_11]: On that barstool issue, just quickly, I did have a chance to go online and I kind of glanced through some of those rules and regs, and I really didn't see anything on any limitations with barstools, to be honest with you.
[SPEAKER_11]: So, I mean, I might have missed it.
[SPEAKER_11]: I went through it pretty quick.
[SPEAKER_11]: They weren't anything with percentages or minimum or maximum stools.
[SPEAKER_11]: And then I think it's, like you said, the building commission has to basically say the size of the place and establish a seating capacity.
[SPEAKER_11]: So at that point, we could probably work with them.
[SPEAKER_11]: And I mean, well, it's something we'd have to discuss.
[SPEAKER_11]: I don't think it's a bad idea to have bar stools, especially in these larger places now.
[SPEAKER_11]: It's more people enjoy sitting at the bar than they do in a table.
[SPEAKER_11]: But I don't know if it's right, wrong.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, we'll figure it out.
[SPEAKER_12]: We'll figure it out.
[SPEAKER_12]: I just don't want to be doing something that all the other communities are doing.
[SPEAKER_12]: And then I have to hear, oh, you know, Medford Square should be a destination,
[SPEAKER_12]: like Arlington and Somerville, so you're right.
[SPEAKER_12]: We'll get to the bottom of it.
[SPEAKER_12]: We'll figure it out.
[SPEAKER_12]: We'll make the necessary changes that will benefit the community.
[SPEAKER_11]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_12]: Good, good.
[SPEAKER_12]: So you wanna make a motion since Ben wasn't at the last meeting, you wanna make a motion, please?
[SPEAKER_11]: Sure, I'll make a motion to accept the minutes of the September 21st License Commission meeting with the numbers item added to add in the minutes, the vast dual issue.
[SPEAKER_12]: Good, all right.
[SPEAKER_12]: I will second that motion.
[SPEAKER_12]: All in favor, say aye.
[SPEAKER_12]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: That's approved.
[SPEAKER_12]: Minutes are out of the way Daria.
[SPEAKER_12]: Alright, so I was looking at the agenda and I'm going to exercise Chairman's rights and I'm going to bat out of order a little bit.
[SPEAKER_12]: We had asked Mr. Carroll to attend our last month's meeting, and he wasn't able to make it.
[SPEAKER_12]: But I think I saw him.
[SPEAKER_12]: Did I see him?
[SPEAKER_12]: Did I hear?
[SPEAKER_12]: I think I heard Maury's voice.
[SPEAKER_12]: Maury, are you there?
[SPEAKER_12]: There you are.
[SPEAKER_12]: Oh yeah, I see it.
[SPEAKER_12]: I think I want to just jump down to item number seven that was on the agenda, and that's you, Mari.
[SPEAKER_12]: We asked you to come before us to give us an overview of what's happening with your restaurant, if you don't mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're on mute.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, there we go.
[SPEAKER_04]: Now I gotcha.
[SPEAKER_13]: Sorry about that.
[SPEAKER_12]: Terrific.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_12]: So as I said, if you could give us an overview of what's going on, what's happening.
[SPEAKER_12]: Tell us, tell us, Mari, what's happening.
[SPEAKER_13]: Right now we're kind of, we're just kind of stuck in limbo.
[SPEAKER_13]: We're trying to work out some things.
[SPEAKER_13]: It's got ongoing conversations with the property owner.
[SPEAKER_13]: I'm kind of like stepping back and we put together a new restaurant group with very familiar restaurant people within the city that would actually be taken over.
[SPEAKER_13]: So if it stays in fruition that we will stay there, we could call for a transfer of license to a new corporation as far as that goes.
[SPEAKER_13]: I don't see us renewing the license this year for that location under 21 Main Street Restaurant Group.
[SPEAKER_13]: I think it's going to be kind of defunct.
[SPEAKER_13]: We're going to just shut that down.
[SPEAKER_13]: probably go in a different direction.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: Well, thank you for that.
[SPEAKER_12]: It just, you know, the three of us live in the community and you hear all sorts of crazy things and you know, that's why I wanted you to, Hey, you know, come before us, just set us straight.
[SPEAKER_12]: So, you know, we can dispel all the rumors and everything that you hear.
[SPEAKER_12]: So I thank you for that.
[SPEAKER_13]: I've heard a long time and I don't know.
[SPEAKER_13]: You know how that goes.
[SPEAKER_13]: It's always been that way.
[SPEAKER_13]: And that's the way it is.
[SPEAKER_13]: But as far as I can tell you right now, we've put together a new operating group.
[SPEAKER_13]: Like I said, well-known restaurant people and people in the city, Kiwanians and restaurant people.
[SPEAKER_13]: And so we are going to do something in the city.
[SPEAKER_13]: There's no question about it.
[SPEAKER_13]: It's highly unlikely we're gonna do it back in that spot.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay, so you won't be renewing the license.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: And I thank you, had a lot of great meals at your restaurant.
[SPEAKER_12]: So I thank you for what you've done for the community and I hope you don't give up and you work something out with another group.
[SPEAKER_12]: So we look forward to seeing you pop up again somewhere in the community.
[SPEAKER_13]: Yeah, I feel real good about it.
[SPEAKER_13]: It's gonna be positive and it's gonna be good.
[SPEAKER_13]: But right now that's where I'm at.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay, cool.
[SPEAKER_12]: Well, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_12]: Like I said, I didn't want to, you were at the bottom of the order.
[SPEAKER_12]: You were in the seventh position.
[SPEAKER_12]: So I wanted to just hear you now and kick you loose.
[SPEAKER_12]: So thank you.
[SPEAKER_13]: Hey, I appreciate it, everyone.
[SPEAKER_12]: All right.
[SPEAKER_12]: Take care, Maury.
[SPEAKER_13]: All right.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_13]: Have a good day, Maury.
[SPEAKER_11]: Good luck in your new venture.
[SPEAKER_13]: Thanks, Bobby.
[SPEAKER_13]: See you, Ben.
[SPEAKER_12]: See you, Maury.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thanks, Maury.
[SPEAKER_12]: All right, let's jump to item number one on the agenda, which is a one-day license for the Medford Public Library.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's me.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Leilani.
[SPEAKER_12]: Hi, Leilani.
[SPEAKER_12]: How are you?
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you for coming on this afternoon.
[SPEAKER_12]: We really appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_12]: Tell us a little about the event.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so we are doing our annual meeting, I think, Barbara, I came last year Barbara has typically come as well to this meeting.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it is all of our members only members are allowed and we also invite staff, I believe it's 21 plus.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we are having Reggie, I forget, we're having a singing group.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so it's going to be singing.
[SPEAKER_01]: We'll have a meeting and then some singing and some music and dancing and just looking for beer and wine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It'll be some volunteers pouring beer and wine, essentially.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we're expecting about, I think our RSVPs went out or invitations went out last week.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're expecting that we typically get about 100.
[SPEAKER_01]: Um, and, but we'll see what happens over the next couple of weeks.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: Bob Ben, any questions, any concerns?
[SPEAKER_11]: Um, no, I don't have any, um, uh, well, on a, uh, everything the library's done has been great.
[SPEAKER_11]: Um, never had any issues there.
[SPEAKER_11]: You folks know the routine, so I don't see an issue with this at all.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Um, I don't have any concerns either.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, same thing as Bob said.
[SPEAKER_03]: Um,
[SPEAKER_03]: Is there insurance, Alan, just on file?
[SPEAKER_03]: How is that working out here?
[SPEAKER_07]: Barbara should have sent it in.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: We probably have one from the last time, but it wouldn't be hard to just keep updating them as we go along.
[SPEAKER_12]: I think it would be good practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's good for a year.
[SPEAKER_01]: Daria has it.
[SPEAKER_12]: Oh, and it's current.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's not from the last one.
[SPEAKER_12]: When was the last one, like back in May or June or something?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, Barbara sent me an updated one.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, terrific.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're good.
[SPEAKER_01]: We try to keep on top of it.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, great.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: All right, then.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, when he got one of my fellow commissioners says let's make a motion and get this one off the table.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I'll make a motion.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I'll make a motion to accept the event at the Met for public friends and met for public library annual meeting.
[SPEAKER_03]: on 11-5-2022 as laid out and explained by Lulani today.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: Bob, you want to second it?
[SPEAKER_12]: I'll second that motion, yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: All in favor, say aye.
[SPEAKER_12]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: Lulani, your one-day license has been approved for the date.
[SPEAKER_12]: I hope it's a success.
[SPEAKER_12]: I hope you have over 100 people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Have a good day.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bye-bye.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good, let's jump to the next one, item two.
[SPEAKER_12]: This is the event at Tufts, I believe.
[SPEAKER_12]: One day license at Tufts, so we have, who's representing?
[SPEAKER_08]: Hi, it's Heather West here from Tufts Catering, how are you?
[SPEAKER_12]: Hi Heather, very well and yourself?
[SPEAKER_08]: Good, good, good.
[SPEAKER_12]: So tell us a little about the event, yeah?
[SPEAKER_08]: It's through our Fletcher Graduate School, they host a cultural night
[SPEAKER_08]: They try to do this at least six times a year.
[SPEAKER_08]: This one is currently for the Asia night where we provide a cash bar and they actually work with local restaurants and provide the food.
[SPEAKER_08]: So it looks like they have a list of different locations.
[SPEAKER_08]: Most of them are Somerville restaurants, Cambridge restaurants.
[SPEAKER_08]: So again, we provide the bar.
[SPEAKER_08]: And we just got word that Fletcher Student Affairs is going to be hosting the soda and water.
[SPEAKER_08]: So the students, which they don't have to buy that.
[SPEAKER_08]: So they'll be drinking more sodas and waters because it's free.
[SPEAKER_08]: So the event runs from 7 to 11 PM.
[SPEAKER_08]: We close the bar, obviously, earlier than that.
[SPEAKER_08]: And it's at 51 Winthrop Street.
[SPEAKER_04]: OK.
[SPEAKER_12]: Is Eric still involved?
[SPEAKER_08]: Yes, he is.
[SPEAKER_08]: And he actually was going to be on this meeting, but we have an event starting at 3.
[SPEAKER_08]: So he passed the torch to me today.
[SPEAKER_08]: OK.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I don't have any questions because this is a, an event we used to see more, you know, more often in this event and we had no issues with this event.
[SPEAKER_03]: It was always done well.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then the same question is, I guess, just about insurance, Daria or Alan, do you know?
[SPEAKER_08]: I owe Daria the insurance.
[SPEAKER_08]: So I told her I'd have that by this afternoon and we just sent over our tax exempt form.
[SPEAKER_08]: So she has that, but.
[SPEAKER_08]: Again, you guys, we do need the insurance to today.
[SPEAKER_12]: And you'll have the minimum requirement for insurance correct.
[SPEAKER_12]: I think you guys usually have what a million 2 million for an aggregate policy.
[SPEAKER_08]: Eric sent it to me and you said it's a 2 million policy.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, yeah, that sounds right from the last time.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, no, pretty straightforward.
[SPEAKER_12]: Ben's right.
[SPEAKER_12]: I mean, all the events you've had there and there's been no brawls, nothing.
[SPEAKER_12]: They've all been very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: I remember those days.
[SPEAKER_12]: Bob, any questions or concerns on your part?
[SPEAKER_11]: Sure, I'm where I'm a little new to the game.
[SPEAKER_11]: But I'm an about it too tough.
[SPEAKER_11]: So I know toughs very well.
[SPEAKER_11]: My question, one of my questions is was 51 Winthrop Street.
[SPEAKER_11]: Is that the old Sacred Heart Church?
[SPEAKER_08]: Yes, they actually call it Breed Hall.
[SPEAKER_08]: But yes, it was the church.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_08]: Across the street from
[SPEAKER_11]: So this event is going to be held indoors, obviously.
[SPEAKER_08]: Indoors, yeah.
[SPEAKER_08]: And from my understanding of the event, they have the bar and the food, but it's actually almost a cultural show.
[SPEAKER_08]: So they'll have either dancers or some type of entertainment from the cultural center.
[SPEAKER_11]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_08]: You can stop by.
[SPEAKER_11]: And you had like 220 people there.
[SPEAKER_11]: I imagine Tufts University police are going to be detailed there.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Great.
[SPEAKER_11]: Everything looks great to me.
[SPEAKER_12]: Good question, Bob.
[SPEAKER_12]: I have a question.
[SPEAKER_12]: Did you say Reed Hall or Breed Hall?
[SPEAKER_08]: Breed Hall.
[SPEAKER_08]: B-R-E-E-D Hall.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: OK.
[SPEAKER_12]: All right, cool.
[SPEAKER_12]: Again, it's pretty straightforward.
[SPEAKER_12]: We're very comfortable with
[SPEAKER_12]: All your other events, we don't see any issues here.
[SPEAKER_12]: One of my fellow commissioners, if you'd like to make a motion, we can definitely take care of this one.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, I can make it if you like.
[SPEAKER_11]: Make a motion to grant the one day license on October 22nd at Breed Hall, 51 Winthrop Street for Tufts University with pending the copy of the insurance that Dari is waiting to receive.
[SPEAKER_12]: Ben, you want to second that?
[SPEAKER_12]: Second that.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: All in favor, aye.
[SPEAKER_12]: All right, very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: Your one day license carries.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_12]: Right, thank you.
[SPEAKER_12]: Hope it's a success.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: All right, take care.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Item three.
[SPEAKER_12]: The Neighborhood Produce LLC.
[SPEAKER_12]: Who do we have for that, Matt?
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: How are you, sir?
[SPEAKER_12]: I'm doing great, how are you?
[SPEAKER_12]: Good, good.
[SPEAKER_12]: I had to look up where, I'm like, where is 649, you know, I had to look it up.
[SPEAKER_12]: And I go, oh yes, that's the parking lot I used to park in when we'd go to Soundbites for breakfast, but now you can't get in there anymore.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's all blocked off, yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: So tell us about the event.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so,
[SPEAKER_00]: Neighborhood produce, I don't know if you're familiar, little grocery store in Somerville, we have first location very small store 450 square feet in Winter Hill.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then our second location in ball square actually sits on the Somerville Medford line, and it's our five year anniversary of opening up the first small store.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so we're having just a little kind of anniversary event customer appreciation type thing in the parking lot behind the store so it ends up being Medford where we used to park.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what it's going to be is some of our food vendors that we've worked with will have a tent.
[SPEAKER_00]: One of our longtime employees is also the manager of Remnant Brewing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so she had the idea of doing a cranberry beer for the event.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so we'll have that available for people as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: But mostly it's going to be a family friendly type thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what our customer base is largely, young families.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so we'll have a little photo booth area for people to kind of take photos in front of kind of like this fake cornfield thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And yeah, just kind of a way to say thank you to everybody for five great years.
[SPEAKER_12]: Nice, nice.
[SPEAKER_12]: You picked a great place because it's all walled in there.
[SPEAKER_12]: There's only one way to get in.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's off the street, off of Boston Ave.
[SPEAKER_12]: Everything else is buildings.
[SPEAKER_12]: So you picked a great, a nice area.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you for the diagram.
[SPEAKER_12]: This is something new.
[SPEAKER_12]: We always want a lay of the land, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_12]: So we thank you for doing that.
[SPEAKER_12]: And you have the insurance.
[SPEAKER_12]: We see a million dollar coverage.
[SPEAKER_12]: I don't know, Bob, Ben, any questions or concerns about this one day license request?
[SPEAKER_11]: I don't have any concerns or questions about it.
[SPEAKER_11]: I just have one quick question, Matt.
[SPEAKER_11]: I noticed on your address on the first page, you've got it as 7 Oakland Ave.
[SPEAKER_11]: and it doesn't say Medford or Somerville.
[SPEAKER_11]: I assumed it was Somerville because on the certificate of liability, it's 7 Oakland Street, Somerville.
[SPEAKER_11]: Is that the correct address just for our records?
[SPEAKER_00]: It should actually 7 Oakland Ave, Somerville.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so let me check with my insurance agent, make sure he didn't get it wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, just make sure they spelled it correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, there isn't seven Oakland Street in Somerville and so there's can make some confusion with that sometimes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, well that's, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So this is Oakland Street and Oakland have in some of them, there is yeah the Oakland streets over by.
[SPEAKER_00]: Union Square and then Oakland Avenue is in Winter Hill and Oakland Avenue is the right one.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's actually our home address me and my wife.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Somerville.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_11]: And I'll just scratch out on the insurance liability and make sure that it says have and you can square that away with your insurance people if you like.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, heaven forbid something happens and they go, oh, wait a minute, you know.
[SPEAKER_11]: They're going to be looking for you in Union Square.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: So for your own protection, Bob, nice catch.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_12]: I don't have any further questions.
[SPEAKER_12]: If you guys don't want to make a motion.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I'll make a motion.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was looking up where it is and now I'm sorry, now I know where this is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I'll make a motion to accept the one day license for the event for neighborhood produce and on November 5th, 2022 for Matt Gray to approve the event for the one day license.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'll second the motion.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: Um, uh, thank you for the motion.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you for the second, uh, all in favor to accept the one day license for 11.
[SPEAKER_12]: Five say aye.
[SPEAKER_12]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: Now your, uh, your one day license request has been approved.
[SPEAKER_12]: And, and like I said, just get that corrected.
[SPEAKER_12]: You never know.
[SPEAKER_12]: You never know, but, uh, uh, I hope it's a success.
[SPEAKER_12]: No rain.
[SPEAKER_12]: We'll cross our fingers, make sure there's no rain.
[SPEAKER_12]: So enjoy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_12]: Good luck with your event.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: Darian, number four is the city event at Wright's Pond.
[SPEAKER_12]: Was there an application completed?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, I sent it to you guys.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, you did?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like three hours ago, I believe.
[SPEAKER_12]: Oh, I didn't say it.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: I apologize.
[SPEAKER_12]: Bob, Ben, did you get a copy of it?
[SPEAKER_11]: I saw Daria sent it over.
[SPEAKER_11]: I just hadn't had a chance to print it.
[SPEAKER_11]: We can take a quick look at it right now.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm sure it's fine.
[SPEAKER_11]: It's where it's a city event.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_11]: It's not the market November 20th, is it?
[SPEAKER_11]: No, this was- No.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's going to be an event up at Rice Pond.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I know.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you also sent, Daria, you also sent that one at... Yes, it might be in the same email, yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why.
[SPEAKER_12]: Bob, can you see it on your screen?
[SPEAKER_12]: I can't get in.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'd have to get on my home email.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm not that technical, but I see it on my phone.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: It's a one-day license on 10-29-22, correct area?
[SPEAKER_11]: I don't have that.
[SPEAKER_11]: 300 plus and the mayor is the contact information.
[SPEAKER_11]: Kevin Bailey and Lisa Coliani, managers on record.
[SPEAKER_11]: It's for wine and malt.
[SPEAKER_11]: Registered nonprofit, yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Wrights Pond Elm Street, city-owned property.
[SPEAKER_11]: And Medford Brewing will be providing the alcohol.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yep, everything looks fine to me.
[SPEAKER_11]: Dean's concessions for food.
[SPEAKER_11]: And obviously the city is self-insured, I would imagine.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Nobody falls in the water.
[SPEAKER_12]: Cold water.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Hi, I'm Lisa.
[SPEAKER_12]: Hi, Lisa.
[SPEAKER_06]: How are you?
[SPEAKER_12]: Good.
[SPEAKER_06]: Good.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: Um, yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: So I work in the mayor's office.
[SPEAKER_06]: And yes, we are planning to get somebody to get a police detail.
[SPEAKER_06]: Originally, I had spoken with the chief about the street, but it's state
[SPEAKER_06]: road.
[SPEAKER_06]: So we're looking to have somebody in the parking lot near the, you know, near the beer and all that stuff.
[SPEAKER_06]: So it's the second time we've done this, but the first time we've had beer.
[SPEAKER_06]: So yeah, every time.
[SPEAKER_06]: Well, the last time we did it, it was it was great.
[SPEAKER_12]: So Lisa, you mean the the access road to Rights Pond?
[SPEAKER_12]: That's a state road?
[SPEAKER_12]: It is.
[SPEAKER_12]: Wow.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, Elm Street, Elm Street is.
[SPEAKER_12]: Oh, Elm Street.
[SPEAKER_12]: Oh, I thought you meant off Elm Street, the access road into the into Wrights Pond into the parking lot.
[SPEAKER_06]: No, you mean like the driveway?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: No, no, sorry.
[SPEAKER_06]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's, that's city.
[SPEAKER_03]: All right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Lisa, did you guys do it last time at this same time of year?
[SPEAKER_06]: We did.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes, we did not have a beer garden the last time.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's only the second time.
[SPEAKER_06]: Last year got rained out.
[SPEAKER_06]: But this is the first time doing a beer garden.
[SPEAKER_03]: We've been kind of asking for like a diagram of events.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is there anything that exists that is a diagram?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yes, can I share my screen by chance?
[SPEAKER_06]: And then I could also send you.
[SPEAKER_12]: That's Daria's host and I think she would have to.
[SPEAKER_06]: Sorry, Daria had asked me a couple of times for a diagram and I finally found something that I could share.
[SPEAKER_06]: Can you see that?
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, cool.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, awesome.
[SPEAKER_06]: So right where the purple box is, is where the beer garden would be.
[SPEAKER_06]: So behind that, and unfortunately I don't have a picture of that because it's not on Google Maps where I could actually pan around like on ground level, behind that is the bath house.
[SPEAKER_06]: And there's, you know, the restrooms are there, first aid is there, a deck is there, and all sorts of lighting is also there.
[SPEAKER_06]: We'll have the lightning tower from DPW in the general vicinity.
[SPEAKER_06]: And yeah, so that's, that's where it'll be.
[SPEAKER_06]: That's the proposal anyway.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_06]: And there will be no cars in the parking lot.
[SPEAKER_06]: We just pedestrians.
[SPEAKER_12]: How many Lisa last year, how many attended.
[SPEAKER_06]: Last year it rained, so we had to cancel it.
[SPEAKER_06]: But the year before, I don't know, we got snow that day, but I would say if I had to guess, there was probably like 150 or so.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, so we were planning on, you know, double.
[SPEAKER_06]: But actually I misspoke, there will be cars in this area, but the parking lot will be blocked off and I have to get with traffic on that to see where we should be blocking off.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: All right, so you plan on being closer to the snack bar as we used to call it?
[SPEAKER_12]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, I got you up on Google Earth, I can see it too.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: I still can't access it on my phone.
[SPEAKER_12]: The Wi-Fi stinks here, but I'm fine with this.
[SPEAKER_12]: Ben, Bob, any questions on it?
[SPEAKER_12]: No, I'm fine with it.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: We get a motion, we can take care of this one?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, it seems good, sir.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was just looking at this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: To me, the diagram is kind of, you have to like really know that area to know what you're looking at, because I don't really know what I'm looking at.
[SPEAKER_06]: Are you looking at the screen with the purple box?
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, so let me see if I could find,
[SPEAKER_06]: the drive up.
[SPEAKER_06]: I do have it on my computer.
[SPEAKER_06]: Let me just see if I could.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, it's a little off.
[SPEAKER_12]: Then where the crosswalk is, that's the way to the beach.
[SPEAKER_12]: You know where the lines are, that gets you access to the beach.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's the sand.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, to the left.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, the top left, that's the beach, yeah.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: That was a good one.
[SPEAKER_11]: Zoom out.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, there we go.
[SPEAKER_06]: Can you see it?
[SPEAKER_11]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, great.
[SPEAKER_06]: So right, can you see my cursor right here?
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, so this is where the purple box is right here.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, and so you'll have one police officer?
[SPEAKER_06]: We'll see what is recommended.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because I think for 300 people, it'd recommend more.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't know that though, but... Yeah, might be.
[SPEAKER_12]: Well, you'll adjust accordingly.
[SPEAKER_12]: I mean, I hope you have 300 people and you'll adjust.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, it's in everybody's best interest to make sure there's protection in there and... Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay, I don't have any questions then.
[SPEAKER_03]: Any other questions?
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, good.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's have a motion.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, I can do that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I'll make a motion to accept the one day license for the October 29th event run by the city of Medford and the mayor of Medford for the seasonal party.
[SPEAKER_11]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'll second the motion.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: Um, thank you for the motion and second, all in favor and accept the one day license to be held at rights pawn for their event.
[SPEAKER_12]: Say aye.
[SPEAKER_04]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_12]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: Your motion carries.
[SPEAKER_12]: I hope we'll cross our fingers again.
[SPEAKER_12]: No rain, no rain.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, no rain.
[SPEAKER_12]: No rain.
[SPEAKER_12]: All snow.
[SPEAKER_06]: All snow.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_06]: Great, thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_04]: I appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_04]: All right, very good.
[SPEAKER_06]: Calm down, please.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's from 6.30 to 9 on the 29.
[SPEAKER_04]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_06]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_06]: Bye-bye.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_12]: Item number five, application for amendment.
[SPEAKER_12]: Agent Officer Stock Ownership Interest, Ocean State Job Lot.
[SPEAKER_07]: That's me.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: Hello, Ms.
[SPEAKER_12]: Dennis, how are you?
[SPEAKER_07]: Good, how are you?
[SPEAKER_12]: As we read through the application,
[SPEAKER_12]: It appears that we're adding Mr. McGrath on as an LLC manager.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes, our previous LLC manager relocated to a warmer climate and is now remote and so cannot be the LLC manager for our Massachusetts stores and liquor licenses.
[SPEAKER_07]: So we are changing the LLC manager to Bob McGrath, who is located in
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: Is there anything else that we don't see?
[SPEAKER_12]: I thank you.
[SPEAKER_12]: I see the applicant statement, the entity vote, the Cori request form.
[SPEAKER_12]: You guys are very thorough as always.
[SPEAKER_12]: We appreciate that.
[SPEAKER_12]: I think that's it.
[SPEAKER_12]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_12]: That's the only change.
[SPEAKER_12]: Hey, I did have a question on item two.
[SPEAKER_12]: The second, where it has LLC manager, director, no.
[SPEAKER_12]: Is that all that area?
[SPEAKER_12]: Is that accurate that the continuation of item number two?
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: Let me just check this.
[SPEAKER_07]: So you're looking at item two.
[SPEAKER_07]: I just want to make sure I'm on the same page as you.
[SPEAKER_07]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's this proposed office of stock and ownership interest.
[SPEAKER_12]: That's item two.
[SPEAKER_12]: And then there's the continuation page to that.
[SPEAKER_12]: So I just wanted to make sure that that whole area is accurate.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes, it is.
[SPEAKER_12]: I'm just trying to make sure.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_12]: All right, good.
[SPEAKER_07]: That looks good.
[SPEAKER_12]: Ben, Bob, any questions on the adding of Mr. McGrath to the LLC as the manager?
[SPEAKER_11]: I don't have any.
[SPEAKER_11]: Questions with that, I do have a question though.
[SPEAKER_11]: I seem to be the address police today for some reason, I don't know why.
[SPEAKER_11]: On page two, Alan Aronow, name of, he's a principal LLC member, and he's got listed as 60 Frybrook Road.
[SPEAKER_11]: It doesn't give us city, state or zip.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm assuming it's somewhere in Rhode Island because all the other ones.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah, I see that.
[SPEAKER_11]: But my question is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_11]: The honors query request form, I looked it up.
[SPEAKER_11]: And it states he's 135 Laurel Wood Drive.
[SPEAKER_11]: But that query request form was back on May 24th of 22.
[SPEAKER_11]: And that's in East Greenwich, Rhode Island.
[SPEAKER_11]: So is that his correct address?
[SPEAKER_11]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_07]: I don't know that off the top of my head, to be honest with you.
[SPEAKER_07]: They're both East Greenwich addresses.
[SPEAKER_07]: I can definitely find out which one is the
[SPEAKER_07]: latest, but my feeling is it's the one that's on the Corey request, because it wouldn't have gone through if that was wrong.
[SPEAKER_07]: And I don't think that's true.
[SPEAKER_12]: It would have been kicked out.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah, it would have been kicked back.
[SPEAKER_07]: But I can clarify that for you.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, if you could, if you could just clarify that, and we'll get the correct address on there.
[SPEAKER_11]: Just God forbid, we ever have to get in touch with them.
[SPEAKER_07]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_11]: That's the only thing I found.
[SPEAKER_07]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: And when you're retired, you got nothing better to do.
[SPEAKER_12]: No, no, this is good.
[SPEAKER_11]: No, thank you for catching that.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, thank you for catching that.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: Ben, any concerns or questions on your part?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, I didn't have concerns.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, I went through it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It seemed like there was a lot of, you know, everything was in there, all the percentages of ownership.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like you said, Alan, pretty thorough.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I didn't have any questions.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: Well, let's make a motion so that they can keep moving forward with this.
[SPEAKER_11]: I can make the motion if you like.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_11]: I make a motion to approve the application for amendment change of offices, stock or ownership interest.
[SPEAKER_11]: Um, for the, um, ocean state job lot at 30 commercial street in Medford, um, with the.
[SPEAKER_11]: Correction of Alan Aaron knows address on page two.
[SPEAKER_11]: And I think that's it.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_11]: Cause we, we send this off to the ABCC.
[SPEAKER_11]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_11]: So we want to make sure we're sending them the right information.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: That all matches up.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: Daria, I've highlighted that section.
[SPEAKER_12]: You're probably doing the same thing.
[SPEAKER_12]: So, very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you for the motion and the second.
[SPEAKER_12]: All in favor of the application for amendment, change in officers or stock or ownership interest, say aye.
[SPEAKER_12]: I favor very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's been approved.
[SPEAKER_12]: Good luck, Miss Dennis.
[SPEAKER_12]: And yeah, if you could get to the, from what Commissioner Delfano is asking if we could get, we can get an accurate address.
[SPEAKER_12]: Nowadays, I don't know, you just get on and
[SPEAKER_12]: get on the internet and you can just find everything.
[SPEAKER_12]: I don't even know if that's good or bad.
[SPEAKER_12]: You get so much information now.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'll make sure to clarify and get the direction over to you.
[SPEAKER_12]: Please.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: Last item.
[SPEAKER_12]: Let's see.
[SPEAKER_12]: Smashburger.
[SPEAKER_12]: Elizabeth, is that you?
[SPEAKER_09]: No, I'm with Hasbro Brewing.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: Daria, who's representing?
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't think they're able to jump on today.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm online.
[SPEAKER_10]: Denise O'Brien.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good, Ms.
[SPEAKER_12]: O'Brien.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay, so if we're reading it correctly, it's an amendment or a change in manager.
[SPEAKER_12]: You're looking to
[SPEAKER_12]: put Ruben Silvestri as the new manager, correct?
[SPEAKER_10]: That is correct, yes.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: Tell us a little about this.
[SPEAKER_12]: Tell us, when was the last manager?
[SPEAKER_12]: How long was the last manager there?
[SPEAKER_12]: Just give us a little background as to what's happening and bring us up to date.
[SPEAKER_10]: Now, that is something that I am not familiar with.
[SPEAKER_10]: I just didn't want us to be a no-show.
[SPEAKER_10]: I tried, this was my error.
[SPEAKER_10]: I'm the licensing coordinator and I missed, I made an error and did not have the hearing.
[SPEAKER_10]: So if you guys want to table this and I can get the, I can get Ruben to show up the next time.
[SPEAKER_10]: He has a lot more information on when, you know, all the things changed.
[SPEAKER_12]: I see.
[SPEAKER_12]: And plus you could give us a little,
[SPEAKER_12]: I know I have part of his resume here, too.
[SPEAKER_12]: You know what, Mr. Bryan, I think that's a great idea.
[SPEAKER_12]: If you guys don't mind, we can table this and we can revisit it next month and we can ask what we need to know to approve the change in manager, if you don't mind.
[SPEAKER_10]: No, I don't.
[SPEAKER_10]: And I'll schedule it.
[SPEAKER_10]: And I apologize.
[SPEAKER_10]: I just didn't feel comfortable being a no-show.
[SPEAKER_10]: But it was my error in not letting him know that there was a hearing.
[SPEAKER_10]: So hold it against him.
[SPEAKER_10]: Hold it against me.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, no.
[SPEAKER_12]: No harm, no foul.
[SPEAKER_12]: We'll get you back on next month's agenda.
[SPEAKER_12]: No problem.
[SPEAKER_10]: Wonderful.
[SPEAKER_10]: I appreciate that.
[SPEAKER_12]: All right, cool.
[SPEAKER_12]: All right, thank you.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay, that's that one.
[SPEAKER_12]: Gary, what am I missing?
[SPEAKER_02]: There's just one more for farmers market.
[SPEAKER_12]: That's what I'm missing that that whole email.
[SPEAKER_12]: Bob Ben, were you able to hold that down?
[SPEAKER_11]: I did read the email and it said they were moving the whole farmers market to City Hall this week.
[SPEAKER_09]: Well, it's November.
[SPEAKER_09]: It's the November, it's the Thanksgiving market.
[SPEAKER_09]: It'll be in city hall.
[SPEAKER_09]: And we just needed an amendment to the permit you guys already approved for the season to change of time and location for that one day.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can I have a question, Daria?
[SPEAKER_03]: Did you send, cause I'm looking at the one day license for this, but it's, it's not,
[SPEAKER_03]: It is for the Wrights Pond seasonal party.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that email.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but they shouldn't be filling out a one day license application because they already have a special permit for yes to serve on the markers.
[SPEAKER_09]: Generally to pour by the glass.
[SPEAKER_09]: We're not looking at glass.
[SPEAKER_09]: We're looking at you to
[SPEAKER_09]: sell for off-premises sales.
[SPEAKER_09]: So it's just like all the other farmers markets, and this is already an approved date by you guys.
[SPEAKER_09]: It's on our special permit.
[SPEAKER_09]: However, our special permit doesn't show the date and time of this special market.
[SPEAKER_09]: It includes a date, but it doesn't say 12-4 and it doesn't say City Hall.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, that's the location and, and usually, you know, Elizabeth, when we do have one day requests, we always ask for a diagram, you know, show us, you know, where, where are you going to be positioned?
[SPEAKER_12]: Where are you going to be?
[SPEAKER_12]: You know, where's your table?
[SPEAKER_12]: So you're absolutely right.
[SPEAKER_12]: All we're doing is moving the venue to another location, but now that opens up, you know, the commissioner's requests and concerns about where you are in the city hall parking lot.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay, we've never done this, so I don't know how they generally do this.
[SPEAKER_09]: I'd be happy to get something from the market manager and send it along to you.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, it doesn't have to be an architect or an engineer.
[SPEAKER_12]: Just, you know, just show us where, you know, give us the lay of the land, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_09]: I can probably have that for you tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_09]: Is there any way we could get conditional approval for the amendment provided you get the diagram?
[SPEAKER_12]: I don't see why not.
[SPEAKER_12]: I mean, because we've already gone through the majority of our questions and concerns about the event.
[SPEAKER_12]: We just wanna see where you're parking in the lot there.
[SPEAKER_12]: So yeah, I think we could do something by proxy, sure.
[SPEAKER_09]: Great, terrific.
[SPEAKER_09]: I will reach out to Jane and Mike and see if they can send me a diagram and I'll email it along to Daria for you guys.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, Daria, is that okay with you?
[SPEAKER_11]: That's fine, yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: All right, cool area did send out the email to us at 1106 this morning.
[SPEAKER_11]: And it was for.
[SPEAKER_11]: Medford farmers market is having the market at the city hall on November 20th.
[SPEAKER_11]: And the house bearing LLC, who was already approved for farmers market.
[SPEAKER_11]: till that date is just looking to amend the location to, it says to be inside the city hall, but this is definitely outdoors, correct?
[SPEAKER_11]: I don't know, I've never- Oh, you're not sure, okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: And I think the time is 12 to four rather than three to seven, so- Okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, we were notified in the email about it, but- But there was no document in that email that pertained to this.
[SPEAKER_11]: There's no document.
[SPEAKER_11]: No, it's just the email.
[SPEAKER_11]: Yeah, it's just a narrative.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, there's we already filled out all the paperwork for the farmers market or approved for the special permit.
[SPEAKER_09]: And we fill out a one day permit.
[SPEAKER_09]: And we're like, I don't think this is the right thing because I'm pretty sure one day is for pouring by the glass.
[SPEAKER_09]: So we weren't sure what what you guys would need from us to make this happen.
[SPEAKER_09]: So okay.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah, the diagram.
[SPEAKER_12]: Jerry, I think with Elizabeth giving us a diagram and we can just kind of clip it to the original application and we can just make a note that there was a change in location.
[SPEAKER_12]: And I think that'll be fine.
[SPEAKER_12]: That'll all work.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: All right.
[SPEAKER_12]: So that's your homework assignment.
[SPEAKER_12]: One drawing, please.
[SPEAKER_09]: All right.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you so much, guys.
[SPEAKER_12]: OK.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_09]: All right.
[SPEAKER_09]: Bye-bye.
[SPEAKER_11]: Bye-bye.
[SPEAKER_11]: Do we have to put that in the form of a motion, Mr. Chairman?
[SPEAKER_11]: Oh, that's a good, you're right.
[SPEAKER_12]: What do you guys want to make a motion?
[SPEAKER_11]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'll make a motion to have the House Beer Brewing LLC from the Medford Farmers Market move their location for a permit already existing
[SPEAKER_11]: to Medford City Hall on November 20th.
[SPEAKER_09]: And change the time to 12 to four.
[SPEAKER_11]: I'm sorry?
[SPEAKER_09]: Change the time to 12 to four for that date.
[SPEAKER_11]: On the 12 to four, yeah.
[SPEAKER_11]: And yeah, per a sketch, drawing sketch of the location where it's going to be at City Hall, explaining whether it's interior, exterior, or where on the property.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: And then we can vote on it.
[SPEAKER_12]: We don't need to have a meeting.
[SPEAKER_12]: Derrick can send us out the information and then we can all vote.
[SPEAKER_12]: So we have an email record.
[SPEAKER_09]: Does anyone need to second that?
[SPEAKER_12]: Ben, you want to second that?
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, you can second that.
[SPEAKER_12]: I'm going to put her in the commission.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, Elizabeth, you're now in the commission.
[SPEAKER_12]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you for the motion.
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_12]: For the second, all in favor, say aye.
[SPEAKER_12]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_09]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_12]: So, Elizabeth, get that stuff to us so we can take care of it for you.
[SPEAKER_09]: Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_04]: All right.
[SPEAKER_04]: Bye-bye.
[SPEAKER_12]: So, Daria, I'll ask you again.
[SPEAKER_12]: Is that everything?
[SPEAKER_12]: Did we get everybody?
[SPEAKER_12]: Like I said, I can't get in my email, so I don't know what else is in there.
[SPEAKER_12]: That was it.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: Good, good.
[SPEAKER_12]: All right, so the very last one is any and all other business that may arise.
[SPEAKER_12]: Dari, on your mind, anything that we should be aware of?
[SPEAKER_02]: Not that I can think of, no.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: We made a note about Carol, so he won't be renewing his license.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay, that adds back.
[SPEAKER_12]: I had asked Daria how many all-alcohol licenses that we have, and I think it was 31, did you say, Daria?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, for all-alcohol, yes.
[SPEAKER_12]: And then malt and wine, there were five, I think, correct?
[SPEAKER_12]: Something around that ballpark, yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's interesting because people
[SPEAKER_12]: I'd be in the square and people would just kind of grab me and say, what's happening?
[SPEAKER_12]: And we need another restaurant in the square for the shows at Chevalier.
[SPEAKER_12]: And I agree.
[SPEAKER_12]: I agree.
[SPEAKER_12]: And what we don't want to see is anybody close.
[SPEAKER_12]: But it was interesting.
[SPEAKER_12]: Some of them said, well, if he closes, what happens to the licenses that go away?
[SPEAKER_12]: I'm like, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_12]: We have plenty of all alcohol licenses.
[SPEAKER_12]: So it's not like, I think people confuse it with the package licenses and they think, you know, oh my God, that's it.
[SPEAKER_12]: You know, we're out.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's like, no, it's nothing like that.
[SPEAKER_12]: So I hope
[SPEAKER_12]: Mr. Carroll bounces back in another location, that's something bigger and better and nicer.
[SPEAKER_12]: And then I hope someone looks at that spot and says, hey, I can do this with it and make a go of it.
[SPEAKER_12]: So it all helps the city in the long run.
[SPEAKER_11]: I have a quick question, Helen and Ben, and I'll probably answer it.
[SPEAKER_11]: All of you, where I'm fairly new, the reading that I've done
[SPEAKER_11]: As far as the license renewals, from what I've read, and I don't know if I'm understanding it properly, is all the establishments have the month of November to renew.
[SPEAKER_11]: And if there's like a November 30th deadline, if it's not in, then at that point they have to renew, they have to apply for a whole new license.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mm hmm.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Is that something that we're involved with?
[SPEAKER_11]: Do we review these?
[SPEAKER_02]: That is me.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it actually before November 30th?
[SPEAKER_03]: If they send it in after?
[SPEAKER_02]: Are we denying?
[SPEAKER_02]: They cannot send it in after so like, yeah, they have to.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I'll some of these I have to chase down but
[SPEAKER_02]: It specifically says on the paperwork that I sent out that it's due by November 30th.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you renew by November 30th, after November 30th, I'm sorry, it's going to be considered a brand new license and they're going to have to reapply.
[SPEAKER_11]: That's kind of the way I understood it and I didn't know if I understood it correctly, you know?
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah, the pressure's on.
[SPEAKER_12]: And for the life of me, other than Carol's, I can't think of anybody else that would not be renewing.
[SPEAKER_12]: Daria, have you heard anything or seen anything?
[SPEAKER_12]: I think it'll be the same except for Carol's.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that might be the only one.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I had three last year that closed down, but this year I think it's Carol's.
[SPEAKER_02]: I feel like there's one more, but I can't remember which one.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_12]: As you drive around the community, you just look and go, oh, yeah, oh, yeah, but okay, good, good, good.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: Um, if there's nothing else on the agenda, um, if we can have a motion to adjourn, that would be great.
[SPEAKER_12]: I appreciate all the help you guys have been doing and wrap it up.
[SPEAKER_03]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I appreciate it too.
[SPEAKER_03]: Um, I can make a motion to adjourn the, um, October 19th meeting for the Medford licensing commission, the
[SPEAKER_12]: Thank you, Ben.
[SPEAKER_03]: I second the motion.
[SPEAKER_12]: Good.
[SPEAKER_12]: OK, so all in favor, aye.
[SPEAKER_12]: Meeting adjourned.
[SPEAKER_12]: Daria, I can't believe a month has gone by so quickly.
[SPEAKER_12]: We'll see you again next month.