All right, welcome everybody to day three of the Medford Jazz Festival. For those of you I haven't, yeah, I know. It's amazing. It's flown by really quickly. We've had a lot of great music featuring students and professionals from around the area. Those of you I haven't met, my name is Jonathan Fagan. I'm a composer, educator, pianist, but I've been producing this for about five years now. And this year in particular, we've just had a lot of help. So a few thank yous before I turn it over to this amazing band.
First to the West Medford Community Center, historic space. We were showing some of the performers around inside earlier, and there's a lot there. There's a lot of history, a lot of amazing artists who have come from this place. So in between sets, I really hope you'll go inside, take advantage of the Danish Pastry House, who has set up headquarters there. I've been eating a lot of it, and everything just keeps getting better. It's amazing. So also to the Arts Alive Foundation, Medford Foundation.
They've really helped us financial support Morningside Music Studio, the Medford Arts Council, Triangle Manor. We've got some beautiful t-shirts up there with two of our volunteers who are also involved in eating Danish pastry house at the moment. And Berkeley's Institute of Jazz for Gender Justice, which is where this band is from. I heard them playing a little earlier. Sounded incredible.
Terry will tell you more about the history later, but it's a beautiful way of bringing that program full circle with where Terry Lynn Carrington, who's a legendary drummer from around here, really got her start, which was here. And her parents are still involved in this community. Thank you also to our Patreon members, who are folks just like you, put in a couple dollars a month. It helps us pay for things like jam sessions, for the actual festival itself.
Over the years, it's really added up in a meaningful way. So if you're looking to get involved, there are numerous QR codes that you can scan to find out more about that. Two, the people working the cameras, Medford Community Media, you all, you three have gone above and beyond. I was thinking at least one camera would be great, but now we have three. So it's really, it's great to get high quality video. This is also being live streamed for those who couldn't be here in person.
Lastly, to the Winchester Community Music School, to EXP Realty, and to Staples for our wonderful programs here. And thank you, of course, to our volunteers and staff, to Shayla, my partner, who's done basically everything, to Reese and Eva up there, the tables, and to Bruce, who's been also stepping in and doing just about everything.
Now I'll turn it over to Terry Carter, who manages many different things here at the Community Center. Also the former Poet Laureate of Medford, has written a lot of stuff. I know some of you saw him yesterday as part of our project, the Ally Project, but really couldn't do this without him. And he's going to tell you a little more about this band and about the space. I love that. That's cute.
So let me just take you through where we've been so far. So on Friday night, we started out with a student night. And it's very interesting because most of the students were of the older, more mature variety. And they're from Morningside Music School. And they put together two different bands. And they were fantastic, phenomenal, and quite delightful. And then Anita Wood came. Anita came.
from Medford, not originally from Medford, but grew up a good portion of her childhood here. And she brought her band, it was called A.J. and the Groove, and they were similarly wonderful. So that was night one. And then yesterday afternoon, we started out with Brazilian Flavor with Receita de Samba featuring Anna Borges and Bill Ward, and they were smoking hot.
And then, as Jonathan said, the Ally Project, featuring myself and Jonathan, Greg Toro, and great drummer Gordon Engelgau, we finished up. So today, we're into a new groove, and it's Berklee's Institute of Jazz and Gender Justice, under the leadership of Terry Lynn Carrington. And we have, from the Institute,
We have Jan Portish on bass. And he's got the big sexy today, all right? So that's the biggest bass you're gonna see this weekend. And we have Eugene Han on piano. Okay. My man in yellow here, Fall Ray on sax. Okay. And on drums, Ivana Cuesta.
Okay, and I just want to say a word about Ivana Cuesta, a feature of the group. She's a drummer, she's a composer, she's an educator from Santo Domingo, Dominican Republic, and she's known for her powerful artistry and ability to blend diverse musical traditions. You'll see all this. She holds degrees from Dominican Republic Music Conservatory and Berkeley College of Music, where she studied with well-known artists, including Neil Smith, the aforementioned Terry Lynn Carrington,
Francisco Mela and others. She's a compelling live performer. You're gonna see all this. And she is leading up a band that really, really smokes. So I'm gonna get out the way and let them do what they do. Welcome to day three of the Medford Jazz Festival at the historic West Medford Community Center. Ladies and gentlemen,
Ivana Cuesta and the Berklee Institute of Jazz for Gender Justice. Let them do their thing.
? ? ?
do do
? ? ? ?
do do do
do do
? ? ?
do
? ?
Great. Hey, guys. Thank you for having us. It's a pleasure for us to be here. This is an amazing place. It's my first time here, and maybe all of you, right? First time? Yeah. So thank you so much for the invitation.
Like Terri said before, my name is Ivana Cuesta, and I'm part of the Justice Institute, led by Terri Lee Carrington. And the music that we want to breathe today is music composed by women, but also non-binary people. So what we want to try to do is
just bring something that sometimes is not well recognized, I would say, in the music industry. So that's why, yeah, we just choose really nice tunes. But also from some, actually from some of our professors.
So the first tune that we play, it's called Chaos. It's one of my tunes that I wrote, I think, two years ago. And it's in my album, Alert to the Earth. So you maybe had the sense it was a little bit chaotic, and really loud, and really noisy. But that was how I actually felt.
the pandemic ends. So I think everyone probably wrote a music, a song or something after pandemic because it was really something that affect all of us. So the next tune that we're gonna be playing is Kowtow by Caroline Davis. I hope you enjoy it.
uh uh
uh
Music .
do do do
do do
do
you
the bass drum.
the bass.
do do
do
you
do do
the bass.
the neck.
do do
So...
the bass.
So, again, thank you very much.
the bass drum.
the bass.
I'm going to play it.
you
the bass.
do
you
Bye!
Okay, so we're gonna do one more.
Yeah, okay, perfect. Well, so the last one that we're gonna do is called Smoking Gun, and it's by a saxophone player, like I said, Diane Stevens. And I just wanna say thank you so much, everyone. I wanna say thanks to the organizers, thanks to Jonathan, Abby, Terry, and everyone, actually, for having us. It's a pleasure, and I hope we can come back
Another year. Thank you, guys.
? ? ? ?
? ? ?
? ?
This is why you have engineers, because that's regular people. We don't know where the heck we are on stage. In any case, ladies and gentlemen, Berklee's Institute of Jazz and Gender Justice, featuring Ivana Cuesta on bass, Jan Portisch on the keyboards, Yujin Han, and on the saxophone, big and little, Fall Ray.
All right. It has indeed been a pleasure to hear y'all play. You're wonderful. We got to send a thank you note to Terry Lynn for releasing y'all to come over and hang out with us for an afternoon. And we wish you continuing success in your studies and your teaching and all of the different things that you're doing right now. It's an amazing honor.
My dance spirit is alive and cheerful And where does the heavy sound roll? Where does the party roll and the girls dance? Where do the people get together and celebrate? From Bim Bam and Onyop, where is it heard?
Why don't you come with me tonight Where the rhythm is unchanged And the spirit of the dance is still alive
Yeah.
? ? ?
? ? ? ?
Ž Ž
? ?
do
? ? ? ?
♪
? ?
? ? ? ?
Music.
Bye.
? ?
? ? ?
do
you
A little bass, definitely.
Thank you.
Every once in a while, it'd be a nice.
Yeah. Yeah.
do it
Try to sing. Say it again.
do
Bye!
you
I'm kidding. I'm kidding. I'm kidding.
Bye!
♪
Okay. Sarah, how many are in love currently? Oh, how many? Oh, how many? Oh, oh, okay. How many are still searching for it? To the point where my Lord is always quivering. Claire, how are you?
I'm done. Please forgive me. I'm not even emotionally real.
The wind is high up today.
do do
We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are. We are
A thought of reminiscing. And I'll never forget you. And I'll never forget you. And I'll never forget you.
you
So,
It's the best time for me when I have musicians and calling out tunes and we all know them.
You just now figured it out, lady!
Music playing
Nobody knows that song, right? Nobody knew that song before I met you here. Okay, so do me a favor and don't ever go back and actually listen to what the song was like. You're gonna be like, she didn't do it the way Donna did it. Because I will have ruined it for you for every correct version because that was some scum.
♪ I must find a way ♪ ♪ And I have found the only way for me ♪ ♪ I don't believe in threatening grief ♪ ♪ What I mess around with is fright ♪
Bye!
♪♪ ♪♪
I pray for everyone here today and all the people who are listening in the atmosphere to have a simple today and a simple tomorrow and hopefully a simple week coming up. Whatever is stressing you, whatever is complicating your spirit and got it all twisted up,
Listen to Joe.
do do
the next one.
you
He just made that up. And I took his lead because I followed him wherever he goes. Anybody smell pollen?
Did I mention that I write? Okay, so forgive us, we're going to subject you to a couple of my songs, alright? I promise, you won't die. And there will be no polling.
do
you
do do do do do do do do do do do do do
A rabbit, 60 mile an hour winds. No raging fire to put out. Just a smoldering ember within. No drawn out recitation. Just three little words to say. Just your smile. No dozen roses, box of candles.
couldn't eat that anyway. No drawn out recitation, only three little words to say. No weeping or wailing or fainting in the aisles. Just your smile. Just your smile. I didn't need a moon or the glow. Hear trumpets, choirs, or strings.
♪ That it'd be too soon to know anyway ♪ ♪ Who answers when that bell rings ♪ ♪ Yet I knew when I looked into your eyes ♪ ♪ My lonely days were through ♪ ♪ And all the fireworks and rockets in the world ♪ ♪ Couldn't make it any more true that no bells ♪ ♪ Could warn me of my pending fall, no clue ♪
That this would be the sweetest dream of all. No heartfelt invitation. RSVP'd in grand style. No abstract complication. No 14-day vacation. I'm going to live my days on just your smile. You got me loving, loving, loving.
Just three little words to say. Marry me, baby. Love is forever. What's for dinner?
♪ And take away the joy of your smile ♪ ♪ Just your smile ♪ ♪ Just your smile ♪ ♪ Just your smile ♪ That was nice. That was so much fun. He said, I liked it, Dad. He said, I liked it, Dad.
Okay. Now, he said he didn't like it a little lot. He liked it a lot lot. A real, real, real big lot. God bless you. I'll get your number at the end of the show. You can sign up for my follow along, tag along behind me group. Oh, it's called a fan club. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I forgot. Here's another one.
Now get ready, because you're going to be inspired. But I don't think there's any tissues. So just hold it. Hold it until you get home. OK? I've got a tissue up here for me.
This is called Why Can't We Live Together. I wrote it back in the days of the assault on Rodney King. They did the interview with him and he asked, why can't we just get along? And right after that, this song came on my heart. And now, how many years ago was that?
A lot of years, so this song has been really 30 years, 34 years. So this song is still living and it's still reasonable to plead with the heavens and to plead with everyone around you. ♪ I have a dream ♪
fills my sleeping and my waking hours. It's a dream of us together, learning to live with each other, settling all our strife. We've got to see there's so much we can do to change calamity, just us two.
♪ Starts with me and you, so let's get started ♪ ♪ Healing the brokenhearted, walk up to every brother ♪ ♪ Asking each other, why can't we live together ♪ ♪ Give me what I'm due, and I'll give it back to you ♪ ♪ Why can't we live together ♪
You know I'm gonna reach for you when things go wrong, to keep me strong in stormy weather. So tell me. This cruel, cruel world is all we got, so let's make the best of it.
It's compassion that we need. Then we'll have a one world nation built on cooperation. It won't hurt to help me. So can you tell me, why can't we live together? Give me what I'm doing, I'll give it back to you. Amen. Why can't we live together?
I know I'm gonna reach for you when things go wrong, to keep me strong in stormy weather. So tell me why, what a joy it is to live, all the goodness we could give.
In one accord, in harmony, no ill feeling set the wheels in motion. It's more than a notion. Let's take a stand in the caring hand.
You know I have to reach for you when things go wrong. So why can't we live together? You know I'm going to reach for you when things go wrong. I know why. You'll look around. You'll want me there.
You want me in your prayer. So why? Why? Why we gotta argue and fight? Argue and fight every day and every night. Why, why, why, why, why, why, why, why, why, why, why? Oh, why? Why can't we live together?
♪ Why we can't get along together ♪ ♪ Together, you and me, all together now ♪ Can I get a amen, hey! Why can't we? Why can't we?
That always gets me very emotional. Oh, don't do that, George. Okay, back to life, back to reality.
Where are we now? What town is this? This West Medford Mass. We in the backyard of what church? West Medford Community Center. A lot of history here. A lot of joy, a lot of tears.
90 years work and we are still banging, banging, banging, burning, burning, burning. And the wheels kept turning. What you say is we'll still be learning.
La, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la,
I said, baby. Oh, oh.
♪ Stormy Monday, that's what they call it ♪ ♪ But Tuesday's just as bad ♪ ♪ They call it stormy Monday, y'all ♪ ♪ But Tuesday's just as bad ♪ ♪ Wednesday's worse ♪ ♪ And Thursday's oh so bad here ♪ ♪ They say that the eagle flies on Friday ♪ ♪ And Saturday I go out to play ♪
They say that the eagle flies on Friday, and Saturday I go out to play. Sunday I'm in church, and this is what I'll say. Father God, we come to you now, bound in your Holy Spirit, bowed down on our knees and praying for mercy.
Mercy. Mercy, please. Mercy, please. Yeah.
This is your chance, last chance to join in, so snap!
That was George Russell. Did anybody need to hear that? George Russell. George W. Russell Jr. Okay, I think everybody should get some, since he took a big old chunk of the cake.
Take your time, take your time. Set it up, set it up baby, set it up.
Oh my God, oh my God, oh my God. Sean Farias.
I'm on Paris.
♪ La la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la la
They call it Stormy Monday. But you know Tuesday's just as bad. They call it Stormy Monday.
But baby, Tuesday's just as bad. And they tell me Wednesday's just as bad, just as bad. And Thursday's oh, so sad. They say that the eagle flies on Friday. Saturday, I go out to play. The eagle flies on Friday. Saturday, I go out to play. And then Sunday.
I go to church. I get down on my knees. I cry, Lord. In my heart, I cry, Lord. In my soul, I'm asking you, Lord. For my mommy in heaven, I'll be saying, Lord.
My sister and my brother and my father and my family, up there with you, Jesus. Up there with the angels. I cry, Lord, have mercy. I cry, Lord, have mercy. I cry, Lord, have mercy. Have mercy.
I cry, Lord, have mercy, have mercy on me. Yeah! Yeah! Yeah! Yeah! Hallelujah! Thank you so much. Thank you so much. Thank you so much. God bless you all. Thank you.
Thank you. Yes. Unless you want an encore. Hey, so listen. Would anyone like an encore? All right, OK, all right. We're going to have them do one more track, then we'll come back and say our goodbyes and thank yous. But you've been a wonderful audience, so sit tight for just five minutes more. Should it be gospel?
Okay. Acapella. Look at me.
I'm as helpless as a kitten up a tree. You can join in if you want to. And I feel like I'm clinging to a cloud. I can't understand. I get misty just holding your hand. Should I move up a half step or a down step? Walk my way.
And a thousand violins begin to play. And it might be the sound of your hello. The music I hear gets me misty the moment you're near.
You can say that you're leading me on. But it's just what I want you, I want you to do. Don't you notice how hopelessly I'm lost?
♪ That's why I'm following you, baby ♪ ♪ You better believe me ♪ ♪ On my own ♪ ♪ Must I wander through this wonderland alone ♪ ♪ Never knowing my right foot from my left ♪
My hat from my glove. I'm too misty and too much in love. I'm so misty and too much in.
God bless you all. See you next time. Have a great rest of the day. Thank you so much. Ladies and gentlemen, one more time for the inimitable Donna McElroy.
All right. On the keys, the equally inestimable George W. Russell Jr. Those of us who have known him for a long, long time can call him G-Dub. Don't get twisted. All right. Big man, big bass, big sexy, Sean Farias. And you know you got to give the drummer some, it's Sean Skeet.
All right, you heard it here live and in living color at the West Medford Community Center. I'm Terry Codd. I've been your genial host. I'm going to bring my main man, Jonathan Fagan. He's going to do thanks and acknowledgments. You've been a lovely audience, and we've enjoyed you just as much as you've enjoyed us. Thanks again, everyone. Oh, there we go.
Thanks again so much to the West Medford Community Center for hosting us all weekend, especially to our MC, Master of Ceremonies, Terry Carter over here. To the Danish Pastry House over here, elevated the event to another level. Please go in and grab something on your way out. Thank you to our volunteers and our staff, to Shayla, to Reese, Eva, all the folks working sound and video over there, Medford Community Media.
And thank you most of all to our musicians, this wonderful band. I think we're going to all leave here inspired and moved. So thank you so much for coming and just, you know, blessing us with your talents. So stay tuned for more from the Medford Jazz Festival. If you feel inspired to, drop a couple dollars in the donation box or scan a QR code on your way out and sign up for our email list if you'd like to know what we're up to. We hope to keep many things going throughout the year.
So, all right, have a great afternoon.