Hello, everybody, today is Wednesday, March 27th, and this is the March meeting for the Commission of Persons with Disabilities. Commissioners, would you like to go around and introduce yourself? Sure, yeah, I can take the lead on that. My name is Linda Braden, I'm the vice chair of the commission, and I've been on the commission for the past
two to three years. I'm a resident of Medford and I guess my specialty and contribution to the group largely is for digital accessibility. So I will pass, I'll popcorn it over to Sue Bibbins, Susan Bibbins. Hi, I'm Susan Bibbins. I am
My pronouns are she, her, hers, and I'm a resident of Medford, have been on the commission for
I don't know how long, but it's been so long that I've forgotten how long I've been on the commission, but it's a long time. I've been chair and vice chair formally, and so that's been my experience. And I live in South Medford. Thank you.
I'm Sue Falafan and I live in on the Medford Malden line up in the Heights area, I guess. I think I'm getting close to a year and a half, if not two years. And that's about it, I guess. Commissioner Nabb and
I work at Mass General Brigham. I've been a commissioner for three months. And I'm going to move over to Joe. Hi, I'm Joe Casey, lifelong resident of Medford. I live up in the Heights, North Medford. And Medford's been a good city to me. And I'm just here to help, to see what I can do to make it a better place.
I love it. I love what you said. Right. So I think the next, the first thing on the item on our agenda is actually before we dive into the agenda, is anyone able to take notes in Gabby's absence or does anyone have any? Yeah, I guess that's the first question.
Is anyone able to take notes? Linda, I'm taking very brief notes. I can help support with very brief notes. Okay, awesome. Thank you, Frances. So moving on to the first item on the agenda, the motion to approve the February 2024 meeting notes. And I actually have a question about this.
Do we need to, Francis, this might be a question for you, or you can let me know who I need to ask. Do we need to provide the Medford Senior Center clarification on our request before we approve the meeting minutes so that that can be captured in the meeting minutes, or do we want to provide the clarification in the March meeting minutes? Does that make sense?
I'm not sure if Francis or let's go ahead and approve the minutes for February. Yeah. And then any clarification can be put on March notes. Has everyone had a chance to read the minutes? I read them and I approve.
All right, can we get a vote to approve the minute? Oh, go ahead, Frances. It looks like Sue approved and Susie approved and Sue seconded. Am I getting this right? Yeah. I guess we need to put it to a vote. All in favor? Aye. Great. Looks like it passes unanimously. So that would mean that there were no nays and no abstentions. Great.
We can move right along. OK, so the next thing on the agenda is the Medford High School Building Committee update from Commissioner Knabb. Take it away.
Yes, awesome. I wanted to let the commission know that Medford High School applied and received the grant to start a phase one new building plan. And they're looking for members to sit on the building committee. There was a discussion about having someone with connection to the disability commission.
And separately in my day job, I focus on health care. And there's lots of opportunities that schools have to embed health care services directly on campus. And I would really like, if I'm selected to be on the high school building committee, I would want to channel
this commission's input into the process and then also try to help think about what school health care services, mental health, and other supports would be necessary for the new high school to be as inclusive as we can make it for all residents. So just wanted to keep the commission informed and
Hopefully I can circle back with news of some appointments and we can go from there. Commissioner Knapp, quick question please. Did you already apply to be on the committee?
Yeah, there was a deadline and it was last Friday. Yes, yesterday. Commissioners, I don't know how you feel, but again, this is one of those things where as members of the Disability Commission representing the City of Medford, it is important that when there are opportunities like this, someone is at the table.
There are many other aspects that don't necessarily get seen because as the ADA coordinator, I have to review plans. I have to be on the ground. I have to respond when people are saying, like, we can't park in our accessible spots because there's a car that's always there.
So I think that this is critical. None of us are individually responsible for the state of the high school at the time that the high school was built. It was up to par. It was one of those top-notch buildings.
well, it's like, what, five, six decades later. So having the ability to really inform on what is truly accessible, I think it's going to be huge. And I think it's going to be great. And any way that, you know, I urge the commission to support Commissioner Knapp's
I guess, application on behalf of the Disability Commission, and you don't have to do this, but even if you're so inclined as to just write a simple note that says, we the commissioners of the Disability Commission support the nomination of Commissioner Knapp to represent the Disability Commission at the table. This is huge.
And then on another note, I'll just plug. Can I ask Cameron something? Yes, please. Am I allowed to ask Cameron something? It depends. If it has to do with the high school update, yes. If not, I would probably wait. It does have to do with the high school. Yes, then go ahead. So Cameron, are you thinking about, and are they thinking about, because I've read about it a lot,
Are they thinking about a totally new site? Are they talking about demolishing the old high school and then having an alternate site and then rebuilding on that same site? Do you know what
I don't. I think we can figure out. I'm under the impression, Sue, that this is just started based on the city's receipt of the grant. And so I don't know how far the planning has gone or if there are sort of leanings one way or another about a new site. But I can report back if I get selected and can channel that information, I'd be happy to.
Because I'm very interested in all that. I taught in public schools forever. I have a lot of whatever about demolition, about renovation, blah, blah, blah. And when you're talking about a high school built in 1950 versus now, it's a totally different, totally different.
That's all I'm saying. Well, if you want to, as the Disability Commission, again, just a suggestion, not a must-do, if you feel comfortable, if you want to send a note to support Commission Announce application, I think that that's a great idea. I obviously on my end will be supporting it because soon you will be happy to know that
I might, we might finally have all the accessible spots out of the parking lot and in the front loop at the high school in April during April holiday.
Again, barring Mother Nature's cooperation, of course. This is something that we've been working on for a long time. We remain challenged fiscally and in other ways.
I have had all the necessary meetings and there's a final meeting that will be happening. I think it's next Wednesday and. We does have the machines. To do the paint work, so I'm hoping that.
The weather will be nice during April vacation, and that front view will be strictly for accessible parking and 1 of the spots will be dedicated to purple hot veteran parking. Right. Wonderful. So.
Somebody talk to Mother Nature. Oh, Sue, do you have your hand up? Sorry, sorry. Yeah. Commissioner Ognab, I just wanted to say that I have, I had,
two kids that went to the high school and I've been working with Francis on getting the high school, particularly the high school, up to physical accessibility.
We've been working on a lot of physical accessibility, sort of minimum standards. So if you want to collaborate or ask me questions or pick my brain, I'm available for that. I'm all over that. And I also work with the
I know a lot about universal design standards and stuff like that. So if you want to ever pick my brain, I'm available for that. Perfect.
I might throw the idea out to add this as an agenda item in a future month's meeting so that we could do a collective brainstorm. And I'm happy to do some one-off interviews to pick folks' direct lived experience and, you know, the knowledge that we each have.
So, you know, it would be great to do sort of a joint brainstorm to get all of the ideas and then I could work with each of you to flesh them out one-on-one. I also wanted to make a motion to write a letter to support CAM to the, write a letter to the housing, no,
What was it again? Building committee something, something. We'll find, we'll find the right. Building committee and development committee in support of CAM's appointment to the Medford school, high school redevelopment. Right. Commission.
Susan, were you making that motion for you to write the letter? As a commission, we would write and send a letter.
As a commission, I don't necessarily write letters well. So I'm looking for any assistance.
Francis do we need to have that in the motion when when Susan just made that motion, we couldn't remember the formal name of the building. No, I'm sorry, Francis, but I was asking is do we need to have the person who's going to write the letter who starts the letter, like, who's actually we can.
We can, I mean, Susan has made the motion. If somebody seconds the motion, I can just speak on some, share some simple language that you can use. It's really a statement. It should be something like along the lines of we members of the Disability Commission stand behind Commissioner Knapp's application to the blah, blah, blah on our behalf. It's really what it is.
Okay, so I have to figure that out now. Okay. Yeah, I could. While she, while she continue with the meeting, I'm listening. I could put something in the chat, which, which sometimes it's easy when I type it out, it makes better sense. And then you can all agree to okay, that statement sounds.
good or doesn't sound good. But someone needs to second Sue's motion. Okay. I'll second it. Okay. So Sue and Susie. Yeah. Then all in favor, say aye or raise your hand. Aye. Okay. Aye. Great. Looks like it's passed unanimously. So there's no nays and there's no abstentions. Perfect.
Anything else on that topic that we want to cover before we move on? I don't want to cut it short if there's more to discuss. I'm going to go on mute so that I can type in the chat to flush out the idea, and then I'll just raise my hand when I'm ready to read the statement if you're all in agreement. Great. Does that sound good to everyone? Yeah. Great. The next thing on the agenda is the ADA Municipal Grant.
This goes back to an email that was sent to us about an opportunity to apply for funding. Let me see if I can find the note. It was passed on, awarded from Tom, then from
Of course, I'm having trouble finding it now. Sorry, Linda, you're looking for the MOD? Yeah. Let me see if I can pull that up for you. I remember it was a, I thought I flagged it. Confirmation, no, that's not it.
Municipal. I've got it up for you. Yes, fabulous. So we got notice of this municipal ADA improvement grant grant application. I think this was all forwarded via email and. Let me see if I can.
For instance, it looks like we're seeing just a slice of, oh, perfect. Yeah. So the application information, it looks like the application is going to be open from May 1st. And any town in Massachusetts, any city or town in Massachusetts is eligible to apply. So this would be money that we could apply for improving the items here, like in programmatic access or removing barriers encountered by persons with disabilities.
Um, you know, in, in any of the city facilities. So, if you scroll down a little bit more. Yes, we've got a project there's opportunities for a project grant or a planning grant.
And so with these descriptions here, we wanted to discuss with the commission to see if there's anything that we want to actually apply for the grant to use the money towards improving anything for accessibility. So the project grant.
Sounds like it's like a one-time project and then a planning grant sounds like it's something to set the wheels in motion for something. Go ahead, Frances. I wanted to let you know that the city did apply for this grant last year and the city did not. Okay.
Sorry, I got distracted for a minute. The city was not an award recipient of the grant. The other thing that also happened is I believe the school side applied for this grant as well. So coincidentally, I was speaking with the assistant principal, assistant superintendent of the school.
And I think that it is best that the city of the O2, when I say the city, I mean O2155, one application and one application only comes from O2155. So it shouldn't be the commission for persons with disabilities because you're not a fiduciary. It shouldn't be the school and then the city. It should just be one application.
I was speaking with our traffic engineer because you know as soon as there are some issues at the school.
that I would really love to be able to address, such as the need for curb cuts that could run anywhere from $4,000 per curb cut, depending on how many of them you do, to $13,000
ran per cup cut if you only doing a few. The school certainly needs and when I say the school and speaking more about the high school now, certainly needs real accessible curb cuts, especially if we are starting to come into, Sue, would you say baseline compliance? Yep.
I'm reading your lips because you're on mute. Are you talking to me? No, I'm talking to Sue. Your minimum compliance. I'm talking to Sue. Yeah, yeah. So we're coming into like that sort of baseline compliance by making sure that the accessible spots are in the proper area.
There is also the issue with City Hall, you know.
a very, very public space where last year it was 100,000, the facility director and I applied for, you know, it was just very simple. We posted it out. We just needed $100,000 to start with updating wayfinding. What is wayfinding? It is signage. It is accessible, universal compliance signage.
You know, yes, the fancy styles that we have at the very top of certain offices are nice, but those are not compliant. But we didn't get that. So, you know, I'm throwing these ideas.
Out there traffic engineer says that, you know, he feels that the curb cuts have a bigger. Bang, and that should probably be the direction that we should go and then we should try to. No more figure it out elsewhere.
I don't know. Francis, what did we apply for last? What was the item or what was the project that was applied for last year? It was wayfinding. Wayfinding, okay. But inside the city hall building. I think the school tried to address some accessible things as well, but it was two separate applications. Okay. Then if we, as a commission, I guess that's a question the commission that we should discuss, as a commission,
do we support like the curb applying, using the, applying for the grant to use the fund for curb cuts for, and Frances, you were saying this specifically for the high school, is that right? I think the curb cuts for the high school are, you know, from the time that I have been on, I just, I can't. Yeah, and that's for the current high school, right? Right now it is, you know,
whatever we can do right now with the high school, because remember, right, our students, it's not just our students that go there. That space is used for people who are going to see shows, people who are going to events, people who are going to pick up their children, people who, you know, people coming from other towns.
Well, if you're taking public transportation and the bus drops you off, good luck figuring how you're going to get up. Yeah. Literally. Yeah. I mean, that to me sounds like a great application. I have very little experience with grant applications, but it sounds like very discreet, very specific, very much like this is how much
It'll cost, it's for something beginning and an end, it's definitely going to make a difference. Do we need to make a motion or something as a commission to support that? Commission can support it. The way the MOD grant applications work, their application is within their system.
Right so it's not something that you print out and then you have to write, you just go in the system and you put it in. So, last year, Paul, the facilities director for the city site did the application and I was a supporter. I do, I think that the commission can support it. I would have to look back at some of.
I will all the information soon to see if there is additional stuff from our universal access meetings. That I could.
On there, or we could just keep it at as curb cuts and check in. With engineering and see what other areas. Need curb cuts in the city. Personally, I would prefer I would prefer areas that open up increased access.
Right? So don't put a, I don't live in Medford, but don't put a curb cut by my house in Medford, right? Put a curb cut, let's say, to make it easier for somebody to get from one side of the Fellsway to the next. Just making that up as an example. Yeah. I mean, that makes sense. So is there anything we need to do as a commission to move that forward or support it or anything we need to do as a commission?
I think that if the commission chose to support, they give the commission felt that curb cuts focusing on the current school. And then expanding out should be the priority. I would suggest that emotion be made. And this, you know, a.
a motion be seconded and then a roll call vote be taken because this is all very, very new. Because as I think about it, if we can just think about the amount of dignity that it restores, if we can just chip away at things, not saying that it's going to be done overnight, let's just keep chipping away. I'm happy to make a motion.
to support a grant up the M.O.D. grant application to be made for curb cuts at the high school and other places around the like public places around the city. Did I cover all the bases Frances? Yes, yes.
Is there a second? Great. And then, Francis, that reminds me of the roll call vote. Do we have to, is that meaning that like we go around and name each person? Yes. Okay, great. So then that would mean that I'll just, I'm happy to facilitate that. So I'll go around and say, Joe, how do you vote? Yay, nay, or abstain? Yay. And Susie, how do you vote? Yay, nay, or abstain? Yay.
Okay. Thank you. Cam. How do you. Yay. Awesome. So we have unanimous passing of that motion. And then anything else we want to discuss on that before we move on,
No, that is it. I will let Assistant Superintendent Cushing know of my meeting. Oh, and I see him tomorrow. And I'll let the facilities director know. I don't know, maybe there's something we can do differently this time to make sure that the wealth flows to us. But I just, I feel like this,
This would really help. I mean, yeah. Great, then the next thing on the agenda is an item I put on was resources to put on the web page from this is carrying over from. Last meeting when Gabby was talking about writing up a list of.
resources add to our web page and she did that. She sent it to me. I wanted to run it by the rest of the members of the commission to see if there are any additional resources that other folks know of that we want to add to this list. And it might be helpful for us to have our
Would you do need to share it? Yeah, I think that would be helpful. I was also going to just put the link to our page as it currently is so folks have a reference for what it looks like and where we would be putting these resources. So I'll put the link. To our current page in the chat. And on that page.
We have a section called Additional Links, and a section that says Useful Links. And the Useful Links break it out into government agencies, financial, different categories, which
We might be able to find another name other than useful links, like maybe resources or something like that. But that's for another day. This is where the additional links or the useful links section is where we're talking about adding the links that Gabby sent along. And I will share my screen.
Okay. Share. I'm going to share this one. Okay. So, um, Gabby sent. A, um, Google doc, we're working on Google doc, uh, together. And so I wanted to share this with the commission to see what their thoughts was. As far as what's here and to see if there's anything folks would want to add.
The Medford Special Education Advisory Council, Medford Council on Aging, the Senior Center, Medford Recreation, Mystic Valley Elder Services, Medford Planning Development Sustainability, Medford Park Linktree, Medford Library and a link to sign up for their digital newsletter, some city alert sign up. We've got the Office of Planning and Development Sustainability newsletter sign up.
Community Preservation Act newsletter sign up, city newsletter sign up, some Facebook, like a Facebook page, the Medford, Massachusetts Facebook page, the Go Green Medford link, also potentially like a link to the Instagram and the Facebook for Go Green Medford, Medford Family Network newsletter sign up, city recreation programs,
And like the comprehensive plan, got some other plans listed out here. And it looks like we've got Medford Parks Link tree down here again. I just wanted to read them out so folks could could hear what's on there. Any other resources that folks that come to folks minds at this point in time, this is not the only time you ever can add resources, but I thought this would just be a good time.
to make sure that we're collecting whatever's on top of mind for folks. Yeah, Suzy, see your hand. So I'm thinking that there is, I do a lot of links to transportation for disability. And I don't see any of them on there, but I would have to look them up, like tomorrow. Yeah. Because there's some two or three big links about transportation for disability.
disabled. Not only in our community, I know that one of these here has a link. It's up higher. I don't have it in front of me. But they're either in our city or outside our city. So I really want to get that on there. Okay, yeah, if you send them to me, I'd be happy to add them to the running list. Okay.
And then, Cam, can I see your hand up? Thanks, Linda. One link that we might consider
putting under health care would just be linked to MassHealth. And the state has an integrated eligibility system. So when you apply to MassHealth, if you qualify for other social services, it'll let you know. And so getting health care, MassHealth, and that integrated eligibility system, I think, would be a really key resource.
Great, yeah, do you have the URL for it or? Yep, I'll bring it to you. OK, perfect yeah and I can add that on there. That would be got a lot of miscellaneous. One other thing that would be really great. We've done that. I think we've did this last year just as a yearly cleanup. If folks could take a look at the resources that are on here and
decide, like, decide if you think that they're still relevant. Disability Law Center is a really good center.
Yeah, I didn't mean you had to look at it right now. There's some things that I'll need Gabby's feedback on, so we'll move this on to the next meeting as well. But by next meeting, folks could take a look at this and see if there's anything that doesn't quite fit anymore, bring their suggestions to add resources, or if you want to email me in the interim.
I'm happy to collect them. Francis, is there a motion I need to make in order to continue working on this?
If you want to continue working on it, I think that it would suffice to say that we should just say we'll continue working on it. I mean, this is definitely a work in progress. Remember also that the individual pages of the website are set up a specific way. There is only so much
way that we have with redesign and things of that nature. I can't remember the exact words. We still have a lot of cleanup that needs to be done. This is a mess that was inherited. We just have to take our time and go through each step. I would say simplify and make things easier.
Yep. You know, additional links, useful links. What's the difference? Resources are resources, and maybe we should just call them resources and list them alphabetically. Yeah. Right? I mean, I don't know. Yeah, we can definitely. I 100% agree with that, and I'm happy to come up with some suggestions about how to reorganize everything from additional links on down on the page for accessibility and usability.
I think it's, you know, I think it's one of those things that shows up maybe on the agenda next month as a continuous work in progress. Yeah, that would be great. Yeah. All right, I'm going to stop sharing my screen. And then let me see what the next item is on the agenda.
Car Park, Shanine, looks like, was she supposed to be? Yeah, go ahead, Frances. I was under the impression that she was going to spend 15 minutes at each meeting, 15 to 20 minutes just discussing
car park updates unless that has wrapped up so i've just consistently left her on the agenda okay um but i do have i do have the right if you would like me to read edge sure i i'm okay with that if others are okay with it
All right. We, the members of the Medford Commission for Persons with Disabilities, write to support the application of Commissioner Cameron Knabb for the blank, blank, blank. And the blank, blank is because I can't remember that long name of what they called it. So if you like that, I will put that in the chat.
Yeah, that's good to me. Anyone has opened the floor to anyone else who has thoughts or ideas? Great, it's a go. Okay, and I will list the names of all of you that are on here. I will make sure I share this.
with all of you. Nobody please respond because if you do, even just simply saying, oh, that's good. This is great. I'm excited about this. Just from last month's open meeting law training, we could just innocently find ourselves in all kinds of situations. And then I will make sure that this gets in the hands of
the selection committee, because it has to be whoever's doing the selecting. And do you think that it would be helpful to get this to the school committee as well? Yeah, okay. I'll make sure it gets to the selection committee and the school committee as well. And I will definitely find out the correct name. It was called something.
I was muted, sorry. I was just saying thank you for doing that, Frances. Oh, you're welcome. All right, so the next thing on the agenda is ablewell.org. The question is, well, there was correspondence shared with the commissioners on March 23rd, 2024. Are the commissioners interested in inviting Mary Wilson to an upcoming meeting to share more, provide clarification?
Did everyone get a chance to read that email that Francis sent? Yep. Great. Then do we have like a million windows open? Do we want to discuss anything about that? How do we feel about that? Would we want to have Mary Wilson come talk to an update? I do. I'm for it. Yeah?
I just shared it because I'm not familiar with who Mary Wilson is. The request actually went to the clerk's office, and it seems like Mary wanted to write an article to put it on the webpage for the Commission for Persons with Disabilities.
So that came in as I saw some of the agenda items. So I thought, I think that maybe this is really an opportunity to ask more clarifying questions.
you know, and to find out if there is a true connection, because I see the Disability Commission's webpage as a resource webpage, right? But if there is an article of importance or if somebody says that, you know, my passion is writing articles that focus on the different disabilities that are highlighted during the month throughout the year, very, very different.
from just random articles. I don't know what style of article, you know? And of course, I would welcome to if, you know, if Mary was a person with a disability, yes, I would, you know, welcome her to write something for the disability page because of that lived experience. But I felt like the commissioners really need to like,
think this through and maybe hear what Mary has to say. Yeah. Do we need a motion to invite Mary?
I think the question was from me, right? Yeah, correspondence shared. Yeah, I think the question was from me to the commission. So you can simply state, I can simply, you know, take it that commissioners, because I saw some commissioners nodding, and Joe, you said yes. Invite Mary, also no, or do roll call vote.
On the fence. You're on the fence. Yeah, I don't know. I think on the one hand, it could be valuable on the on the other. She could. Require compensation. Or ask for compensation.
and she could or she could espouse theories or beliefs or values that are counter to our our values and um and she could just
You know, she's out of the blue. I've never heard of her. I've never read an article by her. And I'm on the fence. I think we have other things that might take up our time.
I definitely understand what you're saying, Sue. I mean, usually when I get requests, they come directly to me, right? My name is listed on the website, right? It's fully transparent. So this came through the clerk's office. In addition, I did go to the able.org website. It was very light.
I'm not sure what I, I mean, I felt like when I went there, I had an open mind, but I still found it very light. I was unable to get there. My computer, my tablet kept expressing an error message. Okay. Yeah.
So, yeah, the the able well dot org link in at the bottom of the email actually goes to an email as an email.
yeah but then you have you know then yeah copy paste it yeah i just i am okay with it being a no right this is just one of those things i mean as far as this compensation that would never happen i mean we don't accept solicitation right right you know but i i clearly understand you know
I clearly understand what you're saying, Susie. I didn't come running to you guys fully excited. Like, hey, guess what? I just came across it. It was just cause for hesitation. Yeah. I can see why you brought it up, but I can also see why it's very vague. Yeah. I don't know. What are you thinking, Linda and Susie? Would there be a way we could, would it be helpful if we
wrote back and asked if they require compensation before we invite them. Even if they require compensation, it would never happen. We don't solicit yet. That's what I was thinking, is that if they require compensation, then we know it's an automatic no. Yeah. I wouldn't even want to engage in the conversation if it's that. I just feel that the outreach came from an interesting avenue.
Right. That's why I was thinking if we reached out and said, do you, would this- I don't even have the bandwidth to engage. Yeah. There's something about the website. I don't know if it's the website. I don't know what it is. There's just something that isn't-
That might not be worth even having them like the time to have them come to our meeting to discuss what people do.
in my email, right? There are people in my email that reach out to me and I haven't responded to them because sometimes it's very simple. It's like a new, you know, online degree, higher education, you know, online education or something. So that's very simple, right? I can take that information, send it over to comms, have them put it in the resource link.
They come directly to me. This person didn't come to me. This person went through the clerk's office. What is their connection to the city clerk? Is this a phishing email? I have no idea. I just know, I don't wanna engage in any back and forth correspondence unless it's a, please come to the next commission meeting on such and such day so that you can share more. They're not even here today and our meetings are posted.
Mm hmm. Mm hmm. You know, and I do like what what you know, I would like to write an article on for your site. What are you writing on? I don't know. Yeah, would this be so my question the next question for the commission would be would able well the website, which I can, I now have pulled up I can put a link to in the chat. Would it be something that.
We would want to list as a resource on our website. My line of thinking here is that if it's not even something we would want to list on our website as a resource and there's probably no reason to pursue it further. Like, if we're not willing to be like, oh, this is a.
Yeah, I don't, this is Cam. I don't know much about it, but one thought is, you know, we could just, one of us, instead of inviting the person, one of us could just learn more. And then if we don't think it should go on the resource list, cause other things are more important. You know, I think we thought a lot about what should go on the resource list. So maybe that's one way to think about it.
So as you can see, this is the extent of the site. Really just the one page. And it's contact. That's it for resources. That's it.
Well, looking at their site, and I definitely open the floor to other folks to to voice their their thoughts and opinions, but looking at their site, it doesn't look like it's adding it would be adding anything to our site that would be specifically relevant. I'm, I'm imagining. I mean,
This is total speculation, but I would imagine that the article that based on her email, I would imagine the article that she'd be writing would be something similar, like three things you can do to make living with a spinal cord injury easier, but based on what she was saying, the digital nomad lifestyle while managing disabilities.
I don't know if that's something that we're like that topic or any topic would be something that we would want like to have a single article on our web page as a resource about. All right, well. I'm going to. I'm going to take this as a no.
Yeah, back to Cam's idea. Is there anyone who wants to do a little bit more digging and learn more about this organization? Anyone who wants to engage with or engage with Mary to find out more? Doesn't sound like it.
I think they should have put more effort into the website, and then maybe we would care more. I don't know. Yeah, I don't. I love you, Cam. There's just something. There's something. I don't know what the thing is. There's something I don't, you know. Too vague. Yeah. I'm open to
So there was a woman, when we had our disability fair, there was a woman that reached out to me and she was a yoga instructor. And initially, I was like, OK, you teach yoga. All right, that's nice. What can we do for you? Why do you want to talk to us? Why do you want to come? We're not paying anybody.
Well, it teaches a specialized kind of yoga. I have to look at our list. I can't remember what it's called. But it is for people that have diabetes and neuropathy, people with cerebral palsy, people with physical and neurological and nerve related complications. It begins with an S.
have to look it up. And something like that, yes, I would be interested in because you know what? You would not know that something like that existed. So, but this, I don't know, my cancer and I don't think this is gonna add anything to your site. All right. Thank you for letting me not make that decision by myself.
Anything else anyone wants to chat about the Ablewell or Mary Wilson article? Any last thoughts before I move on? All right, the next thing on the agenda is the response to requests section. So we've got a couple requests here. So the Medford Housing Authority,
An invitation has been extended for a representative from the Medford Housing Authority to attend the April meeting and discuss the resident input process. That'll be on next meeting's agenda. Then the next item is the Medford Senior Center. Looks like we need some additional clarification. Are you asking about inviting employees or inviting attendees? This was clarifying from last meeting.
I know that, Cam, were you working on that with Yvette? Would you happen to know? I was. Oh, you were, Susie. OK. Would you happen to know? What I remember is that we wanted, somebody had suggested that we get to the senior center. And I had sent, when they're having events,
and that somebody would represent us there. I was gonna be away for St. Patrick's event, and then I don't know what the next event was. I've been away, so I haven't gotten on top of that. But whether we can attend and sit there. Anyway, that's all I remember about that.
Yeah, that's right. And then the other part, Linda, because we talked about it and we went back and forth, so it was confusing. I think what the commission wanted to do was suggest that we have one of our commission meetings where if folks are able,
They, we all attend, you know, we coordinate with the senior center to reserve a large space where we could meet and then members of the public could attend in person and we would have sort of publicized that we were going to be in the building.
we were going to have our meeting and that we were happy to connect and just listen to folks. And so, um, okay. Yeah. So then Linda, I think that is sort of what we would suggest is, um, I'll go back down to the senior center and find out their next, um, events. I don't, that's fine, but I want to go to something, um, next weekend, if this is an okay time,
They're having a wellness event at the new library in Medford. I want to say next Saturday, the 30th. And I know the Medford Recreation Department will be there. But that would be, now that I think about it, would be a fabulous place to have a little table.
can I just wrap up the senior center invitation only because I'm confused. I want to make sure that it's clear. We don't have to meet by Zoom. We can also meet in person. We can also meet hybrid. So I want to make sure that's clear. I would not
be renting space from the senior center for the meeting. Reason being the senior center closes at four. The council and agent is a business, so when I use them and use their space, guess what? Have to pay. So where is that coming from?
Additionally, if we're going to have an in-person meeting, right, which is fine, we would want to make sure that it is in an accessible location. City Hall is completely out on Wednesdays, because remember, you've got council meetings that are happening.
Um, so, you know, I-I asked, you know, back in the day, where did people have these meetings? Oh, the DPW offices, and the library, and the this and the that. I'm sorry, I don't consider... The library itself, the physical location of the library is access... is... is... The library is an accessible library. But getting to the library is not accessible for many people. People think it is because it's on High Street. It's not. There are many people who are actually afraid
because it is extremely congested, the visibility is bad, and at the time that we have our meetings at 5.30 in the evening, I'm not putting that stress on anyone, right? So then that leaves us with options such as looking at the schools, which would be the next big space, and it depends on what they have on their calendars.
But I say this because I just wanna make sure that folks know that Zoom is not the only option. We can do hybrid and we can do in-person as well. And then these are open meetings. So I would not single out just one group to invite because then you're gonna have to answer a lot of questions. These are open public meetings. So we should probably just advertise that, hey,
going to be in person, come meet or maybe if you wanted to do more of a social advertise that, hey, this meeting is going to be like our, you know, social pastries and like refreshments and do it that way.
Yeah, I think what, and I could be wrong, I wasn't the one who came up with the idea, but I think the idea was because folks have challenges getting, you know, getting around that we should go to them. And that, you know, having one of our meetings be hybrid and having some people be at the senior center would be nice,
And I hear you that we don't necessarily have to do anything special to make that happen. Maybe we should consider rotating a few different in-person locations in different months so that we're not, you know, accidentally excluding a population or a geography from attending in person if they wanted.
And then we could obviously let them know that virtual participation is always welcome. But I think Yvette was suggesting that some of us go to the senior center and because we would be there, it would maybe be more accessible and residents would interact with us and would feel more appreciative that we went to them.
and minimize the work that they had to do to attend. Right. Frances, would something like that be possible?
To be quite honest with you, I really don't know how the senior center closes at four. The events are usually at noontime. I'm sorry? The events there, the big events, St. Patrick's or whatever else, are usually at noontime. I think Susie was saying that the events happen at noontime. Susie, are you suggesting that we change our meeting time to noon? No.
I thought myself and Cam were saying, we meet them. It's not a meeting. I thought like two months ago, we talked about just being there and saying, do you know about the disability board? It wasn't a meeting, but maybe I'm breaking, I don't know.
Susie, I think that there are two different conversations going on. I think you're referencing outreach. Remember when you wanted to do some outreach? Right. But Cameron is responding to a request that was made.
So that's sort of like a different conversation. The senior center closes at four o'clock. So being able to go there and have a meeting is not on the table unless the disability commission has a way.
My office is an accessible office. So the option is for people to also come here. But if we are going to have all commissioners on site, it's not going to be big enough. We don't have access to the chambers. So these things, they sort of need to be planned out.
Yeah, I have just one question and then I'm happy to email Yvette to kind of clarify what the idea is. The one question I have is I've never been to the senior center or I think, do people live there? No. That huge skyscraper is empty. No, that's not the senior center. What is the big skyscraper?
The huge skyscraper that you see them working on, that's senior housing. That has nothing to do with the city, that is Medford Housing Authority. Yeah, but for instance, that's, so what Yvette is saying is that's where the people we want to invite to our meeting, that's where they live, and so we should be really close to them.
I agree. Okay, so that's the set, so that's Medford Housing Authority. They're a different entity. They're not run by the city, they're overseen by the federal government. So, and you know, they're ours. Yvette had just talked to them, and that's the connection. Like Yvette went there, and they're willing to host us, and they just wanna know when.
I mean, they could certainly host something. I mean, they have Tamponi, which is over, that is on the western side of Method. I don't think they're doing anything at that location right now because that building is under construction. And again, it would be,
The time, I think, would be the issue. But are you talking about hosting having a meeting happen there? I'm still confused. Yeah, I think that is the idea. Yvette was suggesting that rather than meeting in a place like the library and trying
you know, make people come to us to be able to attend in person, which, as you pointed out, you know, like, it's not, it's not at all, you know, all that easy to get to the library. And so Yvette's suggestion was she had gone to that senior housing center and asked them if
you know, we could meet on location and then the residents would be able to share their experience with us and potentially attend our, you know, our meeting in person since we were there. So that, you know, I think that's what, that's all the idea is, is just, you know, if we wanted to host a meeting so that they could come down,
So basically, this has nothing to do with the senior center then. Because the senior center is something completely different. Oh, Sue, what happens? You've lost your volume now. I don't know what happens, Sue.
You can't hear me. Okay. Now we can hear you. Most of the, they have events at the senior center about once a month about noontime. And most of the people that attend are from that senior housing building or other senior centers, whether they're private or whatever throughout the city.
And what I think two months ago we talked about was being there. I'm not talking about our 5.30 to 7 o'clock meeting, that somebody would be there, one or two people from the commission, and be there saying, we're from the commission, if you have any questions or suggestions, we're here.
Did you have anything to add? Sue B, that is. No, I just said that. You're Sue, I just said that. Do you have anything to add, Sue? It sounds like you're saying something different than Cam is. So you're talking about two different events, a meeting,
and something at senior center. Are you talking to me? Yes. Okay. I think Kim and I are on the same page. He knows that that big building is full of senior people. I know they're Medford Housing Authority. I know that very well. A number of them are disabled, very disabled.
And what we're saying is, why don't we go to the senior center where those people go for a lot of different social things? They go for busing to malls, they go to play card games, they go to yoga chair stuff. Why aren't one or two of us there when they have a bigger event
like st patrick's like where at the senior center okay and cam is talking about having a meeting at senior housing no i don't think so
How about we do this? I'm going to make an executive decision here for everybody. If members of the Disability Commission feel like they want to attend things that are occurring at the senior center, which is run by the Council on Aging, the short squat building,
As part of outreach and things of that nature, let me know. I can arrange it with Pam as long as no more than two people attend. And the reason I say no more than two people is so that we don't run into any forum issues accidentally, right?
Give me advance notice. Don't call me the day before and say you're planning on going tomorrow. The reason I say give me advance notice is so that I can see if we have any leftover swag or something that you can take with you. Now, that is just for outreach. Now, back to Cam's suggestion.
What I'm understanding is that Commissioner Welch put forward a suggestion of maybe having one of the evening meetings be an in-person meeting. Again, for the record, making it clear.
Meetings are in-person. In-person meetings have not been canceled. The hybrid model, I mean, the online model has just continued because for many people, it actually works for them and it's actually equitable because they are not running from transport to transport waiting for rides, whatever. Folks are more than welcome to join me in my office
if they want to be in person. But if we are to post an actual in-person, in-person meeting, we would need an owl or somebody to lend us an owl because you can't be in person and be hybrid at the same time, depending on your location, right? And we would need a space that everybody could get to easily.
And if Kristen or Sandra or somebody from the housing authority, the Medford Housing Authority, if they are willing to set up space for us, I would have to double check and make sure that it could be at 530. Now, if you all agree that, hey, you know what, maybe our final meeting in June before we go on hiatus,
wish you have like a meet and greet in person, and it can be at a specific location, I can help support that as well. But to be clear, the Senior Center is run by the Council of Aging, very, very different. The Housing Authority is also different. And whilst those two buildings are close together,
I've got to also add that many non-Medford people also attend the senior center. So that's the misconception is that everybody from the buildings goes to the senior center. It's actually not accurate. I have a lot of non-Medford people that also attend. So maybe, you know, think about that and then just get back to me individually via email.
All right, yeah, that was a super summary. So that again. I didn't hear that. That was.
Yeah, I was saying I was saying super helpful Francis. I think you summarized it well and and I know I will email you with how I'm thinking so just yeah, thank you. Okay, and then I don't know where Susie is, but maybe Susan will be back shortly. So. Should we?
move on to the next agenda item? Yes, I think so, because we're at 6.55. Yeah, so it looks like the next thing on the agenda is Frances put on a commissioner term expiration and to kind of be planning ahead for the next set of terms. And so if you're interested in renewing your term or appointment, please send an email to Frances indicating your interest no later than the May 2024 meeting.
It looks like pretty much all of us have, not all of us, but most of us, the great majority of us. Kim, since you've just joined three months ago, you are not on the list for renewal quite yet.
I am, Gabby is, Joe, you are, Susie, and Yvette. And it looks like, yes, Susan, Bibbins, you are also in the clear for now. So any of those folks who are interested in renewing your term or appointment, please send an email to Frances indicating your interest no later than the May 2024 meeting.
And then on the second page, we've got some new business. Looks like what the question on here on the agenda is, what steps are the commission taking to recruit for the vacant commissioner position? So this would be like the secretary position and possible vacancies that will arise from the non-renewal term limits. And what support does the commission need to be effective with its recruitment?
So I don't know if there's anything like off the top of anyone's head that we want to talk about now or if we want again, given the fact that we have three minutes left, if we want to think about these things and bring this to the April meeting about how are we going to recruit for the vacancies on the commission.
I have a person that I've talked to that is raring to go and she submitted her application and she wants to serve. I would recommend her.
That's great. Are you comfortable emailing me her name only because I don't want to, the person is not here and I don't want to speak about them. Yes, yes, absolutely. Thank you. That way I can follow up because the applications actually don't come to me. Ah, okay. They go into like some smart sheet portal thing. Okay. That way I can follow up. Okay.
Yes. Thank you. All right. Well, we can keep thinking about that and bring that to the next meeting. We can talk about renewals and vacancies next meeting. We've got one thing under correspondence and announcements. There was a flyer attached in the e-mail with the agenda.
The Metro Regional Disability Inclusion Summit is happening on April 11th from 9.30 to 2 at the Walter Denny Youth Center, the Boys and Girls Club Dorchester, and there's an address there in Dorchester if anyone is interested and able to attend. Is there any other information you wanted to include on that, Frances? I think that that is
I'm just trying to ransack my brain quickly. That is pretty much it. The ICCM, Islamic Cultural Center of Medford, in partnership with the interfaith community, is holding the Community Iftar on Sunday, April 7th from 6 to 8.
Iftar is the meal that is eaten when the fast is broken during the time of Ramadan. So they're holding the community one Sunday, April 7th, 6 p.m. to 8 p.m. It will be at the McGlynn School in the cafeteria.
there will be people of all different faith practices. That is what the interfaith group is about. So please consider yourselves invited and feel free to attend if you would like. Trying to think of what else is happening, so much is happening. I couldn't get it on the Arab American Heritage Month.
I couldn't get everything together as I had hoped. So we're entering, we're exiting Women's History Month. Woo-hoo, go women who have pioneered and channeled the pathway forward in so many different avenues of life.
Arab American Heritage Month is coming up. I know that our Arab community has a variety of different events that are occurring. Those events end with a big events in April.
that will include a fashion show, music, food, and I'm just going to get you the date for that. That is on April.
So that will be on April 27th from 3 p.m to 6 p.m at the Andrews Middle School. That will be music, face painting, pictures, light refreshments.
And I believe that is all, I believe that is all that I can think of for now. Prescription drug take back day is coming up as well. So that's a great opportunity. If you've got any medicines that you don't use anymore that you wanna dispose of, that's happening soon. Yeah, and then your season is ending in June.
So, yeah, just two more months, and then the commission is on holiday. So, think about, you know, any, you know, your, you know, future plans, like anything that you want me to start looking into to prepare for your new season, that kind of stuff. Great. Thanks, Frances. You're welcome.
Any, anything else anyone wants to bring up? All right, do we have a motion to adjourn? Looks like Sue is making a motion to adjourn. Do we have a second? Motion to adjourn. Joe's second. Sue, Susie, how do you, how do you vote? In favor of the adjourn? Okay, and then Cam, how do you vote?
Yes. Okay. I see it in the chat. I also vote yes. So we are adjourned unanimously. So everyone have a good night. It was good to see everyone. Thank you. Bye.