do do
years now and this year in particular we've just had a lot of help so a few thank yous before I turn it over to this amazing band. First to the West Medford Community Center, historic space
We were showing some of the performers around inside earlier, and there's a lot there. There's a lot of history, a lot of amazing artists who have come from this place. So in between sets, I really hope you'll go inside, take advantage of the Danish Pastry House, who has set up headquarters there. I've been eating a lot of it, and everything just keeps getting better. It's amazing. So also to the Arts Alive Foundation, Medford Foundation.
They've really helped us financial support Morningside Music Studio, the Medford Arts Council, Triangle Manor. We've got some beautiful t-shirts up there with two of our volunteers who are also involved in eating Danish pastry house.
Berkeley's Institute of Jazz for Gender Justice, which is where this band is from. I heard them playing a little earlier. It sounded incredible. Terry will tell you more about the history later, but it's a beautiful way of bringing that program full circle with where Terry Lynn Carrington, who's a legendary drummer from around here, really got her start, which was here. Her parents are still involved in this community.
Thank you also to our Patreon members, who are folks just like you, put in a couple dollars a month. It helps us pay for things like jam sessions, for the actual festival itself. Over the years it's really added up in a meaningful way, so if you're looking to get involved, there are numerous QR codes that you can scan to find out more about that. To the people working the cameras, Medford Community Media, you three have gone above and beyond.
I was thinking at least one camera would be great, but now we have three. So it's great to get high quality video. This is also being live streamed for those who couldn't be here in person. Lastly, to the Winchester Community Music School, to EXP Realty, and to Staples for our wonderful programs here. And thank you, of course, to our volunteers and staff, to Shayla, my partner, who's done basically everything.
To Reese and Eva up there, the tables. And to Bruce, who's been also stepping in and doing just about everything. And now I'll turn it over to Terry Carter, who manages many different things here at the Community Center. Also the former Poet Laureate of Medford, has written a lot of stuff. I know some of you saw him yesterday as part of our project, the Ally Project, but really couldn't do this without him. And he's gonna tell you
Love that, that's cool. So let me just take you through where we've been so far. So on Friday night, we started out with a student night, and it's very interesting because most of the students were of the older, more mature variety, and they're from Morningside Music School, and they put together two different bands, and they were fantastic, phenomenal,
quite delightful, and then Anita Wood came, Anita came from Medford, not originally from Medford, but grew up a good portion of her childhood here, and she brought her band, it was called A.J. and the Groove, and they were similarly wonderful, so that was night one, and then yesterday afternoon, we started out with Brazilian Flavor, with Recita de Samba, featuring Anna Borges and Bill Ward, and they were smoking hot, so.
And then, as Jonathan said, the Ally Project, featuring myself and Jonathan, great Toro, and great drummer, Gordon Engelthal, we finished up. So today, we're into a new groove, and it's Berklee's Institute of Jazz and Gender Justice, under the leadership of Terry Lynn Carrington.
We have, from the Institute, we have Jan Portage on bass. And he's got the big sexy today, all right? So that's the biggest bass you're going to see this weekend. And we have Yujin Han on piano. My man in yellow here, Fall Ray on sax.
She's a drummer, she's a composer, she's an educator from Santo Domingo, Dominican Republic, and she's known for her powerful artistry and ability to blend diverse musical traditions. You'll see all this. She holds degrees from Dominican Republic Music Conservatory and Berklee College of Music, where she studied with well-known artists including Neil Smith,
the aforementioned Terry Lynn Carrington, Francisco Mela, and others. She's a compelling live performer. You're gonna see all this. And she is leading up a band that really, really smokes. So I'm gonna get out the way and let them do what they do. Welcome to day three of the Medford Jazz Festival at the West Historic West Medford Community Center. Ladies and gentlemen,
Devon Equesta and the Berkley Institute of Jazz for Gender Justice. Let them do their thing.
Ž Ž Ž
Ž Ž
Ž Ž Ž Ž
♪
Ž Ž
Ž Ž Ž
? ?
Hey, guys. Thank you for having us. It's a pleasure for us to be here. This is an amazing place. It's my first time here, and maybe all of us, right? First time? Yeah. So thank you so much for the invitation. Like Terry said before, my name is Ivana Cuesta, and I'm part of the Gas and Gender Justice Institute, led by Theronine Carrington.
And the music that we want to read today, it's music composed by women, but also non-binary people. So we want to try to do is...
just bring something that sometimes is not well recognized, I would say, in the music industry. So that's why, yeah, we just choose really nice tunes. But also from some, actually from some of our professors. So the first tune that we play, it's called Chaos. It's one of my
My tunes that I wrote, I think two years ago, and it's in my album, Alert to the Earth. So you maybe had the sense it was a little bit chaotic and really loud and really noisy, but that was how I actually felt.
the pandemic ends. So I think everyone probably wrote music as a song or something after the pandemic because it was really something that affected all of us. So the next tune that we're going to be playing is Kowtow by Caroline Davis. I hope you enjoy.
Ž Ž Ž
you
do
? ?
Mm.
Thank you, thank you. Okay, so I just want to introduce really quick the band. Like Terry actually said before, so we have Eugene on piano. We have Jan, right? Yeah, it's a German name, I can't. But yeah, Jan on bass.
So the next tune that we're gonna be playing is called Yoda by Linda Oh.
do
Ž Ž Ž
? ?
? ? ?
Ž Ž Ž
What?
Ž Ž
? ? ? ?
Mm hmm.
have fun!
Great. So the tune that we just played right now, it's called Amelia, and it's by Melissa Galdana. So I probably choose a lot of tunes that are written by saxophone players. But all of them are amazing. I don't know. I just love it. So the next tune that we're going to play is a tune that I composed. It's called On Going Cycles.
And I would say maybe when I was thinking, when I was composing this, I was just thinking like how everything come back to the same place or everything come back again to like harmony basically. So all of us are going to start in different points in music, but there is going to be one section where everyone is in unity.
This track is part of, like I said, also of my album, and it's related with the earth. And like how, you know, the seasons and all of that, and we come back again to the beginning. And sometimes we think like, oh, we're never going to have summer again after eight months of winter. That's how I feel, and I already have nine years living here. You know?
everything come back in the right time, not sometimes when we want it, but when we need it. So this is ongoing cycle.
do do
do
♪
Ž Ž
. .
? ? ?
♪
Ž Ž
so
Ivana told me to say something. So this is it. Thanks. Thank you all for being here. My name is Paul. Thank you. This next song is mine. So I thought I would introduce it. There's a quick story to tell with it. So there's this piano player who teaches at Berkeley and lives in Boston. His name is Kevin Harris. Does anybody know Kevin?
Kevin's amazing, he's been an amazing friend and mentor to me. And I had him over at my house a couple weeks ago, and we were playing, and out of the blue, no conversation started to this, he just goes, I love turtles. And then leaves it at that, and then we didn't even talk about it afterwards. But I remember that moment so clearly. Meanwhile, I had this tune that I've been writing,
uh, that renamed, like, Titleist. So after that interaction, I named this tune Kevin's Turtle.
do
¦
? ? ?
? ?
. .
Ž Ž
okay so we're gonna do one more
Yeah? OK, perfect. Well, so the last one that we're going to do is called Smoking Gun, and it's by a saxophone player, Diane Stevens. And I just want to say thank you so much, everyone. I want to say thanks to the organizer, thanks to Jonathan, Abby, Terry, and everyone, actually, for having us. It's a pleasure, and I hope we can come back.
I love you. Thank you guys.
Ž Ž
? ? ? ?
Ž Ž Ž
♪ ♪
? ? ?
do
This is why you have engineers, because that's regular people. We don't know where the heck we are on stage.
In any case, ladies and gentlemen, Berklee's Institute of Jazz and Gender Justice, featuring Ivana Cuesta, on bass. Now Kordish, on the keyboard, Eugene Hahn. And on the saxophone, big and little, Paul Ray.
It's been a pleasure to hear y'all play. You're wonderful. We gotta send a thank you note to Terry Lynn for releasing y'all to come over and hang out with us for an afternoon. And we wish you continuing success in your studies and your teaching and all of the different things that you're doing right now. It's an amazing ensemble and we've been blessed by your performance today. So thank you very, very much.
All right, all right. So we're going to take a little pause for the cause. We're going to make the changeover between performers. And we'll be back as soon as we can and get this party started again. You've been a wonderful audience. We appreciate you. You don't have to go anywhere. You can go inside. And the Danish Pastry House has got deliciousness.
spread across two tables. There's liquid inside to keep yourself hydrated. Make sure you pay attention to all the different donation stations that are around for the community center and for the jazz festival itself. I have, if you weren't here yesterday you might not know about this, but I have my poetry books upstairs on the table.
We also have t-shirts if you'd like to take a look. They're $25 a pop, but the color is beautiful and the design is just as good. So make yourselves comfortable. We want to have you back, so enjoy yourselves.
Hello everyone. Come from far and wide, young and old.
Real big applause for my man.
That's on the Jamaican side where she has to have all the jobs. All right, so we're at day three. For those of you who haven't been here, we have had a little bit of everything. We've had the morning side.
We've got the Morningside Jazz All-Star, Thursday night. We've got the Needlewood, A.J. in the Room, Thursday night. Yesterday we had Jonathan and myself, the Allied Project, and we have Mexican De Samba. So you've heard a lot of different kinds of music. And then today, obviously, we had some real flavorful jazz with Ivana Cuesta and the Berklee Jazz and Gender Justice Institute.
We're going to take it to a whole nother door now. All right, so listen. Every once in a while, if you're nice to your friends, they'll be nice to you. So I just want to say, these folks, we kind of go way back. And I'm going to start with Donna McElroy, our vocalist. I don't know if any of you have heard of Fisk University in Nashville, Tennessee.
I'm at least one alum in the audience, and I'm an alum myself. And Fisk University in the 1870s sent a group called the Jubilee Singers, basically who all the crowned heads of state in Europe, and they raised enough money to come back and actually fund the school.
And that group of jubilee singers still exists today, and they are world-renowned and well, well-traveled. And Donna McElroy was one of those jubilee singers back in the days at this university. She has since elevated herself a number of times, Grammy-nominated, traveled throughout the United States and the globe, singing just about everything with just about everybody.
She's the chair emeritus of the voice department at Berklee College of Music. So give a big hand to Donna McElroy. Okay, I'm still at Berklee. Making people behave, on the drums, Sean Skeet.
I should have mentioned that. And then, my man, we've been friends forever. Our time together goes back to him as music minister at Jubilee Christian Church, but it was the Covenant at the time, not the Jubilee Club. But this is the inestimable George Russell Jr.
all right and then back on the big sexy head you can see it the hourglass shape
have their day. They are musicians at play and they are about to slay. I'm a poet, y'all know it. Let's do it. George Russell, Donna McElroy, Sean Ferrius, and Sean Skeet, live in the human color.
Glad that happened before we got started. You cute, you cute, you cute, and you know it too.
look at you and suddenly something in your eyes I see soon begins bewitching me that old devil moon that you stole from the sky
make this moment so hard to handle. Stars in the night, ladies in their night, can't hold us.
like oh
you
And suddenly, something in your eyes I see Soon begins bewitching me It's that old devil moon That just stole from the skies that old
You and your plans make this romance so hard to handle. Stars in the night, blazing midnight, can't hold us together till you're last to dance with you. You got me flying high and wide on a magic carpet ride full of butterflies inside.
In your eyes, just when I think I'm free at the door. Oh, catamaran, air in your eyes fills me with love. Oh, fa-da-pa-da-pa-do-do. Oh, do-pa-pa-pa-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da.
What a lovely day. Anybody got an extra towel? I'm kidding, I'm kidding, I'm kidding. It's a joke, it's a joke, it's a summer joke.
A one, two, a one, two. ♪ Gee, it's cozy in the park tonight ♪ ♪ When you cuddle up and hold me tight ♪ ♪ Stars above, they seem to know ♪ ♪ We're putting on a gig tonight ♪
birds that should be singing
more.
you
Oh-ho-ba-da-ba-do-da-do-da Oh-ho-ba-da-ba-do-da-do-da Oh-ho-ba-da-ba-do-da-do-da Oh-ho-ba-da-ba-do-da-do-da Oh-ho-ba-da-ba-do-da-do-da Oh-ho-ba-da-ba-do-da-do-da Oh-ho-ba-da-ba-do-da-do-da Oh-ho-ba-da-ba-do-da-do-da Oh-ho-ba-da-ba-do-da-do-da Oh-ho-ba-da-ba-do-da-do-da Oh-ho-ba-da-ba-do-da-do-da Oh-ho-ba-da-ba-do-da-do-da Oh-ho-ba-da-ba-do-da-do-da Oh-ho
We're putting on a big, big show. Hear the birds that are flying in the trees. See the humps that they bump up in the trees. Oh, man, we're big and slow.
Kiss! Kiss!
Cut love into a kiss or more. Yes, I know you love me, no. It started at the late, late, late, late, late, late, at the late, late show.
Sir, how many are in love currently? Oh, hands. Oh, hands. Oh, oh, okay. How many are still searching for it? To the point where my lower lip always quivers. Hello, how are you?
I'm Donna. Please forgive me. I'm a little emotional today. They love it. See, I'm always ahead with the young ones. Okay. Some more music.
The wind is high out today.
Until you've learned the meaning of truth. Until you've loved the love you had to lose. You don't know, know, know, know, know what love, love, love is. Oh, how, how lips hurt.
♪ Till you've kissed and had to pay the cost ♪ ♪ Till you've flipped your heart and you have lost ♪ ♪ You don't know what love is ♪ ♪ Do you know how much I love you ♪
Oh, reminiscing on how it's... that faithful teens lose their taste for kissing you.
A love that cannot live, it never dies, until you face each charm with strengthless eyes. You don't know what love is.
♪ Ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba, ba
♪ You know how a lost heart burns ♪ ♪ The thought of reminiscing ♪ ♪ And how lips that taste of tears ♪ ♪ Lose their taste for kissing you ♪
love cannot live, yet never die, until you face each dawn with sleepers eyes. You don't know, you don't know, you don't
No, no, no, no, no, no No, no, no, no, no, no You don't know, you don't know You may think you have all the answers But you don't know, you don't know Every time it comes around It hits you from a different direction You don't know, you're under a spell You're not doing so well Upset tummy, get yummy, yummy
You don't know what love is
Nice to be here. This is the best time for me when I'm in front of musicians and calling out tunes and we all know them. Sometimes you just gotta fake it, but. Which is what? Can you do this?
I don't know this one myself all that well. Oh, this is a Betty Carter tune. You know, she was obscure and obtuse in her artistic expression and in her song arrangement and writing. I don't know how to do this.
Okay, there you go. Perfect. Oh, it was so simple. It was a simple lever. He's gifted. I'll remember that. What's your name?
You've been my hero a long time. You just now know it. My daddy's a hero. You just now figuring it out, lady?
Small children found whose hang around like in a daze. Unlike adults have fewer faults and in a few years they'll start to do their big moves. They can move, they speak. Kids take a fall, and in a ball, it's up again. Whose make them cry every day, every day, every day, every day.
♪ Girls and boys lose their toys like in a game ♪ ♪ They'll bounce and all, all in this hall ♪ ♪ They live and all, they live and all ♪ ♪ Baby blues, basic blues, baby blues ♪ ♪ Ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh ♪
♪ All girls and boys see blues as toys in a game ♪ ♪ Blues come their way most every day ♪ ♪ Kids get them in, they let them win ♪ ♪ Kids make blues, take blues, shake blues ♪ ♪ We time on tops, get blues a lot, kids on the move ♪ ♪ Kids in the know, let testing flow ♪ ♪ They get blues, they see blues ♪
They take blues, they break beat. They take blues, they break blues, they beat you. Yeah, yeah, yeah. OK, nobody knows that song, right?
Nobody knew that song before I mentioned it. Okay, so do me a favor and don't ever go back and actually listen to what the song goes like. Because I will have ruined it for you for every correct version because that was some scum.
All right, all right. It was just fine. God bless you, Donna. Now go sit down. OK, what's next, Jimmy? Oh, that's it.
Folks are blessed who make the best of every day Living by their own philosophy Everyone beneath the sun must find a way And I have found the only way for me
I don't believe in fretting and grieving. Why mess around with strife? I never was cut out to step and strut out. Give me the simple life. Some find it pleasant dining on pheasant. Those things roll off my knife. Just give me tomatoes and mashed potatoes. Give me the simple life.
A cottage small is all I'm after, not one spacious and wide. A house that's filled with joy and laughter and the ones you love inside. So you take the high road, I'll take the low road, free from care and strife. Sounds corny and seedy, but yes, indeedy.
♪ I don't believe in fretting, grieving ♪ ♪ But I mess around with strife ♪ ♪ I never was cut to step to strut out ♪ ♪ Give me the simple life ♪ ♪ Some find it pleasant dining on pheasants ♪ ♪ Those things roll off my knife ♪ ♪ I want tomatoes and mashed potatoes ♪ ♪ Give me the simple life ♪
So you take the high road, I'll take the low road. Corny, seedy, yes indeed.
born in the simple life. Simple, simple, simple life.
for everyone here today and all those people who are listening in the atmosphere, to have a simple today and a simple tomorrow, and hopefully a simple week coming up. Whatever's stressing you, whatever's complicating your spirit, got it all twisted up, I rebuke it! In the name of good people. Oh.
Listen to John. We're going to do a trio tune for you now, and from the songbook of Thelonious Monk, it's our own version of a song he wrote called, Well You Need It. But we're going to twist it up a little bit.
do
Bye.
Thank you.
This is my rhythm section, Big Fat Delicious. He just made that up. And I took his lead, because I follow him wherever he go. Anybody smell pollen this evening?
He does, he can, yeah. I'm in a sweet party, can I get an amen, amen, amen. Now I know better, I know better now.
Okay.
Willow, weep for me. Willow, weep for me. Lean your branches down along the ground if I can see.
Listen to my plea Hear me willow and weep for me Gone is my lover's dream Lonely lover's dream Gone it left me here To weep my tears into the stream Sad as I can be Lean down willow and weep for me
Listen to the wind, it says another sin. To leave my heart aching, can't make it all alone. Murmur to the night, to hide it's dark light. For none can find the sign and cry it all alone, alone.
Weak in sympathy, lean your branches down on a lonely snake that runs to sea. Sad as I can be, nearly willow in sympathy.
♪ Music playing ♪
Down, down, down, down below the branches Let the tears flow to the stream
♪ Whisper to the wind and say his love is sin ♪ ♪ And leave my heart aching and I'm begging him on ♪ ♪ Remember to the night, the hottest starry night ♪ ♪ So none can find me sighing and I'm crying all alone ♪ ♪ Oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh ♪
♪ Lean down below and weep for me ♪ ♪ Weep for me ♪ ♪ Weep for me ♪
do do do do do
Did I mention that I write? Okay, so forgive us, we're going to subject you to a couple of my songs, all right?
I promise you won't die. And there will be no polling, no opinions, no numbers, no one to five, nothing like that. It's just fun music. God bless you.
Come on, you're gonna make me blush, and then I'll cry, and then I'll be a mess, and I won't make it through the gig. Yeah, yeah, I see what you did, I see it. Smooth, he's so smooth all the time. He's gonna be smooth. He's smooth. That's what he's gonna be. I know, I know. One, two, one, two, one, two, three.
It's called Just Your Smile. No hills. No rapids. No 60 mile an hour winds. No raging fire to put out. Only smoldering embers within. No balls to roll me over. I'll walk in that longest mile. Just your smile. Just your smile.
No dozen roses, bucks of candy, I couldn't eat that anyway. No drawn out recitation, only three simple words to say. No weeping or a wailing, or fainting in need.
I didn't need a moon or the glow Your trumpets were the strings That'd be too soon to know anyway Who answers when that bell rings Yet I do when I look into your eyes My lonely days were through And all the fireworks and riots in the world Couldn't make it any more true That no bell
A whistle's the warning of my pending fall. No clue that this'll be the sweetest dream of all. No abstract application. RSVP'd in grand style. No double digit, two digit, millimeter.
Yeah.
Ž Ž
No hills, no rapids, 60 mile an hour winds, no raging fires of blood.
It's just smoldering in her within. No drawn out recitation. Just three little words to say. Just your smile. No dozen roses, but for me, I couldn't eat that anyway.
No weeping or a wailing, or fainting in the aisles, just a smile.
It'd be too soon to know anyway Who answers when that bell rings Yet I knew when I looked into your eyes My lonely days were through And all the fireworks and rockets in the world Couldn't make it any more true That no bells Could warn me of my dimly followed clue
That this would be the sweetest dream of all No heartfelt invitation R.S.P.P'd in grand style No abstract provocation No more TV vacation I'm gonna live my days in just your smile If I could have another one
What's to say? Marry me, baby Love is forever What's for dinner? Are we ready? Nothing, nothing, nothing, nothing can take away the joy of your smile
Just your smile. He said I like the dab. He said I like the dab. He said he didn't like it a little lot, he liked it a lot lot. A real, real, real big lot.
God bless you. I'll get your number at the end of the show. You can sign up for my follow along tag along behind me group. Here's another one. Now get ready because you're going to be inspired.
I don't think there's any tissues. Just hold it. Hold it until you get home. Okay? I've got a tissue over here for you.
This is called Why Can't We Live Together. I wrote it back in the days of the assault on Rodney King. They did the interview with him, and he asked him, why can't we just get along? And right after that, this song came on my heart. And now, how many years ago was this? A lot of years. So this song has been really,
30 years, 34 years. So this song is still living and it's still reasonable to plead with the heavens and to plead with everyone around you. ♪ I have a dream ♪ ♪ It fills my sleeping and my waking hours ♪
It's a dream of us together Learning to live with each other Settling all our strife We've got to see There's so much we can do to change calamity Just us two
It starts with me and you, so let's get started. Healing the brokenhearted, walk up to every brother, asking each other, why can't we live together? Give me what I'm due, and I'll give it back to you.
Why can't we live together? You know I'm gonna reach for you When things go wrong To keep me strong in stormy weather So tell me This cruel, cruel world Is all we got So let's make the best of it
The passion that we need And we'll have a one world nation Build on cooperation It won't hurt to help me So can you tell me Why can't we live together? Give me what I'm doing I'll give it back to you
♪ Why can't we live together ♪ ♪ You know I'm gonna reach for you when things go wrong ♪ ♪ To keep me strong in stormy weather ♪ ♪ So tell me why, what a joy it is to live ♪ ♪ All the goodness we could give ♪
In harmony, know your feelings set the wheels in motion. It's more than a notion. Let's take a stand in the caring hand.
Why can't we live together? You know I have to reach for you when things go wrong. So why can't we live together? You know I'm gonna reach for you when things go wrong. I know why. You'll look around. You'll want me there.
You'll want me in your prayers So why? Why? Why we gotta argue and fight? Argue and fight every day and every night Why? Why? Why? Why? Why? Why? Why? Why? Why? Why? Why? Why? Why can't we live together?
Why we can't get along together? Together, you and me, all together now. Can I get an amen? Amen.
It always gets me very emotional. Oh, don't do that, George. Okay, back to life, back to reality.
What town is this? West Medford. West Medford, Mass. Are we in the backyard of what church? West Medford Community Center. West Medford Community Center. A lot of history here. So much. A lot of joy, a lot of tears. 90 years worth. 90 years worth.
And we are still banging, banging, banging, burning, burning, burning, and the wheels kept turning. What you say is we'll still be learning.
♪ For the love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love
I said do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do
Stormy Monday. That's what they call it. Tuesday's just as bad. They call it Stormy Monday, y'all. But Tuesday's just as bad. Wednesday's worse. And Thursday's oh so bad here.
They say that the eagle flies on Friday and Saturday I go out to play. They say that the eagle flies on Friday and Saturday I go out to play.
in your holy spirit bow down on our knees and pray for mercy mercy mercy please
This is your chance, last chance to join in, so snap!
Did anybody need to hear that? George W. Russell Jr. Okay, I think everybody should get some.
Yeah.
Monday. But you know Tuesday's just as bad. They call it Stormy Monday. But baby, Tuesday's just as bad. And they tell me Wednesday's just as bad, just as bad. And Thursday's oh, so sad. They say that the eagle flies on Friday.
Saturday I go out to play, go fly, go fly, Saturday I go out to play. And then Sunday, I go to church, I get down on my knees, I cry Lord. In my heart, I cry Lord.
Oh, I'm asking you Lord, put my mommy in heaven.
I cry Lord have mercy. I cry Lord have mercy. Have mercy, have mercy. I cry Lord have mercy. Have mercy on me. Yeah! Yeah!
Thank you so much. Thank you so much. Thank you so much. God bless you all. Thank you. Hey, so listen. Would anyone like an encore?
We'll do one more track, then we'll come back and say our goodbyes and thank you. But you've been a wonderful audience, so sit tight for just five minutes more.
Okay.
I'm as helpless as a kitten up a tree. And I feel like I'm clinging to a cloud I can't understand.
I get misty just holding your hand. Should I move up a half step or a down step? Walk my way. And a thousand violins begin to play. And it might be the sound of your hello.
The music I hear gets me misty The moment you're near You can say that you're needing me But it's just what I want you I want you
Don't you notice how hopelessly I'm lost? That's why I'm following you, baby You better believe me On my own Must I wander through this wonderland alone?
Holding my right foot from my left My hat from my glove I'm too misty And too much in love I'm so misty And too much
God bless you all. See you next time. Have a great rest of your day. Thank you so much. Ladies and gentlemen, one more time for the inimitable Donna McElroy.
All right. On the keys, the equally inescapable George W. Russell Jr. Those of us who have known him for a long, long time can call him D-Dub. Don't get twisted. All right. Big man, big bass, big sexy, Sean Farias. And you know you got to give the drummer some, it's Sean Skeet.
You heard it here, live and in living color at the West Bedford Community Center. I'm Terry Codd. I've been your genial host. I'm going to bring my main man, Jonathan Fagan, who's going to do thanks and acknowledgments. You've been a lovely audience, and we've enjoyed you just as much as you've enjoyed us. Thanks again, everyone. Oh, there we go.
Thanks again so much to the West Medford Community Center for hosting us all weekend, especially to our MC, Master of Ceremonies, Terry Carter, over here. To the Danish Pastry House, over here, elevated the event to another level. Please go in and grab something on your way out. Thank you to our volunteers and our staff, to Shayla, to Reese, Eva, all the folks working sound and video over there with the Medford Community Media.
Thank you, most of all, to our musicians, this wonderful band. I think we're going to all leave here inspired and moved. So thank you so much for coming and just dressing up us with your talents. So stay tuned for more from the Medford Jazz Festival. If you feel inspired to, drop a couple dollars in the donation box or scan a QR code on your way out. And sign up for our email list if you'd like to know what we're up to. We hope to keep many things going throughout the year.
have a great afternoon.