[SPEAKER_01]: call a meeting to order first thing is the review of the minutes from last time October I believe sure didn't meet in November correct can you is this noise should I mute myself can you hear them drilling out there is that the dental office
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yeah, do I have a motion to approve the minutes from October 2024?
[SPEAKER_01]: Motion to approve the minutes from October.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you, Doctor.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, roll call.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can I have a second first, I guess?
[SPEAKER_03]: Second.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, roll call.
[SPEAKER_03]: Dr. Platowicz?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Jenny Vitale?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Kathleen Charbonneau?
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, motion to approve, accepted, thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, so next on our agenda, we have representatives from MorphoCeuticals at 200 Boston Avenue.
[SPEAKER_03]: They've submitted a permit for an application for an institution to use regulated biological agents as part of a permit application
[SPEAKER_03]: We request that the applicants present an overview of the use of our DNA or other regulated biological agents during a regularly scheduled meeting of the Board of Health.
[SPEAKER_03]: This presentation shall include a general introduction of the institution, its mission, its research or production plans, a timeline of the use of our DNA or regulated biological agents, an overview of the applicant's biosecurity risk assessment and program,
[SPEAKER_03]: and the discussion of the facilities in general.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I'm not sure if you want to introduce yourselves for folks that are here from MorphoCeuticals.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hi, everyone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hello.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I'm Maestan Bogheri.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm a scientist at MorphoCeuticals.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so representing MorphoCeuticals to get actually the permits from the Medford Board of Health.
[SPEAKER_00]: and nice to meet all of you guys.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, should I start with the presentation?
[SPEAKER_03]: Certainly, is there anyone else that here from Office of Certicals that you want to introduce?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, just I think Isabel and Nicole, they're from Spotlight, so they're helping us.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, great.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Feel free to continue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'll give you a brief overview of the MorphoCytical.
[SPEAKER_00]: MorphoCytical is located at 200 Boston Avenue, Medford.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, mainly we are focused on understanding the bioelectric and the bioelectron profile of different tissues during actually different conditions in healthy and disease or disorder conditions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we are also focusing on regeneration, different types of actual regeneration for different organs.
[SPEAKER_00]: So to address our questions regarding the bioelectric profile of different tissues, we need to use actually different fluorescent proteins or reporters that they can tell us what is the actual status of the membrane potential or cell potential.
[SPEAKER_00]: So to achieve this, we have to use, actually, adeno-associated virus.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we have to be able to infect the living animals, like the living mouse or mice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also different types of the cells.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why we need to actually use AAV or adeno-associated virus.
[SPEAKER_00]: Next, please.
[SPEAKER_00]: OK.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, morphocyticals, actually, we are using different auto recombinant DNA or like as a plasmid form.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, they are actually inducing different transgenes or fluorescent voltage sensors.
[SPEAKER_00]: So either we will prepare them here at house or we can buy them actually, you know, from different commercial vendors.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also for the AVV also we might be actually make it in the house or we might actually buy from commercial vendors.
[SPEAKER_00]: It depends on the time and also the other factors.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we are using mice now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so these mice will be divided to different groups for different treatment and also different AAV injections.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this actually we will perform fluorescent imaging and also spatial biology experiments.
[SPEAKER_00]: to find the membrane potential and also change in membrane potential and protein distribution in real time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as I said previously, we must have to use AAV because we want to infect the living mice and living mouse, and that's why we have to use a virus that can infect these mice and cells.
[SPEAKER_00]: Next, please.
[SPEAKER_00]: So again, more physical located at 200 Boston Avenue in Medford.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we have total 1,500 square feet of this space, like 1,100 square feet of lab, and some like 400 square feet of office.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we are now currently five employees and so the lab actually designed as a BSL2 lab.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we have a one main laboratory lab and also attached tissue culture room.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the office actually segregated from the lab and tissue culture by a single space or a single pass air.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and we have actually one class two type A2 biosafety cabinet.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to get access to the morphositicals, we are using the keycard.
[SPEAKER_00]: Next, please.
[SPEAKER_00]: So this is the overview, like a map of the morphocyticals.
[SPEAKER_00]: So here actually is the, like I can see, but there is a lab and then attached to the lab is the tissue culture room.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then after that, like it's the office or non lab areas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Next please.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so we are using different types of materials here at MorphoCyticals.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we are using human actually source materials only.
[SPEAKER_00]: We are using cell lines that drive from human.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, we are using actually viral vectors, and for now, specifically, we are using adeno-associated viruses that actually they are categorized as a BSL-1 viruses, and all these viruses are actually inter-replicated incompetent.
[SPEAKER_00]: They cannot come out from the cells after infection.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, also we are using animal materials and our main actual animal now we are using is mice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, we are collaborating with Tufts University.
[SPEAKER_00]: We are using their actual vivarium and also we are buying the mouse from different vendors like Charles Devere Laboratory or Jackson Laboratory.
[SPEAKER_00]: Next, please.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we have a different safety program and policies.
[SPEAKER_00]: So in terms of safety, we have the biosafety manuals and exposure control plan.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we have an emergency action plan.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we have a chemical hygiene plan also.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in terms of BPPs, so all the employees and more physical members
[SPEAKER_00]: They have to be vaccinated for different vaccines.
[SPEAKER_00]: vaccines like the HPV and also other types of vaccinations.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we have a plan to actually do yearly titration for the HPV and maybe other, actually, you know, the vaccines.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, we have a contract with Mount Vernon Occupational Health Service to provide all these necessary occupational health services.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, next please.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, one of the important things that actually our policy, one of our more important policy is everyone wants to work with the virus.
[SPEAKER_00]: They have to be trained before actually using the viruses or handling the viruses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and that's very important for the morphosyntheticals to make sure that we are following all the biosafety policies.
[SPEAKER_00]: So next please.
[SPEAKER_00]: The actual safety program policies and practices we have in lab, so the policy we have to follow is the full coverage of the foot, so full coverage of the lower leg.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we have lab coats, different types of lab coats in the lab, and also safety glasses and also goggles and shields for working with different types of viruses, cells, or materials.
[SPEAKER_00]: So additionally, we have different types of gloves and also tie-back hair.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's important in morphositicals.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the other thing like Morphine Cytical has, so we are not allowing our employee to use headphones or AirPods in actually the laboratory.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the other thing, so if work needs to be actually conducted after hours, so the person has to inform the supervisor or the safety representative to make sure that he or she is going to follow all the safety and biosafety policies.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, next please.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, food, drink, and actually any ingestible medicines are not allowed inside the lab.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as I said again previously, so the person inside the lab, they are not allowed to use personal electronic devices like phone or headphones.
[SPEAKER_00]: specifically with gloves on hands.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we have different stickers for inside and outside the labs that's showing like different conditions like biohazards areas or equipments and also where the employee has to wear the gloves or lab coats and where they have not and actually they have to remove them when they come out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's called gloves on or gloves off.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we are trying to reduce as much as possible using the sharp things because we are working specifically when we are working with the human materials and viral vectors.
[SPEAKER_00]: And any BSL 2 materials, so it has to be in a leak-proof secondary container for actually shipment and handling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we have planned to have IBC meeting at least once a year to review and actually if we need to add any new amendment to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the IBC Committee of the Morphocytical contains four morphocytical representatives, one community representative, and a non-voting safety consultant mainly from Spotlight Safety Incorporation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Next, please.
[SPEAKER_00]: Regarding the waste management, we are completely following the IBC regarding all the biological waste and disposals.
[SPEAKER_00]: Solid and sharps bio-waste are completely sealed prior to removal by a company called STRECYCLE.
[SPEAKER_00]: Liquid bio-waste will be treated with 10% concentration of the bleach and will be incubated for 20 to 30 minutes before disposal.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have a higher organic load of liquid waste, we are actually mainly using 20% of the final concentration of actually bleach that is determined by the IBC reviewer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So all solid bio-waste and hazardous chemical waste is transported from the lab to the loading dock.
[SPEAKER_00]: And more specifically, I like to operate as a VSQG for chemical hazards and waste.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, we contracted with the Clean Air for chemical waste disposal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we are in the process of getting permit for RDNA and WEST water.
[SPEAKER_00]: Both applications I think submitted and already we actually acquired a flammable storage and we scheduled the registration.
[SPEAKER_00]: Next please.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, we have contracts with different vendors for different tasks.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for example, for biological and sharp waste, we have a contract with Destrocycle, it's completed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for chemical, we have a contract with Clean Earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Occupational health with Mount Auburn and lab.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we have, as I said, plenty of different types of lab coats in lab.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the fume hood and biosafety cabinet got certificate just recently using the other scientific company.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we have a contract with Walton pest control to control the pests.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, we have a contract with a safety consultant from the spotlight safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: So thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any question?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I have one.
[SPEAKER_01]: You said the adenovirus cannot replicate?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: The adenoviruses cannot replicate when they infect the cells.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are incompetent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So there's no chance of human-to-human transfer?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: OK.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's helpful.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I'm glad you have those contracts in place already with the Stericycle and the Hazardous Waste Disposal Company.
[SPEAKER_03]: I know I did ask for a couple more documents and I know they were already sent over by Spotlight.
[SPEAKER_03]: The fuel wood certification has been completed then as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's great.
[SPEAKER_00]: We did almost most of the things we need, I think.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and so I'm in the process of still reviewing the application.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like I said, there were a few missing pieces that have already been sent over as of this morning.
[SPEAKER_03]: So we'll continue to go through that and be able to issue the permit as soon as the application is complete, if there's no other questions or concerns.
[SPEAKER_03]: And when do you expect to be fully operational?
[SPEAKER_03]: once the permit is approved?
[SPEAKER_00]: So we hope to start by January to be fully operational because we almost received most of the equipments we need.
[SPEAKER_00]: And just need the permits to be able to start the work here at InfraCerticals.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you've been actually certified as a BSL2, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: We have a copy of that documentation as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sorry, what documents do you need?
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, that's another... Because I couldn't get that, so maybe... I'll go through the list, and then we'll go through it in e-mail.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'll be easiest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you for joining us.
[SPEAKER_03]: Appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you so much for having me, actually, and thanks for your time.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Bye.
[SPEAKER_03]: Next on the agenda, I just wanted to let you know what's happening.
[SPEAKER_03]: So the Board of Health has received a grant from the Mass Gaming Commission.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's community impact money from the casino, so several
[SPEAKER_03]: Surrounding communities of the casino receive are able to apply for these grants through the mass gaming commission.
[SPEAKER_03]: So we were awarded 1 to do data collection and analysis to understand the impact of gambling on 18 to 20 foils in the community.
[SPEAKER_03]: And now with the, you know, the.
[SPEAKER_03]: asset presence of online gambling, as well as the casino presence.
[SPEAKER_03]: We want to gain some knowledge to inform what we need to do going forward, whether it be for educational campaigns, for some sort of initiatives or support programs.
[SPEAKER_03]: So what we're doing right now is just a basic needs assessment using surveys and focus groups with young adults to really see what's impacting them through their gaming environment.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's kind of exciting.
[SPEAKER_03]: We're really looking forward to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: A couple of communities around us have already done some of this work, so we'll be learning from them as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: But we've contracted with an outside consulting firm.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's actually going to help us with the creation of the surveys and the focus group questions, and then do a lot of the analysis and data collection for us.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's exciting.
[SPEAKER_03]: More to come on that.
[SPEAKER_03]: We're just getting going.
[SPEAKER_03]: So we're hopefully getting the contract in place as we speak, and we'll be moving forward within the next month.
[SPEAKER_03]: So Catherine from the Office of Prevention and Outreach will also be helping to spearhead this program as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: So more to come on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: How much money are we talking about, roughly, per grant?
[SPEAKER_03]: We received $72,000.
[SPEAKER_02]: and for the next year to do the assessment of the following.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hopefully be wrapping up maybe by the fall, but we'll see.
[SPEAKER_03]: See how we do.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then what the hope is is that we can reapply for another grant from the Gaming Commission this year to help us then move forward with some of the initiatives that we learned may be effective once we do the needs assessment.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hopefully be a continuation.
[SPEAKER_02]: of funding.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that application for additional funds is due January 7th.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we have our work cut out for us between now and then, but I'm hoping to be able to do that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then I know Jill was under the weather, but she's on the Board of Health meeting.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I just want to do a quick update on flu and COVID clinics.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I don't know, Jill, if you want to join or if you just
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so we've concluded most of our flu and COVID clinics for the year.
[SPEAKER_04]: We've done them at a variety of different locations, the senior center, the schools, city hall, the library, and then we're still doing a lot of homebound vaccines now because we still have a lot of high dose flu shots left.
[SPEAKER_04]: We actually just ordered some more COVID shots because we're still getting requests for that.
[SPEAKER_04]: So still giving out vaccines to people who still need it, but we did get a good number of people vaccinated earlier in the fall.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, your last clinic was last week at the library.
[SPEAKER_03]: You did pretty well, right?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, we gave out almost 70 vaccines just setting up in the lobby of the library with just walk-ins.
[SPEAKER_04]: So got a good amount of people.
[SPEAKER_03]: Still taking requests for a home bonus, as Jill mentioned.
[SPEAKER_03]: And we do have high dose for the 65 plus population, if anybody's in need, still in need of flu and COVID.
[SPEAKER_04]: pediatric COVID vaccines this year, too.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's been the biggest demand I saw this year.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think because a lot of the pharmacies only, or most of the pharmacies only give COVID vaccines to kids three and older.
[SPEAKER_04]: So there's kind of a gap for the under three population.
[SPEAKER_04]: A lot of pediatricians don't seem to be stocking it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So we gave out a lot of COVID vaccines to babies and little toddlers.
[SPEAKER_03]: Jill Zatupa.
[SPEAKER_04]: Lots of screaming.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I think that's all I have.
[SPEAKER_03]: We still have business tabled on the agenda.
[SPEAKER_03]: Again, anybody wishing to untable that can do so.
[SPEAKER_03]: We can continue the discussion or we can keep it on the table.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's for the negative fee generation regulation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I think we decided to wait and see how things go.
[SPEAKER_01]: So there is nothing to see how things went, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: But a few other communities that have moved forward with it, I believe Chelsea is one of the more recent ones that enacted as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: And also now there's Senator Lewis,
[SPEAKER_02]: uh, is proposing with the state, um, to take a look at state, uh, possibly enacting state legislation.
[SPEAKER_02]: We'll see how that goes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: All right.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's all I have.
[SPEAKER_03]: Uh, anybody want to do a motion to adjourn?
[SPEAKER_01]: Motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can I get a second?
[SPEAKER_03]: Second.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: We'll call on that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Motion to adjourn.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.