[SPEAKER_00]: Welcome to Andrews Middle School, named after Madeline Duggar Andrews, a dedicated student and athlete who showed courage and tenacity to become MedFed's first African American woman to serve as a school committee member.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is my sincere hope that all students who attend Andrews Middle School will show that same courage and tenacity and passion for their learning throughout their three years at Andrews Middle School, as well as throughout their lifetime, as successful and contributing members of our communities.
[SPEAKER_00]: My name is Jennifer Skane, and I am thrilled to be the principal of Andrews Middle School.
[SPEAKER_00]: I bring with me just over 27 years in education as a teacher, school Councilor, and over 10 years in administration.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am a wife and a mom of three grown children, as well as two fur babies.
[SPEAKER_00]: I firmly believe in fostering a positive and inclusive learning environment where every student can thrive, and I am committed to supporting our dedicated staff, families, and students in achieving their goals.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here at Andrews Middle School, students will have the opportunity to engage not only in their core academic courses of math, history, science, English language arts, but explore their interest in courses such as fine arts, chorus, band, computer science, wellness, and health.
[SPEAKER_00]: Students also have an opportunity to study a world language by electing to study either Spanish, French, or Italian.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has always been my philosophy that students learn inside the classroom as well as outside of the classroom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, I highly recommend students join one of our many after-school clubs and activities.
[SPEAKER_00]: These include Art Club, Diversity Club, Gay-Straight Alliance, Yearbook, Drama, and many more.
[SPEAKER_00]: For students who enjoy being physically active, we offer several athletic opportunities to compete against our local communities in baseball, track, cross country, softball, basketball, and flag football.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am proud to serve as the principal and educational leader where over 70 dedicated teachers and staff work daily to promote our school motto of excellence through responsibility and respect, which develops important character traits that will serve them well in their personal and social lives.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you for being a part of Mustang Country, and I look forward to sharing the many ways that we show our Mustang pride.