Okay, so let's get started.
And so we have two items to look at.
One is the document that we've been trying to, we've been struggling to edit on,
on Google Docs, but I don't think anybody besides me has been able to, and Chris Donovan, have been able to edit it, correct?
Fred?
I was able to edit it.
I didn't have any edits, so I was happy with the things that you made.
I didn't get your edited version.
I, I wasn't able to edit it.
Um, I, you know, I, I viewed it and, um, printed it.
Um, I wasn't, I wasn't able to edit it online.
I only have very minor little things that I would change to it.
Um, I think it's excellent.
What's been done.
Okay.
So, um, Chris Donovan, you want to bring it up and we can go over it.
Um, the guidelines themselves.
Excuse me.
Do you want me to go over the guidelines themselves?
Yeah.
Yeah, let's just bring it up and go through the slides.
This is Fred's baby.
It's really wonderfully done.
We finally have some guidelines, some ground rules, some things to tell people.
Fred, right?
So this is kind of the basic footprint of what we're trying to do here.
So I didn't have any additions to any changes to it.
And Fred, it's your thing, but this is our marching orders.
This is what we do here at the District Commission.
We follow these guidelines from people
ask us these questions, this is what we're going by.
Sure.
Let's, okay, so why don't we just go through it and we'll see if anybody has any comments.
Fred, do you want to walk it through, Fred?
Yeah, let me, I think I can pull, let me pull it up here, Chris.
There we go.
Can you, this is your version on Google Docs.
Yeah, and I apologize if anyone, you know, we can't edit to it, we'll figure out, I would say a better approach, but the idea is just to get some of that material out.
In the future, I could just hard code it in an email, but this is really good, Fred.
If everyone can see the screen and see the edits, Chris, as far as I know, you're the only one who was able to get in or had any interest really in getting in to see this, so.
It's a lot, but we're going to go from the general approach.
Section one step one.
Yeah.
So I don't know, Chris, you're welcome to.
No, I love it.
The primary purpose of the Medford Historic District design guidelines is to encourage preservation and high design standards in Medford's local historic districts in order to safeguard the city's architectural heritage and historic significance.
That's just a great statement right off the bat.
Right, Chris Bader, is that?
Yes, yes, I agree.
It's kind of our marching orders.
Then the next line is, you know, kind of, you know, more utility, like, these guidelines have been developed to encourage renovations, alterations, and new construction to repeat the design fabric of the districts and help maintain their architectural and historical integrity.
Now, I think that's such a great, you know, line that I think we need, we need someone to, you know,
champion that statement as this is what we do.
This is what this is all about.
That's such a great opening line.
And so now to get to the nuts and bolts of it, Fred, do you want to read, you know, the ABCs, you know, here?
Well, we don't have to.
We read it aloud, but
But to go over each line item as we go down, is there any talk about moving through it?
I know it's a little bit much, but it doesn't affect the conversation.
The only thing I might add to the first sentence is an additional thing we're safeguarding, which is the character of Medford's historic neighborhoods.
Because this is a totally local thing.
Well, it's not totally local, but it- Chris, are you saying the South Street District or- No, no, the overall, the overall, the first sentence here.
Well, I could add, I mean, I could add that in after, you know, architectural heritage, the, what are you saying that you're saying- The character of Medford's historic neighborhoods.
to safeguard the city's architecture heritage.
Let me see if it comes in here.
The, of our neighborhoods, our historic neighborhoods.
Of our neighborhoods, yeah.
I would add historic.
Is there a way that you can combine those two sentences?
The character of our,
In order to save the city's architectural heritage.
And historic neighborhoods and significance or something like that.
I don't think you need to have it separate, but.
Historic neighborhoods.
And Medford's.
It gets to be a little bit of a run on it.
I think you can, you can.
Yeah.
Historic significance.
I think you could, you could lose in historic significance.
Well, I might take it out if we wanna do a live edit, I could.
Yeah, sure.
Take that piece, maybe I should take that.
Historic heritage, comma, then historic significance.
And neighborhoods.
And then pop in.
Yeah, sounds good, looks good.
in order to safeguard the city's architectural heritage, historic significance, and the character of our historic neighborhoods.
Yeah.
Sounds great.
Great.
Yeah.
Okay.
Do you want to put the word Medford in there and the character of our historic Medford neighborhoods?
No, I don't think any of that covers it.
It's only Medford all the way through.
guidelines have been developed to encourage renovations, alterations, and the new construction to respect the design fabric of the districts and maintain the architectural and historical integrity.
So I think that's a good general approach.
That's the big umbrella we're working under here.
Sure.
Okay.
How about B?
Let's see.
Anybody have comments on B?
Let's just go through C. Yeah, yeah, I think C is important.
Because a lot of these houses have additions from later centuries.
And I think that's, I was impressed by some of the all sort of saying these things change over time.
They're not frozen and everything is changing constantly.
So
even non-original changes can become historic over time.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, D looks good.
Any comments on D?
Okay, let's see.
E, anybody comments on E?
No.
Okay.
Yeah.
Well, the only thing I would say about D, I mean, with respect to their physical properties, that might be interpreted to say you have to replace wood with wood or glass with glass or iron with iron.
And I wonder if that could be taken out.
And really, it's more just the design value, the texture and visual qualities than
Yeah, maybe visual rather than physical or something like that.
Well, visual quality is in this.
I might just consider striking out that, I don't know where the strikeout thing is in here.
I'm not familiar with this one here.
I think in Google, if you're editing in Google, if you just backspace, I think it does it, but I could be wrong.
I don't know if this doesn't seem to have the track changes.
You have to go up to see where it says editing in the top right hand corner.
Hit that little triangle down next to editing.
Up a little bit more.
To the right.
No, to the right of that.
See where it says editing?
No, I don't.
To the right of that, Fred.
The right of that.
I think it's covered.
Right underneath where it says share.
Under the blue button where it says share.
Here it is.
All right.
Editing.
Yes.
Code is suggesting.
Okay.
Thank you.
That was covered by all your pictures, everyone.
So.
So in this case, then if I delete that, there it goes.
It takes just cross that out.
Okay.
Thank you, Melanie.
Yeah.
You're welcome to take over this, Melanie, next time.
So you can be there.
This is good precedence for how to do this communally, if it works.
Yeah.
So that, I think that just loosens up our ability to demand.
I don't think we have to demand, you know, eye for an eye replacement of things.
Apples and oranges a little bit.
Okay.
Any comments on one or two?
I had a comment on number two, but I think Fred just took care of it with that last change.
I wanted to add a sentence at the end of two saying modern materials can be considered, but if that's taken care of with the change that we did in F,
I'm fine with just leaving it the way it is.
Okay.
I think that's a good intent of it.
Excuse me.
I'm sorry.
Is that matching originals?
Maybe I should say, maybe we should add some little disclaimer in there.
So we get some wiggle room in there.
Like if we leave it, like if we leave it in big, like a,
very broad than people would just present it.
And then we could just, so we could say something like modern materials can be considered so that as tech, you know, as things go along, you know, people could present different, you know, things and see if it works out with the overall design of the house.
Yeah.
I wonder what new materials that match the originals, maybe we could just,
that as closely as possible.
I mean, that gives us some wiggle room, I guess, in there.
You can say resemble, match or resemble.
Or resemble the originals as closely as possible, something like that.
Let's call the wiggle room.
Yeah, I think that's a very good suggestion, Joe.
Thank you.
Does that cover your concern, Joe?
I can't actually read what the screen share.
My wife's feeding my kids right now, so I'm trying to have her come in and expand it for me.
But I'm sure that what you put down is going to be fine.
OK.
Okay, so I think that match or resemble the original as closely as possible.
So, yeah.
Okay.
And then for three, this is my edit.
I just wanted to be more, to sort of be more positive.
Yeah, but that's not an outrageous statement when you look at it.
I definitely understand what you're saying, but synthetic signing, it kind of, it really is a nice, simple, right?
That's pretty straight ahead, right?
That's generally discouraged.
Not saying you can't, just saying generally discouraged, but you didn't want to lead with that, Chris Bader, you didn't want to lead with that.
I didn't want to lead with that.
Yeah.
And it says, you know, this is a group decision here.
Yeah, but it says it underneath, you think in the terms,
In the text, it does talk about synthetic siding, but you just didn't want that first line in there.
I just didn't want it first, right?
Yeah.
Okay.
That's what that's all about.
Cause it does say synthetic siding.
You know, if they do put it up because of hardship, you know, you can't really stop them, but we'd prefer.
Okay.
So you want to take that out?
Was it the decision, Brett?
Yeah, that's okay with me.
It's already crossed out here, so we can just keep it out.
Okay, okay.
And then it does give you the option for synthetic siding in the second part of it.
Yeah, yeah.
And it leads with a positive thing, would strongly encourage wood and brick historic materials.
Okay, moving on.
Okay, let's see.
I didn't have any comments on masonry and stone.
Anybody else?
Okay.
How about roofs?
Now this is my own personal hobby horse, but if other people want to say the solar panels, because I consider them personally, I consider them an eyesore, but.
They are an eyesore.
But if they're on the opposite side, is one of the premise, Chris Bader, and if I can ask a question, is one of the premises is viewability, you know?
So if it's not being shown, is that, let's say for solar panels as an example, is that?
Well, it already mentions here that it'd be discreetly placed.
Actually, you should, that's not the correct spelling.
You don't mean discreetly in that sense.
You mean, how do you spell discreetly?
I don't know.
And no, not E-T-E, but E-E-E-E-T.
Oh, yeah.
All right.
Does it come up with the discrete?
There we go.
Yep.
That's the one you want.
That's what you mean.
All right, Chris Bader.
Yeah, I got that.
Well, I have a PhD in linguistics.
And here's where it came into play.
I had something I wanted to add on roofs, the second section.
I wanted, I think that, so at the end of the sentence where it says installation details, I would say like are encouraged and then add like a similar, like we did above to like modern roofing materials can be considered.
I don't know if that's okay or not.
Where are we, where are we?
Roofs number two, Fred.
Roofs number two.
I was gonna, I was gonna paste out.
We could say, we could take this out.
And in position of hardship.
Yeah, I could just copy that out.
Go down here to roofs two and put that in.
You're in masonry.
Oh, Bruce, I'm in two here.
Correct.
And then we'd say, in those cases where reason of demonstrated hardships and synthetic roofing is proposed, something like that.
And there's a second one as well.
New roofing.
Correct.
I would say rather than reproduce it, it should resemble, which we had up earlier in there, should the original.
I meant to the word resemble.
As closely as possible.
Yeah.
You like that, Joe?
Yes, I do.
That's excellent.
Also on, I don't know if I'm skipping ahead here, but on the solar panels, which was line item six, I also wanted to add like solar panels and associated wiring.
So I, because what I've noticed on a lot of the solar panel installations is the wiring run down the house is, it's brutal looking.
You know, it's almost
You know, so I don't know how we'd go about doing that.
Maybe solar panels.
And wiring.
And associated wiring.
Yeah, good job.
Solar panels and related wiring, and other mechanical rooftop components like, you know, air handlers and fans and rooftop stuff will be considered on a case by case basis.
Sounds good.
I would just get rid of the first and.
So just solar panels, related wiring, and other.
There we go.
Yeah.
OK, great.
Everybody happy with this?
Yeah, put it in the rear or put it in the side of the property if possible.
Love it.
Yeah.
On here.
As far as windows and doors, one, I just want to, for example, give just from my own personal experience with a house that's actually in one of our historic districts.
I put in a new bathroom, a whole new bathroom, and I wanted a window in it.
So I put in a wood window that resembled the other windows.
You know, there are situations I think where we want to allow with, you know, new windows.
Or even the removal of windows sometimes.
All right, well, that was from the original Somerville thing that sentence.
Oh, we could take that out.
I don't have a problem with that.
Okay, great.
Yeah, I agree.
I think that's excellent.
And what I was thinking of doing, you know, and of course, just run it by like, so number two,
adding a sentence like, when modern windows are being considered, it would be recommended to use simulated divided light as the preferred option.
Explain that, Joe.
So if a window is going to be replaced in the structure with a modern window to have one that would have the simulated divided light,
So it would be like a simulated divided light.
So what they'll, what they do is, is the, the sash itself, um, it's a, you know, double or triple pain sash, which would mean, you know, two pieces of glass that would have, um, you know, I've gone filling or, or something like that.
And then have, um, you know, on the, on the exterior of the glass of an applied, uh, mutton.
and then in between the two glass, another mutton, and then one on the inside, so that it simulates, you know, the old windows with the, you know, with the muttons of the original windows.
You're saying there's a visual replacement with the old windows to look like it's older?
Yes, so that so if you were going to do a replacement window, you know, if that was going to be considered, you know, it would be much better to do one that's a simulated divided light window, as opposed to, you know, one with, you know, eliminating the muttons in the, you know, the design of the lights of glass
The only thing I'd say about that, Joe, is we probably should ask for authentic divided lights as ADL and SDL.
Authentic divided lights really have individual sheets of glass separated by a muntin as opposed to simulated divided lights, which just have a, like a glue on thing.
So I want, is that part of your intent that we, or are you really distinguishing between authentic divided lights and simulated divided lights?
I don't, I mean, I'm not, so if everyone feels that they want to stick totally with authentic divided light, that's fine.
I like, you know, I like the option of having, you know, simulated divided light in certain circumstances, you know, especially, you know, heading forward with the, you know, with the way things are going with energy costs and,
you know, the way things are going with that, you know, having that option, you know, it's not, if everyone doesn't agree with that, I can definitely move on.
No, no, I would agree with that, Joe, with the following qualification.
If it's indistinguishable from authentic divided lights.
Well, you'll never get that because, I mean, the beauty of authentic divided light windows is that when the,
You know, when the glazing it goes into the into the sash, they're just a little bit off from each other.
So when you look at the house, it has that.
I mean, it's fantastic, you know.
You know, I'm just thinking going forward with, you know, and we can always revisit it later on sometime, too.
I don't want to hold it up on that.
Well, I would say this, Joe, and
I think it's a very sensitive issue here.
We battle over windows more than we should.
So I would try to leave it as open to our discretion as possible, because I'm a little worried.
I wouldn't put authentic divided lights in there, because I think that's going to be like a rock against the glass, if we insist on that.
And simulated divided lights, I think, are a no-brainer.
We could easily get that through.
I'm just trying to keep things, keep our options as open as possible here.
Okay.
You just want to leave it the way it is, Fred?
Well, you added the word mountains, and I think that's critical that we, and so I don't know how to, whether we want to say,
in new window situations.
So again, I'm not sure we want to lock ourselves in.
You would simulate a divided lights is acceptable, but basically we're asking them to come in front of us and make their case for whatever windows they're proposing.
Okay.
So how do we, how do we, do we need to say that?
Or we just leave it the way it is?
Well, that's why I think number three,
I think it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's,
It's a killer when people come with us and we have to fight over the windows.
Yeah, yeah.
So I'm happy to leave it as it is, or I can add one sentence about, again, it's what we've added to these other ones.
And I agree with you, Joe, it's good to put that in there.
Individual instances where synthetic or artificial divided lights are proposed
should resemble the original as closely as possible.
Something like that is sort of what we're trying to get at with all these things, I think.
So I'm sorry, going up and edit that.
So I'll leave it to you guys to sort of sort it out what we want to do on this one.
It sounds like good starting points, Fred.
It sounds like a deeper discussion in windows, like if we wanted to get another little side committee on another day, but just moving forward.
But that's great, Joe.
Thanks for adding some insight to that world.
Yeah, no problem.
All right, so we're just leaving it the way it is for the time being?
Yeah, I'm going to move right on.
That's not a problem.
OK, sure.
OK, so I added number four.
Yeah.
Should I even, should we even be mentioning materials?
In this congressional vote for wood.
Well, you're strongly encouraging.
I don't, I, I don't know.
We necessarily want to strongly encourage much of anything with regards to windows.
I don't know.
It's a very sensitive topic.
I, you know, when I look at houses that have the original windows that historic, there's a huge difference.
I mean, Oh, absolutely.
And if I can replace all the windows on my house to be more like on the original, I would, I know that it's expensive.
Um, I think by encouraging them to do it as one thing, but we're not saying that we're not, we're not going to approve it.
Right.
It's more for the replacement window.
And we've covered this a lot in previous applications.
It's the details of the jam liner and the sash and all that stuff.
I was trying to stay away from hard language that sort of dictates those sorts of things.
Do you want to strike four?
I think myself it's a little,
I don't think it's adding necessarily to our case here.
Okay, so let's just strike four.
Yeah, that's fine by me.
Everyone all right with that then?
Okay.
Yep, that's fine.
Let's see.
Should be retained and repaired, yep.
Is there a comment there somewhere?
I can't see it.
There's a comment in the document.
Oh, yeah.
This comment over here.
I think that's just from my editing over here.
And then Sharon says there is no material indistinguishable.
squats that one as well.
So that relates to this one we just talked about.
Okay.
Anybody have a comment on porches?
I'd like to add, you know, regarding the railing systems, which is a, it's kind of a difficult one, but like, you know, if you're replacing the railings, you know, that we would consider,
if it's okay to consider, you know, railing systems that are not wood, you know, that are, you know, a modern material.
But the only problem I see, so I'm saying that, but the problem that I see with that is, you know, there are some manufacturers that do have historic and excellent looking profiles.
And then there's, you know, other ones that are,
They're nice looking, but you know, they're a modern profile.
So, you know, is that something that's worth leaving out or is that something worth adding in so that, you know, I'm just, you know, I'll go with what other people are saying on that.
Well, I'll mention that, Joe, that number two under E, Porches and Steps,
if new exterior components are needed, i.e.
a synthetic or artificial one, they should match as closely as possible.
And that opens up, in my opinion, all these systems that you're talking about that have historic character, they may not be wood, but they are meant to resemble wood.
So I think number two is trying to leave the door open.
Perfect, okay, yeah, yeah, okay, yep.
I agree.
Excellent.
OK.
All right.
Anybody else on couches?
OK, new additions?
Let's see.
And so what they're trying to do in Somerville, and I agree with it, and we've done it somewhat in our things, is that, you know, you don't have to just copy and paste the part of the house over to the addition.
We've got the historic property.
If it's historic in nature, we want to retain the historic integrity of the original building, but additions can be of slightly different character that we want to
I think they're trying to.
Sort of make them subservient to the appearance of the original building, but they do not have to match it.
What they're trying to get at in this.
In these.
Items here.
How about.
You know, again, trying to emphasize the positive here.
Maybe new year should, should.
You know,
not resemble, but what's the architectural term for something that's, you know, compatible with or?
Well, it says in number one, it says the integrity of the property should be compatible in size, scale, material and character of the property and neighborhood.
I would take maybe the next one out addition should be confined to rear sides, but that's
I mean, I don't know.
I mean, I think that again, there's a disclaimer that whenever possible.
So.
Okay.
It's not possible.
I got to put a. Addition in the front of my house and then we have to deal with it as a commission.
So I think that this is a. Good language to.
Yeah.
You know, sort of leave some wiggle room around what you can.
Sure.
Scale of the addition.
I'm okay with the way it is, but I'm not sure the first clause really helps us very much.
Why not just have a new addition should be compatible in size, scale, material, and character.
We're trying to emphasize what people can do rather than what they can't do.
All right.
So new additions should be should.
I'm going to play devil's advocate here for a second.
Um.
So I mean, some of the reasons I think that we're trying to develop these historic districts is to prevent
You know, I think from an individual perspective, I can see where a developer would use this as a loophole to do whatever they want.
I'm just saying, that's all.
I think it's a good idea.
Without having that in there.
So I think there's an opportunity for people to still come and get it in their front.
But what we're saying is most cases, I don't know, that's just I'm playing devil's advocate here.
Well, again, all these languages and I added a lot of this stuff.
It should generally not.
I mean, trying to leave us as much.
Yeah, that's why I don't think you need to delete it.
Why don't we just leave it in there.
Yeah.
I mean, that's, I think, because, like you said, Melanie, a lot of these additions there.
They're the tail wagging the house at some point, they become bigger than you build them, so.
Okay, okay.
Anybody, any other comments on two, on one?
Okay.
I mean, I think two is good.
I'm not sure it means much to the layman.
Well, as for the architects, that gives them a little opportunity to provide designs that are sympathetic.
Yeah, let's leave it in.
Without copying things.
Yeah.
Oh, and three, I think, is important, too.
OK, any other comments on new additions?
No, it looks fine.
OK.
All right, penthouses.
Now this, well this is just, I don't have a problem with the language of G and H, but I just wonder if they're necessary.
Yeah, what buildings does this apply to?
Yeah.
In other historic districts, I've done a lot of rooftop balconies and dormers and all that sort of stuff.
And I'm thinking this might apply more if we ever get to a Medford Square historic district that those sorts of things come up.
So we don't deal often with rooftop addition.
So if we wanna strike it out and if we need to add it in later, we could, but it was in the Somerville guidelines.
That's why it's in here.
So, but this is not just the, it's not just a deck, but you're talking about just additions, right, too, and going up further, right?
These are vertical, basically this is vertical additions to houses.
Yeah, so like they did that at the old, they just did a vertical addition to the old, in Manfred Square, to the old theater, where the old Elizabeth Grady was, right?
So, and that, this situation would apply to that, is that correct?
I think you're right, yeah.
Do you want to leave it in, Melanie?
I do.
Yeah.
Okay, great.
Let's leave it in.
Okay, H?
Does the word dormer go in there, Fred, or is that implied with that?
Rooftop addition would include a dormer, yeah.
I could put dormers in there, penthouses, dormers, and other rooftop additions.
That's the word we always hear, you know.
All right.
Rent house dorm is another rooftop additions.
Okay.
I like that.
Um, no.
So H you're mainly thinking of like Medford square and things.
Yep.
Memphis Square, I think Haines Square is a good place too.
There's a lot of nice architectural buildings in Haines Square.
I mean, not that any, so I'm assuming this goes to New Science as well, right?
Well, if we get a historic district in Haines Square.
Yeah, I'm just saying in the future, but yeah.
Well, and sometimes it's come up, Chris, with, you know, dental offices or real estate offices and things where people put
signs up on houses because they get converted to an office building or whatever, a dental office.
So that's why it's in there.
Yeah, yeah.
And we actually have a sign of questionable, there's a dental sign on one of the houses in the Simon's district that I don't think is that attractive.
Is that house actually in the district though?
Chris, I don't know if the line wiggles or not.
I'm not totally sure.
I would check whether it's actually in the district.
But this safeguards things in the future.
If that were in the district, we could point to this and say, your sign, we don't like it, or whatever.
Yeah, yeah.
OK.
OK, landscape.
Now, do we actually have control over things that are at grade?
Well, I should be the one to be able to answer that question.
Well, we've had a lot of discussions over the years of stone walls and retaining walls and stone features of driveways and all that stuff.
So I, the truth is if they, if they pull a permit for it, we would have authority over it.
If they, if they do it as part of, if it's not permittable, they're just putting a walk around the side.
We don't have authority really over it, but if they short on a drawing, we can, we can comment on it.
Okay.
All right, anybody have any comments on I?
Okay, Jay?
Excuse me, I'm sorry, Chris, what about trees?
And Fred, what about, you know, sometimes you have these iconic trees, but anything in there about a treetop or the treescape?
Yeah, I don't think we have any authority over trees.
Okay.
We did, but we did.
Yeah.
I think that's right.
A removal of non-original additions.
Jay looks good to me.
Any comments on Jay?
I just need a space in there.
I'll add that in there.
Because Jay and Kay start to get into
Um, and then.
Selective demolition and all that stuff.
So I think.
We would encourage.
Um, non-original addition to be removed.
Um, and then.
Kay really says, listen, if you want to demolish the whole thing.
We consider that an alteration and it's subject to our review.
So these, these sort of get to.
We want to weigh in on that.
Yeah, yeah.
No, I think this is good.
It also raises the issue, which I don't think is addressed in this draft is what about new construction, right?
We had a case a few years ago, and I think you'll remember this Fred and Charlotte,
of a guy on Governor's Ave who wanted to build an entirely new house.
And he built a modern house and the various, I think Fred and Claire both, correct me if I'm wrong, Fred, insisted that the massing of the house be consistent with the rest of the neighborhood.
Yeah, that's an excellent point, Chris, that we don't address new construction here.
That house was a perfect example of it.
And he built a very, I thought, a very nice, modern, unique house.
And I was expecting all hell to break loose when it was done and didn't get a single complaint about it at all.
And it's still there.
We can all go look at it.
I had a friend of mine architect trying to put up a new house on an empty lot in Arlington in a historic district.
And they fought him tooth and nail over a modern design.
And they ended up putting this horrible colonial ish thing in there that had no value whatsoever to anybody.
So I don't know, we could
I don't know what to say about new construction, but I could, I could try to find some language in some other guidelines.
Yeah.
I mean, that would mean we can't really approve this today, but I don't think it's crucial.
Well, again, I think we can approve it and then amend it because number three.
Okay.
So we can.
I'd like to see that.
Yeah.
Go ahead.
No, I had no comments.
Okay.
I think, I think a little section on new construction,
and that we have basically architectural review over new construction and that it's not confined to, you have to build something that looks Victorian or colonial in some sense, which is really, I agree totally with Fred that a lot of so-called colonial architecture is just absolutely horrendous kitsch.
But yeah, let's think about that for something going forward.
All right, so the amendment, I think we can put that in there.
And I would like to find some progressive language about new construction that gives us some ability to not lock ourselves into a work replication of things that don't exist.
OK.
Is it right to amend these guidelines for time?
OK, so part three.
Okay.
Looks good.
Severability.
I think that's legally necessary.
That's the end of it right there.
Yep.
Okay.
I think everybody's weighed in on this.
We have our all member commission members here.
Can I have a, do we want to approve?
Well, I would like just open the door for any last minute comments.
Anybody comments?
None for me.
Okay, Joe?
Nope, looks good.
Is Charlotte still with us?
I don't see Charlotte on my screen, but Charlotte, are you still there?
She may have dropped.
She's here.
I see her.
She's on mute.
All right, well, I'll stop the share.
There you are.
Yeah, I see Charlotte now.
Yeah, can I have a motion to approve in the form that we just went through?
And make a motion to approve the new guidelines for the historic district.
Oh, I'm sorry.
The motion should be not only to approve, but to approve posting them on the HDC website, which, by the way,
We'll be coming up next week.
It's, you know, there's been a snafu with the, with billing and they shut down the website for a little while.
Can we just come up with 25 million extra dollars on the budget?
And I would add to the motion that they're going to be, I'll put today's date on them, March 23rd, 2023.
So they have a specific date.
Okay.
Okay, yeah, so the motion is your, Chris, can you revise your motion to approve and to post on the website?
I'd like to make a motion to approve and to post on the website the new historic Medford district guidelines.
I second the motion.
Okay, thank you, Melanie.
Fred?
Yes.
Chris Donovan?
Joe?
Yes.
Okay, Charlotte?
Perfect, okay.
And I vote yes as well.
So yes, unanimously approved with all members present.
Good, good.
Well, this is huge.
I think this will really, you know, this will make our job going forward a lot easier.
Good job, Fred.
A lot of work done in that, Fred.
Good job.
It was very, very well done.
Excellent job.
I will thank you all and thank Somerville.
I copped them.
Now I'll try to, I hope I can save this version here.
That would be my next challenge here.
So yeah.
Okay.
So Charlotte, did you ever get access to that with the shared thing through Google?
And Joe, did you ever get through the shared access through that?
Chris Bader, did you?
I was able to post my
My, my comments.
Yeah.
So you Melanie did did you because I'll work with you each individually.
Work out, I should be.
I'm gonna have to let me try.
I got there.
I was able to view the original one.
And I viewed it the last before we met last.
Two weeks ago.
Um, so it's just using the Google account and then being able to pull that document up that share that's the ultimate and there's a lot of form bees in there.
There's also a folder.
What is the historic South Street historic district form bees in there.
So there's two folders one with all the Medford form bees, and the other one just a South Street district.
Form B. So that's how it's kind of organized.
And one of the files is the guidelines that Fred's working on right now, editing, and it should be updatable.
But Joe, how'd you do with yours?
Did you ever get access to it?
I was able to access it.
I was able to print it, but I wasn't able to make any changes.
alterations or changes to it.
Maybe some about editor and owner kind of stuff, but you saw it and that's big and we'll figure the other stuff out.
Maybe steps for me on this stuff, I guess.
Me too, me too.
And the form Bs, you should be able to see them.
Charlotte, finally, did you see it?
I'm all set.
Good, okay.
Chris Bader?
Yes, yes.
So I'm still looking for your email.
So I just pulled up the historic design guidelines.
But there was a folder that you sent out to wasn't there.
So just in your Google account, if you go to some subcategory to shared with me, there should be invitations from that.
But I'll resend it to you tonight and see if you can follow up.
And I'm happy to follow up.
I have two emails.
It has to be a Gmail.
It has to end with a Gmail.
Yeah.
So you have to send it to my Gmail account.
Right.
And then Tringalia Gmail.
I'll follow that.
I'll follow up on that.
Chris, our next meeting, when's our next meeting?
Our next meeting is on April 13th.
April 13th.
Okay, so to adjourn, Krista, anything else?
No, no, no, we don't want to adjourn yet.
We want to go over.
The plan.
Oh, boy, we're out of time.
The outreach plan from, from.
She did a great job of sort of outlining a bunch of things.
I don't have it right here in front of me, but maybe, maybe.
Do we want to talk about that next time or do we want to go over?
I know that you wanted, I think one of the reasons we were meeting was to go over at this time too, because there was, I felt that there was some kind of urgency to start the plan.
Wasn't that what we talked about last time?
Yes, yes.
Well, let me see if I can, let me see if I can upload it onto the screen here.
Let me just try to get it up left to my screen.
Thank you.
I got to find an email and then open it here.
I think I have it if you want me to share it.
Do you want to share it, Melanie?
You might be better off with that.
I have a lot of windows open, but so hold on a second.
I have it right here.
Share, share my screen.
Where's the button?
Down here.
Okay.
Right, can you guys see that?
Yep, yep.
Okay.
Okay, so this is a very short document, so maybe we can go through it.
And I don't think everyone has had a chance to look at it.
I only got it from sharing myself about an hour ago.
So I agree with Sharon that outreach to the owners and to the neighbors and general public are both crucial.
And by neighbors, I specifically mean butters in the sense of the statute, that is.
people who own houses or live within 300 feet of any house in the local historic district.
Chris, is there a way maybe to get that list?
Because the 18 houses are pretty finite, pretty straight ahead.
Yes, yes.
Dennis, are you still on?
What's going on, sorry?
Just wondered if you
Or, or someone in City Hall can provide us with a list of houses that are within 300 feet of any of the houses in the proposed local historic district.
Yeah, if you send me the map, the list of the houses, I can do that.
I can create a map.
It's pretty easy to do.
OK, terrific.
Yeah, I thought so.
Yeah, there's software that they have at City Hall that makes it pretty easy to do that.
So the plan will be to go after those 18 houses, and then the separate plan is to go after the abutters with 300?
Correct.
OK, so
Then stage one, she wants to reach out to, only nine are on her occupied, that's interesting.
And then let's see, anybody wanna add to this?
Who's who and who's been notified and who hasn't.
Yeah, that's kind of what that is.
So if anyone has any identifiable connections to those other ones.
You know, they can sort of chime in, but, um, right.
Sorry, my son's coming in.
I'm going to put guys on you for a second.
Yeah, we definitely want details here, like who has been notified, like which houses are owner occupied and which aren't, and which resident owners are on board and which haven't been contacted or maybe opposed.
I think we want to sort of have a spreadsheet, maybe again, shared on Google Docs, although we've had mixed results with Google Docs so far, but maybe there should be a spreadsheet on
on, yeah, we can put that up.
Yeah, Sharon did one of those last time.
I think it just needs to be copied onto Google.
She shared that with us at the last meeting.
Okay, okay.
Can you take care of that, Chris?
I will, yep.
Okay, great.
So I just have one question on this.
I know that Sharon's on here.
I know, Chris, if you, one of the things I didn't see in here, maybe it's part of the discussion is how things are going to be communicated.
Because I think that is just as important as who and when we communicate to.
Yeah, Melanie, by by email, probably by email, so I think that would be if we can get an email address of these owners and providers, too, I guess to that extent, that's getting that requires us to communicate for all communication to be.
not exclusively, but to include postal mail.
So that anytime we reach out to somebody by phone or in person or by email, we also need to reach out in writing to the people who don't necessarily have access to, for example, for properties that are not owner-occupied.
You see what I mean?
It needs to be mirrored.
Whatever we do electronically has to be mirrored with postal mail.
So that was, I guess, my question.
The other question was, what's the message?
Yeah, exactly.
We can go through that and talk about that afterwards or not, but I think one of the things that we'll go through this and we can talk about it later, I guess.
I think that's one of the key things that's missing here is like, what is the message?
Like, what are we trying to do?
I'd like to put some joy into this thing, something exciting.
And that's where I think to put all this on the table now, because this was really about the guidelines, which was a great step
But is there joy in this celebrating the South Street Historic District?
Are we talking about the shipbuilding narrative there and the Mystic River?
That's what I thought we were bringing to it.
So there should be a celebratory coming, a little press article about it.
The mayor is involved in it, the historic society involved in it to talk about this.
So we can talk about that at another time.
but that's part of this messaging.
Maybe that's essay Melanie was asking about, but how do we get this message out?
We will send them Chris Bader or some kind of postcard for those people, the abutters and the 18 people in the district.
Is that the basic thought that will at least get, well, right.
But I think, I think your point in Melanie's is, I mean, yes.
So go ahead.
My point is when you, so just given our, the history of the forestry one, and there was a lot of, um,
You know, there was a lot of good comments, a lot of people for and against.
But I think my thought was that, and Chris, I'm really leaning on you because I think you're the one, I don't know, I'm envisioning this postcard with like this old picture of like these old houses and the ship and really talking about the history and what we're trying to do rather than just saying, hey, we're gonna make this into a historic district.
But the reason behind what we're doing and why we're trying to preserve Medford's history.
I actually, I made a little trifold, you know, a piece, but to try and get that terminology on there is what I'd love to kind of go over.
It kind of was simplistic, you know, what I wrote, but I thought maybe the first thing, because we were trying not to butt heads and trying to get some goodwill for this early on was to, um, um, get the owners behind it.
Chris Kelly was saying, we really need to get the owners to drive this, which I don't get because it's us driving it.
of the story, so trying to figure out how many people really will come to City Hall.
Chris Bader, we're going to have a moment in front of City Hall to debate this.
It's going to be up or down, right?
We're going to have an up and down vote on this?
No, no.
So as far as City Hall is concerned, first there's a public hearing, which we should undoubtedly do in person, but we can also consider doing it remotely.
If we did it in person, we would want the whole city council, the whole big chamber at city hall.
And so there's that public hearing.
And after the public hearing, then there's a meeting of city council for an up or down vote on whether the historic district is gonna be approved.
And those are two separate meetings.
Okay, so according to this plan too, some of it's get something on the website about what's gonna be happening with South Street.
So when is that thought of to put on some kind of announcement that this has been underway and we'll be coming with some decisions soon and with new guidelines?
Yeah, yeah.
Well, and Chris, I'd remind us also that we need the report from Chris Skelly
Yes.
Hopefully is, is the story.
His version of the story.
We're trying to tell.
Regarding the ship building and.
Yep.
That's the preliminary study report.
Fred, the preliminary study report.
Right.
Yeah.
That's required as part of the mass historic commission guidelines.
So if we could just ask Chris,
We paid him to do this.
He has to do it ASAP, basically.
We've settled on the boundaries.
We want him in consultation with us to craft a narrative, knitting together the history of the area, the architectural heritage of the area, all that.
And we want him to do it probably before our next meeting.
Yeah, and for Melanie, for you just to say, to keep the pressure on for the step one, to reach out to those rest of those 18 homeowners to find out, you know, to tell them what's going on, I think is important.
And when we finish that, I feel like, okay, everyone who's supposed to know knows, then it's the second tier, whether it's that postcard that goes out between that and maybe something on the website, it's out there now to the public, you know, at a larger scale, and we put a flag in the ground.
Okay.
So we'll get, we'll get onto those 18 houses in the next two or three weeks, maybe for the next meeting or for the next meeting to that.
And that will be done.
And then we'll see if we can get something for the letter has to grow to the butters.
Okay.
Do you Chris is the, is the trifold.
brochure, can you put that on Google Docs so everybody can, we can go- I will, and I'll send it on email too, just for ease of- Okay, but let's, yeah, let's go over it at our next meeting the way we went over the guidelines.
I know it takes time, but I think it's important to get the language right.
So why don't we- I think I threw something out there off the guidelines, some Fred's early iteration of the guidelines on there, but it's just an idea of, it's a picture of this, you know,
I think he used grandfather's house, some little factoid, but we'll tighten it up and make it something specific.
Okay, so you'll have, you'll put that, you'll put a draft of the tri-fold up on the Google Docs, Chris?
I will.
Okay.
Let's see, and I will definitely,
get a draft, if possible, in the next week from Chris Skelly of the preliminary report, which as Fred mentioned, is actually statutorily required, but is also part of the whole outreach process.
And, okay.
So Chris, how do we do get a blurb on the historic district website?
How do we get an update on a new paragraph on there?
That will, I will work with, are you, well, we can either, there are two options.
Either somebody, it's a, what is that website software called that allows you to edit websites?
What's it called?
It's called CMS, content management solutions, but it's not that sophisticated.
What's the one that's used for web blogs?
WordPress.
WordPress, yes.
It's a WordPress site.
So conceivably someone, some member of the commission could take it on, or I can get someone at city hall to do it, or we can have the website provider do it for us.
Those are the three.
Those are the three get someone from city hall and you show me I happy to follow up on it, Chris, in the future, but be nice just to get something out about South Street.
You know, something's in the plans or, or we just, or at least we just pass some new guidelines.
Fred, right?
So we just actually just pass those guidelines.
Correct.
Let's get that out there if we could just that 1 1 blurb.
Yeah, right.
I think, you know, we've approved obviously we want to approve everything that goes on the website.
So.
Let's just put the guidelines on the website for the moment, but let's draft something.
We should probably think about a page that relates to South Street.
And we should, so- I can write that, just like two paragraphs, just a quick overview.
Yeah, can you do a first draft of that, Chris?
So you actually have two things on your plate.
Well, probably more than two, but so the, the, the trifold, you know, which is going to be a paper document and the webpage, you know, the webpage that, that will be put on the city website.
And then we can go over those and edit them and approve them and, and get them ready to go at our next meeting.
Does that sound good?
That was good.
Yep.
Okay.
And that meeting again was Fred.
April 13 April 13 to adjourn.
Um, yeah, let's just let's have a quick look at step at stage two.
Or maybe why don't we adjourn?
And you know, we were everybody's tired, I'm sure.
Step two is the website, Chris.
So it was the website and spreading the word.
So I think we just touched on that.
It gets a little deeper.
The beginning steps are to get something on the website and yeah, post something on the website.
Sounds good.
Okay.
Do people want to keep going or should we adjourn and resume on April 13th?
I, as long as we're moving this process forward and we can keep, keep hitting on these steps that we've, we've talked about and Sharon's outlined here.
Okay.
I think we just got to keep, keep the ball moving here.
Yeah.
Okay.
Um, so yeah, so let's adjourn.
Let's, uh, let's adjourn and we have three, uh, action items.
Um, uh,
Well, I guess for I should arrange for the guidelines to go up on the website, which which we've authorized.
I will also press gives Chris Kelly to get the first draft, but so hopefully.
Preliminary preliminary study report the preliminary study report and to get that finished and to get it to all members of the commission in time to review it before the April 13th meeting.
That's 2 action items for me.
And then 2 action items for Chris.
Are to put the trifold up on the.
on Google Docs and same with the proposed text for the website, the webpage.
Does that sound good?
Yep.
Okay, can I have a motion to adjourn?
Motion to adjourn.
Okay, second?
Second.
Okay, thank you, Charlotte.
Right, so Charlotte?
Yes.
Fred?
Melanie?
Yes.
Chris?
Joe?
Yes.
Okay, excellent.
And I vote yes as well.
Okay, so I'll see everybody.
Chris and I will follow up on those four action items and we'll see you all on April 13th.
All right, sounds good.
Thank you.
Thank you, everybody.