Hello Sunny Fam and welcome to your 10 minute vibration plate workout. If you're looking for a workout that's consisting of warming up and mobility, this is the place for you. So let's get started. First exercise we're going to do is neck mobility. Go ahead and start your vibration plate. Whatever setting you feel most comfortable.
Go ahead and step on. So, first, drop your right arm, your right ear, excuse me, to your right shoulder. Back to neutral. Left ear, left shoulder. Neutral. Again to the right. Enjoy the stretch. Neutral.
Left ear, left shoulder. Go ahead and pause the beat. Back to neutral. Now what we're gonna do is go ahead and drop that right ear to the right shoulder. But then you're gonna pivot your chin down to the shoulder and look down with your eyes.
You'll be feeling a nice pull just behind the ear. Hold it a few beats. Head up, back to central. Go ahead and drop that left ear, left shoulder. Once again, now you're gonna turn your chin to the left shoulder. Once again, you'll get a nice pull right behind the ear and down the neck. Come back to neutral. Now we'll do some rotations. Go ahead and look over your right shoulder.
Pause. Neutral. Left. Neutral. Right. Neutral. Left. Neutral. One more time on each side. And left.
Now we're gonna do a bit of lymphatic drainage. We're gonna start with the right hand going over the left, just underneath your left chin and make the figure eight under the chin and down the neck. This helps get rid of swelling, waste and toxic. Go ahead and keep pulling. Doesn't have to be nice and firm, doesn't have to be hard. Right across the chin, down the neck.
against the chin and down the neck. Go ahead and start on the right side. Again, under the chin and pull on down the neck. Chin and pull down the neck. Again with the chin and pull down the neck. There's no rush, enjoy.
Let's go and back to the left side. Let's do five on this side. Nice and smooth. And then we'll go back to the right. Last one here. You even have lift nodes right under your clavicle. So if you would like some massaging just above the clavicle.
A few strokes, you can do that as well. Now we'll start with some torso rotations. You can have your arms completely out if you like, or fist to fist where your elbows are out. Go ahead and rotate to the right. Neutral. Left. Neutral. Right again. You can pause for a beat there. Back to neutral.
Left, back to neutral. Right again, back to neutral. This is so good for circulation. It can be used again as a warm up, a cool down, first thing in the morning. Left, back to neutral.
Right. We're gonna pick up the pace a bit. And when we pick up the pace, we're gonna double up on each side. So starting with the right. One and two. To neutral. One and two. If you have any lower back issues, be mindful that you don't overdo it. But it also helps getting the range of motion in your thoracic spine, especially if you do a lot of seating all day.
Back to neutral, double up. Neutral. Go ahead and do it with your arms fully extended. Gives you a totally different sensation. If you want to pick up the pace, you most certainly can. Right, neutral, left, neutral. Right, neutral, left, neutral.
Our next exercises will be calf raises. If you're new to the vibration plate, you can have a chair placed on the side of you where it can help with your balance. You can even be close to a wall. You're gonna go up on your toes. You're not holding for long because once again, you're on a vibration plate. So up and down smooth. Up, down smooth. You can put your hands on your hips if you like. If you need more assistance with balance,
You can do your hands out, one hand out, one hand, the other hand on your hips, whichever is most comfortable for you. You will get a burn on this. The reason being is because with that pause, your calves and the arch of your Achilles have to work a little bit harder. If this is a little too extreme for you and you're getting a burn, you can go ahead and alternate.
just simply rotating each foot heel to toe. Again, make sure you're breathing, keeping your core tight, shoulders back, chest up, proper posture. You don't wanna be hunching over. For one, it's hard to breathe that way. Two, it doesn't look good on anyone. If you wanna finish out, you can go back up to regular calf raises.
Check in with yourself. Remember, the hardest part is showing up, so I'm proud of you for just even gauging, making the attempt. You'll get better over time. Rome was not built in a day. Going back to alternating if you like. We have 10 more seconds here. The next exercise will be good mornings. You'll be placing your hands behind your head.
Go ahead and make sure you still have a shoulder-width stance. Placing your feet, make sure you're dead center. Hands behind your head, draw in your core. Make sure you're breathing and held your nose. And you're just gonna hinge at the hips. Meaning that your hips are gonna extend outward behind you, and up nice and slow. Find whatever cadence is most comfortable for you. One, two, three, pause. One, two, three, up.
Keep your core tight, one, two, three, pause. One, two, three, up. You'll feel this in your hamstrings. You're gonna probably feel this in your calves a bit too, because we just finished doing calf raises. So this is a good mobility, full body warmup, lymphatic drainage, in addition to helping with your circulation.
Nice and smooth. Down nice and slow. Pause. Up nice and smooth. Let's go down by four, pause for four, and up for four. One, two, three, four, pause. One, two, three, four, up. One, two, three, four, back down.
Please make sure you're not holding your breath. Make sure you're breathing. Periodically, you can take that deep, cleansing breath. Inhale through the nose. Blow out through the mouth. If you're not certain that you're breathing, because sometimes we do shallow breathing, you can actually make a sound with your breath.
All right, now it's time to cool down. You guys are almost there. Arms down. We're just gonna do hip sways, and that's literally what you're gonna do. You're just rocking back and forth. If you want, you can do rocks and circles. Hands on your hips. This is primarily, like I said, for a warmup. Also, just to get you used to the equipment.
Go ahead and alternate. You can go the opposite way, or you can just stick with the sways. Want to spice things up a bit, go ahead and add your arms. Deep, cleansing breaths. We're gonna go back to calf raises.
Just 30 seconds. Here we go. Once again, if calf raises is too difficult, use a chair, a wall, countertop, or alternate. Just toe to heel, alternate feet.
We're stopping in 5, 4, 3, 2, 1. Thanks Sunny fam, I appreciate it. See you guys next time.
If you've enjoyed this workout, I invite you to follow me on the SunnyFit app. There, you'll find more classes from me. I am on the cycle, I am on the rowers, and I also teach dumbbells. Plus, many more from all of our awesome Sunny trainers. If you haven't downloaded the SunnyFit app yet, click the link in the description below.