Es que yo le había regalado tanto cariño en las vacaciones. Ya, ya, ya mi hijita. Por favor no es para tanto. Hey guys! Welcome back to school! Hello! Welcome back to school! Yeah! Today, we're going to learn about the alphabet in Spanish.
It's called el alfabeto. But first, like and subscribe. Look down below and look for the subscribe button. What do you do on your vacation, Maria?
We went to Disney World. I went to Disney World too. It was so fun. I didn't get the dress, but it was so much fun. Like, really. Literally, so much fun. So, I went to the Little Mermaids. And guess what? I went to a fun rollercoaster.
And I was almost gonna pass out, but it was still fun! It was really, really fun. Okay, let's start. First, let's talk about the alphabets. Let's say them. Repeat after me. Okay. A, I mean, ah.
Music. A, B, C, D, E, F, G, H, I, J, K, L, M, N, N. N, yeah. N. I'm just being silly sometimes. Okay.
Eñe, O, T, Q, R, S, T, U, W, X, Y, Z! It was so fun, right?
Yeah! But let's see how many letters are there. Count with me. Okay. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12,
13, 18, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27. Oh, there's 27 letters. But now, let's say, let's do
the English this time. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20.
21, 22, 23, 24, 25, and 26. That's 26 letters. Hmm. How does that even do that? 27 letters here. 26 letters here. We could do more than that. 26 is less.
27 is more than 26. Okay, let's do the vowels. Vulgaris. Okay, let's say the letters. But this time,
A, E, I, O, U. Hmm. Let's see. Let's see. Where's the letters in this picture? Hmm. Is it right here? No. Is it right here? No. Is it right here? Yeah. How? This.
Oh, it is the letter A. Ah. See you next time. Okay, welcome to part two. Okay, but this time we're gonna do the vowels but with words. Palabra.
and the vowels okay let's draw something okay let's draw a eyeball I know what it is okay eyeball estrella
A star! I know! An island!
Coconuts Coco, Coco, Coconuts, Coconuts Now last one We got three right! I know! Bear!
It's easy. Just circle to here.
Olives. Grapes, they're healthy for you. One, two, three, four,
I'm going to play I'm going to play I'm going to play
Estrella, star. Isla, island. Oso, bear. Last one. Uvas, grapes. A, e, i, o, u. It was a fun, fun time having fun with you and learning with you.
bye guys next time i'll i'll teach you how to tie your shoes but next time bye guys
Hey guys! Welcome back to school! Welcome back to school! Today, we're going to learn about the alphabet in Spanish.
It's called El Alphabeto. El Alphabeto. But first, like and subscribe. Look down below and look for the subscribe button.
What do you do in your vacation, Maria? You went to Disney World. I went to Disney World too. It was so fun. I didn't get to dress, but it was so much fun. Like, really. Literally, so much fun. So, I went to
to Little Mermaids, and guess what? I went to a fun roller coaster. And I was almost gonna pass out, but it was still fun! It was really, really fun. Okay, let's start. First, let's talk about the alphabet. Let's say the alphabet.
Repeat after me. A, I mean, ah, music. A, B, C, D, E, F, G, H, I, J, K, L, M, N,
I was just being silly sometimes. Okay. N-J-O-P-Q-R-S-T-U-V-W-X
It was so fun, right? But let's see how many letters are there. Count with me. One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight,
nine, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27. Oh, there's 27 letters. But now,
Let's do the English this time. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.
18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, and 26. That's 26 letters. How does that even do that? 27 letters here, 26 letters here. We could do more than that.
26 is less than 27. 27 is more than 26. Okay, let's do the vowels. Vocales.
Okay, let's say the letters. But this time it's gonna be a little different. A, E, I, O, U. Hmm. Hmm. Let's see, let's see.
Where's the letters in this picture? Is it right here? No. Is it right here? No. Is it right here? Yeah. How? This, this. It is the letter A! Ah! Let's spell it. But,
See you next time. Okay, welcome to part two. Okay, but this time we're gonna do the vowels but with words. Palabras. E. E and the vowels. Okay, let's draw something.
Okay, let's draw a eyeball. I know what it is!
okay a star
Hmm, Isla. Hmm. I know an island. Dot, dot, dot, dot. Sand. This is the sand. Now the tree.
Coconuts. Coco, coco, coconuts, coconuts. Now last one. We got three right. Okay. Also. I know! Bear.
It's easy. Draw a circle. Two ears.
Grapes, they're healthy for you. One, two, three, four,
and I'm for trees.
Estrella, star. Isla, island. Oso, bear. Last one. Uvas, grapes. A, e, i, o, u. It was a fun, fun time having fun with you and learning with you.
Bye guys! Next time, I'll teach you how to tie your shoes. But next time. Bye guys! Hey guys! Today we're going to learn about the alphabet in Spanish. It's called, El Alphabeto. But first,
like and subscribe but what do you do on your vacation maria what did you do in the vacation you went to disney world so good i went to disney world before with my daddy um i saw the princesses i didn't get the dress but it was still fun
saw a little mermaid i saw everything even i went to a fun roller coaster in disney world it was very very fun but i was almost gonna pass out it was very very fun okay okay who else did on who else go with
Hey guys! Welcome back to school! Welcome back to school! Today, we're going to learn about the alphabet in Spanish!
It's called El Alphabeto. El Alphabeto. But first, like and subscribe. Look down below and look for the subscribe button.
What do you do in your vacation, Maria? You went to Disney World. I went to Disney World, too. It was so fun. I didn't get to dress, but it was so much fun. Like, really. Literally, so much fun. So, I went to
to Little Mermaids, and guess what? I went to a fun rollercoaster. And I was almost gonna pass out, but it was still fun! It was really, really fun. Okay, let's start. First, let's talk about the alphabet. Let's say the alphabet.
Repeat after me. A, I mean, a, music. A, B, C, D, E, F, G, H, I, J, K, L, M, N,
I was just being silly sometimes. Okay. N-I-E-O-P-Q-R-S-T-U-V-W-X
It was so fun, right? But let's see how many letters are there. Count with me. One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight,
nine, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27. Oh, there's 27 letters. But now,
Let's do the English this time. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.
18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, and 26. That's 26 letters. How does that even do that? 27 letters here, 26 letters here. We could do more than that.
26 is less than 27. 27 is more than 26. Okay, let's do the vowels. Vocales.
Okay, let's say the letters. But this time it's gonna be a little different. A, E, I, O, U. Hmm. Hmm. Let's see, let's see.
Where's the letters in this picture? Is it right here? No. Is it right here? No. Is it right here? Yeah. How? This, this. It is the letter A! Ah! Let's spell it. But,
See you next time. Okay, welcome to part two. Okay, but this time we're gonna do the vowels, but with words. Palabras. E. E and the vowels. Okay, let's draw something.
Okay, let's draw a eyeball. I know what it is!
Okay. Arbol! Estrella.
Isla. I know an island. Sand. This is the sand. And now the tree.
Coconuts. Coco, coco, coconuts, coconuts. Now last one. We got three right. Okay. Also. I know! Bear.
It's easy to draw a circle to your
Grapes! They're healthy fruits.
1, 2, 3, 4, and 5. OK.
Arbol, tree. Estrella, star. Isla, island. Oso, bear. Last one. Uvas, grapes. A, e, i, o, u.
It was a fun, fun time having fun with you and learning with you. Bye guys. Next time, I'll teach you how to tie your shoes. But next time. Bye guys. Hey guys, today we're gonna learn about the alphabet in Spanish. It's called,
Alphabeto. But first, like and subscribe. But what do you do on your vacation? Maria, what did you do on the vacation? You went to Disney World. So good. I went to Disney World before with my daddy.
I saw the princesses, I didn't get the dress, but it was still fun. I saw the little mermaid, I saw everything. Even I went to a fun rollercoaster in Disney World. It was very, very fun, but I was almost gonna pass out. It was very, very fun. Okay. Okay. Who else did on, who else go with me?
Es que yo le había regalado tanto cariño en las vacaciones. Ya, ya, ya mi hijita. Por favor no es para tanto. Hey guys! Welcome back to school. Hello. Welcome back to school. Yeah! Today we're going to learn about the alphabet in Spanish.
It's called el alfabeto. But first, like and subscribe. Look down below and look for the subscribe button. What do you do on your vacation, Maria?
We went to Disney World. I went to Disney World too. It was so fun. I didn't get the dress, but it was so much fun. Like, really. Literally, so much fun. So, I went to the Little Mermaids. And guess what? I went to a fun roller coaster.
and I was almost gonna pass out, but it was still fun! It was really, really fun. Okay, let's start. First, let's talk about the alphabets. Let's say them. Repeat after me. Okay. A, I mean ah,
Let me see. A, B, C, D, E, F, G, H, I, J, K, L, M, N. N, yeah. N. I was just being silly sometimes. Okay.
Eñe, O, T, Q, R, S, T, U, V, W, X, Y, Z It was so fun, right?
Yeah! But let's see how many letters are there. Count with me. Okay. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12,
13, 18, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27. Oh, there's 27 letters. But now, let's say, let's do
the English this time. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20.
21, 22, 23, 24, 25, and 26. That's 26 letters. Hmm. How does that even do that? 27 letters here. 26 letters here. We could do more than that. 26 is less.
27 is more than 26. Okay, let's do the vowels. Vulgaris. Okay, let's say the letters. But this time it's gonna be
A, E, I, O, U. Hmm. Let's see. Let's see. Where's the letters in this picture? Hmm. Is it right here? No. Is it right here? No. Is it right here? Yeah. How? This.
Oh, it is the letter A. Ah. See you next time. Okay, welcome to part two. Okay, but this time we're gonna do the vowels but with words. Palabra.
E and the vowels. Okay, let's draw something. Okay, let's draw a eyeball. I know what it is. Okay. Eyeball. Estrella.
A star! I know! An island!
Coconuts. Coco, coco, coconuts, coconuts. Now last one. We got three right. Okay. Also. Okay. I know! Bear.
It's easy, just circle to the edge.
Ostrils. Ovas. Grapes, they're healthy for you. One, two, three, four,
I bought a tree!
Estrella, star. Isla, island. Oso, bear. Last one. Uvas, grapes. A, e, i, o, u. It was a fun, fun time having fun with you and learning with you.
bye guys next time i'll i'll teach you how to tie your shoes but next time bye guys
Es que yo le había agarrado tanto cariño en las vacaciones. Ya, ya, ya mi hijita. Por favor no esperes tanto. Hey guys! Welcome back to school. Hello. Welcome back to school. Yeah! Today we're going to learn about the alphabet in Spanish.
It's called el alfabeto. But first, like and subscribe. Click down below and look for the subscribe button. What do you do in your vacation, Maria?
He went to Disney World. I went to Disney World too. It was so fun. I didn't get the dress, but it was so much fun. Like, really. Literally, so much fun. So, I went to the Little Mermaids. And guess what? I went to a fun roller coaster.
and I was almost gonna pass out, but it was still fun! It was really, really fun. Okay, let's start. First, let's talk about the alphabet. Let's say them. Repeat after me. Okay. A, I mean, ah.
Let me see. A, B, C, D, E, F, G, H, I, J, K, L, M, N, N, N, yeah. N. I was just being silly sometimes. Okay.
N, O, T, Q, R, S, T, U, W, X, Y, Z! It was so fun, right?
Yeah! But let's see how many letters are there. Count with me. Okay. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12,
13, 18, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27. Oh, there's 27 letters. But now, let's say, let's do
the English this time. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20.
21, 22, 23, 24, 25, and 26. That's 26 letters. Hmm. How does that even do that? 27 letters here. 26 letters here. We could do more than that. 26 is less.
27 is more than 26 okay let's do the vowels vocalis okay let's say the letters but this time it's gonna be
A, E, I, O, U. Hmm. Let's see. Let's see. Where's the letters in this picture? Hmm. Is it right here? No. Is it right here? No. Is it right here? Yeah. How? This.
Oh, it is the letter A. Ah. See you next time. Okay, welcome to part two. Okay, but this time we're gonna do the vowels, but with words. Palabras y palabras.
E and the vowels. Okay, let's draw something. Okay, let's draw a eyeball. I know what it is. Okay. Eyeball. Estrella.
A star! I know! An island!
Coconuts. Coco, coco, coconuts, coconuts. Now last one. We got three right. Okay. Also. Okay. I know! Bear. Rawr. It's easy.
One, two, three.
Mussels. Uvas. Grapes, they're healthy for you. One, two, three.
I want a tree.
Estrella, star. Isla, island. Oso, bear. Last one. Uvas, grapes. A, e, i, o, u. It was a fun, fun time having fun with you and learning with you.
bye guys next time i'll i'll teach you how to tie your shoes but next time bye guys
Es que yo le había agarrado tanto cariño a las vacaciones. Ya, ya, ya, ya, mi hijita, por favor, no es para tanto. Hey guys, welcome back to school. Welcome back to school. Today, we're going to learn about the alphabet in Spanish.
It's called El Alphabeto. El Alphabeto. But first, like and subscribe. Look down below and look for the subscribe button.
What do you do in your vacation, Maria? You went to Disney World. I went to Disney World, too. It was so fun. I didn't get the dress, but it was so much fun. Like, really. Literally, so much fun. So, I went to
to Little Mermaids, and guess what? I went to a fun rollercoaster. And I was almost gonna pass out, but it was still fun! It was really, really fun. Okay, let's start. First, let's talk about the alphabet. Let's say the alphabet.
Repeat after me. A, I mean, ah, music. A, B, C, D, E, F, G, H, I, J, K, L, M, N,
N. I was just being silly sometimes. Okay. N, O, T, Q, R, S, T, U, V, W, X,
It was so fun, right? But let's see how many letters are there. Count with me. One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight,
nine, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27. Oh, there's 27 letters.
But now, let's say, let's do the English this time. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.
18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, and 26. That's 26 letters. How does that even do that? 27 letters here, 26 letters here. We could do more than that.
26 is less than 27. 27 is more than 26. Okay, let's do the vowels. Vocales.
Okay, let's say the letters. But this time it's gonna be a little different. A, E, I, O, U. Hmm. Hmm. Let's see, let's see.
Where's the letters in this picture? Is it right here? No. Is it right here? No. Is it right here? Yeah. How? This, this. It is the letter A! Ah! Let's spell it. But,
See you next time. Okay, welcome to part two. Okay, but this time we're gonna do the vowels, but with words. Palabras. E. E and the vowels. Okay, let's draw something.
Okay, let's draw a eyeball. I know what it is!
okay a star
Isla. I know an island. Sand. This is the sand. And now the tree.
Coconuts. Coco, coco, coconuts, coconuts. Now last one. We got three right. Okay. Also. I know! Bear.
It's easy. Draw a circle. Two ears.
Ostril. Uvas. Grapes, they're healthy for you. One, two, three, four,
in the rain. I'm for trees.
Estrella, star. Isla, island. Oso, bear. Last one. Uvas, grapes. A, E, I, O, U. It was a fun, fun time having fun with you and learning with you.
Bye guys! Next time, I'll teach you how to tie your shoes. But next time. Bye guys! Hey guys! Today we're going to learn about the alphabet in Spanish. It's called el alfabeto. But first,
like and subscribe but what do you do on your vacation maria what did you do in the vacation you went to disney world so good i went to disney world before with my daddy um i saw the princesses i didn't get the dress but it was still fun
I saw the Little Mermaid, I saw everything. Even I went to a fun roller coaster in Disney World. It was very, very fun, but I was almost gonna pass out. It was very, very fun. Okay, okay. Who else did on, who else go with me?