I want to be a star.
Hi, I'm Mr. Hester and I teach media technology at Medford Vocational Technical High School.
In the media technology shop, students get a wide range of skills in video production and audio production.
This can be operating cameras, operating sound equipment, video editing, and we also touch a little bit of animation as well.
Something that interested me about this shop was the learning aspect of how to use cameras, how to learn how to do news broadcasts, editing clips, doing visual effects as well.
What interested me about this shop was the ability to not only be behind the camera and learn how to edit and be very creative, but also to be in front of the camera and be performing.
A lot of corporations are hiring their own video teams.
There's more and more jobs in the video industry and it's a great opportunity for students that come to this program to get a jumpstart on that career in the video production world.
My favorite project that I've worked on is probably my TikTok segments, ST in the Halls.
You should go follow that at not official Medford High.
What is it?
Not Medford High official.
No, official's not in it anymore.
It was never.
I thought it was.
Okay.
After high school, I plan to go to college to study sports media and communications.
What interests me is the editing part.
I really like editing, doing effects, visual effects.
I also like using cameras and microphones and all that.
Thanks for watching our video profile.
I encourage you to come check out the shop.