On March 29th, 2023, Governor Haley signed into law a supplemental budget bill, which, among other things, extends the temporary provisions pertaining to the Open Meeting Law to March 31st, 2025. Specifically, this further extension allows public bodies to continue holding meetings remotely without a quorum of the public body physically present at a meeting location, and to provide adequate alternative access to remote meetings. The line is just not making any substantive changes to the Open Meeting Law other than extending the expiration date of the temporary provisions regarding remote meetings from March 31st, 2023 to March 31st, 2025.
First item on the agenda is notice of intent DEP file number 215-0235, self-reservoir dam improvements. Continues from November 15th. The town of Winchester has filed a notice of intent to conduct improvements to the self-reservoir dam on South Dam Road in Medford, Mass., to bring it into compliance with the office's dam safety regulations.
The proposed work will impact the following inland resource areas, bordering vegetated wetlands, bank, land under water bodies and waterways, bordering land subject to flooding, and the riverfront area of Smeltbrook. This project is being filed as a dam maintenance limited project per 310 CMR 10.533I. Dennis, I can give a little summary of where we're at. So I think everybody is
Pretty familiar with the project in general after the last meeting. I think we left it with kind of 3 topics up for discussion. Which are the BVW temporary impacts. Tree replication and invasive species management. For the BVW temporary impacts, we clarified the note on the plans to.
include seeding with wetland mix in that area. Also, I discussed maintenance of that area with the town of Winchester. They have a brush cutter that will allow them to control growth in that area without entering the wetland with machine.
If that is unsuccessful, they also are willing to go in there with different types of brush cutters and string trimmers by hand to keep that area controlled and stop any trees from growing in that area. Any comments or questions on that topic from anybody on the commission?
Thank you for clarifying that and adding the note regarding seeding. That note is on the plan, I presume? Correct. I think the original note just said, like, cease back for a seeding schedule or something to that effect, but we clarified the wetland seed mix in that specific area. So the next topic I have is tree replication.
open that up for discussion. Dennis, I'm not sure if we got anywhere with anybody from those different agencies from the city or... From the city, not so much, unfortunately. I've been playing phone tag with Aggie and she knows about the issue and she knows that, I mean, she basically said she's willing to help.
Like, you know, when it comes to, like, you know, getting trees and putting trees in the right spot. So she's willing to do that. It's just a matter of, I was trying to hope to get her on this call tonight, but she got called away to some sort of tree thing. I think a tree fell somewhere or something and she had to go to it. So unfortunately, that was sort of my plan was to just get on here briefly, at least sort of go over what might be expected and what.
Might be done, but she is, you know, she has said, you know, with the her and forestry department would be. Willing to help us out with finding places and finding proper proper. Trees to put in and, you know, that's. Basically, and then trees meant for the same thing. Like, they, they sort of said that. They have a good list of places in the city where they think trees should go.
And that maybe we can sort of follow their locations as well. And so I think. That's probably the best we can get from them for right now, because I think part of what we're going to sort of figure out is what that mitigation might actually be.
you know, in terms of, you know, numbers, frankly, probably is what we're gonna have to sort of discuss, you know, given, I mean, I don't, I mean, given the sheer number that have to come down, I don't know if, I don't know, I don't know if I think a full one-to-one is probably,
makes sense given the safety issue on the day. Like, for some of these just have to... some of these probably honestly should have come down when we did this a few years ago with the initial work on the dam, but they didn't. And so it sort of got pushed to this time. Because I can't remember where... was the 20 foot rule in effect
Is that like a recent thing? Yeah, the 2015 project. I mean, there was trees on the slope, like growing, you know, right in the heart of the dam at that time. So we kind of, we tried to limit it at that point in time to just, you know, obvious ones like that are, they were right in the middle of the dam, basically.
So this, and this project is obviously a lot more, you know, a lot more earthwork involved in this project. And this is really a structural rehabilitation of the dam. The other one was more focused on, you know, utility work in the area. And I'm just trying to remember, trying to see if I can find the old order, but I'm pretty sure, here we go. No, it's fine.
just trying to look through my files as I speak. I'm fairly sure that in that instance, it also wasn't a one-to-one. I mean, I'm pretty sure in Winchester, the plantings were, I mean, we did the drive in a couple hours and it was probably maybe, I mean, 15 to 20 trees at most that were planted. I think that's accurate on that 2015 project. Yeah.
Because I know I just drove around with the head of the water department. We basically went, and it was, you know, there were some up by the reservoir, some across town. It was a few scattershot areas that were near different areas, and they were put in. And I went over there, I think, once for them to scout out the locations. And at the time, like, you know, I think six months or a year after they were planted to see how they were doing. They seemed to be thriving, so.
Before we conclude this, I'd like to speak about the next item on the plan, invasive species management. And I can speak for the commission when I say we appreciate that you brought this up to the town and that you've had, I guess, a positive response from the town. Yeah, so the town is agreeable to perform invasive species removal.
we kind of discussed adjacent to the site. And when I say adjacent to the site, I kind of mean along Smeltbrook, which runs along the toe of the dam in that area, and then anything within the water treatment site slash access road area there. It's a pretty big area, like over two acres, probably three acres of site.
Not that it's all invasive species in those areas, but that's what we discussed, and they're agreeable to do that. We would pull a plan. I know we touched briefly on a plan at the last meeting, and we would be pulling that plan together. We'd have to do it over the winter because the removal would be put onto the contractor performing construction at the site.
Well, so.
in thinking about that, that's a substantial area. So that's very heartening. But of course, if you just remove invasives and let things be, the invasives will come right back. So a couple of questions. And I think the answer to the first one might be no, but I need to ask, are any of these sites, would they be appropriate for any tree planting, tree or shrub planting? And is that a possibility?
I think I can talk. I've been talking with our geotechnical engineers about trying to squeeze a few more trees in on the dam site. It's going to be limited. It's not going to be, it would definitely be less than 10 if we could fit any at the dam site.
The water treatment plant site, the project that Dennis was talking about, I think we did squeeze a few more in there. It may be possible to get a couple more there, but that's a pretty thickly wooded area as well up there at the treatment plant. So I think we could squeeze a few in there, but probably less than 10, I'm going to say, between those two areas.
It just occurred to me, if we're looking for sites to plant for additional plantings, it would be helpful to be able to shade out or make a dent in invasives coming back and taking over within the next year upon removal. And that was kind of a question, too, as far as a plan goes. Haley had a few kind of detailed questions, I think,
On what the commission would be looking for as part of that. Yeah, definitely. So I just was wondering, kind of, you know, we've done the habitat assessment. Essentially, we identified a few invasive species adjacent to the smelt brook.
And kind of looking for what you might be looking for, being if, you know, we know there's bittersweet out there where you'd be looking for, you know, these are three suggested methods to removing bittersweet, you know, for the contractor to utilize or discuss with the town what makes the most sense. Or kind of what makes sense to identify the areas where there may be invasives because there hasn't been, you know,
a full habitat assessment didn't take place at that entry to the water treatment plant. So we don't have as much data there, but we know there is some similar species within that area. So I guess what makes sense to pull together and also coming into the winter months where it's not the best for identifying plant species out there, it's possible, but definitely not the best conditions. So what would be expected for us to pull together in order to please the commission?
I have an idea when it comes to that. Taking account in the fact that you're not gonna be able to see a lot of stuff, that's a really fair point. Heidi, would it be possible for us to phrase our order of conditions to mandate a square footage and have the applicant produce a boundary and present that to us once
warmer months hit when they're mobilized for the adjacent dam project and have that filed as a separate project when the time comes, just as an idea, just to throw it out there. I'm not sure the town of Winchester would go along with an additional filing, but we certainly could include a condition
requiring a plant that shows the extent of species to be removed. I am pretty comfortable identifying plants in winter. It's often easier, it seems. And you know, bittersweet when you see, you know... The core that we see all the time, we definitely have a red berries coming out now.
So yeah, we would want to specify the extent, the species to be removed, how to dispose of that plant material if appropriate, and what to plant upon removal, and the time frame for all of this as well.
And that would be something for our review and approval. So we would get to review that again. Haley, is that consistent with what you were thinking?
Yeah that's along the lines and I think just identifying the square footage is kind of what it comes down to if it's a general x square feet or is it an approximate rectangle and going back you know what how do we identify the square footage per se or is it going out there and you know it's not going to be possible to identify each and every invasives on that area. So what makes the most sense for you know everyone to be
How much I guess because obviously we don't remove everything it'll just take over again, I understand that for sure. If you specify an envelope and which would be a targeted area. Okay. You can look to do that. Because yeah, you don't want to clear cut. You don't want to remove the native species. Right. Definitely don't. How does that sound to you, Craig? Yeah.
I think that makes sense too and kind of what we were thinking. Okay. Are there state, do you know if there are DEP guidelines or DCR guidelines that we can state or point to for removal management to kind of simplify things? Is there state guidance? Well, there's a lot of guidance out there. Does DEP have guidance? If so, it's not very current.
But let me see if I can. We have some general templates to, you know, working with different species that we see commonly and different suggestions of how to deal with them. And that could be a kind of method of here's the options. What do we think makes the most sense in this area? DCR has a document on managing terrestrial invasive plants.
look to the Army Corps as well. There's a Massachusetts Invasive Plant Advisory Group, MIPAG. I totally forgot I had attended one of their meetings once. They have a guidance for effective management of invasive plants as well.
There was some training that was done at UMass that I took after I started here. And all I really remember from it was when I mentioned I was from Medford, the guy who was in charge of the meeting basically yelled at me because Medford was where the gypsy moths originated from. Yeah. That's just terrible. Yeah, apparently. I never knew. I'm sorry, 120 years ago, a guy dropped a glass before any of the ancestors even made it to this continent.
What species are we dealing with primarily? Bittersweets, one of the main ones that was identified out there. Yeah, but there's no knotweed I'm hoping. I thought I saw knotweed at the pond along the drive up to the treatment plant when I did my site visit. All right. It's not
Spread a lot yet, so it might be relatively early in the not we because I mean, if it had it would be. It would it doesn't appear like, you know, like it's taken over. Yeah, but well, I mean, well, so that's why that's why it's kind of good. If we can get it now. This is like the best time to really jump on it relatively early in the process before it's just completely enveloped the pond. So if it yeah, not we'd of course will have.
its own methodology for removal. Generally, cut and dab methods seem to be the most, the only effective way. So Haley, is that kind of enough information? I mean, I'm sure our typical removal plans, you know, follow a lot of the Massachusetts guidance and DEP and Army Corps guidance.
Are you good there on what we need to pull together? I think so. And, you know, we will look to kind of weigh in and we might, you know, look for a little guidance. Here's our first kind of go at things. What are we thinking as we're pulling things together just to make sure we pulled together the most effective plan? We'd be happy to look at that. That would be great.
Yeah, great. And, you know, as I pretty much said on the previous work up there, if you need anyone to come down there and walk around, I always get excited to go up there. So I'll be happy to do a site visit. Perfect. Hopefully it's pretty straightforward and get right in there and identify a few species and where they're the densest. Yeah.
So I didn't, I'm sorry to have moved the conversation away from the tree planting, but I just thought that there could be some nexus between where to find a place to put trees and invasive species removal. Or even, good, good, yeah, never mind, I'm not going to finish that thought.
Just to confirm, I think in the notice of intent, it was 147 trees removed and you're proposing to replace eight? At this point, yes. Okay. I don't know if any other commission members have a number in mind. I certainly would like more than the 20 that might have been put in in 2015. Yeah.
I think we could, you know, write in a special condition if we can come to a number of trees and, you know, just say that they'll be installed at the direction of us or the tree warden. But, you know, 147 divided by 2 plus 8, I think, came to about 65 trees. I'm gonna...
throw 65 out, see what any other commission members think of requiring 65 trees somewhere in Medford. Dennis, do you know what the ratio was back in 2015? We know 20 were in, but how many came out? And you're muted. Sorry. Some of you just came in the opposite.
What I was going to say is if, I hate stepping away because I just moved into here. Well, I moved in here a little while ago and I'm still moving things and figuring things out. I think I know where the old file might be. If you want to give me like two minutes to run over and just grab it and you know, I'll be right back.
I'll do the same. I think I found that order of conditions from 2015.
So I'm clear. The 147 trees to be removed, that was within that 20-foot exclusion zone. It wasn't total, though, right? So if we're going to get into numbers, I do have a little bit of a breakdown here. So total trees taken down on site is 147 trees within the BVW area.
there's 24 trees within the BBW area. The way, you know, all the resource areas are on the site, you know, buffer zones coming off the BBW, off the Smelt Brook, off the reservoir, I think like two trees might fall like right in that, like a little triangle that isn't in a buffer zone. So basically there's 24 in a resource area. I guess is there any
Like, is there any other is there something that. Sticks out to you more as far as a number goes like. Within like, the 100 foot riverfront area. There's 41 trees within the 100 foot riverfront. I thought that number meant something. I mean, I can get into like, bordering land subject to flooding and stuff, but there's it's kind of stuff starts to overlap and.
Yeah, I'll get the whole areas in different resource areas and different buffer zones. Do you have any idea how many are not in the BLSS? Because that's a zone A. I don't really trust the boundaries of that because that's going to be guesstimated.
So, do you know how many are being impacted outside of that. Outside of their not sorry how many are being impacted. If you ignore the bordering land subject to flooding. I think I think there's like, so the only area that is only bordering land subject to flooding.
Is area like up at the top by the spillway and I think there's like 3 trees up there. So, yeah, the whole right side where most of the trees are coming down or is all within other. Gotcha all within other resource buffer zones and areas.
Okay, I found the old filing. So my memory wasn't quite off. So basically just reading the NOI and some of the other stuff, there were 28 mature trees removed, but only 8 were replanted. So it was 8 of 28. So it's a little under a third were put in. I think I may have gone and seen trees that weren't part of this project when I did the drive around.
Because I think they probably, I'm assuming Winchester probably put a bunch of trees at the same time, and they probably just couldn't differentiate between the trees for us and the trees for everybody else. But it was, and I did find the part of the order that referenced it too, and it was basically all, and this was just the language in this, all trees that will be replicated will be done in conjunction with the Winchester Tree Care Fund, and all the replicated trees will be placed, you know, within the neighborhood adjacent, and the location of the trees will be presented to the CONCOMM. I think language like that could probably be used to,
for this part of the tree restoration. So. Well, I suggest that we maybe go with the ratio of one tree planted for every three removed, which would bring us to 49 trees. And it sort of kind of fits with the 41 within the riverfront area.
Just out of curiosity, Heidi, do you think it more appropriate to tie it to the impact to the riverfront area or to the ratio? Or does it matter? I'm neutral. I would do ratio just so it encapsulates the whole project because I don't think the riverfront area is any less important than the DBW area. I like that approach.
Michael and Haley, what do you think about that? I mean, I think it sounds agreeable. I don't think the town of Winchester is, you know, the start of this, we've always said we were willing to plant trees, work with you guys on the number.
It sounds like Riverfront area is important to you. I guess my only if unless the VVW, but I don't know, I think. Your mitigation requirements are typically. Does that typically fall into Riverfront area? How I how I read how I read the language on the tree replication, it's it's somewhat vague and I think.
It probably is so you can kind of work with work with people, depending on the project. You know, it says full mitigation. But it doesn't really specify what. What buffer zone or what area is included there. But I think I think the number, I think a 3 to 1 to 3 or 3 to 1 however you want to word it. I mean, I think that that would be agreeable to that.
And do you think that maybe 10 of those can be squeezed into the invasive removal area? Yeah, I think the number, because I was looking at a 20 foot spacing for the trees. And I think I squeezed eight in different areas of that site. So between eight and 10?
Yeah. And then, you know, we'd be looking for some guidance from whatever agency in Medford is that wants to head this effort for the remaining 30 or whatever it comes to.
Okay, so I think we're talking about, obviously, a couple of conditions here. First of all, I want to make sure, Dennis, that the order cites the most current plan set, which would include the note regarding the seating downstream with the New England wet mix. Do we need to see an O&M plan
For that 20 foot buffer for maintenance, the BVW, because if we write that into the condition, the conditions close. Would that terminate that maintenance requirement? I'm sorry, what do you mean by the conditions?
ignore that, but do we need to see an O&M plan on how the town needs to maintain the BBW area within that buffer zone, or are we okay just taking their word on it? I think an O&M plan is a good idea. We will be, as part of the dam rehab project, we will be drafting an operation and maintenance plan. It'll probably be post-construction. I don't know if that would work for you guys.
Um but I'll throw that out that we will be drafting an O&M plan as part as part of the construction project. Oh if if we just condition the that you know with the O&M plan one of our standard orders is standard conditions is you know anything you know
Failure to, like, you know, basically, failure to do some of the, anything, any of these conditions may subject the applicant to an enforcement order. If the commission finds by majority vote said changes to be significant and or deviate from the project plan's notice of intent or the order of conditions, then the condition may require the applicant to file a request to amend the order of conditions or a new notice of intent. And we will need to close this with you, right? As we provide as-built plans and that type of thing. And that would all be drafted.
together the O&M plan, the ASBIL plans and all that, if that works. I think we could include a condition that states that the O&M plan shall include provisions for maintenance in the BVW area or something to that effect to make sure that it's captured.
And then regarding the invasive species management, I think the condition would be something to the effect of an invasive species management plan shall be provided prior to the start of construction? That's fine. As far as our schedule goes, we're going to need to get that far enough along for a contractor to put a price on it.
Okay, so shall be provided to the commission for review and approval, shall be provided prior to construction for the commission's review and approval. And that plan shall address the envelope in which species are to be removed, the species to be removed, and the methodology.
And furthermore, that there should be eight to 10 trees planted within that from the tree mitigation. I'm not sure what to call that exactly. But you know what I mean.
then I think we spoke about, and anybody else could help with the conditions here, that there'll be 49 trees, approximately 49 trees will be planted to mitigate for the 147 to be removed.
The wording from that, I think we can just steal from the 2015 order and replace with Medford tree people. Do we need to specify the number or can we say a 1-3 ratio in case that number changes due to construction if they have to expand the footprint for staging or unforeseen circumstances?
Yeah, that's a good idea. And that they'll be installed at the direction of the tree warden. Warden, definitely.
Any other conditions that we can think of? No, from me? Yeah, back to the invasive species management, we could specify that those envelopes will include areas near Snell Brook and the water treatment plant. Just to make it, narrow it down a little bit.
I had a little bullet in the email, Dennis, too, on that. And I guess I'll just add on that species. I think I'd like it done by a professional wetland scientist and then anyone, if there's going to be use of herbicides, that they're licensed in Massachusetts to use them.
Yes, that's a good addition. Okay, any other discussion from the commission? And I can see there's no one here from the public, but I have to say, is anyone here from the public that would like to speak?
Okay. Seeing none, do I have a motion from the commission? I'll make a motion to issue an order of conditions with the conditions discussed previously. Is that good? I'll second that. Great. I'll take a roll call. All in favor? Caroline? Aye. Craig?
And myself as an eye. Thank you very much for working with us. We appreciate it. We look forward to reviewing the invasive species removal plan and everything else. Thank you so much. We'll be in touch as we're getting through that process. Thanks. Have a great night. Good night.
No, we're done. Were you done? Really? Okay then. So we need to approve the minutes also. Yes.
and you saw that. My clarification, Dennis? Yep, I just did your clarification and Caroline's and Craig's as well. So all the input I got are in the minutes as we see right now. Great. Then do I have a motion to approve the minutes for November 15th and... November 1st. November 1st, right. November 1st and November 15th. Is that right?
So moved. Seconded. Excellent. I'll take the roll call. Caroline? Aye. Craig? Aye. Eric? Aye. Myself is an aye.
I know just regarding next week, I know, Craig, you said you are not available. Are the other, are the rest of you all available next week or not?
Yep, I'm here. Okay. And Heather said she was, and I'm going to try to get hold of Alex. And just to make it a little bit easier on us, we just put on another call for looking for members who want, so hopefully we'll get someone, you know, shortly. So, um, that we should make things a little bit easier. And then, uh, oh, and, uh, the Clippership Connector is actually beginning. Oh, wow.
They are going to be doing some of the tree removal probably in the next starting very soon. Hopefully I'd be just like visit last week with myself and the DEP because there's the superseding order. So the DEP actually has, you know, they're the ones, you know, because so basically most of we had, there were 2 just for FYI for those of you who weren't.
here. The initial filing was appealed and so there was a superseding order put on and that's basically from Medford Square all the way down past the boat club on, you know, just past Riverside Avenue. There's another part of the pathway is going from there all the way to where the schools are. That order, that was a separate filing and that is so we're sort of the
we're sort of, I mean, I'm still technically, I mean, I'll be going down there and visiting the entire job, because it's one big project, basically. But, you know, any issues with the order would be first go to DEP, correct? Am I correcting that? Yeah. Yes, they're the issue. They're the issue and authority at this point. So. Who was there from DEP? Pam. Pam came to Medford and she didn't tell me. She's going to hear from me. All right.
You gave her up. Yep. Easily. Willingly. Tell her that. Didn't involve any unquestioning whatsoever. So it was, it was, it was good. It was, it was a good site walking. I think everyone's pretty excited. Yeah. Starting up. Yeah.
So, I think, and our standard condition regarding pre construction meetings. Yes. Reconstruction site, it's mostly erosion controls. So. And which basically, you know, means pre construction. For at least for me anyway, like, once you rush controls and that's what I usually do my site inspection because.
it doesn't make sense to do it before the erosion controls go in place and then do it again. So, and that's what we basically just walked the whole length of it and everything's in place. So there was one slight little tiny things. There was a slight little discrepancy between the second order and the first order for some of the erosion controls, but between Pam and I, we were able to hash it out and we decided to do the more strenuous one. We figured that was for the better.
So, great. And just if you're going to be driving by, there's a access point right off Riverside, like, when you go under the bridge past the salt and salt, and that's how they're going to be getting a bunch of the. Vehicles down and it is from there instead of having to come in around through the neighborhood.
And the work at the parking lot by the Condon Shell is pretty much done. They just paved and fixed up that area now. There's going to be... We've been meeting with them about the trees, the replacement trees for that area. So those are being worked on. I know Aggie was actually... That was the last time I saw Aggie, and this was like three or four weeks ago over there was...
That planting, so that's pretty much near completion. Is that a pump station? The elevated sort of thing? Yeah. I think it's an access point, but it's. Yeah, it is for that as well, but it's yeah, it's very big. But it's. Yeah, it is like a.
But it's like the access point for it, they had to go up higher. Instead of going down, they brought it up. But I'm trying to think of anything. Nothing else is in the pipeline that I've heard anyway. That doesn't mean there isn't something, you know, going to get dropped on my lap tomorrow.
Because that seems to be the way it happens a lot of times. I like it when people actually give me advance warning, but sometimes they don't. So, all right. So I think we're good then. I'll send you... I meant to send you guys the last few days about the stuff for next week. So I'll send that to you before I leave tonight for next week. And I will see some of you then, others... I have a motion to close the hearing. Yes.
I'll make a motion to close the hearing. Second. All in favor, Caroline. Aye. Craig. Aye. Eric. Aye. Myself, aye. All right. Now we can go. Bye, everyone. Bye. Have a good night.