Isaac, what did you do in shop yesterday? Well, I had some light bulbs and some switches. I was taking vitals. Wow. You were taking vitals? Yeah. That's actually pretty cool. How do you go to school? We go up there. We go up there too! That's weird. It's like we go to the exact same school. We do go to the same school!
So basically, whatever button he presses on the keyboard sends a signal to a website. And every half second, the robot checks that website for those numbers constantly. And then once the website numbers get changed, then it sends it to the robot. The robot notices that the numbers changed, and it does whatever key he is pressing. So it can pan to the left and right. It can move left, right, forward, backwards.
Then I have to measure how long it is, and I have to measure the height.
have the tire run. It shows how much it's off on each side. And Mr. Brown and Lord have assisted in the renovation of this cafeteria by painting and installing the screen and they actually built these speakers from scratch.
the students in the Construction and Craft Laborers Program. This is cosmetology, and it is a four-year vocational program, but students can earn their license as a cosmetologist with the State Board of Cosmetologists.
So this is our culinary arts program. It's a four-year program, and this year we just started with the Post-Art Massachusetts Restaurant Association program. So students that now enroll in this program get certification as a food service management program where they can get college credit.
at Johnson and Wales University, the Culinary Institute of America, as well as any community college in the state of Massachusetts.
wired this smart TV so that people can watch TV while they're in here. So this is going to be our new hospitality program that will be combined with culinary arts. And our students in the construction and craft labors program are building out a mock hotel. So here will be the reception area where guests would actually check into a hotel room.
We have a conference suite over here that will occur. So the tables were donated, the chairs were donated. So we're going to create a little conference room over here. In here, I'll take you into the master suite. So there'll be a bed in here where they can learn housekeeping, obviously with the nightstand. And then we have a mock.
So this bathroom will not be running or operable, but they'll be able to kind of learn the housekeeping skills that they need. So you print programs, business cards, and you design them.
You can get a vacuum hose in there.