Okay, let's kick off. Thank you, Daria. Let's start the hearings. I have 103. Before we jump into the actual hearings, we just want to accomplish some housekeeping issues. So let's look at the minutes. Daria, I wanted to thank you for revising
uh, the September, um, September 21st minutes, um, to item number six to reflect that the commission is, uh, exploring, uh, with other communities about, um, bar stool, uh, requirements. Um, I don't want city council to think we're ignoring their, their requests. Uh, so it's very important to, so they can see it on you on the agenda that they know where
we're looking into it and we're not ignoring them. I don't want that. So thank you. So Bob, do you want to make a motion to, to accept the September 21st revised minutes? Yes, I'll make the motion to accept the revised September 21st minutes of the license commission meeting. Very good. And since Ben isn't here, I'll second the motion. All in favor say aye. Aye. Okay.
So that one's out of the way. The minutes were September 21st with the revision. Let's go to October 19th. That was a lot there. I didn't realize we had such a full agenda on the October 19th meeting. So I thank you for capturing the essence of the meeting. I have reviewed them, Bob. Have you got a chance to look at them? Yeah, I did, Alan. And everything looks like it's in order.
As to what the meeting was on October 19th, I'll make a motion to accept the meeting minutes of October 19th for the license commission. Very good. Um, I second that motion all in favor say aye. Aye. Okay. The minutes for the 21st, September 21st and 19th have been approved. So we can, we can book them. Okay. Um, let's go into the agenda. Um,
I want to bat out of order a little bit, I want to exercise Chairman prerogative, so I want to go to Jingle Bells. I see Elaine in my top left corner here on my screen. As I was saying earlier, it looks like your application
is completed completely, but Elaine, we usually ask, you know, tell us a little about the event so we can hear what's go, how the event, what the event's all about, and everyone else that's attending here and too can hear a little about it. So if you don't mind, you know, just a few words on it.
Well, it's a little bit different this year than before. Typically what we do at four o'clock on a Saturday, we would load up buses with people that have donated to the Jingle Bell Festival, and we would allow them to take them around to tour homes in the city of Medford, anywhere from four to five homes. Once they do that, they come back to City Hall Chambers,
and we have a buffet dinner, and we serve wine and beer with that. Each person gets two red tickets, so they limit the number of drinks that they have, and everybody buys tickets to purchase the trees and the gifts that are on display, and then everybody goes home.
nice this year we were assuming that people wouldn't want to have their homes trampled by a hundred people or so so they're going to be doing a concert so everybody that has bought tickets for the jingle bell festival for saturday night will go to the little theater in medford high school they will have a uh see a concert by the community choral
After that, everybody will drive back to City Hall where the buffet dinner will take place. And again, they'll each get tickets for wine. It's only wine and beer. Right. Very good. In the final destinations at City Hall, you said, right? Everyone goes back to City Hall. Sure. Okay. And I know you were saying it's 22 years.
It's been a very successful event and you guys have, I hate this word, pivot. That's the new word now. Everybody's pivoting. So I know you guys have pivot to adjust for COVID now. And as you said, no one wants to be going through people's homes. So I see everything except for, Daria, do we have the insurance on that? Daria?
No insurance. Okay. Really? Because Judy owns an insurance company. Yeah, that's why I'm asking. Yeah, she always does that every year. Well, I just got the one day license on the okay. Can we diary? How do we get reach out to miss long again to get the policy so we have we know it's an effect for that night? Yeah, I will email her. Okay, good. All right, good. Elaine to if you could give Judy a nudge, that would be good.
Absolutely. And who did she send it to? Daria? Daria, yeah. Okay, I'll make sure she's she's aware of it and she gets it done. Okay, good, good, good. I don't know. I don't have any questions. Like I said, you know, this is a 22 year old event. And there hasn't been any incidents. Oh, I thought you were going to say I was 22 years old. Yeah, I look good, but not that good. Bob, any comments? Any questions?
No, I reviewed all the paperwork Alan. Everything looks great. Like you said they've been doing it for 22 years. I know Elaine. It does a great job with it. And, yeah, I make a motion to.
Uh, to accept the application for the one day, uh, beverage license, um, pending the insurance liability, uh, form being received beforehand. And that's for December 3rd of 2022 for the fundraiser jingle bell festival. Yes. Very good. Yeah. Perfect. I, um, I won't tamper with that. Uh, I second that motion. Um, all in favor. Aye. Aye.
All right, very good. All right, Elaine, your one day license has been approved. Good luck. Thank you. I hope it's a successful event. Yeah. Thank you. All right. Bye. Daria, I have number three. It says a representative from the city of Medford will present a one day license application for a season party. Who would be doing that for the city?
Daria? Lisa. Lisa? Oh, yes, Lisa. All right, now you're in the top left corner of my screen. Okay. So, Lisa, tell us a little about it. So this is going to be for the winter extravaganza that's going to be held on Wednesday, November 30th from 5pm to 7. I'm just going to shut my door. We're getting a little echo because I'm next to Daria. Sorry, excuse me.
Okay. So, we're going to have about 40 craft vendors and artisans cookie decorating a DJ Dean's concessions.
reselling that sort of thing. And we're going to have a beer garden. We had it last year, and it worked out really well. It was for two hours. We had it in the front parking lot. I provided a map. I can show you if you don't have that. But it's basically the front corner of the parking lot. We've worked with Medford Brewing a few times. They're great to work with. And yeah, it was a really good event. Nice. Nice.
Um, I hope you have more than 40. I hope you have more than that. So, um, those are 40 vendors. Oh, I'm sorry. Yeah, no, no. I thought you meant 40 people. Okay. We'll have more than that. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Very good. Um, Bob, any questions? Again, this is a, an event that's been going for a while, so I don't have any questions.
No, I'm familiar with the event. Everything looks great. All the paperwork looks great. I see the photo of where the Bear Garden is going to be. I wouldn't anticipate any issues. Lisa, the only thing is I noticed the estimated number of guests are 800 plus. I'm sure that you guys have been in touch with the Memphis Police Detail Desk just to make sure.
That is on my list to do today actually with police and fire police. I'm actually they're going to hopefully police and fire are going to escort, you know, on Elsa Santa Olaf. So, there'll be a part of it. Okay, great. Yes.
Yeah, I believe that's how it's been done in the past. Yeah. Yeah. Awesome. Well, yeah, with that in mind, then I would like to make a motion to grant the one day application for the winter extravaganza on Wednesday, November 30, from five to 7pm at City Hall. Very good. Yeah, I, I second that motion. All in favor say aye. Aye.
Very good. It's been approved. Let's hope it doesn't rain or snow or sleet or hurricane, whatever. So hope it's a success. Thank you. You're all set. Thank you so much. Take care. Happy Thanksgiving. Bye-bye. Bye-bye. Okay, let's jump over to Smashburger. Who do we have for Smashburger?
Hello, yes, myself and the general manager, Ruben Silvestre. Very good. Thank you. So we see an application for or an amendment to change a manager, correct? Yes. All right. And we appreciate you coming back for a second bite of the apple, so to speak, because I think Denise didn't realize that she
He just came and she didn't have all her ducks in a row, but I see this time we see the complete package and we can see the individual who's going to be now the manager. So again, tell us a little about what's happening and tell us a little about the manager, please.
Yes, so Ruben, he's actually on this call also. He's the GM now, so he'll be taking over. The previous managers just didn't work out. Very good. Bob, any questions?
Now I had a chance to review. All the paperwork for the change of manager everything looks like it's an order. Yeah, yeah I don't have an issue with any of that I make a motion to accept the change in management. The smash burger that's located at 4.95 Riverside have a method for Mister. Ruben Street to be so that's true here. Yes. Now I
I to look at it all looks in order. I thank you very much. It's it's great. I second the motion all in favor say aye aye aye very good. Very good gentleman. Ruben good luck. In the change of manager amendment has been approved. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Yeah.
Okay, let's go to. Station landing. Attorney John you there and yeah, yes, I'm here. Thank you. Mister chairman. Commissioners so yet we have to back to back applications these the neighboring hotels, both owned by Cohen management Inc.
The first is at 85 Station Landing on your agenda, which is the Town Place Suites, Fairfield Inn & Suites, that's the dual brand hotel. Looking to accomplish two things. One is the request for a change of officers. That is we are appointing David Rebich as a chief financial officer. That position didn't exist before, so we're just adding him, and he is listed on the Secretary of State's office as well.
And the second part of that application is the appointment of Vincent Sassone. Vincent joins us as well. And by way of qualifications, he has over 10 years in the hospitality industry. He's been with Colon for quite some time. He's a prior manager of record at the AC Hotel by Marriott in Boston. So he's already been vetted and gone through the process. And he'll be, he's a general manager here in Medford at both locations, and he will be the manager on both of those licenses.
If you need to take them separately the second one is is the AC hotel by Marriott Medford same ownership call management Inc and you know just same same application same requests as stated prior. Yeah, no no I thank you once again we you know Bob and I went through all the paperwork it's all complete I thank you very much for being efficient.
It's a delight. Mr. Sassoon, if you don't mind, can you tell us a little about your history? I know Attorney Ayotte did, but we always like to hear from the new manager. Tell us a little about yourself, if you don't mind.
Yeah, so you know, I've actually been with colon for about 10 years now, I actually had the pleasure of open up the 95 station landing hotel as an operations manager, left opened up the AC ink block in downtown Boston, was there for a couple years and opened up the AC Cleveland circle right at the border line by Boston College. So I was on both liquor license there, during the pandemic went back to ink block. And then as of this past May, back to station landing where I got to have the opportunity to oversee AC and town place Fairfield in.
Nice, nice. In all your past experience, not that you'd probably tell me, but any incidents or any problems or anything with the liquor? Yeah. Hopefully, no. No, let's not go there. All right.
Mister chairman I mean also to that and you know they have I think 1819 licenses throughout the state and no violation now. Yeah, no violations. Let's keep that way. Yes, yes, no I I said that the certificate of good standing we saw I saw everything in the air. Yeah. So one thing I was scratching my head and I'm you know. I'm not with the CIA nothing like that but I was looking at your your
passport picture in your license picture? I don't know. Tony, did you see that package there? I just had some questions whether that was, is that the same person? Is that younger and older? I don't know. Well, Vinny's there if he wants to, I think. It's a young Vinny, I think. I think, yeah.
Yeah. I, I was saying to Bob, I said, you know, we're not, you know, it's not like we're, you know, but I'm like, uh, okay. It's a, it's a young Vinny and an older Vinny. Yeah. I think it's the same ones we've submitted prior and it's passed, you know, obviously gone through and up the chain and, and, uh, yeah, those are valid documents. So yeah, no, no, I'm not buying anything. I just, it just kind of caught my eye. That's all. That's all. Yeah. So,
Bob, what do you think we, do you want to take them one at a time? Because one has, you know, the manager and the director, and then the other one is just the manager, I believe. No, I think we have a DACA on both. We should have a DACA on both. It's the same on both? Okay. Yeah. Oh, let me see. Oh yeah. No, no, you're absolutely right. I see two Corey request forms. Okay. Good, good.
you know the same and I think maybe since be it might. He's yeah that's what's wrong me. But yeah, I mean if we can whichever way you want to do it. Mister chairman we can make a motion to accept. Both of them at the same time with a boat. Basically the same owners same managers same change of officers. Yeah.
which I think I think that's fine and then there was well reflect that in a minute so I think that's fine yeah. All right, would you like me to make the motion place.
I'll make a motion to accept the change of officers and the change of manager. Change of officers to David Rebich and change of manager to Vincent and I don't so so for both locations. The AC hotels by Marriott at 95 station landing method. And the town play suites Fairfield in in suites at 85 station landing method.
Very good. Thank you, Bob. Um, I second that motion. Um, all in favor say aye. Aye. Aye. Very good. Uh, Tony, I had to thank you for putting these packages together. We really, really appreciate it. And, uh, everyone have a happy Thanksgiving. Thank you. Yes. You too. So it's been, it's been approved. All right. Thank you. Good luck. Thank you. Appreciate it. Have a good day. You too. Ciao.
So I think just two items left. There's an entertainment license area for Amici. Is that or is that is that off the table or is that still? No, I sent it to you guys. It has all the signatures. OK. OK. Yeah, I just wanted to make sure. And then. All right. So let's let's take care of Amici for the entertainment license application.
at 21 Renan Road in Medford. So, Bob, any questions on that one? Yeah, I just have a question. I don't ever remember seeing a restaurant at that location. That's by the Portland Plumbing Group, correct? It's a club. It's a club. Oh, it's a club. Yeah, it's not a restaurant. I never eaten in that place. Sounds like a nice guy and restaurant.
Okay, that explains it. And the only other question I had is I did not see a signature from the police chief. He signed, so I have, what had happened is that I sent it around, but sometimes like they don't respond to all, they respond just to me with the signature.
So I have one paper that has the chief's signature, but that doesn't have anybody else. And this one that has everybody else but no chief. Doesn't know chief. Yeah, but they all signed off on it. So I'll get chief to sign that one once I see him. But he signed off. OK. Do you mind, once you get the chief to sign with everyone else, do you mind sending that to us? Because I have folders. I keep everything. So we have to go back. Yeah, no, I do too. I do too. I don't want to have different sheets. OK.
But good all right to me to come I think that's where on. The method to call on Ian's have their meetings to I think that the me to call some okay. Yeah. Okay so let's do a motion. Yeah. I'll make a motion to grant an entertainment license. At the image of before I do I'm sorry Mister commissioner to the chair. They adding
New category. Yeah, any categories because it did they just have that one category that know so they have a new team and by devices but they're adding one more. Okay just. I started on here. It's a time by performers by performers okay.
All right, so they're adding that it's comedian and D slash DJ in addition to devices devices. Yeah. All right. So OK, I'll make a I'll make a motion to amend the entertainment license.
For me she's a 21 read and have met fit masks to add comedian slash DJ on to the devices portion of the license. Good good good yeah, very good. I second the motion. All in favor of the entertainment license say aye aye. Very good. So Gary that was all set also. It's been approved.
And looks like the last item is a deep cuts deli. Jeff how are you good to say yeah. Thank you for taking on this venture we we appreciate it. You know that the mayor's goal has always been to make the method square destination. So thank you for.
you know, fulfilling that or stepping up into that, so. Oh, yeah. Yeah. No, I mean, we're super excited about this opportunity too. This is, you know, pretty much what we've been trying to do since, you know, the beginning and pre-COVID. And that's, we opened up our spot in West Medford, you know, during COVID as kind of, it was always intended to kind of be a temporary spot, you know, while we looked for a permanent home. And this, this space is more than we could have asked for.
Good. So tell us what's on your mind. You're here on our agenda, but so what's going on? Tell us. Yeah, I've been talking with Daria and just kind of coordinating what our licenses were. So she recommended I just kind of come in here and talk to you guys about our plans.
a little different than what's, you know, what happened with like Medford Brewing and some of the restaurants. And so what we want to do here is we actually want this space to be a brew pub as opposed to a brewery. And the biggest differentiation between those is that the brew pub
can apply for a full liquor license and sell liquor, wine, and beer from other places, as opposed to a brewery that is only allowed to sell its own manufactured product. So that's kind of the big difference for the license that we're looking for.
So you won't be brewing on premises and pouring, that's not what you're doing? Oh no, we will be. Yeah, we're going to have a brewery. You'll be brewing your own beer, right? Your own formula? Yeah. So we have a five barrel brewery in the basement here. And then we're just going to supplement that with wine and cocktails and stuff. So, you know, people who don't like beer also have something to drink here.
Sure, sure, I think. So you're doing both, you're doing both. Right. Yeah. And so that's the difference is when you're, you know, the classification of a brewery, you can get that the farmer brewery pouring permit, which I believe you guys adopted last year. And
And that's the real intention of that is to operate outside of the liquor license quotas. So the breweries don't take away their licenses from from other establishments but the group of designation. You're not eligible for the harbor or for that and you're supposed to get a full 6.12 liquor license. Yeah we diary had had discussed that with me and
And I'm a banker, I'm not a lawyer. And I have asked for some legal advice on that because I don't, because the way the city is right now, we have several, all alcohol licenses, no problem with that. But then we don't have a combination of an alcohol and a farmer's brewing, pouring license.
So I don't know if that's what I've been trying to get an answer to, is do you have to have both? Can you do one? If you do one, does that exclude you from the other? Honestly, Jeff, I don't have an answer for you yet, and I apologize. And I know you're moving forward.
And I thank you for that. This is brand new. We've never had this come before us, this combination. So we're all learning this.
Right. Yeah, that's, um, you know, I've opened four breweries before and I know kind of the, you know, ins and outs of all those, you know, the licenses from federal to state to local. Um, and so that's what, for, for a brew pub, you're, there's the state says you need to apply for a local liquor license to start.
Yeah, the fire report permit is only for her. All right well like I said we're we're looking into it and but I thank you for coming here and and telling us your your vision and you know telling us what you want. And then you know we've always you know we've always pride ourself on helping the community because we really believe that method should be a destination and
and we'll do whatever we can to assist, you know, the risk takers like you guys. So let us do some homework and, you know, we'll get back to you with an answer. Okay, great. Yeah, yeah. You know, I'm here to help and I'm actually, you know, I'm the GC on the project. So I'm down here every day and available pretty much anytime if there's any more questions.
Good, good. And Daria, we have Jeff's contact information, email, phone numbers, all that stuff. Daria? I have Jeff's email. Sorry, I just have people coming in, so they've just not given me a second, so I apologize. Okay. All right. Well, as long as we have Jeff's contact information, so if we have any follow-up questions or whatever, but as I said, let us do our homework and we'll get back to you, okay?
Okay, yeah, perfect. And would I be able to ask Jeff a couple of questions? I'm sorry. I'm sorry. Yeah, be my guest. And Jeff, I'm kind of new to this game. And I, I know what type of license you currently have and what you can do with it. And I did a little research on my own. And, you know, I did find the pub brewery license on the ABCC site. And, you know, it
The things that questions that we have are that probably licenses issued by the state not the local licensing authority. So Mister chairman I don't know do we have to adopt. Brewery licenses before
before they come into the city, like we had to adopt the farmer's brew license, or did we have to adopt the farmer's brew license? These are the questions we should look at. And I do understand that, you know, with a brewery license, from what I've read, you can brew and you can sell retail and on-premise.
as well as apply for a section 12 full liquor license, which should cover your, instead of a farmer's pour license, that will cover all your pouring for your brew and your
liquor, the way that I'm reading it. It's it and it says, basically, it says on the ABCC, it says you can't hold both the farmer brewery license and a pub brewery license. Yeah, it's one or the other. So one or the other. I'm seeing it that, you know, you may need a well, you're going to definitely need a brewery license.
and you're gonna need a section 12 full alcohol license, but I'm not sure if the city has to adopt the pub brewery license first before we grant it, or do we have no say where it's applied for through the ABCC? Yeah. Yeah, that's a good question. It's a good question. Yeah.
I just submitted yesterday for our federal license. So that process is starting. So then they issue us a federal brewer's notice. So once we get that, then we apply with the state ABCC for the pub brewery license. That's independent of the town or local.
And so then once we get that, that's what lets us brew onsite legally and sell at retail. But you're not allowed to serve on premise until you- To pour, that's where we stopped in, that's right. Yeah, so then that's where the local authority comes in is for serving onsite. Alcohol license.
Yeah, that's what you are saying. And you can also, anybody that brews in bottles for you with your name on it can also be sold and served, correct? That's for a brewery, for like a farmer brewery. Which is what you have now.
That's what we have at our other location. Yeah, but not here, but not here. Right, right. They have a farmer's brewery here. Because that isn't that what you sent me over the area. That's our existing spot in West Medford.
Yeah, it wasn't through the city of Medford, you received that farmers brewery through the ABCC and that's my question is, yeah, did we have to adopt the farmers brewery.
I imagine we might have only because of Medford Brewery that we also granted a pouring license for them as well. But all they are limited to is their product basically that they brew and they can sell retail or on premise.
I'm just wondering, did that have to be adopted by the city when we first came into that? Because I wasn't around then. Possibly if that's the case, then we're going to have to start looking into adopting a pub brewery license, if that's such a thing. If not, where it's issued through the state. It says in black and white that it's the state, not the local licensing authority.
So, I'm not sure which way we got to go like Mr chairman said, you know, we're going to have to contact the legal department or whatever and get an opinion for you. Yeah. Yeah, which way we have to go with that. Yep. Yeah, I mean, that's what the state one is, is the one that lets you.
or manufacture it. And it's mostly the two designations are really, it's all about taxes and paying, you know, taxes and excise tax, how your product is stored and paid for and all that. And that's why a license lets you sell at retail.
but not serve on site. So like when we did our spot in West Medford, you know, we just went through the state and didn't have any interaction with the town. Right. You know, I'm not trying to say it's not in your jurisdiction, but it's, you know, it's, it's a, it's a state thing and not a local thing. So now when you were adopted,
When you apply for what your goal is with the pub brewery license,
Is that something these these are the questions we've got to find out to is that something that's going to be a change of type of license that you'll have to apply for going from the farmers were to a pub brewery in also a new license to get a section 12 all alcohol license or they combine both it looks like it's 2 separate but it's on the section 12. Yes, yeah, they're both they're both separate we are.
We're one entity, but every location gets its own license.
We're going to end up shutting the West Medford place and we're applying for a new pub brewery license for this location. But in theory, we could hold separate ones at the two separate locations. They just don't have both at one location because there's certain restrictions that they each have.
And the number one difference being is that a farmer brewery is allowed to self-distribute their own beer. A pub brewery is not. So they don't let you have both. So as a pub brewery, you would not be able to sell to wholesalers to sell your product? Is that correct? That's what the pub brewery is required to sell through a distributor. OK. And it's self-distributed. OK.
And they're debating changing that rule. But that's kind of the big differentiation right now. And we plan on, we don't really plan on doing any distribution out of this location. Yeah, yeah, you'd need a little larger place, I would imagine. Yeah, I don't think I can make enough beer to. Yeah, you'd be in a two-wheeler, wheeling it across the street to the parking lot.
Yeah, that'd be crazy. Okay, Bob, anything else? No, I think that pretty much cleared up the questions that I had and, you know, we can look at it on our end. And one last thing, Jeff, do you have a target opening date? We're kind of shooting for
end of January, early February. And that's, I think it's real down to, you know, it'll be this liquor license will probably be the last thing that we're, that we're going to just because it's all this kind of consecutive process that takes.
OK. No pressure, right? No pressure on us, right? One other thing you might want to consider when you're putting your paperwork in is to also put in an application for an entertainment license if you plan on having any type of entertainment or whatever, and you can get it all done at once. Yeah. Yeah, we'll be doing, because we're going to have a lot of entertainment here. So we'll be putting in for that. And I know there's for devices, that's another one.
I think, is that it for entertainment would be devices in right in person. Yeah, yeah. So yeah, we'll be putting up for those two. Okay, good.
Well, thank you, Jeff, for coming on, you know, giving us some insight. And like I said, we just, you're a first for this. So we're, we're kind of learning and, you know, reading and trying to, we'll do the best. We'll do the best. We'll try to make this all work and make all parties happy. Yeah. Yeah. No, I appreciate it. Okay. Good. All right. Thank you, sir. Good luck. Good luck. Thanks.
David Ensign, PB – He, Him, His.: Daria very good, there was a good meeting anything you want to bring up because you always say the last item on the agenda. No, that was it. David Ensign, PB – He, Him, His.: Nothing else. No. David Ensign, PB – He, Him, His.: Any. David Ensign, PB – He, Him, His.: yeah we did get I did get feedback about the meetings being able to whether the Commissioners are able to.
have meetings in person just to discuss rules and regulations. I did read through, it was enormous. I don't know, I wonder if to be just on the cautious side, we should, you know, publicize that the three commissioners are meeting somewhere, you know, in the city clerk's office, just to be on the, you know, just to be on the up and up.
But we'll, you know, when Ben is around, the three of us will talk and we'll put together some dates because we really, Bob, I think the three of us really need to sit down and go through the old, all these old rules and regulations and talk about how do we, you know, try to get them into the 21st century. So, and it's very difficult to do this on Zoom, you know.
Yeah, and it's and I'm sure some of the stuff that we come up with are going to have to be reviewed by the legal department as well. Yeah, make sure we can
you know, we're in our own lane type person. Yeah, yeah. Yeah, I think it'd be a good idea because it's especially with these new places coming around. You know, like, like, Jeff that we're just talking to and you got that great American beer hall. And I mean, there's some pretty serious entities coming into the into the city now. Yeah, it's good that we can, like, yeah, up with the 21st century. That's right. You know, we can lock down the rules and
and make sure we're applying them equally to everyone. Yeah, I agree, I agree. How are the renewals coming Daria? A lot of fun. You need help? No, I'm okay for now, it's just.
It's just a lot. If you need me for anything, don't don't worry about, you know, don't feel like you can't reach out. Just reach out. And I've got some extra time, even if you need me to just stuff envelopes or do whatever for you. You know, I appreciate it. You're welcome. Terry, do you know from. For two cheese has renewed because, you know, we hear all sorts of things that they're they're not they're closing the end of the year, they close the next year.
Because, you know, I haven't gotten anything from them now. Okay. Because, you know, we hear all sorts of things out in the street. And to me, the proof in the pudding is whether they renew their license or not. If they don't, then that's the proof that they're not going to be an ongoing entity anymore. So, yeah. Okay. All right. Good. All right. Bob, any questions, concerns, fears, swears, anything on your mind before we
We adjourn. Okay. Good to go. I just can make a motion to adjourn. Very good. I second that motion. All in favor say aye. Aye. Daria, thank you for all your work. We appreciate it. Like I said, we'll be circling back on deep cuts deli. Deep cuts deli. Okay.
Do you want me to go in the back door and give Ralph a call over at the ABCC, you know, to see exactly what this guy might need or what this guy might have to do as far as do we have to adopt it or we don't have to adopt it? I think that would be a great idea just to pick his brain on this. Like I said, we're, you know, because we don't have a combination. We have two different things. And, you know, that that's our problem, you know, because we never had
the foresight to combine it with something else because we were so focused when back in 2018 I think it was we were just so focused on on the on the ones who are brewing that we kind of adopted that farmers.
brewing license with the pouring license and it never occurred to us that you might have a different type of entity or a different type of a structure. So yeah, I think that the pouring license from what I'm reading, but like I say, if we can talk to Ralph, I'm sure he'd give us all the answers we need, but
I think the pouring license is replaced by the section 12 all alcohol license because you pour all alcohol and all beers and all wine. So maybe I think that's like an umbrella for the brewery versus just a farmer's pour license like Bedford has just to pour their own product. Yeah. OK. Yeah. If you don't mind reaching out and picking his brain, that would be great. And then share with us.
And before I do, I'll text you. And if you want, actually, we'll do it over an email. You, yourself, Ben, and Dari are on the questions I'm going to ask him. And then if you want to add anything to it, or if you want to see if we can set up a conference call with them, or whatever you think we might
want for information, maybe he can help us out too on the Barstool thing, advise us one way or the other. He's a good guy to get information from. Sounds like a good resource at ABC.
And he told me, he says, give me a call anytime. He says, you know, he says anything you need, blah, blah, blah. So, and he lives in Everett. So I understand he's, you know, he's a local guy anyways. That's how we learned. We learned from the commission there. They walked us through the whole thing with the breweries and the differences. So remember when he passed, the commissioner passed, he died. All right, good. All right.
Thank you. Thank you for everything, Daria. Good to see you. Happy Thanksgiving. Happy Thanksgiving. If you want to call it whatever you guys do it then. Adjourn? Yeah. Yeah. So let's call it 149. We're adjourning. Very good. Sounds good. Thank you. All right. Thank you. Take care. Bye-bye.