Okay, so I can kick us off really quick if you'd like, Ayo.
So, hi everybody.
We are here from Eversource Energy.
My name is Yana Linhart.
I'm from the project services team of this Mystic to Lubern project, Eversource, and we're here to talk to you about milling in your neighborhood.
So, Steve, if we can go to slide two.
I just want to share the map
yep, of the milling area that we'll be tackling this spring.
And I have with me Ayo Osamboni from Eversource.
He's the engineer on this project.
And I'm going to turn it over to Ayo to speak a little bit about the two options that we have before us.
One is milling work during the day, and the other is milling work during the night, and the differences between those two options and the benefits, you know, differences between the two.
So Ayo, I'll give it over to you now.
You're muted, Ida.
You can't hear me now?
That's better, right?
Yes.
Well, thank you, Anna.
I think you basically explained everything in a summary of what we're trying to do today.
We are going to milling on Winthrop Street.
So the goal today is to present the two options of milling on Winthrop Street between Victory Park and Mystic Valley Parkway.
We're talking about about a 0.6 mile altogether.
As you can see, the duration, we're going to have about six passes with a million equipment due to the width of the road and also the hours per day.
A number of days is dependent on if we select a daytime or nighttime work.
The noise level, which is something that everyone asks, so we're going to come out and just talk about that, is the equipment itself is about 75 decibels.
which is basically equivalent to a big truck going in front of your house.
So we just want folks to understand that.
Next slide.
Okay.
Excuse me one second.
So we have two options.
So option one,
which is the daytime is going to take a longer time.
And option two, which is the nighttime, is going to take less time.
So the hours for option one is from 9 a.m.
to 3 p.m.
The goal is to begin this work April 18 to May 8.
So we're looking at 11 days of work.
The impacts of daytime work is there will be traffic detours with significant impact to adjacent streets.
So we know that because, you know, we have a lot of traffic coming through during the day.
For nighttime, we're looking at.
We're looking at that work being done from April 18 to April 24th, which is about five days.
So there is some savings in time.
when you do nighttime as compared to daytime.
So also there's going to be traffic detours, whichever option we choose, there's going to be traffic detours.
But remember, there's less traffic at night.
So that means that there's still going to be, there's going to be less impact to adjacent streets during night work.
So overall, I think the goal is which option would the community
prefer daytime or nighttime.
I think that's what we're here to present today.
And I think, too, if you have any questions or if you want to relay in the chat what your preferences are, that'd be fine, too.
If you want to raise your hand, just use the emoji hand raise icon on the bottom.
And I'm keeping an eye on that chat, Steve.
And I think anybody can just feel free to speak up as well.
Absolutely, we're here to answer the question, so.
All right, I have a question.
Given the fact that the week of April 18th is April vacation week, why couldn't, if it was gonna be done during the day, why couldn't the start be earlier and the end be later?
Because the high school won't be in session that week.
I can answer that question.
There's a lot of competing factors in this these hours.
It's not just the high school, there's morning commute, there is bus routes.
There's a lot of businesses that go through there.
So, one, while it is school vacation week.
And there will be less than normal traffic for that one week.
There is, you know, the rotary route 16 and all that.
So we have to take in all the competing interests.
And so this was the timeframe that was laid out to the city.
I guess I have another question would be, you know,
The nursing home is right at the rotary.
Have you been in touch with them?
If you were going to do it during the night, I would think that would impact those people too.
Well, there is a caveat here.
DCR, which owns the intersection of Mystic Valley Parkway, has already directed Eversource to do that work in the intersection at night.
the city of Medford is currently leaning toward daytime hours for this work because of the noise.
So, but we wanted to get, you know, if there's overwhelming, you know, input that you'd prefer night work, then we'd be happy to switch it over tonight.
Thank you.
I don't know if there are any other questions or anyone has anything they want to add or anything like that.
Please let us know.
Also, you can raise your hand with the emoji icon if that's helpful.
I guess, have you had much response from anybody else on Winthrop Street so far?
We have.
outreached individually to a few people that we knew about, but we wanted to set up this community to everybody, to the whole group, as many people as possible, just to kind of get a collective interest of what people were thinking, and just to have basic transparency with the project.
And we really wanted, obviously, to get the input from direct abutters, too, about this.
So that was really our main focus for the meeting.
I mean, in all fairness, I really I'm not concerned about the people coming from Winchester, driving through that are steering traffic.
I'm concerned about the abutters that would have to listen to this and have this work
for a series of many days and the traffic associated with it.
Now, I understand that it's a huge inconvenience and we wanna just try to make it as transparent as possible.
Yeah.
I mean, I am in a butter and it's truthfully, it's been very aggravating for the past three years to have this work done in front of my house.
So I'm kind of torn.
I guess I would just rather
get it over with, you know?
I believe that's what we're trying to do.
Overall, there's going to be, because the work is going to be done in segments, we're looking at 80% of the folks are going to have one night of real inconvenience.
And the other 20% are going to have two days because of the fact that
you know, when the milling equipment stops, and it is going to start from that point on, that way it stops, the house, the neighbors where the equipment stops and where it starts again are going to get two nights of inconvenience.
So the goal is to go in, get it done, and with less minimal traffic impacts.
We'll work with the town and with the borders on what is best for them.
Ayo, maybe you should mention how this work is going to be broken up into phases.
Weren't you mentioning that this was going to be like three sections?
Yes.
Yeah.
So the goal is to we're only going to mill segments at a time.
So we're going to mill.
We're going to have six passes.
So and we were looking at being in front of a home for about 20 minutes.
And then the noise goes down.
Then we come back again.
So we're having the process six times.
So, and once that segment is done, we're not coming back there for milling.
We're going to go to another segment of roadway to mill.
So that's the way we're planning this work.
So basically it's not five continuous days of it.
It's going to be much less for just the one at Butter.
It would probably be one or two nights.
Yeah, correct.
Because you're not staying in one place all the time, the equipment is moving constantly.
And if it was during the day, it would be not 11 solid days, it would probably be
three to four days, you know, for that one section in front of the house, but yeah, we can't get a lot done because of traffic concerns.
So it's more efficient to get it done at night.
So, but if we're going to do it in a daytime, now you're having staying in front of the same house and doing one segment, and then we may have to go back and do the second set.
So that's, that's the impact.
So that we, I think, um,
of folks need to consider as we think about this.
Hopefully that helps.
That does help.
I appreciate you taking the time to talk to us about it.
And I guess my vote would be just to get it over with as quickly as possible.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Bill, I think you have a question.
Yeah, I'm right on this.
I'm right on with upstream as well, right across from Victory Park.
Personally, I would prefer nights as well, just to get it all with them on the same boat.
Does this include weekends by any chance?
Any of this work, whether it's the nighttime or dinnertime?
No, we haven't included weekends or holiday or weekend work is not scheduled.
So, so the, the 18th is actually a holiday or so 17th holiday.
17, the 17th of holiday.
Okay.
So it is the holiday.
So you'd be starting that Tuesday.
Yeah, we're starting on the 18th.
Yep.
Okay.
My, my, my, my vote personally would be for Mike just to get it done with, but that's just my vote.
Thank you.
Okay, any more questions, please use the hand emoji or ask questions in the chat.
Also, this info, the PowerPoint will be up online and we'll push it out on our social channels as well for anyone that's interested.
Hey, I guess maybe if that's it.
I don't know if you want to wrap up by or given, maybe just do a quick recap of the project or wherever you guys think.
Yeah.
So I think a quick, quick, quick cap is, you know, we were hoping the plan is to have all the, um, um, brands, uh, all the mitigation completed by July.
So, uh, by that, you know, so that's, that's the plan.
So we're going to, so this is on.
Once the milling is completed, then the next thing is we're going to do the paving.
So we are working with Owen, and we're working with the town to make sure that we can expedite.
We do understand the concerns from the citizens of Medford.
And we just want to thank you for giving us the opportunity to install
our line within your town.
We know it's been a big inconvenience for the citizens themselves.
Our goal is to come in and try to get this work done as quickly as possible so that we can mitigate continued impact to each other and folks of Manfredstown.
Um, actually, I just have a question.
Oh, and when will we have to make this decision by which time to do it?
10 minutes now.
Right now, the direction from the city is that it'll be day work.
If it needs to be, if the, if the consensus is that it should be night work, it should, we should make a consensus within the next week or so.
to give Eversource enough time to schedule the companies that do the work, enough lead time to get out there and make those changes.
That said, you know, I mean, I think by April we should have a decision.
Great.
Yeah.
And so obviously we'll message that out whenever we have a final confirmation of when this work will be.
So.
Yep.
Great.
Okay.
I guess if no other questions, I think, I think we'll wrap it up then.
Very good.
Thank you for this opportunity to present the two options.
Thanks.
Great.
Thanks, everybody.