Okay, good evening. So we've got a couple, we're still waiting for a couple of members, but Mari's on his way, and Nova and Eunice. Did you forward that to Gene as well? Yeah, I'm just, I had to look for it, so. Okay. All right, I just sent it over to them, so you should be jumping on in a couple minutes. Okay, sounds good.
OK, Jean's on. OK. Does she need access for? Yeah, she probably needs to be. She needs audio access. Hello. I have audio. Hi, Jean. How are you? We're there. No problem. We're just getting started. And Mario will be here in a minute. He needed the link. We have a quorum, so we can do the minutes. Yeah. OK, let's start with the minutes. Everybody get a chance to look at the minutes. Move approval.
Move for approval, second? Second. All in favor? Aye. Okay.
All right, so I know you've gotten my email. I assume you got my email talking about Milva's schedule change. So I really want to make sure that we stick to, you know, getting to like what I think is the most important thing that we need to have done, which is kind of hashing this out while Milva's here, going through the pros and the cons, coming up with a consensus if we can,
And then, uh, you know, we work on your presentation pieces, which I think, um, next week when we do the presentation, you know, we don't need to have a complete and perfect presentation. I think that you both can talk to, um.
what is in your presentation, you can show your tables. And I think it's enough for the committee of the whole to have, you know, to gather information. I honestly think that once we start the discussion with them, I hope it doesn't go too long, but I do think they'll have a lot of questions about the information we gathered or did not gather. And so it'd be an interesting conversation, but tonight I wanted to start, if it's okay with everybody, with,
The pros and cons that I had sent you, Milva has done an edit to it. I appreciate that. Taking out some of the...
language, which I agree with. So I want to start as narrow as we can. Just so you know, when I wrote these up the first time, I wanted to make sure that a couple of things, that it represented all the pros and cons that we've heard about and have validated.
I also know that in the pros and cons that were added into this, um, I took out all the names of the people who said something. Cause to me, I think that putting their name there only devalues everybody else's survey because it's, there's not one survey more important than the other. Some people may have experiences and we will call on those experiences, but, um, a con is a con and a pro is a pro. So, um, I wanted to, um,
Milva, do you want to share your sheet? Or do you want me to share my sheet? Yeah, do you have it handy? I do. Do I have the power to share? Yes. OK. Is there any way to put it up against the original set? You won't be able to see it.
But I'll show you that. I didn't take any. There was none taken out. It was only that she edited them. And if we want to, I'll read to you what the original was there. No problem. Let me.
Okay, share screen pros and cons. Okay. Can everybody see that? Yeah. Okay, so let's.
So you can see that also Milva has comments on the side there. So I don't know any other way of doing this other than to just read through them and just everybody agree that that's what we all intended were those pros and cons from the original list. And again, I have the other list right in front of me. So if you want to know what the original pros and cons were, I can read that to you as well. Ron? Yes.
Um, can you, can you make, it's a little, can we see them all? Can you, um, I don't know how I can do that. You take off the comments. It seemed like it was bigger at the bottom. You see the percentage, the zoom, make it a little smaller than we can see. Okay. Yeah. Um, okay. I was like a little worried that we had more cons and pros. Yeah.
And I was wondering if we should try to make them a little more equal. We may be able to. You know, the thing with the pros versus cons are that it's just, it's not a pro versus a con here. They don't match up. But I understand what you're saying. And I guess the recommendation will identify which way we go. But there may be one here that we may want to combine or eliminate when we go through it. So let's just...
So, and again, this is a, not your opinion, it is a validated opinion that some people have. So I think we all know, you know, I think we, you know, if we said one of the pros is- That's good. Is that better? Yeah. Whatever you did a minute ago was even better, was even bigger. Yeah, I just didn't want to lose the bottom there. That's good.
Okay. All right, so number one under the pros is it guarantees at least one councilor from each ward. That's a fact. And that is a positive, I think, if one of our goals is diversity and inclusion of the entire city. Does anybody have a comment on that one? It's kind of basic 101 of the pros.
Okay, so I'll just go right down all the pros first. Fewer candidates on the ballot allows voters to become better educated and informed about their choices. So if you want to know what it originally said. I think I added that one in there.
How does that, I'm confused though about that. So right now we have 12 people running for city council currently. I mean, we've had, to trigger a primary or a preliminary, you need 15 or more. So, I mean, in the general election you could have
up to 14. Yep. But in a prelim, you can have 25. Right. Or whatever. So we get down to the general and you can have 14 people. So we have 12 now. How do you
What do you mean by fewer candidates on the ballot? Because when you, if in a ward system, you would only be voting for four people as opposed to seven right now, seven. Oh, okay, I see what you mean. So if you had, if we did the hybrid with, let's say eight plus five, so that would be 13. Then you'd have six that you were voting for. So you would be researching and looking
Yeah. And I actually, somebody, you know, in our comment stream in from, in our, we've been trying to get public comment and this was actually one of the comments by a member of the public. That's why, because it was, it's not, it's, it didn't come from me. But you'll notice it's also listed as a con too. Mari, you had your hand up as, what did you, do you want to unmute? Yeah. Yeah. Sorry. Sorry.
Yeah, but also if I understand it correctly, let's say like Ward 1 would only have the councilors running for election to Ward 1, as well as all the at-large candidates that they would be voting on, correct? Correct. Yeah, that's what I thought. Okay. So some people say that's a pro because you can focus. Others would say it's a con because you don't have say in the whole formation of the council.
you don't vote for as many people. Right. But to Maury's point then, you could have, you know, so if we did the eight plus five being 13, so you've got, you're looking at the five at large, but then you're sitting in ward one and there's, you know, five or seven or 12 running for ward counselor.
So, I think anything over two running for the ward council would go into a primary and the last two left standing would go into the general. There would have to be some kind of rule that would go across the board because if you're gonna do it, you're gonna have a primary. You'd do a primary for everybody. So if ward seven had one person,
And Ward 2 had six people as ward reps. And you're going to have a primary for them. I think you'd have a primary for everybody. I think you would too. I think you would too. You do have a primary unless there's more than two. But you also have the at-large piece too. Exactly. To Ron's point, it's just like no different than if Paul Delato's running. He runs unopposed, but he's on the ballot.
with his name and a line underneath for write-ins. The same thing would be like if the ward one councilor was running unopposed, you still could have a write-in slot as well as the at-large that were running. If you had seven or eight running for that one seat, you'd have a primary as well as the at-large would always be listed, I would imagine. First, you have to decide if there's a primary based on, number one, a primary for the mayor.
If there's a primary, everybody gets into the primary. If there's, then you go to state representatives. If there's state representative that need to have a primary, which is the case, then every person in the city would have a primary. Some primary- Last year there was a primary for mayor and there wasn't a primary for city council two years ago, I mean. Right, exactly. There was a primary for mayor and school committee, I think, but not city council. So do you think that the council would,
If there's a ward that only has one ward candidate, but there's a mayoral primary, and everybody's voting, nothing would be on the primary ballots for wards.
That's what I think, but I don't know for sure. I think we need to find that out. Is it pertinent to our- It's more logistics. I mean, once we decide to do it, the election board will say how to do it. That's the primary, but I think this pro was about the final election, right? Correct. Yes. Correct. It's not relevant for that exact point.
Yeah, and again, it's not, we're not making a decision on this. We're just trying to validate the pros and cons. Then we'll, so is everybody okay with how that pro reads? Yeah. Okay, so I'm just gonna check them off as we do it. So number three is- Can I ask a quick question? Is it too much background noise coming from me because I'm trying to get in here? No. Okay. I'm not hearing anything. It gets to be too loud, let me know, yeah? We'll shut you off, yes.
All right. All right. Makes running for office more accessible. Cost of running campaign reduced to smaller voter pool. I mean, we've already talked about this at length, I think. I mean, that's a valid pro whether you agree with it or not. I mean, does that explain to you?
I think it's true, it's just not as... Yeah, right. Yeah, no, I think that's what we're, you know, we're just validating that that's a good call. From the pro folks, that's one of the ones they say all the time, is it'll make it easier for me to, and maybe find new people to vote, to campaign. Okay, so I'm taking three and say it's okay.
Number four, having a point of contact within their neighborhood improves communication. That's a pro. I think I agree with that. I might clarify who's communication. It's not clear what you mean. Communication between- Ward residents. I would say instead of neighborhood, like their individual ward or something like that, pertain it to the entire ward. That's a good point.
Yeah, having a point of contact within war improves voters communications with the Council or something. It's with City Hall or no, I mean, and doesn't.
necessarily, I mean, City Hall will be more responsive, but they have one person they can call. Yeah, well, I mean, yeah, I was just thinking of one of the interviews we did with the department head who actually specifically said that this person thought that ward representation would make City Hall, it would make their voters' communication with City Hall easier because their ward representative would
be able to deal go to know how to move through City Hall in a more effective way. Yeah, something like having a point of contact within their individual ward allows them the ability to communicate or
say, um, accessibility to their, uh, to their individual counselors. I think that's the right, it is kind of accessibility. Yeah. Cause the, I mean, it, it improves it. It makes your counselor is more accessible to you and responsive responsiveness. I mean,
Well, I mean, if it says, you know, having a point of contact within their ward, residents and their counselors would improve communications. I mean, it's almost like, you know, the relationship can be more direct. Correct. Right. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, I'm just trying to get the words. Yeah, I know, I just want to get the words.
I mean, what if we said residents would have a point of contact within their ward for communication or something? Yeah, improve communication. Communication. A point of contact within their ward. Yeah, that's what that's. Can you see what I just changed or you can't see what I just changed? Yes. Okay. So having a point of contact within their ward, residents and their counselor would improve communications, would have improved.
would have? I think Jean had the beginning changed, right? Residents would have a point of contact within their ward. That's pretty succinct, though. If we just said residents would have a point of contact within their ward? Well, yeah. I mean, so it says now, it says one of the pros is having a point of contact within their ward.
then it says the next sentence, which is the residents and their counselor would have improved communications. You want to put in ward counselor? I would put could, because we don't, because that's. Well, again, a pro is kind of like, I'm trying to convince the cons what to, you know. I know, but we don't know for sure that that would happen, so. I'm going to add residents and their ward counselor would have improved communications.
Is that okay? Do you want to have would or could? Even if you wanted to do like accessibility, communications, and relations, so it's more of a one-on-one type. First, do you want it to say could? Yeah, I think could, because would sounds like it's- Could have improved communications and accessibility.
Okay. Wood sounds like we're promising something. Yeah. Well, I mean, we could maybe play with that a little bit later. Yeah. It's hard to like edit within a group. I'll send this out and you guys can slash away. Um, okay. So number four is good with the changes with edits. Yeah. Okay.
Number five is eliminates duplication of work when at-large counselors may be working on the same goals or issues. Yeah, I mean, it's a pro, but I mean, it's a fact of life right now, even in an at-large world, I mean. Well, I just, I mean, what if we just said eliminates duplication of work? Yeah, I don't know. I think just in the idea of making them as succinct as possible. I agree with you.
I mean, it's self-explanatory, right? I agree. To get their votes through, they're going to need the at-large counselors and so forth to be working with them. I think, yeah. Eliminates duplication of work. And if somebody has a question on it, then we can answer the question. OK. Yeah, exactly. OK. So we're approving that with edits. Yeah, I think I wrote that one down when I did the pros and cons. How do you mean?
you know, give me an instance where it would be, you know, reducing or eliminating duplication. I can give you an issue of, I go to Car Park and I see a broken swing and I call Knight, Bears, Sen, Collins and say, hey, who's going to fix this? And they all come to Tuesday's meeting with this on the agenda.
If it was Zach Beers' territory, you would more than likely call Zach Beers. And he would call DPW and get it done. Yeah. Right. That's all. Just identifying a rep with a different place. That makes sense. OK. Number six is ward representation generally thought to increase diversity of representatives. Yes.
Yeah. I mean, I do think, I just don't know if generally thought makes it, I mean, it's true that- You want to just say- You could be able- I mean, there's research that has shown that that's true. Generally. I mean, we can just say one representative may increase diversity of representation.
How about often? How about inclusive? That's good. Often increases. Often increases are, you know, what was I going to say? Not so much diversity, but it's inclusive of all neighborhoods within the city or all sections of representation.
Well, I think that the diversity. Diversity is a key word that everything has to be diversity. It just increases the representation throughout the city of the individual areas. Well, we did that in number one, right? Yeah, no, this is more about racial, ethnic, income.
And that's what a lot of the literature shows. I mean, if word representation often increases diversity of representation, that's all. OK. So are we taking out generally? Yeah. Yeah. I'm just getting out generally thought too and putting often increases diversity of representation. That's good. I think that's good. OK.
So we still have to debate this, so I'm just trying to get the words down. Okay, number seven is increased number of counselors would improve council efficiency, i.e. more subcommittees. In other words, if you have 11 reps, I think that you have the ability to have more projects being divvied out amongst the counselors, kind of like what we do.
Well, I'll tell you right now they have something like 15 subcommittees already. And I mean, I watch most of the meetings and there's only about five subcommittees that.
you know, meet with any sort of, and actually probably more like three that meet with any sort of regularity. There's some of them that I don't think I've met at all. I do. That was a point for them to go to biweekly meetings that we were going to have. Yeah. And I also, I think though, I think it logically says that if I have seven people doing, uh,
if I have 11 reps doing the work of seven, I get either more subcommittees or better efficiency within those subcommittees, because now I have, I can add two members to some of the big licensing and those kinds of boards. So. Yeah, I think we could take out the more subcommittee, just leave it. I just used it as an example to explain. Yeah, I know. But I think we could, then that could be one of the things that we could talk about when we talk about it. And I would also just put could, just because
I don't know. It is. It does say it does. I did already make that change anticipating it. It says could improve. Yeah. Okay. Okay. So seven is seven is good with edits. Yeah. Yeah. Eight at large representation will still exist for three positions. Uh, should we just say at, cause do we know the number? Yeah, I would, um,
We'll still exist. Maybe we just say still exists in a hybrid system because that's what we're talking about. Right. Yeah. Because it could be three or five. Yeah. Everybody okay with that. Yeah. Okay.
Uh, number nine is the needs of each distinct neighborhood better represented. Is that a, is that a redundant from one? What do you think? It's not because it kind of talks to the, uh, now I have somebody that's going to fix the sidewalk. Uh, you know, you'll have a, you'll feel like you're, you know, you have somebody representing your needs.
Yeah, you know, I guess. I was thinking this was more like, because we know some words have never had any representation. Sure. The city council may not understand the unique needs of word one and four, like they may not know the traffic issues they may not know walking to school so it's more they're more familiar with the neighborhood.
So they- Yeah, okay. So the needs of each distinct neighborhood better represented, is that not saying what you just said? Well, I was just replying to Milva's wondering- Yeah, yeah. No, you're right. Yeah. Better represented and understood or something? Okay. We can add in. I think adding in understood is a good one.
The only reason I would maybe stay away from represented is because when we talk a lot about representation in this issue and- People don't like that. No, we're talking about representation in a particular way. And even though the word can be used in this way,
I'm not very articulate tonight. We're talking about something different. Yeah, I hear you. Okay. Well, according to that, we're concentrating on the neighborhoods. Shouldn't it be the needs of the ward? Yeah. Each ward neighborhood instead of district. But the neighborhoods in the ward, because the wards have... Say the needs of neighborhoods in the wards.
In each ward. Or within the ward, yep. In a ward, yeah. Okay. In a ward. Okay. Good. Everybody okay with that?
Yeah, let's go in front of the whole committee anyway. Yeah, no, we have a bigger step to make after we get this edit done. So is there anything else that you want to add to that side of the ledger in terms of pros? I mean, I think we covered it all. Or is this somewhere else? Do we want to say most cities of our size have hybrid representation?
It's a trend for cities of our size in our state. Or is that not really a pro? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, I don't know. I hear Eunice. Oh, she's muted. Oh, sorry.
You know, Milva, I think if you made us all hosts, we can mute and unmute ourselves. I muted myself for a second because I had something on television I just wanted to hear real quick. I didn't want you guys to hear it and interrupt you and I couldn't unmute myself. I think, you know, some of the general things, you know, like talking about how we compare to other communities and things can be maybe done in the intro.
In terms of X amount of cities and towns, X have ward representation and they have hybrid at large. This amount has amount of wards plus three, this amount of wards plus five.
Certainly, but to Gene's question was, is it a pro? Should it be listed as a pro? And I will say this to Gene's point, too, is I think it's valid because the con right beside it talks about a negative about ward representation and uses historical views of outside of Medford. If you read into where that con comes from, it says ward representation can divide the city into its different parts.
You may want to say in the con, you may want to say hybrid ward representation has seen a lot of success throughout the Commonwealth. Yeah, I mean, you would assume that it works or it would have been changed. That's a good point. Right, yeah. And it kind of combats that one that's right beside it too. I would say that the hybrid ward representation is
the preferred. You wanna say most common? It is more than the most common. I mean, it's almost every other city. Right. And Cambridge is one of the other cities that doesn't have Ward, but you can't really count them because they have ranked choice voting. So there's like maybe three, I mean, there's very few. Have we interviewed Patricia yet?
Yes, David, Daveed, and Phyllis did. And do we have her responses up yet? They haven't submitted a report, but I asked them to send the views on word representation, and I summarized them last week. Yeah. Because that's where most of my cons came from that I had typed in.
Yep. And most of them are, I think those, the ones, the last four are those comments, I think. Correct. Summarized. Yeah. Some of them are. Yeah. Those are yours. I put all yours that you wrote in these comms. So, all right. So we'll leave it as the hybrid ward system is the preferred method throughout the Commonwealth. Period. Okay.
Okay. So we accept those 10. Is there anybody have anyone else you want to add at this point? The only other one I was thinking is that, um, so far the majority of comments we've received has been in favor of board representation. Is that a con or is it how we're going to make our decision?
a pro would be I mean, a pro is a pro is why did those people who said they want that? Yeah, what's the reason why? So you definitely the survey information? Well, we would we put that in our data. But to me, it's more of a
It's not a pro of the decision. It's everybody agrees with the pro side, which you're, you know. Yeah, I wasn't sure. I mean, it's definitely a pro in the sense that it might, people may lean towards it because it seems like what most residents want at least. How many survey responses do we have now? Do we know? Almost 400. Okay.
Good. I'd be interested in the age breakdown or the length of residency breakdown in terms of the answer about word representation.
Is it the younger or more recent residents that want it? We don't have that information. The demographics aren't broken down question by question. That would be interesting. Just for the whole survey. Right now, it's a pretty large majority that thinks that the council should switch toward representation.
And most of them think the hybrids, yeah. It's really large, actually. Can those results be shared with us on a regular basis? Well, we can talk about that. I mean, I think that we can keep track of the number of responses and kind of the general responses.
I don't know. I think maybe we should just wait and discuss it when it's finished. Because we don't know what's going to happen with the survey in the next month or two. And I think Jean's either blocked from speaking or she has a comment.
Sorry, I meant to turn my video off, but I- Do you have a comment, Jean? No, I just wanted to be unmuted. Okay, all right, so let's move to the cons. We can always go back if we need to. The cons are ward representatives may focus on only their ward needs and not those of the whole city. It's valid. Yeah, I think that's proved by the studies that we've- Yeah, no, I think it's a valid con.
I agree, but I think we have it in there twice, so. Okay, let's go down, and I just took them as they were added, so we can delete whatever you need to. All right, so number one is okay, everybody's okay? Yeah. And number two, residents vote for fewer candidates, so it's the opposite of the pro in people wanting to have a full say in every candidate. So the pro is I can focus on four, or at least one, not as many,
And the con is, I want to do many. Yeah, I think you need to have the flip side of the coin. Yeah. So we could make that exactly, how do we want to say that? Just write residents vote for fewer candidates as a con? I mean, their choices are, they have fewer choices.
Right, but do we want to eliminate the example that says currently vote for seven seats versus, do you want to get rid of that? Yeah. Okay. Yeah, I think that that's. Voting for fewer candidates reduced, you know, means less, I don't know. Right, but is it basically what we say in the next one? Well, that's, they seem similar.
You don't have a say about other words. Well, we can put that up there and eliminate number three if you want to just take that whole sentence and move it to number two. I think that's what it's, I think that's what the beef is, right? That's the point that that's why. Yeah. Yeah. Right. I mean, we can, so we could combine, so we combine three and two. I think so. Yeah.
How about instead of saying say, we use the word voice to not have a voice over any other words. Yeah, that's better. And basically when it comes down to it is that voters can't choose all their city councilor. Exactly. That's actually, I like that.
Yeah. What do you want to say? Voters can't choose who all the, you know, who all the city councilors are. They can only. Voters have a limited choice. They can only choose who represents their ward and. At large. And the at large councilors. Does this say it?
Yeah. There you go. I mean, the other point with the one year, the third bullet is say there's a counselor who's
other wards feel like is blocking things that are important to them. They can't vote that person out. So I don't know if it's different. But that goes to the whole argument of ward versus at-large. It happens now, but this way, it's only one person versus the rest of them that they feel is also... One person blocking it isn't going to be able to stop it.
Gene, your point is very valuable, but that is the other side of the coin of saying, you know, you can't touch my ward. But if you wanted to do that, you would sacrifice guaranteeing a ward, each ward has a rep, in order to give them the power to eliminate one.
Yeah, I guess I was just trying to think, is there another point, like when you're voting, you're not able to vote for all the city council, but voting's where you voice your opinion, right? So if someone's served a term and then you're unhappy with them, you have no recourse, I guess. You have no recourse over the, I don't know if that's a different way of saying, I don't know if that's any different than what we've already have up there.
Do you know? I think it's just sort of what we would elaborate on about that. But we could just say something like, it's hard to read that blue. Voters cannot vote for or against, they can't vote for or against counselors outside their ward.
Yeah, if something gets put in an individual ward that the residents were really up against, so, you know, like a marijuana dispensary, yet the rest of the rest of your counselors in that large feels, oh, that's a good location, so it gets voted in. They don't have a choice to go after the ones that voted it in. They're still stuck in their individual ward, who probably their counselor
Yeah, that is the whole argument. That is the whole argument of this ward versus at-large. That's the whole argument right there. So, okay, so voters cannot vote for the entire city council. Milva, what did you want it to say? Or against. I guess that's right. Or against. Yeah, present both sides. Right. Okay.
All right, I'm deleting. So number two is okay with the edit? Okay. And number three has been deleted and combined into number two. Yeah. Great. Okay. So we're on to number four. Ward boundaries may not reflect how communities see themselves. I think that's pretty well expressed. Yeah. Okay. Everybody approve that one? Yeah. All right. Populations change.
Population change can result in unequal workloads for counselors. Yeah, it'd be helpful if we knew, like I know we have a maximum and then, but like some words 4,000 and others are six, I don't know.
Yeah, I don't know how you fix that anyways. I thought they were evenly. Yeah, I thought they were pretty even. They're pretty even. But also the other piece of that too is that just because you have a lot of people doesn't mean that the 2,000 people ward is less complaining.
And depending on what's in the wards, some, you know, it could be like, if you have Medford Square in your ward, you know, you're gonna maybe be busier. Right. On the flip side of the coin is if you're in a heavily, like commercial area, you're gonna have less residents to deal with. So I mean, I'm just talking about that area, I mean, yeah. Well, for example, if you look at Ward 4-1, which kind of encompasses,
from Boston Ave towards the Somerville line, kind of upward. I live on just, you know, off of Winthrop, so I'm in 4-2. But if you go up to where the Boston Ave and Winthrop cross, 4-1 starts like on the hillside, hardware side of Boston Ave. And if you go down Winthrop, if you're going towards Somerville,
The left-hand side is basically all Tufts. So the dorms, the academic buildings, and things like that. So you're not going to be hearing from students. They go directly to Tufts for things. The right-hand side is the residential side. And this is borne out when you see the voting results, too. It's probably the lowest voting.
Warden precinct in the city. On the other hand, I suppose if you're dealing with tufts, you're dealing with big issues. So you might not be hearing from as many individuals, but then you're dealing with the monstrosity that's tufts.
Yeah, I mean, again, it's a valid con, whether it's- Wait, no, I think we should say ward differences can result in- Yeah, I agree. That's what I was thinking is- Okay, ward differences can result. Got it. Okay. Ward differences. Ward size differences? I would just say differences. It might not even be size, right? Yeah. It could be like what's in your ward or-
Yeah, I think that's good. That's general. It's good. Ward differences can result in unequal workloads for counselors. Okay. Does anybody want to change that? No, I think that's good. Okay. So that was number five. Everybody's good with that? All right. Number six is if you don't vote for a ward candidate who gets elected, will they serve your needs? Okay. That's a con.
I don't agree that this is, that this should be on here. I mean, it's no different than today. The way you want it, you know, and yeah, any any elected office. Well, yes, but again, it's it's it's a question of is it a con? Or is it a con that will make you decide again? So it's not a con specifically of ward representation.
Unless it's going to be, you know, you've got a much smaller neighborhood. And now you're expected to just go more transparent. So you know people more and you're having an issue in your neighborhood and you contact your word. You're expected to contact your word representative you do have your at large but what if you're
I don't know. I mean, I don't know if Donato mentioned it, because he actually saw it happen in other cities. Well, Malden has wood representation, and he does what he represents a piece of Malden, so he's probably seen it. That did not come up in my discussion with Malden. So this is like the person knows that you didn't vote for them. Because it's a small community. Or no, you might have canvassed for the opposition.
You don't have a sign on your lawn. Yeah, I just all I'm saying is, I think it applies to any elected office. I agree with you. But it does. You're saying is because it's this small neighborhood thing, you're getting into hyperlocal intensifies, right? And you will have at large, but like now, if it say you went for a candidate and
They didn't get elected and so someone's mad at you. You have other, you have all six other people that choose. And from the con standpoint, if I'm, if I'm living in Ward three, and I'm holding signs for Jim X, and the other guy wins.
I don't, from this standpoint, this is not what I believe, but from this standpoint, I don't really have a ward rep anymore. I need to use, you know, the guy in ward five. I'm just, all I'm saying is I don't agree with it. I'm just saying, I'm trying to explain what this issue is. Yeah, I get it, but. I hear you. It just makes little sense to me, that's all. Yeah, well this is why I took names off of who made these up. Right, I just, the only reason I'm saying where I got that one is just
I thought he may have some experience based on representing Malden and Medford. I mean, if we're talking about this, it's not just if you don't vote for them, it's if they don't like you. Right. For some reason, right? Right. It's like, your house is ruining the neighborhood because you don't mow your lawn enough or something. But also remember that- There could be any reason that somebody would
A state rep has to live in Medford, have a history in Medford, and then he has to go campaign in Malden. So maybe he experiences some of that there too. I don't know. I don't know. Okay. That's fine. If you guys want to leave it, it's fine. Yeah. I mean, all right. So we're not, we're just leaving it as is. Yes. I like it, but.
I agree with Jane. I think it's a con because if Bill and Bob are running and you have Bill's sign on your lawn, but Bob wins. To Milva's point too, it happens all over the place too.
People know who's holding signs. And the reverse is true too. If you are holding signs for a counselor and that counselor wins, you expect that you have a better relationship because of that. So yeah, that's why I do it. Okay. Number seven.
Ward representatives might prioritize their wards above the needs of the entire city. Very valid point. I feel like that was number one. Yeah, I think that's number one. Yeah. Oh, I got you. Just a repeat. Yeah. Focus on that. OK, so that is a repeat. That was one of the add-ons. All right, so we're getting rid of that. It's already there. Yeah. Right? Yeah, I think so. Yeah, it is. It's almost word for word. And I think that's one of the big major cons.
Okay, number seven is approved tonight. All right, ward number eight, ward representation can reduce the number of qualified candidates. And I think that's valid because if there are currently four, I don't know if there are, but if there's three reps in one ward, only one can be the ward rep and the other two have to go into the general at large. So it is true.
Um, I don't, I don't know. I don't get that one. Yeah. Well, let's say, let's say right now, candidate A, B and C come out of Ward 3. Only one of them can be the ward rep.
Yeah, so so in the case, so two of them have to decide because you have to decide whether you're going out large or ward. So not only do I if I decide to battle it out in the ward against the other guy thinking I'm going to win and I lose, I don't only lose, I'm out of the I'm out of the council. So I think that's what that talks about. But isn't
I think that's only going to happen on the first year that this goes into it. I agree with you, but I think the person who wrote this... What determines them being a qualified candidate, because...
I think there are counselors on there now that aren't qualified, but that's my opinion, you know? I think that that's worth a comment. I think, and I'm trying to think for the person who thought that was important, and I think that that's the reason, is because if this happens, it's going to impact how they campaign and how you win. So it's not like, you know,
If you were, and I think that to delve deeper, it's like those folks think that one of the people who don't win could be in the top eight people on the ballot. You know, you could be one of the top seven, I mean, of the ballot and still not be on the council because you ran against somebody in your own ward. So it's not a, and that number one guy in the ward could have gotten.
Well, it doesn't, it doesn't because if I ran for, if I ran for at large, let's say that, let's say that I'm running and I decide I'm going at large because I, I think that the person will beat me in my ward. So now I go into the at large population and I finished number four, which means, yeah, number four, which means I don't get in. But my number four guy, it's hard to tell because the wards will have less numbers anyways. So there's that.
Is it that you're thinking they've already thought they're going to get beat. So they didn't go one-on-one. I'm just, I'm just, I'm just, I just want to get to what I'm trying to get to is what the con is. And then, then we can talk about is, you know, how do we decide what our recommendations that are valid. This came from Patricia and the way I,
piped it out originally from the notes that I had from a Facebook post of hers from a couple of years ago was, ward representation can reduce the number of qualified candidates. If two well-qualified candidates, let's call them Bill and Bob, are running against each other in ward one, and they're both exceptionally well-qualified to be counselors, Bill gets in. Bob now
doesn't get a seat at all, but maybe if they had both run at large, and again, they're well-qualified, then they might've, you know, if we had an all at large, they both might've gotten in, but because in a ward, only one gets in, Bill gets in, Bob doesn't. Yeah, I guess I- To Mari's point, who's qualified is very subjective. Yeah, I don't like qualified, it's sort of,
I also don't see how it, because we have an at-large system now, and you know, a lot of people would say that the more qualified candidates didn't get in last time. Yeah, I do think it's valid in some way, but to say qualified kind of bothers me. Yeah, the qualified, maybe the, maybe you say ward representation can reduce the number of,
I mean, you're basically you're saying in a way... We could say ward representation can impact the election of top candidates, which is true.
I think we're struggling to put it in there. Yeah, again, I just don't want to, I don't want to take it out because it's not the answer. It's the question that we're trying to get to. But if we say that ward representation can impact election results, why don't we just say that? I don't think that, that doesn't really say it. Well, it's kind of, it does because it, you know, you're forced to, again,
eight people of an 11 member council will get in because they're in the ward. So right now there are seven people that get chosen at large. Now it's gonna be three people in that hybrids scenario. I think it's, we're saying if multiple people that wanna run, let's leave out qualifiers like qualified. If multiple people in a ward wanna run,
they're limited with their options of getting elected, right? Like we're saying, let's say Ward 2 has five people that run a run. They could have all run and at large and might've all gotten elected. But now if you go to a hybrid. Yeah, why don't we just, can we just say Ward representation can limit options of candidates and just end it like that?
But no, to the point though, at large, all three, if it's three or five, they could all come from the same ward. They could come from a heavy, heavy voting. You know, sorry. Maury, right now, seven could all come from ward two. It doesn't. Exactly. But now only, if you go to hybrid, you only have three. Let's say, let's say this, let's say it this way. And then it's wide open.
If we say- I feel like this is a problem for the candidates, not the- Well, I mean, the candidates could be a con. We just say ward representation may limit candidate options. And for whatever, but if that doesn't, if that's not a factor for you, then it's not a factor, but it's kind of-
We need to be able to back all these things up if people say, well, what do you mean it limits options? Well, I think we can explain that. I think we can explain that question in terms of what we just talked about. What I'm trying to do is give a statement of a con that somebody has represented in discussions.
that if you wanted to take the other side of the table, somebody could legitimately say, well, why would I do this? If I'm saying limitations, the number one limitation I see is a ward that currently has two or three counselors on it. Now that counselor has to make a decision. And that's what I mean by their options have changed. That's all.
Candidate options, shouldn't it be candidate, not candidates? Because we're not talking about their, right? It says candidate possessor. Oh, so we want to say we're talking about the options of candidates as opposed to candidate options for the voters? Well, yes. Well, we can say either way because either way it impacts the voters. I feel like just say candidate. How about do you want to say, you want to say election options?
No, candidate options. That's what we just talked about, right? So ward representative may limit candidates' options. Just candidate options, meaning the options of candidates. OK, got it. So you may be like three people in ward two, but now you're limited. Yeah, OK. Is that how you're framing it, Milva? Yeah, I understand what you're saying.
More from the field of the vote. Yeah, the candidate options are going to be limited in terms of
Everything we just said, I guess. I don't know. Because we know most of them come from, is it ward four? Two and four, right? Or I forget. Two and six. Two and six. I mean, maybe we do want it to be the candidate's options. And that is the reason why you would- I mean, we said it would make it easier for them to run for office. Now we're even saying it's limiting their options. Does that make sense? I think it makes more sense to me. Yeah. Okay. Yeah. So you want it like that? The possessive, yeah.
Candidates you want it as candidates option. Yeah possessive, right? I Yeah, that's what I had. I thought you wanted it. Yeah. No, I'm sorry. I made this all very confusing. I'm sorry No, it's good because now What this pros and cons is it's it's a it's a it's a Checklist of how you should make your decision and looking at some of the options if you haven't thought about them already I
And the final one is kind of concise. The purpose of the city council is to represent the whole city, not to make it easier to get elected. Now that does, that goes back to number one, but it says it a little bit differently. Um, that doesn't make sense to me though. Well, I mean, I think all the points that say, you know, it's easier for.
me to run a campaign because I have to do it in a smaller area. I think that's what that means. I don't need as much money. I think that's what that's answering. However, there's other pros that we outlined. That's not the only reason for ward representation. So like, to me, if you're going to have that one there, you should just say the purpose of the city council should be to represent the whole city and end it there. The purpose is to represent the whole city. Got it.
Or should it be? Is it? Or should it be? Well, from that standpoint, a person would argue that, Jean, I think. Yeah. I think that's right. Because the candidate, even though they're working with their individual ward, they should be also working what's in the best interest for the entire city. Well, to be honest with you, I don't think that, I think 99.9% of the work they'll do
it requires that you do the whole city, because it's one of 11 votes. So you're not going to be able to say, we're not empowering them to say, this ward says no, you can't do that here. I'm approving permits. There's no powers involved in this. You still have to get along. You still have to work as a unit. So, okay. So that's how we're changing that with edits. And then the final one we've already talked about, number 10.
I would just take out, divide the city. I don't understand, why into its different parts? Divide, you just want to, may divide the city? Is that what you want to say? I don't think you need to divide. Divide is divisive, you know what I'm saying? I would say, you know, just take out into its different parts. Yeah, okay. Is that?
Do you want to say, yeah, okay. Do you want to say may divide the city? Hitting one part of the city against another in terms of, you know, what one would might want or not want. The rest of the city, the rest of the council, it may not go along with that thinking. You don't think representation can divide the city says that? Yeah, it does. I think, well, do you want to, is it may or can?
Can't, either one. I just want to say nay. Seems more forceful. It's a good one. Nay can. Yeah. Nay can. All right. Is there any other additional pros and cons that we didn't get to? I think you did a great job. It was good. Yeah, I think it's good too. I think it gives them a platform to use, right? At least show what we talked about. And if they have questions, again,
We're going to be able to answer the questions. That's the key. Exactly. Okay. So, um, having completed that exercise and we have 25 minutes, I think it's, uh, without further ado, I think, is it not time to discuss the, um, is anybody want to, uh, give their vote so that we know which way we're presenting here?
I mean, it's up to you, if you want to have a discussion. I think the next logical step before we start dealing in the details of the presentation is where are we at? I mean, I know we've had two straw polls and, you know, we've
I know there's been questions. Why don't we answer it the other way? With the undecided ones, have they come up with a decision yet? Well, I mean, if everybody's ready to vote yes, if somebody wants to further discuss and get more details because they're on the fence, I think this is the time to discuss. Well, then let me say this then, because I'm the undecided one here. Yeah.
I was thinking about this off and on over the last few days after I read the pros and cons and went back and I listened to our last meeting to go over my own piece with the data and stuff to make sure I was clear on what we needed. But I was listening to a good deal of the meeting again. And I feel like we as a subcommittee and then we, the 11 of us, seem
And the survey's still out there. We have just under 400 responses we learned tonight and hopefully lots more to go with it being available for two more months. I feel like we're predisposed toward representation without hearing from a wide swath of the city. I do wish that these pros and cons were out there now
as people are responding to the survey, they may feel like one way is the way that they wanna go where they haven't really seen the other side and maybe there's something on the other side that says, oh, I didn't think of this. I thought I was going with board representation, but wow, I saw that con and I really think now I've changed my mind.
I feel like we as a group are predisposed to ward representation. I almost feel like, you know, and I watch too much Law and Order, but that we've already zeroed in on the suspect and we're just, you know, making the evidence fit the suspect instead of looking at the evidence and seeing where it leads us. You know, I would know what we want to do.
How about we go back to the entire thing without mentioning any names and say, this is what we've come up with with pros and cons. Three or four are in favor of this way. One person is against. And let's have a discussion with the whole committee and see what they do without mentioning any names who's in favor or who's against.
Well, I think, let me just say a couple of words. First of all, I think one of the responsibilities, as I understand this committee, is to do the work and to also pass forth a recommendation. Now, to Eunice's point, we are creating a presentation that's going in front of the Committee of the Whole, and then it's going in front of the public, that presentation.
without, with only a recommendation. So our recommendation is this, the committee of the whole recommendation could be totally different. That's why it's, you know, it's not worth writing up a full presentation if they decide against what we recommend.
And then in October, whatever date that is in October, the public meeting, that's gonna be their first chance to look at this one singular piece of what they'll be voting on once it gets on the ballot. So in terms of giving them the pros and the cons and all the information, that's really the purpose of the public meeting is to give them that ability to fully understand. And I think our charge is to number one, provide the information, which we can check that off because I think we've done
ample research, and I also think that a, you know, an honest vote, I mean, MOVA's called for a vote twice the last two meetings, and an undecided vote is an okay vote. I mean, the reporting back is, you know, four people voted for, one person is undecided. Now here is, now let's go to the Committee of the Whole. It's valuable information. Then if the Committee of the Whole says seven,
four, three undecided, maybe from that we'll decide to go back and do more work. But in my opinion, in my strong opinion is that if we pull back and start creating more research again, we will be, there's definitely more research to do, but we also have a ton of, you know, there's a school committee, subcommittee starting. I'm sure Milva has other ideas for more and more subcommittees.
We have to, in my opinion, we have to cut it and say, okay, we did our job. We're either for it, against it or undecided. And then we pack up that box of data and we put it in our file and we'll recall it when is necessary. But we really have an obligation to get this thing done and to at least understand that we're presenting in front of the public and then the public should give us their opinion. It's not nothing we're doing, nothing.
until nothing is in stone. If the public comes back with 100 surveys saying, you guys are crazy, I don't want board representation, then we have to represent them. That's what this is all about. But I also think that we're charged with the responsibility of not only doing the research and putting the data together, but also letting them know that because we've dug so deep, we have this opinion. And I know that if we didn't have this vote, they'll be asking for that vote. At least I would hope they would.
That's just my two cents. Anybody? Jean, go ahead. Well, Eunice, I think I heard you say you're undecided, not against. Right, undecided. And I don't mind putting my name out there. I mean, I own what I say. Sure. No, and it's fine. I want to clarify that. And then I think if we vote, I agree with you, Ron, we have to start
moving forward so we can get to the drafting. But if all the survey results come in and it's very negative about ward representation, I'm assuming as a committee we might reopen that discussion and say, okay,
Here's where we're headed. But now we've looked at everything. And so that I don't think our vote here is final final until we go through all our public processes. That's how I'm thinking of it is that I agree 100% 100% and until
You know, until there's a vote of the actual the vote, not the front of the city council vote, not the mayor's vote, but when it gets on the ballot, that's when we know that this thing will pass this one piece of so many Milva. Um, I just want to say.
I think Jean's understanding is right. The same way that we, the committee decided that we would keep the mayor unless the public, unless we had some reason to change course, which has not happened yet. I also think that, you know, I do think it's okay to do our presentation next week before the whole committee and just give them the information. And then, cause the committee is going to vote.
hopefully next week. So we don't have to make this vote and we don't have to go to the whole committee and say, well, we voted and this is what we think. We could just make our presentation and then let the committee discuss it and vote with the whole committee. Yep, we can. And we already have two votes on the record. So they'll know, I think they'll understand. And maybe that is the way to go.
to just give the presentation and then, okay. I agree. I know. What do you guys think? I mean, if this is, these are, you know, we put together these pros and cons, give them the data about, you know, the representation of the historical representation of wards for the past 20 years that we collected.
just, you know, all the stuff that we collected, just tell them. And then, and it will open a discussion, and then there will be a discussion, and then at the end of that discussion, we'll have a vote. Right, and the only thing to that is, in that discussion, the presentation is going to, if I'm listening to a presentation, to me, it's hard for me to, you know, knowing that we're already in public, given my opinion,
I can't stand up there and be neutral. I think people will know that, you know, what my opinion is just by the way I'm talking in the discussion, because not only are we presenting, then we're discussing it. So the first thing I, you know, I mean, we're going to give our opinion. I'm just, I'm just, maybe I'm dead wrong, but I just thought that the subcommittee would work through this and make a recommendation.
And then whatever happens, we did talk about that. Yeah. That was our charge. I mean, have we talked about, are we majority vote? Um, are we consensus or are we majority vote? Um, we haven't made any rules for this subcommittee. Yeah. I just don't, I don't think we, I don't think a straw vote needs to be any more than four.
Harmon Zuckerman, PB – Peter Vitale PB – He, Him, His): To two yeses to knows one undecided. I mean, it doesn't, it has no impact on what happens. It's just information for the people receiving the information. Well, for our recommendation. Yeah, only comfortable making a recommendation. If we have consensus. Oh, or are we
okay making a recommendation and just saying we're four in favor, one undecided, and here's our recommendation based on that. Because everything we say on the, we're recorded, it's all public record, we can't hide who's voting. So I don't think we have to. I still think we're fine going and just giving our presentation, having a whole committee discussion, and then having the committee vote.
So we make no recommendation at the end of this presentation. I mean, we can say, um, our thoughts during the presentation, we can say, you know, but I, but, um, I don't know. I don't think it's a necessity. I mean, I, I'm okay with doing whatever. I mean, I, again, my opinion was that I thought the expectation was that we would come back with a clear
presentation showing that we know the facts and did the research, and based on that and the hours that we've spent on this, we would have a recommendation. But if that's not- I'm okay with that, too. And if we did do that, we already know what it is because we've already taken, you know- Yeah, I don't think anybody's changed their mind. No, and I just don't, I don't, if it was three to two yeses to nos,
we would probably consider coming up with the two options in detail. And if we still, we can do that if you, if you, I mean, I think everybody knows the two choices. Well, I do know there was at least one committee member who talked about wanting to be, understand the differences between a hybrid system and what would the benefit of that be over just enlarging that large city council?
Yeah. Um, you know, and so we haven't talked about that option really very much. What if we just made the at-large council larger? Right. But we have a little bit because that's the same thing. It's still that large, whether there's seven, whether there's 25. I mean, what is the, what is the research necessary to do that? I don't know.
I don't know. I know that the person who, or the committee member who was wondering about that was very concerned with diversity. And I think that it's pretty clear that the research and the data is clear that ward representation increases, you know, increases diversity. A lot better than, I mean, at large is just a larger random sample. Right. But I mean, to that point, to that point, if we're showing
Ward representation and we're showing at large, we need to show that just increasing the number. And then again, I'm just saying, it's like, if I was listening to our presentation, one of the first questions I would have is, well, what is your opinion? And I'm not saying we need to delve into a lot of the stuff. I'm just saying post it as part of the data, because we have two public votes already.
I'm okay with that. And if we just say, you know, the committee has, the committee vote, the final committee vote was whatever it is. I mean, I'm not sure. Yeah, I mean, the committee's gonna vote, so, you know. Yeah, it is, right. It's a living document too. And then we're gonna vote again with the committee, so. Correct.
Yes, yes, yes. But I mean, undecided is not a vote. I mean, it's a, I can, you know, they don't, you know, we can all vote undecided. But I mean, I think that we've taken two votes. I think that whatever vote you have, and if you've changed your mind, I think that's really important. I think taking the vote is very valuable, because at the end of each session, I'd like to know if anybody's changed their mind and why. So I do think it's valuable. But to me,
I'm just, I just think that it would be nice to have a vote and explain, you know, which vote, which one of the options, and we can put the third option in there. It's just simply adding 11 at live draft. Is that what you want? Let's just go ahead and vote again and, you know, see if anybody's changed their mind. I don't think it's that much of a game changer one way or the other because
If I'm not on this committee and I'm on the whole committee, and when you present this to the entire committee, whether you are endorsing one over the other is not a factor on how I feel. I'm going to make up my own decision one way or the other. Yeah. Yeah. And I'm assuming that, yeah, that's very true. I'm just saying to me, to close the book on the subcommittee is have a result. And whatever that result is, it's fine.
I think we have some housekeeping stuff we have to do and I know we're leaving right now. Yeah, I'm really sorry about that. We have to end right at eight.
You have to open it up for public comment a couple of minutes before. Yeah. Cause I just want to like who's doing the slides and how are we voting together? Can we vote quickly and then decide whether we want a recommendation slide or not? And then the housekeeping. Okay. Okay. So those in favor of hybrid ward representation, just for a show of hands. Four. Those in favor of,
At-large, raise your hand. Those in favor of adding the at-large council to 11. I would just say adding to the existing number of at-large councils. Delimiting to or from, but that's up to you guys. In any undecided. One.
One. Okay, so it's four, four for hybrid, zero for at large, zero for adding more counselors and one undecided. Okay? Yep. All right, so let's go very quickly back to, I'm gonna write the intro and get that out hopefully by the weekend. And then that, is it Eugene that does the first part or is it Eunice?
So do we want? Can we go back to the presentation part? Yeah, I got to find it. Yes. It'd be good. I don't know if we're going to run out of time, but Ron, if you gave us an agenda, like who's doing what. I think we said I go first. Yeah, I think we wrote it. Or maybe it should be Eunice goes first, and then I go. I think Eunice went first. Let me see. I have it here. I'm just going to find it.
And I think the stuff Danielle gave me, I think I can update if I can figure out the data. I think I can update my slides for the eight wards. OK. So we have actually what we did originally was you were first, Jean, with your demographics. Then Eunice was with her election data. And that was with the slides that we chose from last meeting. Yeah. Right?
And Eunice, I know that you had more data that you're either waiting for or... Yeah, Jean and I did some work yesterday on the
you know, actual candidate wood representation data and put together some slides yesterday. I don't think we have time to look at them. Um, but as for the rest of the data, you know, I, I'm trying to get stuff from the city. Um, it's proving difficult to say the least, um, uh, in terms of, you know, getting that data that we wanted,
that would give us the turnout versus the candidates, the ward turnout, I don't think that I'm gonna be able to get that. Yeah, I think, did we get the, what were we looking for? The number of candidates by ward, is that? And you have that, except it doesn't go back. Yeah, we have that. We did.
We have the voter turnout by ward versus the registration registered voters. I don't think I'm going to be able to get. Yeah. I did go back to, to Maury's point last time, going back further, I did actually spend, um, a good portion of last weekend. I went, the, the data on the city website goes back to 2005, not 2001, as we talked about the other day.
So I did go back over the weekend and populated my spreadsheets all the way back to 2005. But all that was available there pretty much was the breakdown by candidate and by ward of how many ballots, how many votes they received. Turnout was just, you know. Did you work with a gene on the tables or the pie charts, whatever you were doing?
As far as, you know, what candidates represented what. So you're going to show. Any turnout or anything I can't get. So my vision is this. My vision is that we're talking through this at our meeting. So what I just need to know is, Jean, you have your two slides. And, you know, we're going to limit it to your talk about where this information came and what the slides mean. Right.
OK, so you've got that. You're comfortable with that? Yeah. Danielle just gave me a big data dump for the eight wards. And it's up to me to analyze it. So I just have to make sure I can actually write the algorithms and figure it all out. And I asked David to help me. So the by ward slide, I'm going to try to do. I'm trying.
OK, I got you. So if you need something, just email the group and we'll. So your piece is the slides, and you're going to talk to it. And Eunice, you have how many slides do you have? I think there were, what, four? I think they're in the folder. So you can look at them. I put them in the folder. There's four. OK. You can look at them and let Eunice know which ones you like, I guess. You can kind of present it in different ways.
Okay. And Eunice, you're prepared to do the same and talk about how you gathered it and then talk to the charts and what they show. Right. I may touch base with you on offline about some of the other data. Sure. No problem. No problem. And Milva, you're going to just briefly talk about an option. Very briefly. Depending on what
If the word demographics come through, then there may be something else to say, but. Yeah. And then I'll just put the, redo these, the edits on the pros and cons. And then just in my intro, I'm talking about the surveys and the interviews that were done to help compile this information. And the current makeup of the council. Yeah. And yeah, the current makeup of the town, what it looks like, what the three options are.
I'll also talk about the straw vote and the recommendation, how we see it. And then we'll move to a discussion about, um, and we'll probably pull up that pros and cons slide again and have everybody discuss that. We talked about a map. So I sent you the recent map. I saw that new map. Yeah. I saw that new map. Yep. Yep. Yeah. And again, we did discuss them.
I do too, and I think if we trim ours to less time, it gives more time for them to ask the questions, and that's gonna drive the discussion. Yeah, I think that's important to try to make our, be as succinct as possible because the committee's gonna wanna. Yep, yeah, so I'll work on that this weekend, my piece, and send it out so you all can see what it's gonna look like, and then we'll. Are we trying to put it all into one PowerPoint? I can, I can do a PowerPoint.
Let me start a PowerPoint and I'll send it out and you can all look at it this weekend and see. We'll just look at it, not discuss it. Right, we can't discuss it.
I tried to move our data slides into Google slides and it changed everything. Well, and the other point, Jean, too, is I don't really, the presentation I'm more concerned about is for the public meeting. But if we're just in this meeting and you pull up your information for the committee, I think that's okay.
You know, they want a visual and I'll have some visual stuff, but I think the most important things are the, you know, what we were looking at, your demographics, Eunice's historical data, a bit from Milva, and then we show the pros and cons and what we voted on. I think it's... And then we'll develop the PowerPoint. Okay.
So we have one minute. Sorry. Okay. So public. Let me just get open the public. Is anybody here? No. Bill is here. Okay. You may not want to speak. Bill, you there? Yeah, can you hear me? Okay. Yeah.
Okay, so I just have one question, and this is maybe out of you guys' jurisdiction. If you guys, let's just say we went with more representatives, whether it's ward or at large, who decides to pay for them? Do they make their own pay? No. I don't know. That's a long time. That's a question we'll have to look into. Yeah, no, I just curious, because I know like Malden,
representative only gets like 14,000, I think ours gets 30,000. And if we add more, is it going to be at that 30,000 level? Or? Oh, you know, that's my question. Yeah. Excellent question. You know, because that's, you know, if each ward is getting like, I know, like, I've checked in mall and their ward representatives in there at large, they all get the same, which is I think,
Yeah, I mean, it's either like 14 or 17 or something like that. Yeah, it's very like, it's almost, it's almost half what we get. So I was just curious if we're adding more, are we going to that, to that level? Well, that's actually a valid con. Yeah, we don't, we don't know. Well, I don't know if it's, it's not, I feel the answer to your question. It's not in this subcommittee's role and we don't set budgets or dollars as a, as Milva's committee does of the whole. So I would say no.
Okay. I don't know that our committee does either. Yeah, no, I don't think we can change salaries or things like that. I hope not. Good question though. All right. Thank you very much. And thank you guys again for all you're doing. Thanks, Bill. Appreciate it. All right. It's one pass. So we got to pay Nova overtime now again. You get a full hour. You get a full hour. All right. Thank you all. I'll be in touch this weekend. Okay. All right.