Welcome back to our next edition of Coffee Chats with Kingsley's.
My special guest is going to introduce herself today.
Hello, my name is Caroline Kingsley.
I go to the Brooks School and I am in second grade.
What are we talking about today, Caroline?
Strategic plans.
What's a strategic plan?
I don't know.
No.
What is a strategic plan?
So when you start doing something, do you have a plan beforehand?
Yes.
Sometimes yes, sometimes no, or always?
I usually have like based on kind of.
Yeah.
So the same thing should be true for our schools.
So if you're running a school district or a company or something,
Kind of knowing the basics of what you wanna do before you get started helps you do it in a way that makes more sense and that's easier.
Does that make sense?
What do you think would happen if you try to do something without a plan?
You might mess up and like,
Like, bomb the whole thing?
Yeah.
Mess up the whole thing?
Right, and we don't want to mess up the whole school district, so we're going to create a plan.
Okay, thank you for coming to Coffee Chats with the Kingsley's.
Cheers out, people!