[SPEAKER_00]: Welcome back to our next edition of Coffee Chats with Kingsley's.
[SPEAKER_00]: My special guest is going to introduce herself today.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hello, my name is Caroline Kingsley.
[SPEAKER_02]: I go to the Brooks School and I am in second grade.
[SPEAKER_00]: What are we talking about today, Caroline?
[SPEAKER_02]: Strategic plans.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's a strategic plan?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is a strategic plan?
[SPEAKER_00]: So when you start doing something, do you have a plan beforehand?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes yes, sometimes no, or always?
[SPEAKER_02]: I usually have like based on kind of.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the same thing should be true for our schools.
[SPEAKER_00]: So if you're running a school district or a company or something,
[SPEAKER_00]: Kind of knowing the basics of what you wanna do before you get started helps you do it in a way that makes more sense and that's easier.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does that make sense?
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you think would happen if you try to do something without a plan?
[SPEAKER_02]: You might mess up and like,
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, bomb the whole thing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mess up the whole thing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, and we don't want to mess up the whole school district, so we're going to create a plan.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, thank you for coming to Coffee Chats with the Kingsley's.
[SPEAKER_02]: Cheers out, people!