I'll just do it to my computer.
We have a Medford school committee meetings, which is a special meeting on July 24th, 2024 at 5 PM.
It will be held remotely via Zoom.
The purpose of this meeting is provided in the agenda section below.
This meeting is being recorded.
The meeting can be viewed live on the Medford Public Schools YouTube channel through Medford Community Media on your local cable, Comcast 9, 8, or 22, and Verizon 43, 45, or 47.
The meeting will be recorded.
Since the meeting will be held remotely, participants can log or call in by using the following information.
The Zoom link and the meeting ID is 891-7279-2499.
Questions or comments can be submitted during the meeting by emailing medfordsc at medford.k12.ma.us.
Those submitting questions or comments must include the following information, your first and last name, your Redford Street address, your question or comment.
Member Rousseau, if you could call the roll, please.
Certainly.
Member Bramley.
Present.
Member Graham.
Here.
Member Ntapa.
Member Olopade.
Here.
Member Rheinfeld.
Present.
Member Rousseau present.
Mayor Lungo-Kern.
Present.
Seven present, zero absent.
We all may rise to salute the flag.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America and to the Republic for which it stands, one nation under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all.
And we have executive session pursuant to chapter 30 a section 21.
Section 2 to conduct strategy in preparation with nonunion personnel or contract negotiations with nonunion personnel, which is our superintendent of schools.
It's a motion to go into executive session.
So moved.
Second member Graham roll call, please.
Yes, 7 in the affirmative, 0 in the negative.
Motion to go into executive session is approved and that will be just with the school committee and Attorney Greenspan.
Mayor?
Yes.
And Marissa?
Do we want to, we should let the public know whether we're going to return to open session afterwards or not.
I don't think that we will.
Yeah, I don't think so.
Okay, so we will not return.
We will adjourn from within executive session.