[SPEAKER_00]: Hello, everyone, and welcome to Method Happenings, a show for and about the city of Medford.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am John Petrella, and the purpose of this program is to give Medford citizens facts and information to help you make informed choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: Our guest for the show today is Nate Merritt, better known as the kid from Riverside.
[SPEAKER_00]: The reason Nate is joining us today is Nate is a candidate for our Medford City Council.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I would also like to mention that Nate is often, I mean often, in attendance at city council meetings.
[SPEAKER_00]: He speaks up on issues and concerns for the residents of Medford.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I want to thank you, Nate, for joining us today.
[SPEAKER_00]: Looking forward to you answering some questions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So welcome to the show.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thanks for having me, John.
[SPEAKER_00]: OK.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the first question, or what I always like to start off with is, who's Nate Merritt?
[SPEAKER_00]: Give us a little background.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tell us about yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: All right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thanks for the opportunity.
[SPEAKER_02]: So my name's Nate.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm actually a systems engineer, bachelor's and master's out of UMass Amherst.
[SPEAKER_02]: I've been working as an engineer for 17 years.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was born and raised in Western Mass, so I am not from Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: Interesting.
[SPEAKER_02]: I moved out here in around 2009 and met my wife.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I actually knew her from college before, but we got together.
[SPEAKER_02]: And yeah, so my mom was a nurse.
[SPEAKER_02]: My dad was a fireman.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he was on the job for 30 years.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I grew up on a small tree farm.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's something I still keep up today.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I myself went to the fire service, and it's funny, because my dad would say, son, don't go into the fire service.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a lot of politics.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, well, sorry, dad, because not once, now, but twice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I'm actually 25 years now as a MAS certified EMT.
[SPEAKER_02]: and I'm a private pilot, husband, I got two young boys, they're great, and I bought my home on Riverside Ave in 2014.
[SPEAKER_02]: About five months later, after first buying my home, my welcome to Medford was a car crashing through my front yard, taking out my whole front fence, and it hit the building next door.
[SPEAKER_00]: Riverside Ave.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what brought me to the City Council my first time.
[SPEAKER_02]: There was something happening at the building next door.
[SPEAKER_02]: They were going to open a business and I was worried about the traffic flow because it's probably one of the strangest intersections.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can see where the stoplight is before the driveway.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so I just raised a concern because of the traffic flow.
[SPEAKER_02]: I didn't want to see anyone else get hurt.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that brought me to City Council and since then I've tried to offer practical solutions
[SPEAKER_02]: whenever I can, not just be a complainer, but try to offer some solutions.
[SPEAKER_02]: So for example, and I don't even remember when it was, but there was talk of needing money for, I don't know if it was the fire station, the library, so on and so forth.
[SPEAKER_02]: Instead of raising taxes, I said, hey, what if you gave people the option in their property tax bill to make a donation?
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you look in the upper right corner of your property tax bill,
[SPEAKER_02]: you'll see a spot to make a donation for the library, the police station, or the fire department.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that was an idea I came up with during public comments at a city council meeting.
[SPEAKER_02]: So obviously, someone heard me.
[SPEAKER_02]: They took your advice, it was a good idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there we go.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's a good thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm a person I believe in limited government.
[SPEAKER_02]: We're five miles from a group of people 250 years ago that maybe thought the same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that said, government should work for the people.
[SPEAKER_02]: and not necessarily the other way around.
[SPEAKER_02]: And we should always be careful if we're infringing on individual liberties.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what this country was founded on.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I also understand the need for government.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a balance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And your father, like I said, you're really getting into politics now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all right, so you gave us a good introduction there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, what reasons are making you run for a seat on the City Council?
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you know, why do you want the job?
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll be honest with you, John, I don't want the job.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'd much rather be at home playing with my kids and spending time at city council meetings even now and I've said that before.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I think unfortunately we can either complain about it or we can do something about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I'm at the point where it's time to try to do something.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think we need to give a voice back to the people.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think, unfortunately, the way things have been running for the past two years, for example, you look at recent meetings that have happened zoning, especially in Salem Street.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I was there and I saw people for hours sitting there making comments and concerns.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there was, you know, the Community Development Board had incorporated
[SPEAKER_02]: suggestions from, you know, the residents, and I watched a city councilor just say, yeah, I don't like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Change it and just go their own way.
[SPEAKER_02]: And to me, that's not sad.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that I can also start giving some critical thought to some issues.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that people are maybe good intentioned, but I think we need to start weighing pros and cons of things, and especially always asking the question, how does it benefit the residents of Medford today?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's awesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: That should be number one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Always should be the residents of Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, honestly, I'm kind of tired of sitting back and watching the agenda removing the rights of our citizens.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we have rent control on the table.
[SPEAKER_02]: You've got a tree ordinance coming up.
[SPEAKER_02]: You've got zoning.
[SPEAKER_02]: I saw what happened with the charter.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: And same thing where the voice of the people was lost.
[SPEAKER_02]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unilaterally.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think our sense of community is deteriorating and there's an agenda and it's being plowed forward.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're plowing forward with it, John.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I agree.
[SPEAKER_00]: I agree.
[SPEAKER_00]: I hear you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's a good answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Great answer, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know, you've given us some good reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are good reasons why you're running for a seat on the city council.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I'm going to ask you this question.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I've been to City Hall.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've seen you offer solutions.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a matter of fact, you seem to offer a lot of solutions.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you know, I'm going to go ahead and ask.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, what solutions do you have?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can just pick out one or two from the answers you just gave me.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what solutions?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you going to, do you think you can come up with or you have for the concerns you just told us about?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I think something that could be done even today is, you know, sometimes these city council meetings go long and there's a lot of people that want to be heard.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I've been there till 12, 1 in the morning.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I've seen people that want to talk, and they go home because they have jobs in the morning or, you know, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: They just can't stay up that late.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I've seen sometimes where the agendas have been rejiggered.
[SPEAKER_02]: And we're talking about national issues that
[SPEAKER_02]: The city of Medford can impact, but we're sucking the oxygen out of the room instead of dealing with the local ones.
[SPEAKER_02]: And people wanna speak about the local issues, but that gets tabled until after 11, 12 p.m.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I think something we could do is if the meeting runs past 11 o'clock, we're done, shut it down, table the rest of the agenda to the next week.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everyone should be heard.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when it's running that late, that's not fair to anybody.
[SPEAKER_02]: And we shouldn't be making decisions literally in the dark of the night.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, and I think everyone,
[SPEAKER_00]: has seen that happen, I mean, on more than one occasion, where the meetings have gone incredibly late.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, I'll just chime in with, I've been there where important issues get pushed back.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there'd be talk, you've, we're both in the same room, where national issues would come into play, they discuss those first, nothing to do with Medford.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you had a key issue like the charter commission, you know, what's going on with the charter, and boy, we wouldn't get started until 10 o'clock at night on some of that stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: And a lot of people do have to go to work and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know, good answers, good answers, Nate.
[SPEAKER_00]: I appreciate the honesty, too.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a big thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, do you see any steps being taken
[SPEAKER_00]: you know, by the current administration, you know, to resolve some of these issues you just talked about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there anything going on that you think is going to resolve these issues?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you think it's possible to resolve?
[SPEAKER_00]: Put it that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think people are trying, but, John, if everything was hunky-dory, I wouldn't be running.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll be honest with you.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that the administration needs to really consider doing an audit of the city finances.
[SPEAKER_02]: We're talking $5 million that's missing from the school committee budget and then found and $34 million.
[SPEAKER_02]: We're making Enron and Arthur Anderson look good here.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's nothing to laugh about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good answer, yeah, I hear ya, I hear ya.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that in terms of the sense of community, there's a lot of red tape.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm gonna tell you a story real quick.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I told you I got little guys.
[SPEAKER_02]: One of my favorite parks I like to go to is Logan Park.
[SPEAKER_02]: There, there's a little fire truck, like playground thing for kids to go play, little kids to play on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I had my son with me and I noticed the wooden boards were, they were in rough shape and I didn't want my kid to get splinters or any other kid.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I called the mayor's office, wrote an email, said, Hey, listen, this is a couple boards.
[SPEAKER_02]: I get it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm willing to go fix it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't want to just go start ripping up, you know, pressure treated wood and putting bolts in.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll have the cops down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I said, Hey, can I get some top cover and just let them know what I'm willing to do?
[SPEAKER_02]: And this is on my own nickel, my own time.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is sawing a couple boards and installing a couple carriage bolts and nuts.
[SPEAKER_02]: This isn't rocket science.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm an engineer.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is not rocket science.
[SPEAKER_02]: I hear you.
[SPEAKER_02]: It became a whole production and I talked with, you know, she put me in touch with some of the parks folks and nothing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then a couple months later it got fixed.
[SPEAKER_02]: And meanwhile, I've got to watch my kid like a hawk and I'm working like for everybody.
[SPEAKER_02]: And this was initially something that was donated to the city by a resident.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it's not like the city wound up purchasing it or something originally either.
[SPEAKER_02]: So there are people willing to do
[SPEAKER_02]: you know, help out the community and not necessarily for any money.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, that's volunteerism and that's a good thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think if we had a better sense of community and maybe we find a way to eliminate some of the red tape, you'll find people who are willing to pitch in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I agree with you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's, that's a good point.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, that's what we would call a small issue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Important, nonetheless, but that's a good point because it's the little things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, there's a lot of people in this city that will do the little things.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the bottom line.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know, I appreciate that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I really do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Small stuff matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: A lot of talk, you mentioned real quick the zoning in Medford, and there's so much going on right now with the zoning.
[SPEAKER_00]: And meetings and people, it's on Zoom, and a lot of people, I gotta be honest, they don't know too much about all the zoning, what's going on.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's your position on zoning?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's coming to Medford, I mean, they're doing things.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's your position on it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you have a position?
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that zoning is a huge concern overall, and I know there's a lot of chatter about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think my personal view is it's something we should look at, but it's like everything else, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: Extremes are not necessarily good in general, in any system, in any government, in any operation.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that said, I think right now what we're seeing is essentially it could be mass gentrification.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a lot of rezoning happening all at once.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll give you an example again.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a talk of we need more affordable housing.
[SPEAKER_02]: I ask the question, what is affordable to you?
[SPEAKER_02]: I have two kids in daycare.
[SPEAKER_02]: I have a mortgage.
[SPEAKER_02]: And all the other expenses that go along with that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I still somehow afford it, but we've had to make choices along the way.
[SPEAKER_02]: So more supply in the city of Medford, I don't think is gonna move the needle at all in terms of the cost of rent, the cost of mortgage.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we're going to go increase the supply.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I heard from a city councilor that said, well, I'm not going to go explain the details of supply and demand.
[SPEAKER_02]: I got it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But this is like attacking a tank with a toothpick.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there are greater economic forces at play than anything the city of Medford can influence.
[SPEAKER_02]: So why are we addressing the zoning to begin with?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it for the needs of the residents?
[SPEAKER_02]: And what's the benefit for the current residents of the city?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, my concern with the zoning really is more about the commercial and the industrial side.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: A lot of people don't know this, but commercial and industrial pay twice the amount the residents do.
[SPEAKER_02]: And for every commercial business or industrial zone you lose, who picks up the tab?
[SPEAKER_02]: The other commercial businesses.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the residents.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're talking taxes.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you're basically talking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm talking taxes, but also wear and tear on your services.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your fire, your police, your EMS, your roads, your schools.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's correct.
[SPEAKER_02]: All that has to be taken into consideration.
[SPEAKER_02]: My house is a single family house.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I came to Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: I wanted a single family home, and I don't think there's anything wrong with that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Some people are meant for condos, and I'm not one of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's part of what attracted us to Medford.
[SPEAKER_02]: We know how that right now my house under the new plan will be zoned for three family So they will tear my house down.
[SPEAKER_02]: They'll buy it from me for whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's say we're 750 today Yeah, someone else could buy it for 750 000 and have their family And and and use a starter house.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah instead Contractor's gonna come
[SPEAKER_02]: buy it, tear it down, turn it into a triplex, and sell each unit for a million dollars.
[SPEAKER_00]: Who's that affordable for?
[SPEAKER_00]: I agree with you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always been about choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess my opinion, it would be nice to see some affordable housing in the city, but there's a limit.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's how you go about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I agree with most of what you're saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're making some good points here.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you're making some very good points.
[SPEAKER_00]: So okay, let's move from that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's get on to, it's no secret.
[SPEAKER_00]: You mentioned it, economic growth in Metfin, best described as stagnant.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I think everyone's aware of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's no secret.
[SPEAKER_00]: So as far as spending and taxes go, do you have priorities?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you have a plan?
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, what would you, you get elected to the city council, what are you looking to do?
[SPEAKER_02]: I think the question isn't how do we get economic growth.
[SPEAKER_02]: The city is not a publicly traded Wall Street company.
[SPEAKER_02]: What's the metric?
[SPEAKER_02]: And I've asked that publicly before.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not revenue dollars coming in and every year you want more revenue.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no earnings ratio on the city.
[SPEAKER_02]: The metric in this case should be sustainment.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what we should be looking at.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when you have industry leaving, that's a problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: We need to fix that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not growth, it's just keeping what we have at a minimum.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's try to work that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Example, August Bush, down on Riverside Ave.
[SPEAKER_02]: Before the overrides came in, right, they probably read the tea leaves and they had a choice to make.
[SPEAKER_02]: Do they operate out of Quincy or do they operate out of Medford?
[SPEAKER_02]: They chose Quincy.
[SPEAKER_02]: OK.
[SPEAKER_02]: So now, the latest I heard, you tell me if you've heard any different.
[SPEAKER_02]: I know Market Basket was maybe considering it, but so was the MBTA.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the MBTA is the lead bidder.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're the highest bidder last I heard.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's over 20 acres, and it's like 24 acres of property, commercial property.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So if the MBTA winds up actually purchasing that property, that's 24 acres worth of commercial tax revenue gone.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the MBTA, they'll pay the permits and fees to build their structures, but then they don't owe a dime for taxes afterwards.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that burden is going to shift to the remaining commercial industrial.
[SPEAKER_02]: And this just begins quicksand.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a spiral.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I think, and there's plenty of vacant commercial buildings, it's not just in Medford, I've seen it actually in Malden too, near where the Aviva Trattoria is, near Exchange Street in Malden.
[SPEAKER_02]: Big sign, 300,000 square feet available.
[SPEAKER_02]: Across the street from my house, 400 Riverside Ave, 100,000 square feet available.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I've seen those signs too, yep, yep.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think we really should be focusing on and talking with them, how do we get these buildings filled?
[SPEAKER_02]: In terms of the local area,
[SPEAKER_02]: You've got Wooburn.
[SPEAKER_02]: Wooburn's got a lot of industry.
[SPEAKER_02]: When people want to go build buildings here, they go to Wooburn to go get their heavy equipment, to get their building materials.
[SPEAKER_02]: They buy steel there.
[SPEAKER_02]: These aren't things that necessarily negatively impact the surrounding community.
[SPEAKER_02]: In fact, they've done a really good job.
[SPEAKER_02]: Malden.
[SPEAKER_02]: Malden's got the Panadosi Bakery.
[SPEAKER_02]: They make bread.
[SPEAKER_02]: You've got the New England Coffee.
[SPEAKER_02]: They have a lot.
[SPEAKER_02]: You've got National Grid.
[SPEAKER_02]: What are we making, Medford?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I hear ya.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sausage.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, no, I hear ya.
[SPEAKER_02]: I love Bianco sausage, don't get me wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, me too, me too.
[SPEAKER_00]: Great product.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's what we're making now, is sausage.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good plugin for Bianco's.
[SPEAKER_02]: Absolutely, if you've never been to Bianco's, go.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: I love the chicken sausage.
[SPEAKER_02]: We have vocational schools, we're one of the few in the area, we should be promoting that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unit Man's the nearest one, that's up in Lexington, and a lot of people don't wanna drive that far.
[SPEAKER_02]: And we gotta use the river,
[SPEAKER_02]: We're unique.
[SPEAKER_02]: We've got a river, we've got interstate access, we've got major routes and highways, and we've got the T. We should be capitalizing on that and fostering it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think that river's going to, if it's even up the square, and I'm not, but if things get done right, and if people really look into it, that could be a big revenue driver.
[SPEAKER_02]: Anything that brings people from out of the city into the city to spend money and support the local economy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, no, I hear you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's more commercial, industrial.
[SPEAKER_00]: Spending and taxes.
[SPEAKER_00]: We can go on for weeks, but we're not going to, but we could.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know a lot of people
[SPEAKER_00]: talk, you know, there's all different sides to this story.
[SPEAKER_00]: The two basic sides are, you know, control your spending, you know, let's really take a look at what you have and, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: Right now, it looks like they're just looking for more taxes, taxes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you know, the bottom line is, as far as spending and taxes, what do you think?
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, do you have any priorities?
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you feel about that Barlow X?
[SPEAKER_02]: I think the fact that we passed two overrides, and don't take my word for it, look at the video.
[SPEAKER_02]: You had the city council president and you had the mayor dancing.
[SPEAKER_02]: at the thought, not the thought, but at the fact that people now are only paying only $400 more a year in their taxes.
[SPEAKER_02]: How's that working out?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's my thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, spending is necessary.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sometimes tax increases are necessary, but nobody should ever be happy about it, and certainly nobody should ever be excited.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that was the wrong attitude to have on that, and that was a little unprofessional.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that said, also, we've got a lot of lawsuits happening in the city.
[SPEAKER_02]: That needs to stop.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not doing anybody any favors.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's a waste of taxpayer money.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then there's other little gems, which I get it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to pay people.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to have nice things.
[SPEAKER_02]: But when you go back to the well, now you've got to start really taking a hard look and understanding what are my needs versus my wants.
[SPEAKER_02]: I deal with this with my kids.
[SPEAKER_02]: We all do.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when I see that we're paying two grand a year for a poet laureate.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you asked for 500,000 for roads and streets.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: I got to wonder what else is going on.
[SPEAKER_02]: And again, when you start seeing millions that are going missing and people refuse to do an audit, again, this is making Enron look good folks.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: I hear you.
[SPEAKER_00]: All right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know, let's get on to something else now.
[SPEAKER_00]: You did not attend school here.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think, I guess you've lived here for around 10 years, you said.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know, Medford has rich history.
[SPEAKER_00]: I love history.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's me personally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Always a big history fan.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, so you've only been here for 10 years.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you think about the history in Medford
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, what do you know about the history of method?
[SPEAKER_00]: Put it that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's a few things in Medford, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: And you're correct.
[SPEAKER_02]: Normally, the things you would learn in school, I didn't have that opportunity, because I know about the things instead in Western Mass.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: In my school, we learned about General Knox, and he went and captured a whole bunch of cannons from Fort Ticonderoga and brought a little caravan through the state of Massachusetts, including my hometown, what's now Route 20, and parked them on Dorchester Heights and liberated Boston.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's one of the things that brought my hometown to fame.
[SPEAKER_02]: Medford built clipper ships.
[SPEAKER_02]: Medford had brickyards.
[SPEAKER_02]: Paul Revere rode through on the way to go warn about the British trying to interfere with some patriots over in Lexington and Concord.
[SPEAKER_02]: Apparently there's some rum.
[SPEAKER_02]: that Medford is known for.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, Medford made some good rum, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've never had it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I heard the recipe's still around, but I've never had it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I heard someone's bringing it back, so that'll be interesting, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So one of the ways I learned some of the history is from the Mystic River Bend Park.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's down behind the McGlynn schools and around the corner from where I live.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so I went and I took some pictures yesterday.
[SPEAKER_02]: I went out in the rain because I wanted to make sure my information was accurate.
[SPEAKER_02]: The signs look about the same rough shape that they did when I first saw them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's sad because, I mean, we have community preservation funding.
[SPEAKER_02]: To me, this is literally preserving your community.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's in the name, Community Preservation Act.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Some of those signs are unfortunately in such disrepair.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's graffiti on them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there's a lot of great info that talk about the river, how it used to be salt marshes and where throughout the years where it changed the ecology.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now there's graffiti on them and they're barely readable.
[SPEAKER_02]: One of them looks like it was melted in the sun or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a shame.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think we really should be taking care of our city better.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And little things like that go a long way.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's probably been like that for almost 10 years.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, like I said, you're looking at some, I like looking at the little things, a lot of big things, but you know, it's nice that you're looking at some of the little things too that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're little, but they matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you show
[SPEAKER_02]: that you care about your city, maybe you won't get trashed as easily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, yeah, I hear you.
[SPEAKER_00]: I hear you.
[SPEAKER_00]: I really do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Um, some great answers.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uh, all right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I'm just gonna basically, you know, these are more like personal questions, silly questions.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know what you want to call them, but, um, you know, we're going to have some other candidates on.
[SPEAKER_00]: I like to just find out little things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, uh,
[SPEAKER_00]: What would you say are the least and your most favorite things for you to do in Method?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I mean, you know, there's got to be things you love to do and maybe some things you don't like to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Give it a shot.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you think?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm a father with young kids, so I don't get to go out as much as I want, as much as I used to.
[SPEAKER_02]: Usually, my fun things now involve them.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll say, fresh donuts over at Donuts with a Difference.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's unique.
[SPEAKER_02]: Good choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Remember, I grew up when Dunkin' Donuts used to make all the donuts in every store, and the old man was there, time to make the donuts.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it's a unique thing that we have, and I love their donuts.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're awesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: I bring them to work with me when I can.
[SPEAKER_02]: People love them.
[SPEAKER_02]: The various parks in the city, I'm involved using those.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're great.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's what I spend a lot of my time doing.
[SPEAKER_02]: As far as things I don't like,
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I'd be remiss if I said, you know, going to city council meetings, but I'll be honest with you, staying up until 12 o'clock at night, going to city council meetings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't, I don't love that.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't think anyone loves it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, uh, driving down my street, I don't know what am I driving down roads in the city of Medford or am I in a, you know, looking at Germany, occupied France and world war II.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: A few potholes, huh?
[SPEAKER_02]: A couple potholes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not sure what happened here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, I hear ya.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe I like a little bit of history.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's, you know, good answer, good answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, I remember, you know, I had two children, and I remember back when they were young, he did a lot of, you know, everything is for the kids.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, that's the way it should be.
[SPEAKER_00]: And CB Scoops.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, CB Scoops.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's one of the things we love.
[SPEAKER_00]: The kids love it.
[SPEAKER_00]: We go there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, it's great.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're dealing with the kids.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're at that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know.
[SPEAKER_00]: I feel you.
[SPEAKER_02]: We eat the ice cream.
[SPEAKER_02]: We watch the train go by.
[SPEAKER_02]: My kid loves trains.
[SPEAKER_02]: We literally get to see the train.
[SPEAKER_02]: And we'll sit there and just watch the bell.
[SPEAKER_00]: I miss those days.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're bringing back good memories for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're getting down on time here.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I do want to ask you.
[SPEAKER_00]: I always ask this.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, growing up in Method my whole life, if I wanted to go find someone, I always, you know, depending on who it was, I knew where I could go find them, put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I wanted to find you, if I wanted to get in touch with you, Mr. Merritt, where in Metford would someone look for you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Someone wanted to meet you, introduce you, whatever, where would they meet you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where would be a good place to look?
[SPEAKER_00]: And I know you're busy, you've got kids, but...
[SPEAKER_02]: If there's a hot topic going on, you might find me at the podium at a city council meeting on a Wednesday night.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've seen you here plenty of times.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like I said, I've attended quite a few of those.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're always there.
[SPEAKER_00]: One of the things, one of the many things I do like about you is
[SPEAKER_00]: solutions.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're always given solutions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that, to me, that's nice.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a nice thing to hear someone, you know, no screaming, no stomping your feet, but
[SPEAKER_00]: Serious subjects, a lot of serious stuff going on, but I like it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're offering solutions and that's, you know, that's really important.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unfortunately, the show's come to an end.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was a pleasure having you, it really was.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I do have an email address that people can reach me at.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, yep, give us the email.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's meritformedford at gmail.com.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, two R's, two T's.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's F-O-R, not the number four, but that's all right.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I got a website that I'm working on, but it's not up yet.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I don't have an apparatus working my campaign.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is a grassroots, you know, thing, so.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know what it is, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Takes some time, takes a lot of work, and you're a very busy guy.
[SPEAKER_00]: But we'll get that up and running.
[SPEAKER_02]: So in the meantime, the email's good, or come for me at a city council meeting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thanks, John.
[SPEAKER_00]: Appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, thank you, too.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we'll have you back again.
[SPEAKER_00]: So when you're all set with your other accounts, we'll announce them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we're going to have you back, I can tell.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that time again.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I want to thank Nate.
[SPEAKER_00]: First, for joining us on Method Happenings.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I want to thank them for being a candidate for our Method City Council.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's nice to have some new faces, very qualified people running for the city council.
[SPEAKER_00]: I also want to take a minute, I have to thank everyone who has been watching the show.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're getting out in a lot more places.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, we're getting some more feedback.
[SPEAKER_00]: Um, and we're getting good and we're getting negative, uh, and I don't care.
[SPEAKER_00]: We'll take whatever, but it's nice to get the feedback.
[SPEAKER_00]: Um, if you'd like to share any comments or have any suggestions for a show, or if you want to appear on a future show, please, you can contact us at johnpatroller55 at gmail.com.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uh, you know, we'd be glad to have you, uh,
[SPEAKER_00]: join us on a show and Our show has come to an end.
[SPEAKER_00]: So once again, thank you all for watching and stay informed
Ta-da!