Okay, we may as well get started. The emergency public meeting of the City of Medford Liquor License Commission for 8-23-24 will come to order. We do have an agenda for this meeting. And I don't think, we don't need to do the minutes of the last meeting, correct, Daria? We can wait till the next monthly meeting? Yeah, next month, yep.
Okay, great. Okay, so why don't we get right into that then? Get right into the agenda. We'll go right down the list. Representative from the City of Medford will present for a one-day license application. I think that's you, Lisa, correct?
Yes, yes, thank you so much. Thank you so much for having this this emergency meeting. I'm very sorry that you know you had to do it off schedule and we do appreciate it. Thank you. So yes, so we are requesting a one day license for Medford Brewing Company to be the beer garden at the upcoming pumpkin float, which is this Saturday at Wrights Pond from 6 to 8 30 PM.
We've done this for the last, I think, four years now. I think three of it has had a beer garden, and we have it in a specific area at the pond. It's right in front of the bathhouse area.
I'm sorry? You used to call it the snack bar. The snack bar, yeah. Right in front of that. And it's cordoned off with like riot fencing. So, you know, people can't just kind of sweep in. You have to literally enter from just one specific area. And we have like no alcohol beyond this point signs.
And that's about it. So yeah, they're going to be serving beer and like mulled wine. Nice.
Yeah, you folks do this every year. I guess the last couple of three years that I've been on, we've had no problems. It's a pretty smooth thing. And as you say, it just kind of got bypassed in the shuffle. But we don't mind when there's a situation like this. We can ensure a special meeting. That's not a problem at all.
Alan, any questions? No, no, I'm familiar with the event. I grew up up the Heights. I'm very familiar with Wright's Palm. We used to sneak in there after hours, all that stuff. But no, it's a great event. Lisa was telling me about it, because I was asking Daria if the pumpkins float. So they were kind of giving me an overview.
But I'm perfectly fine with it. I'd like to make a motion to approve the one-day license for October 26, which is Sunday from 6-8.30 PM. I hope you do have 700 guests. That would be fantastic. Thank you. Like I said, that'd be my motion to accept the one-day license for Sunday.
Okay, and I will second that. All those in favor, aye. Aye. Very good. It is approved.
Awesome. Thank you. I just want to make one thing. It's for Saturday. Oh, I'm sorry. That's OK. Sunday? Yeah. Saturday, the 26th. OK, perfect. Yeah. Well, the rain date's the 27th, right? The rain date. Yeah. Yeah, I believe the rain date's the 27th. Correct. Yeah. I'm sorry. So the 27th. No, no, that's OK. That's OK. Thank you so much. Again, it's much appreciated that you did this for us. We really, really appreciate it. No problem. Anytime. OK.
Bye. Thank you so much. All right. Ciao. Bye, Regina. Okay. Let's see. We've got a representative from Arts Collaborative and that's Regina. Hi, Regina. Nice to meet you. I don't think you were here last time I was on.
Yes, I wasn't able to make the last meeting, but Alan took over. He was our past chair. He does a great job as usual, so we knew we were in good hands. Yeah, that's great. We have, I guess, three events, three one-day licenses that you're applying for, so if you could just give us a little information. I mean, if they're all basically the same. Yeah, they more or less are. So if you're not familiar, we're an arts center.
first physical community arts center on Mystic Ave. We just opened in January and we just acquired our alcohol insurance and so now I'm just starting to offer some beer and some wine at our closings and openings. So the one on the 7th, it's a Thursday evening, it's a closing reception and then we have one, it's an opening reception on the 16th and then for the 17th it's an open studio so the public will be able to come in and see the artists at work.
And so those are all really similar. It'll be a cash bar, not expecting anything too big, but just wanting to have some options open for Argus.
Okay, great. I just did notice on the first event, the one on the 7th, yeah. There was just no address on page with the very top. That was just a typo. It is on 162 Mystic Ave, so.
Yeah, that's what I kind of just figured. I looked at the other two and they were both those as well. Okay. I trust that you where you stated you do have the insurance liability. I trust that the city has the area has that on file where you were here. Yes, they have it for a year till next September. Okay, great. That's that's terrific. And let's see.
We have a diagram with the first one. Yeah. Should have a really similar one because it's going to be the same setup where the public is in the main space, that alcove is where the art is, and the bar will be to the right side. Okay. You have a bartender that you'll be doing the serving? Yeah. I have tip certification, so I'll be on site for all three of these events.
Oh, great. So it'll be myself, probably, or our other TIPSA certified staff giving them out. Fantastic. And you're aware that you are a non-profit. So at any time, besides being no charge to you folks, you do have the ability to serve all alcohol being a non-profit. If at any time you want to do that, it's available to you as well. That's great. That's awesome to know.
Mm-hmm. Thanks. Allen, do you have any questions for Regina? No, I do not. I looked through, you're right, just a little typo on the first one, but the others are fine. We have the insurance, we have the diagram, so we have a good idea of the layout. So I'm fine with that. I have no questions, pretty straightforward. Bobby, do you mind if I make a motion, I lump them all together?
Sure, that'll be fine. Okay, so I motioned. Can I just ask Regina one quick question? Oh, sure, sorry. You had a similar event last month, correct? We had a similar event on Saturday, actually. It was the first time we ever got a one-day permit. It was very smooth, and I was grateful. Thank you. That's what I wanted to ask, just to see how it went, how you guys did. It went really well. Good, that's good. That's a good thing. Okay, so you're familiar with it? Yeah.
No, I was going to say Regina to I know you were on the last meeting and we were telling the folks from the library that if you ever have an event and you have a licensed caterer, you really don't a 1 day. Yeah. So that.
So that was a good teachable moment for Joe. All right, so Bobby, do you mind if I make a motion for all three? No, go right ahead. All right, I can see the trash truck coming, so it will probably get loud. All right, so I make a motion to approve the one-day license for three separate events. The event to be held on 11-7, 11-16, 11-17.
And I hope everything goes well. So that's my motion. I'll second that motion. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Hearing and seeing none, your application has been approved.
Thank you so much. All right, best of luck. I hear that Javier had given you kind of a quick- We did, we had a really helpful meeting. Yeah, just so I can understand, so I don't cause any more emergency meetings. I'll be prepared now every month. I understand when I need one and when I don't, like the catering and we're for private and we're not selling anything, just basics like that. She was really helpful.
Yeah, no, that's great. Anytime you can reach out to Daria, she'll answer your questions. Just give her a little bit of leeway, you know, before the meeting. Wealth of information. Yeah, I just said, you know, Regina, I hated to say no the last time, but I just, you know, we just don't want to violate the state open meeting laws and have someone point the finger at us. And so, but we're able to accommodate you. Yeah. Yeah. I appreciate it so much. Thank you. Cool. Great. All right. Thank you.
And okay, we had a couple of things, Alan, you got a few minutes to spend, Dari. Dari, do you have any news for us? Did we reach out to KP for that one day? Yes, I reached out, but haven't heard yet. But I do have another question about
Ardor dining for Alta Cuba. Alvaro wants to continue, not to serve on the road, I guess, but on the sidewalk. He has seats. So the city is fine with it, but
If the city is fine with it, and as long as you agree with me on this, Alan, as far as we go, we get to grant that every year. We don't have to go through the state anymore. The city sends out their department heads and all of their inspections pass with the building department, the zoning board, everybody.
We're okay with them serving alcohol out there. I don't think we need to get a alteration of premise because it's not really a permanent structure. Correct, Alan? Correct. I don't think there are any limitations either.
I'm sorry, what was that? I don't think there's any date limitations for the seasonal dining. I was looking at it too, and I didn't see any date limitations. Yeah. Because I thought the same thing. I was like, I feel like there's a date limitation, but I looked through it, and I didn't see any. And I think Mother Nature will take care of that. At some point, it'll just be too cold. Exactly.
And you're right to your 1st thought. As long as the city, it meets all the codes and there are no violations. I. Yeah, we're, we're fine with that.
Yeah, there's not a problem there. And it's not, you know, I'm sure like, like you said, the weather will, will take care of it. I mean, sidewalk heaters or something, maybe, I don't know, for a little while, but then yeah. Yeah, I think he just wanted mainly for the show, Chevalier shows, and then it's been beautiful this weekend. Yeah, he just wanted, you know, for the crowd. So yeah.
Yeah. No, not a problem with that at all. Yeah. And what Daria and I was speaking about yesterday, I just stopped in there. When I heard about the three licensees that were looking for a extension for New Year's time extension to go until like, I believe, one o'clock.
It bothered me a little bit, especially about Bocelli's because they don't have an entertainment license. I knew there was some issues there for the reason why they didn't apply for a new entertainment license because what I found out yesterday, the reason being I went and spoke with the building commissioner and he said that
If we issue an entertainment license, it'll change their category of their business from a restaurant to a nightclub. So if they leave things the way they are, they can still have functions down in the basement as a restaurant, as long as there's no entertainment, bands, TVs, whatever. I see.
And I said, OK, well, that's good. I said, so if they want to come before us and have food available,
He says, we don't have a problem till one o'clock. And he said, yeah, no, that is not a problem as long as there's no music or entertainment. No entertainment. Yeah. So I says, OK, that's fine. So then I went and checked with the city clerk because that was bugging me, because I don't know how long their license goes until that. I don't know if you've got it on the record, but their actual license to serve, they one of the
1 o'clock ones, or no? Let me look. Because if not, then the city... No, I don't think so, because if she asked for 1 a.m., I don't think they're till 1 a.m. Let me just check real quick. Let me just check on what I did last year for renewals. Because we've got a 1 a.m. on Oasis and on Great American Beer Hall, the other two that are looking, correct? Yeah, so I'm wondering why...
why Oasis would even look if they're a tell of 1 a.m. anyways. They're probably just looking for us to extend the liquor license out to 1 a.m. We can only extend it out as far as the common Vic says. So if the Oasis got extension of hours, they may not already be extended to one. That's the reason why they would ask. OK.
Now, that's why I look for 2 o'clock, but the city won't do 2 o'clock. Their limit is 1. And the thing is, Alan is the.
The clerk was very, he had his heels dug in pretty good. And he, I actually, he says, where did you get that information? I says, I get it from the building commissioner, Scott. I says, you can call him. Because he says, I had a conversation with him the other day and that's not what he said. I said, well, you can call him while I'm standing here in your office. And he did, and they kind of,
went back and forth a little bit. And what the city clerk requires, even for a one-day extension of hours, they want the licensee to go before the city council to extend the hours for that one day. And it's like an 8-, 10-, 12-page thing that they have to fill out.
And before they go to city council, it's got to be advertised in a paper for two weeks. He says it takes about six weeks to do it before they do the advertising, they get on the agenda and everything else. He says they're not going to have time before New Year's. If they do, it's going to be pretty close. Yeah.
You know, I'm counting eight weeks, unless I'm counting wrong, but I think we can give them the option if they want to attempt it. But what I would strongly suggest to them, or to anybody else who's gonna go before the council to get an extension for one day, get an extension for the whole year. Just change your license time to 1 a.m. Seven days a week, 1 a.m., you don't have to worry about it.
And according to the city's rules, all alcohol licensees can operate from 11 a.m. to 1 a.m. Monday through Saturday, and from noon to 1 a.m. on Sunday.
we want to invoke the 33B, which allows them to come in a couple hours earlier on a Sunday, like for that Patriots game that was just on a special event. Somebody does brunches, we can grant it for the whole year. But they'll probably have to do the same thing, go before the city council and through the city clerks. There's a fee, they have to pay a fee. So you're gonna pay a fee? Just get them changed for the whole year. Now we don't run into this problem anymore. I don't think anybody will,
I don't think anybody will say anything about it or have any issue with it, but. You know, Bobby, when you explain it, it sounds very, very straightforward and simple. Is there a way to get back to both Challis and Oasis just to let them know that that's the policy or that's the procedure?
Well, if Oasis has a 1 a.m. license, if they do, then it's a moot point. If Bocelli does not, they gotta have, I mean, we can let them know what the... Bocelli don't, yeah. They don't let them know what we found, but we should strongly encourage them to contact the city clerk.
Yeah. And we will let them know what the rules are. OK, if you're OK by the city clerk and the council, the rules are you got to have food out until 1 a.m. when liquor is being served. And also you cannot have any entertainment. You can have party hats, you can have the blowers, you can have the happy new year, whatever you want. But there's no music, no entertainment. Right. OK. So it's kind of
Because in not that we're being prejudiced against them or anything, it's because you don't have an entertainment license. Correct. Correct. That's a license. Correct. Problem. Right. And they don't have the entertainment license because for whatever reason, it doesn't meet the.
The newer codes, the standard codes, right? Yes. It violates the ordinance. It turns the business description from a restaurant to a nightclub. I see. It's entertainment. Technically, all these places that we give entertainment licenses to,
considered nightclub category, I guess. That was right from Scott from the building department. And one of the other inspectors who was involved with this when Bocelli's was taken over by the new owners, he was standing there as well. He says, we already really looked into this hard. And I says, well, I kind of figured that was the case where they never applied for an entertainment license. They could get one.
if the building owner sprinkles the whole building right and brings it up to code for up to code that type of business but he's not going to do that i'm sure okay um so it makes sense yeah that's kind of when you know what all i could see was
another station nightclub via Godfrey or another coconut grove. I mean, you know, the odds are minimal, but something happens. It's just like, you know, I mean, it was, it's difficult to get out of that basement if you don't know where the other exits are. I mean, everybody knows the main one that comes in from upstairs dining room.
But there's another one by the bathroom that goes up the pike. And then there's another one I heard that goes up through the kitchen. I just, I mean, unless the building department and the fire department say that, yeah, it's okay for a night, then I...
You know, I wouldn't be okay with it unless they said it was all right. And even if they said it was all right, it's still got to go by the city clerk and the city council for the hours to get raised to 1 am. Yeah.
So that's logical. Yeah, very logical. I think, Daria, you know, if we get the message out to Bocelli's so they can start the ball rolling, because if it does take six to eight weeks, they're running out of time. Yeah. Well, that's what I was going to suggest to Daria if you want to reach out to her and just explain that. If she has any questions, she can give me a call.
Or whatever, and I explain it a little more detail, but we definitely want her to. To go before the city clerk. Just to make sure that she's doing what they want and, um.
and do it ASAP, but I would also wait until you hear back from KP Law with the question that is this a MedFed ordinance? I mean, you know, last time, you know, we went through with the club licenses, it's, you know, the building department, this was before Scott got there, but they said that,
they couldn't have their licenses till 1 a.m. and it was completely wrong when it was looked into. So, you know, I'm not saying they're wrong, but it may be a good idea just for KP to take a look, and especially where it was advised by Ralph at the ABCC to check with your legal counsel, the city's legal counsel, before you give them the okay.
That's what we're doing. And we kind of know this is the rules, but let's make sure that this is really the rules. I don't know. Yeah, I know. Makes sense. Makes sense, Bobby. Makes sense. So I think that's about all we had. There was nothing else pending, right? One question, though, just to clarify.
Should I clarify that they cannot have entertainment at the Bocelli's? Bocelli's cannot have entertainment. Okay, so I think that needs, maybe needs to be said to them too because they might be doing it. I don't, I mean, I don't know. I'm just assuming. If they're doing entertainment.
We don't know about it unless there's a complaint filed. And then law enforcement, our law enforcement, we notify Lieutenant Lockowitz, have him investigated. And then if there's an issue that there is, in fact, entertainment down there, we'd have to put a stop. Hold on. I lost you for a second. Hold on. Oh, OK. Hold on.
That's okay. Take your time. I don't know why I can't find my mouse right now. Oh my God. Put out a little cheese. We'll find them real quick.
Why? I was, I was playing around with my computer and it went over to my iPad right next to the computer. I don't know why. Oh, that's funny. We just blew a few. So that's why I lost you guys for a second. Oh my God. You're breaking up and freezing a little bit too. Yeah. So everything is turned off at the moment. Okay.
Yeah, well, a few so. Give us a 2nd, make it time.
I got until 317 when Apple's supposed to call me, I got a new phone. And I was trying to, Cheryl's phone went through perfect. My phone was, for some reason, I couldn't remember a password to the app store where you get all your apps from. It's different than the Apple ID.
Yeah. And you get a 16, a 16. Yeah, exactly. We haven't had new phones in six, seven years. So this new one with the Apple and Jensen, blah, blah, blah. But it's just like, they didn't believe me. I said, well, we're in an Apple store and, you know, it's, this is from an Apple phone and blah, this is the accountant. Nope. We're going to shut you down for several days. They shut us down seven,
I think at four o'clock on Saturday.
Saturday or Sunday, Sunday. And I still haven't been able to log into that account and half of my apps don't work because I purchased them out of the app store and I can't get access to them. So they sent me an email saying, somebody will call you at 317 on Wednesday the 20th. It's like, this is high security stuff, man. But anyways, so I got until 317.
Daria, are you back? Can you hear us? No, probably not. I wonder if she wants to stop it and start it again. I wonder. That might make sense. I don't know. Can you do that? Why don't you hang up?
I'm not a big Zoomer. I don't know too much about how to work this foolish thing. Yeah. Yeah, I think something's freezing up on her end because see your picture? Yeah, yeah. I always say technology is wonderful when it works. Yeah, exactly. Exactly.
I think you had to shut off the video one time too, right? So we could get your voice. Something was going on. Yeah. Any trips planned? Can you hear me now? Oh, I can hear you, yeah. Can you hear us? Yes, I can. Okay, great. Okay, that's the thing. Turn off the picture, that's all.
So I think we left it where we were just, before we do anything, let's get an opinion from KP Law. I think that's kind of where we were. Yeah. Yep. That's the last thing I heard. Yeah. And then after we get the answer from KP Law, hopefully it'll be within a day or two, you can reach out to Bocelli's and let them know exactly what we're doing.
Because in a sense, I'm reaching out to them, tell them to do all this stuff. If KP Law says something different. Yeah, they don't have to do it. Exactly. Right. Right. Okay. Okay, cool. Great. Mr. Chairman, should I make a motion to adjourn? Sure. Are you all set, Daria?
Yeah, yeah, I think I didn't know if you had any other questions with that. No, I think that was it. Okay, so I make a motion to adjourn today's meeting. It's 1.30. Okay, all those in favor. Aye. Hearing and saying none, the ayes have it. Very good. Thank you. Good to see you, Bobby.