I'm Lisa Hughes from WBZ TV and it is an honor to be here today. I had the pleasure of visiting the garden with Bill and Patty Campbell on Thursday and the greatest joy was to see their reaction.
This park, the way it was designed, the attention to detail, the way so many people chipped in to raise the money to make it a reality, and the excitement. It speaks to the power of what we can do when we work together. When we form a circle around one another in the way that we did in 2013, in some of the darkest days in our community's history, and dedicate ourselves to making something good,
Crystal's legacy, and that of Sean, and Lindsay, and Mark, inspires us to be kind, to lift up one another. I now call upon the Medford Police Honor Guard, the MIT Honor Guard, and the Middlesex County Sheriff's Honor Guard to present the colors.
And now while we are all standing, please welcome the members of the Medford Ritalin to join us in the Pledge of Allegiance. To the flag. We pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America.
Ladies and gentlemen, please remain standing while Stacey Clayton sings our National Anthem.
by the dawn's early light, what so proudly we hailed at the twilight's last gleaming, whose broad stripes and bright stars
through the perilous fight, o'er the ramparts we watched were so gallantly streaming?
And the rocket's red glare, the bombs bursting in air, Gave proof through the night that our flag was still there.
O say does that star-spangled banner yet wave O'er the land of the free
and the home of the brave?
That glorious noise was brought to you by the Bedford Strong Motorcycle Group. A group that has been raising money for the establishment of Crystal Campus for the last four years. And we draw on this memory so that we may have a moment of silence in the memory of Crystal and Shawn.
As we gather, let us pause and recognize that there are things much greater than ourselves, mysteries beyond us, questions impossible to answer. The hardest questions to answer begin with the word why. Our thirst for the why of things is not quenched on this earth, but through the
These hints include things like sunflowers that turn their face always to the sun, water softly flowing yet hard enough to carve canyons, and most especially the inner courageous spirit of those among us who exemplify strength, dignity, leadership, love.
people like Crystal Campbell, whose love reaches beyond her short time on earth and gathers us today. As today we gaze upon this beautiful new garden, let us pray for Crystal and for Martin, Lingzi and Sean. We pray for all those injured.
for all that responded, somehow running towards the scene rather than away from it, and for all of our families who remember. Let us look upon God's creation and pray for deep peace. Deep peace of running waves to you. Deep peace of the flowing air to you.
Deep peace of the quiet earth to you. Deep peace of the shining stars to you. Deep peace of the infinite peace to you.
And one of them is our Transportation Secretary, Stephanie Pollack. And I would like to invite Madam Secretary to the podium to talk a little bit about her dedication and that of her team. When you're in the transportation business,
You come to many intersections or bridges or stretches of road that have been dedicated in the memory of someone who was very important to many people, important enough for something to be gained for them.
And even before I was secretary, I was one of those people who would always read the little plaques on the bridges or at the intersections. Because having a physical manifestation of those we have lost is really important to us. It's important to know.
that they won't be forgotten. That's one of the things I think all of us who have lost a loved one share, is this deep-seated need to know that that very special person, that unbelievable soul, will live on. And the physical manifestation of the bridge or the intersection or the relieved road is important to us all.
It is a rare thing, at least in my world, for that manifestation to be in the form of a garden, and in fact a peace garden. And I will tell you that the men and women of NASDAQ are deeply honored to have been part of the construction of this peace garden. It is a very different project from the kinds of projects that we undertake, but it is no less important.
than the other kinds of projects we do. So I want to thank everyone, particularly Paul Stedman and the folks at Highway District 4, the folks from Daigle, the contractor who brought all of the pieces together in less than a year to bring the vision of this Peace Garden that was shared by so many people to a reality.
And it will mean not just for those who were lucky enough to know Crystal and Martin and Lindsay and Sean that they won't be forgotten, but it means those of us who never were lucky enough to know them will also have a place and a way to learn about them, to remember them, to honor not only the manner of their deaths, but the manner of their lives.
And in my faith, in the Jewish faith, this is the month before the Jewish New Year of Rosh Hashanah. And during that month, it is traditional to go visit the cemetery and to put a pebble or a stone on the grave of your loved ones. And the reason for that
pebble is that way of saying, I was here and I haven't forgotten you. So I say to the souls of Crystal, Agnes, Ian Martin, and Sean, we are here, we have not forgotten you. We are honored to have all played some small part in the process of making this piece start to become a reality. And it will ensure, I hope,
that your souls rest in peace, that your loved ones find peace, and that all of us share in the peace that this garden represents. Thank you very much.
I asked Patti Campbell the other day if it was really important that the word peace be in the name of the garden. She said, yes, because it's the reason people move to this country, because they want their families to be safe, and because that's what we believe in. And the next speaker we are about to hear from moved to this country while bathing in 2011 with his daughters and his wife.
Fuat Mbele was at the Marathon, as so many of us were in 2013, and today he would like to share his poetic interlude with us. Please, Fuat. Hello, everyone. I am here, here at Duttonwood, American,
and my English not right. Please, sorry for my mistake. We have gathered here today in the hope of peace for the Christians and all the other promised loves most.
Here her brother's city has come, praying for one of its own, her daughter in our hearts. At the forefront is your family, holding flowers in their hands, missing you, Christi, so much today and every day.
The city of Mansford built a park in honor of you and gave it your beautiful name, Crystal Campbell, surrounded by flowers and light. It is truly a beautiful place. It also unfortunately reminds us of the Boston Marathon bombing, the day when enormous, epic flowers bloomed, blood trickled down.
My heart was beating fast that day, worried for my one daughter. She was watching the Boston Marathon nearby. I worried she may have the same misfortune. Watching the marathon from the sidelines, you Christians were one of the unlucky ones. And we will always remember you in every flower's bloom.
We come to this park every day, giving yourself time to heal, getting over a broken heart. No matter who you are or who you represent, we thank everyone while praying for Christians and others. And yet, the blood still trickles down all around the world for no reason, and all high
I hear his crystal voice to ask love and peace. Please, God bless. Boston Strong. Our next speaker is one of those people who never truly rests. In fact, in addition to running the Jimmy Fund Walk today, he ran the entire Boston Marathon this morning.
He is a Medford native. He is the BAA Boston Marathon race director. And my dear friend, please welcome Dave McGowan. First of all, I thought it was great that the Method Little League kids were here doing the Pledge of Allegiance. I played for the Method Little League, too. And I haven't grown an inch since then.
why I run. On behalf of the Boston Athletic Association, the Boston Marathon, and all the runners around the world, I want to thank both Mayor Burke and Mayor Glenn for inviting me to this very special occasion. I can't imagine the pain one feels from the loss of their child.
I have five children myself and I love them more than anything in the world the way Crystal's parents loved Crystal. So it's fitting that this Peace Garden represent the Boston Marathon course. As Lisa said, this morning I ran the entire marathon course in memory of Crystal.
I had to, I had to reflect. I never met Crystal personally, but I felt she was with me every step of the way this morning, as were Martin and Lindsay and Sean. This garden is a fitting tribute to Crystal, Sunflower, Martin, Baseball Glove, Lindsay,
books, and Sean Badge. April 15, 2013 impacted so many of us. In the past three years, I've traveled the world, and everyone remembers that day. The entire world was impacted. The running community was impacted. But I also experienced resolve and perseverance
an amazing will to stay strong. This very area of the city of Medford is very special to me personally. I was born and grew up right down the road from here.
38 years and one month ago, I finished running across the United States from Method, Oregon to Method, Massachusetts for the Jimmy Fund right over there. I've never seen a city rally behind one cause more than the city of Method did that
until now. And although you might be able to take me out of Medford, you can never take Medford out of me. How wonderful it is that you, my hometown, have done this for the Campbell family, for Martin, Lindsay, Sean, and all the survivors, and for all of us.
Patrick Down, a Boston Marathon survivor, said it best. He said, he refuses to see himself as a victim of violence, but rather as an ambassador for peace. Peace has never been about the absence of evil, he said, rather the existence of the good in all of us. This is what this Peace Garden truly represents. And Martin wrote, no more hurting, peace,
He was right. No more hurting. Three quick stories of recovery. That day, my eight-year-old son, Mike Martin, was sitting at the finish line in the bleachers. He saw everything. Two days after the marathon, I went home, and I saw my son. And he came up to me, and he hugged me. And he said, Dad, I never, ever, ever want you to direct that race again.
He associated danger with my job. I put on a road race. He persevered. He worked hard. He processed. Two months later, he came up to me and he said, Dad, remember I told you I never want you to direct that race again? I said, yes, Luke, I remember. He said, you know why? I said, why? He says, because I want to direct it. Jeff Baumann.
I asked Jeff a few months ago if he'd come and run in a one-mile celebrity race I was putting on. To my surprise, he said he would do it. Jeff trained like you wouldn't believe. He was determined to do this mile. He'd never run a race in his life. He trained. He would email me and say, I'm training hard, Dave, for this race. He showed up at the race. One mile, two laps.
All of a sudden, I looked to my right as I was introducing all the celebrities, and there was Carlos Arredondo. Carlos helped save Jeff, as you saw in that iconic picture. I asked Carlos, do you want to do the celebrity mile too? He said, sure. But Carlos was in a wheelchair. He had just injured his leg and was in a cast. He had someone pushing him. Long story short,
who did that first half mile, and then Jeff was the very last person. All the celebrities had finished, and Jeff still had a lap to go. Every celebrity jumped into the race behind Jeff and walked with Jeff the last half mile. All of a sudden, we're coming towards the finish. This guy's pushing Carlos. Jeff turns to me. He said, Dave, do you mind? I would like to push Carlos. He gave me his cane.
Jeff pushed Carlos across the finish line. Three years later, Republic. Lastly, Patrick Downs. I was at the Disney Marathon in January. I was standing at the start. I got a tap on my shoulder. I looked behind me. I said, oh, hi, Patrick. What are you doing here? He said, well, I'm running in the half marathon.
I said, you're running in the half marathon? He said, yeah. I said, but you just.
I couldn't believe it. He's running in the half marathon. I ran the marathon, the half marathon, I finished, and I went into a tent, waited for Jeff. I get another tap on my shoulder. I look, I said, oh, hi, Jeff. It was Patrick's wife, Jess. And I said, so why are you here? She said, well, I just ran the half marathon. I said, you ran the half marathon? She said, yeah, on a hand cycle. She lost both legs.
We waited for Patrick. Patrick came in, I shook his hand, and Patrick turned to me and he said, Dave, I want you to tell all those people in Boston how much we appreciate all their support and how much they are an inspiration to all of us. I said, Patrick, I think you have it backwards.
Imagine. So those who have been impacted have actually inspired us more than we have inspired them. So finally, to Crystal's parents and to your family, you will always be in our thoughts and prayers. We will always remember Crystal as this Peace Garden will keep her memory and her beautiful smile alive forever.
And I don't have a lot to give, but what I do have that I want to give to the Crystal family is my Boston Marathon medal from 2013. It symbolizes friendship, resolve, and most importantly, peace. Thank you.
There's a place that I know, where the sick and the wounds grow. And amphitheatres have their fun. Where the cares of the day seem to slowly fade away.
And the glow of the evening sun Leaves when the day is done If I get there late, let my mind meditate On everything to be done
If I search deep inside, let my conscience be my guide, then the answers are sure to come. Don't have to worry now.
When you find peace of mind, leave your worries behind, and don't say that it can't be done. With a new point of view, life's true meaning comes to you, and the freedom you seek is won.
Peace is for everyone. Peace is for everyone. Peace is for everyone.
You know, a little over a year ago, when former Mayor Michael Flynn asked if I would join him in a group of people at a fundraiser that I'm sure many of you attended, the goal was to raise $15,000 for this park. And by the time the night was over, we had more than tripled.
The former mayor had a vision for this park that is so incredibly well realized that it is as if someone took the rendering and put a photo of what's here today right in front of us. It was an amazing vision, and on behalf of everybody here, I don't think we can thank you enough, but we do want to hear from you. Former Mayor Mike McGlynn.
Welcome, everyone, and thank you. I'm excited, as I see the faces in the crowd, of those who worked, volunteered, and donated to fulfill the vision for this space, which was a combination of ideas, but with a single goal of celebrating the lives of Martin Richards, Sean Foyer, Lise Lu, and Crystal Campbell.
to celebrate the survivors who have overcome devastating challenges, to lead the healing process with grace and strength and compassion, and to celebrate our first responders, public safety officials, citizen volunteers, the National Guard, fellow runners, BAA staff and hospital personnel,
for their immediate and selfless heroic actions, and who are responsible for saving many additional lives. I want to thank Mayor Stephanie Muccini-Burke for her leadership in shepherding this project through to fruition, and Secretary Stephanie Pollack for making this day a reality.
Thank you to those who helped kick off the fundraising drive. President Anthony Monaco from Tufts University, Bill Cummings from the Cummings Foundation, Bob DiSalvio of Winn-Boston, the state and federal government, along with hundreds who generously gave nearly $1.5 million to build and maintain the Crystal Campbell Peace Guard.
People have been supportive and determined not to let Crystal's passion and energy for life that would be forgotten. The celebration of her life continues. On April 15, 2013, was a devastating and tragic day, but also a time when people came together to support one another with a renewed commitment for a better quality of life for all.
Their spirit is what this Peace Garden represents. People came together to redesign and reconstruct this land as not only a part of the healing process, but also as a memorial to the four people who reached out in their own way to spread peace upon the earth.
Sean Collier was a police officer, providing a safe environment for faculty and staff. Martin Richard, who at a young age, ministered to us all, preaching a message of stop hurting people. Lingzi Lu, through education and music, sought a better quality of life for many.
and Crystal Campbell, a leader who nurtured her friends and guided and supported her co-workers. We have all heard the loving stories of their actions. There was a hymn entitled, Go Make a Difference. One line states, we are the salt of the earth. All that the people see is the love of God in you and me.
They went forth and made a difference. And every time their story is told, here or elsewhere, they will continue to make a difference.
When you walk down Clippership Drive, and read the marathon mile markers, and continue to the fountain, and see the flack of Sean's police badge, baseball gloves, glitzy loose books, or crystal sunflowers, you cannot help but be inspired and comforted by their message. For generations to come, this message will be spread over and over again.
Thank you to Pam Shadley and Skylar Chick of Shadley Associates for all of their hard work on the design. Thank you to President Maureen for her thanks to the electric field for the construction and reconstruction of this site. When the finished product looks exactly like the design picture, you know it's a job well done.
And I must thank the crew who work daily with me on this magnificent site. Laura DiLorenzo, Mark Rumley, Clodagh Stoker-Long, Lisa Evangelista, Medford's own Frankie DePaola, Tom Tidland, Paul Stedman, and Paul Malloy. Two and a half years ago, our nation was once again challenged by the forces of evil in our world.
We have all shared a profound sense of grief for those we lost and for those who loved them. But when we think of the lives of Lindsey, Crystal, Martin, and Sean,
we think of what they accomplished. Our response to the forces of evil is to celebrate their lives in a unified voice and let it be known that the American spirit is unbroken. We energetically embrace our future, our freedom, and our way of life.
We celebrate Crystal's life. She was a Medford Mustang class of 2001, an alumnus of UMass Boston. Crystal was a member of the Medford High School band and the girls' softball team. We celebrate her ongoing, fun-loving, deeply passionate, and energetic life. Crystal lived life to the fullest.
She touched the hearts and souls of not only family and friends, but hearts and souls throughout the world. She loved people. I'm sure she is watching us now displaying that million-dollar smile and thinking about all the new friendships that have resulted from everyone working together on the Peace Guard.
We can only imagine how many more will develop over the years as people come to this site to relax, to view, and to listen to the fountains. When this project began, Bill Campbell, Bristol's dad, said he could not wait until it was finished so he could bring his grandson, Billy III, and enjoy his company in the beauty of this park.
The word is out. You're going to have a lot of company. Let there be peace on Earth. And let it begin with me. Let there be peace on Earth, the peace that was meant to be. May God bless us and provide us the strength to persevere, to heal, and to love. Thank you very much.
This time, we're now playing Walk the Rainwater, the first of a new version of A Foster Nurse.
We're going to use a little bit like applause to kind of get that going.
It's one thing to have an amazing vision, and then to take over that vision, and as we would say on a Sunday, take it over the bowl and execute on what was there before you with the passion and dedication that Mayor Burke has. This was truly a labor of love for so many people, and even on Thursday, when one of the workers was here and so kindly turned on the fountains for us so we could put some video on television, it was clear that there was tremendous pride in what's here now.
And there's an eagerness to share it with all of you and people who have come here for generations. Ladies and gentlemen, please welcome the woman who helped get this to the finish line, the clear hearted soul into a real stepping stone.
Good afternoon dignitaries, clergy, friends, survivors, first responders, and especially the families of Crystal, Martin, Lindsey, and John. Your strength and courage since September, April 15, 2013 has given us the ability to come together to heal from that traumatic time in the Commonwealth's history.
As a community, we share in your sorrow. As a community, we share in your healing. And as a community, we are hopeful. We are hopeful that this special place in our city, a living memorial that countless individuals, entities contributed to, to bring to fruition, is a testament to the longing we all have for a peaceful, reflective space.
I thank former Mayor Michael McGlynn for his vision and fortitude to plan this garden, which sits just a few blocks from the Campbell's residence.
I thank Secretary Pollack, Highway Administrator Tom Tinlin, and their team for their expertise and funding to assist in this project. And I thank the Dagles, Pam Shadley, and all city departments for their work and oversight. We, the city and state, are a shepherd for this beautiful Peace Garden on behalf of all of those who gave us so much.
As versed by the Dalai Lama, when we meet real tragedy in life, we can react in two ways, either by losing hope and following self-destructive habits, or by using the challenge to find our inner strength. In the days, weeks, and years following the horrific events, these families, first responders, and survivors have demonstrated pure strength by their actions and words seen and heard around the world.
Who can forget the words by Rob Rogers during his eulogy of his brother Sean Collier? Live long like he would. Big hearts, big smiles, big service, all love. Who can forget Mr. Bill Richard's remarks during a recent dedication of a statue to his son Marvin at his and his wife Denise's alma mater, Bridgewater State University?
Reminder to all, unlike the past, the story of the future is not yet written. Martin's message of peace will live on. Our hope is for Martin's legacy to live on through today's children and to show that no matter the age, you can always choose kindness.
Who can forget Zheng Lu's expression at a memorial mass for his daughter, Lingzi? An ancient Chinese saying says, every child is actually a little Buddha that helps their parents mature and grow up. Even though we brought up Lingzi, and yet today, while reflecting on her short, 24-year life, we as parents admire and appreciate her kindness, courage, and her yearning for a beautiful life.
and who can forget Mr. Campbell's humble comments following the groundbreaking of this Garden of Peace. But the weight is lifted. It's like a rejoicing now. No more sorrow. You couldn't ask for any better. Crystal would have loved it. We're so lucky to have a community of people hearing so much. It's overwhelming, just beautiful.
To the Colliers, Lews, Richards, and Campbells, we are so proud to honor the memories of Sean, Lindsey, Martin, and Crystal, and remember the positive impact that they had on all of us. To the survivors, the courage, strength, and bond you built is an inspiration to all of us. To the first responders and ordinary people that ran to instead of from, you are our heroes.
We all must remember that this Peace Garden not only signifies their memory, but also our commitment to observing peace every day. With this unveiling in the shadow of the International Day of Peace this past Wednesday, we must always remember Martin's message conveyed through a simple drawing of red full hearts and the words, no more hurting people. Peace. God bless you all.
In just a moment, Mayor Burke will join the families for the dedications of the plaques, but first, I would like to welcome to the podium U.S. Senator Ed Markey. Thank you. To the Campbell family, to the Paulga family, to the Richard family,
We honor you today. We honor the memory of the sacrifice which your family has made. That is why we are here. And the great poet Milan Kundera said that the challenge in life
What we say here today is that we remember. What we say here today is that we will never forget what happened on that day, three and a half years ago. Mayor McGlynn, you had a dream, you had a concept. You understand patriotism. We just celebrated
The life of your great father, Jack O'Lynn, two weeks ago, that great patriot who served us in World War II, and that ghost brigade. And we know how much this means to you, how dedicated you have been throughout your entire life, making sure that those who sacrificed here in Bedford are remembered.
And Mayor Burke, you as well, you have taken this concept and brought it to a perfect execution. Something that will stand here forever to help everyone remember what happened here. And the wonderful thing about today is that we are going to remember the indomitable spirit of Crystal.
But we're also going to remember Martin Richard. And there's a baseball glove, a little boy that we're going to see. I took a little sneak preview of him right there next to his name. At this point, he talked about peace. And next to Sean Collier, a badge. He was a peace officer. That's what he did.
This is a Peace Garden. Lindsay Liu, an international student who came here to this land of the free and the home of the brave, we celebrate that here today as well.
By the way, I just want to mention that we have with us here the great mayor of the city of Boston. We have Marty Malt, who is here today. What about a clap for the folks? It would be so great for them to be here. Our great congresswoman, Kathleen Clark, who is here today.
And Stephanie Pollack, the Secretary of Transportation, who did such a fantastic job in making sure that such a thing of beauty would be here forever. So Crystal grew up here in Medford. And Patriot's Day is a very special day in Medford. Paul Revere looked up in the Old Law Church to see if it was
One at my land, two at my sea. And then he began his ride, captured by Longfellow. Every Patriot's Day, as Paul Revere would ride through Lenton Square, and Crystal would see Paul Revere, as we all did growing up. As he stopped just 200 yards from here, where we had our Patriot's Day ceremony.
has been celebrating the patriots of Metric, the Minutemen who came out to fight for liberty back in 1775. That is what the marathon celebrates. It celebrates Patriot's Day, where one million people from Massachusetts come together to celebrate that day, where the people of these villages, like Metric, stood up for freedom.
So that is commemorated every single year here in Bedford. On these streets that Crystal walked every day of her life, we celebrated that freedom. That's why she was there at the marathon.
She went to the finish of the marathon every year. She was there with her bright blue eyes, with a huge smile on her beautiful, freckled face. She was there with her friends. She had a gift for friendship. She had a legion of friends. That legion of friends is here today to remember her.
They are here because she was a very loyal, very happy, very beloved friend of all who knew her. Her spirit is the spirit of Medford, and it is the spirit of America. That is what will be remembered. She walked these streets. This will always be here as a way to help all of us to remember her.
She shared her humanity. She shared her spirit. And this is the answer to those who hate America. This is the answer to those who want to destroy us. Even those two weeks ago in New York, in New Jersey, who mentioned Patriots Day.
Martin Luther King said the answer to hate is not more hate, the answer to hate is love. The answer to hate is peace. So even today she boosts our spirits.
Crystal, in the same way she set the finish line of the marathon to boost the spirit of her friend who was running in the marathon, is boosting our spirits once again here today.
So we come here to celebrate her spirit at this special place for each one of us, where we can come whenever we want to celebrate her life, to celebrate all of their lives, and to celebrate the fact that we live in the greatest country in the world, a country whose values of freedom and liberty and diversity
a protection of religion, a protection of every single ethnic group in our country, is what it is that makes us the greatest country in the history of the world. And each of us can come here.
and celebrate and reflect upon that greatness every single time we leave to refresh our souls. We thank each of the families. We thank the city of Medford for bringing together this tremendous group of people. May God bless the families. May God bless the United States of America. Thank you, Senator.
Mayor Burke will now be joining members of each family for the dedication of the plaques, beginning with Venerable Gish Tenley representing the Lu family and unveiling the plaque dedicated to Lu Xilin.
We are honored to be here. And to Bill and Patricia and the entire Campbell family, I want to thank you. This garden is inspiring. It's transformative. As Mayor McGlynn mentioned, and Mayor Burke mentioned, what Bill had said, it is a beautiful, beautiful place to come. And it's being unveiled on a beautiful, beautiful day. And crystal, you can feel crystal with every breeze that comes through here, keeping smiles and all of that.
This groundbreaking happened just under a year ago. Now it's a vibrant, fitting memorial to four beautiful lives that we lost three and a half years ago.
You can certainly, as you're sitting here, sense the energy and compassion that went into building this memorial. It's a result of enormous acts of kindness, donations, and grants, bringing the community together for this cause. It's something that this city should be very proud of. I sure know Crystal is very proud of this garden.
Nothing will ever heal the wounds of the loss felt by Crystal's family and friends. The same goes for the other families. But I hope this memorial brings some comfort. That it'll always be a place of reflection, healing, and peace. For Crystal's family, I hope it reminds them of Crystal's upbeat personality, her warm heart, and certainly her love.
Crystal, as you heard, was a beloved member of the Medford community. But she was also a beloved member of the city of Boston community. She attended UMass Boston. She worked in our restaurants. And she made our city better and brighter. After her passing, the world learned about her spirit. And now everyone, as everyone comes to this memorial, we're going to be reminded about the life and legacy about Crystal, Martin, Lindsay, and Sean.
I know this garden is going to shine even through the winter. Every Boston Marathon, as was mentioned earlier, is going to bloom. It's going to be a reminder and a sign of the historic of our country, that it was founded here. And it joins other wonderful memorials set up by the families that honor the victims. The Children's Wharf Project in South Boston, the Martin Richard Statue and Institute in Bridgewater State, and the Granite Sculpture honoring Sean at MIT.
People are going to continue to rally around the marathon finish line to celebrate the city and our state's resilience and pay tribute to these four incredible individuals. And now they can come here to the Crystal Campbell Peace Garden to remember their lives and to be inspired and also to come here when they're in pain themselves.
to get a sense of peace here. They can also be surrounded by the small beautiful garden what it offers and reflects on how the beauty of goodness and how that goodness is in the world. I want to close with one of my favorite quotes and one that I know helped many others in the difficult days after the marathon.
As Dr. King Jr. said, darkness cannot be driven out by darkness. Only light can do that. Hate cannot be driven out by hate. Only love can do that. That's what this memorial represents. I want to thank you all for being here, and to all the families, thank you very much. Thank you, Mayor.
And now, with that beautiful spark, Jane Richard joined her mom, Denise, for the unveiling of the plaque dedicated to Martin Richard with Mary Brooke. Flower.
We are so honored to have so many members of the Campbell family with us today. And Bill and Patty, would you join Mayor Burke? Crystal's plaque with the sunflower for the anthem.
Good afternoon, Mayor Burke, Mayor McGlynn, Bill and Patty, Crystal's brother Billy, Kelly and Joe, Denise and Jane, all the dignitaries that are here today, as well as family and friends. I feel honored to be here today to help commemorate this park and its message of peace and positivity.
And although I never had the honor of meeting the four young people whose lives are commemorated here, I'm sure it would be comforting for them to know they're being remembered in such a beautiful way. Last year at the groundbreaking, speaking with Patty, she had mentioned to me that Crystal would love this park. And more recently, in speaking to Crystal's friend Karen and Matt, they told me as well that she especially would really love this.
She would love that this place has been created in her memory and would be moved. As we are reminded almost daily of the turmoil that exists in the world today, this garden will be a haven for those seeking refuge from the turmoil. A place to be grounded and enjoy a few moments of peace and tranquility. The definition of peace is freedom from disturbance, quietude and tranquility.
freedom from, or the cessation of war or violence. The definition of a peace garden is a public botanical garden created to commemorate the end of conflict or as an expression of commitment to peace, especially world peace. This memorial garden is true of that definition.
It is an expression of the commitment that Campbell family and the city of Medford and those residents of Medford have to create a space that honors four people that sought peace in a turbulent world. This garden is a reminder of how the hatred that stole four precious lives can be overcome by love in a united community.
In this beautiful, peaceful sanctuary, we can reflect on the goodness, passion, and innocence personified in these symbols. As mentioned several times today, the symbols, the baseball glove for Martin, the book for Lindsay, the police badge for Sean, and the sunflower for Crystal.
The center of the fountain was created making it rise above as it represents the survivors and future peace. This park is a beacon of their life which will serve to remind us of what true character should be. When we see the symbols represented here, one can't help but think of how communities can unite despite chaos and tragedy.
That there is hope and determination that we as a community can and have risen above. And although we are reminded of the innocence lost, we are also reminded of the wisdom gained and the messages that Martin, Crystal, Lingzi, and Shawn left for us.
It's very fitting that we can see symbols of their youth, beauty, life, vitality, learning, and selfless service everywhere we look within this garden. We can take great comfort knowing these symbols have not only been woven into every aspect of this garden, but will remain etched in all the hearts of those who visit.
Although pain and despair have touched us all, it is critical that we take and emulate the character we see represented here in our lives every day. May God bless you all and keep you safe. Thank you. Thank you, Roseanne.
It's my pleasure now to bring Bill Campbell to the podium. Good afternoon. I just want to say one thing. Mike McGlynn did have a vision, and that vision is here today.
And my wife, my family, I just want to thank you, our community, where we live. We love each and everyone. Thank you so much. God of peace and healing, on this day of memory, let us find renewed hope in this Crystal Campbell Peace Garden. May its sunflowers, waters,
and memorial plaques serve as a loving tribute to the lives of Crystal Campbell, Martin Richard, Lingzi Liu, and Sean Collier. May their memories be for a blessing. May we recall the selfless deeds of the first responders who extended their arms in love and comfort. May the scarlet of peace stand as a testament to our faith that love rules over hate, peace over violence, and hope over despair.
May this garden of peace inspire renewed dialogue and understanding, as when we speak to each other, we can create a world of harmony and peace. May this Bristol Campbell Peace Garden inspire us to fulfill among us, in a small way, what is written in scripture.
I shall give peace upon the earth, and you shall lie down in none to make you afraid. I shall abolish from the earth the predatory beast. The sword shall never come upon your land. Justice shall roll down like water, and righteousness like a mighty stream. And like all Jewish prayers, I will end with a prayer for shalom, for peace. May the one who makes peace in the heavens bring peace to all of us and to all of humanity, and let us say amen.
♫
¶ ¶
¶.