On July 16, 2022, Governor Baker signed into law an act relevant to extending certain state of emergency accommodations, which among other things, extends the expiration provisions pertaining to the open meeting law to March 31st, 2023.
Specifically, this extension allows public bodies to continue holding meetings remotely without the form of a public body physically present at a meeting location and to provide adequate alternative access to remote meetings.
The Act does not make any new changes to the Open Meeting Law other than extending the expiration date of the temporary provisions regarding remote meetings from July 15, 2022 to March 31, 2023.
Okay.
Which, remind me then which item is first on our agenda?
The Riverside Avenue amended notice of intent, so I'll read that.
Amended notice of intent, 121 Riverside Avenue, DEP file number 215-0231.
Medford Housing Authority has filed an amended notice of intent for work associated with modernization of the existing property, 121 Riverside Avenue, soft install apartments within jurisdictional areas, Inland Bank and 200-foot Brooklyn area in Mississippi.
Thank you, Dennis.
So can we have a present here about the modification problem?
Sure.
Applicant's representative?
Yeah, good evening.
Tom Hughes with Hughes Environmental Consulting.
I'm here with Steve Sawyer, and I want to note that Gabe Cicirello and a number of the project team members are
I have a motion to approve the commission's approval of the parcel.
Basically, we're up against a funding deadline, which was the end of January.
It's kind of being extended daily and we run the risk of losing the funding source for the project because we don't have sufficient rights to the D. O. T. land in which to satisfy the lender.
So.
What we have done is we have revised the plans to come up with an alternative that does not rely on the parking or the stormwater improvements that were on the DOT land.
We are still in negotiations with DOT.
DOT is segregating out those negotiations over the parking area itself and then the rights to connect into their stormwater system just because of the processes involved.
We do hope
to obtain all the rights to go back to the original plan at some point, but for securing the funding, we have to have an approved alternative that does not rely on any DOT land or access.
So we're going to ask you to approve the amendment, and in that approval amended order, include a condition that allows us to go back to the original plan should we secure sufficient rights to do so.
So given that, what I'd like to do is turn it over to Steve Soar.
He can point out on the plans, you know, where the DOT land, where we were relying on it before and what he's done to change the stormwater management system and to shift some parking onto property in order to make this all work.
So Steve, do you want to take away?
Yeah, sure.
Dennis, could you allow me to share screen?
You're good to go.
Okay.
All right, can everyone see the screen?
Yep.
Yes.
Okay.
Great.
So there we're talking about.
So the property line here, you can follow me.
See my cursor falls here, jogs over and runs down.
Along the Eastern side of the property, so our original intent was to resurface this and actually expand some parking down in here.
curb this entire side and pick up, you can see in the magenta, the original swale location that would dump into the forebay.
And then the original location of the infiltration basin was sort of mirrored and nosed across into the MassDOT land area.
And then we overflowed into that easement area.
So, at this time, we're not allowed to do any work on the, you know, do any work on the mass dot area.
Mass dot land, so what I've shown here, this is the drainage divide.
This red line dotted line.
So this, this water still flows towards our property.
Towards our property, and we can collect in.
and treat it, while on this side, on the MassDOT, we're not doing any paving.
We can't, there's a break in the curb.
This water sheet flows off into that bituminous swale.
It's on MassDOT land.
And unfortunately, at this time, we fully expect that we'll revert back to treating this parking lot and diverting it to our basin.
But at this time, in order to secure funding, we have to take all the work off that.
So with that,
What we did is where there's no improvements down at the lower end.
We're ending the parking lot here as it exists today.
I've installed a trench drain at this location.
I'll zoom in a little bit and actually going to switch to another plan.
Oh, man, it just froze up.
I'm freezing up.
Okay, I'll stick with this plan.
For some reason, my PDF viewer freezes up.
I may have to reopen them.
It'll take a second.
But so what we're doing is we're installing a trench drain at this location.
And we've extended the swale up, the westerly swale up to pick up the parking lot.
So we run it down into the forebay and then into the infiltration basin.
And then we're discharging into an outlet control structure and then through a pipe into the river.
Actually, if you don't mind, what I'm gonna do, I'm gonna reopen.
It's gonna take me a second, but I'm gonna have to stop share.
and reopen my PDF drawings for some reason.
Hold on a sec.
Steve, would it be easier if I shared?
Maybe, yeah, for some reason my, everything frees up my, Adobe's just frozen up.
All right, Dennis, can you allow me?
There we go.
Steve, mine are stacked onto, you know, I'll have to page.
Tell me where you want me to go.
Yep, next page.
Next page.
Come on.
Back.
C-104?
Yeah, you're missing one.
It was C-105.
It's a great question.
I don't have C-105 in what you sent me.
All right.
Hold on a sec.
Yep, please bear with us for.
Yeah, sorry, I'm so sorry about that.
Yeah, this thing is completely.
I may have to reboot my computer.
All right.
Maybe if you want me, I have C105.
Yeah, go ahead and why don't you?
We're just going to go around the room till somebody.
Yeah, somebody.
OK, hold on just a second.
I'm assuming it would be this one.
Tell me if you see it, guys.
Is this a C105?
There we go.
Perfect.
Yeah, so if you can zoom in a little bit to that lower right-hand corner.
Give me a second.
Right here, this area?
Lower.
Actually, you're in the other, you're in the, there we go, right there.
Okay.
Yeah, so, as you can see, we've had to extend this swale up to pick up the existing parking lot.
We did install a trench drain at the bottom.
You can at the very bottom of the parking lot to pick up.
All the up gradient, we're directing all this.
Yep.
And we're directing all the storm water through the swale into the into the floor bay and into the infiltration basin.
With an outlet control structure, and then then it discharges into the directly into the river.
It's all treated now.
1 item of importance is we're keeping these the same size.
So these are basically size.
For they were actually oversized to begin with, even for that additional payment that we're not picking up.
Number 1, I don't I fully expect that we're going to be picking that payment up again.
I'm confident that we will.
But this is sized for the full water quality treatment and the water quality treatment and recharge.
Important note with the discharge, the flared end outlet, we are discharging, we're not in the water.
We're about six inches to 12 inches above the high water.
So we won't be working in the water.
So it's fairly straightforward.
We will extend the erosion control to the top of the rock, and then we put a boom and a silkscreen around the area that we're working for that area that we'd be working.
It's a very shallow trench.
I think we're only down about three and a half, four feet to get that pipe in the ground, so it's fairly straightforward.
So, other than that, I was still meeting as far as the storm water.
That's on our property, we're full meeting the full the full treatment and recharge.
So there's no change with that.
Unfortunately, at this time.
Like, I can't say enough, I fully expect it will be.
Going back to that other design to pick up the parking lot.
And then the only thing that might happen with tip mass dot is if sometimes if they won't let us tie into that bituminous well.
We'd end up, we'd end up having to install the outlet control structure that the outlet control.
But as far as water quality treatment, I fully expect that we're going to be picking up that that mass dot land.
And in fact, I think our company now is, they've asked us to provide a proposal to provide this survey for the conveyance of that land area out to the housing authority.
So all indications as we're moving forward in that direction.
But that's what I have as far as the ask for the amendment and look forward to any questions.
And if I can add, one of the things we did maintain is the plantings within that swale.
We did try to make this as still as good a proposal as we could.
Heidi, you're muted.
I'm sorry.
Thank you.
You'd think after two years I'd remember.
Thank you for walking us through the modification.
And so, open it up to discussion and questions by the commission.
And if you could stop sharing for a moment, that would be helpful.
I can see people.
Sorry about that.
Hold on just a second.
Tell me if it's no better.
Yeah.
I would like to just ask a bit about the other swale, because I'm not remembering it as well as I should remember, because there's two sections, there's a little section in the middle, and there was something going on with that section in the middle, I think we talked about last time, but I'm not exactly sure if we resolved everything with that, you know, that left swale.
Um, I think I think the left, the less oil we were looking to.
Um, you know, the left swell isn't is, um.
It's not, it doesn't have the meandering.
Um, it doesn't mean, or it's just a, it's just a grass well.
On that side, but I think that.
What we did is okay on the opposite side, we had the room and we provided that the type of swale they think that what was imagined over on that other side.
However, we are getting the appropriate water quality treatment on the west side with the grass swale, the forebay and the bioretention basin.
So we are achieving the required water quality treatment on the opposite side.
We're not making any changes over there.
There's no need for it.
But there was no room to widen that swale out.
And I think with the use of the forebay and bioretention area, it achieved the same intent as far as water quality.
There's no pipe.
There's no treatment structure.
It's just going over a small weir.
Is that how it's discharged into the river?
On the on the on the West side.
Yeah.
Yes.
So it's, it's, it's open.
You know, it's open flow.
It flows into the 4 bay, then it flows over aware into the, into the.
No, into the by retention basin and then over a, it's a very flat.
We're over that into the, the original, the original swale.
Which actually is part of their project is is we're matching.
we're matching basically the edge of where they're making the improvements.
Would it help to bring the plan up again, Alex?
No, no, no, I've got it.
I've actually got it here in front of me.
Oh, okay.
From what Dennis had sent me.
So yeah, I'm looking at that too.
So I think we did resolve then everything we needed to talk about with that.
Western portion.
Yes, yes, that was resolved.
Yeah, because it does stick out.
It's a very strange looking situation with the bocce courts and, you know, that very steep embankment.
But I think that's probably what you needed to have with that parking lot the way it is.
Yes, and also those are one foot contours, so I believe it's a two and a half to one.
It's not as steep as it looks as far as the contours.
It's a bank, but with one foot contours, it looks a little steeper.
Typically, people provide two foot contours.
to clarify, yes, that whole area was approved, and the only changes that we proposed in the amendment on the plan are those ones on the other side that Steve reviewed.
Yes.
So, you know, just the subject of the amendment that we've got before you is that of the soil.
But we're happy, again, we're happy to answer clarifying questions on the project as a whole.
Yes, understood.
Thank you.
I don't know if that's the right way to put it.
It's, I believe as part of this, there's, we're integrating it with the Clipper, what is that?
The Clipper ship walking path.
So there will be, you know, the plan would be if we go in this direction while we were, you know, I've already reached out to, I believe Stella Lansing.
It sounds as if they may not be in, it may, it's questionable whether they'll be in construction next summer for that pathway.
It sounds like it might be the following summer.
But we'd be as far as any work, we'd be in close coordination with them.
So, any disturbances, of course, we would want to get our pipe in.
Prior to the pathway, if we end up moving in that direction.
So, any of our disturbance would be temporary.
We'd restore it prior to them coming through and putting the path in.
And to answer that question, what might be helpful, I'm gonna share my screen for just a second if that's okay.
I can find my Adobe.
Mine's still frozen, so I don't know what happens frozen.
It's because of your background, look where you are.
Well, actually, if I turn it off, if I turn that off, you'll see the rafters of my attic.
Why is this not showing up?
Give me a second here.
I have an aerial that would be really helpful in showing you kind of what's there, but I don't know, share screen is just not really cooperating here.
It's just not showing me Adobe as an option to share right now.
The only reason I ask is the plan set indicates tree cover around where the outfall is popping up.
So aerial might clear that up.
Yeah, no, and I think it would.
Let me close the share option.
Let me close a couple windows here and maybe that will give me the option.
There we go.
So I think we're talking outfall roughly in this area, Steve.
Yeah.
So if you notice, there's really not much to speak of.
You get a riprap slope.
There are some kind of, you know, little bit of vegetation along the top there.
My guess is that the DCR project is probably going to impact a lot more than our outfall will.
We're certainly open to a condition that we replace any damaged vegetation during the installation of the outfall.
I mean, it might be like one small sapling or something, and there could be a good, decent chance it's an invasive sapling at that.
So it will be replaced with native if it's invasive.
So hopefully that's helpful.
Now I'm going to stop sharing while I'm ahead.
It is.
Thank you.
Appreciate it.
Great.
Thanks.
We've talked about a couple of conditions, but first, oh, I'd like to know if there's anybody from the public here that would like to comment on the proposed modification.
Hearing none, I'd like to ask the commission if they would like to make a motion on the proposed amendment of this order of conditions.
With conditions.
I make a motion to accept the amendment with the condition and that if funding or not funding if go ahead does come through from the DOT that the plans could revert back to the previously accepted plans.
Do I have a second?
Yeah, I'll second that.
Proceed.
Thank you.
I'm going to take a roll call then.
Heather?
Aye.
Eric?
Alex?
Aye.
And Craig?
And myself, aye.
Thank you so much for helping us move this forward.
You're welcome.
I just want to make sure that Dennis has the two conditions that we spoke about, which is that the condition that we revert back to the original plan should approval be received by MassDOT.
So basically what I sort of have is just an approval for the previously accepted plans is given the previous, the language is a little wonky, but so then the previous order will valid.
Does that make sense?
We'll revert.
That's the language, okay, thank you.
Also,
any vegetation damaged by the proposed outfall shall be replaced with native vegetation.
Yep, I've got those, I got that one, I wrote that one.
And then all other conditions are carried over from the previous, from the original.
It'll be the same one so I'll work on that tomorrow and get it
to the clerk's office and mail it up to DEP tomorrow.
So you can start using tomorrow as your timing.
All right, excellent.
So tomorrow is day zero of our 10 business day appeal period for the amended part of the order only.
The remaining part is already cleared.
I'm saying that more for the client team.
Okay, all right, thank you.
Thank you.
And don't forget that Monday is a holiday.
Right.
Okay, so anyhow, again, thank you so much for being on.
Yeah, thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you so much, everybody.
Thank you, Heidi.
Thank you.
Good luck with MassDOT.
We're making progress.
Take care.
Good night.
Second item in the agenda, notice of intent, Malden River pathway DEP file number 215-0215 be submitted.
Massachusetts Department of Conservation and Recreation has filed a notice of intent for the extension of the pedestrian walkway on the east side of the MBTA parking lot at the Wellington station and on the west side of the Malden River with work located within the 100-foot bunker zone to bordering vegetated wetlands and bank and within the riverfront area and bordering land subject to flooding.
Excellent.
Who would like to speak about the project for the applicant?
Mark.
Mark, Mark it is.
So we started this, John's on also.
We started this, I think this is the Wellington Greenway.
I can share my screen real quick.
Give me one second.
I made you already host.
You're good.
Thank you.
And did that work?
Yes, it did.
So you can see the yellow, the green are phase 1, phase 2, and phase 3.
This is phase 4 area in here.
This is a proposed 10 foot wide walkway.
We filed a notice of intent quite a while ago.
I think we performed a site walk, and then possibly COVID derailed our progress.
And so we're back here to reactivate everything and find out the best path forward.
I have plans if you want to see those also.
These are the plans.
I'll start at the beginning.
Yeah.
Mark, I think we have two new members in the interim.
Oh, OK.
Sure.
I'll definitely go over them.
Yeah.
So let me go back to this one and explain.
I'll zoom in a little.
And you can see this is the path.
This is Wellington Station.
This green part was completed a couple of years ago.
And so the proposal is to connect this green path along the shoreline
There's a level spot out here today that we plan on utilizing.
It's a heavily treed area, so that's one of the things we discussed in the commission earlier, was about some of the tree clearing that would be needed to create this 10-foot wide path.
Eventually, then it comes through the clear channel property.
AMFM Broadcasting and connects to Wooden Memorial Bridge, which this piece in purple was constructed when they did the Wooden Memorial Bridge project.
So this is the last, the missing link, so to speak, of the, I believe it's the Bike to the Sea is the proper name for the entire project.
So we'll start.
The first few plans are just here.
And one more.
There we go.
So it's just a pretty straight path.
This line here is the boarding land subject to flooding.
It's zone A. So this work is outside of jurisdiction.
It is within the buffer zone.
The riverfront area is here, although this project is subject to a Chapter 91 license, so the riverfront area does not apply to the project.
So we come along here, and let me jump to the next sheet, and connect to here.
This is where, I mean, I'm sorry about that.
So I'm sorry.
We come along here on a 10-foot walk, continues out of boarding lane subject to flooding.
eventually till we get to here, where we have a small area of boarding land subject to flooding.
And, sorry about this.
And then we have some work in jurisdiction here, which is some work in boarding land subject to flooding.
There's some compensatory flood storage created here.
And again, a little more down here, some more minor impacts to boarding land subject to flooding, the 40 square feet of fill.
and 380 square feet of square feet of fill and then there's compensatory mitigation for the boring landscape to flooding impacts proposed at the same elevation in the same reach.
Hopefully I haven't lost anyone.
So basically there are, this is mature trees out here where we're
that we have to go through.
I think we did have a site walk with the commission to determine the best path for those trees.
I think one of the other issues that derailed us a bit was there was a homeless issue out here.
People are living out here and we're trying to figure out the best way to deal with that issue before we went forward.
I think that concludes everything I had to say.
Are there any questions or any more information I can pass along?
Thanks for that, Mark.
Yep.
Does the commission have any questions or comments?
I mean, this is essentially what we saw, what we discussed before, and there have been no significant changes, and I know that at least two or three of us were on the walk.
Am I correct in that assumption?
Yeah.
Okay.
Yeah, it was nice and cold and rainy and near snow, but yeah.
But nothing has changed since that time, correct?
Okay, thank you very much.
Is there any, well, there's some space in between the pathway and the parking lot.
Is there any plans to kind of replace some of the trees that are being removed to make the path?
You know, other plantings in the area?
Can I defer to John?
I think we did have some discussion of some minor planting.
Yeah, we did.
I don't know.
There's a fairly steep, I assume you can hear me, there's a fairly steep drop off in the parking lot to the path.
And there's a lot of trash and et cetera, et cetera.
And I think I think the plan was when we began the work and saw which trees were removed was to really bring the environmental agent out or bring members of the commission out and sort of decide.
Which areas should
Now include new trees.
I remember in the budget, which is a little stale, we did have a significant allowance for new plantings.
So the answer is yes.
If you said, okay, tell me exactly where they are, where they will be, we can't do it at this time.
Does that make sense to you, Mark?
Yeah, no, that is true.
So we have money budgeted, but we don't have a planting plan.
That's correct.
Is that right?
Yes, sir.
We could condition the order of conditions to review a planting plan prior to construction.
Yeah.
Sure.
And in my mind, that makes the most sense based upon my memory of the environment and some of the situations we have there.
I think that's the most rational approach at this point in time.
We did propose a second sidewalk soon after the initial clearing.
That would be a little better to traverse the path and see where the best places to plant would be.
I would go along with that.
Yeah, good.
One question that I had reading through the NOI, I mean everything looked
pretty good to me.
There didn't seem to be a construction phase pollution prevention and ENS plan per standard eight.
The NOI basically says that it's not qualified under the CGP, which is fair, but there's still a handful of items that need to be pulled together per standard eight for site operator and
Stazing and other things like that.
I didn't see that manual unless I missed it.
I think that sounds right, Ed.
Do you?
I'd have to go look.
Let's go back and check.
It has been a while, I admit, since I looked at this package.
But we'll look into that.
Can you suggest a condition, Mark, that would address that?
Yeah.
That's all I had other than that, though.
Everything else looked good to me.
Good.
Thank you.
Just out of curiosity, how did you resolve that homeless camp?
It looked like it had been emptied prior to our walk, but has there been any rehabitation?
I don't think anyone's been out there since... The last time I was out there, which was after the walk, there was rehabitation.
There was?
Okay.
Sad but true, yeah.
Yeah, unfortunately.
As part of the project, when the project really begins, the work really begins, that will probably be one of the first items that will have to be addressed.
Okay.
And I know the city actually has
a social worker who basically has been going down to those areas and trying to help the folks there.
Okay.
So I don't know exactly, I'm trying, I don't know exactly what was the last time they went because I don't really talk, see those folks and they don't really get, they're almost never in the buildings.
So, but I will check with the health department and find out, you know.
I didn't mean to distract from the, I just figured.
No, but it's, it's just good to keep in mind on them.
Yeah.
know that he's like I've talked to them in the last few years, they've come in just sort of asking questions about that area.
Especially when it's like fairly vegetated, it's fairly isolated, and you don't really see those there too often.
Correct.
Yeah.
Great, then before we discuss potential conditions, I just, I don't think there is, but are there any members of the public that would like to comment on the proposed notice of intent?
Hearing none, then let's talk about potential conditions for this project.
I've heard one of them, which should be the middle and review of a planting plan to the conservation commission.
Prior to construction.
I do want to say after the after the initial clearing.
Submittal of the plan after the initial clearing or.
A site a site site walk plan flaring.
Okay, so those are 2 separate items, so we have to separate them.
I think it would be maybe condition the site walk after the clearing and then following that site walk, a planting plan would be submitted.
That sounds good.
Yeah, I think so.
That would be good.
That makes the most sense.
Yeah.
It's going to be hard to understand it without
Yeah, yeah, you've been there.
Just, I mean, unfortunately, there might be some, you know, you can't because we go before and say we're all going to take down these 10 trees and then all of a sudden you just find there's something you know you might be able to leave one tree or another one has to come out you don't really.
Right.
Yeah, so but once the clearing is there, you know, just I think also what's usually in there anyway, but there's there's always a note of use notification to me prior to in our regular order.
It's just notification to me prior to
and I go over there and check out the erosion controls and also just do a site walk and sort of, you know, then at that point, once the erosion controls are in place, we'll have a little, I'll have a little bit better idea as to what might be taken down anyway.
And then once they're actually taken down, then we'll invite you all.
I suggest that the trees to be removed, be flagged.
Yeah.
I think that's the easiest thing to do so everyone can see.
So if we can have a,
that.
And then lastly, we would like to have prior to construction, please address the items from standard 8 of
I apologize for being pedantic, but going back to the planting plan, are we saying submission of or approval of a planting plan by the commission?
I think we need approval, I mean, submittal and approval.
Just say approval means it has to be submitted first, so it has to be approved, it can't just be submitted.
We had it worded as only submitted before, so.
Okay.
So I have submitted an approval of a planning plan prior to construction.
Great, thanks.
Do I have a motion from the commission?
I'll make a motion to approve the project with the conditions that we've discussed.
I second that motion.
Excellent.
I'll call the roll call.
Alex?
Aye.
Greg?
Heather?
Aye.
Eric?
And myself is an aye.
with the project and I can't wait to see it.
Thank you.
This is going to be fun.
We will get this done.
I'm still young enough to walk it.
Thank you.
Thank you all for participating tonight and I appreciate both the commission and the applicant and the representatives coming this evening.
Thank you very much.
I think that's all I have to say.
Thank you.
Good night.
Does the commission want to stay on for.
I just wanted to give you just a one quick heads up where it's just a filing in the next.
but because they're doing just they're putting a new pathway like around the park listen so but once that comes in I will send it off to you so I would anticipate a hearing on March 1st if we get it in in the next actually maybe not I'll see maybe it might be gonna be in 15 comes in later when I actually get it it makes more sense now that I don't get it in the next day or so but
I was kind of looking, I assume, I thought there was one more Wednesday this month and there is not.
So.
Shortly, that's the 1st.
Are there any meeting minutes that we need to approve, or are we all set on that?
I realized today that I never sent them to you, so I will the last meeting.
I think I was 1 behind it and because it's been a while, I just forgot until.
the last meeting we approved the meeting before.
Okay, so it's just.
Yeah, so the next hearing will approve both sets of minutes for yeah, yeah, thanks for the reminder correct.
I second the motion to close the hearing.
Great.
Alex?
Let's close it.
Heather?
Aye.
Eric?
That's my two buddies.
And Craig.
I am hungry.
And Lisa.
Ditto.
Very nice.
Okay, good night.
Thank you everybody.
Bye all.
Have a good night.