Hey listeners, this is Danielle.
And Shelley.
Shelley is a radical Dravidian and racial equity activist.
And Danielle is a community mobilizer and changemaker.
And this is the Medford Bites podcast.
Every two weeks, we chew on the issues facing Medford and deliver bites of information about the city by lifting the expertise of our guests.
Join us in discussion about what you hope for the future of Medford.
And as always, tell us where you like to eat.
All right, thanks so much for being with me this evening.
If you don't mind just starting us off by introducing yourself with your name and pronouns and who you are.
My name is Tarek Samman, and I use he, him, and I'm running for Congress in District 5.
Great.
Thanks, Tarek.
Great to meet you.
So we're going to talk- Thank you for having me.
Yeah, of course.
We're going to talk a lot more about your run for Congress.
But before we do that, I'm going to ask you the question that I ask everyone on the podcast, which is, what is your favorite place to eat in Medford?
And what do you like to eat there?
Well, first of all, for full disclosure, I don't live in Medford, I live in Cambridge.
So I will go with my favorite restaurant in Cambridge, if you don't mind.
There is this restaurant, it's a Chinese restaurant called Zoe, it's on the border between Cambridge and Somerville.
And I like going there.
I like their noodle, their chow mein, and I've been ordering from there nonstop.
Oh, cool.
I'm not sponsored by them, but they didn't pay me to say this.
No money exchange chances for this project.
Cool.
Thanks for sharing that.
Can you tell us a little bit about, so it sounds like your district would cover part of Cambridge, part of Somerville, part of Medford.
All thanks to gerrymandering.
I mean, the way that they drew the district is quite frustrating, because with gerrymandering, what happened is that the people in office decide their own constituents, rather than the constituent deciding their own representative.
And the way that is structured, there is around 23 to 24 cities.
Par of Cambridge is with IANA.
If you know Central Square, from Central Square toward MIT in the South is with IANA, and then from Central Square toward the North and Somerville border is with Katherine Clark.
And Somerville is not part of the district, even though two of the cities on the border of Somerville, Revere and Malden and Cambridge, are part of District 5.
It's all gerrymandered.
And even Lowell was part of the district, and then they also removed it.
I think the last time they did gerrymander, I think 2021-2022, as I remember.
But yeah, that's the district.
It's quite an interesting district.
It's quite big.
Certain cities fall within the working class, lower income, and a certain part of it is with the middle to upper class.
The way they even divided it doesn't make sense, but it is what it is.
That's why we're running for offices and this gerrymandering thing.
Okay, great.
So, yeah, so thank you for sharing that.
So, but there is a section of Medford that is included in.
Yes, Medford is in my district and it's 1 of my favorite cities.
I'll tell you that you're mine too.
And so right now, Catherine Clark is in this, this position that you'd be running for in the fall.
Yeah, perfect.
So can you tell us, you know, it sounds like gerrymandering is part of it, but what kind of helped you arrive to this decision to run for office?
I think when people ask me why I decided to run, I usually have two answers, one short answer and one long answer.
The short answer is because I want to serve.
I want to serve the people.
I want to serve those who are politically homeless, those who their voices are not being heard, those who their pain are not being recognized, and those who are starting to believe in a hopeless reality that pushing them away from participating in politics or believing in the governmental institution.
I want to serve these people.
And my long answer is, I am one of these people.
I am politically homeless.
My voice has not been heard by my representative.
My pain has not been recognized.
And I'm starting to feel hopeless.
But at the same time, I believe that when we are faced with circumstances like this,
It's the duty of the youth of my generation to step up, fight back and pay the sacrifice.
And by paying the sacrifice, I don't mean to resort to violence, or just be cynical.
I mean to participate in politics like you've never participated before.
Aim high, run for office, engage and be very aggressive, go and knock on doors, phone bank, do everything to
restore the country that you believe in, which unfortunately for my generation, those who were born in the 1990s and early 2000s, they grew up in an America that's completely different than those before.
We went through the Iraq war, we went through the Afghanistan war, we went through the economic crisis in 2008, and we went through the disappointment with the Obama presidency and then Trump presidency.
So I don't think my generation have seen anything
extremely positive of this country.
But at the same time, I believe that we can change that by taking responsibility and stepping up.
And that's why I'm running.
Okay.
Yeah.
And so it sounds like there's a lot of critiques that you have of kind of how our government is being run right now.
And I guess if you could like kind of share some of your top priorities, if you were elected, what you'd want to kind of start in terms of change?
I think one important thing is to ask ourselves this question, what got us here, right?
Why did Trump win and Kamala lost?
And the quick answer is money in politics.
The super PACs helped Trump get back into presidency, and the same super PACs made Kamala Harris not take a decisive decision on issues that matter to her campaign, and that made a lot of people not vote for her.
So the issue of money in politics
And corruption in Congress is one of the top priority that our campaign is focusing on.
And it should be the top priority for all the other campaigns who run in the wave of Democrat 2.0 and who want to enter office in the midterm election.
Because I truly believe without fixing the corruption and the super PAC influence in our Congress, we can't achieve all the beautiful things that we want to achieve.
I mean, I would love to promise the world to my people.
I would love to promise a future where
They know their children are going to be safe.
They know that they're going to have free health care, free education and ability to function in a society without hate.
But when I was creating the platform and running my campaign, I told my team, I don't want to feel like I'm lying to my constituents or promising things that I know we can't deliver.
Because when you enter Congress, you'll be dealing with 400 other Congress members and you will have to negotiate with them to get the thing that you want.
The rules of the game are not fair, because these same 400-plus Congress representatives are influenced by money and politics, and they have favors that they owe.
Because of these favors, they can't compromise or vote on child care or vote on health care.
bend the need to stay in office, because they're not used for people to participate and engage in politics or donate to them.
They're used to being slaves to their own super PAC influencer.
So yeah, the first one is we need to fight corruption.
campaign corruption, election finance.
I need to be also a true representative.
I need to be a listener.
It's a big issue in our district.
They don't feel that their representative is listening to them.
They don't see her as active as they would wish her to be.
And the third one, of course, which is an issue that everyone is concerned about, which is affordability.
So affordability and the way that our campaign frame it is to make the American dream affordable.
Because, you know, for immigrants, let me give you a data point.
Twenty five percent of people who live in our district are foreign born.
So we have a decent immigrant population, and I'm also a son of an immigrant, and my story is also very similar to a lot of their stories.
And we all came here for the American dream, yet we've been, our expectation was high, and it was faced with the reality that the American dream sometimes only makes sense if you're sleeping, because it's too expensive to afford.
So these are our top priority.
But on our campaign website as well,
When we started this idea of running the campaign, and I started talking to a lot of people, I talked to professors at Harvard and MIT, I talked to people in my own district.
And one thing, there's this professor at Harvard, his name is Marshall Gans.
I think he's quite popular among people who know about campaign.
He was the architect behind Obama's campaign.
And he also trained Mamdani staff, and he went there and he met with them.
And he was one of the first people that I talked to.
And he told me this.
He said, the reason why the Democrats lost the presidential election, it's because when they went around talking to people, they were telling them how to feel rather than listening to them.
And that was a big issue.
So he told me, you better get 100 volunteers, go around, talk to people, and then build a campaign around values, not issues, values that bring all the people together, that people share, that people care about, and urge them to participate in politics to make a change.
It's been a long process, but so far I'm proud of the progress we achieved, and I'm hoping to make a change that
I envision, you know, you should have a vision and you should follow that vision and we'll see how it goes.
I'm wondering like what you've learned so far by talking to people, like if anything has surprised you or if there's anything that's come out of your... One thing that surprised me is the fact that a lot of them don't know who Kathleen Clark is.
In fact, when I started doing my research and
Another thing I want to talk about is polling.
So because our district district 5 is considered a safe seat, a blue district, it's not that interesting to those who are.
conducting polls because it's not a swing state.
So when I started doing my research, there was not a lot of polls about approval of Katherine Clark.
There is not a lot of polls of people, the issues that they care about.
However, there is UMass Amherst University here in Massachusetts, and they conduct a lot of polls, and they usually do it at a state level.
I've read their polls and I've talked to people, and usually the first thing people don't recognize who Kathleen Clark is, and sometimes they think that Ayanna Paisley is their own representative.
A lot of them, you know, because they're not used to people knocking on their doors for federal election, local election is different.
They were surprised that, you know, I'm running for Congress and I'm talking to them.
Like, I remember I went to the street and I started recording some videos and talking to people, interviewing them.
And they're like, you're running for Congress?
Oh, that's surprising.
And like, they got excited.
Like, they would love to see it.
So, yeah, the first thing that surprised me is the fact that they don't know who's Kathleen Clark is.
Secondly, the fact that it's a very educated district, and you will hear a lot of interesting things that you've never heard about, like ideas and propositions.
I'm like, this is really interesting.
If this campaign starts getting some steam and some attention, I'm going to propose all these new ideas.
out-of-the-box ideas and ideas that also relate to AI, which is unfortunately an issue that not a lot of Congress members are talking about.
So caffeine clogs not being known, the fact that the district is very educated.
And the third one is, it's full of young families who are really concerned about the future of this country.
And another data point that I want to add is that 65% of the people in our district are independent.
and their young families.
So when I went around talking to them, they told me how much it's hard to afford things, how much life had been really difficult, and
I remember this story, one of the Uber drivers that I talked about my campaign, he was an Algerian American who came to America in the 1980s or 1970s.
And he worked really hard to, you know, set up his own business, get money and build a future for his own children.
And I remember he was telling me about his success in business.
And I'm like, in the back of my mind,
Why are you still Ubering?
Are you doing it as a pleasure to talk to people?
And he said, I'm doing it to help my children pay for their own student loans.
And I remember hearing this and I got so angry.
I'm like, it doesn't make sense.
And then another story that I also have,
I was talking to this old guy who, it happened actually today, and he told me how he used to own a business and then because of the economical situations, his business went bankrupt and now he's looking for a job.
But because he's old and now with this all new ways of hiring people and using AI to filter resumes and CEO, he told me it's so hard to get into a human.
And I don't know how this whole AI hiring thing works.
I don't know.
I'm not able to get a job because of it.
He just put me in front of people, and I can't convince him to hire me.
If he listens to this broadcast, you know what I'll be talking about.
He lives in Revere.
So I'm still waiting for your City Council meeting if you want me to come.
He told me, he lives in Revere.
He usually attends the City Council meeting.
I'm like, I want to show up in one of these meetings.
But yeah, all these stories that you hear about, you know, people struggling and the more details you get really, really frustrated and angry.
And here's why I told you I'm running for those who their pain are not being recognized, for those who have stories are not being heard.
And we all have these stories.
And if you're a Republican or a Democrat or independent or wherever you stand on the political spectrum, when you hear these stories, your heart will ache.
You will feel the pain because you're probably facing the same struggle.
You probably heard these stories.
You probably live in these stories.
So yeah, stories, stories, stories, and the amount of stories that I heard, it's heartbreaking, just heartbreaking.
It's, I mean, and now with the ice, it's, it's add more pain.
Yeah, it does like make me wonder.
So when, so on this podcast, I like interview other kind of local politicians, like city councilors, school committee members, mayoral candidates, and the sense that I get is that there's
this demand, or this not demand, there's an idea that people have of like, what these positions can actually accomplish.
And I think it's kind of vague sometimes.
So like, what is in the role in like, as a congressperson, like what are what is like actually within your power to change?
Or like, what would be what would the role be able to accomplish?
I think as a Congress member, you should view it in two lenses, the lens of how you're going to act locally in your own district and the lens of how you're going to act in Washington, D.C.
behind closed doors.
So locally, and this is also on our platform, one of the main issues that we're going to be focusing on is I want to connect with all the city council members, all the local politicians, all the constituents, all the independent media, and build a strong coalition that will make us
influence our own politics and at the same time solidify our position against all those who are trying to divide us, whether it's through ICE entering our communities or other threats.
So that's the first lens.
Locally, I should be an organizer and be open and listen to the people.
In Washington, D.C., you should be
Negotiator, you should understand that these politicians are influenced by, you know, super packs and the language that they're using behind.
In a closed door and in public is completely different.
And if you watch any of the Congress members' interviews, you'll hear stories of how they talk about their colleague who comes to them after a vote and tells them, this is very brave of you to vote on this, but I can't do it because I'm afraid of losing my seat or my party turning against me.
You've probably heard this if you watch any of their interviews.
And if I end up coming to Congress, I want to play the role of
making sure that these Congress members put the American people first.
I want to emphasize to them, like, hey, when you do the oath for office, it's for the country.
It's for the Constitution.
It's for the people.
You don't do it for the super PACs.
And I'm not going to be, you know, compromising on my principles and values.
I'm not going to, you know, do like vote on certain things and then put an explanation.
Oh, we needed to compromise here and compromise there.
I mean, compromising is important, but
there is a certain limit when it comes to your values, when it comes to your principles.
And unfortunately, we've seen a lot of Congress members compromise.
And the issue we are facing right now as well with Congress is that there is this video that I watched a long time ago, and it's a video of Nancy Pelosi's daughter going around interviewing Congress members who lost their position or they're just retiring.
I think she did it in 2018.
You can go and watch it on YouTube.
And I remember at the end of the video, she asked him this question.
First of all, they were very cynical of the Congress and they understand the popularity is sinking.
And at the end of the video, she told him, how do we form the Congress, something along the lines.
And they were like, it's up to the American people.
And then you go to the commit of that YouTube video.
The people are literally saying on the commit, but we voted for you to fix the Congress.
Oh, my God.
It's just disconnect with people in the position of power, of not recognizing that it's their duty to fix the rules of the game.
It's their duty to represent the American people.
You don't just go there and get used to your own position and get used to being in Washington, D.C.
that you lost touch with your own constituent.
But at the same time, if you want to talk about your power in Congress, so when you enter Congress, you are usually assigned to committees.
And then the committees are divided between the Democrat and the Republican.
And in Congress, your basic role is to sponsor bills that the people want you to sponsor.
And then after sponsoring a bill, you go around and negotiate, and you try to make the other Congress member to co-sponsor the same bill, so it brings more visibility and support, so it passes the committee level.
But the issue that you face in Congress is that once you sponsor the bill and go to the committee, 90 percent of these bills die at the committee level.
And that's because of the whole polarization, the whole control of super PACs, the whole, you know, I'm not willing to compromise.
I'm not willing to, you know.
vote in a certain way.
But even if the bill, if you were so lucky and your bill passed the committee level, then you have the floor.
And usually the party in the position of leadership is the one who controls which bill goes to the floor for the vote.
So you have all of this polarization, all of this division in Congress.
And because of this, it's almost impossible to achieve anything.
That's why I told you from the beginning, we need to address the rules of the game.
We need to fix the rules of the game.
Otherwise, we can't achieve much.
Are there other like-minded people that are already in Congress that you feel like you could join with?
Exactly.
The issue of corruption and fixing the Congress is an issue that a lot of politicians have ran on before.
However, this time is different because of the new wave of Democrat 2.0 who are running for offices all around the country.
It started with Mamdani changing the whole
turning the whole political world in America upside down.
And now because of him, a lot of politicians, a lot of new Democrats are running for offices.
You have senators, you have running the House at the House level, and they all have this pledge of not taking money from super PACs, from corporate PACs and foreign PACs.
And you've never seen this before.
And the reason why we've seen it is because they all realized finally that, you know, we can't achieve, you know, Medicare for all.
We can't achieve, you know, universal child care.
We can't, you know, end the whole overseas wars if you don't fix corruption in Congress.
If you don't fix how we run our campaign, if you don't put term limits, if you don't
do all these kind of stuff.
And in order to do them, you should not be taking money from these super PACs.
And now because of this new wave of Democrats who are running for office, I'm telling you there is hope that we might be able to change the rule of the games.
And I'm going to be part of that coalition.
I mean, talk about Rohana in Congress right now.
He'd been in the front lines fighting for banning super PACs, fighting for term limits, fighting for all of these issues.
And it's funny enough, even when it's come to the Epstein files, he was the one who helped with releasing it, you know, with co-sponsoring a bill with Thomas Macy.
And you didn't see that from our own democratic leadership, whether it's Hakeem Jeffrie or Katherine Clark.
And the reason is because Hakeem Jeffrie and Katherine Clark basically take a lot of money from these PACs, and they can't, you know, go on their bad side.
When you talk about taking money from super PACs, is that money that funds a campaign?
Is that money that personally pays these politicians?
Or where does that money go?
Usually, so there is this website called Open Secret that usually if you go there, you'll see each Congress representative and which money they, and the money, and you'll see the money that they get and who's paying for it.
And there is this, on Instagram, there is this guy,
He has this video, I'm probably sure that you saw them, where he said, you know, is your Congress a piece of, you know, and then he tells you their finances and their insider trading history.
And usually if you go to their website, you'll see the super PACs that finance their campaigns.
And usually also the super PAC can act independently by creating ads that attack the candidate that they're running against.
And we've seen this.
before with the AIPAC and all those pro-Israel PACs, how they create
They do opposition research where you basically find dirt on the candidate that you're running against and then you create ad to fight them.
Now usually these super PACs involve a lot with these dirty games.
They do a lot of it.
And they also help finance the candidate.
So I think there's a limit on PACs money for the candidate, but also on OpenSecret and other websites, they started like, because of all the
the attention that APAC is getting.
And because they're trying to find other venues to give money to their own favorite candidate, they usually send it through the dark money side or even through other individuals.
And there is this open secret website where it basically shows you these individuals and which PAC they are related to and how much money they give.
And of course, it's not just APAC, it's also BlackRock, Amazon,
you know, the healthcare industry, the real estate industry.
It's a lot of things.
And unfortunately, after Citizen United in 2010, so Citizen United, it's a Supreme Court case where basically they said that money is equal to freedom of speech.
So you can spend as much money as you want on a candidate.
However, what happened afterward is that the target, I think the story was the target supported a candidate who was anti-LGBTQ.
And because they did that, they got a lot of pushback.
So in order to find a back avenue so they could support the candidate without getting a pushback, they created these PACs.
So they give money to the PACs, and the PACs do their dirty work, whether they give it to the candidate or create ads that attack their opposition.
The problem with me is I read a lot about the frustration that people get who work in Congress, and I've talked to a lot of people who told me, you know, it's really frustrating, this influence of money on politics, and this whole story about super PACs and money in politics.
And you would assume that knowing all of this, that would make me decide not to run for office or decide to shy away from it.
But at the same time, as I told you from the beginning, it's the duty of our generation.
It's a sense of responsibility that although we inherited this country that's not ideal to our own standard, that doesn't mean we should accept it and let our children inherit it.
No, we should step up and we should fight back.
But yeah, and then another funny thing that I always like to talk about when I have this kind of discussion is like, you talk about insider trading, you talk about super PACs, right?
And the reason why we talk about them is because we know about them, right?
Insider trading didn't become popular until the early 2000s, and then Obama administration was the first one to do something about it.
And the same thing with super PACs.
I mean, super PACs got amplified after Citizens United.
But my point is, these two things we talk about because we know about, how about the things that we don't know about and we don't talk about?
And that's what's really scary.
Like, that's what we get surprised of every now and then with, you know, a new scandal, a new Epstein file, a new God knows what.
And that's the thing.
If you want to enter Congress, you should promise your own constituents that you will be transparent.
You will tell them about this whole black box thing that happened in Congress.
You should be more active on social media.
And you should tell them exactly what happened and they should know what happened.
That way they send you to Congress.
Yeah, that's a lot to think about for sure.
Thanks for explaining some of that stuff.
It was helpful.
Are there any other key points of your campaign that you want people to know about?
Yes.
So our campaign is divided into, we have the values and we have the principles.
For the values, we believe in three things.
The first one, we need to usher in Democrat 2.0.
And that basically means we need a new democratic party where the leaders are strong, united,
that doesn't promise change and then deliver excuses, that step up for the people, that put people first.
And the second one is we want to make the American dream affordable.
We want to make housing as a human right, healthcare for all, education without burden or barriers.
And the third one is we want to restore our American
values and defend our freedoms, and that means we need to defend our academic freedom, we need to defend our right to protest, we need to defend independent media, and we need to defend the freedom of speech, and we need to defend our immigrants, because an attack on one of us is an attack on all of us.
So these are our values of the campaign.
And then from these values, we get all of our, we build all the platform around these values.
So I know that usually when I go around, and that's why I want to talk about this, that when I go around, a lot of people will be asking me about various issues.
Like, what do you think of that?
What do you think of this?
And I always tell them about my values, because once you know my values, you'll know my stand on these various issues.
And that way I'm talking about it.
But yeah, this campaign is all about values.
This campaign is all about the people.
It's a grassroots campaign.
It will cost a lot of money.
I'm not delusional.
I know it's going to be an uphill battle.
But at the same time, when I'm faced with these obstacles, the question is not, how do you tackle the obstacle?
The question is, is it worth it?
You know, those who have a why can tackle anyhow.
And I think it's truly worth it.
And I think that
We can't achieve it without the support of the people.
And we need the support of the people.
We need people to be engaged.
We need the people who are cynical and hopeless to believe in this campaign and join us and be part of this change.
And that's the message that I would like for people to know.
And it sounds like we're at a point in our, in, you know, the reality of our country right now, where hopefully people are ready for something like that and that people are ready for some hope and something to kind of try to move us forward.
Exactly.
I always like to ask if there's any events that you want to plug or ways that people can get involved in your campaign.
So, with our campaign, we started an exploratory committee last August, and we spent the next couple of months doing coffee hours, but it was more of a private coffee hours where I'll go around and talk to people every Saturday in Cambridge.
And now because we filed with the FEC and we're public, we posted on Meetup and we're posting it on our social media accounts.
So every Saturday around 11 a.m.
in Luxor Cafe in Cambridge, we're having coffee hour.
So you can go there and sit down and meet with me.
And we are trying to expand it.
So the idea is I'm trying to
pick local businesses, local coffee shop businesses in my district and turn them into a headquarter for my campaign where I could go there and have coffee hour.
And we usually try to pick ones that next to universities.
So look for cafes next to Harvard.
And I'm trying, I'm looking for one in Medford.
We have a couple of one in mind, but I'm also trying to expand to other cities.
And the idea is like every Saturday I'll go for an hour and eat to each of these coffee shop and sit down and talk to constituents.
For coffee or shy.
I mean, we call it shy over change because I don't drink coffee.
I don't want to be like, hey, come for coffee hour.
I'm like, are you drinking coffee?
No, I'm drinking shy.
Oh, you lied to us.
But I call it shy.
I call it shy over change because I don't drink coffee.
But we call it coffee hour because that's what people think of when it comes to like cozy atmosphere to talk.
But yeah, we're doing it in Cambridge right now, and we're going to expand to Medford, Malden, and the other cities.
So if you're listening, if you're outside Medford and you're listening to this podcast,
And you have a coffee shop.
And even if you're in Medford and you would like to have us for a coffee, I would please reach out to the campaign.
tarikforcongress.com, T-A-R-I-K for congress.com is my website.
And before ending this, I just want to mention one thing I wanted to talk about from the beginning, which is last month, I went to Medford City Council meeting.
And the atmosphere there was really
surprising for me, because it didn't feel as like it's a city council meeting, it felt like it was a family gathering, where people know each other, where people are like enjoying the conversation and participating with their own politician.
And I remember this instances of like, there's this old lady who was knitting hats for the city council members, and then she brought the UN Charter of Human Rights, and she showed it to them.
And she was like, we should follow this.
Oh, my God, this lady, like,
So I remember I went with Micah, you've had him on your podcast before, and I told him, you know, I wish that the meetings in Congress were exactly like this, you know, where it's friendly, everyone is happy, and the people can attend them transparently.
So yeah, Metsford, I love you guys.
It sounds like you went to a gentler meeting.
They're not always like that.
In some families, your uncle will still yell at you across the dinner table or whatever in the city council meeting.
I mean, as long as there's no intention to hurt.
then you can yell at me as much as you want.
If we can have a civil conversation afterward and still lovers and still friends, I'm more than happy.
Yell at me as much as you want.
Yeah, it is something that I've learned about the residents of Medford is that
They all care very deeply.
They might not necessarily agree what they care about or agree with the end result, but they all have a lot of care for the city and mostly for each other.
So it is a good place to kind of see that kind of energy with constituents.
That's why I told you from the beginning, it's one of my favorite cities.
It should be a role model for the other cities because of how engaged the constituents are with local politics.
And I'm hoping that you all, if you're here in this podcast, be engaged in federal politics.
Come and join our coffee hours.
Yeah, no, that's great.
That would be great.
Well, thank you so much for taking the time to talk with us.
Thank you for having me.
Yeah, and good luck in the fall.
Thank you.
Thanks so much for listening to today's episode.
The Medford Bites podcast is produced and moderated by Danielle Balacca and Shelly Kisherman.
Music is made by Hendrik Irenese.
We'd love to hear what you think about the podcast.
You can reach out to us by email at medfordpod at gmail.com, or you can rate and review the podcast on Apple Podcasts.
Thanks so much for listening.
Guys, what's the name of the podcast?
Medford Bites.
Good job.