Hello, everyone, and welcome to Method Happenings, a show for and about the city of Medford. And I am John Petrella, and the purpose of our program is to give Medford citizens facts and information to help you make informed choices and to discover city services or businesses you may not have been aware of.
And we have returning guests today. It's our honor to have them both. Mayor Brianna Longo-Cohen and Milva McDonald, who is the chairperson of the Neighborhood Ambassador Task Force. Thank you both for coming. It's really nice to have you on again. Thank you. Thanks for having us. We're going to get into the ambassador program today, but before we do,
I have to bring up car park because I know it was the ribbon cutting today.
Yes, yes, we cut the final ribbon for Car Park which was a project we've been working on for over five years. Yes, and today we officially opened the splash pad and most importantly had Congresswoman Clark here in Medford who obtained probably at least two million in funding just for the basketball courts and the shade cover which has solar panels on top to power
the lights within the park, which is amazing. So we're so thankful. Without that federal money, some ARPA funding, additional park grant, we couldn't have made that possible. And it's a park for the whole community to enjoy, from babies to elders to dogs and everybody in between.
It's amazing. It was a great moment. I heard it was, and I heard it from good sources. I got phone calls today, how beautiful it is. I got to get up and check it out myself. Please do. Congratulations on that. That's a great thing up there. Thank you. It really is. Team effort. We have a team that works monthly, and Amanda Centrell, one of our planners, led the charge, so it was definitely a huge team effort.
Very good, very nice. Okay, so as I said, we're happy to have you both back on the show. And we're going to be discussing the Neighborhood Ambassadors Task Force today. We'll jump right into it. And, you know, the first question everyone's asking, not just me, you know, what's the purpose of the task force? Who initiated it? And a three-part question, who initiated it and why?
I can start and then Milva can fill in the blanks on this one. As a city, we are trying to get out communication any way possible. We have a monthly newsletter. We do a robocall biweekly, so about twice a month with events and important meetings. We have social media and we also put out press releases on
quite a few things a week that are happening that we want the residents to know about. Those posts are then shared within our newsletter and on social media, and we are doing everything we can to communicate out. I know you're helping, John, getting the word out on so many great programs and businesses.
But still, you find people that will say, I didn't know about that, or that wasn't communicated out well enough, or I wish I knew. We do our best to try to get people to sign up for the robocall or the email or the text messages for notifications.
And in one month, it seemed that I had a school committee member that was very concerned about, you know, just reading those comments on social media, but still knowing that, yes, the city's doing a lot.
Why don't you member parks made a great recommendation? Why don't you put in some of your robocalls the different communication platforms at the end? So we started doing that and around the same time. I had coffee with milva And we had talked about different things in the city And then I had a separate coffee with jim jim silva who I call the mayor of south medford. He started yes tomorrow
Wonderful guy. Yeah, he is he started smarto and he's still active with making sure that important press releases or city news or City Council news is shared if it has to do with South Medford so between those two different coffees and the school committee member and seeing what I was reading on social media with
just we need more communication. We kind of collectively said, what if we had a neighborhood task force where you had one or two people from each neighborhood that could serve on a committee just to enhance communications
And, you know, let the city know what we needed to do better or how we could expand and enhance our services. So with that, the Neighborhood Task Force idea was born. I thought it was a great idea. It wasn't my initial idea alone. It just came out of this month of just where you were seeing a lot of
I didn't know about that. I wish I knew. And thankfully, I obtained the support of Milver and Jim and a few others, and then we picked, you know, we worked on picking a task force. But that's kind of just in general where it originated. I don't know if Milver has anything to add, because she was at one of the coffees where we were discussing this.
Yeah. I mean, I remember, um, it came from just people talking together who love the city and love the neighborhoods and just are always, I mean, Jim especially is always thinking about ways to help people and strengthen the city and strengthen neighborhoods. Um, and that communication and that, um, idea to just make it,
smoother, like, I feel like the ambassadors are sort of a conduit between the people and City Hall. So, you know, as we get this program going, as the ambassadors just sort of really dig in more,
And as people become more aware of it, I think it will just get stronger. This is like a two-way street now. It's like two-way communication. City, the people, back and forth. I think it's what Jim Silver had done 10, 15 years ago with South Medford. He went and he introduced himself to his neighbors. He got to know everybody that lived in the community. And then he created an email list that he could push information out to.
him helping push out city communications to his neighborhood when it was an issue affecting him. Kind of in my head, I'm like, we could have somebody like this in every single neighborhood, focusing just in the communications. Now, there's been some issues where
complaints have come in to some of our ambassadors and it's not for complaints necessarily. Like you have a complaint, call my office, call a city department, email us. These ambassadors are truly as here's information that my neighborhood needs to know and you know what city, we feel like we could have done this better or we should do this or add this. So we're still working out the cracks. We've had two or three meetings.
continue. I'm so thankful. They've scheduled meetings over the summer. They're not going to break. And I think within the next few months, you're going to see more come out of the task force. But yeah, it's going to take a good six months to really plant the seeds and kind of watch it grow.
Okay, I got to say this. I know quite a few people that were picked. I think you made some great choices. I love the fact that you're with it, Milva. I know you'll do a great job. And I know there's a lot of other people on this.
You know, that's, can you tell us how, you know, these people were picked? Uh, how were they placed as ambassadors? I mean, what was that process like? Sure. Um, the city put out a press release asking for, um, applicants that were interested in helping with communications in their neighborhood. Um, we, we received a good amount of, um, applicants and,
I knew I couldn't do it alone, so I brought in a team of five or six that separated who applied from which neighborhood, and I was really looking for a politically diverse group of people. I tried to do that with the Charter Review Commission as well, because the Charter is just somewhat governing the city. It has to do with politics. And what we did, we were hoping for a committee of seven to nine people, because
I tend to think that the seven to nine is a good number. Anything larger can, you know, the more you have, the harder it is to kind of control and make sure everybody's at all the meetings. But we really did think there was so many amazing applicants. Like, we're so thankful for everybody that applied. And definitely those that weren't, we would love to get them on another committee. So what we did was, or what I did, I was, got some feedback from a group, from the group of people, and picked two from each neighborhood.
And I said, if one – and then we picked a date – Wednesday at 6 o'clock, we're going to have these meetings. We told those 15 people, you've been chosen. These meetings will be once a month at 6 to 7.30 on Wednesday nights. Please let us know if you're still interested.
And from that 15, you know, a few weren't able to do it, but we thought that was a fair way, I thought that was a fair way to at least start the process and start this committee. And there we ended up with 13 plus throughout the process. Milva stuck out for me as somebody that could lead and lead exceptionally well. We saw Milva, what Milva did with charter. I think everyone in the city is well aware of Milva.
Who she is, what she is, the things she does for the city. I agree with you. It's great. No, it is. It is. On point, just, you know, on top of everything, very responsive, caring, and to create a document that Milva McDonald and the team built, the whole charter committee built over the 18 months to two years and have all those meetings and community meetings and listen to feedback and to
come up with that document from such a politically diverse group of people was pretty remarkable. So I know that if, you know, I'm not available every Wednesday night, although I'm going to try to go to the July meeting and a meeting here and there, but there's no one better to lead the charge and be that person that can communicate with me on a weekly basis on this task force than Milva. So I'm very happy that the way that it turned out. And Milva said yes. Well, thank you. I think it's great. I really do.
Yeah, I just applied to be an ambassador, and then the mayor asked me if I would chair, which I was honored, as I was also honored to chair the charter committee, but it was a team effort, the charter, and I see the ambassadors also as a team effort, and that's one of the things that I'm most excited about, is creating a really solid team to do this.
I gotta say, you know, you're a great choice. I mean, you guys are doing a, I think it's just, I don't usually give my opinion, but I think this is a great program. I really do, and it's good, you know, I look at
I know a lot of people and I think it is diverse and I think that's the key. You're going to have a lot of different opinions and it's good. I think it's a great, great thing. I really do. I think this is a great program. I think there's a ton of potential for this.
And, you know, I got to ask, you know, what are some of your, let's call them goals, what are your early goals and do you have any long-term goals for this?
Well, I mean, for me, one of the early goals is just to get the team going, as we talked about. I want the ambassadors to get to know each other and connect with each other and throw ideas off, you know, each other and get, and the other piece is to get the ambassadors
familiar, I mean, they know their neighborhoods well, but there's so many resources at City Hall and there's so much there. And one of the things that the ambassadors will be doing over the coming weeks and months is just becoming really familiar with what's available there so that that can be shared with residents and also listening to residents and conveying what they're hearing to City Hall.
sort of getting the pulse of what's happening on the ground, um, and sharing that with City Hall. So, you know, we're having, uh, uh, department heads or members of departments at City Hall come to our meetings and just talk to us about what's available. And out of that also, there might come ideas about, um, ways to collaborate. So, um, yeah, those- that's sort of early goals. Right.
Yeah, and I think just kind of what we talked about earlier with what Jim did for South Medford, they're talking about ideas now, more than I could even imagine. Email blasts, gaining an email database for your neighborhood.
you know, welcoming new neighbors to your, if you, you know, figuring out who's new in the community and knocking on the door or, or, you know, if some ambassadors may not want to knock on doors, but they give a letter, I'm your ambassador. Here's a form you could fill out so you could sign up for the city's
newsletter, and you can also sign up for robocalls, and also know they're going to be attending different community events and being present and letting people know we're here to help build communication so that you're in the know, and there's just so many great ideas coming out of the committee that we kind of have to formulate.
figure out what will work for everybody and create that checklist. All great stuff, really. I mean that. And I would say another long-term goal is just to enhance and increase civic engagement and excitement and just empower residents, too, to realize, yeah, I really can have a relationship with City Hall. And I can be part of my community in really meaningful ways.
And I think that's very important. I really do. And we have our connectors and liaisons that work for the Office of Prevention and Outreach. So the team has already met with that group. It's 12 people that are amazing. They work for the city part-time. I think one is full-time, but part-time. They all speak a second language. So this is just an extra way to enhance making sure that not only does everybody feel welcome and accepted and
be part of the city and government, but they can get their questions answered. They can get help when they need it, they can get supports when they need it, and they can know through communications what's going on in their own community, from high-level meetings to a grand opening at Carr Park. Awesome stuff.
All right. Next question. You know, and I know this, reaching out and hearing from Meffitt residents, I mean, it is a tremendous challenge. It has been for a while to really reach out. You know, I guess the question is, what are some of the ways, you know, the Ambassador Task Force, what are some of the ways
you know, that maybe they can solve this or resolve it. I don't know what the... Well, I think even just enhance or help. So for example, we do pretty well in Medford when we put out a survey. It seems like there's a lot of
busy, busy people in our community. Everybody's working and taking care of their families or their parents. And we do a lot of surveys. But it's a matter of people knowing about the surveys. So although we do get pretty good responses, the ambassadors will know about every survey that we put out. And whatever platforms, either they're using all the same platform or some are doing email blasts, some are doing door hangers, some are going to community events.
It's just an extra way to say, hey, did you know this city was doing this survey on a park that's right down the street from us? Please fill it out. You can drop it off at my house, and I'll bring the whole package of them to City Hall. So even enhancing things like our surveys is just one thing that I think the ambassadors will help with. And that goes along with when community meetings are, especially when it has to do with their neighborhood, and so much more.
Yeah, and as we get more established and we start to get to know the city staff and department heads, if a particular department is putting out a survey that's particular to a neighborhood, we can contact the ambassador and say, hey, just wanted you to know this, whatever help we can get to get the word out. I mean, there's a lot of ways. We have the emails and the contact information of every ambassador currently on the website.
Right. So people can find them. And you know, people are starting to contact ambassadors through that. So that's one way. And you know, presence at events, as the mayor mentioned, is another way.
You know, some of the ideas also people have talked about is, you know, block parties kind of getting just to get people more connected in their neighborhoods and coffee hours, bulletin boards. I mean, there's a lot of ideas. Yeah, I'm sure you do have a lot. It sounds like you got a lot of ideas. And I know you guys will definitely follow through on it.
We had a wonderful porch fest two weekends ago, and I just got a compliment on it, although it was run privately and we help advertise. Got a compliment that it was the most, I think we had about 20 block party permits, and the city was just buzzing. It wasn't as packed as Somerville was, but you had so many residents that were just going from block party to block party, or hanging out at one block party, and the feel was
was amazing, so I can totally see our ambassadors next year taking that map, that huge map of the city of Medford and where all the 150 porches were, breaking it down to their community and publicizing, hey, neighborhood, did you know we have 10 porches in our neighborhood alone? Come meet your neighbors and flyering doors or do an email blast once we get that full year under our belt.
I think that's great, especially the blog parties, because it's nice to have like the...
A lot of neighbors don't know each other anymore. I hate to say it, but they don't. And to me, that's a great, great way to get people to, you know, we're all looking for the same things, you know, just, you know, we really are. That's the way I've always felt. So, all good stuff. So, you know, you guys mentioned a lot of communications, you know, that the group is working on.
you know, can you share something like, I don't know, maybe like a timeline? I mean, I know this is going to take time. And everything, I think the audience is going to love what you're saying. And I think people are really, the people I've spoken to are really happy about this. I mean, you know, and I know it's just starting out. So can you give us like, you know, maybe some type of timeline when
Well, I'll say right now, I mean, we're still building the program, but it is active. So people right now can reach out to ambassadors, communicate with them, get help with issues. I mean, ambassadors can't solve your problem, but they can help you become aware of what resources might be available to address problems.
We are meeting over the summer, as the mayor said. We are going to be at the farmers market on September 10th. So we'll be there with a table and hopefully meet a lot of people and let people know about the program. And one thing that's in the works, it's not completely scheduled yet, but
The one idea that came out of our last gathering was an open house for ambassadors somewhere, maybe the library, in the fall. So people will be invited to come and meet their ambassadors. And then different ambassadors will be doing different things within their own neighborhoods. Right. Sort of a free-for-all, right?
I mean, every ambassador is an individual, so yeah, and every neighborhood is different. So yeah, it won't be the same neighborhood to neighborhood.
But if there are going to be — the ideas are still being discussed. And if there are going to be specific checklist items, I would expect sometime in the fall. You know, if they're all going to do email blasts, you know, you're going to give us a few more months, but — Oh, no, I know. Listen, we all know. I mean, it's — you know, it's just starting out, and it does. It takes time. And once it gets rolling, though, I think this is really going to take off.
Yeah, and we're also keeping track of all the communications that the ambassadors get so that when we meet with city staff, we can say, okay, you know, we have these, this is what we're hearing from people and, you know, they can sort of sense, um, okay, that sounds like an issue we should be addressing or, you know,
et cetera. Yeah, no, I think it's a great program. All right, so I know you're joining forces with the Friends of the Method Public Library. That's for the library car drive in September. I have a library car, I just want you to know that. Everyone should have one, because that library is an incredible place, but that's for another show. Do you have any other
joint ventures or similar things you guys are looking to get involved with? Not at the moment. We were very excited that we were asked to work on the library card drive. Of course, you know, the library is beloved by all, pretty much. And we welcome ideas for other collaborations. One of the things
At our meeting in May, the health department came and spoke with us and they talked about their excitement about the program because some of the issues that they work on are very conducive to neighborhood
cooperation. So they talked about, you know, if ambassadors can get groups together in the neighborhoods, if anybody's experiencing rodent issues, we would love to help, you know, so, so the ambassadors can kind of, um, help get things like that going. So, um, I think that there will be more and, um, they'll come from maybe whatever's happening in the neighborhoods or, and like the library card drive, you know, we were asked to help. So,
Yeah, I think that's a great thing. I just like that, that it's going to be, everything you're saying, just- And they'll be at the farmer's market, like Milva said, in September. So as they have a table, more and more people will realize who they are, what they're about, and it's all about communication. So I can see more and more city staff and groups looking to the ambassadors for help and support. They are not, again,
ones to go and complain to or try to get their problems solved, but ambassadors can lead them in the right direction. Hopefully everybody knows this is all about communication. How do we make sure we know what we're not doing well enough and can enhance and how do we make sure they're helping.
push out communications so everybody knows of that zoning meeting regarding their neighborhood or that new Medford High School meeting that affects families and kids and everybody who lives in Medford who, you know, will foot the bill. So, just so much that they're going to be able to help with. There's a lot people need to know. Yep. There's a lot people want to know and I think this is
This is going to help, that's for sure. It really is. All right. So now, these are my questions, because this is what I always think about. So we have the task force. Like I said, you've got some great people in there. Is the ambassador task force like a permanent position? Are there any plans for the length of service? You know, each member will serve.
You know, is it voluntary only? Is that how this works? I mean, what what are you guys? Sure. This is not by ordinance. This is not a board or commission mandated that you have to be at every, you know, every meeting. This is volunteer basis. Some meetings are on Zoom. Some meetings are in City Hall. Milva just hosted at our house to get people to know each other recently. So I can see this group really succeeding.
Again, it's going to take a little time to get our feet wet, but I can see this group really succeeding.
I have another 18 months in this term alone, and I would love if the task force could be active during this term, at least. But no, there's no term limits, no stipends, unfortunately. This is just a mayor's task force to try to enhance communications and make sure people are aware of everything the city has to offer, and we can learn on how to enhance and do better.
So this is great. I like this now. Um, you know, I, I, this is probably way out there in the future, but like, you know, the, the, the neighborhood task force, you got a person for each neighborhood. I mean, can, is it possible, like, will they be holding meetings like with the neighbors? Maybe like, is that a possibility at someone's, I don't know, backyard barbecue or whatever it is.
Possibly. Yeah, I think there could be a coffee hour here or there and tell us how you learn things. You know, they could do their own surveys. How do you in the hillside, my neighbors in the hillside, how do you want to learn about what the city is doing and what events there are and what meetings there are and how to get involved and when there's a survey that comes out. So yeah, I could see some ambassadors wanting to do that. Yeah, definitely. I bring that up because I get together with guys every Saturday morning. You know, we have coffee.
And we try to solve the problems of the world, but it just doesn't seem to be happening. You're helping. We try. Hopefully this helps get the message out there, you know. And I really do believe that's something Method needs, you know. Communication, people coming together, everyone working together. I think a lot more gets accomplished that way. I really do. Always felt that way.
Okay, so here's the last question, and believe me, I have a lot more, so maybe we bring you back again, you know? I love having you guys on, so I had you both on separately, and it's always a pleasure. So who do you see benefiting from this program? I mean, you just see, I mean, you see a benefit to the staff at City Hall, people that live here, I mean,
If you had to wrap it all up, I'm sorry to interrupt, but who do you see? The number one group of people that I think I see that we want to benefit from this are people that are not receiving communication.
for one reason or another. They're new to Medford, they're not on social media, they don't have a computer, people that move in and they're new, new families or people that need support and don't realize how much the city has to offer from our recovery coach to our social worker to our liaisons and
Connectors that speak a second language. So I think the number one group we want again to benefit from this are our residents all of our residents, but especially those that for one reason or another aren't learning as much as they should be about what the city has to offer and what we're doing and events and
public meetings that are affecting, that could affect them, their family, their neighborhood. Um, so overall I think it will benefit every, all of the above, but our residents, this is why we're doing this. Okay. I agree. That is the main driver. Um, but I, but I also do think it will help city staff as well. Um, you know, and I'm hoping that city staff will eventually see the ambassadors as a resource. Um, and that residents will see the ambassadors as a resource. Um, and, uh,
you know, all the things. Right. We just had a few listening sessions at Tufts Park, because we're going to be doing that tot lot over. And it happened already, but I can see all of our park projects, when we need feedback from neighborhoods and residents, this is a way to enhance that. Whether it's an email blast or a social media post, but the ambassadors can say, hey, did you know there's these two listening sessions
at Tufts Park or the next park we do, go down or fill out the survey if you can't make it down there or go talk to Amanda and the planning staff and let them know what you want to see for your kids and your family and the neighborhood. So I do see this as a definite positive and a great enhancement for our community. That's great. Yeah.
Mean I've done this kind of thing in my neighborhood, you know Like there were parking issues because I live near the commuter rail and you know calling meetings talking about that resolving that issue So I just I have a list from you know All of that and then when I know that there's an issue going on that I think residents want to hear about
I email my list and say, hey, you know, FYI, there's a meeting at City Hall. And the more people we have doing that kind of thing, the more people are going to feel engaged, empowered, connected, and the more the city can do its job for the residents.
You mentioned parking. I love that one. No, really. There seems to be a lot going on with that again. When I was young, I just have to throw this quick story in. When I was young, we had like four cars in my family. Our neighbors had two.
Like, it always worked out in the wintertime because, seriously, you knew every single neighbor. And the people that had driveways, boom, you know. As a matter of fact, me and my brothers used to fight all the time because who had to move this car, that car, whatever. So, that's interesting, you know. But we all, I think this is going to help with that, you know. I hope so. I really do. I think it is. I think it's great. I really do.
And you have some ambassadors already doing – putting out minutes of the ambassador meetings out online, being very transparent. And some will be able to dedicate a couple – an hour or two a week. Some may do more. All we're asking is for people – we're so thankful for the team that we've built. And as people may not be able to do it anymore, we'll
put new ambassadors in, but it's a really great group, and I'm really happy with what's happened so far. It's only been a few months, and I look forward to see what's to come. I'm the chair. I'm not assigned to a specific neighborhood, but my contact information is on the ambassador page, and I welcome anyone who has ideas, thoughts, questions, issues to contact me anytime, too. Well, you know, I hate to say it, but it's that time again.
It is. So, you know, I want to thank Melva, Mae and Brianna. Thank you both for joining us, Method Happenings. I really think this is going to be a great program. Wish you both continued success. Thank you. And whatever you guys decide to do. Really. Thank you. You too.
Thank you for joining us. Thank you so much. And we're available for you. If you need anything we can do for you, let us know as far as the program. I'll be back. Yeah, no, let us know. We're here for you. I have a couple issues I want to talk about this summer. That's fine. That's fine. That's fine. Unless you don't have the air conditioning in here, then. I know. That is the only thing, usually. Oh, good. I'm kidding. I'm kidding. No, no, it is. It's awfully hot in this studio. That's just the way it is.
all the lights. All right, so I also want to take a minute, of course, to thank everyone who has been watching the show. Thank you for your feedback. We're getting a lot of feedback. If you would like to appear on the show,
please just contact us at Method Happenings 02155 or 02155 I should say at gmail.com. You will be able to watch replays of this program on Method Community Media Access Channel
Please check out our website MethodHappenings.com where you can now either view, listen, download. There's a podcast of this program. There's a lot going on with Method Happenings. And also you can find all of our shows on YouTube. Just go to YouTube.com and search for Method Happenings. Please like and subscribe to our channel and videos.
This is getting longer and longer. You can also find us on Facebook at Method Happenings, and we also have our own subreddit. And you can find us at reddit.com slash R slash Method Happenings. For the Method Happenings team,
For Paul, Marco, Bruce, James, Joe, I am John Petralla. And remember Method, please stay informed. Great show. Great. It went great. Thank you.
Ta-da!