and through the wood to Grandmother's house we go.
The horse knows the way to carry the sleigh through the white and drifted snow.
Over the river and through the wood, oh, how the wind does blow.
It stings the toes and bites the nose as over the grass
Welcome to Looking Back at Metro History.
I'm Laura Duggan, your hostess.
This is our Christmas special 2025.
As you know, we always like to go to the North Pole this time of year and interview the folks up there who are busily getting ready for Christmas.
I recently got a text from Mrs. Claus saying that Santa's two brothers, do you remember them, Elvis Claus and Brady Claus, will be coming back again to visit Big Brother Santa.
Frequent viewers of this show have probably recalled that last year the Claus brothers had a big reunion.
And if you didn't see it, you can still see it by going to metfordtv.org and then watch it there.
Anyway, Ade, are you ready to go to the North Pole with me and do the filming?
Yeah.
Oh, good.
Let me get my my coat on.
It's pretty cold up there, as you do.
Yeah.
Like your coat.
Wow.
That's a nice one.
Are you ready?
See?
Almost ready, gonna zip up here.
Gotta make sure my collar's right.
I wanna look good.
All right, there we go.
All righty.
Now, let me bring up the World Travel app.
Okay.
N-O-R-A-V-E.
T-H, space, P-O-L-E.
Ready, Day?
Yep.
We're here.
I think Santa's house is just over the ridge over there.
Okay.
Come on.
Let's get going.
Just a little further.
We're almost there.
I hope.
Just over the ridge.
I know where it is.
Still there?
I should have worn my snowboots.
Almost there maybe?
I hope so.
Oh, here we are.
Why do you ring the doorbell?
Oh, hello, Laura and Jay.
So nice to see you again.
Hello again.
Has Santa's brothers arrived yet?
No, not yet.
Would you, Laura and Jay, would you like some hot chocolate?
I sure would.
Yep.
Well, here are some snickerdoodle cookies for you and Santa.
Thank you so much.
You know how Santa just loves these cookies.
Let me get you some hot chocolate.
I'll be right back.
Dave, are you getting all of this?
Ho, ho, ho.
Well, hello, Laura.
Hello, Dave.
So good to see you again.
You too, Santa.
I brought day as well as my wish list.
I didn't want it to get lost in the mail.
Oh, it's shorter than last year.
Have you been a good girl this year, Laura?
I'm always good.
Here I come with a hot chocolate.
Oh, let me take a look at that.
Oh, Santa, I would like, yes, one of those, too.
Can I have that, too?
Christmas is coming.
You know I'm always good and jolly with you.
We're jolly.
Yes.
Oh, yes.
And one of those, too.
Yes, one of those.
Oh, dear.
Here's your hot chocolate.
Have a good day.
Thank you.
Oh, and here's the other one.
Okay.
All right.
We'll go put this away.
Such a list.
Santa, I can't wait to see your brothers again.
What are they expected?
They should be here any minute.
Ooh, that must be them.
Get ready, Day.
Yeah, that's how you do it.
That's how you do it.
Good to see you guys.
Absolutely, catch that ball.
Two hands.
So glad you could come back here.
We've all had our last Christmas.
Oh, right.
Nice to see you.
Good to see you, too.
Hug.
The Claus Brothers.
Day, are you getting all of this?
Yep.
Oh, yeah.
I'm glad you came, but man, this is my busiest time of the year.
You picked a great time, but I'm busy.
But I'll spend time with you guys.
Well, you're busy too.
You're all over the place.
That's right.
I tour all over the world.
And I'm telling you, I got to play gig after gig.
And you just got this one gig, one night of the year.
And what about you in the playoffs?
Yeah, we got the bills coming up.
We got to kick their butts.
But I appreciate it.
And I'm here for you guys.
Listen, you guys couldn't do what I do.
I'm telling you, one year and one night.
In preparation, I'll tell you this.
You guys try and do my job for one week.
and I'll give you the easiest part of my job.
What's that?
Maybe wrap some presents, you know, get the sleigh ready.
One week.
Our revolution has an entire genre of music.
I think I can drop off a couple packages.
Well, you know, Mrs. Claus and I haven't had a vacation in 400 years.
We could certainly use a nice little trip somewhere.
How about it?
You guys take over one week.
We can do it.
How about this?
We mine the store up here in the chilly North Pole, and you head down to where I filmed one of my movies, The Beautiful Island Nation of Hawaii.
Mrs. Claus?
Aloha, aloha.
Pack your bags.
Oh, the manual.
The boys need this manual.
Read this thoroughly before you do any of your chores.
Okay.
Okay?
He's all in the manual.
Not a problem.
Piece of cake.
Get your bags back.
I just packed a few things.
A few?
Come on, darling.
You got your rock collection in here?
Go on, I know.
We're going this way.
Hawaii's that way.
Bye, guys.
Aloha.
Bye.
Take care, brother and sister-in-law.
That's it.
How about a song?
I think we could do a song.
How about this one?
Love me tender, love me true.
I will save Christmas with you.
I love how you just make stuff up.
Oh, thank you.
Thank you very much.
But maybe, maybe we should focus up and huddle up on what our first course of action would be, brother.
I think all we got to do is we got to get that reindeer and the sleigh and do the magic to get them flying all over the world.
We can do that.
It's not a big deal.
We just came in from the chilly cold.
Why don't we start with something a little warmer, like wrapping those beautiful presents.
Oh, I can do that blindfolded.
Not a big deal.
All righty.
Claus Brothers, high five.
That's it.
Be naughty or be nice.
Be on this list.
Let's get to Christmas wrapping.
You got it, bro.
Oh.
Trying to wrap some presents.
Don't know what to do.
I think we're so lost, I think we need more glue.
Hey bro, you know how to do a ribbon?
Tie a bow?
How do you do this?
I always had my stage hands help me with the ribbons and all my festoonments.
Listen.
We're caught in a trap.
I can't gift wrap.
I think I taped it too much, Brady.
How's that?
These are not up to our standards.
Really?
Well, I think I have to call an audible then.
We're going to have to do this later or find someone to help us.
Let's see what the manual says here.
He says, we're really in charge of Santa's sleigh, that we really should line up Santa's sleigh.
Step one, we need to line up the reindeer and then hook them up to each other.
Let's do that part of it.
We can do that, can't we?
I think so, brother.
All right.
We can manage that.
Let's do that.
I used to have a bunch of gorgeous horses, and reindeer are just horses with a hood ornament on top.
I'll round up those galloping beauties.
and you get the sleigh ready to rock and roll!
Rock and roll baby!
Okay big brother, I've got these reindeer all lined up.
All right, let's look at the playbook here and see what the next thing is.
Step three is crack the whip and we soar into the sky.
Sounds good.
Here you go, brother.
There's the whip.
All right.
Red.
Green.
Forty-two.
Set.
Hike.
On Dasher.
On Dancer.
On Prancer.
On Vixen.
This is not good.
What in the tinsel tossing tarnation was that?
The reindeer just gave our sleigh the slip.
Step one, we line up the reindeer.
Checkerino.
Step three, we crack the whip, right?
Checkeroonie.
We forgot step two.
We didn't hook them up to the sleigh.
Oh, checka whoopsie.
Don't be cruel to me, brother, for totally fumbling the ball at the end zone there.
Oh.
I'm the guy that screwed up there.
I gronked it.
I'm sorry.
No.
We gotta call.
We gotta call him.
We gotta give him a little jingle jangle on his Santa phone.
Oh, brother.
We're in the soup now.
Boy, this Hawaii is great, isn't it, honey?
Oh, it sure is.
I'm having such a good time.
We should do this more often.
Absolutely.
Thank God for my brothers, huh?
Oh, yes.
Yeah.
It's the phone.
I better get it.
Hello?
Hi, guys.
What's up?
What do you mean, you lost the reindeer?
and you're having trouble wrapping the gifts.
Well, the elves have a very high standard, you know.
You want us to come back.
Let me ask Mrs. Claus, because she's having a wonderful time.
Honey, the boys want us to return.
They're having problems.
Well, you tell those two brothers of yours.
They're on their own.
We have a week, and we're going to keep the week.
By the way, I have to work on my tan.
You know that, dear.
And later, I have to get my nails done.
Red, of course, of course.
And oh my goodness, I have a lesson.
It's a surfing lesson with the Duke.
I'll see you later.
Bye.
I don't know if you heard that, guys, but you're out of luck.
You gotta figure it out.
Did you use the manual?
I left you the manual.
Did you use it?
You did.
But you left out a part or two.
We'll see you in another week.
Good luck.
They thought my job was easy.
Bartender.
GJ, things look bad here up at the North Pole.
Do you think Christmas might get canceled?
Yep.
Maybe I can get help.
Fortunately, Christmas isn't here yet.
If we can just hold things together till Santa gets back.
What if we beam up some more helpers from around the world?
I have my special world travel app on my laptop.
I'll beam up some Norwegians to round up the reindeer.
And for wrapping the presents, how about some folks from Macy's gift wrap department?
Let's give it a try.
We're back!
What a relief.
There you go.
One for you.
Didn't want to mess your hair.
Aloha, aloha.
We're so happy to see you, brother.
Well, I gotta admit, you guys really did a good job.
You know, I had my doubts, and I must apologize.
The elves loved you guys.
You did a great job.
Great job.
Teamwork, that's what it's all about.
But it's good to get home.
Yes it is.
It's good to get home.
And I think I can speak for both of us in that we wouldn't have been able to do this if it wasn't for the help of Laura and Day.
All the way from Medford Community Media.
Thank you girls, thank you, thank you.
Thank you, thank you very much.
So maybe next year too?
let's do it all right all right but it's not that easy is it it's not that easy a job is it
No, but we love it.
We love it.
We want to help the kids.
We want to help the community.
We want to help bring love and joy to the world.
And I told Mrs. Claus I want a football for Christmas so I can practice for next year.
No more fumbling.
It is so wonderful to see all the Claus brothers getting along so nicely, especially on Christmas.
What better way to kick off this moment of brotherly harmony than with a little music?
Oh yeah!
You have a tune for us, bro?
Why don't we sing Blue Christmas here?
Oh, one of my favorites.
Here we go.
And a one, and a two, and a Christmas, here we go.
I'll have a blue Christmas without you.
I'll be so blue just thinking about you.
Decorations were red on a green Christmas tree.
Won't be the same, dear, if you're not here with me.
Some of those blue snowflakes are falling.
That's when those blue memories start calling.
You'll be doing all right with your Christmas of white.
And I'll have a blue
Blue, blue, blue Christmas for us!
Yay!
We got it!
Merry Christmas!
Day, it's time to get back to the station.
Here we go!
Oh, that was great.
It's always wonderful to see family members getting along, especially around Christmas.
I agree.
No, yup.
Thanks, Day.
All right.
Thanks for filming.
Now it's time to read one of my favorite books, The Night Before Christmas by Clement C. Moore.
Everyone get comfortable out there in TV land.
"'Twas the night before Christmas, when all through the house, not a creature was stirring, not even a mouse.
The stockings were hung by the chimney with care in hopes that St.
Nicholas soon would be there.
The children were nestled all snug in their beds while visions of sugar plums danced in their heads.
And Mama in her kerchief and I in my cap had just settled our brains for a long winter's nap.
When out of the lawn there rose such a clatter, I sprang from the bed to see what was the matter.
Away to the window I flew like a flash, tore open the shutters and threw up the sash.
The moon on the breast of the new fallen snow gave the luster of midday to objects below, when what to my wondering eyes should appear but a miniature sleigh and a tiny reindeer.
When a little old driver so lively and quick
I knew in a moment it must be Sank Nick.
More rapid than eagles, his coursers they came, and he whistled and shouted and called them by name.
Now Dasher, now Dancer, now Prancer and Bixen, on Comet, on Cupid, on Dancer and Blitzen, on top of the porch, on top of the wall, to the top of the wall, now dash away, dash away, dash away all.
as dry leaves that before the wild hurricane fly, when they meet with an obstacle, mount to the sky.
So up to the housetop, the coursers, they flew with a sleigh full of toys and St.
Nicholas too.
And then in a twinkling, I heard on the roof, the prancing and pawing of each little hoof.
As I drew in my head and was turning around, down the chimney, St.
Nicholas came with a bound.
He was dressed all in fur from his head to his foot, and his clothes were all tarnished with ashes and soot.
A bundle of toys he had flung on his back, and he looked like a peddler just opening his path.
His eyes, how they twinkled!
His dimples, how merry!
His cheeps were like roses, his nose like a cherry.
His droll little mouth was drawn up like a bow, and the beard on his chin was as white as the snow.
The stump of a pipe he held tight in his teeth, and the smoke had encircled his head like a wreath.
He had a broad face and a little round belly that shook when he laughed like a bowl full of jelly.
Ho!
He was chubby and plump, a right jolly old elf.
And I laughed when I saw him in spite of myself.
A wink of his eye and a twist of his head soon gave me to know I had nothing to dread.
He spoke not a word, but went straight to his work, and filled all the stockings, then turned with a jerk, and laying his finger aside of his nose, and giving a nod, up the chimney he rose.
He sprang to his sleigh, to his team gave a whistle, and away they all flew, like the down of a thistle.
But I heard him exclaim, ere he rode out of sight.
Happy Christmas to all, and to all a good night.
Did all of you enjoy that as much as I did?
Now it's time to say goodbye.
This is Laura Duggan, your hostess, hoping to see you again on Looking Back at Medford History.
and I and everyone here at Metro Community Media want to wish all a very merry Christmas and a happy new year.
♪ Oh well those blue snowflakes are falling ♪ ♪ That's when those blue memories start calling ♪
We'll be doing all right with your Christmas up wide.
And I'll have a blue, blue, blue, blue Christmas.
We got it!
Merry Christmas everybody!