Thirty-fifth regular meeting of the Medford City Council will come to order. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Camuso? Present. Councilor Caviello? Present. Councilor Knight? Present. Vice-President Leonard-Curran? Present. Councilor Marks? Present. Councilor Penta? Present. President Del Rosso? Present. Seven members present, none absent. Please rise and join me in saluting the flag.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America and to the Republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all. 15-758 offered by Councilor Knight, be it resolved the Council President establish and appoint an ad hoc CPA subcommittee to work on the implementation of the voter approved Community Preservation Act
Chair recognizes Councilor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much. As we are all well aware, several weeks ago, the Community Preservation Act was passed by way of ballot question. The next step in the process would be for the Medford City Council to establish a Community Preservation Commission, Mr. President. I've been on the phone with the Community Preservation Coalition, which is a
an organization that helps administer the setup of the community preservation committees. And, um, I bring this resolution forward so that we can sit down and invite them to join us and provide us with some technical expertise as to how to move forward in this endeavor. Very good. So on the motion of approved by council and I, councilor Penta. One of the unfortunate things about this past election, it's over 3000 people didn't have an opportunity to vote on this because they weren't either instructed or they failed to turn over their ballot.
which basically would have enlightened us as to what was the real true feeling of the folks here within this community, recognizing that it was a tax on top of the tax that they were already paying. So I would hope when, when, and if in fact this committee ever does take place, um, that a complete explanation as to this five year commitment that needs to take place by the city. Um, and unfortunately the taxpayers will not have an opportunity to have a choice. It'll be the committee.
that will be appointed, they don't make that choice. So the vote that took place this past November gave no indication as to what, if any, this money was going to be used for. And more importantly, and most importantly, the guarantee from the state is only at 18 percent. It's not at 100 percent. And as a result of that, taxpayers for the next five years and this year happens to be the lowest of all the years that CPA, since it's been around since 2001, it's the lowest it's ever been.
And if it continues to go in this mainstream, the taxpayers of this community are going to wind up paying for something that they never got their commitment back from the commonwealth. So unfortunately, the misinformation that went out there, the guarantee of the money coming back from the state is absolutely not there. The fact that it's a five-year commitment and the fact that almost 3,000 people failed to vote on this because they either not instructed or they didn't turn that ballot over, I just don't think it's a real true indication.
of where the city wants to go on having another tax on top of a tax. Thank you. Mr. President, if I may. Councillor Knight. I bring the resolution forward because it's our duty, based upon the legislation that was passed by the voters. This is by no way a referendum on whether or not this ballot question was a good question, a bad question, or anything else. The fact of the matter is, the question was on the ballot, the question passed, and now the ball's in our court.
to move forward and implement, Mr. President. I know Councilor Pinto was very supportive of this endeavor back in 2001, I believe. He actually brought this paper to the table and asked the council to vote in favor of it at that point in time. So, Mr. President, I'd ask that the committee be set up, that there's no need for further debate. This is the next step in the process. It is what it is. You know, the vote passed, the vote passed. And now it's on us to move forward and be sure that we take the appropriate steps and meet our obligation and our duty and do what we were elected to do. Thank you very much, Councilor Knight.
One of the things that the taxpayers need to be aware of is the fact that, yes, while it might have won by some 1,200 votes and 3,000 people didn't vote for it, the fact of the matter is they didn't have an opportunity to know what they were going to be voting for and on. That's the difference between now and 2001. So whenever this committee is set up,
I think they really need to have a full-fledged understanding of maybe having some public meetings to take place to get an idea, and the five categories that are out there that it's offering, what the money can and will be used for, not because of the decision of a nine-member committee. That's what I'm trying to say. That's the difference between then and now, and that's a big difference. Again, Mr. President, I think that the committee would be tasked with the function as to determine how many public hearings are going to happen, what the process is going to be. I think that that's something that should be done as a community, as a group.
with a number of people putting their heads together to determine what the best practices are, Mr. President. So I'd ask my council colleagues to support the resolution. On the motion of approval by Councillor Adam Knight, citizen, you'd like to speak, please say your name and address for the record. Welcome. Thank you, Mr. President. I'm Robert Capucci of 71 Evans Street. And speaking specifically to the agenda item that Councillor Knight brought up,
What you'll be voting for is a subcommittee to discuss how this City Council is going to go ahead now that this vote is passed. And my question, Mr. President, I guess to Councilor Knight, through you, the Chair, is will this subcommittee be a public meeting that everyone can attend? I can answer that if you'd like, but we'll allow Councilor Knight to answer that question.
matters of open meeting laws? The easy answer to that question, Mr. President, is yes. Thank you very much, Mr. President. Thank you. Further to, Mr. President, please, if I could. If I understand this law correctly, another question would be, in listening to Councilor Knight speak, is that this body now sets up that full nine-member
committee, and from the way I understand it, it's a nine-member seat. Five of the seats are already preordained from various departments, like environment. But the other four seats is what this body has power and control over. As to how. Point of information, Mr. President, that is inaccurate. That is inaccurate, Mr. President. If you look at section 5A of the CPA statute,
The CPC must consist of at least five members. The council has the ability to establish four more at-large members. We don't have to. It all depends on what the committee wants to do. It's not up to the council to determine whether, it's up to the council to determine whether or not they would like to have five members, six members, seven members, eight members, nine members, ten members. Well, not ten. It goes up to nine. But Mr. President, so that's actually not the case. The council doesn't have to have nine. It can have five plus one. It can have five plus two.
But again, I think that it's in the best interest of the community. If the chair understood the motion correctly, this is a motion to establish a committee to begin the process. Correct. This is not the final committee. Right. And this is not the end of the end of the end. Yeah, exactly. And I think that the reason that we're putting this committee together is to determine what direction we want to go in. Each community that
adopts the Community Preservation Act is required to establish a community preservation committee, and that is a function of the legislative body, Mr. President. So instead of us unilaterally doing that, I think it would make more sense for us to have a subcommittee that's in place that has members of the community that are also willing to participate and be involved and help us craft something that works for everybody. Very good. If I could, Mr. President, this is, again,
part of the misinformation that went out to their counselor, Penta was speaking on the director of preserve Medford, who was one of the lead advocates of this CPA told me personally that what has to happen now by the law is a nine member panel has to be formed in five of those people are already coming from various departments. Now I'm getting different information from counselor night tonight. So it's a very,
Very confusing thing. And it's very taxing on the citizens. Mr. President, if the messenger would like, I can share a copy of the document with the gentleman. I would like that very much. Mr. Messenger, if you could convey that copy. Mr. Messenger? Absolutely. Thank you. Thank you, Mr. President.
Good evening. Please state your name and address for the record. Thank you. Jones here for DC to Road North. I just have a point of information for the council. Um, just with respect to the, uh, the amount of, um, matching funds from the state this year, I'm reading off the community preservation website dated November 17th, 2015.
The Massachusetts Department of Revenue has released a community preservation trust fund distribution for each CPA municipality. This is for this year. All CPA communities will receive a 29.7% match on round one of the trust fund distribution this year. Thank you very much. Thank you. Thank you. On the motion of approval by Councilor Knight, all those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Roll call vote, Mr. President.
Councilor requests a roll call vote. Mr. Clerk, if you would please call the roll. Councilor Camuso? Yes. Councilor Caviello? Yes. Councilor Knight? Yes. Vice President Longo Kern? Yes. Councilor Marks? Yes. Councilor Penta? Yes. President DelaRusso? Yes. On the vote of seven in the affirmative, none in the negative, the motion passes. Now item number 15759, offered by Councilor Knight. Be it so ordained that the City of Medford adopt the provisions
of Massachusetts General Law, Chapter 68, Section 9, entitled, Deferral of Excise Tax Due by Massachusetts National Guard Members and Reservists on Active Duty and Dependents. Chair recognizes Councilor Knight. Mr. President, thank you very much. Presently in the city of Medford, I have passed out to all the members here a printout from the city's website.
And it would say, when are payments due for motor vehicle excise tax? Payment of the motor vehicle excise tax is due within 30 days from the date the excise bill is issued. A person who does not receive a bill is still liable for the excise plus any interest charges accrued. Therefore, it's important to keep the registry and the post office informed of current names and addresses so excise bills can be delivered promptly. All owners of motor vehicles must pay an excise tax. Therefore, it is the responsibility of the owner to contact the treasurer's collector's office if you have not received a bill.
If an excise tax is not paid within 30 days from the issue date, the amount will be assessed a $5 demand charge plus interest. If payment in full, including the demand charge, is not received within 14 days of the date issued, a warrant with additional charges will be issued. Warrants are turned over to the Deputy Collector Kelly Ryan and Associates for further collection and registry action. Mr. President, Chapter 68, Section 9 of the General Laws reads, in any town accepting the provisions of this section and notwithstanding any other provision of this chapter to the contrary,
Any excise due under this chapter by a member of the Massachusetts National Guard or Reservist or a dependent of a member of the Massachusetts National Guard or Reservist shall be deferred while that member is on active service outside the Commonwealth and for a period of up to 180 days after the completion of that service. No interest or penalty shall be assessed for any period before the expiration of the 180 days. Mr. President, a vote for this is a vote for our veterans, a vote for those that service our country, Mr. President.
It's a deferral of their excise tax that's going to be due them if they are deployed, if they are out of the Commonwealth of Massachusetts for a period of time for which their excise taxes due. It doesn't cost anything to the bottom line, Mr. President. At the end of the day, the excise tax responsibility still lies within the individual.
However, I think that it would make sense for us to adopt this provision, considering if we have a resident in the city of Medford who is a National Guardsman who has been deployed to Iraq and their car is sitting in the driveway and their affairs are up in the air and not in quite great order because they're deployed overseas and their family life has been affected dramatically because of this. This is the least we can do, Mr. President, to provide them with some relief until they return and get their affairs in order. So, with that being said, Mr. President, I'd ask that my council colleagues support this resolution, and I'd ask for a roll call vote.
On the motion approved by Councillor Knight, chair recognizes Councillor Camuso. Thank you, Mr. President, and I definitely support this this evening and I want to applaud Councillor Knight for bringing this forward. You know, all too often everyone sits behind this rail and in other elected positions throughout the Commonwealth. We say we're father veterans and we stand proudly with the veterans on Veterans Day and on Memorial Day. We honor the sacrifice that many have made. But this is a real tangible piece of
legislation that this council can stand behind boldly and send the message loud and clear that we're walking the walk, not just talking the talk when it comes to supporting the veterans. So on behalf of the local veterans, I'd like to thank Councilor Knight for bringing this up and I support it wholeheartedly. Mr. President, I've got no problem supporting it. I'd like to put a B paper attached to that because is there any kind of a law that exists out there that
holds and abeyance any service person's mortgage payments until such time that they come back home? Because sometimes if an individual goes overseas or is in the service and he has a family here and they just can't meet the financial obligations that are required of a mortgage payment, just like we're doing with the excise tax and the cars, is there any kind of law out there? Can we get an answer back? Is there some kind of law that holds and abeyance mortgage payments until such time as the service person comes back?
Mortgage payments or property tax payments, Councillor? Mortgage payments on their home. That's not a function of the council. That's not a function of the local government. That's why I asked for clarification. It may not be a function of the council, but it's a function if they have mortgage payments and then if the city wants to be generous enough, they can turn around and take their property tax assessment, whatever it might be. Right now, we have so many servicemen, not only are coming home,
that have post-traumatic stress, that have physical infirmities, that they have so many disabilities that are confronting them, you know, and our government on a wholesale basis is just putting a lot of this stuff on hold while they're talking about bringing in, you know, illegal refugees and
things of that nature. But if we're going to take care of people within our own community, I think we should look at what can be beneficial to them. And if it means filing a piece of legislation, then so be it, whether it's a property tax reduction or hold that in abatement or even a mortgage, um, uh, holding a mortgage in abatement, whatever it might be, they deserve to have that benefit, uh, available to them. Move for approval. Roll call vote, Mr. President. Move approval. Uh, the motion for approval on council,
Knight's motion. What were you, were you an amendment to this? Yeah. Chair recognizes Councilor Marks. I was just wondering, Mr. President, uh, if, uh, anyone in the national guard or reserve is now currently have to register with our office, our local veterans office.
just say before they go overseas. Is there a process in place now where at least we know who is actively involved, maybe overseas and so forth? I think, if I may say anecdotally, I think in the process of deployment, the local veterans agent is notified by the deploying agency, whether it be National Guard, Army, Army Reserve, Navy, et cetera. So we may be able to get a number from Ernest Lindsay on
uh, the number of veterans. Um, certainly he has an accurate accounting. I'd like, I think this is a very worthy, uh, uh, resolution offered by council at night. Uh, I would like to see if we can get, uh, the potential deferral impact on the community. Um, it may be small in nature, but I think it's worthwhile to take,
I'll look at and see what that number may be. And also, if we can get some feedback from Ernest Lindsay, our Veterans Administrator in the city, to see how many, if they do register with the Veterans Office when they go overseas, and also if members of the National Guard are all registered with the Veterans Office, or how does that work? I'm honestly not sure. So, you know, I think that'd be interesting to find out.
So can we add that as an amendment to the paper? Absolutely. Mr. President, the impact, it would be a zero sum impact because the obligation to pay the excise tax would still remain. It would just be deferred until their return and it, um, penalties and interest couldn't accrue until after the 180th day of their return. Right. So, so in essence,
the financial impact would be zero because they'd be getting the same amount of excise that they would be getting if, in fact, the person wasn't deployed and was here. The only loss that we're seeing is on penalties and interest. So we're just not penalizing an individual for being deployed and servicing the country while, you know, they're not able to be here and pay the excise. Right. But if they're overseas for an extended period of time, we run our budgets year by year. So if there's a large amount of deferrals in a particular year, that does impact the budget.
I'm not sure what the number is. It may be very small in nature, but it would impact the budget. And I'm just asking that we get a copy from Mr. Pomp, maybe the treasurer collector's office or Ann Baker on the potential impact. This is a great resolution. Point of clarification of Madam Vice President. I just saw it differently. I thought I would, I would see an impact to the budget, but I would think it would be minimal. Um,
So I'm not sure what you're saying. It's deferred, but that time that they're overseas, they don't have to pay for. So there is a period that the city will be losing a minimal impact amount of money. The money's still due. If I say that your bill's due on January, excise tax comes out. So January, your excise tax gets levied. It's due by February 2. But I'm deployed. I'm overseas, or I'm out of state, for that matter. Legislation just speaks for being out of state. So I'm out of state. I'm at Fort Bragg.
And I'm at Fort Bragg until June. I come back on June 3rd. I have 188 days, 180 days from June 3rd in order to pay the excise tax before I will be fined and assessed penalties. And I'm telling you, I read it differently. I read that they don't have to pay while they're overseas and it's just that portion is deferred. You don't have to pay period and then you start for the 180 days. So there will be an impact to the budget. It will just be very minimal.
how many people, you know. Well, that's what we're going to find out. Yeah. I read that differently. Very good. Counselors, Mr. Capucci, if you would, please just again, state your name and address for the record. Thank you, Mr. President. Robert Capucci, 71 Evans street. Uh, as a veteran of the army reserves, I can, I can tell you firsthand what happens with a lot of these reservists, the national guards is,
they either sign the title over to a family member, they take their car off the road, and the minimal impact would be just that. This is a great resolution and idea, but if you really wanted to make an impact on these soldiers' lives, instead of deferring their excise tax, which they probably already made arrangements for to defer themselves,
There's a long list of other taxes in the cities that could be deferred. This new CPA tax surcharge, for instance, the water tax, the property tax. If you want to really do something for these soldiers, look in that area, because this is, with all due respect, a lot of bark with no bite. Thank you, Mr. President. On the motion for approval, Councillor Knight. This law's been on the books for quite a period of time. The City of Medford has not adopted it.
We have a local option. I feel as though it would make perfectly good sense for us to adopt this local option, Mr. President. Bark or bite, decide. It's something that's going to help people, and it's something that I support. Thank you, Councillor. So on the motion for approval of the B paper offered by Councillor Penta as amended by Councillor Marks, all those in favour? All those opposed? Motion carried. And on the main motion offered by Councillor
night. Uh, does that require a roll call? It does as it ordained. So, uh, Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Camuso. Yes. Councilor Caviello. Yes. Councilor Knight. Yes. Vice-President Long-Term. Yes. Councilor Mox. Yes. Councilor Penta. Yes. President DelaRusso. Yes. With a vote of seven in the affirmative, none in the negative. The, uh, order passes.
15-760, offered by vice president Longo Kern, be resolved that the council be provided with the last three years, including 2014, certified free cash numbers. Thank you, madam vice president. Thank you, president de la russo. Last year we asked for the preceding three years with regards to certified free cash. I believe we had the last five years. So I'm just looking for
My main request has to do with certified free cash numbers that probably came in sometime this month for 2014, which is the number that we obviously didn't have last year. Because I know we were averaging, it was anywhere from 500,000 to a million and a half that we're putting into free cash from any given year's budget within the last five years. So I want to know, since tax discussions will be coming up in December,
Next Tuesday, I believe, I'd like to have that number, if we could, what was certified free cash for the last three to five years. If I could just amend this, three to five years, so we can make an educated decision when it comes to our decision that we need to make before the end of the year.
Madam Vice President, as amended by the Vice President, all those in favor? All those opposed? The motion carries. 15-761, offered by Vice President Longo Kern. Be it resolved that the fire chief provides the council with an update on the work that has been completed on the fire stations while under warranty. Madam Vice President. Thank you, President De La Rousseau.
We had discussions about this. I brought this up last week. There was a warranty for all the work that was done. The million point three that went out to bond with regards to improvements at the fire stations and the fact that I've had trouble with it with regards to where the warranty is concerned. So if we could get an update and see what work has been done
What work has been requested of the contractors or anybody who's done any work on the fire stations within the last year and how have they been improved upon or updated or made sure that the warranty is taken advantage of? Because I know we only had a one-year warranty on that. So if we could just get an update on what has been done under that warranty the last six months to a year.
Thank you. And I support this. Thank you, counsel. If she doesn't mind, I'd like to make a B paper that is in line with the fire department, but the new pieces of apparatus that were just purchased over the last 12 months, the rear step on the truck, unless you wear a size 4.5 shoe,
you can't safely do your job when you have to pull hose and stuff off of the back of the truck. It's about a thousand dollar part, I'm being told, I have not confirmed that, to extend the bumper so that a fire department personnel can safely stand on the rear step of these trucks. If we could ask the fire chief to look into it and to get this fixed. In the interest of public safety,
because, uh, this, this is certainly an issue I saw it firsthand down at engine two and, uh, someone's going to get injured. Very good. We'll do that as an amendment if it's all right. So, uh, on the motion of, uh, vice-president Longo Kern as amended, all those in favor, all those in favor motion carries 15 dash seven, six, two offered by a vice-president Longo Kern be resolved at the Medford city council, not approved.
of any bond or expenditure that does not have a written explanation of such expenditure at least seven days prior to said vote. Madam Vice President. Thank you, President De La Russo. I just think we need to, we have a new administration coming in January. We have two new city councilors who are coming on board. And I think we just need to set an example and make a strong recommendation or request of the administration going forward that we
When a bond is before us, you know, we had over about $800,000 in bonds before us last week with barely minimal paperwork. Two of the three, we had absolutely nothing in front of us to review, digest, ask questions on. We're basically somebody, you know, thankfully Louise was here, Ms. Miller was here to discuss them.
But we had nothing in writing. I was scrambling to take notes. I was scrambling to decide whether a $200,000, $300,000 expenditure was going to be a good one or a bad one. And it's something that you can't do on the spot. You can't even do it an hour or two beforehand. I personally would like at least seven days to digest and review. Time after time after time, we have the administration before us telling us how it's
It's in dire need to be passed. It's urgent if we don't pass it. And we get the A, B, C, D, and E, and F of why, if we don't pass it, it's going to not be good for the city. And I just really want to move forward making educated decisions. I think all seven of us need to be able to have paperwork in front of us explaining whether it's $100,000 or $3 million, we need
to have the paperwork in front of us to make an educated decision. And I think if the seven of us stick together and the new seven in January stick together and really make that, make our voices heard that that's the way, you know, business should operate. That's the way a city should operate. That's the way, you know, the respect we should get because we are the ones that respond to constituents. We are the ones that have to explain.
and understand the vote we're taking, and I think it's very important that we get the paperwork beforehand. Even if it's the Friday before a Tuesday meeting, that's better than nothing. I mean, last week we had hundreds of thousands of dollars that they wanted us to vote on, and we did not have anything in front of us besides a one-liner saying, please approve of this $200,000 bond initiative. You know, that's on the backs of the taxpayers. That's on the backs — our children will be paying that money back.
because some of these bonds go into, you know, 20 years from now, people will still be paying them back. We need to be able to get some documentation in support and be able to do our own research, be able to look into the numbers ourselves. You know, I, for one counselor, keep at least two to three years' worth of budget books in my office at home. You know, I have to be able to digest something, not just talk about it and vote on it 10 minutes later.
And the whole issue with, you know, just scrambling, the administration scrambling to get the fourth vote, I think it's a disservice to the taxpayer. And I just hope it stops, and I hope we send a message that we, it's a no-brainer. Just give us some documentation one week prior to a vote so we can call and ask questions if we need to, so we can get our questions ready for the Tuesday night, and we can make an educated decision. And I just want to, I'm trying to hammer it home because it's really important, and I'm
starting to get very frustrated and I hope that, you know, our two new counselors hear me loud and clear as well and just demand the respect and demand it for the taxpayer and the rate payers and the citizens of this community and our children who will be paying back these bonds. So, I just ask for approval. I ask for a roll call vote and I just think it's important. Thank you. Thank you, Madam Vice President. Chair recognizes Councilor Knight. Mr. President, I, too,
I think that this is a good resolution in theory. However, in application, I think that there might be another way that we can do it that will not rely on us sticking together. It won't rely on an us versus them mentality, Mr. President. That would be a change of our city council rules. And maybe if we change the rules so that no paper related to a bond or expenditure shall be introduced to our agenda.
unless we are in receipt of the paper seven days before and in writing. That will take the ambiguousness out of it. That will take the reliance on other members out of it. I think that we'd also have a concern, Mr. President, we really can't preclude somebody as a member of the body from voting on a paper that they want to vote on unless we use parliamentary procedure. You know, tabling at section 22 and at section 20.4, which we learned a little bit about a couple weeks ago.
So with that being said, Mr. President, I certainly agree with Councilor Longo. I agree with everything she's saying. However, I think there might be a stronger mechanism in order for us to implement such. So I'd ask that the matter be referred to the Rules Committee for construction of a rule that would govern the City Council and govern and dictate how money papers are going to be introduced to our agenda. If we don't get the seven-day explanation, if we don't get the explanation within seven days, it doesn't get put on the agenda.
If matter doesn't get in the agenda, it never reaches the floor. If it never reaches the floor, it doesn't reach a vote. And if it doesn't reach a vote, the expense doesn't get expended. Thank you, Counselor. Chair recognizes Counselor Pinto. Mr. President, we already have a rule. It's rule number 20, disposition of all items appearing upon the council agenda. And referring back to what Counselor Alongo-Curran has just alluded to, I agree with her 100%. Section number four under rule 20 states that any financial paper appearing on the council agenda for the first time
shall be automatically laid on the table for one week when such action is requested by any councillor. Common sense would tell you that we did this a couple of weeks ago because we got over $800,000 worth of a paper in front of the papers, three separate papers, to be voted upon. And as a result of that, since we had received nothing in our informational packet on a Friday afternoon, we had laid that on the table with the hopes that we would get more and further information the following Tuesday, which was this past Tuesday evening.
Here it is again now the third Tuesday in a row. And again, asked for the information. And then we did not receive one scintilla, one document, anything that represents itself regarding those three papers. So the council rules are obviously in operation. And after the seven days, if you've called a rule seven, a rule number four, excuse me, on the section four under rule 20, I apologize. You'll be able to have any one council say, listen, we haven't gotten the paperwork in front of us, you know, and we're not going to entertain this any further until such time it comes.
You already have the rules there. Sending it to the Rules Committee is nothing more than another delay tactic. You already have it. It's built into your rules. And common sense will tell you, if the rule tells you how you're supposed to be operating, and you fail to get the information that you're supposed to be getting, well, then you take the very next step. You just lay it on the table. You leave it on the table until such information. And that's what we have right before us right now. We have three papers that I would assume will just stay on the table. We've asked for their information to be forthcoming.
We've had the city audited, and then we had Louise Miller appear before us, and we still haven't gotten the information. So I think right now it's operating pretty good, and it's right in front of us right now. And I think council owes the obligation to the taxpayer, as Councilor Longo-Kern has alluded to, to not discuss that paper until we have an opportunity to receive the information to go forward. We don't have to wait for the next council to come in. It's happening right in front of you right now with three particular papers that you've asked for the information, you've laid it on the table,
You haven't gotten the information. It's three weeks running, and I don't know why, but if this is the way this administration wants to work, then so be it. Hopefully, the new administration doesn't do the same thing, but this is what you have in front of us. These are our rules right now, and I think they're operating pretty good on these particular matters. Thank you. Thank you, Constable Benton. Good evening. If you'd like to speak, please state your name and address for the record. Welcome.
My name is Michael Ruggiero. I live on 18 Pembroke Street. I would like to suggest to the Councillor that she adds an amendment to this legislation. It would be useful if information that was pertinent could be presented digitally also so people could view it at home. It seems to be a rather small request that if there is a large item, $300,000 debt that the city is going to have to pay for,
If we could have this information available to us digitally, it'll allow us to actually do a little research beforehand. The second thing I'd also like to recommend that we could have a digital recording on all committees of the whole meetings. Today, we just learned that there's going to be about a 7 to 15% rate increase of the water bill.
If that information could be presented digitally to the average citizen, I think that would be useful, so at least they could hear it at home. And thirdly, I just want to address the general tone of the meeting. It's frustrating when the administration continually bulldozes through certain choices that this legislative body is governed by.
Is there anything more we can do than just reminding the administration that they have seven days to provide financial information so people can view it? Thank you. Good evening. Welcome. Please state your name and address for the record. Hi. My name is Joyce Paul. I live at 8 Mason Street in Medford, obviously. I just want to thank you for bringing up the issue of this. I'm a little bit surprised. This is the first time I've spoken here.
I realize this evening I've heard my name mentioned many times. I'm a taxpayer, and I hear that word many, many times. I represent a lot of people who are taxpayers, and I am, like, amazed that you would spend any amount of money without having a period of time to look at it when I get my bill at the store from whatever
you know, whatever bill comes in the mail, whether it's my property taxes or anything else, I look at the bill and I think about it and I say, well, that's good or bad. I may look back on the previous bill and decide whether it's a good thing or not. So I thank you very much for trying to be careful with my money because, um, I and all the other taxpayers would assume that you would do that. So I definitely support, um,
whatever you can come up with to make sure, when you spend the money, that you know what you're spending it for. Thank you. Thank you. Good evening. Please state your name and address for the record. Andrew Castanetti, Cushion Street, Merritt, Mass. The most recent speaker made some good points. I wanted to reiterate some of it.
And Councilor Brianna brought up a good resolution, although Councilor Penta also mentioned we already have the tool in your chest as we speak, as he used before the Section 20, I believe it was called. Not being a lawyer, however, I've noticed how this is written, be it resolved that the Memphis City Council not approve it of any bond or expenditure
that does not have a written explanation of such expenditure at least seven days prior to the said vote. It's a little vague, a written explanation. They could just say, I have to do, I need the money to do whatever, part three of some bridge project. And I think more importantly, we'd want some sort of itemized explanation.
And I would think that seven days prior, you should have the information. That should have been going on since day one, 100 years ago. So if you go to a bank to borrow money, they ask you why you want to borrow it. So if you want to borrow it or have the taxpayers responsible for it for the next 20 years, if it's a bond, we would think we should know what it's for.
In detail. Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Castagnetti. Chair recognizes Councilor Marks. Thank you, Mr. President. I thank Councilor Longo Kern for bringing up this important issue. I believe it was about maybe eight years ago that we had a number of these concerns that were coming before the council. And at the time, the council president was Bob Mayarco. And Bob Mayarco made it, it wasn't a council rule,
But he made it a rule through the president that any expenditure or loan order had to go to a committee of the whole meeting first. And that forced the hand of the administration to provide documentation to the council at a committee of the whole meeting. And I think what's happening now is that that process has been circumvented, and the mayor is getting these particular resolves right on the council agenda, trying to put
heat on, because, you know, let's face it, many of the issues are very important issues. We had the issue with the drainage at Winthrop Circle. We had the issue with the fire stations that came up not too long ago and so forth. There are many important issues that are out there that we do need loan orders and expenditures. And I don't think anyone behind this really is doubting that. But the fact that we're unable to get any type of supporting documentation,
any type of feedback. I did receive a call last week before this was on the agenda from the mayor's office asking to speak with me. That probably happens maybe once a year that I get a call, and I knew what it was regarding, but I'll be quite frank. I refuse to do business over the phone. I refuse to do business without having supporting documentation. I refuse to do business, as the gentleman just got up,
microgerial where there's no transparency. And to me, not to have written detail on the agenda, which is really the only public document available, and to do things over a phone call is not how I think government should be operated in this day and age. So I support this wholeheartedly. I think that we could accomplish the same goal if the current president of the council chose not to allow these papers to come right before the council for a vote.
but to send them to a Committee of the Whole meeting so we can vet out the issues, we can ask our questions, and have the proper information presented to us in a timely fashion. So, I support this. Whatever the avenue or the mechanism is to get to this, I think we could do it a number of different ways. But I would ask, Mr. President, with all due respect, that you be the gatekeeper on these issues and tell the administration
No, we're not going to put this on the agenda for a council vote until it's vetted out, until we have the full language asking what needs to be done, and then we'll review it at the appropriate time. So, I would ask that this lay in the hands of the council president, under your authority, Mr. President.
Yes. Please state your name and address for the record. Good evening. Joseph Villione, 59 Garfield Ave, Medford, Mass. I want to thank Councilor Michael Marks for stating that he wants written documentation because I've filed public records request after public records request. And sometimes I hear no document on file. When the mayor met with a 501c3 at two pizza parlors, there were no documents on file. We really need to have everything documented.
I think people notice in the newspaper public records laws in Massachusetts are the weakest in the nation. We, the citizens, need to have that documentation. So thank you, Councilor Marks. Very, very important. If I could, just through the chair. Please. I agree with Councilor Knight, too. I think we should talk about it in rules and make it a
on paper change. Rule 20 can only take you so far. It can only get you that extra week. It doesn't guarantee you'll get documentation from anybody. It just tables it for one week, just like we tabled it last week, and we still have no information before us tonight on those $800,000 bond requests. So I would
I would suggest that we do send that portion of the rules committee, but I also would like the council to vote on it. Just send a message that we'd like, um, just an explanation writing. And I would amend it to put a written detailed itemized explanation if we could just a written detailed itemized explanation. So thank you for that of such expenditure at least seven days prior to said vote. I agree with my colleagues and I hope we stick together and just, just for the, you know, so we can get some, um,
facts in front of us before we discuss it with the department heads. I think that's important. And then just, I do too believe it should be online with regards to the taxpayers can see, you know, the same information we see. And with regards to the water rates, I didn't hear a 15% increase. So just make sure before we go throwing that online, definitely check those numbers.
Very good. So counselor, you're amending your motion, your motion. Counselor Knight, are you withdrawing yours? I think Mr. President, we have an a paper and a B paper and a paper to address the rest of this preceding term. And then we will have a meeting of the rules committee to establish the rule. If we look at our rules right now, we have a section 22 rule 22. I'm sorry, not section 22. I don't want to confuse the two, but rule 22 says,
Every ordinance and every order for a bond issued shall, before its passage, be referred to the solicitor, who shall forthwith examine the same as to its legality and notify the council in writing of his or her findings. And we'll see on every bond request that we receive and every expenditure request that we receive, we have a cover letter from the city solicitor. And that's been pretty effective, and we receive that every time, Mr. President. So I think that this is actually, you know,
us working together to come up with a great venue and a great way to handle this. We can handle the rest of this term through Councilor Longo's resolution, and we'll put it on the Rules Committee to address it for the future. When the new Council comes in. Thank you. So on the B paper to send the issue to the Rules Committee. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? And on the A paper as amended by Councilor Longo-Curran, a roll call has been requested. Mr. Clerk, if you would please call the roll.
Do you need to speak on this motion before we call the roll? Councilor? Awesome. Thank you. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Camuso? Yes. Councilor Caviello? Yes. Councilor Knight? Yes. Vice-President O'Connor? Yes. Councilor Moxley? Yes. Councilor Penta? Yes. President DelaRusso? Yes. With a vote of seven in the affirmative, nine in the negative, unanimously, it passes. Thank you, Madam Vice President. Chair recognizes Councilor Caviello for request of suspension of the rules. All those in favor?
All those opposed? Suspension of the rules to take vigilance license, Mr. Counselor Caviello. Thank you, Mr. President. Mr. President, if we could take 15-767. On motion of Counselor Caviello's 15-767, petition for common vigilance license by MB Rajabur Rahman, 6 Hayes Road, number 20 Roslindale Mass 02131 for ZHT Enterprise Incorporated doing business as,
P's Variety, 106 Central Avenue, Medford, Mass. On file, business certificate number 246, building department, fire, police, traffic, health, treasurer. Letters of compliance, state tax ID, workman's compensation, application, and corporate papers. Petitioner is before us. Please state your name and address for the record. Thank you, Mr. President, and thank you all the honorable counselor who is here. It's me, MD Rajabur Rahman.
Three, uh, the address is one zero six central lab, uh, Medford, Massachusetts. Very good. The chair recognizes councilor Caviello for recommendation. Um, are you taking over the, the variety store that's already there? Yes, sir. Okay. Um, Mr. President, I find their papers in order and a motion for approval on the motion for approval by councilor. Um, care of yellow council, Camuso. Uh, nope. I just have one another thing on the suspension and when he's done with his very good, uh, counselor night.
Mr. President, I am in support of the convictual's license for these individuals. However, I do have a request of them. It's a pet peeve when I drive down Central and I drive past Pease Variety, and when the store is open, they still have the security grates down, covered with graffiti on the Spring Street side, Mr. President. So I'd ask that while you guys are in operation and in business and the store is open, that the security grates be opened during operating hours, because it really is a blight to the neighborhood to see the security grates down.
all day long with just the door open and maybe one window. Yeah, the thing is that we just provide a couple of more security systems. Like, we didn't have any CC camera outside, but right now we add up two more cameras, which one you can view from inside the roadside view as well. It used to be like all the cameras was inside, but recently we add up two other cameras, which one you can see, like,
record it or everything from outside, whatever, coming into your store or anything. So don't get me wrong, Mr. President, I certainly respect their right to protect their asset. However, I think during normal operating hours when somebody is in there, the grates could be lifted. And I'd also ask that a correspondence be sent to the convenience store on the corner of Fulton and Salem Street, asking the same. On the motion of Councilor Knight, or the amend, on the motion of Councilor Caravaggio for approval as amended by Councilor Knight,
with that communique to be sent to Fulton Street through the clerk's office. All those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Congratulations. Thank you, sir. Thank you, sir. Thank you. Congratulations. Thank you. Do you want to do 15768? Please, Mr. President. 15768, petition for common vigilance license by Lana Garcia, president, 200 Humphrey Street, 7, Swampscott Mass, 01907, for Gula Brazil, Incorporated, doing businesses as
House of Bread at 295 Salem Street in Medford. Is the petitioner present? On file we have business certificate 243, building permit, fire department, police and traffic impact report, health department treasurer, letter of compliance, sales tax ID, state tax ID, workman's compensation application, and corporate papers. Please state your name and address for the record.
Yeah, hi, Mr. President. My name is Roberto Santos. My wife is Lana Garcia. We want to continue the business in a bakery, and that's it. Very good. My address is at 225 Humphrey Street, Trump Square. Very good, you're welcome. Thank you very much. Chair recognizes Council Member Cafiello for recommendation. Thank you, Mr. President. Are you taking over the bakery that's there now? Yeah. Mr. President, the papers seem to be in order.
Motion for approval. On the motion for approval by Chairman Cafiello, all those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Mr. President, can I ask a question on hours of operation, if you don't mind? I'm sorry, go away. Hours of operation? Please tell us your hours of operation. When you intend to be open, from what time in the morning to what time in the evening? From 6 to 8.
6 a.m. 6 a.m. to 8 p.m. As I review the regulation to be opened at 7, are they not, Mr. Clark? 7? Let me see if I have a special permit. Are you going to be open just to bake at 6 in the morning, or are you open to sell?
The vehicle right now is stay open. I just changed the order. Yeah, the open is 6 AM to 8 AM. OK. That requires a special permit. If he's going to be open for retail at 6 o'clock, he might have to sit there. If you are going to open at 6 o'clock for retail to sell, you have to come back to us for a special permit.
So you have to go to the clerk's office to start that process. If it's your intention to open from seven to 10 PM.
then any retailer has the opportunity to work within those hours, unless there's a previous... What number is this? 295? Okay, no, they have Monday to Sunday, 5.30 a.m. It's tied to the location? Yeah. So it's tied to the location, so you may... So you do not need a special permit. Move for approval, Mr. President. So on motion approval, all those in favor?
All those opposed. Good luck. Good luck. Congratulations. Thank you, Mr. President. While we're under suspension, we have a taxpayer and my friend, Mr. Jack Coakley, that would like to address this honorable body. Good evening, Mr. Coakley. Please state your name and address for the record. My name is Jack Coakley, 69 Gawley Road. I'd like to start by saying a couple of months ago, I saw the guys out in the street drawing lines.
make an hour's warm-out. So I approached them, and they said, yeah, we're putting new gas lines. I said, oh, great. I thought about converting to gas. So the guy was actually very, I think he was a city worker. And he was very helpful. And he said, well, if you are hooked up to the main, it shouldn't be a problem if you want to convert to gas or if you want to bring gas in your house. He then left a note and said, I'm sorry, you were cut off in 2002 or something. So I since found out, by the way, it's illegal
to not — like, in other words, they're trying to charge people who aren't on gas, so the National Grid does their dit. But it's actually illegal not to put in a brand-new gas line. I have a customer — I sell trucks for a living. I have a customer who puts these in. It's actually against the law not to put in the new plastic PVC pipes. So the fact that I was hooked up has nothing to do with it because they're under legal obligation to put in a new pipe. So, really, they're just taking advantage of people.
taking their money. So basically they're stealing, in my opinion. So I figured I'd take care of that when they, because they drew the lines like three months ago. I figured I'd take care of that when the time came and fight it out. Right. So the guy was, like I said, he was nice about it. So this morning, uh, my wife called me a little frantic and, uh, she said, you're not going to believe what, uh, what just happened. And I said, what happened? She said, uh, I came home, uh, from walking the dog and, uh,
I saw the sign. It's not very clear, but I'll pass it on to Paul. It looks pretty official. I don't know if it was put there by the city or if it was put there by the contractor, but a sign clearly says no parking. Do you want me to read the sign so people, you can, I can, yeah, it says, uh, I can say what it says.
I'm not that bright, but maybe a little brighter, maybe, maybe a little brighter than the engineers for the city, but not that bright. Um, so, uh, it says, uh, no parking tow zone, uh, from seven to four, seven to four or five. It says five. Oh yeah. Well, that sign says some of them say four different ones. There's different signs all over the, uh, sidewalks, Mike and, uh, uh, Monday through Saturday, effective 1130.
through December 28th. So when I called City, my wife was frantic, so I called the DPW, and I got a very nice woman, actually, who was very, not very helpful, but tried to be. And she said, well, the money's been approved, it's been, I said, well, what do you want me to do with my cars? Would you like me to put them in my living room, or, you know, where do you want me to put them? And she said,
But we don't know. I said, well, did anybody think of possibly, because you know, they were doing this when it was warm out. Did anybody think of maybe saying to the residents, this is going to affect the whole of Corley road and all of twice circle. Um, that's on this next. Did anybody think about saying, Hey, maybe we should get together and get a little community input here and figure out maybe some solutions. Maybe we could have called tops, maybe a little late to that now.
see if they had some parking for us. Maybe we could have, I suggested to her, I said, well, why don't we take down the fence or open up the gate at Barry Park? Maybe we can put something down so it's not so soft. Maybe we can put cars in Barry Park. She goes, well, I don't know if we can do that. I said, well, we only have six days. But you know, if we'd had a meeting at the library or something, maybe we could have figured something out. And what about the old people? What are they going to do? How are they going to get to their house? It states here in the letter, by the way,
This is a pretty, now I'll pass this back. I'd like it back, but if you want my copies. I'm picking some stuff out here. Will I be able to park on the street during this construction? Restriction notifications posted throughout the, well clearly no notify residents, but I'm trying to, there's one here that says, somewhere in here, and it's in these two things, you may not have access for certain periods of time to your home.
And we will try to limit that as much as we can. So when 75-year-old said resident walks up with her bundle of groceries from George Street in the snow when it's 20 below zero, when they were drawing the lines in like August, we're going to tell her, sorry, Grandma, go back to George Street. We're not ready to let you have access to your house.
And if anybody forgot, it's Christmas. I can't go on Black Friday and go to Amazon.com and order anything because they can't deliver packages to my house. So I can't order anything online for Christmas. It just kind of sort of dumbfounds me that
Yeah, it's right here. I need a copy of it. These are the two letters we received today. So it just sort of dumb farms me that, uh, I don't want to use the word stupid, but maybe negligent. Let's use negligent that the city could actually be that negligent and to somehow think that this is okay. Is there really anybody here that thinks it's okay? I'm just asking. I mean, I don't, I don't want to come off like a jerk. Look, if we got gas leaks in the street and that's what the answer was from the woman at the DPW,
I'm a resident, we have to fix the gas leaks in the street. Is it inconvenience in me when I'd rather it inconvenience somebody else? Yes, of course. But the fact is, if the gas leaks are in front of my house, they have to be fixed and I understand that. And I'm not an unreasonable person. But I do think that there should have been some kind of communication, some kind of better thought out planning. Hey, it's Christmas, this is probably not a good time to rip the street up and tell everybody to put their cars somewhere else.
You know, that's kind of more my thought. Like I said, when I asked her about the park, I said, you know, can we push the fences down? Can we use the tennis courts? Can we? She was a nice person. She was trying very hard to help me. She tried to get George on the phone, whoever George is. I don't know who that is. But, you know, I got to find George. I got to find George, whoever George is. I'm like, okay, I'll hold, you know. So, like I said, she was really trying. She spent 20 minutes on the phone with me. I had her name written down. It's in my office. She really did try.
You know, the fact is, I'm just wondering, is there any intelligent life over the DPW? They got a nice brand new building and you know, as the sun shining through there, I mean, I just, you know, because we, I mean me personally, I want the new street, I want the gas line, you know? So my question to you is, you know, can we have multiple city councilors? I'm looking for everybody find out a, who's the negligent person that dreamed this up and B,
Can they, are they bright enough to figure out maybe some solutions and some, you know, to figure out how to make this a little smoother? And can it be delayed? I mean, probably not, because it's only going to get worse as time goes on. I'm also going to mention that this plays into, Paul knows, and I think Bobby knows, I fell off my roof last year.
My lovely daughter, who's here with me tonight, was taking me to a medical appointment. My car was in front of my house for about a minute and a half, and she was helping me get out of the house because I was on crutches. And I ended up with a $50 apartment gift, you know, because they were driving around in their Escort, you know, trying to tag people during the, you know, great snowstorms of last year. I'm probably going in January to have, from that same injury, to have bone fusion surgery on my foot.
I'm going to be in a cast for three months. I kind of don't want to be coming down goalie road from the dame school on the hill in my nice school, you know, in the ice trying to get in the house. I mean, I guess my point is, did anybody think it would be a better time when it was warmer? Now, if you read that letter, I actually don't, as I said in the beginning of this conversation, and this is my last part of it, I happen to not be a national grid gas customer.
Unfortunately, I am a National Grid electric customer, right, with their rates. But it says in that letter, they're going to disconnect people. And it also says, it's going to be possibly for days. So there's going to be old people. I got a wood stove. If they disconnected me, I got a wood stove. I could stay warm. But there could be some 90-year-old woman on the street with no heat for two or three days. In case somebody forgot to tell the geniuses at National Grid in the nice, big, beautiful building
Yeah. It gets kind of cold in December sometimes. If you remember last December, it was a little cold and you're going to shut the heat off for two, three, four days. I mean, who thought this up? I'm just, I mean, like I said, I'm not really that smart. I didn't go to, you know, I went to five different high schools and I just kind of looked at it and went, you know, I mean, I just, I just hope that the people we have employed are a little smarter than me.
So, I mean, I just — you know, I would like somebody — Paul has my cell phone. I'll give it to anybody else. I'd like somebody to get back to me with some answers so we can do something. I don't know. Yeah, I don't know if you guys think the PAC is crazy, if that's a crazy idea or something. So — Mr. President. Thank you very much. Chair recognizes Councilor Camuso. Thank you, Mr. President. And, Jack, I certainly understand your frustration, as I indicated on the telephone earlier today. I believe there's a timeline that National Grid is supposed to stop digging unless it's for emergency situations.
And I thought it was around November 1st or October. If we could find out, first of all, who this gentleman George is, and secondly, once we do find out if a permit was issued. And I don't want to sit here and say we should put the whole project on hold, because I don't know if there's people on that street that are waiting for gas, for if there's leaks. I don't know the circumstances. But to not notify the neighborhood well in advance,
well in advance and come up with some sort of a solution. Um, it's, it's mind boggling. Well, the other thing I'd like to mention, I think the least national grid can do, I feel probably they should give us all of us a year of free gas, but I'll put, you know, but they could at least put the gas in for nothing to try to charge us a couple of grand to bring the gas in after kicking us out of our house and tell us we can't order
Christmas presents online, the least they can do is bring the gas in for nothing to try to charge us. I mean, really, that's just a little out of control, in my opinion. So if you want to try for the year, we're free gas ball. Good. I'm coming over your house for the winter then. No lie. If we could find out at least like, like you say, the city of Medford has control over.
the permitting and as far as giving them the permission to do it. If we could find out the circumstances surrounding it and we can get back to Jack tomorrow because he needs to let his neighbors know. I know there's other people in the neighborhood that are concerned about this. There's some senior citizens that live on Dwyer and in Gordley that depend on the sidewalks and the infrastructure in that immediate area. So I just, I wish there was more communication.
And it wasn't at four o'clock this afternoon, or earlier in the afternoon when Mrs. Coakley brought it to his attention. But if we could just get the answers and find out too. From the engineering office? From the engineering office. And if this is some upgrade for the purpose of convenience, and it's not an emergency, and it's convenience, that we do put it off until the springtime when the nice weather. Because the snow plows are going to be right behind. They're already talking about snow.
and it's just going to create a problem after a problem after a problem. They said gas leaks. So if it is gas leaks, that's one thing. I mean, if it's gas leaks, it's gas leaks. We see the stories of houses blowing up. You have to take care of it. You can't put the fire department or the neighborhood people in danger. But if it's not gas leaks, and it is just because they have 13 customers that want to sign up,
and start selling gas. My point is, can we use the park? Can we do something about it? Yeah, and that was my second point. And Jack had a very good idea. You got Barry Park down the corner. Yes. You have the new, I call it the new Dame Schools. The Walnut Hill Properties owns a property there. If maybe they would give us a couple spots, do something to alleviate the neighborhood's concerns. And last but not least, last but not least,
You've got to think that between November and Christmas is not a good time to be ripping up a street that's going to last 30 days, other than an emergency situation with gas leaks. But they knew about it two months before this. Exactly. They did know about it because they were talking to me about it two or three months ago. I'm just saying a little planning might have said, geez, December's probably not a great time. Exactly.
As you know, I talk to you quite frequently and I will, uh, be updating with you tomorrow with what we can find out. I appreciate what you guys can find out. Thank you. Counselor Penta. No. And the paper that you have there, Jack, there's a question on the bottom of the line there that says, are there going to be any, I think restrictions as it relates to the parking and the second, they're going to make everything possible, but that's a city of Medford sign that's posted.
that says no parking from seven in the morning to five at night, whatever it might be. So I'm assuming that since they didn't come before the council to get the permit, I mean, where do they go? The building department? I don't know. It says that they were issued from the DPW. So if they were issued from the DPW, I thought all permits that applied for would have to come before the council, Mr. Clark. Is that true? I mean, if you want a copy of the paper, it says through the DPW.
There's stuff to come, you have to open up a street. They're opening up a street for Digley, for Gasley, correct? They're supposed to post a $10,000 bond as well. We're going to get that information tomorrow. It says in here, but it definitely says it's through the DBW. We'll amend that if we could, Councillor, if it's all right to amend the paper to ask the city engineer to
explain the entire permitting process for this project, and why wasn't there sufficient notification and forethought put into this that the citizens are put in such dire straits. I mean, to imagine that people, whether they're old or young, may be without heat for four days in the middle of the winter is ridiculous.
Councilor Knight. Yes, Mr. President. I also find it confusing that they'd put the restrictions. Mr. Coakley. Mr. Coakley. A quick question for you, sir. Were these signs posted the full length of Goley Road into ISR? They're like on little horses, saw horses.
But would it go from Summit Street to George? Yeah. Summit Street to George? Pretty much, yeah. In a round, wide circle, too. In a round, wide circle as well. It says on this paper here that they're going from- The reason I ask is because I've never seen National Grid, first of all, work on a project after 3 o'clock in the afternoon, number one.
but they're restricting your parking till 5 o'clock in the afternoon. And number two, I don't understand why, if in fact they are going to do the project for the whole entire street, why it's not done in segments as opposed to shutting the whole street down. Well, that's kind of what I think. Well, yeah, yeah. That was what I thought, too. Like, I can understand if they said to you, hey, can you, well, first of all, the tow zone thing is a little offensive, right? But if they said, listen, you know, this day we're going to be working, can you come? If we're coming, the crew's coming at 7, can I go out and take my daughter's car and my car and move it down the street?
Okay. It's a little inconvenient, but you know, don't threaten that Derek Stevens is going to be there and you know, in three and a half minutes, you know what I mean? It's just, I understand it has to be done. It's extremely inconvenient, but I do think the second part of this, uh, Councilor Knight should be, why are they charging or trying to charge Medford residents for the connection? When they have to put the new pipe in legally, they have no choice. It's illegal for them not to.
And I'm a hundred percent certain. I don't, I don't doubt it for one bit. You did your homework. You know what I mean? You see a lot of people come up here that don't. They can't use the steel pipe. It's against the law. They have to use PVC pipe. So anybody who's in there, it has to be replaced. So saying that you hooked up to the main has nothing to do with the put in the pipe. Nothing. And they're not allowed to go through the houses anymore from the foundation. That's illegal. Right. On the motion by council Penter as amended by counselors, uh,
Councilors Penta and Knight. Yes. The matter that we're voting on right now would be to have the city engineer explain the process to us in the permitting process and the restrictions and why this is going to happen. Right. And then we're going to also have a couple of other side questions that the clerk has taken down. Yes. The main motion that we're voting on would be to have a meeting with the engineer.
In a report back. In a report back. Okay. Great. Yes. So on that motion, all those in favor. Aye. All those opposed. You're welcome. Congratulations. Good luck with the surgery. On the motion of Councilor Penta to revert back to the regular order of business. All those in favor. All those opposed. Aye. 15-763 offered by Councilor Penta. Be resolved that the public safety concerns at Roosevelt Circle be concerned. Councilor Penta.
Mr. President, this is not the first time we've had to bring this up, and this seems to be an ongoing situation. As you're coming up the exit to Roosevelt Circle going south down Route 93, it's a combination of the lights being off, and then once you go halfway around the circle, the lights are off. I know this was presented to Representative Donato before in the past. There was some concern about the state coming in there and doing it. Apparently, they still haven't found time to do it. It's a direct public safety hazard, especially for people going around that rotary.
trying to take the right either to south border road or down to forest street in Medford. It's absolutely dark over there. Um, the light's coming off the ramp and then on the opposite side of route. So once again, I move that that be forwarded to the state department of public safety and have that forwarded to our representative, Mr Donato, because we're supposed to have been taken care of and it's still not been addressed.
On the motion of Councilor Penta for approval. Roll call vote, Mr. President. Offered by Councilor Caviello. Roll call has been requested. Councilor Caviello. Thank you, Mr. President. I agree with Councilor Penta there. There's a light that's been knocked down for a couple of years now. Somebody must have knocked it down during an accident. And it's never been replaced. Light where? There's a light pole right where he was talking about. Yeah. Looks like maybe during an accident it got knocked down and all of a sudden there was a little piece that was left over.
If that light could be replaced, also. Right at that bus stop where he's talking about, there was a street light at one time. As you're coming off the exit from Route 93 south. It may have been knocked down by an accident or something, but all that's left there is a little piece of pole.
take it on the right just before you take South border road. There's a, there was a street light that was here, which is, which is kind of an odd spot for a bus stop anyways. Say it again, Eddie. What was your amendment? Oh, to have representative Donato go back to the state department of public safety and put those lights back on. They were, this, this is months, this is running for months now that they haven't redressed them.
are on the road, not all of them are out, but the ones that are really significantly out are the ones that take you halfway around the rotary, that take you to South border road and to Forestry. On the motion for approval, Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. As amended. As amended by Councilors Pinter and Caviello. Councilor Camuso. Councilor Caviello. Yes.
Yes. With the vote of five in the affirmative and two absent, the motion passes. 15-764 offered by Councilor Penta be it resolved that a mentoring program for youngsters be discussed. Councilor Penta. Mr. President, the amount of things that are happening today out there and with youngsters not having
Especially youngsters that might be coming from a single-family home. It's just unfortunate that some of the programs that are offered are not being offered. It should be something that should be looked into. And as a result of that, I think it would serve us well to look forward either in through the private sector, the non-profits, because we have a whole bunch of those that take place when we do our community block grant funding, or also in our public and private school.
programs that are out there that can serve a purpose that can mentor youngsters at an early age. There's a wild bill that's out there right now. It's a Senate bill. It passed the Senate. It's on its way to the House. And I'm quite sure this might be brought up next week. But it's sort of like it addresses, it calls itself age appropriate sexual content that's going to be mandated by the Commonwealth of Massachusetts.
into our public school system for children 11 and 12 years of age. And it's causing quite a controversy and quite a stir as it relates to what is going to be considered to be age appropriate and what is age appropriate for the certain part of sexual connotations and sexual education and anything that revolves itself around a child's either awareness or lack of awareness as to where he or she might be going or understanding.
And these are the things I think that need to be addressed. You know, it's unfortunate when you have stuff like that, that they're trying to teach or educate you on, but they won't give you a civics class and make a mandated class to learn about your government, local, federal, and state. You know, it's kind of crazy in this day and age, especially, you know, you're trying to get people involved, and good government are having positions on government on issues.
So with that being said, Mr. President, I don't know what mentoring program the city of Medford has or even offers, but I'd like to get a report back from either the superintendent of schools and any private school organization here in the city of Medford that might offer a mentoring program for youngsters, could be troubled youngsters, youngsters from single parent homes, or just youngsters in general that have become available here to the city. Where was the sexual component in this council?
A mentoring program. Mentoring. Mentoring. M-E-N-T-O-R-I-N-G mentoring program. Sort of like a big brother, big sister, but it's something that's offered through education. If we have it and what is it and where is it? So that, uh, in what entity is to give us this report? Well, either the city, if the city has it, or if the school department has it. Very good. So if, uh, on the city side, Mr. Uh, clerk or the school department, uh, has a listing of,
mentoring programs given by either within the public sector or by private educational entities in non-profits. On the motion for approval by Councilor Panto. Roll call vote, Mr. President. Councilor Caviello. Oh, ma'am. I'm sorry. Councilor Lucia. What type of mentoring programs are you referring to? Well, that's just it. I don't know. Are they after school programs? Are they scholastic type of programs?
Are they athletic programs? Are they community awareness programs? It's a mentoring program that a kid gets after he's out of school. Or he might get it while he's in school. Specialized classes that relate to students that might have disabilities. Are they having special mentoring programs that can make the child adapt to life-like situations? Good evening, citizen. Please state your name and address for the record. Welcome.
Hi there. I'm Rachel Tannenhaus, 26 Pearl Street. And I'd just like to recommend, since you happen to mention students with disabilities, I don't think it needs to be any kind of necessarily segregated program or class. Whoa, got some feedback going on there. Programs or classes or anything like that. But I do recommend as a possible resource. I don't know if you're familiar with the group Partners for Youth with Disabilities.
They're an excellent program. They do mentoring programs and they are an excellent national resource around inclusive mentoring programs that do include youth with disabilities and I was going to suggest that
If you want to make the most inclusive possible program of whatever type, they're really good to contact. And I think they also have some stuff on their website, which is www.PYD, as in Partners of Youth with Disabilities, .org. I am not affiliated with them, although I have been a mentor for a program that they're involved in. But they're one of the premier resources out there on inclusive
mentoring programs, and I think that just calling them up and saying, hey, how can we make sure that everybody's included in this, and do you have any tips for us? They're really awesome people, and I definitely recommend it. I'm not entirely certain what that has to do with comprehensive sex education, but they probably have tips on providing inclusive sex education as well. So, you know, if you want to throw that in there, you can. I think they'll be a little surprised, though. All right, thank you. Thank you, Rachel.
So on the motion of approval. Councilor Canvio. Through my own club, the Kiwanis Club, we have after school programs in the middle school, the high school, and all the way up to the college program. We have a Builders Club, a Circle K Club, and a Key Club, which are all community-oriented things, and they're all after school, involving all types of students, fundraising, and community activities. And like I said, this year we incorporated Northeastern University as Circle Club, which
College students are now involved with our program. So there's an after-school program for these kids to get involved with. Great. So on the motion for approval by Councilor Penter, all those in favor? One more thing, Rachel. Sorry. Just to say quickly also that I have heard that there are some issues with transportation for students with disabilities who at some of the schools who want to participate in after-school activities, but there are some issues with getting them accessible transportation to
help them be able to do that. And so if that's one of the things you might want to look into, if you're looking at afterschool programs and making them inclusive, that all of the transportation policies make sure that everybody can participate. Thanks. On the motion for approval by Councilor Penta, Mr. Clerk, please call the roll. Councilor Camuso? Yes. Councilor Caviello? Yes. Councilor Knight? Vice President Long and Kern? Yes. Councilor Marks?
Councilor Penta? Yes. President Del Rosso? Yes. With a vote of six in the affirmative, one absent, the motion passes. 15-765, offered by Councilor Penta, be it resolved that the city's street sweeping program be discussed. Mr. Councilor? Mr. President, most recently, the street sweeping program has taken off in a very inconsistent manner. Some folks, when they're having their streets swept, have had their cars ticketed and towed. Other streets, cars have not been ticketed and towed.
And again, um, the, uh, allowing, uh, the notification, the notification, uh, the inconsistent notification of what streets, how and when, uh, to be taking place. Not everybody, number one has a computer and not everybody drives to the city of Medford to see the big sign that says a sweet stripping is going to begin on a, you know, there has to be a better program that it has to be identified and a,
in a definitive way where people, like in other cities and towns, know on what particular week and what particular month and what particular side of the street it's going to get swept. And the tagging and the towing has got to be consistent. It just cannot be arbitrary and capricious at any point in time. So with that being said, I know the council has asked for this. It goes back to 2014, and we still haven't gotten a program presented to us as to why and how the best method is. You just can't keep going around banging on trees
You know, put your sawhorses up here, there, and everywhere. That just doesn't cut it. You need a comprehensive program. Same thing with the leaf pickup program. You need to have something that's comprehensive, it's established, people know what it is, whether they get it in their water bill, whether they get it in their tax bill, whether they get it online. Something that basically says this is the way it is. And this goes a long way with having signage that directs itself toward these particular issues.
City of Medford needs to get itself into a direct signage program that addresses a whole host of issues. And again, what better way to have a signage program become operative? It would be a great course to be taught up at the Medford Vocational School, where they could take during maybe the spring or the fall months of the year when the weather is good. Every single street in the city can be identified, the type of street that it is, whether it's a public street, whether it's a private street, the signage that's on there, take a picture of it.
You know, I made this offering about five years ago. It was sent up to the vocational school, and the teacher at that time thought it was a great idea, but it never went any further. Why, I don't know. You know, like so many things, you never find out why. They don't want to do things. But this is definitely a homegrown type of program. It can work well. It definitely would serve a purpose here in this community. But when you have programs that are inconsistent, and you can't get an answer as to why I got a ticket and somebody else didn't get a ticket,
It's sort of like unfair. Same thing with the parking kiosk program. It's an unfair system. It doesn't work properly. Same thing with these parking program here. So I'd like to make a request, Mr. President, that you would probably maybe have a committee of the whole meeting set up with, you know, the council, but ahead of time, have the council have their thoughts come forward.
And maybe open it up to the taxpayers of this community. Maybe just have a, maybe a public hearing so it can be operative for next year. A public hearing as it relates to setting up a designated suite streeping program here in the city of Medford. So we don't have to go through this each and every year and you don't have to listen to the complaints and consistency and transparency will tell the whole story.
So that would be my recommendation, Mr. President. Thank you. And that would go a long way in demonstrating loud and clear to the next DPW director what the expectations of this community are. Chair recognizes the Vice President. Thank you, President DelaRusso. I too just want to discuss the street sweeping. And I think it goes into the big picture of this city with regards to lack of enforcement and lack of uniformity. I've gotten complaints that
from residents on Greenleaf that said there was no ticketing and towing for the street sweeping, and therefore, their street was not properly cleaned. The trucks had to go around cars that were parked there. Then you go up Quincy and Capon, where they were tagging and towing. So they're tagging and towing on some streets some days, and they're completely not enforcing the violations on other streets other days. It's inconsistent.
It's not uniform. The residents are left saying, what's going to happen on my street? Is it going to either be left unclean, or are they going to tag in tow? What's going to happen? I mean, we really just need some conformity within the city. I've said this before on street sweeping. I've said it before on a number of different issues. And we just cannot get it together with enforcement. And I hope the new administration really sits down and takes an approach like other cities do, like Somerville.
enforcement. They enforce everything. Everybody knows it and rules aren't broken as much. And their streets, number one, swept many times during the year. But even if we do only sweep once or twice, let's do it right and let's make sure that people know, people are notified correctly and that it's uniform throughout the community so that people know when that sign goes up, they're not left guessing, oh, will I get tagged and towed, will I not? No, they will get their cars off the road so our streets can get swept, bottom line.
And that goes for a number of different things that should be enforced, which is one of the reasons why we push for parking enforcement, because there was no enforcement. Now we're left, obviously, with a system that's not working entirely, and that's what we're left with. But I agree. We need some conformity, and whether that's us meeting with the DPW or us meeting with the new administration, let's get it done. In the new year, let's get it done.
Excellent. On that motion, uh, counsel can feel. Thank you, Mr. President. I, I too received some of the calls that, uh, not the Congress here, but, uh, the ones I got were from people are complaining that cars weren't getting towed and tagged weren't. We're not going around and they were mad because the street was, and I did make calls to, uh, public departments and according to, um, uh, Mr. Tanaglia and the, and the police department, we had no policemen to go out there and tag and tow the cars.
So that's the reason they didn't get done. Which leads us, you know, again, in our magazine that we get from the MMA, I don't know why we're not using recently retired policemen to do those. I mean, Boston uses them, other cities use them. I don't know why our city's not using the recently retired policemen when the lists are all filled and you can't get anybody else. But that's the reason.
I was told that there were no policemen to do the details. I didn't get any calls. It was the only, only calls I got were the people complaining that cars weren't getting tagged and towed. Thank you. Counselor night. Mr. President, thank you very much. I'd like to amend the paper further. Um, on November 10th, we passed paper number one, five, seven, three, one, a request for the cost of the biannual street sweeping program, as well as a request,
for the numbers as to what portion is handled internally and what portion is contracted out. And I think that falls in line with us establishing a street sweeping program that works for all, Mr. President. This matter was referred to the DPW response on 11-18-15, included in our packet last week. So I just wanted to reiterate the fact that we still await the response from the DPW, and I'd like to add that to the paper as a reminder, Mr. President.
So on this paper, as amended by Councillor Naik, Councillor Penta. Mr. President, you know, doing something biannually doesn't make any sense. It's only twice a year. You know, if you can have a program, you want it. There were some streets that had four sweet streepers on it. Some streets, you're lucky if you saw one. I mean, the logic, it's an inconsistent program that doesn't make any sense. Now, Rick just got through saying, Councillor Caviello got through saying,
that one of the employees in the Department of Public Works said there was no police officer available. What about the day that the police officer was available that was giving out tagging and towing? It's so inconsistent and anyone who's gotten a ticket should appeal that ticket to the city because it's inconsistent as to what's going on. You just can't run programs like this, like Councilor Briano just alluded to. How do you have transparency? You have a new guy coming on or a woman who's going to be a new DPW director.
You know, there's got to be a direction. And this should be a high priority for direction that should be given to this new person coming on. You can't run programs that are inconsistent and incompatible to what's supposed to be done. But you need the signage that goes along with it. So you can't be Houdini trying to figure out what's going on if the streets aren't properly signed. That's why it's a combination of signage and consistency to the program. You can't do it in reverse. You can't have the program then decide to put the signage up. So that's why I would say, Mr. President,
committee of the whole meeting with DPW, you know, and the public to get some of their ideas. This is great. You know, you're, you're, you're going into a new adventure, bring them in, let them know that this is their city. This isn't a closed shop of ideas. Thank you on that motion. A citizen wishes to speak. Good evening. Please state your name and address for the record. Welcome. Yes. Valerie Geiselman, three one eight high street. Well, this week I was happily anticipating having the corner of
High Street and Austin Road swept. And as the sweepers came along, one neighbor ran out and moved her car, and there was still another large van there, and I ran to that neighbor's house. I think I got the right house. Nobody was home, so the street sweeper had to go around it and leave a large swath of leaves, which I will have to pay someone to pick up or do it myself. And so that was very disappointing. I didn't see any tickets on our street.
And I really don't like to see my neighbors getting ticketed. On the other hand, now I have to pay to have these leaves removed. And the other thought is that many people feel intimidated about raking the leaves out. But my understanding is if the leaves come from the trees that belong to the city, and if they're on a berm that actually belongs to the city, that it should certainly be okay to rake those leaves out so the sweeper gets them. The sweeper doesn't come in really close anyway.
So if you loosen up those leaves, and sometimes they're muddy and wet, and the sweeper will pick them up. And they are leaves from the trees that actually belong to the city. They're on city property. And I think that people are intimidated by some of the statements they hear about not sweeping. Obviously, it means not the leaves from your yard on your personal property. So I think it would be nice to have some of those things clarified.
Thank you very much. And is there a community service at the high school that would help senior citizens sweep up leaves and things like that? Someone mentioned it to me, but I haven't found out about it. There is a program? We asked that as well last year, vis-a-vis shoveling snow. I don't know if we got a response back from the school department on that.
Perhaps we did. I can't recall, to be honest. But we'll send that through again. It would be nice if the seniors could call, particularly in this kind of incident, through no fault of their own, the leaves outside. And these leaves happen to be right along the passageway that goes to our door. And try to call maybe the senior center. There's like four or five people that work there. They may have some answers on who to call
My understanding is that they usually do things that are of a safety concern. I don't know if that would fall into the category. And I know they have a handyman, so that's why I didn't know if I could answer that for you. It's usually some kind of safety repair. That's my understanding. But leaves can be a safety issue, too, if they're wet. True. Thank you.
Very good. Those pieces have been added as amendments. Chair recognizes Councilor Caviello. Valerie, in my conversation with the Mayor about this problem, he said, in my conversation with the Mayor in regards to this problem, he said that anyone who calls from where there was cars parked, he would send a sweeper by to pick up the spots where they missed because of cars being in the way.
I would call the mayor's office tomorrow morning and let them know, but that's what I had a conversation with him on, I think on Thursday about this. And he said, yeah, I know the DPW won't be happy with that, but. Very good. So on that motion for approval by council, Penta has amended all those in favor. All those opposed motion passes, uh, offered by council and night be resolved at the Metro city council and MBTA commuter rail division meet to address the recent cuts
servicing the West Medford Community Rail Station. Councilor Knight. Um, yes, Mr. President. Um, recently I was informed by, uh, several people on the train on the way into Boston as well as the conductor. Um, as I was waiting at the West Medford Commuter Rail Station to go in town last Thursday, that they were going to be making proposed cuts to the service at the West Medford Commuter Rail Station. Um, I bear with me for a moment here, but, uh, the morning commute after 8 AM,
West Medford currently has service at 8.27 a.m., 8.45 a.m., 8.58 a.m., 9.30 a.m., and 9.48 a.m. The changes in this service will cut the times to 8.14 a.m., 8.34 a.m., and 9.47 a.m., with what looks like about an hour and 20 minute or so gap between the last two trains during the morning rush hour commute. And I'd be one to argue that 9.47 isn't really rush hour either, Mr. President. I think that's a little too late for people to be getting into town to go to work.
Also on the way home, leaving North Station to West Medford, currently we have a 410 train, a 420 train, a 440 train, a 510 train, a 550 train, a 625, a 655, and a 730 train. The announced changes will reflect a train at 355, 445, 510, 6 p.m., 520, and 725, with service gaps as long as a little bit over an hour, Mr. President, during some of those periods.
I'm really confused about the message that the MBTA sent to the City of Medford at this point in time, Mr. President. We're sitting here, we're dealing with proposed changes to our commuter rail schedule that's cutting service. We're sitting here looking at the privatization of our express bus routes with new contracts. We're also sitting here looking at the state wavering on its commitment to extend the Green Line to College Avenue, Mr. President. And I think that sends the wrong message to the City of Medford that, well, we're just a cutthroat. They're going to lay out tracks here, but they're not going to service us, Mr. President.
I'm very concerned about the direction that this matter is going in. And in recent days, I have been informed that our state delegation, led by Representatives Garbo and Donato and Representative Barber, have met and offered a statement relative to the proposed changes in the MBTA schedule. However, no definite matters have been resolved at this point in time.
And there will be a meeting in coming days with MassDOT and MBTA officials, Mr. President, and I ask that our representatives keep us apprised of that meeting and also maybe the council can appoint a representative or invite a representative to attend. So the purpose of the resolution, Mr. President, is to get more information relative to the cuts at the West Medford Commuter Rail Station and the service thereof, Mr. President. I feel as though it would be detrimental to our community to allow these cuts to go through. I know we have limited control. However, I think we need to put up a fight and put up a stink.
make sure that Medford's not a cut-through for MBTA service, but rather a place where they stop and a place where it can flourish. Awesome. On the motion for approval by Councilor Knight, all those in favor? Aye. Opposed? Motion passes. Mr. President, would you like to make an announcement? I'm sorry. Yes. Two more things. I'm sorry. I apologize. I thought we were all wrapped up. 15-769, petition by Joseph Viglione, 59 Garfield Avenue, Medford, Mass.,
asking for $25,000 transfer from P slash E slash G monies for a new radio station. Good evening, Honorable City Council, Joe Villione, 59 Garfield Ave, Medford, Mass, 02155. We have all that money sitting there waiting for a public access station.
But what if we could get Captain Barry Clemente's Connect CTY messages over a radio station? Local artists, authors, musicians, hockey, basketball, baseball. Councilor Camuso just said to me there's a Malden-Medford game on Thanksgiving Day. That would be beautiful to have on the radio. Because the audio of events, including city council events and school committee events, logged
and kept in a file so that people could go back to them and hear them on podcasts. This is essential to the community. Now, the Chevalier Theater is handicap accessible to the left. If we could take some space off the stage, build a radio station, we could broadcast every single event from the Chevalier live on audio.
Now that would not hurt ticket sales because people would want to see the whole event. But if they couldn't get there and they wanted to hear the event with the permission of the performers, we would have it on radio. This would be a key to building a public access TV station. So with all that money sitting there, I'm asking the city council, if someone wants to get proactive and has access to the mayor, say, hey, you know, what about this idea? So I outlined a really rough sketch
of what the 25 grand could go to, just to get the ball rolling. Computers, a sound board is only $250. You can get microphones for $100. There are packages on the Internet. And we don't even need all that much money. I just put it there as a framework. There are plenty of ways to get a good computer at a good price and to talk to some companies. Maybe a car dealership would give us a deal on a van so that we'd have a mobile van, handicap accessible, that would have the radio and a camera in it.
That's all I'm asking. The money's sitting there. I want to see us get proactive. I've been coming up here for a good decade now. My first meeting was with Mark Rumley and Diane McLeod in early 2003. That's 12 years of honest effort, hard work, and diligence. So this will be very important for this community, especially with the past election. We didn't even have radio. We didn't have television. Well, Malden, Somerville, Arlington, Winchester, Stoneham, Burlington, everyone had TV. We didn't.
you candidates at a disadvantage, and it put the voters at a disadvantage. Thank you for hearing me, counsel, tonight. Mr. President, one of the things that present this as an enticing matter is the technology and communication is ever-changing, whether it be on public access, whether it be the private enterprise system.
But another thing that should be looked upon with this radio station is by making it something locally accessible, you want to encourage handicapped folks to have the same opportunity. And one of the things that the speaker just mentioned, being at Cheviro Auditorium, whether it's there, the public library, someplace that's easily accessible on a bus route for whatever it might be. The proposed location for the high school of the present time is not easily accessible. It's not handicap accessible.
It has too many detriments running against it, especially late at night, evenings, winter time, inclement weather and what have you. But this idea of having a station where people can come and be heard and hopefully be the catalyst that eventually gets ourselves with a public access station, I think it's a great idea. That's number one. Number two, with the mayor sitting on over 300, I believe it's about $370,000 at the present time in public access money and not having public access in the city,
since December of 2013. I believe this is the mayor's intentional failure to move forward on something that he is contractually bound to do according to the contract that he has not only with Comcast, but also with Verizon, who came on a couple of years ago. So what we're looking at is the idea of getting small equipment at a not a very large price. We're not looking at 4,000 to 5,000 square feet of space. We're not looking at buying vehicles. We're looking at something
that can present not only an interest in this community, but it can present itself with accessibility because that's what's mandated in the contract that Comcast just signed with the mayor for another 10 years, unfortunately, another 10 years with the same vendor without having an opportunity to have this thing monitored even after the third or the fourth, fifth year. So with that being said, I think what we should do is to
I think we need to do is to get the exact dollar amount as to what we have. This is coming into the fourth quarter of this year, and I don't think those monies will be readily available until January of next year. So what our monies are as of September 30th of this year, that brings us to the third quarter for Verizon and Comcast, and the idea of having, and they don't have a public access or a cable access committee. And without having a public access committee,
And only leaving this in the hands of the mayor, it's quite obvious that not only whether you were a candidate, not a candidate, or whether you were a person in the community who wanted to see your elected officials or a new candidate running for office, you lost that opportunity because we have no public access. But you're being charged each and every month through your Verizon and your Comcast bill. So if this radio station is the beginning effort, if it's a catalyst to get ourselves going, I think it's a great move to do it.
And with that being said, I would urge my colleagues to urge the president administration to go forward. And he's not going to respond back why he's not having public access, but it's another area to say, let's do this in the interest of not only public access, but it's also a public communication as it relates to what's going on here in the community. Every single person behind this rail, every single person on the other side of the rail.
We'll have that opportunity to be on the radio, to be interviewed, or to possibly have a show that talks about our city of Medford, whether you like or dislike, and where we need to go. I just don't understand why this administration was in such fear of having public access. And I don't know what he could have possibly thought that public access was going to do to him. He's not serving in office anymore. He's retiring. So his office wasn't even that issue.
Every single council that's here that ran, that ran for reelection, every new council that was running, the school committee, they were denied a privilege. They were denied their opportunity to go forward. And that's what public access is all about. So here is another opportunity through the mechanisms of public access to have a public radio offering. And I just think it's a great way to go forward. And Mr. Mayor, excuse me, Mr. President, I'm going to ask that you, and I don't know if you're going to be the incoming president,
Well, who the new president's going to be next year for the city council? Well, you might be the mayor, you never know. But the fact of the matter is this, that whoever the president's gonna be should take the leadership role to move on this particular issue in the interest not only of public information, but just in the interest of the city of Medford. Was it you, Councilor Camuso? They just said they were, Marlin is having this televised for their football game coming up as they, was it? Oh, was it Joe? You said it, I'm sorry, you said it.
Yeah, it's a big game, right? Well, we don't have nobody to do our big game, okay? And we haven't had anybody to do our big game for years. And the sad part about it is each and every month you just keep paying out in your Verizon and your Comcast bills. It's not fair. And the taxpayers of this community, the rate payers for cable television deserve better. They deserve to have their money used and used properly. So that's being said.
on the motion of Council Penter to send this paper to the mayor's office? No, to send it to you, whoever the president's going to be next year, to enforce, to request of the mayor to go forward with a committee, which would be a cable committee that would serve in the best interest of this community, that not only addresses peg access by way of public television, but also public access and a radio system. Chair recognizes Councilor Cafferill. Thank you, Mr. President.
The Method Mall game is one of the oldest rivalries in this country. Yes. Second oldest. And it would be nice if, uh, uh, during my high school days and, um, you didn't watch me play. You may have watched Clark Finn play. You didn't watch me play. Uh, but it'd be nice if we could, you know, maybe get that game on for people who don't go the game. Um, maybe, uh, the high school, uh, could tape it and get it on there for Thanksgiving afternoon. I know a lot of people look forward to watching that game again.
It's the second oldest rivalry in the United States. It'd be nice to see it on some kind of axis. Thank you. I wish I could call the game. I'm not that talented. Yes, you are. Yes, I do. A motion for approval by Councilor Penta as amended by Councilor Caviello. All those in favor? The paper is referring it to me for action for next year.
No, no, no, no, I said we've heard from the President, whether it be Councilor De La Russo or whoever, if you want to take action before the end of the year, so be it. But I think it definitely needs to have a public access committee. And I think at your behest or whoever the President's behest is, they encourage the Mayor to go forward and put that committee together so we can go forward with public access. Clerk has that. I think we'll discuss that in the next term then.
If I may. Chair recognizes the man at the podium. 59 Garfield Ave., Joe Villione again. You know, Malden Access TV, I've worked with them hand-in-hand. I brought a lot of musicians to Malden Access TV. Maybe they'll be taping it, in which case I will contact them tomorrow and see if they are. I would volunteer my services. I have things to do, of course, on Thanksgiving Day.
providing this time, it should be documented. So I will reach out to MATV and maybe we can put it on the government or high school channel. Chair recognizes Vice President Legelmarks. Thank you, President De La Ruzo. I just want to second Councilor Pence's resolve. I think we do need to figure out where we're going to go with the TV access come new administration, especially the voters were disadvantaged. I agree with that wholeheartedly.
Candidates were disadvantaged. We also have had such a failure to move forward, and it's a shame. I feel like we're stealing from the ratepayers. We have a portion of money that's being set aside from your cable bill, and it's not being used. It's just sitting there. We don't know how we're going to move forward, and it seems to be just a complete stall. This is something that has been
on the council's agenda for a very long time, and we luckily were able to shut down TV3 a couple years ago, but it's just an absolute shame that we can't move forward on a TV station that the ratepayers are paying for. I think that if we're going to move forward, the next council and the next administration have to be at the table together to make a decision to see where this is going to go, because as you said, and I apologize for speaking from the chair,
Um, but council Penta has pointed out consistently as have all the other counselors and you met and vice president that, um, uh, people's, uh, uh, portion of people's pay for cable is, uh, uh, being attached for these services. So, uh, we've got to come to a just resolution on this. So on the motion of council Penter, all those in favor, well, call has been requested. Mr. Clerk, if you would please call the roll council.
Councilor Caviello. Yes. Councilor Knight. Based on redundancy. Vice-President Long-Kern. Yes. Councilor Mox. Yes. Councilor Penta. Yes. President De La Russa. Yes. With the vote of five in the affirmative.
One in the negative and one absent. The motion carries. 15-770 to the communication from the mayor. This is a transfer of funds from one account to another. To the Honorable President and members of the Memphis City Council, City Hall.
I respectfully request and recommend that your honorable body appropriate $104,000 from the sale of lots and graves account to the cemetery department salary account. This recommended appropriation is requested in accordance with page 44 of the fiscal 2016 budget. Cemetery department salary account is reduced each year in anticipation of an appropriation from sales of lots and graves. In addition, I respectfully request and recommend that your honorable body appropriate
$182,327 from the perpetual care to the cemetery department expenses budget. This recommended appropriation is requested in accordance with page 45 of the fiscal 2015-16 budget. The cemetery expense budget is reduced each year in anticipation of appropriation from perpetual care. Very crudely yours, Michael J. McGlynn, Mayor, signature file on paper. Chair, on the motion of approval by Councilor Penta,
All those in favor, uh, chair, uh, requests a roll call on this. Councilor Camuso? Yes. Councilor Caviello? Yes. Councilor Knight? Yes. Vice-President Malauulu-Kern? Yes. Councilor Marks? Yes. Councilor Penta? Yes.
Yes. With vote of six in the affirmative, one absent. The motion carries. A motion by Councilor Knight to take papers on the hand of the clerk and then to address papers that have long been tabled. All those in favor? All those opposed? From the city clerk's hand, offered by Councilor Knight, be it resolved that the Memphis City Council express its deep and sincere condolences to the family of David Grassico. In addition, offered by Councilor Marks,
Be it resolved that a moment of silence be held for longtime Metro President Barbara Steele Cassidy on her recent passing. Please join me in standing for a moment of silence. One more, I apologize. And also offered by Councilor Camuso, be it resolved that the Medford City Council send its condolences to the family of Mary May McLean, who passed away recently. May was a longtime employee of the Medford Public Library.
Councilor Camuso. I move suspension of the rules to clear up some of the old business on the council agenda that's been lingering since 2014 in some cases. Yes, on the motion to clean up some unfinished business. All those in favor? Opposed?
17-633 Acceptance of General Laws, Chapter 48, 59B, 59C, 59D, Establishment of Reserve Fire Force. Motion to take it off the table. All those in favor? Those opposed? Motion by council. Motion to receive and place on file. On motion of council to receive and place on file. All those in favor? Roll call vote. Roll call vote has been requested.
First one, so. Reserve fighter. It's been there since 2013, 13, 633. And never was acted on, never pursued. Councilor Camuso. Yes. Councilor Cabrillo. Yes. Yes. Councilor Knight. Yes. Vice President Lowell-Kern. Yes. Councilor Mox. Yes. Councilor Penta. Yes.
Yes, vote of six in the affirmative, one absent. The motion carries. Motion of Councilor Camuso to take 14-540, show class hearing, CTC, gold refinery, 6 Salem Street off the table. All those in favor? Move to replace on file. The motion that the item be received and placed on file. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries.
14-568 solicited as information on channel 3 motion by councillor on night to take it off the table all those in favor all those opposed We got that report several months ago, yeah Yeah, we get the report though. We're waiting to get it. It's just sitting on the agenda now. We got the report We got a report back on that didn't we? Motion to receive in place on file
No, because the paper's been tabled. I mean, this is, I think you can read the resolution. Offered by Councilor Penta, 14-568 offered by Councilor Penta. This is July 15th, 2014. Be it resolved that a brief discussion be made regarding the city solicitor's most concerning information forwarded to the council regarding the dissolution petition of Metro Community Access, a.k.a. Channel 3 and its former president.
No, but the solicitor has kept us updated along the whole process. All right, let him respond again. On the motion of Councilor Penta that... All right, so leave it there. Refer it back to the city. On the motion of Councilor Penta to refer this paper back to the city
Solicitor for further update. All those in favor? All those opposed? Motion carries. 14-739. Motion to take off the table by Councilor Longo Kern. All those in favor? All those opposed? Tax rate and surplus funds tabled December 23rd, 2014. Motion to receive and place on file. On the motion of Councilor Camuso to receive and place on file. All those in favor? All those opposed?
Motion carries 15 dash 0 0 5 motion by a consul Penta to take off the table. Uh, all those in favor, all those opposed, Mary Kate Ben and Roy, uh, to address the council and met the senior center on the consulate Penta particular on this particular matter, this lady was going to appear before the council as it related to the new kiosks that were being put in. And as a result of, I, unfortunately, I don't believe she came to the meeting on that night.
but the Republic people said at that point in time that they were going to have a meeting down there at the end of January. Then they bumped it up to March and then they changed it to a, to a later date. And I think it was in May. So with that being said, um, that was the purpose of, uh, the meeting of the senior center, uh, how and where would the seniors be able to park and what was the, uh, what was the process going to be? So they brought the kiosk down there.
All those in favor, all those opposed, motion carries. 15-056, on the motion of Councilor Knight to take off the table, to provide updated breakdown of bonds. On the motion of Councilor... On the motion of Councilor Long-Current to receive and place on file, all those in favor, all those opposed. 15-631, motion by... Councilor Camus, on the motion of Councilor...
Well, I look current to receiving plays on file. All those in favor. All those opposed. 15 dash 432 motion to take off the table. Uh, leave that there, Mr. President. We'll be discussing that later on. That's coming back this next week. We're meeting on that. That's going to stay on the table. 15 dash five 51 motion to take off the table.
All those in favor, all those opposed, $75,000 appropriate for potholes and repairs. Received, placed on file. That this motion, on the motion of the Council, also received and placed on file. All those in favor, all those opposed, 15-556. What's that? Revised amendment to fiscal 2016. Mr. Clark, what is that? That was the money to cut the budget and then take it out of the other account. The budget passed.
It's over with. Motion of a council along the current receiving place on file. All those in favor. All those opposed. Motion carries 15 dash five 74 update on Medford cable access. Refer this one, Mr. President. Um, can we just leave that upstanding right now? Because it's the other one. It's the same as 14 five 68 from the city solicitor update on the TV three. Yeah. Just, just merge them together because I was going to say merge these two together.
I get you that on the motion of a councilor Penta to take this on the table, off the table, all those in favor, all those opposed on the motion of council Penta to send 15 dash five 74 back to the city solicitor and the administration in it, that'd be merged with 14 five 16 dash five 68 and ask for a speedy response. All those in favor, all those opposed 15 dash five Oh six.
Hearing National Grid and Vizaria Verizon on Canal Street. Motion to take off the table by Councilor Knight. All those in favor? All those opposed? Chair records for a motion. I think they're still working on that. This go back to the table. Pending update from the engineer by Councilor Capuzo. All those in favor? All those opposed? 15-561. Receive and place on file. All those in favor? All those opposed? Without prejudice, in case that gentleman comes back,
Roll call. Roll call has been requested on the item number 1561, which was removed from the table tonight and by a motion of counsel Longo Kern to receive and place on file without prejudice. I'm just saying that, so if the gentleman does want to come back and appear, it's within the 90 days. It's right around the 90 days, but. Very good. Mr. Clerk, please call the roll.
Councilor Camuso? Yes. Councilor Caraviello? Yes. Councilor Night? Yes. Vice President Lowenthal? Yes. Councilor Marx? Yes. Councilor Penta? Yes. President Dela Cruz? Yes. I take a vote of six in the affirmative and one absent. The motion carries. Who's the next two on the table? We've got a couple more pieces in the hand of the clerk. Did I say that backwards? Yikes. Offered by Councilor Caraviello, be it resolved that the City Council congratulate
the Medford Junior Mustangs on their winning of the Eastern Mass Super Bowl. Councilor Caviello. Thank you, Mr. President. I just wanted to congratulate the Junior Mustangs. And I'd be remiss. Several of the girls' cheerleading teams also took first place in some of their competitions. So I just want to send the congratulations to all those young men and women for their great job. On the motion of Councilor Caviello,
that they be congratulated for a great job. All those in favor? All those opposed? Good luck. Be it resolved by the Medford City Council, offered by Councilor Knight, that the City Council congratulate, one, Medford High School golf team, greater Boston League champs. Two, Medford High School boys' soccer team, greater Boston League champs and state semifinalists. And three, Medford girls' soccer, greater Boston League champions and state tourney participants.
Councilor Knight. Mr. President, yes, we've had a very successful fall season this year, and in course with past practice, I'd like to invite the following GBL championship teams down to receive a memoriam citation from the city council in recognition of their hard work, their teamwork, and their efforts, Mr. President. Very good. On the motion for approval by Councilor Knight. All those in favor? All those opposed? With pleasure. Announcements by Councilor Lungo-Kern.
And thank you, President De La Russo. Last week, Council Marks and I, which was supported by the entire council, asked that the month of December be free parking month to help out the commerce within our city. And it wasn't supported by the administration in full, but I just want to announce and make sure that residents know that parking will be free of charge on Saturdays.
during the holiday shopping period throughout Medford Square as well as Haines Square, West Medford Square, Hillside Square, and South Medford Square. So on Saturdays beginning November 28th and ending January 2nd, patrons visiting local businesses in these designated areas will be able to obtain goods and services without having to pay meters or kiosks.
I'd also just like to ask that we do put signage on our kiosk that Saturday is free parking, or we make sure that the meters do not accept money so that everybody knows. I mean, it's going to be hard to get the word out to everybody, but Saturdays from November 28th to January 2nd, there will be free parking in Medford, in our squares. So I want to thank the administration for taking our recommendation.
And moving it forward, even though it's not in its entirety, it's something. It's something for the customers and the businesses. So, thank you. Thank you. The records. Councilor Penta. Mr. President, earlier this evening, the Committee on Transportation met as it related to papers in committee. And some of the things we discussed were the concerns as it relates to the Craddock Bridge, bus stops in Medford Square and in West Medford.
and other ancillary matters. What was disturbing that came out of that meeting was when one of the, um, one of the, uh, business owners came in and indicated to us that, um, per his conversation with representative Donato, who had a conversation with somebody from the mass department of transportation, they have been meeting here with the city of Medford on a biweekly basis with a gentleman from the department of public works. And that is very disturbing to hear that because right now nobody,
assert anything, we have asked on numerous occasions for some kind of transparency as it relates to what is going on, as it relates to not only the Karatek Bridge, the time schedule, the lighting, the closing down of the business, just having some basis of information. We were also told and notified, and Councilor Caviello, he can correct me on this, that the Chamber of Commerce hasn't even been a party to any kind of response or any kind of notification from the State Department of Transportation.
That leaves a big void right now into trying to understand what is going on between the state department of transportation and their interaction here in the city of Medford. If in fact the city of Medford is meeting with the state department of transportation and they are not notifying this council and the office of community development is not being notified and the business merchants aren't being notified. Chamber of commerce is not being notified and the council has asked on numerous occasions for an update as to what's going on.
there was a serious problem as it relates to that whole Craddock bridge operation. Another part of the committee report was asking, you know, it's supposed to be six days a week, double shifts, and everybody knows they're not down there six days a week, double shifts. So maybe that's the reason why it's taking two and a half years to maybe complete this, but further asking a question on that. Also, I believe the bus stop as it relates to in West and South Medford, that's in front of Oasis,
the request to have it be moved across the street to where the dry cleaners is over there. That seemed to be an understandable issue. I believe that there will be a meeting set up in the South Medford area over there quickly as it relates to the bus stop, not only the bus stop moving, but a place for the business merchants when they have deliveries that take place over there. And I believe also the request and the concern was to go forward
regarding the bus stops in Medford Square that would be coming down on Main Street and having them either detoured to Riverside Ave or River Street or whatever it might be. But we got a notification, Mr. Clerk, you can correct me if I'm wrong, that the gentleman who now is in charge of bus stops with the T made an indication that he doesn't come out to nighttime meetings, is that correct? And because he doesn't come out to nighttime meetings, this doesn't make any sense at all.
So we're going to have to figure out another way how to move them. And maybe our representative, Mr. Donato can make this guy understand it. You know, everyone works during the course of the day and you know, and that's part of their job to come to the city of Medford. This is a huge project. It's a new huge undertaking. Bus stops are a huge issue as it relates to this, this whole undertaking as a result of their lack of transparency and coming forward. I believe it was a vote of the committee for which council Lungo current,
and Michael Knox, and unfortunately he had to leave because of a family issue. We made a request that a temporary cease and desist on the whole project of the Craddock Bridge become operative. It's obvious that they're being absolutely non-responsive, non-responsive to the council, not responsive to anyone here in the city of Medford. But the sad part about it is if they really are meeting with somebody from the Department of Public Works,
And we're not being notified. And we have asked over and over and over again. This shows you the complete breakdown that is taking place. And the only way maybe to get their attention is to move, Mr. President, and ask for a temporary cease and desist to bring them to the table so we can have this discussion as to why we, the taxpayers, we, the council, we, the chamber, and we, the administration, aren't being brought up to date and being told it's up to date. You know, it's just an unfortunate matter.
Businesses are being affected. One business merchant came in there and indicated how he had it closed down. Lost over $3,000 worth of business on a particular night, the night that they put the bridge up, with no notification and what have you. So- Go ahead. I don't want to interrupt you, Counselor. Go ahead. If I could just share one piece of information on that long presentation that you gave us. The legislative liaison for the Department of Transportation was aware of the situation with the bus stop inspector.
or overseer, whatever his proper title is. And he's reached out to the legislative liaison for the MBTA and CC'd her on our meeting that's coming up next week when the group will come down and present. I'm in the process of reaching out to her as well, but unfortunately I don't know if you've ever called the MBTA and gone into the phone system
And it feels like you're going into a spiral to another world. So I'm trying to reach out as well. So hopefully- Well, the gentleman that's now replaced the lady that was in charge of bus stops, I'll give you his number. I'll give everybody his number if you want. Oh, I've spoken to him. Yeah. But who I wanted to speak to was the legislative liaison. But it won't make any difference who the legislative liaison is. The fact of the matter is this is all after the fact. And I know you have a meeting scheduled, I think, for next Tuesday? Yeah. Which is next Tuesday.
And I think if they get the temperament that the council is not happy, and this seems to be a forced situation, these resolutions go back to June of this past year, September of this year, for which I've asked on numerous occasions, and other members of the council have expressed their disdain as to what's going on. There's absolutely, it seems to be a forced situation. And the only way to keep their feet to the fire is to let them know that not only are we upset, but we don't approve of what's going on. And all this is is basically having a temporary restraining order against you,
to not do any more business until such time that you get this issue resolved. Who is the clerk of the works? Who is the city's clerk of the works on this particular project? We don't have any of these people. And if we do, they must be mysterious people, because nobody knows who they are. This council should be apprised through every part of that particular project. This has been going on since 2003, when Councilor Longo Kern brought this resolution up for the very first time.
This is now 2015, 12 years later. So the bridge did not sink in 12 years. It's been there for over 100 years. It's quite obvious that it'll make it. The fact of the matter is, Mr. President, sometimes you've got to push and be hard to make sure you get your questions resolved. So that's the result. That was the report coming out of the committee. So I'll move the question to the floor. If I may. Madam Vice President. Madam Vice President wanted to speak. Did you speak, Counselor? I didn't hear you.
I said that I would like a ruling on Rule 35A. Rule 35A. I was just going to say, I was at the meeting at 530 and I too, there's a lack of communication and maybe we should hold off one week before the cease and desist because the communication is between the city council, city hall, DPW, OCD, and the business owners.
The business owners really don't know what's going on. They don't know any given night there's going to be work done. They're going to be shut down, especially the restaurants in the area. So if we could get an update from the DPW director, does MassDOT actually meet with somebody from the DPW every other week to discuss what's going on? Because if so, that communication should be forwarded to the rest of the city and especially the business owners and the city council and obviously the administration.
But I also wanted to get an update from OCD Director Lauren DiLorenzo, because she was not involved in the process a year, maybe two ago, when they were moving forward with it. So I'd like to know now, is she being updated? Does she know what's going on? Does she know any given night when they'll be doing work? Or is that, who knows, and why isn't it being communicated throughout the rest of the city, is my question. Because that is a problem. If I owned a business in Medford Square,
and I knew a temporary bridge was going to be put up, and the street was going to be shut down, I would want some notice. And I would, you know, business owners deserve some notice. So I agree with what Councilor Penta is saying. I was there for the meeting. We listened to the business owners. So if we could just get those questions answered first, because is it the lack of communication within City Hall trickling down, or is there actually just a lack of communication from MassDOT?
The city deserves explanation on an outline of what's going to take place week after week after week, since this is going to inconvenience us for another two to three years. Madam Vice President, so that we're going to do as an amendment. Well, in addition to the report, we'd have to withdraw then the request for termination of activities. But can I just briefly comment?
I receive at least twice a week, because I've been involved since day one on the whole Green Line Extension project, a very well-managed project, whether you agree with it or not.
development of its history throughout the decade here. Nonetheless, twice a week, anybody who's on their email list gets an email blast on updates on every aspect of that project, whether it's in Medford, Somerville, Cambridge. Greenline. Greenline. There's no reason why. It seems to me that this is a matter of Harvard communication. The incident two weeks ago, when they shut down Main Street and people weren't notified
um, is, uh, is horrid. And, uh, there's gotta be an issue regarding communication. I'm not surprised that, uh, any, uh, major construction project has biweekly updates with the DPW or somebody in this building. But, um, it clearly, again, that's not being communicated out. And, uh, there's no reason why the businesses should suffer. And we were told at the beginning, uh, this summer that there would be a outreach person from, uh,
Is it Zane Construction, Zillow, Zane? Zopo. Zopo Construction. So I hope we can get that all resolved, but I want to recognize Councilor Camuso, who's been patiently waiting while I've spoken from the chair. Thank you, Mr. President.
And I certainly agree with Councillor Lungo-Kern's frustrations and the business owners that should have close to up to the minute what's going on with the project, especially when it affects their businesses. But I don't want to send out the wrong message that if the City Council votes for a cease and desist,
that the trucks are going to pack up, they're going to leave, and there'll be no work that gets done. That's just inaccurate. It's irresponsible for us to let people think that we have the power to do that, because we do not. Furthermore, if we do delay it, if we had the authority for a cease and desist, it's only going to add additional days on the end of the project. So it'll be two years and three days if we did that. So as I stated, I think they have to work on their communication.
The particular department that is overseeing this project, which is a state project, if not the City of Medford, the Mass Department of Transportation, as the President indicated, between them and the Gaming Commission, I'm getting emails twice a week.
with updates on the projects. And given that that's the same entity, MassDOT, I don't see why we can't get the same, and interested people like the restaurants, like the banks, like the auto schools and everyone else in the particular area can sign up for those alerts as well, as people along the Green Line Extension route receive weekly. So if we could just ask for that, but I just don't want to send out the wrong message that a cease and desist
is something that we have any control over whatsoever. Thank you. Councillor Pentland. I don't think—I hear what you're saying, Councillor Camuso. It's not sending out the wrong message. It's sending out a message that we're really upset that they have no way to operate like this. But two points. The first one is this, that even if this were to happen, that back in the days—that's not true because they were supposed to be doing two shifts right from the beginning. They're lucky if they work three days a week, if they're working three to four right now.
and they're not doing double shifts. So I'm not really worried about that. I'm just more concerned over the fact that if, in fact, these meetings have taken place, then the responsible person in behalf of the city has failed to notify the appropriate authority, whether it be at the mayor's office, the council, OCD office, or whatever it might be. And the last part, Mr. Clerk, I forgot to mention, is to get the minutes of those meetings. I believe it's on there. The minutes of the meetings that
DOT has had whoever the city person is that has been to the meetings on this biweekly basis, you know, if, um, if a representative Donato has been told by DOT that the meeting has been taking place, uh, according to him, as he explained to one of the business vendors in the community, then, you know, something's going on here. Nobody knows nothing about it. It doesn't make any sense. It's unfair. So with that being said, I'll hold off on a week until we, after the meeting of next Tuesday, and then, uh, let's just see where we're going. But you know,
Hopefully, they'll be really forthcoming with some of these things. They're willing to budge and work with us. Beyond that, you just hope the MBTA comes here, too, because you can't piecemeal this thing together. It's not making any sense. Well, it's not that. That's why we have our representatives and senators. This is where their clout comes in, OK? If they're really worth their salt as an elected official up in the statehouse, they'll get those people here from the MBTA, because they're not going to want to hear us.
So on the motion of... Mr. President, I agree with Councilor Pinter, you know, as far as the lack of communication and even with the chamber and everybody else. But again, I don't know if we're in a position to dictate whether we can do a cease and desist order on this company. But I do recognize that there does need to be more communication happening here. And I'd hate to send the wrong message to the construction company.
by, by sending FC synthesis. Very good. So on the motion of council of Penta that the city council receive, um, the minutes, the minutes of meetings, any and all meetings between the city representative and D O T. Okay. And also that we have a representative, um, point of order council night pursuant to council rules and the rule 35, no report of a committee shall be received unless agreed to in committee and actually assembled.
Rule 35A, the council and the president shall review all committee papers in a committee of the whole meeting thereafter. Well, the whole idea, Mr. President, is every single committee that's made a report has been voted upon and accepted by this council. Now, all of a sudden, what are we going to do? Go to a committee of the whole meeting and discuss what took place there? If the council wanted to be there, he walked right by, couldn't come into the room. The rules are the rules, Mr. President. There may be rules, but you know something, Mr. President? Let's be a little bit logical here. Read the rule. No report of a committee.
shall be received unless agreed to and a committee actually assembled. The committee was actually assembled. It was the transportation committee.
It wasn't a committee of the whole. Read rule 35, OK? That's what took place. And then we'll read rule 35A. The council presidents shall review all committee papers in a committee of the whole meeting, which hasn't happened yet, Mr. President. It most certainly has. And I personally, based upon the plethora of information that the gentleman's given us, based upon the information that the gentleman's provided with us, I'd like to do a little bit more research, because there might be some questions that I have, Mr. Brown. Well, maybe if you came into the meeting, you would have been able to understand what was going on. That wouldn't have changed anything.
That wouldn't have changed anything. Mr. President. We are going to, yes, we're going to wish everybody a happy Thanksgiving. Move on the paper. I'm not going to rule on this paper tonight. Why? Because I need to study it. I challenge the chair, Mr. President.
It's quite obvious. And that means that every single committee that meets and comes to this council floor and submits a report and submits a report and the council votes on it. That's those have all been illegal. Is that what we're saying? They've all been not right. That means every single committee that's gone and had a committee report and came back to this council, read the committee report and the council voted on it was done wrong. Why are we doing this? And what do you even have a committee for? Point of information, Mr. President. I believe the explanation of the committee report is informational.
for the other members of the council who don't serve on that committee. And then when we meet on the committee... The committee report was brought forward like it always is. Mr. President, I wasn't talking. Mr. President, I rest my case. I'm not going to be interrupted repeatedly. I rest my case, Mr. President. Good. Be an obstructionist all you want. Move the paper, Mr. President. There's nothing wrong. Either that or change all the rules around here, because these committees mean absolutely nothing. I've read that. You've opposed it in every step. These mean absolutely nothing. Move the paper, Mr. President.
Why don't we take a recess?
In effect, uh, there is no agreement, uh, or ability for the, uh, um, committee to, uh, retract a part of what it agreed to, uh, report out since it's not been reconvened nor is its membership present. So therefore the questions that the motion is that the following questions be asked and those questions were enumerated.
by the councilor and taken down by the clerk. On that motion, all those in favor? Aye. All those opposed? Thank you. Happy Thanksgiving again. And the records of the meeting of November 17th were presented to Councilor Caviello for inspection. And we're grateful before we do the records. Councilor Camuso, yes. What do you think
I posed this to the body in the form of a resolution, having a committee of the whole and take up all papers that are in all subcommittees. We have stuff in there from 2007 that just never dealt with it. Or they could have been acted upon. They could have been acted upon, exactly. I looked at the list. So in other words, every time the clerk prints out the city council tracking sheet for subcommittees, committees of the whole, it's just wasting ink and paper. Therefore, I think that this,
time where, especially with two members of the council are moving on into retirement, it would be the appropriate time to clean up the business beforehand of this particular council. I think it's a good idea, but whatever the council wishes. And if we want to keep stuff in certain committees, you keep it there. But there is stuff that works itself out. I think procedurally, Mr. President, papers need to report themselves out of committee, have to be reported out of committee to meet the committee of the whole, right? So they'd be in committee until the subcommittee reports them out.
So everybody has to call a subcommittee report. So the subcommittee meetings would have to be called. Or each individual subcommittee chair can perform an audit of the items that are in their committee, and then report back to the council what's sleeping and what's alive. And then we can meet as a committee of the whole and discuss what's going on from there. I mean, whatever procedurally we decide to do. I mean, I think procedure is important, Mr. President. Procedure is established so that we're open and transparent.
I agree 100%, but I also think we have to do whatever the proper procedure is to clear up the council tracking resolution. It's 17 pages long. I say that in a funny fashion. It's not 17 pages, but it's quite lengthy, and it's stuff that we're talking about buildings that don't even exist in our community anymore. We get papers, and they're talking about the DPW water building that burned down. The water building is no longer there. Whatever the proper procedure is, I think we should address all of it.
And a lot of the ones that are on Committee of the Whole, although they may not have been reported out, have all been acted upon otherwise. If not, you guys deal with it next year. I mean, if it's been in committee since 2007, chances are nothing's going to happen with it anyway. That is true. We can be cognizant of it any time we call a committee meeting. Do you want to do it on a Friday night? No, we can do it this Thursday, 10 o'clock, instead of going to Medford-Hormel Stadium. Madam Vice President?
I was just saying we can do it in stages. Next person that calls up subcommittee on safety, report all the papers out, plus have their meeting. Perfect. Committee of the whole meeting. Let's spend an extra half hour so we can go through those papers and then have our committee of the whole meeting just to take it in stages. Mr. Rules is going to, yeah. The rules are the rules. I didn't make them up. They're in place so that we can provide order so that it doesn't turn into lunacy. You know, that's why we have the rules.
We're avoiding lunacy at all expenses. The records, how'd you find them, Councilor? Mr. President, I have found the records in order, and I wish all my fellow councilors a happy Thanksgiving. On the motion of Councilor Caravaglio to approve the records, all those in favor, all those opposed? On his motion for a happy Thanksgiving, all those in favor, all those opposed? On Councilor Pente's motion for a dismissal, all those in favor, all those opposed?