meeting. We have a linkage trust committee meeting October 31st, 2023.
$1,080,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,
open space plan for parks, $3,025. Rights Pond rain garden project, $24. Professional technical services, $1,677.72. Electric ice edger, Wakanti Rink, $8,000. Harris Park project, $23,648.26. Brooks Elementary Park improvements, $5,610. For a total of $47,265.78.
roads linkage expenditure accounts, UHF radios for DPW, remaining balance is $4.62, and our water and sewer linkage expenditure accounts, we have for piers to infrastructure due to flooding, $6,193.50, Boston Ave water main replacement, $8.70, and sidewalk infrastructure, $750.96.
$101.77 for a total of $7,054.93. So first I'll just take the attendance before we have our two papers. We have member, actually it's three, sorry, President Morrell. Present. Director Dickinson. You're on mute, Bob.
and give us a thumbs up. Oh, no, no. Okay, present, Bob is present, and I am present, three, present, zero, absent. We have approval of $9,172 in Parks and Recreation Linkage Trust Funds to go towards the change order cost of the Gillis Field accessibility renovation. Is there a motion for approval?
motion to approve. I'm president Morrell seconded by director Dickinson if you want to just give a thumbs up seconded by director Dickinson and I'll call the roll president Morrell. Yes. Director Dickinson.
can you hear me now? Yes, I can. Yes. Yes. Okay, great. Yes. Okay. And myself? Yes. Three in the affirmative, zero in the negative. And then we also have approval of meeting minutes from October 27, 2022, and October 6, 2023. Is there a motion for approval of those minutes? Motion to approve. Seconded by? Second. By Dirk Dickinson. I'll call the roll. President Morrell?
Yes. Director Dickinson? Yes.
I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
The Riverside Plaza Park project was $1,000.80, and the Riverside Plaza project was $3,600. Got it, okay. And these would all just go back to the general, the linkage fund, these accounts would be liquidated, they go back to the linkage fund, like general account?
I have a motion to approve. I have a second.
And myself, yes. So first item on the agenda has been approved, which was the approval of the liquidations of inactive project accounts. And that is it. Motion for approval to adjourn. So moved. And seconded by? So moved. Director Dickinson. Second. Thank you. Motion to adjourn. Call the roll now. President Morrell. Yes. Director Dickinson.
Yes and myself yes meeting is adjourned, thank you very much appreciate your time thanks everyone.