It's about 10 guys that have an opportunity, not just to stand on the podium, but to stand on top of the podium. And today shook out exactly how we thought it was going to shake out. Yeah, we know that this race is going to be extremely tight. And with 400 points available, it is going to be something where all of these athletes have to focus on seizing the moment over all else.
And the person who sees the moment the best yesterday was Jason Hopper, who will be donning the white leader jersey for the first time in his career. Yeah, you love to see it. Jason Hopper stormed onto the CrossFit scene a few years ago and has been an athlete close to those podium dreams.
And this weekend, he's going to have an opportunity to make it a reality. We'll see how Jason now dons that pressure of the white and red leader jersey. The pressure is about as tight as it can be, as the leaderboard is more compressed than we've ever seen after day number one. Two sets of ties on the leaderboard. But Jason Hopper is not alone, because Jay Crouch is tied in points with him at 260. That's right. Jay Crouch, we talked about having that it factor yesterday. And it's it in the CrossFit competition.
looks like a very well-rounded output, and he's got that in droves. He might not be an outlier and win any event outright, but you're going to see him towards the top a lot. And that's how you chase the podium of Fitness on Earth. And Roman Krennikov, who had a great event, won. And just a solid day overall, sitting in third place, four points out. That's right. Roman's a consistent threat, and he is a home run hitter, Chase. So there's going to be some stuff on the menu, and it could pop up today within these 400 points.
that are going to be right up Roman's alley. Here's what's on the menu today for you viewers at home. Event one will start with the men for day number two. Four scored events, 400 points up for grabs. And I couldn't think of a better way to put it, but today is truly moving day for these athletes. Individual action from MVP Arena coming up next.
I don't know if I can describe 6PM in one word, but if I had two words, it'd be controlled chaos.
Each of our classes has its own unique characteristic. The 6 p.m. class is a little unique in that it used to be a class that we had a hard time filling and over the last year or two it's become our only capped class because we will now have upwards of 23 to 26, 27 members in that class so it kind of become its own little family.
Some of the groups in 6PM, they're either highly competitive or they're kind of just starting out. It is controlled chaos. It is chaos.
Everybody just kind of understands how busy that class is, and everybody loves it so much and wants to be a part of it, that they help me kind of control all of it. Nobody's ever interfering with each other. Everybody works really well. Everybody shares a barbell if they need to. If we have to run two full heats on a workout with like a 10-minute delay, it's not a big deal. They're so good about just listening. They actually listen, unlike some other classes.
We do kind of a social beer club once a month, where a group of us will go out and visit a local small business, try them, just get outside these four walls. Maybe someone from the 5 a.m. class may meet someone from the 7 p.m. class, where they usually wouldn't. That gives them an opportunity to find camaraderie and family and home. Keep it a nice, tight core. We're gonna go five, straight arm pullovers.
6PM Cross is unique in that I think it's kind of a really cool cross section of not just our gym, but I think of kind of society.
You have a couple of our coaches that may attend that class. And then you have some people that didn't really know CrossFit from anything before they joined here. And now they're definitely getting outside their comfort zone. We have young kids who are just trying to move and stay healthy. You have kind of the three fire breathers in there as well that like to go head to head and enjoy that push that they give each other.
A little friendly rivalry, a little competition every day. Me, Brandon, Dustin. We had this thing where we'd always send like a Matt Frazier, you know, meme over to whoever won the workout that day. Progressed into, what if we did a leader's jersey? Whoever won the workout that day would wear the shirt the next day and everybody else would have to look at him wearing the dang leader jersey and then, you know, do the Matt Frazier pose.
So we always kind of know who the top dog in the gym is. Usually me, almost never Brandon. I mean, I'm just the old guy trying to just hold on to whatever I got. I was lucky enough to win yesterday, so I am wearing the new jersey today. And still! This is my social interaction. And I'm just, you know, proud to have these guys as buddies. And they want to compete with me. They want to compete next to me and against me. So, yeah, I'm really appreciative of these guys. He's got to do his laundry again tonight.
A lot of the uniqueness of our gym and our classes is the way each class becomes its own family. They don't miss a class. They show up for each other and they support each other through everything. Cancer survivors and all those things in that class. It's a microcosm of not only incendia, but I think it's a microcosm of society, which is really cool.
Welcome back inside MVP Arena as day two of the 2025 CrossFit Games continues. And it is effectively moving day here in Albany, New York. I'm Chasing with Adrian Condi and Mr. Saxon Pancheck.
Welcome back, buddy. Welcome back. We are here for event number four. You've got to test this event. But this is the CrossFit Games. Dave Castro just announces a little twist to what we announced. And the 300s are going to 400. And we're adding an extra 50 feet at the end on that last handstand walk. Yeah, I think this is, originally with the 300, I thought it was going to be a little bit more about the transitions. I think it's going to be who can clear the fatigue the fastest on that run.
And with this particular event, it is the Albany Grip Trip, Adrian. And this is about as classy as you can get. We've got some monostructural work. We've got the deadlift and the handstand walk. What's the wrinkle here in this particular event? I mean, the wrinkle, of course, is the additional running. But it's going to be a 400-meter run. They're going to go through 12 deadlifts. And then, of course, we are now
Handstand walking 100 feet, where they're going to go 50 feet out and 50 feet back. What's your tempo recipe for success here? You've got to be pretty disciplined on keeping your cadence. And that's going to be with the runner. It's going to be a little bit of a blind run, knowing where your competitors are. And then you've got to race the rest, which means it's OK to break those deadlifts. But you need to be urgent in getting to that next set. And it's a similar approach with the handstand walk.
Lane assignments for heat number one. We have two heats to start the morning off. We flip the field, we've got two sets of 15. Rescoring after every single event. Have a lot of athletes.
trying to get their way out of the bottom 15. They had a tough day one, and good for them. They got 400 points up for grabbing. Saxon, you tested this. Where are the athletes, and when are they going to feel it the most in this event? I think getting into that second run and that third run, I think that's going to be the most important, especially with those runs being a little bit longer. I think looking at their posture running, it will be a really good indicator.
Day two underway, starting with the 400-meter run. On these runners, and Adrian, we've talked about this, we went long yesterday on the run, six miles, but that was outside.
on some asphalt and roads. What's the difference between that and the runner? Well, it's a few things. And Saxon and I were actually chatting about this right when he got up here. I was like, sir, these woodways are a little different than what you can find between most floor wall affiliates. And what this tends to do is add some taxing to the back half of your body. The hamstrings, the glutes, the low back are going to be fatigued a bit differently than what these athletes feel when they're running on regular asphalt.
The meters will be designated in front of their lanes. Again, 400 total. And speaking like Air Runner to Air Runner, there's a difference, too, because we haven't seen a Woodway version in live competition, maybe ever, especially at the CrossFit Games. What's the difference? Yeah, I think there's a little more tension in it. So I think it's going to blow that posterior up just a tad more. And I think you'll spend a little bit more time on there than you're expecting. You know, we're looking at these athletes just passing that 200 meter mark and we're about a minute 10 in.
You know, that's putting us a little over two minutes for a 400. So I would say outside, these guys are running anywhere from a minute 30 to a minute 45. So there's going to be a little more time on there for sure. Again, this is five rounds, 40-meter runs on the runner, 12 deadlifts at 350 pounds with the axle bar, and then 100-foot handstand walk down and back 50 feet across the field. Now, in a five-round event, Adrian, is that
is that you use that first round to say, hey, listen, I know how I felt in testing. I know how I felt in the warm-up area, but let's see how I feel out in the competition floor. Use that first round to get a feel for how your body's responding.
Yeah, I mean, to a degree, Chase, what you want to do is make sure that you get off that runner in full control, but immediately ready to deadlift. Where you'll start to see athletes run into trouble is if they get off that runner and there's a lot of pausing and waiting before they approach the bar, you know they overshot their run pace. First athlete off the runner was actually Tiago Lucis at a split time of 2.35.
You tested this event, and the early twist was that the deadlifts would be done with an axle bar. 350 pounds for elite games athletes like this necessarily isn't the heaviest weight, but for 12 reps times 5, 60 total, what's the trick of that axle bar?
Yeah, I think it's fast, manageable sets. You got to stay over top of the barbell. Don't move your feet. Make sure you're dropping it over your shoes and pick it up right away. You're seeing Nick Matthew here. He moved pretty quickly on that deadlift. He was aggressive. He's kind of looking around and seeing where other athletes are and how they're breaking. Right now, I would say he's kind of controlling this race, and we'll see what he does on this next run.
The deadliest split, the fastest one, is Colton Mertens, who finished it in 19 seconds. Nick Matthew, as you mentioned, was six seconds behind him. But it'll be Matthew to the runner first. Handstand walk split for Nick Matthew is 37 seconds. Most of the time will be spent on the runner. If that's the case, is there more of an emphasis to push the pace on the one that's going to take the longest?
I think, yes, but I think also, you know, if you push that too hard, it's going to blow that posterior up a little bit more. I think, you know, who can clear fatigue the fastest within that first 100 meters, you know, if you can do it in the first 20 to 50, I think that would be ideal and be able to pick that speed up. I think seeing who gets off this next run will be a really good indicator on who's going to be able to move through these next two rounds.
fastest split we had on the first 400 meters. We said it was Tiago Lucis as Colton Mertens had the fastest deadlift split, seven seconds faster than anyone. And Colton Mertens is one of those athletes that had a great off-season, great in-season qualifying. Best place finish was 18th at the CrossFit Games. And finding himself in, I would say, a place on the leaderboard that is not going to suit him for the rest of the day.
It's not optimal for Colton. He's going to have an opportunity to do some moving. We know that with what is looming and what has been announced. We understand he's going to have that there. Nick Matthewchase, what I like about what we saw there, he was very composed on that first run, which he's clearly showing that again. But him making fast work of those deadlifts put him in that situation that Saxton alluded to where he was the one in control as we made our way back to the treadmill.
One of those things you said looming later today, it'd actually be the next event for the individuals. And that is a one rep max back squat. And I can't think of two things worse to set me up for success there than all the 2,000 meters of running on a runner and 60 heavy deadlifts with an axle bar. Hey, posterior city today. Yanukovsky in his 10th CrossFit Games.
had just missed last year for 10 consecutive, but he is in rare company of 10 CrossFit Games appearances. Nick Matthew off the runner first. Nick Matthew split on the first one much faster. Sorry, on the second one, much faster, 2.04.
He's breaking those into 9 and 3, quick break. I like that. You know, a small set before kicking up on those handstands, I think it gives him a little extra breath to be able to make that transition pretty quick. And the cadence on that is very fast as well. He's not spending too much time at the top where he's under tension. Andrew, you see a lot of these athletes breaking up early.
Is that coming from testing or conscious decision, knowing that this event is more of a grind than people may think it's going to be? No doubt about it, being very predicted and practiced. Also, I think it's a bit of a response to that grip fatigue. You're going to notice a lot of difference in bar speeds as we watch the deadlifts come off the ground. Some of that is their ability to move a load. And some of that is the grip fatigue, in which if they move too quickly, they're only going to fatigue their hands even more through rep to rep. And we did a lot of pegboard and hanging yesterday.
Well, it's called Albany grip trip for a reason. And we talk about grip on the axle bar. But one thing that people may not understand, handstand walking is a taxing grip element as well. Absolutely. You know, the time under tension on the handstands, especially, I mean, you're talking 100 feet, you know, over five rounds. That's going to add up. McMatthew still in the lead.
And Nick Matthews, one of those athletes that is really looking forward to that max back slot. Colton Mertens had a tough day yesterday. Some of that was execution, but another that was equipment. And, you know, Saxon.
I mean, you see what happens in a day like that. How do you treat last night and respond coming into this morning? I think you have the present. You have to focus on the present and the points you have on the table, and that's it. I think everybody will have, most people will have a bad event at some point, and that was your event. So now it's time to move forward and see what you can capitalize on next. I will say this, if you look at Colton Stride, he has a very fast cadence.
When you're moving on one of these runners, you don't want to be reaching. That's where you're really going to tax that posterior. So he has a fast, choppy stride, which is going to allow him to move a little bit more and use those quads rather than those hamstrings.
Colton Mertens on the left, Nick Matthew on the right, Bill Leahy sitting in third overall in this heat. A lot slower cadence than we saw with Colton Mertens. Yeah, definitely. And we'll see what happens on these next two runs. Like I said, I think that third round and that fourth round
on the run is going to be kind of the bread and butter, meat and potatoes on this workout. So if he can move there and save a little bit in the tank, I think he can make some moves here. But you cannot wait until the last round to make your move. That needs to be made on the back end of this and into this next round. Curly in that middle round of five is Nick Matthew on the right side of your screen. It's about 15 meters left to finish out his third 400 meter.
And you look at his transition, you know, whenever he gets off here, he's right on it. He's hitting nine quick, and then he'll take that little bit of a longer break. And you're seeing some of these other athletes break those into fours, where they're taking, you know, that rest can start to add up pretty quick. He's off the runner, right on the barbell, hands on it, and he's moving. And that cadence is fast.
And 350 pounds with that thicker axle bar. It's about twice as thick as a normal barbell. The problem with that is, yes, it's grip for one thing, Adrian, but whip that you're not getting is another.
Yeah, the barbell is going to be a little bit shorter in length, and the thicker diameter is also going to add to the resistance to the bar to bend at all. And that bend and width is something we get really familiar with when we're used to only using traditional barbells. So this is certainly the odd object experience at the CrossFit Games. Nick Matthews, still your current leader in this heat, followed by Bill Leahy in second.
You do not have to go 50 feet unbroken. That yellow line that Nick Matthew just passed is a 25 foot mark. So athletes do have the option to take a break in the middle, though we haven't seen any athlete do that so far.
This is interesting what we're seeing. Even as Saxton and I talk about it before we get going, we're like, OK, maybe this puts a little bit more onus on the run. And within this heat, at least, we're noticing that might not be the case. These guys came out that were more reserved and had more urgency in the transitions. And in their breaks are the ones that are leading the way. Absolutely. I think we'll see Leahy make a move here. His transitions seem to be pretty quick on these handstands. And, you know, I think.
Once this run's done, we'll see. You know, I think those top three will stay those top three. Colton Mertens will take a break at the halfway point. If Mertens does have a big chink in his armor, it is high-volume handstand walks, as Bill Leahy on the right does 50 feet down and back, and back on the runner. So Mertens was off the deadlift first, but Leahy caught him on the handstand walk.
McMatthew to 18th place finishes to start the day yesterday and that 22nd place finish in that pegboard event as Jack Rosema gets to the woodway runner just to his left.
And the unfortunate thing for Nick here is that we've got coaches and athletes in the back right now witnessing what he's doing, understanding exactly how long he's taking on that woodway. And they're like, OK, cool. Can we do this on transitions? And then that means you've just got to be off the woodway in this time. So he's got 15 guys watching him, his every move, breaking it down so that they have an opportunity to one-up his score. Nick's got to be focused in order to get a score that's going to be within the top 15 for this one.
McMatthew, your leader in this heat. Heat one of two. Jack Rozema, great finish last night on the pegboard event. I tell you what, that pegboard event was just an absolute grenade on the leaderboard last night.
Love to see that. I think having events like that that shake things up, it will make it interesting over the weekend. That was a skilled test and execution. I think that's important. You have to be able to execute on some of these more complex movements. We'll have a bit of that later tonight. Dave Kaschu announced events six and seven. That is going to be a wild night. That will be more execution based on pacing in racing. That is the skill itself. As Bill Leahy
a little slower on the run but it seems to be affording him a bit more energy on the walk yeah you know i mean if he's making his move on the handstand walk and we're finishing on that handstand walk 150 unbroken or 100 105 125 150 total yeah 150 total feet in that final round yes sir um hey moves can happen there bill leahy rookie appearance at the cross of games actually got his
I'd say he was more known in our circle of being a tester for games events back in the day. Had an Achilles injury last year at the West Coast Classic. So the turnaround he had in a year is quite incredible as Nick Matthew is the only athlete off the runner and back onto the fourth set of deadlifts.
Saxton, it's a five-round event. The round of four, I mean, that's just kind of that death trap. You have to move. You have to stay awake. You know, you can't get comfortable. Even if people aren't making moves or anyone looks close, put the throttle down here.
Yeah, this is the one, even in training, right? This is the one where you have to remind yourself that round before the final round, where everyone is lured into the final round. We're all going to give our best on the final, of course. But if you can somehow manage one of your most focused efforts here in the second to last round, that's really where you get an opportunity to create that separation. This transition here with Nick, this is, I would say, his longest transition. Now, he's keeping these unbroken, but it will be interesting to see what happens on this last handstand walk.
Here comes Leahy, and his transition's quick. Bill Leahy at the bottom part of the street. Nick Matthew actually got called back, because you have to start with both hands clearly behind the start red line. And that little misstep, when you got Bill Leahy breathing down your neck on the handstand walk, as Nick Matthew is done with round four and moving into his fifth and final round.
Bill Lahey starting to close the gap, although maybe running out of room as we just have one round left to go.
14 minutes in, the time cap has now moved up to 22 minutes. So everyone will have an opportunity to do all 60 deadlifts. Hey, you're finishing this. Bill Lahey on the right, Nick Matthew on the left. Nick Matthew hasn't had the best split in any single particular part of this event. However, his consistency is keeping him in the front of the pack.
And Saxon spoke to this about stride length and frequency. And Nick Matthews got a pretty short, choppy cadence. But keeping it quick with a faster turnover, when we get a chance to see Bill, we see that he's a little bit longer, a little bit slower. And then you wonder, is that accumulating for him on his deadlift? Or is he waiting for a moment to maybe speed it up here going into the final?
Yeah, you've kind of seen that stride lengthen a little bit more. And when you look at athletes' shoulders and chest when they're running, I think that's a good indicator with how they're feeling. And you can kind of see he's coming down a little bit. I'll tell you who's looking strong on this run is Colton. Colton Mertens.
Again, he has to put the work in on the run. He's been putting the work in on the deficit because we know the difficulty of the handstand walk. One thing to remember, though, Bill Leahy, in the last 100-foot handstand walk, made up 12 seconds on Nick Matthew. In the final round of this event, we're adding another 50 feet. So Bill Leahy may have an opportunity to catch and pass Nick Matthew because he's making up all that time on the handstand walk.
Absolutely, and that could be something he's thinking is like, hey, let's take this run a little bit slower. We got an extra 50 feet here, a little more time, and let's move on these deadlifts and make a move on the handstand walk. I always think you want to be in the lead, but if you can keep that contact and know that you're feeling good and you can make a move, I think that's a strong position to be in. Approaching the 16-minute mark.
As Nick Matthews on his final 50 meters. His meters designated in the bottom left of the runner. Chalking up those hands like a pure vet right there on that wood way. Not going to waste time in the transition. He's ready to rock and roll with that chalk hidden behind his monitor. Nick Matthews was off. He had to break the last deadlift set up into three. He was off the 16-10 mark.
His cycle rate really is impressive with that 350 at this point in that workout. The way he's able to maximize time under tension by simply just moving the bar quicker from the ground is really lending itself as an advantage for him. Two final reps for Nick Matthew with a solid run and set as he looks over to his right shoulder to see where Bill Leahy is.
Matthew had a 20-second lead coming into the barbell. Now we have an extra 50 feet on this final round as Bill Leahy. Making a move. He's going to try everything he can to get to that handstand walk. But Nick Matthew is doing exactly what he needs to do to stay ahead of Leahy. 50 feet down for Matthew. And that deadlift, it's getting tough for Bill Leahy.
And you can tell it's labored by how hard he was slamming it into the ground to get it back going. But no rest whatsoever. And Nick Matthew breaks at the halfway point for the first time. Matthew's done with his first 50 feet. Nick, or second 50 feet. Late, he done with his first.
Matthew has 50 more feet to the finish line. This is where we're in a little bit of foreign territory for Nick. We haven't had to do this extra 50 feet the entire event, and now he's got to finish with 50 more. Getting a little shaky on that walk. Will he break it 25 feet again? He will, keeping his eyes on Bill Lahey. Nick Matthew is 25 feet.
And Matthew will get it. 18-17 for Nick Matthew. Bill Leahy will break at the 25-foot mark for the first time. Bill Leahy will be in. Second in the heat.
This is heat one of two. Ty Jenkins came across. Really flew through his final round. Enrico Zanoni. He got actually had to get called back earlier as Colton Mertens is trying to get across the finish line. And he'll be in.
Yeah, I don't think Jenkins got his hands across that line. I think he had to go back and redo that 25 feet. Jorge Fernandez. We're going to his final 150 feet. Jack Rosema. At the 25 foot mark, he'll keep going.
And you're seeing this last 50 feet be a big factor. That is a wide handstand walk. Yeah, they got wide. You don't want them to get wide. When it gets wide, you're in a bit of trouble. Two minutes before we hit the time cap, Jorge Fernandez taking a break before he makes his last extra 50 foot handstand walk to finish this out.
He has 25 feet left to go. Yeah, we talk about accumulation of work. And I mean, we're getting through 60 of these deadlifts at 350 with a fat bar. Already 350 feet of handstand walking as you lead into that final round. And so it's certainly, we're seeing its toll add up on these athletes as they enter that final phase.
Absolutely, and looking what this will do later today with the back squat coming up and we got some gymnastics movements on the bar, you know, grip and posterior will be a big factor. Moritz Fiebing, fishing out his final handstand walk. Got a little over a minute to go.
About a minute to that time. Yeah, Sasson, you've been a part of a lot of different competitions around the world in your career. But what is it like being at the CrossFit Games? Yeah, it's special. You have so many events. And I think that that's one of the biggest things is you have to be present in what you're doing.
You know, if you get caught up, it's easy to play the what if game. You know, I wish I did this. I wish I did that on previous events or look forward to other events of like, this is where I want to make my move. You have to bring it for every event, because at the end of the weekend, you will always look back and you're like, I wish I had a point here, three points here.
Every point counts. And, you know, I was talking to Scott a little bit about this yesterday. You know, you had some people kind of struggling on that pegboard a little bit. You see the champs who can overcome those moments of slipping out of the pegboard. Like, how do you handle that adversity and be able to overcome it? 10 seconds before you hit the time cap. And just two athletes left out on the competition floor. One of those being Yonakoski.
But Nick Matthew, wire to wire, takes heat number one for event number four. And these highlights presented by Rogue Fitness.
Nick Matthew came out and executed to a high level right out of the beginning. We talked about it being predominantly a run workout, but Nick really wasn't the first one off that wood way in the early rounds. But it was vet moves just like this proper pacing, using chalk in his transitions to even finish up his run. So there was no.
wasted moment, and he made light work of that 350 pounds for all 60 repetitions. We did start to see Bill Leahy make up some ground on the handstand walk late, but it was Nick that was able to understand himself at a very high level, find his way across the finish line, and it ended up not being a very close race. Mr. Nick Matthew is our event leader so far.
Nick Matthews set the time to beat in heat number one and we only have one heat left to go so 1818.86 for heat number one. Saxon, thank you for joining us in the booth. I appreciate it. Event one, event four, heat one is done. Your standings after one day of competition
Jason Hopper donning the red and the white for the first time in his career with 260 points. But Jake Crouch will be right next to him on the floor, tied at 260. And a four-way tie for points in fourth place. This is absolutely incredible. Event number four, Albany Grip Trip.
It is grippy, and Chase, it's a little bit trippy, especially on that final round. Five rounds for time of a 400-meter run, which the athletes just found out about prior to taking the floor. 12 deadlifts at 350 pounds and a 100-foot handstand walk until round five, where it's 150 feet.
For more on this event, let's go down to Mike Arsenault. Thanks, Chase. I had a chance earlier this morning to spend five minutes on one of these woodways, and immediately, the first few strides, you feel it in your hamstrings. You guys alluded to that in the first heat. Very hamstring dominant. If you tilt your torso forward to try and take some pressure off your hamstrings and save them for the deadlifts, that's when you kind of get the roadrunner going and you get out of control with your stride length. So you have to find that happy medium between saving some hamstrings and making sure you have that smooth cadence throughout the entirety of the 400-meter lap.
Thank you, Mike. You're laying assignments for heat number two for the men. These are your top 15 after day number one. And the points are close. We've had a four-way tie for 240. For fourth, a two-way tie at the top of the leaderboard. And can Jason Hopper hold onto the white jersey for another event? Event number four underway.
Okay, Chase, I'm going to already tell you, this heat is not like the last heat that we just watched. We've got some runners on deck here in this top 15, and I think they're really already showing us that they're coming out at a much aggressive, much more aggressive pace on those woodwinds. Jay Crouch tied for first place in points as Jason Hopper holds on to that tiebreaker. But what a day for Jay.
Yeah, Jay did exactly what we expected him to do. Well-rounded from start to finish. Again, we can give him the category, in the most positive way, as a creeper. He's going to creep through this weekend. He might not win 100 points at any one given event, but he is going to be steadily towards the top. Roman Korenikov is in that third overall position. He's between the point spread of ties on the leaderboard as
Roman, as he usually does, gets a lot of fanfare from the crowd. But heavy is the head that wears the white leader jersey, Jason Hopper, donning the red and white for the first time in his career. What type of pressure does that come with?
It comes with a lot of pressure, and I think there's a unique mindset that you have to go in. Yes, you want to acknowledge that, hey, you're in a position that you want to be, but you also have to equally acknowledge you have so much more work to do and simply get hyper-focused on one event at a time. It's just nice to see an outfit that matches his hair color for the first time. Hey, the audience said they loved it. So who's he going to listen to, the crowd or his wife? We know it's always wife.
Always like Jason Hopper in the center lane, Jake Kraus to his left. Jake Kraus is off the runner first, along with Ricky Garrard and Austin Hatfield.
We saw a lot of this in the first heat as well, where it was very crowded at the bar, quick transition from the runner, many athletes select and opt for a pace that's really similar to one another. And then we're going to start to see some paces start to settle, as we're already seeing the deadlift rep be broken up. 12 deadlifts at 350 pounds with that big axle bar. It's Ricky Garrard is trying to keep pace with his countryman, Jay Crouch.
Ricky Garrard is donning the leader jersey last night in the third event. Lost it in the pegboard to Jason Hopper. 50 feet down, 50 feet back. Athletes can stop in the middle at that yellow 25-foot halfway mark, but we haven't really seen that until the later rounds due to fatigue.
And that transition was extremely fast here by Jay. I mean, it was literally looking like the transition of a shuttle run. His feet touched the ground, and immediately he was right back to those hands and upside down. Jay Crouch back to the runner, had the second fastest split of all the athletes in the first round at 238. Ricky Gerrard had the fastest at 236.
And this is where we're really going to start to see some large separation from heat 1 to heat 2. It's going to be the cyclical speed at which they hold on the woodway. I would argue that Nick Matthew may have some of the faster deadlift splits, even after the event entirely is said and done. But this is where so much time can be made up on these runners. And these men all have the fitness to attack it aggressively. Jason Hopper, your overall leader after day one. Had 300 points yesterday. We've got 400 points.
on the table today. As Jason Hopper's looking side to side, trying to catch some run paces. And I think this makes it harder for Jason. He's very much one of those athletes that feeds off of the presence and positions of other athletes. We see him constantly looking left or right. And here, it's a bit more of a blind experience, as you can only hope to read stride cadence and a bit of body language from knowing where your competitors are. Jason Hopper.
Lane 8, Roman Krennikov, sitting third overall. Just a handful of points separate the two. Four total points, that's one place on the leaderboard as your 2023 CrossFit Games champ, Jeff Adler, is looking to work his way back into that podium contention. Won the first event of the weekend.
won the first event of the weekend, 2023, second in that 5K, won Helena. We've got to keep our eyes on Mr. Jeff to see any time there's running present, whether it's mixed modal or single modality, you've got to keep your eyes on what this guy can do. We know he's got tremendous self-awareness, but he's got a lot of fitness there when it comes to running. Go from one champ to another. You're reigning CrossFit Games champion James Sprague.
Last year at the 2024 CrossFit Games, James currently sitting in 8th overall with 196 points. And to his right is your 2020, 2021, and 2022 Games champ, Justin Medeiros. Can't miss him in no shoes. Three champs in one heat. On to the second round of deadlifts. Jay making very short work of those deadlifts. Jay Crouch.
Much faster split on round number two. And this is where even as Saxon mentioned earlier, you kind of settle into that position here in the round two where you've now opened up your lungs, your heart rate's up high. You can settle into more of what we would consider natural mechanics and intensity there. You're familiar with this feeling. That first round sometimes a little awkward in a triple. You got to get familiar with the flow and the feel. Jake Crouch is done with round number two.
As he advances to the runner for the third time. Jay looking sharp and in a great position. Joined there by Callien Souza. Callien Souza at the bottom part of your screen in lane number 14 is currently sitting second. In this heat. You only have two total heats, two heats of 15.
Chasing time to beat set by Nick Matthew at 1809.13. Suzette actually had a great event one finish earlier yesterday.
And again, you're wondering, hey, does he have these marked in his mind and on his scoreboard as opportunity events for him? And if so, can he seize the moment? More often than not, athletes feel extra pressure, Chase, when they know this can be a home run for me. This can be a really high-scoring event, because it's not just that I'm going to mix in within the leaderboard. It's like, I've got to take this moment and make it my own. So we'll see how Sousa can respond to that. And it's a question you ask athletes all the time. Do you get more nervous in an event you're going to be bad at or the one you're going to be good at? Yeah.
Austin Hadfield, 10th last year in his rookie debut at the CrossFit Games. And his name has also been put in the hat of athletes who could podium, if not win, in his second year. Had a tough finish last night in the pegboard event, like so many did. There was a lot of chaos in that event. And this is one where he wants to work his way back closer to that podium position.
Yeah, we'll say it a lot through the course of the weekend, but this is how you really challenge the mindset of a champion, a future champion, anyone who wants to stand even close to that podium, is how do you respond to adversity? All of these athletes will experience at some point this weekend, it's going to be a hand tear, it's going to be a miscued tempo, it's going to be some missed reps. How do they respond?
Jay Crouch looking comfortable there on the right. All these athletes continually holding a pretty steady cadence from what we've seen from open all the way into this third round. Jay Crouch is off at the same time as Callie and Sousa, but Sousa has a two-rep lead on Crouch. And a third set of deadlifts, 12 reps with the axle bar, 350 pounds. Crouch will break. Callie and Sousa.
Looks less built for deadlifts than he does for running on the air runner with the length of his limbs. He's got to make that barbell travel a long distance for sure. But it's Jay kicking up at the same time as Susan on the far side of our screen. 50 feet down. You can break at the yellow 25-foot mark, but no one's done it intentionally yet.
Crouch and Souza deadlocks in event or round three here in event number four.
often chase, when you're in a position like Jay Crouch, you're looking for your addlers and your hoppers and your athletes that are closer, your Krennikovs to the podium position. But with this weekend, an athlete like Souza, with 400 points available today, is just as much of a threat as anyone out on the floor, and every point is gonna matter. So Jay's even looking over his shoulder at the outside lanes as well, it's important.
Jason Hopper tied with Jay Crouch in points, but he's holding that event win tiebreaker he got last night in event number three. And he's trying to keep pace with your heat leader, who may be able to snatch that jersey off of him in one event.
more on this woodway runner let's go down to mike arsenault so guys have a great vantage point down here on the floor i'm basically looking down the row of woodway runners and watching jay crouch and jason hopper through every round of the run thus far jay crouch's posture has stayed the same he's perfectly upright has a very smooth cadence hopper his stride length is starting to go a little bit on him a little bit more random and he's getting a forward lean so adrian you and i were talking
this morning that that's a sign of you're trying to take that pressure off your hamstrings a little bit and we're seeing Jay Crouch as we move deeper into this event creating more separation between himself and Jason Hopper by having a better run cadence and better posture and a little bit better position through the run portion.
Yeah, Mike, I completely agree with you, even as we see that right here on our screen. It's like, hey, Hopper now has settled into a more consistent cadence as we get deeper into each run. The unique thing that's different between he and Jay is that it takes Jason about 100 to 125 meters before he seems comfortable on the runner each round, whereas Jay gets back onto that woodway and looks
just as if he leaves every round. And so that consistency really adds up, because it's going to accumulate in seconds. And within five rounds, five seconds here and six seconds there, really accumulate. And it's going to be shown on the leaderboard when it comes to the outcome of this event. Jake Kraus done with his fourth 400 meter. He's tied in points. Looking for a little separation between him and Jason Hopper, but he's got to.
Worry about the task at hand, and that's staying ahead of Kaylee and Sousa. Yeah, and Sousa's been consistent with a shorter rest between these breaks. Jay takes a very intentional longer break there to break up his repetitions. Sousa staying a little bit closer to on top of that bar. Crouch is done.
on his fourth hundred foot handstand walk as we approach the 12 minute mark. You look at the time to be in the upper left corner of your screen, 18, 18.86 by Nick Matthew in the previous heat. 50 feet's done. Kelly and Souza, bottom part of your screen, trying to keep pace with Jay. He makes it up on the run, but Jay is starting to pull away on the handstand walk.
Yeah, Jay with about a 25-foot lead here. This is where athletes really have to stay urgent about technical proficiency. They want to stay narrow with their hands and stay long through their hips. It's going to help them store some energy for the big round that is looming here to finish. Fourth round is done. Fifth and final round underway. Jay Crouch trying to hold off that man in the center of your screen, Kalian Souza. Can Souza make up ground on the run? More importantly, can he hang on to that barbell?
That is a place that Jay is starting to create some separation. Souza starts to creep up on the run. Jay goes a little bigger on the deadlift with a little bigger rest, but it's just enough to sneak in and be to those handstand walks early. And in this position right now, he is in control. The consistency that Jay Crouch has had yesterday, fifth, third, and fifth.
This is exactly what you need to do. And tell me if you've heard this one before, Adrian. James Sprague has now moved up into third after being absent for the last 12 minutes.
That's how you play the game. An athlete like James is very self-aware. He trains in intervals very often, and he tries to ingrain in himself the ability to what we categorize as negatively split an event or a workout, where you merely get faster as you go, regardless of the task at hand. Here's how he got here. In the fourth round, he had the fastest deadlift split at 23 seconds, and he had the fastest handstand walk split at 39 seconds.
James Sprague back on the runner for the fifth time. Does he have enough time to run down Drake, Crouch, and Kelly and Souza? And that's the question. And that can be sometimes the drums of trying to negatively split an event is, did you push too late? Do you push too soon? And do you give yourself an opportunity to settle in where you hope to finish the event?
I'll tell you what, nothing fires me up more than seeing a young athlete like Kallion Souza, though, come to take someone's points, regardless of where he's sitting on the leaderboard or where he has expectations to finish this weekend. He's come to shake some things up for this event, and you'd love to see it. Kallion Souza's home country is from Brazil, but he trains out of the United Arab Emirates at CrossFit Calais. Jake Crouch is done.
Crouch is breaking up the deadlifts each round. Does he feel the pressure to hold on on the fifth one? Jay Crouch will break. Halley ensues it to the barbell for the first time. You can see some discomfort settling on Jay's face, which tells me he had a very specific outcome intended for that rep scheme. He wanted to hit it. He grinded through it just to make sure he got there. Yep.
Crouch is done and he is three minutes away and 150 feet from his first event win at the CrossFit Games.
Someone told Jay in the back that I said he may not win an event outright today, but he'll be consistently at the top and he took it personally. Jay Crouch also took a very short rest after the first 50 feet. Now remember, in the fifth and final round, there's an extra 50 feet and Crouch breaks for the first time at the halfway mark. Here comes James Sprague.
James Sprague takes a break at the 25-foot mark. That lets Jay breathe a little easier. He's got plenty of time for the time to beat. Crouch is up. 50 more feet to the finish line. This is where you start to feel that pressure, Chase. Are you gonna do it? No, he's gonna break. It's smart, because that time under tension really starts to add up here. 25 feet left for Jay Crouch.
And for the first time in his career, Jay Crouch wins at events, and he'll be donning the white leader jersey. Wow. With Callie and Sousa there in second place with such an impressive finish. That walk across the finish line almost cost him right there. Callie and Sousa was only four seconds behind. James Sprague.
has plenty of time in the center part of your screen as Jason Hopper in the white leader jersey just finishes his hundred. And this was much needed by James. James was outside by a significant margin of your top six. We have four athletes tied at 240 between fourth and sixth place. Jason Hopper, 10 feet left.
A little hesitation there, a way to reconcile that by Jason. Good fight for Hopper. Jeff Adler working on his final 25 feet. And just a massive handstand walks as Pepper will get in just ahead of Adler. Austin Hatfield is also finished.
As Ricky Garrard is trying to get in ahead of Nick Matthews' time of 18.18. And by the way, this shakes out in where athletes are finishing in every single event. We said points were precious, point gaps are tight. They all matter. And as Harry Lightfoot
with the elegant forward roll there out of the handstand walk. Now Roman Krennikov was sitting in third overall with 256 points. He was four points behind Hopper and Crouch, 16 points ahead of that four-way tie in points for fourth.
Up and down and all around, Chase. That's what we can expect all weekend long. Even after we rev this and we still got 300 available points, it's gonna be how composed can they stay and how do they respond to where they sit on the leaderboard. Let it go and look forward to what's next. Three minutes left before we hit that 22 minute time cap. It's Collin Bossard.
finishes his first 50 feet of his 150 foot handstand walk to finish round five. What a performance like Haley and Sousa, who's walking with Bossard. Sousa made up 20 seconds on that last set of deadlifts. I mean, he came storming on the deadlift, storming on the handstand walk. We were celebrating for Jay Crouch, and all of a sudden we're like, whoa, he was literally right there.
Final 50 feet for Bossart. Bossart's rookie debut. He goes past the 25 and with the crowd behind him, the men for Switzerland. Will close out his final handstand walk. But Adrian.
Knock, knock, who's there? Another Australian wearing a white leader jersey. This time, it's Jay Crouch. Replay, Spakibot Road. Yeah, Mr. Crouch came out with winning on his mind to start day two. Very focused.
for first place, but of course, we know Mr. Hopper gets to don the red and white because he had an event win. Well, Jake Crouch said, well, I'm going to go ahead and reconcile that by getting myself one. And he came out today aggressive on the runner, and it suited him. He's got the fitness and was able to navigate. Very beautiful, his pacing through all five rounds. It was him getting the crowd going here to start this Saturday morning to come across as the victor in the final 25 feet. And of course, he had some time.
You know the name. It's Crouch. Don't be confused. I'm here to win. Your results of the men's event number four. Jay Crouch gets his first event win at the CrossFit Games. And that result will get him his first white leader jersey. Knees down with Mike Arsenault.
Jay this is your fifth in-person appearance at the CrossFit Games but your first event win and this will be your first time wearing the white leaders jersey. Why do you think this year has been the year that you've broken through?
Oh, man, it's just the team around me. I have the best team in the world around me, and that's proven. And yeah, I'm super grateful to have those guys around me. I looked up to them for a very long time. So yeah, to call them family is super special. Yeah, the work I've been putting in. I've been doing this stuff for a long time. And yeah, to, I guess, prepare the right way that winners do.
And this is the result. Through four events, you're the only man in the competition to have four performances top five or better. Where does that consistency come from? Oh, man. I feel like that's been a strength of mine for a while, is just being that consistent guy. But I've never been able to, let's say, make that top step of them being top fives.
Yeah, I mean, you do well in this sport when you don't have any holes. So yeah, that's where we want to be. And how much you've been working on that top end squat strength to get ready for another event we have coming up later today? Again, I don't want to toot my own horn, but back squats are very good for me. So I'm looking forward to it as a best case scenario. I feel like Dave's maybe been on my Instagram looking at all my strengths, because these workouts are stacking up pretty good.
doing a little Instagram creeping. Jay, congratulations. Go get that White Leaders jersey on. Thank you, guys. Shout out to my family back home. Love you guys. Adrian. Toot toot. Toot toot, baby. Jay Crouch Chains coming down the tracks, y'all. The men are done for Individual Event 4. Don't go anywhere. The individual women coming up next.
Welcome back inside arena as today's coverage is presented by Belites. We are Belites and we are made not born. Good morning, everyone. As the 2025 CrossFit Games continues here in Albany, New York, I'm Chase Ingram. Along with me is Adrian Conway and Mike Arsenault will be joining us from the floor. He's seen it once before, the Albany grip trip presented by Pasture Provisions.
It is five rounds for time, 400-meter run on that Woodway Runner, 12 deadlifts at 220 pounds for the women, and a 100-foot handstand walk, of course, until round five. You get an extra 50 feet. Your lane assignments for heat number one of two, as we are going two heats of 15 and 15. These are your bottom 15 after day one of competition, as we have our second final heat after this.
Your vision fuels victory athletes to watch, and all eyes are on one athlete who makes her 10th and last appearance at the CrossFit Games this year, but she is not alone, as Jona Koski and Tia-Claire Toomey are three athletes that join the 10 Games Club. And more on Brooke Wells as we go down to Mike Arsenault.
Oh, Adrian, more on Brooke with you, sir. Yeah, listen, all of us could give you some more on Brooke. We've gotten 10 years to watch her at a very high level. She's an athlete that has been a fan favorite. She has also finished as high as fifth two times at the CrossFit Games.
has come back from injury. We have seen her grow up in the CrossFit space. So we've got a little bit of it all from Ms. Brooke Wells. And it was a shock to me when she announced that this would be her last year competing at the CrossFit Games. But I can tell you what, she's going to go out fighting tooth and nail for the best finish possible. One of two underway for individual event number four. You see Abby Dolmit. We had a tough day yesterday. Dolmit, one of the athletes that
could be in podium contention this weekend and just not having the, at least day one. But the good news for Dominic is that there's 400 points up for grabs today.
Yeah, and she's an athlete that you like to consider doing pretty well on an event like this. We know, historically, she's actually got some back issues that she's dealt with and managed throughout sports as a youth athlete, coming up through gymnastics, something she's had to be mindful of even coming into the sport of CrossFit, as it was almost something that helped strengthen her back and posterior. So you wonder how she approaches these deadlifts that, of course, she's going to do in high number throughout this event.
400 meter runs on that wood way runner to start See Carolyn Frivo there in lane number two One who knows her way around a deadlift bar Yeah, she knows her way around a deadlift bar chasing anything athletic I mean she's moving quickly through space on a regular basis and she's gonna be a good runner to Gracie Walton
in this first heat. If you look at what's stacked up later this afternoon, we said there's a lot of points up for grabs. So what is, we have tonight an event six and seven, maybe an awesome opportunity for Gracie Walton to put herself back into that top 10 position. Gotta get through this first event of the day. As Gracie Walton is watching her fellow countrymen.
Donning that white leader jersey, Cristina Lividadakis, qualifying out of the Rebel Renegade Games. This is her first appearance at the CrossFit Games, as Jennifer Muir is off the runner first, along with Mariana Mesa. Muir, another rookie out of Scotland. Muir actually made a little splash in name for herself in the 2020
three semifinals as Brooke Wells is on to the deadlift as well. Now, if you think prime Brooke Wells, this is a home run potential event for someone like with Brooke's skill set. You've got running, deadlifts, and a handstand walk.
Yes, you do. You've got it all. And we're starting to see some real variation in regards to who's kicking up and when on this handstand walk. We talked about it with the men. We're going to start to see some variance in through the first two rounds. And then we'll start to see some consistent settling points for these athletes based on pacing of the run and how they navigate all the transitions from the deadlift to the handstand walk. Mariana Meza on the left side of your screen out of Mexico is your...
early lead on the handstand walk as Abby Dahlman in the center lane just passed the CrossFit decal has moved into first place after this first round. Dahlman is done. Actually looks like lane 10 already on the runners, Gracie Walton. Yeah, you mentioned her, Chase, and we talked about her a little bit early there on the left of the screen in all black.
Her running stride and cadence, we're getting a great shot of it here, is that it's longer and faster than a lot of the other competitors, and that's what got her that early lead into round one. We'll see if she sticks with it all the way through five.
Gracie Walton had the fastest deadlift split in the first round of 21 seconds. She was one of two athletes that looks like they went unbroken. It was her and Caroline Prevost. So even though the run's going to take longer, when it comes to pacing, Adrian,
There are still massive opportunities to make up. Because if you can make up 10 seconds on deadlifts, that's 10 seconds you don't have to run faster on the air runner. That's right. And it's a double positive. If you can conserve energy on the runner, although it takes so much time, and then be faster in the transitions, you're going to literally feel better into round four and five. And we see that that plays a huge component in the outcome of this one. And Gracie Walton, one of those athletes that has the complete understanding, just like we saw with the men, that even if you set the fastest time in heat one,
There's 15 other women that are watching exactly what you do, and they'll be willing to make those tweaks and changes in order to get a better time. I mean, think about the men's. For the first time in a long time, both men who were leading after the first heat in both heats ended up winning their respective heat between what Nick Matthew did and Jay Crouch. Lucy McGonigal.
It's her rookie individual debut at the CrossFit Games, but as the youngest athlete competing this weekend, Lucy has two team championships under her belt, and she is one of six athletes competing here this weekend that have team games championships. Gracie Walton back to the deadlift, went unbroken on round one, and with a hand in the air, takes her first break.
Yeah, and that's what you want to see right there, Chase. Even when athletes break, that it's short and calculated. This is what we mean by race the rest. And there she goes, no hesitation. Wow. Right upside down. Just speaks to the confidence she has in her handstand walkability. As Gracie Walton is, has top 10 potential. Had her debut at the CrossFit Games last year. Gracie Walton out of Australia.
took the event win in Firestorm as Abby Doman is back on the barbell on the left side of your screen. While she's on the bar, Gracie Walton, after the second round, is already back to the runner. So fast upside down there by Gracie, we've kind of
generally mentioned the handstand walk in the volume. 550 feet, that's almost two football fields for everybody watching if you want to get a good visual. And we're taking for granted how high of a skill demand that actually is. Any crossfitter within the four walls of an affiliate will understand that is a very tough task. And Gracie Walton is pretty much running not just on the woodway, but also upside down at this point. Gracie Walton currently sitting in 19th overall.
We have 30 athletes competing. One of the smallest fields we've ever had at the CrossFit Games on the individual side. The only other one being 2020, where they took the top 20. So Gracie Walton is looking to try to get herself closer to that final heat, which traditionally is the top 10. Brooke Wells has moved into third.
Brooke Wells had a tough day yesterday. We saw the inability to get up the pegboard in that third and final event last night. We saw the emotion come out there.
how important it is to have maybe a great event for a potential bounce back to get back in the game. There's a lot of events left to go this weekend. Yeah, a lot left. And historically, we know Brooke struggles with upper body pulling, right? So the pegboard wasn't a huge shock to us, but certainly she expected better than a 20 second. And she's in this unique situation where she's verbally committed to, hey, this is my last year. You've got a real unique opportunity here to set yourself up for success.
in day two that can keep you emotionally invested in the fight towards the top. Because otherwise it could be really easy to check out also. I speak earlier about this being her 10th and final CrossFit Games. She has announced her retirement earlier prior to coming in. She has three event wins under her belt and has finished in the top five twice in her career.
400 meters on those Woodway runners. This is the third round of five. As all athletes are chasing, Gracie Walton, who's off the runner, and back to the barbell. 220 pounds on the bar.
Gracie here looking a lot like we saw from Nick Matthew in the earlier heat, where her cycle rate is faster. She's descending quickly from the top, but it's that bar speed from the ground to lockout that is creating a tremendous advantage for her right now. Gracie Walton still had the second fastest split on the round two of deadlifts at 22 seconds. And Prevost has the fastest at 20. But even with that break, Gracie Walton is still in that mid-20 time frame.
Everyone else is north of 30. So not only is Walton having a good run, she's got a great deadlift and clearly doing well on the handstand walks. She had the fastest handstand walk split in round number two. 50 more feet for Walton.
Great job there by Gracie, keeping a neutral gaze for her handstand walk, not trying to overarch and look too far ahead. She's just spotting right between where her hands are going to go. This helps prevent a lot of that upper neck and upper trap fatigue that a lot of athletes build by looking up too much. And her fellow Australian, golly, maybe I need to move to Australia if I want to get fitter. Emily DeRoy. Something in the water. On the right side of your screen is sitting in second, as Brooke Wells on the left side, holding on to third.
DeRoy on the right. Brooke Wells wasting no time. Brooke Wells is a fantastic handstand walker. Also incredible for her career is that we forget that devastating elbow injury she sustained back in 2021, when it was able to come back the next year in 2022 and still competing at the CrossFit Games.
Yeah, it was extremely impressive to watch the physical recovery by Brooke. I mean, that's a pure example of the fitness built through years, right? We talk about fitness being a buffer from sickness and injury, and she had a devastating injury. But the stability and strength in her upper body and her mental fortitude is what allowed her to have that gracious recovery and get back on the competition floor. Yeah, just to see her come back, to compete at all in 22, letting them get fifth place at the CrossFit Games that year.
Gracie Walton. You can see Emily DeRoy in the far left, who's sitting in second. Two women from Australia are your two leaders in this heat.
And Chase Gracie's face says it all. She is hyper-focused on her pace. She knows exactly what she wants to hit. And of course, I'm sure she's watching the meter tick up towards her end goal. But she's really watching, how fast am I running? And what do I need to do to change my body posture and position in order to do that? Again, another savvy vet move there, chalking her hands up as she gets near concluding this run so that she's ready to grab that barbell and get to the deadlifts.
This is our 19th CrossFit Games, starting all the way back in 2007. And it feels like the tide is turning with fresh, new blood at the games. Lucy McGonigal is your youngest athlete in the field. She's currently sitting in fourth in this heat.
Lydia Fish is sitting in second place. Anika Greer makes the games for the first time after years of heartbreak. Miriam Van Wor has won the Open two times in the last two years. And just to see not only is the future bright in terms of age, but the amount of countries that are being represented with this new batch of athletes. Yeah, it's really amazing as we even watch Lucy here grind through this run.
These athletes are new here to the competition floor. They don't got the same kind of life experience as someone that's 35 years old that they're competing against. So they're learning so much, and they're starting so young in our methodology that it lends itself as a huge advantage. And that was just the rookies. Gracie Walton, this is only her second appearance at the CrossFit Games. She works her way into her fourth handstand walk.
all alone there on the handstand walk. And that's a good feeling, Chase. It's not one you often get. We mentioned this yesterday. When you're in the lead, it's not one you often get. Sometimes you get it when you're the last one on the floor. But this is a really great feeling. Gracie not taking the time to soak it up, because she's focused. She knows she's got a lot of work to do left in this one more round that awaits her. I'm used to the other one. I'm used to being the last one. Gracie Welln takes a break as Brooke Wells has moved into second place.
Walden takes her first break at that 25 foot yellow mark. Athletes do not have to do 50 feet unbroken as Walden gets to her final run.
Yeah, Brooke making slight work of those deadlifts, showing that she really has paced it greatly up into this point. Daru there taking a bit of a longer rest on the right, which shows that she's operating a touch more at her threshold. Brooke choosing to break up her handstand walks in the 25 foot segments. Daru has gone unbroken, was able to make up a little bit more time in previous rounds there, but Brooke's in a pretty strong position right now for that second place finish potentially, at least going into round five.
Brooke finished with her first 50-foot handstand walk. Again, it's 100 total each round except the fifth and final round. They'll have an extra 50 feet at the end. Brooke will stop at 25. DeRoy will go the whole 50. Brooke Wells closing out her fourth round.
textbook round there by brooke to kind of finish that up we talk about as a recipe to success racing the rest and who we're watching right now gracie walton she hasn't taken much of it at all throughout the course of this event so far the transitions that she's had as well there's the rest during the the movement but the rest between them is a key component especially in a
A three modality event, five rounds is a lot of opportunities to waste time in an event like this. That's right. It's very tempting, Chase. You get off that runner and the last thing you want to do is pick up something heavy, especially when you've already done it 48 times. But it's the discipline and the tenacity and the attitude of these athletes that is really the deciding factor in how they get into attack mode from movement to movement.
That is something that they have to practice and they have to be very in the moment of in order not to listen to their body. Because from a comfort perspective, you don't want to advance as quickly as they are. They're choosing to do it because they want to win. 100 meters left for Gracie Walton on the right side of your screen, your leader in this heat. Time cap is 25 minutes as Walton is in her fifth and final round.
Brooke Wells on the right her twin sister Sydney who's been a individual games athletes in her own right and her mom looking on never the easy position to be in chase I've competed at the CrossFit Games many times and I think my family's more fatigued at the end of every day than I am. Gracie Walnes off the run and on the bar
But she's had one of the, continuing to have one of the fastest, deadliest splits of any athlete in this heat. Again, this is heat number one of two. So we have two heats of 15 as Walmart break for the second time. So she has yet to do that. Maybe setting herself up for the longer handstand walk to close things out.
And simply put, she's at the top end of her threshold right now. We're seeing it from a body language perspective. You see the fatigue on her face. But this is what is asked of you when you're trying to really maximize your output. She's trying to save just enough for this last 150 feet. 50 feet down and back and one more to finish in the fifth and final round. Walton is done.
She took a break at the 25 foot mark in the previous round. And one thing to note, we still have 15 of our top athletes after day one coming up after this. So though she's well ahead of the other 14 in this heat, she has to understand that there are 15 athletes and coaches watching and using her pace for race strategy.
That's right. And for the men, we got an opportunity through those two heats to see how much this final 50 feet really does add in extra challenge in this specific event. So as she gets ready for this final turnaround, there's a lot of pressure here on the time waste right now that she's taking in order to be prepared for the final 50. 17 and a half minutes in.
Gracie Walton makes her final 50 feet as she stops at the 25 foot marker. 25 feet left to go for Gracie Walton. She'll get across the finish line and the time is set for heat number two. Another Australian
with a top performance in their heat. Brooke Wells is off her final set of deadlifts as she's finishing up her first 50 feet of the handstand walk. Oh, that was her last. Wow, Brooke Wells closed the gap significantly on that last 150 feet. Emily DeRoy, I'll give you zero guesses to where she's from.
Another Australian moving into third place. Whoa. Great save there. She knows it. If you've ever walked on your hands at all, you know that feeling. And that's a scary one. 50 more feet to the finish line for Emily. Emily making her second appearance at the CrossFit Games as an individual. She made it back in 2023.
Decided to take a year off, go team, win a CrossFit Games championship on that team, and then make it again as an individual this year. Deroy is in. As we have plenty of time before we get to that 25 minute time cap. That is Lucy McGonigal.
finishing up her final 50 feet. Great finish for the youngster. And she's feeling every bit of it. Lucy Magano has actually been staying with and training with your seven time CrossFit Games champ, Tia Claire Toomey. Jen Muir.
Working on her final 50 feet. Jen, you're doing a great job using her lower body as leverage to help propel herself forward. Gymnasts might say, hey, these CrossFitters, they're bending their knees while they're walking. Well, yeah, we're walking and we're not performing. We're trying to cover forward distance and it helps us do it faster when we get that bend in the legs. Abby Dometz in.
She was trying to outrace to the finish line between her and Lexi Neely. So we are past that 20-minute mark out of Kanyo.
You can hear how hard these athletes are working. That's right. And for those of you that have never walked on your hands, it is an extremely difficult position to breathe in. Your ribcage is typically expanded a bit. You've got pressure through your upper body. There's no reprieve. And as you try to fill your lungs and exhale smoothly, it doesn't really exist. There's a strong bracing. And you heard it there from Kanyo as she was trying to make her way to the finish line. Lividadakis is done.
Still have about three or four athletes left onto the floor. As Sydney Mikulishin is in. So we have Sung Young Choi, Mariana Mesa, and Luisa Marquez. Finishing up their final round. Choi is in.
It's hard to find a place for the muscles to recover in this triplet chase. You see athletes shaking out their arms. Their legs are blown up from the deadlift and the running, but still using their arms on the deadlift. There's really not a moment of reprieve here. 25 more feet for the rookie out of Mexico. Actually qualified at a far east throw down.
She trains at a CrossFit Waddox Fitness. And Meza is in. Final athlete left on the floor, Luisa. Luisa Marquez. This is more my speed.
If I want my own alone time, this could define my short career. No rush. No rush. Oh. A little camera time. Two minutes left before that time cap. And for everyone watching at home, too, this is a unique scenario where we run on a stationary propelled erg, right, in the form of this woodway right now. We're actually...
penalized for being a lighter, smaller athlete. Mass moves mass when it comes to a stationary erg. And so the foot power and drive that you put into this is going to reward you a lot like body weight and power is rewarded on the rower and the biker, because we're not moving our body through space. So there's a unique challenge, especially to runners who aren't naturally great runners. Final 12 deadlifts.
We can tell where the sticking point was, though. And it was the deadlifts. 225 pounds on that axle bar. One thing, we talked about the thickness in terms of grip, but also the thickness in terms of frontal plane. Yeah.
Absolutely. Chase, you're talking about that fixed plane on the side of your body. Folks, it's like if we cut her body in half from the side, the closer she can keep it to that line, right down the middle of her body, the lighter it will feel, and the circumference of that bar pushes the load further from the middle of her body, and it makes it feel that much more heavy. I feel this deadlift struggle deeply in my bones. You got a story for us about that deadlift struggle? Listen, I'm trying not to use the word triggered, but we're getting there.
10 seconds before the cap. Come on, finish these deadlifts. One final rep in for Luisa Marquez as Gracie Wong takes the heat. 18 minutes flat, .39 seconds. Let's check out the highlights brought to you by Rogue Fitness.
It was a lot of Gracie Walton the entire event. She came to play today, a lot like did Jay Crouch. And just like the other heat winners, she's chalking up those hands on the run. Another savvy vet move that allowed her to move quickly in and out of each and every transition, which we talked about, Chase. There were a lot of them in this. It takes mental fortitude and a high level amount of intention in order to race the rest here. And she did it just like we talked about, all the way over that finish line.
No particular movement presented a problem for Gracie, not today. And we got another Australian Heat winner. Surprise, surprise. The results for Heat number one, Gracie Walton, 18 minutes, 0.39 seconds, as we have two Australians in the top three. One Australian on the top of the leaderboard is coming up next.
Okay.
Welcome back inside MVP Arena here in Albany, New York for the 2025 CrossFit Games. One heat down, one heat left to go. I'm Chase Ingram. Along with me is Adrienne Conway. Mike Arsenault will be joining us shortly from the floor. And Tia Claire Toomey makes her way out on the competition floor.
Two event wins to start, but that 16th place might make her a little angry to start day number two. Brother, if I'm a Woodway right now, or if I'm a barbell out there that's a fat barbell, I'm a little afraid of what Tia Claire Toomey is about to do right now.
T. Claire Toomey had a little struggle on the pegboard and the only thing I heard from her thoughts about that is that she was just angry at herself for how that went. She holds a six point lead over rookie Lydia Fish and Lucy Campbell tied at 236.
This is what awaits for the Women Air Event number four. It is Albany Grip Trip, presented by Posture Provisions. And it's going to be five rounds for time of a 400 meter run on that woodway, 12 deadlifts at 220 pounds, and a 100 foot handstand walk in 50 foot segments. Except round five, they get an extra 50 feet. Adrian, what are your tempo recipe for success?
We're going to look at keeping your cadence, and that's going to specifically talk to that woodway. It's a blind run. You don't get to race the field here. You've got to stick to your guns. And then you're going to race the rest. We saw in heat one from Gracie Walton. She made fast transitions at each and every opportunity.
Your lane assignments for the second and final heat for individual event number one is we have 15 in each heat. Your leader will be in lane number nine, bracketed by Lucy Campbell and Lydia Fish, who are tied with 236 points and more on the rookie.
Let's go down to Mike Arsenault. Where can you be? Chase, great to be here in a school of fish with Lydia Fish's support system. 16 people strong are here from Wisconsin supporting the rookie. She was the last chance qualifier, making the most of that opportunity, finding herself in a podium position after day one of the CrossFit Games. She's excited to be here.
I've been talking to her brothers, three brothers beside me, sister behind me. And a big focus of Lydia has been her strength. So strength is going to be a big portion of day two. So we'll see how she acquits herself. She just started CrossFit in 2019 after winning a free three-month membership. And the rest of the siblings have started CrossFit as well because the brothers told me they can't have their sister stronger than her. So it's now a family affair. Thank you, Mike. And Lydia Fish, the rookie.
Debuting the CrossFit Games, and then on the second day of competition, you're lining up for the seven-time CrossFit Games champ, Tia Claire Toomey. Yeah, high nerves, high stakes, but you're soaking it in, loving every moment of it. Lydia Fish, go get it. Second and final heat for the individual women for the Albany Grip Trip.
Haley Adams sitting in lane 15 currently 14 overall and Lucy Campbell back for the first time since 2022 after a two-year fight of a wrist injury just to get back to function and now she's here competing in her second CrossFit game she's tied in points for six points behind the woman on her left in the red and white Tia Claire Toomey
declare to me taking a 16th place finish last night won the first two events yesterday to start things off and
Agent not to pull out a Michael Jordan reference, but I think she might have taken that 16th place personally. Yeah, isn't it unique that we're in such a fortunate situation with an athlete that we've been able to watch through the years like Tia Claire Toomey that goes 1-1-16 yesterday, still donning the leader jersey, and we're like, yo, she's going to be angry today. And that's just the sum of her whole career, right? The dominance and the high level of expectation that she's blessed us with for her as an athlete is because of her greatness.
10th year competing at the CrossFit Games. She finished second twice to start her career. As Tia is going for eight CrossFit Games championships. And you hear this a lot from people that, you know,
Grit and groan about Tia's dominance and what that means to the sport. I can't say it enough how lucky we are to be witnessing such greatness for so long. And personally, I'm here to see more of it as long as she can.
Yeah, what can we do to lure her into continuing this? I'm all for chase. So if it's something that we need to say on the broadcast, something we need to call out, let's go ahead and do that so we can get more of this. Amy Kringle on the right and all black is actually first off the runner into the bar along with Lucy Campbell to her left and Tia Toomey in the white and red. Now we saw great performance.
yesterday from a lot of these athletes from the running event to start, as we see Tia get an early start on her handstand walk. So will this all be reflected on the pace that they settle in on the woodway? I'm very curious about for the athletes that are in the top three right now. Now, very early in Tia Claire Toomey's career, handstand walks were not her best movement. But you can bet that she has been focusing on improving that. And with Shane Orr in her corner, you can guarantee that that is a
element that they have worked on significantly as Tia Claire Toomey has already moved into first place after the first round. When we talk about that with Lucy Campbell as well, Chase, with the wrist injury and limitations, she hadn't been walking on her hands and accumulating a ton of volume and training there for that long. So how will she respond to this type of test is going to be a great question as well.
Olivia Kerstetter on the right side of screen, known, obviously, for her proficiency with the barbell. But Kerstetter is fantastic on her hands. Fantastic on her hands. And we saw earlier, even on the men's side, that if you're fast on the barbell, you can make up a tremendous amount of time that it could cost you on the run. So this is going to be a really good balance triplet for Olivia to make a push toward the top of the finish. Tia Claire Toomey.
Still held on to that leader jerseys, even with that 16th place finish. And we talked about her quest, her chase for eight. These are some of the great eights with seven plus championships. Obviously, you have Bill Russell with 11. I mean, look at these names. Don't tell me you don't want to see these people do more of what they're the best at longer in their career. And it's such a treat to have her at seven. And that quest for eight is alive and well.
And look at the names that she's being associated with. Yeah. I don't know if we have one officially. Do we got a CrossFit Hall of Fame chase? Listen, your 20 sounds like a good idea to maybe bust that out. Maybe Mount Rushmore of CrossFit Games athletes. Yeah, it's time. It's time. 18 minutes flat, 0.39, said by Gracie Walton in the previous heat. Haley Adams is holding on a second.
in this heat. Haley, someone that has worked on her strength and power tremendously, specifically in the squatting form. Through her years, Haley was actually able to compete at a very high level when it comes to hinging. And when we talk about movements, the deadlift categorizes as a hinge. And so this is one of those, coupled with the run and the handstand walk that she is also going to be extremely competitive at.
And Haley Adams' career is quite incredible. She took second twice as a teen, won it in her last year, and she's one of six athletes with a teen championship under her belt. But here's her finishes at the games as an individual. Sixth, fifth, ninth, and fifth.
and Haley is incredible on her hands and with the way this is put together as far as the programming is that yes if you're the best at all of them that's your best case scenario but there is room to maybe mask some deficiencies with the run the deadlift and the handstand walk
Yeah, and that's what we're really looking for. When it comes to a beautiful layout of movements and modalities pieced together, this is one of them. Because you could pick any one of these movements and say, oh, that's my thing. But then what about the other two? Or maybe one is really poor for you, but you can then make up ground on the other two. So we're seeing it all play out here. And it's going to be the winner, of course, is going to be the one that can piece it all together and compete at the highest level.
here is done hot on her heels as Haley Adams and Olivia Kerstetter. As Haley is a fantastic runner she looks over her shoulder to see where she's at with the rest of the field is. As good as she is as a runner she's fantastic on her hands as the Haley Adams fan club in the stands cheering her on.
You can see that cadence difference between Tia Claire Toomey and Haley Adams. Yeah, Tia much more of that faster, shorter stride length, Haley being a little bit more elongated and relaxed. Tia likely going to have an attack mode where she's going to be increasing the pace of this run as she goes, especially as she finds herself in the driver's seat.
Lucy Campbell still in the mix, currently sitting in third overall with that tie between her and Lydia Fish. As Lucy peeking over to the, trying to get a peek at Tia Claire Toomey's screen, seeing what pace she's at, and with the endurance background that Lucy Campbell has, she's on the national swim team there in the UK.
Running should not be an issue. But as you said, it's more just time being able to get upside down since recovering from that wrist injury. Yeah, for sure. And just considering her involvement in CrossFit as a methodology, as coach, as teacher. As a broadcaster. As a broadcaster. It's her specialty is literally not specializing. And so she has an opportunity here to really showcase that in this triplet. Lucy Campbell training at a CrossFit Nottingham.
See Olivia Kerstetter, who's in about third place coming into this second round as we are in the midst of the third. Kerstetter at her second individual games, but it'd been a multiple team and Lucy Campbell has made up a ton of ground on the third run.
Lucy Campbell on the right side in the pink and black just to her left. Seven-time CrossFit Games champ Tia Toomey and Lucy Campbell has moved into first. Tia Claire Toomey hot on her heels. We talked about that handstand walk being a big decider here. We questioned how prepared is Lucy. She's looking extremely prepared, very efficient.
Tia might have her a little bit in regards to speed, but we've got so much further to walk. That's less of a concern right now. It's Lucy keeping her close so that she has a chance. And here's the thing with Lucy is that she is not afraid of anybody out there on the competition floor, even though this is only her second time in the CrossFit Games. Obviously, Tia's 10th.
But what we've seen Lucy do this year, yes, she competed in 2022. She won two events at the CrossFit Games, so she has beaten stiff competition over the years. Kerstetter moving into third on the right side of your screen. Lucy made up a lot of ground on that last run.
About four seconds on the run on Tia and two on the handstand walk, on the deadlifts. And that might be it. We know her handstand walks may take a hit just because she hasn't been able to train that over the last two years. However, there's opportunities on the board to make up for what she could lose in the handstand walk.
That's right, and that's what it's all about in regards to competing head-to-head. You've got to know where the juice is worth the squeeze. And if she's feeling good on the runner, and she's feeling good on those deadlifts, that is a great opportunity for her going into this next round to potentially try to have a slight lead going upside down. Just past the 10-minute mark, the time to beat is 18 minutes as Hayley Adams has moved back into third place on the left side of your screen.
And it seems like it's her and Olivia Kerstetter back and forth a little bit between third and fourth place. And it's where Haley gets back on that runner and is able to get a little bit more momentum past Olivia where she sneaks back into that third position. Lydia Fish finishing up her third set on the handstand walk. She's a good runner, great at gymnastics.
We know that deadlift at that weight with that bar will be a tough point for her. She had a great performance last night with a front squat clean complex. Yeah, actually impressed me tremendously the way that she moved those final two barbells, Chase. And this is where we talk about strength through years and fitness through years. These young athletes have to expedite the process in order to try to catch up on the strength side of things. And what we know for an athlete like that is that even
Her experience on that runner gets harder because of how difficult the deadlifts actually are. Lucy Campbell back to the barbell, has made up a little bit of that ground she lost in the handstand walk to Tia Toomey. Though Tia Toomey is moving that bar a little quicker on this fourth round as Haley Adams on the left side of your screen, still holding on to third place.
And looks like Lucy Campbell's just gonna hold on to the bar. Let's go. Wasting no time overhead. Forcing the pace for Tia Toomey.
What I like about Lucy's walk is that she softens her elbow in order to get her cadence forward. There's bend there. She's able to keep her hands a little bit more underneath her. Tia decides to almost waddle her walk. She pivots her shoulder slightly. This is just a little bit of energy bleed. And both these women are at their threshold. Yeah! Here we go, baby! Let's go! Now, Tia has been walking faster than Lucy, but Lucy is starting to pull away, and Tia breaks!
Lucy Campbell is done as she starts round number five. This is her opportunity. Here we go. She's got to put significant distance between her and Tia, because you always have to question, Chase, how fast is Tia going to run here? And how much will this extra 50 feet coming up affect everything towards the end of this event?
Lucy Campbell was tied in points for second place with 236. Tia Claire Toomey is in first place with 242. Lucy Campbell, if she holds onto this, can put herself solidly in second.
And if Tia holds on as well, she'd be two points back of the seven-time CrossFit Games champ. Chase, we talk about this comeback from Lucy Campbell. I saw her compete at elite competitions this year, standing on top of the podium against other CrossFit Games competitors that are historied, even previous champs like Laurel Horvath.
besting them in person events. And that really put me on notice of her mindset and her competitive advantage that she brings when it's time to compete in person. And we're getting to witness it right here. She goes head to head with the champ. Lucy Campbell's been faster on the run. She went unbroken on her fourth set of deadlifts. Again, that is a thick bar and it's 220 pounds. Can Lucy Campbell hold on? It's one thing to chase down the champ. It's another thing to be chased by the champ.
50 meters left for Lucy Campbell. She's focused, Chase. Body language still looks very positive. Tia's focused. She knows exactly where she wants to be or where she wants to hold. Lucy Campbell went unbroken on her fourth set. The efficiency of Lucy's deadlifts all event long have been extremely impressive. Narrow stance with her feet, getting her feet directly under her hips, softens her upper back, not as a fault, but as an advantage to get the bar to the ground quicker.
Lucy Campbell with the crowd at her back is going to try to go unbroken again as she does. 150 feet stand between her and her third event win at the CrossFit Games. Tia takes a break. Lucy Campbell going for unbroken on her first 50 foot handstand walk.
This is where she gets a chance. She's like, okay, I've got time. I've got some space here. Lucy Campbell kicks up again. Tia Clare Toomey on her hands. Tia Clare broke at the 25 foot mark in the last round. Lucy Campbell going for another 50. Now remember, we have one more 50 foot section in the fifth and final round.
Lucy has plenty of time for the time to beat. She just has to focus on Tia. Lucy Campbell's on her hands again. Lucy Campbell has been at a competition for two years. She's won three events.
Since she's returned, she's beat a previous champ and the Queen Slayer, Lucy Campbell, takes down another one! Haley Adams is trying to catch Tia because Tia got a no rep on her second lap.
Tia still has 50 feet to go. And it's the accumulation of that inverted position, Chase. And Haley Adams is the four points that Lucy Campbell needed. 25 feet left to go for Tia Clare. She will not be in white and red much longer after this, as Tia may be getting past
As she does not get to the finish line, she's gotta look out for Kerstetter. Five feet left to go for Tia. Tia will get third in the events. The point drop is four per place. Lucy Campbell with six points back coming into this event as Kerstetter has crossed the finish line.
Ariel Lohan, work on her handstand walk. We're at the 18, we still have seven minutes before we hit the 25 minute cap. Amy Kringle, takes a break at 25 and here comes Ariel Lohan. It's a race to the finish.
between Campbell and Kringle. Brandon across at the same time. Daniel Brandon. So three athletes right there at the finish line with Ariel Lohan, Kringle, Brandon, and Sturt. Wow, what a race. What a race. Lydia Fish.
just trying to close this one out. We knew it would be a tough one for her because of the deadlift. Miriam Van Wor is working through her final 50 feet across the competition floor. Miriam Van Wor.
She's won the Open back-to-back years, 25 and 24, her first time on the competition floor here at the CrossFit Games. Raptis is in. Von Rohre is in.
Claudia Gluck still has 100 feet left to go. As we are five minutes away from that 25 minute time cap. Going on broken all the way back.
For some of these athletes, this is a big point of contention in regards to how they paced this thing, how they started this thing. Again, we see a lot of athletes get off in round one around similar times, and then we see this parity towards the finish as Greer's across. Annika Greer is in. Claudia Gluck.
Finish her final 50 feet. Fisa Ghaffi won the event last night on the pegboard. Just trying to do everything she can to finish this event to start day number two. Fisa Ghaffi was sitting in ninth overall coming into this event.
Yeah, and struggling a bit, even with the handstand walk. And of course, we understand there's been a tremendous accumulation throughout this event so far to get her to this fifth round. But even the pace at which she's moving on her hands, that could have been a significant time loss throughout this whole event, where other athletes are simply just walking faster on their hands. And what we have coming up, Adrienne, is this.
strength test of the games. Obviously, strength has been tested in the clean. It's being tested here in the deadlift. But a one rep max back squat is what is looming for these individual athletes. Now seeing this event take place, what is that fatigue element, that mental element coming in to that strength test for these athletes? Well, along with yesterday, the three events that we worked through yesterday, and then this morning.
the distance that was covered in the run, and all these deadlifts is certainly going to accumulate and certainly affect what we see from a performance perspective on this back squat later. Lucy Campbell will not be wearing pink and black much longer, and Tia will not be wearing white and red either. A little wardrobe switcheroo going into the back squats later.
who won the in affiliate semifinal still I say still has plenty of time but sometimes when the athlete is like listen can we do about that 22 minute time cap that the guys have can we uh can we get that back
And ladies and gentlemen, strap in because it wasn't a single under that tripped her up. Lucy Campbell has done what no one has been able to do in the middle of a competition. See how we got there. Check out these highlights presented by Rogue Fitness.
Chase, it was Tia, it was Amy Kringle, it was Haley Adams, but ultimately, it was the one who was able to compete with Miss Tia Claire Toomey, Lucy Campbell, that was the threat the entire time. She was very consistent through rounds one and two. And then what we started to notice is that Lucy would create an advantage for herself, coming off the deadlift, into the handstand walk. Tia chose to broke and Lucy did not. There was some efficiency
highlights that lead all the way from her deadlift with her narrow stance, slight softening of her upper back in order to increase her cycle rate. These are all intentionally done by Lucy, but it was the handstand walk that really blew our minds. Coming off of a wrist limitation. How can you build the proficiency and capacity to have such a strong finish in an event like this? And she put it on display here to start day two. Lucy Campbell is your leader.
Lucy Campbell takes the event and takes the white leader jersey away from Tia Claire Toomey and dons it herself for the first time in her career. She is down with Mike Arsenault.
Lucy, two years ago, you were told to pick a different sport. Last year, you underwent another surgery on your wrist. And later this afternoon, you're gonna be wearing the White Leaders jersey for the first time. What has been the last two years like for you, this odyssey, mentally?
Um, it's been super tough, like, I'm not gonna sugarcoat it. It's been, like, some of the lowest times of my life, just thinking about, you know, what I was gonna do with the rest of this if this didn't work out, and, you know, not just in sport and CrossFit, but in everything else that I love to do. I used to journal a lot, and writing used to hurt my wrist and all that sort of stuff, so...
Um, it really threw a spanner in the works, um, but just, you know, trying to take it day by day and not focusing too far ahead, um, and just take the next step that I could and, you know, now I'm back and in a position that I've never been in before and that's pretty special. Where does that, where does that perseverance come from? I literally don't know, um,
I said on an Instagram story a couple of weeks ago that when you're in it, resilience feels a lot like vulnerability. And I was crying more than I ever had done. I was really trying to let myself feel all the emotions. And I think there's a lot of narrative that to be mentally tough, you have to ignore all of this sort of hard feelings. And actually, I think it's the opposite. You just have to acknowledge it. And I don't know where it came from, but it was just, as I say, take one step at a time.
Well, the mental strength, the mental focus is very impressive. Physically, it looked like there were a few points yesterday. We are still somewhat favoring the wrist a little bit. Are there some movements that give you a little bit more pause now as opposed to before the operations? Yeah, for sure. Front rack continues to be a struggle. We're very selective with when I do it.
So if that was shoulder to overhead that I was having to do yesterday, if there was any kind of jerk movement, then obviously we can't avoid it. But I've now sort of added another tool to the toolbox in terms of the zombie clean. And so being able to resort to that and lessen the pressure on my wrist for the events to come is really useful in terms of being back at this level. Well, tremendous performance. Your third career event win. Well done. Thank you.
Congratulations to Lucy Campbell. Adrian, you have been an elite level in multiple sports throughout your career. Coming back from injury is one thing. How sweet it is to see that resilience pay off. It's the best thing, Chase. And what we're seeing here from Lucy Campbell is top notch.
human, right? And I say that this goes far beyond her as an athlete. This is her as a human, her vulnerability, her willingness to share what the struggle is like, even with us in that moment. But it's her being connected to what she's experiencing and now persevering through the hard work, the zombie cleans, the adjustments that she's got to make in all these events.
And she's doing it today. It's been very impressive. Well, Lucy Campbell will be in red and white and she has a new challenge. Can she keep it for another event? Teams are next here at the 2025 CrossFit Games.
to you by Rogue, Don't Weaken, the official equipment supplier of CrossFit and the CrossFit Games. Belites, we are Belites and we are made, not born. The United States Border Patrol, the an agent of strength. And Sotva, unlock the superpower of restorative sleep.
I became the owner of CrossFit Spur after being introduced to CrossFit in probably 2010, 2011. Coached at a local box for a bit. Really enjoyed it more than I thought I would. Ended up getting my L1 and decided that I'd like to go off of my own and give it a shot.
Way better. Good. We're just outside of Albany, a small town called Glenmont. I worked in the town that Crossfittsburg is in for many, many years. It's a neighboring town. Got to know the community really well. But after kind of being here and growing through word of mouth, organic growth, and people starting to understand that what we do is make people healthy, we sort of earned a reputation of making people better.
anything no matter what they wanted to do. John and Lauren will do just about anything to help anybody get better at anything. I'm convinced of that for sure. You have an AMRAP for 14 minutes. My wife Lauren has been a member at the gym for longer than she was an employee here. She's an organizer for sure so she does a great job keeping everything in line, taking care of the boring stuff that people don't quite understand all the ins and outs of business ownership.
I don't know that the gym would be able to run without her. It certainly would not have been able to expand the way it did without her. We are probably the largest in the Capital District, definitely one of the largest. We've got 6,500 plus square feet of floor space. We've got two rigs, full corral of bikes and rowers and all the endurance machines you could possibly want.
COVID hit, the reality set in that we might not be opening for quite a while. We ended up creating sort of a fitness library. We labeled all of our equipment. And we allowed our members to come in twice a week and swap out their equipment. So they each got to take two pieces home. But through that, we didn't lose a single member.
In addition to the CrossFit space, we have some offices next door where we've got a therapy room with contrast therapy. We have a cold plunge. We have a sauna. We've also got a barber shop. We have two massage therapists that are here full time. We've also got a chiropractor. We've got a little bit of everything to offer for anyone looking to get healthy.
I've been a member here at CrossFit Spur for 10 years. It's just grown and grown and grown, this business. Doubled, almost tripled the size of it. So many new members, so many members that have been here for quite a long time, as long as me. So it's really great.
I moved here during grad school, and honestly, if it wasn't for this community here, I probably still wouldn't live here. John and Lauren have created such a great atmosphere. Everybody here is like-minded. Everybody supports each other. His programming is fantastic. And what's really impressive, when the people don't know this, they don't realize what goes into the coaching aspect. They don't see the notes that I see from him saying, this is what I want you to focus on today. Make sure they do this. Don't let them do this.
I want you to check this. He's not throwing stuff together. It gives you a different perspective. It's not just a place they go work out. This is where their friends are. This is where they enjoy spending time. It makes going to the gym something that they want to do, which I think is part of the reason that we've grown the way we have. It's their place.
What's the key component when we look at functional movements? What are we looking for? The ability to move a large load. Long distances. Quickly. Ready and go. And now reach up. Mastering the nine foundational movements is key to building strong, efficient CrossFit skills.
The squat, front squat, and the overhead squat. The press, push press, push jerk, deadlift, sumo deadlift, high pull, and the med ball clean. We can basically break down all of our human and athletic movement to a foundation of these movements. And stand, missy, send your hip back a little bit more, delay your knee. These movements teach essential themes like core stability, posterior chain engagement, and full range of motion across the joints.
Skills that transfer to many other functional movements. Get these right, and you'll have the foundation to confidently move, lift, and thrive.
So,
Today's coverage at MVP Arena in Albany, New York of the 2025 CrossFit Games is presented by Veletas. We are Veletas, and we are made not born. Welcome back inside this year's Coliseum alongside the seven times CrossFit Games athlete Bethany Flores, Bella Martin down on the floor. My name is Joel Godet. The rest of our crew,
Glad to have you with us for team competition. And if you thought that Campbell City CrossFit was going to be in first place after four events, you go to Campbell City CrossFit in Winston-Salem, North Carolina. They were shocked when we spoke to them this morning. A phenomenal first day. Q21 is in 11th place, trying to crack their way up into our second heat based on their performance in our first event today.
All right, team event number five, it is up over and back brought to us by the United States Border Patrol. And Bethany, this is a grinder. This is we have six total rounds. It'll be a 20 minute time cap. The first three rounds are 40 chest of our alternating pairs every 10 reps with 10 worm over and back into three rounds of 28 bar muscle ups, alternating pairs every seven reps, seven worm over back on the shoulder.
United States Border Patrol be an agent of strength Bella Martin's pretty strong. What do you got for us? Well, I'll tell you what guys this is the first event of the weekend for the teams that requires pure teamwork and Communication those teams that can communicate on the rig for the bar muscle ups in the chest bar. It's quick sets It'll be pretty important and have no no reps there but it's going to be on that worm and
where the teams that have trained together, the teams that have good communications and probably fewer big personalities are going to be proven successful here on this kind of moderately longer test. We'll see if the team can go no reps. Every single one counts. So you're going to want to make sure you're communicating clearly and moving as quickly as you can, guys.
Bella, thank you. Cued 21 in 11th place as the highest seeded team in this first heat. It'll be in the middle of the floor on lane five. CrossFit 1124 in lane six, overcoming a last place finish in the first event with a first place finish in event number four. To get themselves back into contention, they are in lane six.
Speaking of 1124, they are one of our Vision Fuels Victory athletes to watch. The group from Marietta, Georgia, a second year team at the CrossFit Games. They added Jessica Androsik, 161 in the middle of your screen, a mayhem athlete looking to make some big strides. And then Q21, they are looking to be the best Latin American team to ever compete at the CrossFit Games. 17 is the number to beat. That was Big Friends back in 2017.
And away we go with pairs to the chest-to-bar pull-ups. You don't have to specify which gender goes first here. It can be either your males or your females, but you must complete 10 repetitions of chest-to-bar pull-ups before you switch to your second pair. A lot of pulling yesterday, Bethany. How do your pulling muscles feel?
I hope OK with some of these athletes, but you might be a little sore with some of these, especially the bar muscle ups when they get to the three rounds of bar muscle ups. I foresee that being a little bit of some trouble for some of the athletes, especially having to hold at the top. Those triceps are going to be little spicy.
40 total repetitions here. We were talking to Butcher's Lab team in second place overall just before this event began. And Pernilla Christensen said, I feel really good about my pulling. And Thomas Stroyer looked at us and said, no, biceps are a little taxed from the pegboard climbs yesterday. Yeah. I think a lot of the athletes, though, it's the lower body. They said they're pretty sore with the hamstrings and the lower body just from a lot of running they did yesterday. A lot of running.
two sets of ten for each of these athletes. That gets you to 40 total and then on to the worm clean up and overs. And this is all about teamwork, Bethany, specifically because of the return to the initial shoulder. Yeah, one one misstep and man, that's a long, costly no rep. And you have to start from the ground. You have to start the whole rep over if you get some type of mishap or no rep. And that's not fun, especially with these. This is a new movement to.
All the athletes haven't done this in competition before. Maybe some of them have done it in practice, but.
It's gonna be interesting to see how the communication goes with this movement. That's the tricky piece to it. Typically we've seen worm clean and jerks in competition. So you're picking the worm up from the ground to one shoulder, over your head to the other, and then you put it down. But it's one more step bringing it back to that initial shoulder. And that's where we see some miscommunication steps come through. Not the case for Undivided right there. Pretty clean rep. I will say body blueprint.
We spoke to them in the warm-up area, and they said they've really not touched the worm together. No, no, not touched the worm together. This is the first time. Oh, no. Well, yesterday, the worm was in the game. And there's no worm in the warm-up area. No. Which, to me, sounds a little scary. That would be a scary thought.
To some degree, rewards preparation. You know you're going to see the ultimate implement of team testing at the CrossFit Games. Those teams that have gotten on to a worm, going to have that advantage. Greater Heights, veteran group, right now in your lead, tied with Prostanda going back and forth, also a veteran group out of Sweden.
And there is Greater Heights Overtake. It's a team made up of pieces from last year's Einhorn CrossFit team, last year's Overtake team, and now competing out of CrossFit Greater Heights, which has previously sent teams to the games. They're all Texans, if you just, we'll simplify it. Yes, and they want to be one of the best Texas teams. Don't Stop has that record, 2019, finishing sixth overall, qualifying out of Texas. They got some work to do.
need to make their way into the second heat first and foremost. Yes. So I can see, foresee, you know, even though, I mean, those Chester bars are going to add up very quickly. So doing that, plus trying to communicate on the worm, that's going to add up on the upper body very fast. So we're going to see how they do once they get into rounds three, four, five, six.
347 into a 20 minute time cap. This is the second of three times to the worm and you're taking a look at the Long Island team from CrossFit Undivided. Christine Best, Griffin Raleigh, Christine Zanosko, one of the strongest women in CrossFit, and Mike Needleman, who's previously competed on a team for training Think Tank. That's a veteran group, struggled so far though. 17th, 11th, 16th, and 16th with some work to do today.
When you, Bethany, having competed at the Games, maybe have a day that you didn't expect or see coming, what's your mentality when you start the next one? It's just next day mentality. You just have to reset. You have to let go of whatever happened in the past, whether it was good or bad. Because if you hold on to good things, too, it can also cause some mental mistakes because you just get really excited, but especially when it's bad.
Got to let it go. Do you change your strategy? Do you say, all right, we're not where we wanted to be. We need to try to take some shots and maybe be a little uncomfortable. Depends on the workout. It depends on your strengths as a team and as athletes. If you feel like you can make some moves, especially if you know that you've done the worm over and over again, and you're like, I am so confident, even though we've not done this movement in competition, this is the time to make a move. Got to make some risks.
Greater heights took a 20th in event four yesterday. They are the first team back to the rig. Here comes UNESCO and that crew from undivided. Greater heights on the right side of your screen. Undivided on the left. Sierra Cole, athlete closest to you on the right side. Working with Sidney Waltz, the former Kentucky gymnast.
I think a good note, too, is every round, they can decide which pair goes first. So if the males are like, hey, I'm toasted, y'all get up there, females. Or same thing, vice versa, with the females. They're like, I'm not going. I'm not ready. The males can go first. So that's kind of nice. Looking for synchronized chest to bar.
And it's actually kind of nice that you're looking at your partner here, as opposed to being next to your partner and having to look over. Correct. And then, like, if you're on one bar next to each other, you're having to go a little bit more narrow, which is not fun. So I like this setup a lot more. It's pleasing to the eye, I think, for the fans and people watching on camera, but also probably nice for the athletes.
Undivided making their way back up to the worm they surpass greater heights, but just by a couple of seconds here There is something soothing right like this is this is CrossFit ASMR Just watching lots of people in synchronicity doing Chester bar We hope we want that to happen for them
This is the final round for the athletes that are making their way to the worm of the chest-to-bar. Next time they return to the rig, the movement changes and the rep scheme changes. It will be sets of seven bar muscle-ups in synchronization.
And that's where I'm intrigued to see how their upper body holds up, because with synchro bar muscle-ups, they have to hold at the top, and that extra squeeze and hold at the top, even if it's just one more second, that's gonna add up on the triceps and the upper body, and we'll see what it does to the worm.
That worm implement weighs 365 pounds. The main sandbags weigh 100 pounds for the men, 70 pounds for the women. So you'll always have a male competitor in the front and a female competitor in the back. And then the gaps in the middle are 15 pounds, are they seven? Do you know that? The skin itself is seven pounds. And then the spacers are six pounds. That adds up, that's a lot of weight.
Not every gym has one of these. No, they're probably really expensive. Yet affordable, if you would like to own one at your home. That's true. Here comes Greater Heights. Remember, they were first back to the rig after the last round, but Undivided was first off the rig. So Greater Heights is making up ground on the worm. And keep that in the back of your mind, because this test ends on the worm.
11.24 has surpassed undivided. They've moved into second. Jessica Androsik across from you, working with Sydney Smith. I like seeing the different techniques in the bar muscle ups. I think a lot of the gymnasts do more of like a tipping motion where the feet come maybe a little bit higher, obviously not above the bar. And then we have another one where it's just like a huge arch at the bottom and then coming up.
sets of seven before you can trade out. You can take breaks, but you can't change pairs until you complete seven. I feel like bar muscle ups are one of those movements for the layman in CrossFit that you have on your bucket list. Absolutely. Bethany, how do you get one done if you've never done it before? Oh, man. I feel like with gymnastics movements, it's all about repetitions and just doing it over and over again.
And finally, it just clicks. There's going to be one day where a lot of people, that's why you see it during the open. Everyone's like, oh my gosh, I got it. It just takes numbers, numbers, numbers, numbers. That's how it is with all gymnastics movements. It's a very frustrating thing, let me tell you. But once you get it, it's probably one of the happiest moments that you can get across it.
This is a comfort spot for both of these teams. Sydney Waltz, a gymnast all around at the NCAA Championships for Kentucky. Jessica Androsik, a gymnast, her favorite event, bars. That's a little bit different. This is like a high bar versus the parallel bars, or the uneven bars, I should say. But looks to her advantage, for sure.
It is greater heights that makes their way to the worm and it is again 10 more worm over and backs and look at the synchronicity there. The call to just drop down and pick it up. Wow. Perfection. It's beautiful. That's a team that's probably worked on the worm a couple times at home. Poetry in motion for greater heights and 11.24, just a couple of reps behind.
And can confirm with 1124, Timon and Pumbaa, the matching tattoos on the guys, it's on the quad. So can confirm. It's very important information, if you didn't know. People wanna know the information about that. Riley Good and Tyler Cook, lifelong friends. Well, they've been friends for a long time. All right, the worm is being advanced for greater heights.
And they have two more rounds of bar muscle-ups and worm work. Right behind them though is 11.24. Undivided has fallen five reps off the pace. And also a good note is they have to get
every team member across that huge yellow line before they start doing their gymnastics movements. So, if not everyone's across, they cannot start their movements. It's almost a good time by. Like, it does slow you down, but it also lets you shake everything out. Gives you a little breather for a second, which is probably much needed in this long, grinding, spaghetti mess of a workout. It's so pleasing to the eye, though, at the same time. Let's check in with Bella Martin.
Joel, we're down here on the floor watching 1124. We caught up with Sydney this morning. She was telling us how important it is specifically for them to communicate well on this workout. We saw them at semifinals for the individuals back in June and communication was a huge problem for them. So we were not expecting this team to be able to hold on to almost take a heat win here this far into the workout. You can tell Sydney's talking to her team, keeping the boys calm and it's actually paying off for this team. And they were pretty,
pretty confused and a little bit concerned about this one. Bella, thank you. And because semifinals were online for teams this year, a lot of these teams haven't competed as a foursome in person. 1124 did. They had that experience going to syndicate crown. Semifinal had teams. There were no tickets at stake, though. You get to work out some of those things. Yeah, I think it's definitely an advantage to have that in-person competition.
If you don't, you just, you can't replicate that in training. It just, you just can't, especially like when it comes to intensity and things going wrong. It's a beautiful thing to have that mess up or that hiccup in in-person competitions. And Bethany Flores, things will go wrong, will they not? Oh yes, they will absolutely go wrong. If they don't, you're doing something wrong. Greater heights in 11.24, neck and neck as they head to the worm.
seven minutes until the cap. 10 more worm clean up and overs, followed by one more round of bar muscle ups and one more set at the worm. Honestly, the struggle part has seemed not that strugglesome for some of these teams. The second over.
I'm very surprised. I know there was a team that tried this out at the ranch, and their time was 20.05, so right over the time cap. But I think we're expecting to see a lot of teams hopefully finish this workout. I'm sorry, I stay corrected. Seven up and overs once you get to the bar muscle-ups. Ten on the first round.
And the final rep for greater heights they will advance and the hand is in the air for casey strong Do not put that thing down early. That's good team communication They are neck and neck And there are only two teams that are on their final round of bar muscle-ups
Hendersonville and undivided are heading down to the worm for their penultimate work on that implement. But this is where your race is. CrossFit Hendersonville is in third place, right side of your screen. Dalton Rogers in front.
And you can see just a little bit of the fatigue here, Bethany, that extra push in the dip out of the bar muscle-up. They add up very quickly. And once they go, they go. So if you need to break, break them up. But you don't want to start failing on bar muscle-ups. This is 102 upper body pulls in this event. And there's a no rep for Casey Strong on the right side. How often are you training that kind of volume?
Hopefully a good amount. You want to hit that, because if you don't, then when you get to a competition, it's going to be a nice slap in the face. But that's also showing you that they're leaving everything on the line. They're coming here, and they're going to try. They're putting everything out. And I love to see it. I love to see it.
Looking to set the time to beat here for 11.24. They are 25 points out of right now, the second heat. You can't get to the podium from heat one. Long way to go, but 11.24 needs Riley good to go. Tyler Cook is saying, get up. We're in Albany. Yeah, we got, we had a little bit of some yelling out there, but we got some passion on the floor, passion on the floor. And there goes 11.24.
Tyler Cook pointing up to the crowd. Overtake has hit a snag. And 11.24 is all alone here at the front of Heat One. Seven more reps. Comes greater heights, right behind. This is where it's gonna be costly. You have a no rep.
It could be do or die. It could be between first and second place right there for this first heat. That's the key. 11-24 needs to be clean here. And they just got no reps. Got to start the whole rep over again. And that's what we've seen with Greater Heights. They've actually been very pretty with their reps the entire time. Greater Heights is a full rep behind.
Now we are even, 11.24 is able to hold on. That's an event win and a heat win, back to back, five big booms for 11.24. With greater heights, not that far behind, four seconds.
Now CrossFit For Friends has done some moving while they've been paying attention to everybody else. Here comes Hendersonville Mayhem. But already at the worm is the team from For Friends Smart out of Castellon in Spain, one of the first affiliates in Spain. Led by Elena Caratalla, who has competed individually at the highest levels of this sport, not only at the CrossFit Games, but at the Rogue Invitational.
Three more reps for four friends. Tommy Martinez and Caratalla all train together, both of them. The other two members of this team travel more than 500 kilometers to train on weekends. There is some dedication for the Spaniards on the left. And with one rep remaining, they will be the third team to finish, 90 seconds ahead of the cap here in Heat 1.
Hendersonville. Last team in, and the fourth team to finish. They are filling those worm clean over the shoulders. Camp Rhino is across. I feel like after this, everybody's going to be excited to squat later. Back to the lower body, away from the upper body. Devastation at the finish line. Yeah, they're hurting.
undivided finished. As they should be. They should be hurting. That means that they're just leaving it all out there on the floor. Final three reps for Prestanda. That is Victor Langsvid's box. Third athlete from the right. 30 seconds left to go. Here we go, and in.
Training Think Tank is still back at the rig. Body Blueprint is on the worm. 15 seconds left to go. Remember, this is the second time ever as a team Body Blueprint had touched the worm. They're all veteran team athletes, though. And time will expire on the Body Blueprint crew and TTT.
By the way, in case we don't get a chance, happy 30th birthday, Bryce Broome. Yes. That's a good one. The big 3-0. But 11-24. Pose for the benefit of those with flash photography. Cindy Smith. Yeah, go get your belt. You just want to heat. Take a look at our replay from Rogue.
Wow, what a grinder of a workout. That was a tough one. We had Greater Heights coming out out front. Let me tell you, their reps were clean the entire time. Those bar muscle-ups started to get a little spicy for actually 11.24. And to see them just to continue to move through that, that was amazing. Greater Heights stayed in the lead pretty much the entire time.
Up until the last round, where CrossFit 1124 came with the W right at the end. They did have a no rep, though. And we were scared that Greater Heights wasn't coming, but 1124 stole that win, and they're excited. Time to beat. 16, 59, 45. We'll see how that holds up. And then 17, 03 for Greater Heights.
still have 10 more teams to go on event number five for the 2025 CrossFit Games teams.
This is the 2025 CrossFit Games. We are at MVP Arena in Albany, New York. Today's coverage is presented by Veletas. We are Veletas, and we are made not born.
with Bethany Flores, seven-time CrossFit Games athlete out of PAC CrossFit. Miss Bella Martin out of CrossFit Mayhem down on the floor. My name is Joel Godet from Resilience CrossFit in Medfield. The rest of our crew, glad to have you with us for Heat 2 of Event 5 here at the CrossFit Games for the teams. Campbell City CrossFit wearing the white and red leaders jerseys
With 335 points, a 10-point lead over CrossFit Butcher's Lab, those top two teams between their eight athletes have three previous CrossFit Games appearances on a team. Incredible. Sometimes it's better not to know. Here's your event description brought to us by the U.S. Border Patrol. Be an agent of strength.
They're going to do six total rounds. The first three rounds are 40 synchro chest-to-bar pull-ups and 10 worm clean overs and backs. Then they're doing three rounds of 28 synchro bar muscle-ups and seven worm clean over and backs with the male-male and a female-female pair. It's going to be a grinder and a spaghetti mouse at the same time. The cap is 20 minutes. The time to beat is 16.59. Our recipe for success brought to us by Tempo. Let's get gymnastic.
Yeah, the first one is get your massy. It's a lot of work with the bar muscle ups and the chest to bars. So we're going to see how that impacts them. And then the second one is you're going to have to grind it out. This is one where it's a long workout, a long time cap, and we're going to see how they do when it comes to the end and how they're feeling.
The art of being in first, a third, a second, a third, and an eighth. Those points will add up to a spot in lane five for Camel City CrossFit. Butcher's Lab in second. CrossFit Mayhem is in third, three lanes over the middle of the floor. Down to Miss Bellamartin.
How can you not like Camel City CrossFit? We've got two Masters Games females, a police officer and a firefighter, all on the same team, training out of one affiliate. If that's not CrossFit, I don't know what is. This team came in definitely as an underdog team, but they're in the leaders jerseys, and that's got to feel good. We caught up with them this morning. They said they were a little bit surprised based on how everything's going, but they're trying to stay composed, under control. And tell you what, guys, this is the second time they've seen the worm together as a team. They said they have a worm at the gym.
But they can't get together in time to do it. So we'll see if their communication pays off in this one and if they can keep those leaders jerseys on for the rest of the day.
Our team to watch, Vision Fuels Victory from Zeni. Leaders jerseys for that Camel City team. And yes, they have a worm. No, they don't get to use it a lot because of the fact they all got jobs. This is a team of people that do CrossFit. Bella alluded to the fact that you've got a firefighter, a cop, an RDN, registered dietitian, and an affiliate owner coming together in their free time. And they are in first place.
I love to see it, Bethany. They will love to see it. They were kind of shocked themselves. Yes, sometimes it's better that way for the mindset coming into it. No one's thinking about you. No one's looking at you. You can just kind of be free out there and that's exactly what's happening and what happened on day one. And sometimes you end up with the leader jersey on nice.
Starting with those 40 chest-to-bar pull-ups, they are done in sets of 10. You cannot switch before or after 10. You can break, but you can't switch. Male-male, female-female pairs. And we're gonna see how those add up. I have a feeling that it's gonna get a little spicy, probably when they get more to the bar muscle-ups and trying to do the clean over and backs, but we'll see how everyone handles all of those chest-to-bar pull-ups. CrossFit Oslo is the first team to the worm.
Now, communication will be interesting for Oslo in lane seven, because that team has trained together a lot, for three of them. But Kristen Holta was a late sub, coming in to replace Ingrid Hodenmeier, injured last week. However, Kristen Holta is one of the greatest CrossFit athletes of all time. She is, she is. But, the only thing is, caveat is, she's the greatest, indeed.
So we don't touch the worm in individual. That might be a little tough for her, but hopefully she's been taking notes as the team's been getting ready, and we'll see how they do. In heat one, the fastest chest-to-bar time in the first round was 52 seconds. Oslo beat that by tenths of a second. Time to watch is 16.59. We are a long ways away from that. This is a grinder of a test to start day two.
And we did have a team at the ranch to test this out, and they got 20-05. So they time capped. But we had a lot of people finish in the first heat, so I'm expecting to see that here in the second heat as well. Oslo is second back to the rig. Lara Pair beats them by just a couple of steps.
And they had a good showing yesterday with the gymnastics movements. So I expect no less with the bar muscle ups and the chest to bar. Same thing here in round two and in round three. It is the sets of 10 chest to bars until your team accumulates 40. And you can choose every round with your pair. You can decide who wants to go first. So if the males are feeling a little tired,
maybe the females go first. And then the next round, females feel a little tired, then the males go first. Let's check in with Bella. I'm on the floor watching La Repair, and they had a solid first day. And they're having an even better show out day two. We've got two gymnasts and two lifters on this team. So if there's anybody that's going to be balanced on the floor, it's these guys. They're going to try to get an event win, but they're going to have to catch Oslo. But I think their communication might be what gets them across this line first, Joel.
Well, they are just behind Oslo right now, making their way to the worm. Oslo has completed one of the 10 worm up and overs.
I'm loving those hot pink shoes out there. Those look pretty great. You talk to the people at home, like, how do we find you when we're watching on the screen? Look for the bright pink shoes. I mean, honestly, as a competitor, I do that, too. Just for like your family and friends out in the stands. They want to see those shoes that they can point you out. So good on them for doing that.
Hand is in the air for both Lara Pair and Oslo. David George is on the wrong team. She's got the bright pink over there. She didn't communicate with her team to get the hot pink on. Final wrap on the second. Worm up and overs and Oslo will advance.
And they'll head back to the rig for another round of chest-to-bar and the final round of chest-to-bar. Another note, too, with the team, they have to get all of their members across that thick yellow line before they start doing their gymnastics movements, which is kind of nice, right, Joel? I don't know. I like that because they get a little bit of a rest. But yeah, if they do that, that is some costly no reps. Don't don't get silly like that.
Kind of makes it like a team workout and your affiliate on a Saturday, right? You can't start the next movement until everybody finishes and returns from their run. True. All about teamwork. Which we love to see on team. More of that, please.
Ptolemyr Akinyo finishing with Viktor Helsingov. And now look at the way that Oslo is doing this, right? They're not swapping athletes in and out, right? They're putting themselves next to each other and just popping up and down off the rig. It's saving milliseconds, but those can matter. Everything counts if everything adds up. So those little things are veteran moves for sure, even though maybe those four haven't worked together on a team at the games.
Tola has, what, seven appearances at the games on different teams, so he definitely has his own veteran experience. Butcher's Lab has made up some ground. They're now in second place. Lara Pair is just behind them in third. And then Franco's at the top of your screen is in fourth. Here is Lara Pair. With the hot pink shoes on.
And they've got a nice fan base. It's a fairly easy drive. Yeah, but they should have wore hot pink shirts to go with the hot pink shoes. I'm a little disappointed. They have maple leafs on those shirts. OK, all right, all right. Counts for something. Le Repair is led by Audrey-Anne Peridupuy, the 21-year-old affiliate owner. Excuse me, now 23-year-old affiliate owner. That's really young.
helped buy into the affiliate when she was 18. Wow, that's impressive. 630 into our 20 minute time cap. And as Oslo advances the worm, they are halfway through this test. As far as rounds right now, fewer reps in these back three rounds, but halfway through at the 650 mark, they're going to obliterate the time to be impressive.
I am interested to see how these bar muscle-ups start adding up. You do have to do it synchro, so you have to pause at the top to make sure that you're staying synchro with your partner. And I don't know, that's gonna get a little spicy on those triceps. So we'll see how the worm is in the second half of this. The crew is returning to the rig, but Oslo has a comfortable lead. As soon as the women drop, that means they're halfway through here.
That'll be 14 bar muscle-ups in the bank. And you're going to see different versions of the bar muscle-up. Some people come a little bit higher with their knees and do more of like a kipping gymnastics movement. And then some people are more vertical and just have a huge arch. I think it's just going to depend on comfortability. And sometimes that gymnastics background, you're going to bring your knees a little bit higher. That's what I do.
This is the 20th of 28 bar muscle-ups for Oslo Kreiger, now 21. And they'll break final seven. Those belong to the ladies. Those are your top three teams right across your screen. And I like that they're facing each other instead of just on the same bar. You don't have to go as narrow with your grip on the chest-to-bar or the bar muscle-ups. So I'm pretty sure they're thinking CrossFit right now and how they decided to set it up this year.
to stare into your partner's eyes. It was like the double unders yesterday. Final rep. Linda Kvam and Holta drop and back to the worm. We are now on a round of seven worm up and overs. Incredibly impressive here for the way that this team has moved through this. Again, we talked about how experienced Kristen Holta is in CrossFit.
She's never competed on a team at the games and she's been on this team for a week. Very impressive. That goes to veteran leadership, communication. I mean, Tola Maracanio clearly, who is the team master, is in control of this situation. She's a mom? Yeah, yeah, Cristin Alta.
I think that kind of helps. You're just like, I don't know, you're more level-headed, a little bit more calm. Osla won the first two events yesterday. It was the third time in games history a team won the first two events and the first time Rich Froning wasn't on that team. But then took a 17th in event three. That dropped them off the podium. Right now 30 points out of first place, but they are gonna make up some serious ground.
Five points is the difference between each placing with every event the rest of the way. And Oslo is back to its second set of 28 bar muscle ups. And the guys will go first. And Layer Repair is kind of falling off the pace a little bit. I saw they failed a couple of bar muscle ups with the guys, so it's costly. Any type of no rep, very costly. Elsingoff with a great handball background.
It's a really big sport up in the Nordic countries. Maracanio, former wrestler. Lindigvam, also a great handball player. Played 13 years of it.
They're all team athletes, like they've all been on teams. So Kristen Holta felt pretty confident saying, hey, I've been an individual athlete. My team knows what it's like to be on a team, though. I'm going to blend in if I just kind of play along. And I think when you're one of the best on the individual side, I think you can adapt and overcome. That's just being an athlete. So it's really showing right now with this workout.
And having a team background sports with some of these other athletes, like, that definitely helps when it comes to team and being at the games. Final five reps for Oslo Kreiger. Kreiger, of course, the training program. It has two full-time employees, Joachim Riding and Kristen Holten.
And then a host of coaches. Those triceps are probably on fire. This is getting tough with the bar muscle, especially for the females.
CrossFit and Norway just go hand in hand over the last few years. The country has committed to it on the national level. The boxes have exploded. CrossFit Oslo has almost a thousand members. They have three separate rooms where they can run multiple classes out of simultaneously. It has been an incredible culture growth.
No European team has ever finished on top of the podium at the CrossFit Games though. CrossFit Oslo has that opportunity here in 2025. They do have a chance. Butcher's Lab right behind them in second place.
And they were excited for this workout. We talked to them in the warm-up area, and they were like, yes to the worm, yes to communication. We talked in heat one. Many teams haven't worked with worms a lot. If you walk in the door of Butcher's Lab in the meatpacking district of Copenhagen, there are like four worms stacked up on shelves. They got all sorts of worms to work on. Are they full of meat? That would be fitting. Would be fitting. At least one of them. Hard to keep sanitary.
I mean, it's covered. It's fine. Then they can cook it afterward. Oh, back for their final bar muscle-ups. Ain't you be giving people ideas? Hey, if you don't have a worm, maybe you can just pack a bunch of meat together and make your own worm. 28 muscle-ups on this final round. This is Franco's.
Jordan Kerr. They got some strong people on their team. Yeah, they're looking forward to the back squat. Yes. Very excited about the back squat. Oh, and Oslo has run into a little bit of a snag here. Oh, did Kristen Holta's grip rip? Wow. Kristen Holta's right grip ripped. You just got to go barehanded. It either ripped or she just needs more chalk on it.
And excuse me, that's Uda closest to us right next to Tola. Yeah, she's going back to that right hand a bunch. I don't know if she just slipped, if the grip gave up on her.
Either way, this is the stuff that sometimes doesn't happen in training. You can't really prepare for it. And you just have to make do when you're in that position. And that's why it's nice to have teammates. I saw Tola trying to help her out a lot during that. Now, here's the thing to think about from the overall picture. Final four reps here for Oslo. And Udo Lundeklom is going to go back to the chalk on that right hand.
Camel City is nowhere to be seen. And they are in first place right now, but not by the largest margin. Only 15 points, three spots ahead of Butcher's Lab. So Oslo can finish first here, it's gonna help their case a lot. But if Butcher's Lab, who right now is in second, finishes in second, we may very well see Butcher's Lab wearing the leader's jersey heading into our next event.
which they need because I know for them with the back squat workout, it's not gonna be their greatest. So they need all the points they can get during this workout. If Campbell City finishes in fourth or worse, that puts Butcher's Lab ahead of them. Right now, Campbell City is in fifth. Oslo is the first team to the worm here for the final seven worm clean up and overs. Maracanio calling the shots up front.
Right now, it's all about just one rep at a time. Don't get ahead of yourself. Breathe, be where your feet are at. And you got a minute and a half until the time to beat. Nobody close to you. Butcher's Lab is in second, but it's going to be one and two unless something goes terribly wrong. Franco's coming up behind.
oslo looking for its third event win of the 2025 crossfit games and crossfit oslo inching closer into contention three event wins they needed that they needed that one that was good that should put them back into a podium spot after that 17th on event three yesterday knocked them out butcher's lap
That communication, beautiful. Butcher's Lab across, that is second place. And now here comes Camel City in the white leader tops. But Franco's has finished, that's third. Mayhem is ahead of Camel City. Camel City right, Mayhem left. If Mayhem beats Camel City here, the leader's jersey changes heading into our next event.
And Campbell City just got a no rep, so that was pretty costly. Oh, and you know what? Time to beat coming in to be a factor. Leader's jersey is changing. Mayhem comes across, and the 16.59 from Heat 1, 11.24, that also will beat Campbell City. So CrossFit Butcher's Lab is your new overall leader.
And Camel City is in a little bit of damage control here, trying to stay in the fight. There we go. They come across. And that's where you can see, like, teams that have used the worm before and have that communication and teams that don't. 17.24 was the final time for Camel City. Multiple Heat 1 times are coming in to be an impact there. Greater Heights had a better score.
and each placing is five points on the leaderboard. That's why even if you're in that first heat, you have to give everything you got because those times are factored in. Dylan Hemming is barking commands, eighth day ripping through this final round of seven.
To be honest, that's actually really impressive, because this is at the end of a 20-minute workout almost, and you're exhausted and you're yelling. That's the fitness right there. And it keeps you going. No time for rest. Here comes Proven. 90 seconds left before the cap. Everybody should finish. And if you had any doubt as to which team this is, check the shoes. That is La Repair in the bright pink.
They did run into a snag. Remember, they were in second at one point. But LeRipere is through. And all 10 teams finish in Heat 2.
Five events down for the teams at the 2025 CrossFit Games. Oslo Kreiger wins the event, vaults up the leaderboard. But the bigger story is who came in second, and that's Butcher's Lab, who we expect to be your overall leader when they take the floor again today.
Wow, and this workout was a grinder. We saw Oslo coming out hot at the beginning, and they held pace. We were surprised, but we had Lea Repair and Butcher Slab close behind. We see them on the worm right now, and communication was important, do or die. As we see Oslo just moving forward through each round, just staying ahead the entire time. And then when they got to the bar muscle-ups,
We saw Leigh Ripere almost making a move. Then we start seeing some mishaps on their team with a costly no rep, which got them behind. Then we saw Oslo with the win. She win.
Oslo in 1556. Campbell City winds up in seventh. So two times from heat one. Get in ahead of Campbell City, who were your leaders coming in as we wrap up our highlights from Rogue. Bella Martin, though.
You know, every team has a different way to get to the games. For Butcher's Lab, they made cookies. They were very good. They sold them at the gym to help pay their way here. And it's paid off because they are unofficially your new overall leaders. They are with Bella Martin. Pernilla, I want to congratulate you guys on unofficially an event win as a team. First time ever, but also you will unofficially be wearing those leaders jerseys for the rest of the day. How does that feel to you as a new team?
It feels amazing, like I'm so proud of the whole team because this is our rookie year. We have never been to the game, but I know these people are so fit, and we have worked so hard, and we have so much fun together, and we are really a great team. You are a very good team that has a lot of team communication skills. What did you need to do for this event to take second place and then now move into the first?
We needed to work together as a team and communicate with each other on the room and also on the gymnastic. Like, who is going first? Who is having that extra energy to keep it going? And I think we just did that perfect. We've heard you guys are a long way from home, and your friends and family have supported you all the way here through cookies and a couple of bake sales. What do you have to say to them back home to your gym community?
Butcher's Lab, thank you so much for cheering us up every day, supporting us, and for all our friends. We are just so happy for your support. And for our family and friends who are here supporting us, we are so happy you are here. There's nothing like the love of affiliates. Congratulations, guys. Great job.
Congratulations to Butcher's Lab. They come in second on the event. They are unofficially your new overall leaders, where you can find out if they are officially the overall leaders. That's what we call a cliffhanger at games.crossfit.com. Statistics, leaderboards, event descriptions, and more. Men's Event 5 is coming up next.
The 2025 CrossFit Games are brought to you by CrossFit, forging elite fitness.
CrossFit is my social time. And I think that is true for a lot of the people that come there because they're my friends, they're my family. And we welcome everybody. Our wall in the front is, you come and visit, you're gonna come and see us, and you're gonna get to sign your name on the wall. CrossFit is family, it is. It's one of the side effects, you get in good shape.
My wife signed me up without me knowing. Oh, by the way, you got level one, first of November. And I'm like, we got too much going on. She's having eye surgery next Wednesday on her back. And I'm like, we got too much going on.
And she says, oh, no, I already paid for it. It's not refundable. You have to go. Okay. And then when coach heard, well, this is good, he says, because, you know, you're one of our older participants here, been here forever. He says, this will encourage more people to come. It'd be nice if everybody in the gym was a level one and then just keep going up. I read the bios on our instructors down here last night. That's incredible.
Makes me jealous. I wish I was 20 years younger. It doesn't matter what you do in life. You learn. If you go through a day that you do not learn something, I don't care what it is, that day, to me, that day is a waste. That is my philosophy of life. Every day, you have to learn something. I've done automotive repair for 51 years, and I'll have somebody come in and say, well, I did this this way. Look, that's a better way to do that. You learn something.
I really liked the way they broke things down down here. They break it down. Cal is an incredible instructor, but they broke things down even at a greater level. But the way they broke things down yesterday, it was very interesting. The front squat was
I have never cleaned a front squat because I have bad shoulders, no rotator cuffs, no bicep tendons. A lot of times in a front squat, I'll come off the rack and I'll set it on my shoulders and I can balance. I can lift 200 pounds doing a front squat that way. I can't do 55 this way. But the way they broke it down,
I was like, man, I could do more. I could learn something. And that's cool. So yeah, I'm not apprehensive anymore. Everybody should take this course. You'll get something out of it. And I sure as hell have. My folks made it to their mid-90s and never did nothing. When dad was my age, he was on a second pacemaker. I'm not. I have lung problems. I used to smoke when I was young.
I owned a martial arts school for many years. I should have done this instead of that. I wouldn't have bad knees, plates in my feet, pins in there, plates in my head. I don't need that. This is more controlled fitness than going out and say beating the hell out of somebody. It was fun. This is fun as well.
You can stay right there.
so
world a better place. And we use CrossFit. What if two days could redefine your health and your life?
Welcome to your CrossFit Level 1 seminar. Our goal is to give you guys a better understanding of our definition of CrossFit. When we talk about CrossFit, the definition is constantly varied, functional movements, executed at high intensity. Forget fleeting trends and empty promises. This isn't a magic pill or a quick fix. This is the CrossFit Level 1 course.
Why don't we take a look at Seth and see if there's things we can address. An immersive experience led by passionate, world-class educators, coaches, and trainers, driven to empower you towards a longer, happier, and healthier life. What we realize is that true fitness is a compromise of skills, and that's what we're talking about being generally physically prepared for anything.
Over two transformative days, you'll unlock the power of foundational movements, understand the artistry of effective programming, and grasp the science behind lasting well-being. Everybody's journey is different from the CrossFit Games athlete to the person like me who just started CrossFit two weeks ago.
You'll discover how integrating sound nutrition and movement can be your greatest defense against chronic diseases. You'll learn to move with purpose, live with vitality, and truly thrive. What distinguishes it from other courses is the fact that people are watching how to make people better. This isn't just a fitness course. It's an initiation into a life of intentional health.
It's not even necessarily about where you start or what you do when you start this process. It's can you stick to it? Can you be consistent? Whether you're a seasoned CrossFitter or new to the journey, this course equips you to take command of your fitness and shape a healthier future. Own your health. We'll show you how.
Our prescription for wellness in CrossFit is meats and vegetables, nuts and seeds, some fruit, little starch, and no sugar. And what that is is a prescription to eat real whole foods. At the CrossFit Level 1 course, you won't just learn about moving well. You'll learn about living well. And living well starts with eating well. Because at CrossFit, we believe that nutrition is the foundation to a healthy lifestyle.
There's this theoretical hierarchy in the development of an athlete that looks like a pyramid. At the bottom of it, we've got nutrition, the theoretical hierarchy of the development of an athlete. So really, when we think about this in our training, nutrition should be the first thing that we focus on. In this course, you'll find inspiration not only to move better, but to fuel better, because you can't outwork a bad diet.
If your nutrition sucks, these things will not be where they could be if it were more solid. How we eat either supports or undermines our fitness over time. And all of this will help you own your health, optimize your fitness, and thrive.
There's a timelessness to the message that's contained in the Level 1s. It's the unchanging heart of what CrossFit is. They really helped us out and gave us key ingredients to CrossFit. The learning progression and all that stuff has really helped me out. Since its inception, hundreds of thousands of people have taken the CrossFit Level 1 course all around the world.
I got what I hoped for. I learned the movements, got some techniques corrected, learned some better coaching cues. And it will help you in your own individual journey, even if you never want to coach, in knowing really the methodology behind CrossFit and why it's so different than anything else that's out there. From teenagers to retirees, from doctors to teachers, coaches to students, the CrossFit Level 1 course changes lives, offering every single person
regardless of ability level, the opportunity to understand health, nutrition, movement, and CrossFit. The best learning experience I've had. I really liked the way
They broke things down. Everybody should take this course. The way that they taught, it built a desire to really want to be part of something that was bringing that more into other people's everyday life. In short, our members have the tools they need to approach their health and fitness more productively, more effectively, and more confidently. It's about how we're serving our community and trying to empower them with more skills and tools in order to be able to take this back to their communities.
It's worth every penny. You get so much more out of it than what you paid for it. Empowering you with the knowledge, confidence, and tools to live better, healthier lives. Own your health. We'll show you how.
Outro Music
and
Yeah.
so
Saturday continues here at the 2025 CrossFit Games, but on Wednesday and Thursday of this week, we had the first ever coaches and owners conference presented by HustleUp, where owners and coaches all around the world descended on Albany, New York, and the best minds in the business came together
to create better coaches, better business owners, and better CrossFit affiliates for the most important thing we have in this community, and that is our CrossFit affiliates all around the world. And inside the MVP arena,
We have the racks as we are going to get set to go heavy. I'm Chase Ingram. Along with me is Adrian Conway. Mike Arsenault will be joining us on the floor shortly. And we have our heavy test today. One rep max back squat presented by Lu Xiaojun.
Hey, man, this looks straightforward, brother. They're going to give you a one-rep max. And the secret to this is to make sure that you know your squat. So you're going to make sure that you have an idea of where you want to place the bar on your back. We're going to see some high-bar back squats, some low-bar back squats. And then, of course, you want to start sharp, not slow, which means that you're going to get three lifts.
If you start out sticky and slow, you're not going to prime yourself for the heavy lifts later. And that's where they're going to maximize your points. Now, we've seen a heavy squat at the games in the past of the CrossFit total. But what we have not seen are these new safety squat racks from Row Fitness. And more on that, let's go down to Mike Arsenault.
That's right, Chase. We're going to be dealing with some maximal weights for these guys with this back squat event as Peter Ellis just sets up his bar for his first attempt. So we have these safety racks and safety straps. So these safety straps were measured earlier in the week for each athlete. So they're all different for each athlete to ensure the athletes can get below parallel for a clean rep. But if they have to bail out, they will be protected by these straps. And the athletes are allowed to adjust their J hooks as well to get to a comfortable position before they make each attempt.
Thank you, Mike. Your lane assignments for heat number one. We're back to three heats of 10, as we'll start off with the men. Some heavy lifts, at least listed lifts.
In this heat, in our Vision Fuels Victory, athletes. Lane number two, Morris Feibig. Morris Feibig, an athlete with a listed back squat of 485, at least as a previous best. Now, we're using this data as a reference point, of course. This is why we play the game. The numbers don't matter as much. You've got to see what you can do on game day. And Jorge Fernandez, who has a listed max of 495. The question is, will we see 500 pounds this weekend?
Enrique Morieta. The attempt will be on the right. If you look at the bottom part of the lane, 445 to open things up. Very nice there by Morieta. More vertical in his squat position, choosing the high bar method. And one thing I want to keep an eye on the next time Morieta comes back up is that he tapped the straps at the bottom of his squat.
Moritz, they listed Max. Again, these are listed Max we have. A lot of these athletes like to play a little coy, a little cat and mouse with what they put out as far as what we can see. We're seeing some smooth as butter lift attempts going on right now. You'll notice a lot of these athletes just trying to prime their central nervous system, familiarize themselves with the load on the platform.
And then we'll see some weight start to go up in these second and third attempts. Toby Buckland at 445. Buckland does not have a listed max, says Bronislav Lankovic. Bron very intentional with setting his hips down and back. Really great squat mechanics there. He's setting himself up for some success with those later lifts, the way he mechanically executed there. 430-pound attempt for Peter Ellis.
You'll notice the signal go out. The hand comes forward as a good lift. Judges are looking for that the hip crease lowers clearly below the top of the knee. It was very clear in the standards the athletes have to go below, not too parallel, in order to have a successful lift. Yonakoski competing in his 10th CrossFit Games this weekend.
Now, as far as the lift itself, it just must start before that 20-second time frame is up. Diego Lucis, we've got a last-minute invite with a backfill from the far east throwdown.
475 open here for Jorge Fernandez. Are you surprised to see some of these opening weights that we've seen? This one right here surprises me. Now, we're hopeful to see well over 500 pounds for Jorge. But opening at 475 is a huge load of confidence, no pun intended, for him to hit that smooth.
475 is good for Jorge Fernandez. That is the heaviest weight we've seen put on the bar as Bill Leahy opens up with 435. Leahy has a listed max at 480. And that looks like no issue whatsoever. Tremendous speed going to the down and up there for Bill.
A lot of times, you want to control the initial portion of the descend and then use the stretch reflex, which means a little bit of that bounce out of the bottom of the squat. 435 attempt again for Isaac Newman. He will be your last lifter in this first heat. As he lifts a max of 485, that rep is good as the round one is done. And we'll go back to Enrique Morera.
Question is, is how's that depth going to fare with the straps that he chose to have set? And he's got to get out of the rack cleanly. Yeah, he has a little almost like a stumble coming back.
Good lift, and clearly they made the appropriate adjustment in the bottom. And not uncommon, we've seen, when you are warming up in the back area, now you're being corralled. A lot of times, the first round of any lift that we do seems to be the shakier, worse round. And in the second round, you see some clean lifts.
And what we're seeing is the adaptation of the central nervous system. These athletes now mechanically are more comfortable and confident on the floor. Now it's time to get competition mode. Fiebig just hit 485 as Buckland gets set. Fiebig's listed max. So some of these numbers we have might not be the same once we leave this event as Buckland will hit. Next is Bronislav Lankovic's attempt is at 470.
His list is max is 441, so. And Adrian, as you said, as he sets the hip back. Another reason, another thing in setting his back is he's not tilting his pelvis to do it. He's sitting the hips back while keeping that low back intact. That's right. Yeah, he's doing a great job of it. It's a very traditional, more so into a power lifting versus an Olympic weightlifting style of squat. But it's paying off right now for Big Braun.
Ellis, smooth for Peter Ellis. Temp good at 440. Iwonakoski. 450 on the bar for Koski.
Oh, yeah, great job there by Yona to drive through the middle. That's the tricky part. The squat's going to start to slow when you're at your threshold. That's a vet move by Yona to force his hips forward and keep it under the barbell. 445. And that'll be the first bell we see. And you can see why we are squatting out of that safety rack. Now, the athletes will have to break their bar down and set up themselves. They'll have plenty of time as Fernandez sets up for 490.
Opened up with 475. Now, Jorge was pretty quick there. Have some patience on the way down here, Jorge. Good timing. 10 pounds away from potentially our first 500-pound squat for the day. Leahy hit 435, now attempting 470.
Good lift there for Leahy. 460 on the bar for Newman. Newman with a very vertical torso through his squat. He's got a long torso. Really helps him keep his hips directly underneath his shoulders throughout the full range there. It's impressive. 480 for Enrique.
This is his third and final attempt. This event is sponsored by Liu Zhangjun. That is the shoe that Enrique is wearing, and it pays off. And that, my friend, is the heat of competition and the crowd coming to life. Uh-oh, 530 on the bar. 50-pound jump for Moritz Fiebig.
Oh, kicks! What a jump. What a jump. That's a big jump that he took from round one to round two. Hey, that's what we came to see, though. You'd love to see it. You'd love to see it. 485 for Toby Buckland.
Now, Liu Zhangjun is not just the shoe or the name brand. That is the name of one of the best Olympic athletes to ever compete in the sport. And there's a bit more on the line. If you use the shoes, the athletes will get 500. If you win the event, you get another 3,000. There it is. Five hundo for Big Braun. And score, one on the board for Bratislava Leikowitz.
500 pounds. Peter Ellis, he'll get his lift. Great clean lift there by Ellis. Very structured and strategic there. Still smooth. He had plenty in the tank. 465 attempt for Yonakoski's third and final lift. Now right out of the bottom, he's got to start to drive his hips forward as he presses through the bar.
Not in time, not in time. Lift is good for Tiago. 5.05, and this will be for the event lead for Jorge Fernandez.
He went 475, 490. Can he get another 15 here? Aiden, do you feel like he got a little shy at the very bottom, not bouncing out like he did for the 490? A little shy. Yeah, you really got to fight to maximize that stretch reflex, Chase. You want to use muscle, but if you can get some assistance from the joints and tendons,
just like bill leahy did right there on that repetition it goes a long way 485 is good for bill leahy that's good enough for a third in the heat tied three ways with toby bucklin and moritz fiebig newman watch how tall look at how tall he keeps his chest
And that is one of the hardest aspects. When you can have the unique ability to stay vertical through a squat, you've got to brace tremendously firm. You've got to rely on that belt, press your belly into that belt. And Newman just came up just shy. The question is, would we see it? And now it'll be, how many will we see? But Bronislav Olegovic hits the first 500 back squat of the afternoon.
Our top three lifts, 485, 490, and 500. The replay is presented by Rogue Fitness. Well, we talked about different variations of squatting. Fiebig, one of the athletes that really gets the bar pretty low on his traps, sends his hips back. But man, it was clean speed out of the bottom for his lift attempts.
And then it was Jorge Fernandez. We would go on to see him attempt a lift over 505, but this is where he hit his sweet spot. Finding that timing, and Chase, you alluded to it, really maximizing the stretch reflex out of the bottom. It helps him have more speed out of the hole there.
And then, of course, it was big Ron Alinkiewicz here. A little bit of a wider setup, feet just outside of hip width, strong brace, hips down and back. And then it was textbook squatting as he drove through the bar and gave us that victorious scream for the win. Your heat results.
Big brawn, first 500-pound back squat on the board, Jorge Fernandez in second in the heat, followed by a three-way tie. Now, the tiebreakers will be your previous successful back squats. So as we get further down the line, those second lists will come into play. The second heat of men will be coming up next to take on the one-rep max back squat.
One heat down, two heats left to go in this second heat. Do not go anywhere, because some of the heaviest back squatters we have in the business are about to take the floor. I'm Chase Ingram. Along with me is Adrian Conway. Mike Arsenault will join us on the floor shortly.
It's the One Rev Max Back Squat, presented by Lu Zhongjun. And Adrian, we've got to see one heat down. It goes pretty quick, so you've got to be dialed in and ready to go. What are your tempo recipe for success? Well, these athletes are going to get 20 seconds each. They're going to rotate through three rounds, so they're going to get three attempts. You've got to know your squat, and you've got to start sharp, Chase. You're laying assignments for heat number two.
The top three heaviest squats in the biz are in this lane between Hatfield, Nick Matthew, and Colton Mertens. So Mertens will be kicking things off. He'll be over in lane number one. For more on Mertens, let's go down to Mike Arsenault.
Well, Chase, we just saw the heaviest weight lifted in heat number one was 500 pounds. Well, guess what? Colton Mertens has already eclipsed that in the warm-up area. I saw him hit 515, and it looked like an air squat. So the amount of weight that's going to be lifted by these guys in heat number two is really going to be impressive. Will we see a number from this heat that begins with a six? Remains to be seen. I can't wait.
I mean, we might see it. Hey, look, I'm not going to argue against that. And Colton Mertens needs to be one of those guys with an opportunity there. We mentioned earlier that this event is sponsored by Lu Zhong Jun. That is the weightlifting shoe that is on the feet of several athletes, including Colton Mertens. And they're giving away $3,000 for event wins during the games. They're giving away an additional $3,000 if you win wearing the shoes.
Nick Matthew, that guy has squatted 500 pounds a couple times in a row himself. And guy, I thought he was done loading plates. Yeah, nah, nah, nah, nah. Not when you've got a listed max on our profile at 545. It's like, yeah, yeah, I'm going to keep loading this bar until I look around and see that I've outloaded everyone else at this point. And the man who has the best advantage to be looking around is in lane number 10. That is Austin Hatfield, who will be the last lifter in line
for heat number two. And we just saw him put up 505 for a double a couple of weeks ago. That's right. And if you pay any attention, you know, and people have been talking about this, we see what Hatfield had even been training with. If you're hitting working sets of 505 for a double in training, wow, that gives you a lot of upside and potential for what you're going to hit on the competition floor.
Opening at 535 pounds, Colton Mertens is going to try to kick this max lift off of the bank.
Okay. Oh, my God. I thought Mike Arsenault was being ridiculous. I thought Mike was being sarcastic. Yeah, could we see a six? I'm like, yeah, maybe in the middle of the three numbers, but not the first one. Not to mention Mr. Captain Jack Rosema opening at 500 pounds also. Oh, come on. Okay. I'm starting to get some 2021 Mac heavy snatch 300-pound vibes here. Three back-to-back attempts at 500-plus.
wow 5 15 what is happening
I was like, Colin, I'm sorry you have to go after those three. It's like going after the smart kids in a class project. I'm like, can I have just gone first, please? That's right. Boss Hart, handle your business, though. 420 is still wildly impressive. That's right it is. Keep it up. Yeah, keep it up. And the battle is for overall points, and we can't ever forget that. These guys are trying to concern themselves with their best overall placement, regardless of what all these other behemoths are out there putting on the barbell. And Rico Zanoni settling up for his first attempt.
Great lift there for Enrico. Great job bracing and staying firm throughout that squat. 425 opening lift for Callum Clements.
A little bit more of a low bar back squat here for Clemens. Low on his traps. His bum's going to go further back. Chest will drop forward. Still clean execution. Again, this is all about the athletes knowing their style of squat that maximizes their output. Just mentioned low bar as Ty Jenkins settles in for 450. What's the advantage or disadvantage there between high bar and low bar?
Often we see athletes with a little bit of a shorter trunk, longer legs go low bar. It's going to help them minimize the distance traveled. Put more of the strain chase on the back side of your body, a little less on the front side of your body. Tile hit 450 as Chris Ibarra settles in for 430.
That's good for Chris Ibarra. Do not be confused by the numbers you see at the top of your screen. This is still the first round of three in this Max MaxSquad event. Magda, a young athlete with also a big one rep max lift. We hadn't seen him hit a max in many years, but he knows he's going to prime himself for something heavy today. Also rocking that thick leather weight belt that usually are reserved for
powerlifting gyms as Austin Hatfield puts on 500 for his first attempt.
And it's good for Hatfield. Four 500-pound back squats in the first round as Mertens loads up 555, which is, as far as we know, the heaviest lift he's ever done for one. It's gonna take a second to brace. Big deep breath here.
5.55 is good for Mertens. Jack Rosema was laughing as he strapped up his belt. 5.15 for Jack Rosema.
That'll fight, finish. Nice job there by Jack. Wow. What a fight there to fight to get his hips under the load. And again, that's what we're going to see, folks, as we watch these athletes struggle. They got to get their hips forward in order to avoid failing. Nick Matthews with 535. 435 to the bar.
They've run six miles. They've done 60 deadlifts at 350. I mean, these guys, what they're showing is phenomenal. Enrico Zanoni waiting for his turn as Boszhard gets his second lift. 435 for Zanoni.
You even noticed a bit of a hip shift to the right there from Zanoni. Could be bothered by something on his left. Could have a natural imbalance of weakness. If you're training an affiliate and go through a heavy day, sometimes you notice that about your own movement. Got to stay square in order to win under those heavy loads. Clemens got 425. This attempt is 20 pounds more at 45. And it'll count.
He was feeling good about that when he gave us that extra pause and grimace at the top. Ty Jenkins going for 470. Jenkins will not get that. Chris Ibarra loading up for 450. Based on what we saw from Ibarra, this is a solid jump, but 20 pounds was doable with his bar speed.
Got to get forward. And this is where you start to wonder, Chase, is this the accumulation effect? Are these guys overshooting themselves in their second lift because they feel good, but then they realize that fatigue is starting to catch up? Tudor Magnus jumping 30 pounds from 460. This attempt is for 490. Austin Hadfield has made a 25-pound jump.
from 500 to 525. As Austin Hatfield might say himself, if you ain't first, you're last. That's his mindset going into a lot of these. Not today. Now a decision to make for Austin Hatfield as Colton Mertens is putting on 575. I was waiting to see 575, to be honest. With the way that moved, I'm not surprised. Let's get it.
And the Iron Hog smashes 570 pounds. Great shot of his coach there. Rolls him up for 520. 555 for Nick Matthew.
He got it. Great lift there by Nick. Way to stay the course. When the bar starts to slow that much, it's very easy to want to just back away and let it go. He fought through and got a huge lift there at 555. Boss Hart up for 465. 3, 2, 1, lift.
Rico Zanoni going for 440, missed his previous attempt. Zanoni's got to stay firm out of the hole. He gets a good bounce, got to keep it. Still has his successful first lift. 10-pound increase for Callum Clements.
455. This lift, if he wants to make it, it's going to take some time. He's got to be willing to fight. He's got this low bar approach where his hips are back, less forward. And so he's going to use a little bit more musculature to stand it up. He's got to fight. He does. Wow. And Clemens is happy about that one. Now, Ty went for 470, has now dropped down to 460. Previous best was 450. And the extra 10 pounds are good.
Great execution there by the rookie. Another 450 attempt for Ibarra. Missed his first shot on the second round. 450 is good.
Nice job there by Ibarra. Oops.
Gosh, I'd like to see Tudor slow down his tempo a little bit on the way down, right? And there's a part of this where you have to balance chase and training, the practice of maxing out. It's a valid skill that has to be exercised. Austin Hatfield going for 515. He missed 525 on his second attempt. 515 is good and good enough.
That'll be a separator. That's a mature decision there when you're maxing out. Could have easily gone for another one right there at that opening lift or that second attempt, but I like that choice. 570 is the new weight to beat, and that's just a lot of... 555 for Nick Matthew in this back squat. We knew it was gonna take some fight, and he gave us every ounce of that.
But it was the Iron Hog, Colton Mertens, that loaded up. Not 550, not 560, but 570 pounds. And unfortunately for the rest of the field, I'm going to tell you, there was room in the tank for a few more. So impressive by Colton Mertens. Double payday for him. Lou Jauzum coming through, cutting the checks. He earned every dollar. Colton Mertens takes the heat as his coach celebrates along with the
crowd here at MVP Arena as Colton Mertens sets the bar pretty high for the next heat. Third and final heat, the individual men take on the back squats next.
Welcome back to the MVP arena here in Albany, New York, the new home of the 2025 CrossFit Games. Today's coverage is presented by Belites. I'm Chase Ingram, along with me is Adrian Conway and Mike Arsenault will join us shortly. But if you missed the action earlier this morning, you missed out. Jay Crouch takes the event and takes the leader jersey from Jason Hopper.
He did it in impressive fashion, too, Chase. We talked about him earlier today being a threat that kind of slides under the radar. And someone must have told him, and he wanted to put us on notice. Let me tell you, when it has running, when it has deadlifts, when it has handstand walking, you're going to need to watch out for Mr. J. Crouch. J. Crouch is sitting there, take this black shirt off of me. I want the leader jersey. J. Crouch sits on top of the leaderboard. 12-point lead over Jason Hopper, and Jeff Adler has moved back into podium position.
Only four points ahead of Ricky Garrard. Individual event five is simply named the back squat. Sponsored by Liu Zhangjun. What is your tempo recipe for success? It's pretty simple here. You're going to want to know your squat, which means know the style. We've seen a varied approach. We've got low bar back squats. We've got high bar back squats. You've got to optimize it for you. And you want to start sharp, build confidence, not slow and sticky. That doesn't set you up for success on lift two and three.
For more on this, let's go down to Mike Arsenault. Thanks, Chase. Each athlete has a 20-second lifting window to complete each lift. What does that mean? As long as the athlete un-racks the bar before that time elapses, they are able to complete the lift. In previous heats, we have seen a few athletes utilize the safety bars if they fail the weight.
It falls on the back and it's protected from the floor with those safety straps and it's up to the athlete to then unload the bar and get it back on the J hooks before they complete their next attempt.
Your lane assignments, your top 10 after four events. We're not even halfway through the weekend yet and fireworks are already flying. And in this heat, we have not only your top 10s, but several games, champ. Two of those belong to Justin Medeiros. And we know that Justin Medeiros is a tremendous competitor, Chase. He's coming in this year looking as fit as ever. He follows coaching.
from Adam Nefer and also Jesse Bufano that really go into practice a lot with practicing and maxing out. It's a part of regular upper and lower lifts for both of them. The man who was wearing the leader jersey coming in this morning lost it in the individual event number four, but only a few points behind. And he has himself a pretty heavy one rep max squad himself. Jay Crouch, who in his interview said, Dave must have been watching my Instagram lately because these events
Post up very well for me. Kalyan Soza. Second place finish. In event number four, finds himself inside the top ten.
Sosa with a great lift there. He's a tall drink of water now. He's not a short guy, so he's got a long distance to travel to get to that below parallel position, and had some great positions on his way down and up. Alan Pepper opens with 470. Pepper here, more of a low bar back squat approach, lower down on his traps, sends his hips down and back, clean, as can be on 470. Your 2024 CrossFit Games champion, James Sprague, opening up with 440.
James always getting that bar as low as he possibly can on his traps here. 440 is a great opening lift for him. Strength is something that he's been working at tremendously. Harry Lightfoot sitting in seventh overall after four events. Opening attempt at 445.
Great lift there for Harry, no hesitation, great timing. Again, from a timing perspective, we're looking at the hips down and back, with control at the top, and then a faster stretch reflex out of the bottom. We'll see what Roman chooses here. Roman Krenikov, sixth overall. 475s his opening weight. And that's good for Roman, as he's leaning on the crowd to get him through this max lift. Justin Medeiros.
Looking in championship form. Opens at 470. Smooth opener there for Justin. Again, mechanically. Watch the way he gets the bar in and out of the rack. It's routine for him. He dials in the details. Ricky Garrard, four points out of a podium position.
Jeff Adler, your 2023 CrossFit Games champion. Three previous champions in this third and final heat for the men. Three podium finishers in this final heat for the men. Strong lift at 445 there for Adler. Jason Hopper sitting in second. 485.
45 is good. Yeah, that's a great opener at 485 for Hopper. Jay Crouch wearing the white leader jersey for the first time in his career after his first career event win in individual event number four. Gotta be good at 445 and round one is done.
Back to Calle and Souza. And this is where the competition really comes to life. Everybody being a bit conservative with their openers, and now we'll start to see either what they have potential to stretch to, or if they're going to make this their best lift here at Attempt 2. 415 is good. We still have Burton's best weight of 570.
has the best lift as Dallin Pepper settles in for 495. Got it. Great lift there by Pepper. Low bar approach, butt down and back. Helps him stay firm through his midline, too. You use this low bar approach just like we're gonna see from Sprague here. It helps you stay very firm through your mid-back as you squat down and up. Sprague will get 455.
It's not the heaviest weight we've seen, but that is a good weight for James Sprague. 465 on the bar for Lightfoot. Lightfoot had a pretty squat on the first one. He's got that medium approach, not too high on his shoulders. Smooth tempo down, control on the way up. I mean, it looks like there's a lot left in the tank there for her. We've got five lifts.
Over 500 pounds as Roman sets up for 485. 45 is good for Roman. 490 on the bar for Justin Medeiros. Open with 470.
Got it. Great control there for Justin. Again, routine. Ricky calling for the assistance from the crowd here. 4.55 on the bar for Ricky Garrard. Wow.
No, your squad is huge. I mean, look at the control Ricky goes down with and is still able to render that great stretch reflex out of the bottom to pop him right up. 475 for Jeff Adler. And he'll, oh.
It looked like he had it, Chase. I wonder if he almost got a little lightheaded there. Because he was really close to coming out of that sticky part of the squat. And his eyes looked a little lost as he bailed that lift. And here we go. Our first 500-pound attempt for heat number three. And it belongs to Chase and Hopper. Hopper will get it.
Great lift, Jason Hopper. Jay Crouch asking for a little help from the crowd. Putting on 485. Big jump here for Jay. He knows he's only 12 points ahead of Jason Hopper, so he has to stay close. He's got to get this. Got to fight, Jay. Wow. Two rounds done. We've got two 485s on the bars. Callie and Souza sets up for 425.
Roman hit 485, Crouch 485, Medeiros 490, Pepper 495, and with Hopper hitting 500, that's six guys at 500 or more. This five pound jump would put Dowin into that fifth place position.
So Dallin's gonna keep 495. James Sprague. This is a big lift for James, just to stay in contention. With a long weekend left to go. Got it! Wow! And that's big for Sprague. And he knows it. And for James, the rest of the weekend's gonna be wide open. 485 in the bar for Lightfoot.
Oh, and Harry knows. More there. Yeah, there's more there. He's celebrating that. He's probably had some great strength progress through the summer in training because there's some poundage left, and that's a pleasant surprise for an athlete. Roman hit 485. 495 on the bar for Roman.
Wow. You want to talk about fight. He saw that one all the way through until he couldn't anymore. This is big for Medeiros. He's sitting in fifth place overall. He got it. Justin is doing Justin things. 5.05 for Justin Medeiros. 4.65 for Ricky.
If he gets this, that'll put him outside the top 20. Adler with another attempt at 470. Two more lifters to go, and they're sitting on top of the leaderboard as Jason Hopper throws on 505. Yep.
Needs it. 505 is tied for fifth at the moment. And it's just Medeiros that holds that spot. And Medeiros will have it alone. Huge for Crouch here. If he can get this, he may be able to hold on to this jersey for another event. 495.
And he's not going to get it. And that'll put him at 485. And Justin Medeiros wins the heat. And Justin Medeiros, we've seen this before. 12th, 2nd, 4th, 9th. Not many event wins, but lots and lots of top fives. And he may have stacked another one. And Justin Medeiros looks very dangerous.
We had some great squats in this heat as we knew we would. And this is Dallin Pepper putting on a show with a bit more of a low bar back squat here. Again, knowing yourself, drive through the middle, getting his hips forward and not being denied, no matter what that weight was on his back. But it was Hopper getting up underneath this 500 pounds that really fired up the crowd. Hopper using a very opposite approach to Pepper. High bar, keeping that chest tall, drives through the middle, a little sticky.
No problem for Mr. Hopper. He saw it all the way through. But it was Justin Medeiros, the one that's building this dangerous momentum through the course of the weekend. We talked about Jesse Bufano, Adam Nefer, priming him with maxing outlifts by strategy every week. And it's a skill that Medeiros has learned to master. Look at that. That's how you meet yourself where you're at and maximize where you're at today. Justin Medeiros putting on a show with the back squat.
As the dearest clan in the stands as they always are cheering on the two-time CrossFit Games champ at 505. And it is Colton Mertens who put on a show for this crowd inside the MVP arena. He's down with Mike Arsenault. Colton, we have the Colton Mertens fan club over our right shoulder. 100 points, 570 pounds.
And it looked like there was more left in the tank. You really didn't get a push from the guys in heat number two to see if you had more than 570. How much was left, if necessary? I think I underestimated the bump I was going to get from the crowd a little bit. 570 felt the same as 400 did in the back. So I'm not sure how much more I had in the tank, but it felt way better on the floor.
And that was a new one-rep max back squat PR for you, 570 pounds, picking up those 100 points. A rough day one. How did you reset yourself mentally to come into the weekend? Yeah, day one sucked. But I got to get my ass to work and start climbing up that leaderboard. 100 points on this one. We got 200 points available tonight. And we're going to go for broke. A great start to that comeback, potentially, Colton. Congratulations. Well done. Thank you.
The Liu Zhangzhu promo offer, guys. Looking for a serious upgrade in your lift, save 15% on the Liu Zhangzhu shoes. Scan the QR code now or head to liuzhangzhu.com and grab your pair because Colton Mertens just got $6,000 richer with that Event 5 win. The men are done, but the women are coming up next.
Welcome back inside MVP Arena here in Albany, New York for the 2025 CrossFit Games. You're getting set for individual event number five. I'm Chase Ingram. Along with me is Adrian Conway. Mike Arsenault will be down on the floor later.
Women's event number five, presented by Lu Xuanju, is simple as a one rep max back squat, but it is not that easy. Adrian, what are your tempo recipe for success? These athletes need to know their squat, which means, are they going to go low bar? Are they going to go high bar? Are they going to move fast? Are they going to move slow? And they need to start sharp and not slow, meaning that they need to build momentum for lift number two and lift number three.
Your lane assignments, three heats of 10, starting with our bottom 10 after four events. So we have three total heats of this maxed back squat. Your vision fuels victory athletes to watch over there in lane number two, Mariana Meza out of Mexico, taking the floor here. Mariana has actually been on the scene. If you've been following Guadalupe Luza Latin Cup, she's won it two years in a row.
Now she's on the big stage here at the CrossFit Games. On the big stage as a rookie with a listed back squad at 335. So she's got to be a natural, someone that we keep our eyes on in this one, Rip Max.
Emily DeRoy is back from individual competition for the second time. As DeRoy has one of the heaviest listed squats for the women. Although, if it's anything like the men, we might as well throw those maxes out the window. As we bring in a guest to the booth that knows a little bit about competing on the competition floor, Alex Kazan. Welcome. Hi, thanks for having me.
Alex, we've seen some crazy weights tossed up by the dudes. You've been on this competition floor for years. You've done max lifts in front of the crowds. What is it about the crowd that boosts those lifts for an athlete? Oh, there's nothing like it. Like, the adrenaline. I swear you could lift whatever you think you can lift. You can lift 20 pounds more. It's so cool.
In the background, I'm assuming the warm-up area, you're sitting with your coach. You've got a plan. This is lift one. Maybe look for me for two, three. But does that plan every once in a while? You're like, I don't know. That felt pretty good. Maybe we'll go off script a little bit.
Yeah, I feel like Justin and I usually have a pretty good game plan. First lift, you always want something safe. Get a good number on the board. Second lift is like you're, I'm happy with this. This will be good. And then you want to set yourself up to have some fun on that third lift. Caroline Prevost. Now, Alex, you did qualify out of the NorCal Classic. Caroline Prevost, since you had a withdrawal due to injury, got that spot for you.
And not pouring salt in the wound, but you've competed here. You've finished at the highest level. You get to sit back and watch this for the first time from the stands. But talk about you had to be there. What does it feel like from the outside looking in, for those that cannot understand at home? Yeah. Like, for me, it's really bittersweet to watch. Like, I'm just sitting here like, man, like, I want to throw some weight around and be down there. Yeah, these athletes are incredible. And yeah, it's really fun.
Luisa Marquez will kick things off. 270. Now, I heard you play some bets earlier on a podcast of what that number may be. What do we think we may see? Does it change after you saw what the men did? No, I'm going with my gut. My first thing was 350. I feel like we're going to see at least someone hit 350. That's what I would have wanted to hit. Caroline Prevost sets up for 295.
We are going to go through three rounds of this one-rep backs, back squat attempt. Athletes will have 20 seconds. Now, Alex, how is the recovery from that injury you sustained earlier? Definitely getting a lot better on the mend. For a while, I had some nerve damage, and it's starting to come all back. And now just getting my calves and all the surrounding muscles firing again. So yeah, definitely much, much better.
Sunghyun Choi. She'll get her first lift. 280 on the bar for Christina.
Alex, how important is that first lift? Not necessarily about the weights you put on the bar, but building confidence for the second and third attempts. Yeah, for myself, and I think a lot of athletes can agree, the way you feel plays a huge impact on how the lifts go. So you want that first lift, especially after being in the corral and being tight, you want that first lift to feel good and fast. So that way you keep that going into the next one.
Just saw a miss from Emily DeRoy, who has one of the top five lifted maxes. Yeah, that's a tough way to start there. One of the keys is to start sharp, not slow. And now she's going to have to make some really hard choices as we watch Mikulishin have a successful opening attempt. First 300-plus successful lift we've seen, as Maria Camila Quintero sets up for 290. Now, Alex, we talked about having a successful lift.
What's the plan B if we miss the first one? Oh, I've been there a time or two. Unfortunately for me, usually my misses have involved Olympic lifting. And sometimes you just got to pull and pray at that point. But I think with the back squat, you can be a little more meticulous and kind of assess, hey, was that just too heavy? Or did I just miss my time out of the bottom? And then you make your choice.
But you've got to be smart, because if you miss two in a row, then you're putting yourself in a hole. Jen Muir nails 325 and she's hitting 350. Jen Muir is one of those athletes. Everyone talks about maybe her endurance or gymnastics because of success at the semifinal level. Jen Muir has a power lifting background that most people don't know about.
Well, and that was obvious there, even in her setup and execution. Low bar approach, hips very far back, chest cantilevered forward, and she smoked it using that strategy. 325 is the heaviest weight we've seen as we make our way back around for round number two. Luisa Marquez, also 290 on the bar.
will not get it. Now, athletes, it's different from event to event, year to year. But in this case, they are allowed to go down from that attempt in case they miss it. Yeah, that's nice. It kind of gives you that freedom to play a little bit and not be so stuck. Yeah, it really allows you to have a little less pressure in these jumps. Wow. Great finish there by Meza. 295 is good for Meza.
As Prevost is loading up the bar to 315. 315 is good.
Yeah, good clean lift, and what we'll be looking for on her next jump, Chase, is her ability to get the hips forward out of the bottom. A lot like we saw with some of the earlier lifts from the men. If the hips lag behind too long, you're just going to have to dump it forward. Here come the threes as Seungyeon Choi goes from 295 to 310.
It's so funny. I have, like, the same, like, nerve feelings that, like, I would have down there. I'm like, why am I shaking? Oh, I'm watching you squat with them. Yeah, I know. You're leaning back a little bit. They're leaning forward. It's very hard not to do that, except, Alex, you'll be very tired if you do 30 back squats every time you have to take the floor. Oh, 295. Luda Takis.
Gets her second lift. See if she can make this one. DeRoy opened with 290 and missed that. There you go. And at 275, I mean, it looks more maybe positioning or just wasn't in the right spot at the bottom. Yeah, I mean, and you can even speak to this, Alex. Think about the accumulation of work they've already experienced. Oh, yeah. Does that go into a lot of the decision making, at least with an opener and then maybe the second lift? Yeah, I think, obviously, I don't know what their body feels like. But I can tell you the times I've competed, day two, day three of the CrossFit Games,
Rollin' with what you got. McElishan adds another 10 pounds. 320 is good. Wow. But I'll say, even if you're sore, though, there's something about here, like, it doesn't matter. Like, you still pull out the numbers that, like, you don't think you can hit. 295 on the bar. A five-pound increase from 290. That's good for Quintero. All right, where'd she go? 345? 345. 345.
for Jan Muir. People are going to see this akin to what Justin did. Look at that setup. It's a one-two step back up from the rack. Deep breath. Oh, easy. Oh, my gosh. You know what you do when you see a serious lifter like that? You look at the shoes. No doubt.
Oh, that was so good. Yeah, she wants her heels close to the ground, man. We got different approaches. Some people in their flats, some people in their holy shoes. Those athletes that are geared for the posterior, they like to keep their heels close to the ground. Syria Mejia, she'll hit 290. And we have one round left to go as Luisa Marquez sets up for 285. Missed her previous lift at 290. Nice. There you go. Wow.
Back squats are tricky, too, because everyone's sticking point is so different. So you never know where the lift is going to be made or failed. 305 for Mariana Meza. We watched some of the men get well above parallel and still not finish the lift. Yeah, that's where my sticking point is, right there. Like, when you're pretty much up. Right when everybody's like, you got it. I'm like, no, I don't. This is the hardest part. Yep. 305 is good. 325 for Prevo.
He's already got 315 in the bag. Hoping for another 10 pounds.
She won't get it. But 315 is still good. It's tricky. And it's good for third in the heat. And in that lift, it's like you wanted to see good control out of the top. But then at the bottom, a little bit more let go, a little speed out of the bottom might have helped her just a touch to stand through that sticking point. 325 for Sung Young Choi. And she won't be able to get it. So she's there at 310.
And Alex, I'm looking around, not to get ahead of ourselves, but I see a 3.55 on the bar for Jen Muir. There we go. 3.05 for Kristina Livididakis.
She really saw that all the way through, though. She wasn't going to let go of that bar prematurely. She was like, nah, I'm going to make it bury me before I even bail on it. 300 on the bar for DeRoy. She missed 290 to start.
Got to seventy five. There you go. And three hundred is good. So two ninety must have just been like a lapse in timing or something like that, because that looked pretty good at these loads in this weight and how they feel. Just the little thing out of balance can mean that bar is coming down. Oh yeah. I use a big like hip reflex out of the bottom. And if I don't time that bounce right, it feels like 30 extra pounds on that bar. Oh, so close.
320 will still be good for Mikulishin. That's the second heaviest we've seen. Quintero, she's got 300 on the bar. 290, 295. Stay with 295. And that right there is the beauty of those straps and these racks that we're using right now. And here it is, 355. Let's go, Jen. She's got it. Her last one was so good. The rookie from Scotland.
Trying to add 10 pounds. And Jen Muir making Alex Kazan look like one hell of an analyst right now. Give me Muir. I actually feel guilty. I kind of forgot that she was so strong when I was thinking of who's going to hit 350. And yeah, that's so awesome. So maybe we'll see a few.
That was really good. My first interaction with Jen was at Fit Fest, and she beat me in a clean cycling ladder. And I was like, who is this girl? Wait a second. I'm sure we said girl, too. Your replay is presented by Rogue Fitness.
And while Prevo had a very strong lift right out the gate at 315, I believe this was her second attempt. The timing was there. The bracing was there. She had solid speed out of the bottom, but it was the fight to the middle that allowed her to stand that weight all the way up. And yeah, we're talking three wheels with 315 pounds. And then Mikulishin at 320 pounds. Great setup here.
Mid-bar position for her on her back, patient enough to get her hips through the middle as well in order to help her stand that one up for a successful lift. And that'll be good enough for second place. But it was Jen Muir with 355 pounds, power lifter, low-bar back squat style in the flats. She said, give me, give me, Muir. I think I left a little bit of more in the tank.
What a great lift there and a great way to finish Event 5 for Jen Muir. Jen Muir set the bar at 355 pounds. Sydney McAleishan with 320 and Prevost at 315. Alex, stick around for one more. What do you say? Yeah, I'll stick around for both. All right, Alex will be here. We'll be right back for heat number two for the individual women.
One heat down, two heats to go for individual action for the women. In event number five, this is the 2025 CrossFit Games. I'm Chase Ingram. Alongside with me is Adrienne Conway and Alex Kazan. In the booth with us is Mike Arsenault. He's waiting on the floor.
We have our next 10 athletes ready to tackle the one rep max back squat presented by Lou Jean June It is a simple one they get 20 seconds at each one three rounds through You're laying assignments for heat number two your middle ten for the weekend. You have 30 athletes competing
Does anyone have what it takes to hit 355? Annika Greer is competing for the first time in a long time, and it's been a long time coming. She's, let's hear more about her with Mike Garcino. Thanks, Chase. Yes, this is Annika's fifth attempt at qualifying for the CrossFit Games and the first time that she has qualified after a couple of near misses. She said, of course, she's happy that she's here, but this is not the culmination
of her story. To her this is just the beginning so she enjoyed for a couple days the achievement of making the games but she wants to make some noise on the leaderboard and she can start by potentially working her way into the final heat. In terms of expectations for this event she said 345 will be her second attempt and then she will adjust as necessary from there with seeing what the weights that were put up in heat number one that could make her very competitive in event number five.
Thank you, Mike. Well, 355 is the number she should be looking at. Claudia Gluck, who's sitting in lane number two, is sitting 12th overall.
Luck making her back to back appearance here at the CrossFit Games. Yes, and in 12th, that's where she finished last year. And of course, with a listed back squad at 331, she's one of those athletes that we'll be watching. Will she farly surpass that? Will the fatigue get the best of her? We'll see what she's able to do in this event. In that center lane, in lane number six, you do have the 10-time Games veteran, Brooke Wells.
15th after four events, and Alex seeing Brooke out here. She's been here so long. Back in action again one more time, knowing it's the last time. Yeah. I'm sure her feet, like, I hope she just gets to soak it up. And being removed, you kind of just realize how special the floor really is. And I can't imagine, like, knowing it's your last time. I'm sure she's feeling all the emotions. How do you manage those emotions on the competition floor?
Oh, I've never retired before, Chase. I don't know. But you've had emotions on the competition floor. Yeah, I mean, I feel like I'm pretty good at just moving through, whether it's good or bad. Usually you have to address those after. Maddie Kanye will kick things off, opening up with 285 pounds.
Talking about managing emotions, how about managing forest fires? Hattie Kanyo. Being squatting in front of a crowd of a couple thousand is no big deal when you're staring a blazing fire in the face as a career. Yes, intensity is always relative, Chase, and that is true, even with life circumstances. Maxine Neely saddling up to 295 for her first attempt.
You talk about speed in and out of the bottom. Now, what I'm looking for for Neely is that I'd like to see just a little bit more control in that initial descend so that she can use that stretch reflex in the bottom with control. Otherwise, if the weight goes up, that could lead to a little volatility there for her. Abby Dommett. Sitting in 18th. She's good at 305, so first 300 on the board. Dommett had a bit of a blend there. She got on the only shoes, but she's still using that low bar approach.
Monica Greer opening at 325. OK. OK. Sounds like that 345, and then the jump's probably going to be a little big. Lucy McGonigal, and with the speed of that last lift, you wonder if she even goes more than what she planned on for her second lift. 285 for Lucy, youngest athlete in the field this year at the CrossFit Games. So impressive.
And she's so nice to boot. Brooke Wells 310 on the bar. 310 is good for Brooke.
V. Sagafi, 300 pounds. Sagafi won event three last night with the pegboard and squat clean complex. She's been working on her strength. That was her biggest weakness for a long time that kept her out of the games, and it's what helped get her here.
260 for Alexis Raptus. 260 is good. Easy work there for Alexis. Claudia Gluck opening up at 315. Really no more for her gymnastic prowess. Gluck can squat.
Yeah, listed max at 331. Again, if she's open at 315, this looks good. Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah. That's an old max. That 331 is an old max. That did not look like a max. 295 for Gracie Walton. 295 is good. One round down. OK. Three total rounds here for the winner at max back squat as we work our way back to Hatticano.
Kanyo going for 300. Had a successful first attempt at 285. Great intentionality there by Hattie. I mean, she did a great job at controlling the descend, using that stretch reflex at the bottom. She got some good speed there and stayed with it through the middle. Speaking of speed, Lexi kneeling. 295 looked pretty light. Let's see what she does at 310.
Yeah, that was that quick descent, like you said, Adrian. I think that's kind of where you lose that stretch reflex. Yeah, it's hard. It's a hard balance, right? Because especially with adrenaline and everything in the heat of the moment, it's like you've got to have just the right amount of control before you use that speed. Doming, going for 320. Wow, and then you talk about control. That's it. Control a little lower on the next one. That was close.
You're right. And that is what we're looking for. The judge of standards is going to be hip crease, got to go below. 345, she called it. Now where she's going to go? The most we've seen, 355 by Jen Muir. Yeah, do you think she's going to take a bigger jump to hopefully beat it? Or play it like the same? I put your coaching hat on. You just saw that lift.
I mean, I feel like for myself, when you get to a certain understanding and level of the sport, you're just trying to get the points. So sometimes you got to put your ego on the door and make sure you hit numbers that matter. But depending if you have the room to play, it might be worth it for her to go. You also have to keep in mind there's not going to be a ton of girls that hit 345. So she's already given herself a really good cushion. Cool. Oh!
Greer's already moved herself in a second overall. 3.55 is the weight to beat as Fi Sagafi sets up for 3.15. Oh, that was good. What a fight from Fi. That's what a one-rep max looks like. That was her max. Raptis setting up the 280.
Rappist will get it. If you look behind her, it looks like 3.55 is on the bar for Annika's last attempt, as Gluck gets set for her second attempt at 3.35. So this is now surpassing that listed max, at least that we've got as a reference.
It's wild how quickly it changes right like that first lift looks so light 305 for one
Oh, that looked really easy. That looked almost easier than the first one. That did. How often does that happen? You're warming up. You're in the corrals. It's maybe 15 minutes before you touch a barbell. Oh, yeah. And you come out here. Does Trudy say that second attempt feel better than the first, even though it's heavier? Oh, yeah. I would agree 1 million percent, especially in a lift where, like, you have to go eccentric and up. Like, that first one always feels kind of terrible. Canyon will stick with 300.
Neely goes for 305, missed her last attempt. At 310. All right, we'll slow it down just a little. Oh, nice. Good lift. 305 is good for Lexi Neely. It's 330.
Dummy got the hops before. Yeah, she knows. She's trying to call on all the energy and power that she can to make this lift. It's a long time under tension here for Heavy. Good fight. She's got to be pretty pleased with that last lift. I thought that involved a lot of muscle. Here we go.
look she's upset literally she's like dang it I should have went 365 yes for all of us yeah easy to say in the booth though 355 is good for Greer
That'll still be good tied. Is there a tiebreak for this event? So the tiebreak, and that's what's important, is that the tiebreak is your previous lift that you hit. So if Muir had done 350 and hit 355, that would break the tie at 345. Then you go back to the first lift.
Here we got Brooke. She's got 330 on the bar. 330 for Brooke Wells. It's good. And we haven't seen many smiles from Brooke this weekend yet, but we finally got one. Soak it in, Ms. Wells. B. Sagafi. Two times plus body weight. Yeah, that would be an interesting stat to have their pound for pound percentages, like, at the end.
315 is still good for her. Raftis going for 290. Raftis won't get it. 325 on the bar for Glutz. So dropped a little bit to hopefully get just a little bit more than her first lift.
That's good for Gluck. It's the fourth heaviest lift we've had so far after one heat. As Gracie Walton goes for 315. And she gets it.
You talk about that unique sticking point. We almost saw one there. That was about to be pretty high. She got out of the hole quite a bit before that bar started to slow. I love the post-PR smiles, too, when people just get so excited. So Greer will hit .355, which matches Muir. But Muir, it appears, has the tiebreaker. What was her first attempt? Going in.
It was Brooke Wells with 330 pounds. Now, she's got a best lift listed at 345. But this is her 10th year at the CrossFit Games to be hitting these submaximal loads after a 6K run, or six miles of running and everything else. Extremely impressive. And then it was Anika Greer who gave us not even the closest thing to a smile, only a growl after an easy 355. She's simply looking at that weight saying, I should have bested you by another 10 pounds at least. Anika Greer.
We'll take the heat for heat number two, Brooke Wells, second at 330. We have one more heat to go. Alex, thank you so much. Please heal up. We want to see you back here at the CrossFit Games next year. Thank you for joining us. Absolutely. Thank you. One more heat remains.
yeah yeah
The 2025 CrossFit Games have descended upon Albany, New York. We are inside MVP Arena. As you're getting set for the final heat for individual event number five for the women, I'm Chase Ingram. Along with me is Adrienne Conway. Mike Arsenault will join us shortly from the floor. One rep max.
Don't weaken moment of the day, and what a moment it was. We haven't seen anything like this in a very long time. Tia Claire Toomey was holding on to the leader jersey, but Lucy Campbell, who has a knack for taking down champs, in the final 150 feet, Lucy Campbell, who was tied for second in points,
Back for the first time since 2022, gets an event win. And for the first time in her career, will be donning the leader jersey over Tia Claire Toomey, just two points back. Lydia Fish still holding on that third place spot. Event number five, one rep max back squat presented by Lu Zhangjun.
Adrian, what is your tempo recipe for success? We've watched this play out a few times. They need to know their squat chase. They're either going to use a high bar back squat, high on their traps, or a low bar back squat, where they get that bar as low as they can on their back and really lean forward. But they've got to start sharp. We've seen athletes miss that opening attempt, and it's done nothing but hurt their momentum for lifts two and three. I mean, leaning into it, Lydia Fish, who's sitting in third overall, wearing the fish head.
You're laying assignments for this third and final heat after four events. So we'll go from 10th to first in order. And we'll kick things off.
with Miriam von Rohr in lane number one. More on her, let's go down to Mike Arsenault. Well, Chase, Miriam's one of the strongest athletes in the field and also the most secretive. Once this event was announced, she went out of her CrossFit Games profile and deleted all of her numbers to keep her
numbers secret from the rest of the field and even in the warm-up area asked her and her coach what are her goal weights for this they looked around brought out a sheet of paper with all different permutations of what she might attain and I asked well what would a PR be and I was just told around 365 however I did notice a 385 on that sheet as well so we'll see if a hundred points are in her future. Olivia Kerstetter back for the second time no stranger to heavy lifts at the CrossFit Games.
Van Roer back-to-back CrossFit open worldwide winner. Setting up with 325 to kick things off. Okay. All right. Almost an akin execution to what we saw from Mr. Mertens on the men's side. Very vertical torso, pretty narrow stance. Clean and strong to start. Haley Adams, 260 on a bar.
Haley currently sitting in ninth overall. We'll get her opening lift. You said it before, it's that opening round, just knocking the pre-cobwebs off, even after sitting in the corrals for a bit, as Kerstetter has 310 on the bar. Yeah, that's part of the gamification of coming to the CrossFit Games, is that you've got to learn strategy that's appropriate to prime you for these max lifts, because you've been standing around for 15 to 20 minutes prior to taking the floor after your warm-up.
300, opening lift for Maddie Sterk. Wow, Sterk sitting in seventh, two points behind sixth, three points back of fifth, five points out of fourth. It is getting very tight on the leaderboard as Danielle Brandon has 265 for her opening lift.
Uh-oh. And that's a tough position to be in. We talked about starting fast. That's where it's better to start too light than too heavy in these situations. Amy Kringle going for 275. Gets hit for Ariel Lohan. Ariel Lohan, as she normally does, sitting in fourth overall.
and who notoriously does not max out in her training. However, she says she saves it for the competition floor. And there's a unique mindset that is able to be garnered from Ariel. She has like this lightheartedness to her. Now she's out for blood, don't get it wrong. She comes to win, but she just rolls with the punches so well that it's not a surprise to see her optimize her potential at the CrossFit Games. Lydia Fish, third overall, 265, looks very good for Lydia.
Biggest knock on her coming in is the strength, as you see the fish head fans with her family, huge family. Three brothers, one sister. Tia Claire Toomey. We have not seen someone take the leader jersey from her in competition since the second event of the 2019 CrossFit Games. Lucy Campbell.
Donning the red and the white for the first time in her career. Opening up at 285. 285 is good for Campbell. Looks great. Good clean opening lift right there. That's how you build confidence. Round one is done as we move to round number four. 340 on the bar. Yep. For Miriam Von Rohr. Her 325 is already good for fifth in the event.
Yep, yep. She's priming herself, Chase. That was a great number for her to say, OK, this is where I'm going to pivot, or I need to go this way or that way. Now she's eyeing, what's the best score right now on the leaderboard? I'm going to get that. So she had 325. We know the best is 355. Yep. 325 to 340 is a 15-pound jump. That means she's going to have to jump another 20 if she wants to win. But maybe that's not what she's going for. Haley, unable to get 270.
There's something to be said with the way these athletes execute. I'd like to see Haley keep her head a little bit more neutral from a coaching perspective to help her stay stable through her midline as she stands through the weight. Her setter will get 325. 340 for Von Rohr is good for a third. We have a tie in weight at 355. In your top two spots is Sturt. Sets up for 315. Now 300 was easy for Maddie.
Pretty smooth there at 315. Daniel Brandon opened at 265 and missed it. He's now dropped down to 255. That is good for Daniel Brandon. OK, so now she's got some weight on the board. Now she's in a bit of a pickle. This is a harder choice to make now because of that opening missed lift.
Gringle got 275 in her first attempt, now going for 290. 290 is good. This event's sponsored by Luzhanjun Lifters.
$3,000 on the line for a win. $500 if you wear the lifters. Is there a low end? You got it. Gets $290. It's like if you didn't know better, every lift for her is a max effort, like just awesome. She's so happy every time. Lydia Fish hit $265 nicely as she moves up to $280. Very impressive. Lydia, hey, girl, get some confidence. You look good out there.
One more lift for Lydia. She tries to hold on to that third place position. Tia Claire Toomey also going for 325. Toomey just two points away from getting that leader jersey back. Chase, we know she's focused a lot on endurance. She probably wouldn't admit that this is naturally a peak lift for her right now. So she's banking on reserves, to be quite honest. 325 is good.
And that has Toomey tied for six as Campbell sets up for 295. Yep. 295 is good for Campbell. She looks at her judge like, well, we got it. Final round. Here it is. 360. 355. We've seen twice.
360, you only got to do once. Mirvan Rohr should take the events. 265 for Haley. Got it. 265 is good.
Kerstetter going for 335.
She tells everyone, I'm good. I'm good. With the listed max at 320, that would have been well above Olivia's listed previous max. We know that's not something that she's necessarily focused on developing. But wow, that would have been impressive. 325 for Maddie Sturt. This is big for her, and she gets it. A couple 325s on the board, and that puts her in a tie for sixth.
265, this is what Daniel Brannan missed on her opening attempt. Night and day from lift one to lift three. Amy Kringle rocking the Liu Zhang shoes. If you're looking for a serious upgrade in your lifts, save 15% on the Liu Zhang shoes. Scan the QR code now.
We'll head to liujianju.com and grab you a pair. And that pair of shoes paid off for Kringle. That's right. And she's got $300 in the bag and $500 for wearing the shoes. And she looked surprised that it went down. So $300 is a solid number for Amy Kringle. $295 for Ariel Lohan, who's sitting in fourth.
Really close, almost had it, started to shift a little to her right, decided to let it go. Probably a wise choice. Fish hit 280. She's got 290 on the bar. That would tie her with Lohan, who's trying to chase her down for third place solely. And she's not able to get it. So 280 for Lydia Fish. Tia Claire Toomey for 335.
And she'll get her into fourth if she can hit it. This is a big squat for Tia. This is going to tie a previous best in 2020 if she hits it. And she does. 335, looking very good for Tia Clare. As Lucy Campbell setting up for 305. Tia looking over.
305. Wow. Miriam von Rohr. We're wondering if we're going to see it. And we got what we came for, 360. We'll take the event.
Let's take a look at your highlights presented by Rogue. Hey, we had some impressive lifts all around. Olivia Kerstetter, one of the younger athletes in the field with a listed max of 320. She smoked 325. We also had Maddie Sturt, who made an amazing three lift performance. She was sharp early, but then she was able to come through all the way here to 325 at the end. And it looked like she was close to that threshold, but there still might have been another five pounds in the tank.
Tia matching a 2020 CrossFit Games performance here at 335 pounds. All the more impressive when we know that most of this year was spent focused on endurance and running, and she's still able to rise to the occasion here at the CrossFit Games. She wants that white and red jersey back. And then Miram Von Rohr, welcome to the CrossFit Games. The two-time Open champion has now made it to compete in person, and she's putting on a show with 360 pounds on a back squat. So impressive.
Your Event 5 results, Mirim Van Roer sits on top at 360 pounds, followed by Annika Greer and Jen Muir. And as you said, your two-time Open champ, now the champ of Event 5, she's down with Mike Arsenault.
Okay, Miriam, we talked before this event. You wouldn't tell me what your PR was in the back squat. You deleted your profile before this event to keep your stats a secret to the rest of the competitors. You hit 360. What is your PR in the back squat? My PR is 165 kilogram. I don't know this exactly in pounds. It's maybe around 360, 365 pounds.
My math is correct, it's right around 365 pounds. You're a two-time Open winner. This is your first time at the CrossFit Games. You just won an event, 100 points, competing in front of thousands of fans. What is this experience like for you? Yes, it's a very different experience. I was never in a so big competition, and it's a very great feeling. Well, congratulations, great performance, and we'll see you later today. Thank you.
Congratulations to Miriam von Rohr, gets her very first event win at her very first CrossFit Games. That'll do it for individual event five. Don't go anywhere. The teams are next, and the individuals will finish the night off. Individual event number nine is eight, five is done. For agent Conway and Mike Carson, I'm Chase Ingram. Teams coming up next.
you
Music Music
just fine.
It's the 20, 25 CrossFit games from MVP arena here in Albany, New York, the home of this Sienna saints. And our coverage today brought to us by Valitas. We are really tests and we are made not born. Bethany Flores has been to the CrossFit games seven times. Bella Martin down on the floor, Joel go debt. Glad to have you along with us for team event. Number six, the one rep max backs to squat.
After five events, Butcher's Lab, a group of three-team CrossFit Games rookies, is in first place by 10 over the veteran CrossFit Oslo crew. And then Campbell City, who came into the day wearing the leader's jersey, taking a 30-point tumble from a 15-point lead to a 15-point deficit.
or one rep max back squat. That's it. That's the event description brought to us by Lu Xiaojun. Yeah, it's pretty simple. You have five minutes for the women, five minutes for the men, all in a day. As many reps as you can get to get a max in that five minute window. Let's go down to Bellarmore.
Let's talk about balance of tests here today. We saw the team communication earlier this morning. Now we have whatever these team individuals want to do on their own. And the best part is, it's a direct comparison to what the individuals are doing. Not often do we see two tests in a games weekend, where the team athletes can compare what the individuals did and see kind of how they stack up. Something that's even more fun for this one, if the teams are wearing the luge out jeans, they can walk away with $500.
just for wearing the shoes for one single lift. Tell you what, that's pretty worth it, and that's why I'm wearing them. Bella Martin does have them on. We're trying to get her the $500. She's just got to get a back squat in.
We've got 10 teams in this opening heat. CrossFit Prostanda in lane five, the Swedish super team. CrossFit 1124 has had a couple of good events back to back. They will be our last lifters in this group in lane 10. But our Vision Fuels victory athletes to watch come from Camp Rhino CrossFit in lane six.
Interesting team, made up of athletes born in four different countries, including Nikita Yandov, who has the bunned blonde hair in the back. He's an individual semi-finalist from when he lived back in Europe. Went team when he moved to the US a couple of years ago from Belarus. That's a country that borders both Ukraine and Russia. Obviously a lot of geopolitical implications there. It was a very difficult transition for him, a lot of sleepless nights. He's very close with 2019 Ukrainian CrossFit Games
well, Ukrainian champion and CrossFit Games competitor Oleksandr Shularenko. He's currently serving in the war, and he said, I feel kind of silly sometimes doing CrossFit when he's out there in tanks. They still communicate. They still text. He has Oleksandr's full support from halfway across the globe.
Here we go for a one rep next back squat. Rebecca Divine is going to open at 365. If she hits this, it is the single best lift, and it's the easiest darn thing you've seen from a female competitor today. That was way too simple. She went up and down way too fast. That means that weight is too light, way too light for her. That just won the women's individual. She's got to switch over now. What did we just do for the last hour?
265. Up and easy there for four friends. And 11.24 is meat nugget Jessica Androsik. Successful giving way to Sydney. The slender tender. Now one of the other strongest women in CrossFit. That's the former Christine Middleton, Christine Zanosko. Good at 305. She holds the clean and jerk record in CrossFit competition.
All right, what's key to a one-rep max back squat? I know it's not the Bethany Flores specialty, but what are you doing? It definitely is not. This would not be a good one for me. I think do a weight that you know that you can do, no matter what. Do a weight that you think you can do. And then if you have time, do a weight that you hope you can do.
they should be able to get at least three attempts in, I would say. I know the demo team on the guy's side, they got like four or five attempts, but they were moving. So it's just gonna depend on the athletes. Some of them can lift the same weights, and so that makes it easier when you're transitioning to the next weight, but it kind of just depends on.
how even you are with your partner on that. Your score is your total. The total is the total on the left side. And then the attempt is on the right. 11-24, Jessica Androsik for 325. Now looking pretty good up there. She got a little sticky. That means that it's starting to become a little bit heavier for her, but still got it off pretty easily. What gets you through the sticking point? A little hope.
No, you have enough temps in practice that you know what you can do and what you can push through, but having a lot of lower body. 385. That's scary. Rebecca Divine. That's scary. 20 pound jump. And do you see how easy that was? She's told us. 400 plus? Her goal was 410.
She's going to get a crack at it here with still half the time remaining. There's athletes doing 260, and I'm pretty sure she made that look a lot easier than someone's 260. Bethany, how do you game plan this? Do you take bigger jumps early, or do you take bigger jumps late?
I would do bigger jumps at the beginning because you're doing something that you know that you can do right at the beginning and then something that you think you can do and that's the time to take a bigger jump. A lot of discussions still going on on the floor and one of the things to think about
I mean, that's body blueprint, that's a team from New York. But I was gonna say, one of the things to think about is what weight is on the bar. And we were talking to Butcher's Lab beforehand, and Drosik is good at 335, because they work out lifting kilos. But Pernila Christensen said, listen, sometimes it's easier when you can't do the math and you don't know what's on the bar, just go lift. Yeah, she also said that she writes it down on her arm with the colors, which is not a bad idea. Two reds, one yellow, three blues, let's go.
That's what the Americans do when we go over to Europe. This is Jordan Adcock, and there's confusion right now. There's some yelling going on down there. You can just hear Adcock yelling, what's on the bar? We've got a minute left to go, and that's costly. 335 for Adcock. Oh, excuse me, for Torresllana.
You can see that her knee came in just a little bit on that left side. That just means that probably one left glute is a little bit weaker than her right. How about Rebecca Devine just taking a seat in the back? Good for her. Sometimes that's good. Like a lot of lifters, good lifters, they will sit between each rep just to get as much rest as possible throughout their body. Devine is going to go for 400. She has to get the bar off the rack before five minutes.
After that, she's good to go. Prostanda. Nice lift. Good. Now, here goes Divine for 400 pounds. See how easy she makes this look. Oh, and she got stuck.
But still the single best female total by Rebecca Divine. Christine Best with 350. That was actually a really good lift as well. And we are now in the second five minutes. There is no reset. So this time is ticking, and the guys for undivided will immediately put two reds on. CrossFit 4 is on the left there, Griffin Raleigh. He's going to, we would think, put up some big numbers. We also know his back bugged him a little bit yesterday.
Interesting note too, the guys have to lift from where the girls were on the J-hooks, which makes it a little bit harder. They're having to squat underneath that bar to even get it off the rack, which that's not fun for them, especially when it gets to PRs and heavy, heavy lifts. Scores are at the top of your screen. They're going to be a little bit off until everybody gets one lift in the books. But for now, CrossFit Body Blueprint. Now Q21 back up front at 1460.
Crosby Henderson and Hendersonville had an interesting way of squatting. He was actually looking straight down when he was squatting. Wouldn't recommend that. Joe Piero, good with the reds on the outside. Yeah, those are a better way of squatting, just having your eyes look straight forward. And you'll actually see some people have their eyes looking up or their head popping up, too, when he gets heavier. Easy money for Alexander Alebro.
Really good 365 attempt as well from Wes Peters out of Hendersonville. And now here is Thor at 495. 571 for Colton Mertens on the individual side earlier. Wide squatter. Wide squatter. Probably just feels more comfortable on the hips and the legs. Rapp with 475. For Camp Rhino. Deceptively strong. He's very strong. Yeah.
Don't let him fool you with the size. He is super strong. 4.55 by Mike Needleman. And Undivided is looking to put up some big numbers, trying to recover, because that total on the left is low between Christine Best and Christine Zanosko. So unless that number has not been updated. They have a 4.95 going on. No, they're now at 16.50. So that counter just is off. Undivided's in the lead.
Four is getting ready to go at 525 as a Lebro is good Josh Hong for 495 one of the fittest Koreans on earth And Yeah, Raleigh hit
So Undivided's now at 16.80. If you're putting up a team total that is higher than the year the New World was discovered, you're having a great day. Yeah, having a really good day. Gotta take your wins.
athletes, coaches, and gym owners, this is your app. Download Hustle Up free, and create your profile today at hustleup-app.com. Tyler, Riley Good, rather, from 1124, gonna push them over 1600, if he can hit 490. Griffin Riley is about to go again.
a former football player at Valdosta State. He was always on the bigger side. One of his gym members said, you look like Thor. 5'40"? He lifts like Thor. Oh my gosh. 5'40", looks like 2'20".
Can we just talk about how easy that looked? He's got another minute, and we just got a fail at a Joe Piero. We're going to see if Griffin Raleigh is going to get another lift in. And now it's going to be a real fast re-rack for Body Blueprint and Piero. That fail was a little scary. Going forward is usually not the way they should fail, so to see that could lead into some scary injuries. We need to be careful with that. Hung, going to go for better than 520. Raleigh.
540 was the last attempt, we'll see what he goes for now. 20 seconds left, you gotta milk all this rest. Hong, 505 on the right. 565 for Griffin Raleigh, this will put him second overall.
individuals and teams and it is absolutely fantastic. Griffin Raleigh at 565. Ain't No Doubt came to play and Undivided has a phenomenal showing.
which that's what they said. They said that to us yesterday. They said this was gonna be a good event for them. And Griffin Raleigh just said, should've gone up. Should've done more. Five minutes isn't a lot of time. But you know what? I would rather feel like I could've done more. Yeah. Than miss the one. Correct. You wanna end on a good note, so that's gonna make him feel really good going into day three. 17.35.
Well, here we are with some crazy numbers with the ladies with Rebecca divine. She hit. So much weight compared to some of the ladies on the floor and just making it look so easy. 385 what in the world? She's pretty happy about that and then we had Griffin on the other side like CrossFit undivided 565 like come on. How easy is that?
And he was pretty happy about that. And even saying, I hope that I do more. They win the heat by more than 100 pounds. No big deal. 16.15 out of 11.24, who's coming on strong. They may work their way into the second heat to start the final day off tomorrow. And then 16.05 for Body Blueprint on Bryce Broome's 30th birthday. Training Think Tank puts up 15.90.
We've got one more heat coming up for the teams on Saturday.
final event, final heat for the teams here at the 2025 CrossFit Games on moving day. MVP arena, downtown Albany, New York. Today we are sponsored by Velites. We are Velites. We are made, not born. Alongside Bethany Flores, a seven-times CrossFit Games athlete, Bella Martin is down on the floor. My name is Joel Gaudette.
For the first time in competition, Butcher's Lab is your leader. 10 point advantage over CrossFit Oslo. We see a 30 point swing with Camel City CrossFit. They went from up 15 to down 15 after event five this morning.
All right, event description. This is the easiest event description. I mean, back squat. The women are going to get five minutes, and they're going to transition straight into the men, and they get another five minutes. It's going to go fast. Brought to us by Lu Xiaoju. As we take a look at our recipe for success, that is delivered to us by Tempo Meals.
First one is know, think, hope. Do something you know you can do, something you think you can do, and then go for something that you hope you can do. And the second one is moment to excel. The people on day one got their running fun, and now it's time for those heavy lifters to shine. So let's see them do some heavy lifts. Let's go. Our 10th place team will lift first in lane one. Our first place team will lift last in lane 10.
So our standings in reverse on your screen for your lane assignments with Butcher's Lab wearing those white leaders jerseys. Let's go down to Bella, who is wearing her Lu Xiaojun's.
Chatted with Griffin Raleigh just briefly. He said if he had more time, he would have gone for 600. So that 565, still impressive, but he had more left in the tank. But he's not the only guy that's going to hit in that mid 500 range. In this heat, I'm looking at that Franco's Imamco team with Jordan and Josh Mattis. Both of those guys can hit over 500.
Jordan's PR is around 505, and you've got Josh at 555. So if they have a good day, maybe a couple PRs in there for our men's side of the field. But for the women, all eyes on Dani Spiegel, her first year on team. Her PR for back squat, 370. She'll give Rebecca Divine a run for her money, maybe have the heaviest squat of the day for all the females. We'll see in just a couple of seconds, Joel.
Well, thank you. The vision fuels victory. Athletes to watch with CrossFit Franco's and CrossFit Invictus. But Butcher's Lab right now wearing the white leaders jersey. And the question is, how much damage control can you do? Pernila Christensen told us earlier, this is not a strength event for them, although she did PR her back squat three days ago. Yeah. 319 was it? So we'll see that she I mean, she's starting at 315. We'll see what she can do.
And we are underway. Five minutes to lift for all of these competitors. Females first, then five minutes for the men. And Pernila Christensen, good at 315. She basically hit her PR, and that looked super smooth, meaning she's got a lot more in the tank. 319, by the way, is the ultimate kilo conversion PR. Here comes Dani Spiegel.
Sean Early on the left, Phil Muscarello on the right, being good weight loaders here for their teammate. Spiegel opening at 315. And I like how Annie, she set the bar before she went down. That's how you know that she's a confident lifter, she's ready to go, and she knows that she's going to be able to hit that weight.
When you see people rush out of the bar and go straight down, they're just hoping that they can get that weight and they're not setting themselves up for success. Divine hit 385, so that is the biggest number that the women in this heat are chasing. No one has yet gone over 300 with the exception of Spiegel and Christensen.
Vanila Christensen now going for 325. And she breaks through the sticking point for Butcher's Lab off screen, as the 280 will go on up and good for Ava George at a proven. And her max is 300, so 280 is going to be a little bit tough for her. You saw it was a little sticky, but she still was able to get it up. And her partner is going to hit the same weight. That means that they're probably around the same one rep max. And we'll see how she does in the fifth.
Same thing, looks pretty good, maybe a little sticky, meaning they're getting closer to that one right now. So there's- There's Carson Wolfe, good from Proven, and Emily Rathwell, good from Invictus. CrossFit Oslo, Ura Lundqvam.
And she is through that sticking point. That was sticky. That was sticky. That means that she's getting closer to that one rep max of hers. You could tell that she's looking down, so maybe a good idea to look forward or up as she's squatting up. 335 by Spiegel. Let's watch Dani as she gets the bar out of the rack. Do you see how she sets herself up for success? Takes a nice deep breath.
Nice. That means that she is confident about what she's lifting. Christensen gonna go for 330. Hey, we're gonna get a little PR over here. Butcher's lap. And Peniela Christensen is having a great first five minutes here of the one rep max back squat. I think she lied to us this morning. There's no way that her one rep max was 390.
It's in the math. It's all the conversions. 295 for Hannah Hardy. 325. 325. Yeah. Audrey Ann Perry Dupuy. The beautification of putting the bar back doesn't discount. It was a great lift. She's happy with that. This is a great start for Butcher's Lab.
A 300 lift, and you might even get two 300 lifts. This is set for 295 for Agerbach. And they were worried that this was not gonna be a strong event. Zoe Jones fails for mayhem. Okay, Butcher's Lab going for 295. Let's see if she can hit this lift.
So she's going really, really slow on the way down. That's telling me that that's a really heavy lift and she's not as confident as she's going up. Now you've got an Olympic hopeful. Really good clean and jerk, really good snatch here for Anne-Sophie Taschereau.
Yeah, she can stand up heavyweight. Yeah, 335. Looking good. Knees were starting to cave in just a little bit. That means that starting to get heavier, the glutes are probably a little bit weaker. So something to work on. Now Spiegel trying to pick out her weight. 335 is where she's at. She's going to jump to 350. I like that the guys are helping out. That's so much easier for the girls. They don't have to worry about that part.
She's got to get this off the rack in the next 10 seconds. She won't pass Rebecca Divine, but 350 you will take all day. Spiegel. 350, yes. Does her job for Invictus. And we are now on to the male five minutes. And Phil Mascarella is going to say 350. I'll lift that. Yeah. No, I think they're just switching out the J hooks. Yeah. And that's the thing.
I mean, he may as well squatter while he's here. Put the 350 on the board. Yeah. Sandinista cracks 400. Blueprint just put up a pair of 445s between Harry and OJ Keene.
And DeChico goes to 4.05. You see how the back of his shirt is all chalked up. That's just going to help with keeping that bar in place as they're squatting down and not slipping off. Total Moroccan you just made quick work of 425 off screen for Oslo. You're looking at a couple of 445 attempts. Butcher slag hitting 445 as well.
That is Tomas Stroyer. If you're looking for a serious upgrade in your lifts, you can save 15% on Lu Xiaojun shoes. Scan the QR code on your screen now or head to luxiaojun.com, it's spelled on your screen, .com, and grab your pair today. Lu Xiaojun, three-time Olympic champion, one of the greatest weightlifters of all time. Transitive property.
475 is the best hit so far. That's from Franco's that we talked about with Bella earlier. And we'll go down to Bella now.
He knows how to lift really heavy, at least once. And two, he's very familiar with a heavy back squat. So if you'll watch him as he attempts this next lift, he's going to get that bar really low on his back. And he's going to hinge over just a little bit more in that wider squat. You can see over in lane seven as well. Sam Demeester is doing the exact same thing. It really helps if you're trying to get a little bit more leverage.
In lane six, right side of your screen, 500 pounds here for Josh Mattis. Long levers! Big power! Yeah, some long levers. That's why he's squatting so wide on the platform. Three-time CrossFit Games veteran, and they're just trading him out. Jordan Kerr is going to go for 500, as DiChico just hit 455 for Mayhem. We'll get a
full pit stop change here for Butcher's Lab after a miss. It's something to think about with these guys. They're having to lift off of the women's J-hooks, which it's like an extra lift for them, which isn't always the most fun when you're trying to hit a PR. Two minutes left.
The weight to beat is 1735. Franco's right now is at 1590. I think undivided is going to hold. 1615 is second. That is within reach. That's only 25 pounds away from where Franco's is currently. As DeMeester hits 475 to up Mayhem's total to 1550. That is in top 10 contention.
Only a five-pound jump here for Mattis, the former football player at Missouri State. He was a short yardage back. It's a short jump up to 5.05. And he has got legs for days. Yes, he does. Muscarello hits 4.35 for Invictus. 4.80 in what looks like it could have been a PR over there for Le Repair.
They're in second place right now. So they're in good standing. Franco's is in first at 1590. Then that repair at 1555. This is big. Jordan Kerr at 515.
Yes, good fight. I love seeing the fight like that. That means that they're confident that they can hit this even though it's a super heavyweight. They're strong enough. They know mentally they're strong enough to handle it. We have a 9,999-pound attempt. That's wild. Let's go. Here is Lara Pair. And that's a good lift.
for Lara Pair at 4.85 at the buzzer. 4.55 in the meantime, just went up after the buzzer, but it will count for Helsinghoff, and that gets Oslo to 15.50. Not unimportant for a team that was just out of first place.
1735 is going to be the event win that goes to undivided. And boy, God, they need that. Team that had podium expectations that has struggled so far for a couple of different reasons, but needing to fight their way out of a deep hole. Let's take a look at our replay that is sponsored by Rook.
Well, here we go, guys. We started with three. Danny Spiegel hit 350 on her one rep back squat and making it look super easy. Smooth down, smooth up, like it was nothing. And I love to see that. I love to see that. And then we went over to CrossFit Franco's team. He had a 515, Joel. Are you kidding me? And he made it look way too easy. As we see him go down and come up with no problem.
I think that whole team behind them was jacked up for that. And they needed that. They needed that win. So it's cool to see CrossFit Franco put that one right there. Jordan Kerr with that big number. That's a third followed by a fourth for CrossFit Franco's. Good day on moving day. They are in the top five. Undivided the win. Body blueprint in second. 11.24 in third. Franco's with Bella Martin.
Jordan, 515, that's a PR. You guys were in fifth going into today. You needed this. What did it take to get that 515 open? It really just took the people in the crowd that came to support us and then the teammates. I've been telling this whole weekend that if it wasn't for them, I wouldn't have made it this far. And so being able to put up a big number for them and the crowd going wild is kind of what fueled it. Tell me a little bit more about your community back home, what gyms you guys have, and the community and family that's here with you today. Yeah.
So I'm from CrossFit 4 and 7 out of Missouri. Josh owns his own gym out of Missouri. Sammy's from Pennsylvania, and Hannah's from Virginia. So kind of a conglomerate of people, or gyms, I guess. But we have the CrossFit Franco's family here from Louisiana, and then members from our gyms back home. And so just them spending the time and the money to come support us is really why we do it. We've got one day left to go. You guys are fighting for a podium spot. What's it going to take to get on top tomorrow?
just believing in each other. Brandon Lickett's our coach, and he's been telling us there's no reason it can't be us. We fight hard every single day in training. And just being there for each other and having fun has kind of been the theme. And just whatever happens, happens. The goal is to make the games. Two of us are rookies. And to be fighting for a podium spot is more than a dream come true. So just standing on that dream and that promise and just knowing that we're here for each other really is why we're doing it.
Guys, talk about another good community story. Congratulations. Thank you. Thank you. We appreciate it. Bella, thank you. Brandon Luckett's gym, by the way, is CrossFit Franco's. That's why they compete under that mantle. Kerr and Pew are the rookies. Hardy and Mattis are the veterans. And they said, hey, sometimes we get overlooked. We've been here a long time on teams. No one's overlooking CrossFit Franco's now. Games.CrossFit.com for all your games information, stats, standings, leaderboards, and more. Individuals are back at it. Stick around.
The 2025 CrossFit Games are brought to you by Rogue. Don't weaken. The official equipment supplier of CrossFit and the CrossFit Games. Belites. We are Belites. We are made, not born. The United States Border Patrol. Be an agent of strength. And Sotva. Smarter luxury sleep.
You can't talk about power output without talking about intensity. Now, intensity is just power output. That's the only thing we care about when it comes to measuring intensity. The more power you produce, the higher your intensity. If it was heart rate, if heart rate was important, if heart rate produced power output, let's say I got a gun out and I point this gun at your head, what happens to your heart rate?
Goes up, are you doing any sort of fitness? Producing any power? No. If I told you that we're going to lock the doors and do Fran at the end of the day, what happens to your heart rate? Goes up. Are you producing any amount of power? Are you doing any sort of fitness? No, exactly, right? If I put you in a sauna, are you going to sweat?
That's not intensity. All we care about is intensity, and high intensity is power output. High intensity means high power output, which is why we use functional movements, because they maximise, or one of the best ways to produce high amounts of power. So intensity is just power output. The next question is then, OK, well, why is intensity so important that it's built into the definition of the programme? Why do we love intensity so much?
Intensity is the independent variable most commonly associated with maximizing the rate of returns on variable adaptations. That simply means that intensity is the best way to get results and to get results quickly. Any
fitness program that is absent of intensity, is also absent of results, and absent of results in a time frame that makes sense to you. You want the results pretty much as quick as possible. Agreed? Now, this isn't max intensity. This is not smashing your head against the wall every day going to the gym. It's not max. It's just high intensity. It's just trying to get as much work done as possible. So intensity is just the way to get results.
and to get results quickly. We love intensity because intensity gives us results. What we need to understand with intensity is that it needs to be relative to an individual's physiological and psychological tolerances. It means that intensity is going to look different for each individual that comes into your CrossFit gym. Let's say, like, take two extremes, right? Take, like, take, like, Tia Claire to me and take my grandmother, right? Should they both be in a CrossFit class?
Yeah, they should, right? Because my grandmother needs just, you know, some functional competence, where Tia Claire Toomey's looking for sort of functional dominance, right? But these movements are natural, they're essential, they're safe. So my grandmother needs to be doing thrusters and pull-ups just as much as Tia does, just the end goals are different, right? Now, let's say they're both in your class, right? Let's say that Tia does Fran in like, what are we saying, like two minutes?
Maybe two and a half now if she's like semi-retired, fair? So two and a half minutes, two minutes for tea, right? My grandmother's Fran is going to look a little bit different, right? She's probably going to have like maybe a PVC pipe with like maybe a med ball or a low box to squat to. She's going to squat down to that box with the PVC pipe. She's going to stand up, she's going to press it overhead.
She can do 21 of those. Her pull-ups may be like a jumping pull-up. It might be a ring row. It might be me sort of offering my arm out as she sits on the box. She holds my arm and stands and pulls her chin up over the bar. She can do 21 of those. She'll do 15, 15, nine, nine. As long as both athletes are working to the sort of limits of their physiological and psychological tolerances, they will both continue to get adaptation from the program for a long period of time.
We want my grandmother to push for intensity because we know that's where the results are. Tia Claire Toomey wants the results to go and compete at the CrossFit Games. My mother wants the results to maximise her fitness to keep her out of the nursing home in her advancing years. With me? So both athletes need intensity and they both need exposure to the programme. It just looks a little bit different. It just simply means that we have to scale the intensity back for the individual. Someone's brand new into your gym,
someone's brand new into your gym, they need to probably be introduced to intensity. Once they have good mechanics, they move well, and they're in the gym consistently, then we can sprinkle in a little bit of intensity as they go. With me? Both need intensity, because they both maximize results. We just need to scale it to the individual in front of us in the gym, based off what they need.
you
do do
do
Thanks for watching!
you.
We are halfway through the 2025 CrossFit Games. As the Games is moved to Albany, New York, in the MVP arena, today's coverage is presented by Belitis. We are Belitis, and we are made not born. Hello, everyone. I'm Chase Ingram. Along with me is Adrienne Conway. Mike Arsenault will join us later on the floor. And the boxes are out, and 200 points
are up for grabs in event 6 and 7 presented by the United States Border Patrol. That's right. This one's throttle up and hammer down. Two separate scores worth 200 points, 35 calories on the ski, 28 chest-to-bars, and 24 burpee box jumpovers. Folks, don't blink. It's going to go fast. And then we transition after a one-minute rest into 35 calories on a C2 bike, 28 bar muscle-ups. That's not a misprint. And 24 burpee box jumpovers to finish.
Adrian, what are your recipes for success here? My goodness, we've got one focus for each score here. You've got to go full send on event number six. No holding back on the ski erg. It's going to be hard to make up time once they leave that erg. And then on the back half, event seven, you've got to pace and brake. And that means you've got to be very collected and also plotful.
with how you break up those bar muscle-ups and pace the bikers. The vests are back, and more on those. Let's go down to Mike Arsenault. That's right, Chase. We had the extra wrinkle with the vest throughout Event 6 and Event 7. The athletes are going to have to decide whether they're going for comfort or performance, because the tighter you had the vest,
the tighter is on the chest. If you have a little bit looser, you can breathe a little bit better, but it'll be bouncing up and down on you when you try and do the burpees. And also on the skier, the skier, very, very familiar implement for all these CrossFit athletes. However, doing it, the vest will be a little bit unfamiliar. So just an extra layer of difficulty for these athletes as they move through event six and seven. Thank you, Mike. You're laying assignments for heat one of three, going back to pizza of 10.
And we talked about athletes that are making their 10th appearance at the CrossFit Games. Jona Koski is one of those three. You have Brooke Wells, who has announced her retirement. Tia Claire Toomey has hinted at that, but we are not sure yet, as we are just halfway through the competition. And your Vision Fuels victory athlete to watch, Jona Koski.
In lane number eight now, Yodokoski, we're talking about a burpee box jump over race to the finish line. That's something in his wheelhouse. That's right. When you're racing over any object and it's a short, sprinty, top-type stimulus, he's going to have an advantage. And he's no stranger to high-level gymnastics. Bill Lahey, who's got springboards for legs, is another athlete to keep your eye on on these burpee box jump overs. 35 cals on the skier.
And this is what we're looking at, Chase. How reckless are you willing to be to get to 35 first? It is going to be extremely difficult for athletes to exchange the lead once we exit these skiers.
Now, to add to the challenge, of course, that vest they're wearing is approximately 22 pounds. It's not often that we find ourselves skiing intervals or skiing for meters in a workout with a weight vest on. And as you're hinging at the hip, that adds a little bit of something to it. Is that extra weight actually aid in a movement like this?
It absolutely does. It increases our load. And as we do that and increase our overall body mass, it's going to help us create that downward action that we're watching these athletes go through on the skier. So while it adds resistance as we stand and extended the hip on the way up, it does help us leverage to pull down. Moritz Fiebig, you can see the calories being counted.
On the bottom left corner of your screen, as we're just past the minute mark, Horst Fiebig is done with 35 cals and onto the rig for 28 chest-to-bar pull-ups. And this is where these athletes are going to have to really be calculated. Do you break? And if you do, it's got to be extremely fast.
Tell you what, counting chest or bar pull-ups has never been easier for the judge, because all you've got to do is listen for it. That's right. And the contact that the judges are looking for right there with that chest plate that's actually on the vest, which is nice. It shortens the distance that we've got to travel just a touch. But of course, that compromises the extra 22 pounds. The number to get to.
It's 63, and now it is a race across the floor, as there are 80 24-inch boxes spanning the length of the floor. Athletes will do three at each one. They have to step down on their first rep, step down on their second rep, and then as long as they clear the box and get over, they can do whatever they want to get to the next box, as Moritz Fiebig is six reps down.
And everyone seems to be moving pretty methodically here through these first few boxes. I mean, there's a lot of urgency. They're quick transitioning. You see Kolski here towards the middle of your screen in the green shirt. He's smooth over the box. We're getting a great look at Fiebig here. He's pivoting as he goes over top of the box. It's one of the most effective and efficient ways to allow yourself to step down and still not lose time. Ronisso Valenkiewicz trying to move up to give Moritz Fiebig a race.
But if you think about a short sprint across the floor, Morse Fiebing is a name that's at the top of your list. You may do well as he's on the left side of your screen. On the right side, you see Isaac Newman in lane seven and Yonakoski in lane eight.
Yeah, and what I like from Isaac right there in the middle of our screen is he's really leading with his chest on his burpees. It means on his second one, we'll see here as he faces the box, he really almost worms down, leading with his chest, not creating a lot of stoppage time for his arms as they slow him down. Final three reps for Moritz. Just past the three-minute mark. The time cap is six. He'll get a minute break after this. So the faster you go, the more rest you're going to get. And Fiebig will take heat one for event number six.
Wow, and look at how tight that was there. It looks like Newman may have edged him out at 318.35. Oh, Isaac Newman. What? Excuse me, sir. 318.35. Leading with that chest on those burpees paid off. Lahey's across. Athletes, once they get across the finish line, they will be able to dump the vest as part two, not part two, event seven, will be unvested.
All right, so now this is it. This is the tough part. But these athletes are really going to have their training and their fitness tested at this point. How well can you bring your heart rate down and calm yourself, find some way to get some reprieve for your upper body, allow the blood and the lactate to pull away from the muscles that are going to be under high strain here in just a few minutes? This is how close it's going to be. We were thinking about this as soon as the event got announced last night.
We were saying seconds matter all weekend long. Tenths of seconds are going to matter tonight. 318.35 for Newman, 318.98 for Feibig, and 319.40 are your top three times. One second separating three spots.
Yeah, and I think what we're going to see is a lot of this to come. Chase athletes watching this in the back saw exactly when Moritz Fiebig was able to get off that skier. And they're going to say, OK, that's the time setter. What can I tolerate in order to be faster than that and still go unbroken on my 28 chest-to-bar pull-ups? And then it was here, I believe, that Moritz had the opportunity to really lay down the hammer there. But it was Isaac Newman leading with his chest and flopping to the ground on the burpees. And the sprint and urgency across that finish line is what got him that heat one win.
right there here in event six. Gotta be aware of your surroundings at all time. And the rookie Isaac Newman qualifying out of the Torium Pro gets a heat win. Now once the time cap is set at six minutes, which we are 30 seconds away from, they'll have a minute transition in between the two before we start event number seven.
Now, this event is called Throttle Up into Hammer Down. And when you shed the vest, that's about all you're supposed to do in event number seven. Yeah. Listen, it doesn't get any easier. Taking the weight off. They might rather add the weight back on and do less bar muscle-ups once they hit the reality of hanging from the rig. One minute reset as Isaac Newman has the time to beat for event six.
We get set for event seven. Now the event will start whether you're on your bike or not.
The same rep scheme applies, but we have two different movements, and we're doing it without the vest. That's right. Now we're going to introduce the Concept 2 stationary bike. They're going to do 35 calories on that C2, and then 28-bar muscle-ups. It's a lot longer to cycle eight 28-bar muscle-ups than it was those chest-to-bars, and that's going to be a deciding factor. They've got to know when to break those up. First time we've seen the C2 bike in competition for the individuals.
And event number seven, Hammer Down, is underway. You gotta hammer the pedals. You gotta hang on to the pull-up bar. And then the race on the burpee box jumpovers will be on, but you're not going to be fresh when you get there. Isaac Newman took the heat for event number six. Can he double it up here at event number seven?
These guys all cycling pretty aggressively here. It's hard to read because really for us to have an understanding of the wattage that they're putting out, we'd have to see the dampers and all the things. But we get a beautiful shot of exactly where they're at. And they're just eating up these calories. Some of them almost getting a calorie a second there as they're just ticking by the low 20s at this point, already 46 seconds in. Yunakoski got third in that heat. Again, it is close. One second for three spots between Isaac Newman, Yunakoski, and Morse Fiebig.
My prediction is that we'll see a touch more separation here from these athletes in the finish of this. And it's going to be due to the bar muscle-ups, of course, different strategies at play. But they've got to really trust their fitness from a gymnastics point of view here. You can't just bike fast for no reason if you don't feel like you're going to excel at the bar muscle-up. It's pointless. Bebig off the bike first. 28 bar muscle-ups.
While this movement forces the athletes to travel a much greater range, going from all the way down to a fully supported position above the bar, it's a chance for them to steady and slow their heart rate. It's smooth. It's predictable. There's not a lot of violent hip drive, really, because they're all so physically strong in their upper body. It's more of a swing and a pull. Passing the 10-rep mark. If you look at the top of your screen, we're also cresting the two-minute mark.
The rep count to get to is 63. As Peter Ellis takes his first break as Fiebig hangs on. And Buckland was already down to his first break as well. Fiebig, 10 reps left to go. Isaac Newman on the right side.
Trying to see if he can double up here at event six and seven. Bill Leahy takes a break as well. Can Febig pull himself back in the lead on his second set? The number is 63. Five more reps to go. This is going to be that threshold slash breaking point for a lot of the athletes in this event chase. I think a lot of them have their eyes set on one big set and a smaller set to get to 20,
Fiebing has a second opportunity to not get sniped at the end. Peter Ellis has one more rep. He got called back to the rig in the bottom part of your screen. Enrique Morera is on to the burpee box and forwards along with Yota Koski. Here comes Koski with a bit more urgency running to the boxes.
Bibig did the same thing in event six where he led all the way to the last box and at the last second Yonakoski and Isaac Newman had caught up to him. Moritz still moving at a solid clip here as Burpee's a little bit more urgent than that first score scored event you got to think he doesn't want to happen again what he allowed in that last one.
You see Moritz looking across the field, a bit more aware of his surroundings, as you said, than in event six. Two back-to-back score events, 200 points up for grabs in a span of 15 minutes. Past the four-minute mark. Moritz Fiebig has nine reps left to go. Yonakoski, Bill Leahy, and Enrique Moreira are trying to chase down Fiebig.
Yeah, Fiebig's doing his job. He's doing exactly what he needs to do in order to keep that distance between him and Moreira. He's leading better with his chest than he was on the last round. He typically would lead with his hips, and then his chest would roll to the ground, and he's much more aggressive now. Fiebig on the last box, upper part of your screen. And it happened once. And it's not gonna happen again. Fiebig will take heat one of it's seven.
Enrique Moreno across the finish line. Bill Leahy with a full clear of that box. Leahy's in. Koski's in. Right on the five minute mark. Time cap is eight minutes. Bill really made up some ground on Yona right there on those final burpees. Jorge Fernandez across the finish line.
Olinkiewicz, Peter Ellis across, Tiago Lucis, and Toby Buckland have nine reps left to go. If you look at the back part of your screen, that is Isaac Newman. And the question was, with 200 points up for grabs, event by event, separated by one minute,
Is it worth sending one and hanging on for the other? And it looks like that is what Isaac's plan was the whole time. And that's a calculated risk that athletes have to be willing to take. Know thyself. We've heard Bethany Flores teach us all that lesson throughout the course of this weekend and the time that we've got to spend with her. It's one of her favorite lessons as an athlete, probably as a human.
But it's about understanding where you can get the most bang for your buck, or where the juice is worth the squeeze, as they say, when it comes to points accumulation. And for some, it's about full sending it, even if that's at a sacrifice of a lesser finish in the following event. Buckling to cross the finish line. Newman on his second-to-last box. Again, athletes will do three burpee box jumpovers at each box for a total of eight sections and 24 reps.
Plenty of time before we hit the cap. As Newman is hoping it was worth the send in event six to see how that time stacks up for the next two heats.
But Moritz Fiebing, consistency is always key if you want to excel at the CrossFit Games, as he gets second and first in heat number one. Highlights presented by Rogue Fitness. Yeah, this back-to-back didn't start any better than it could have for Moritz. Of course, there's going to be a lot of scores left to input. But what a great way to set himself up for success. He got the 28-bar muscle-ups in a smooth two sets, one larger set, one smaller set to finish.
And then he didn't have enough urgency in event number six just before this. But event number seven, he wasn't going to make that mistake again. And he finished with the appropriate amount to get him an event seven, at least for now, the score to beat. Your heat results for event number seven, Moritz Fiebig, 443. Not as close as far as timing wise as we saw in event six is Enrique Moreira.
gets 454. Heat one is done. Heat two coming up next.
Saturday night at MVP Arena here in Albany, New York. For the 2025 CrossFit Games, today's coverage is presented by Velites. I'm Chase Ingram. Along with me is Adrian Conway and Mike Arsenault. We'll be on the floor as we get set.
for individual event six and seven. Throttle up, hammer down. And it's an exciting one, Chase. This starts fast and furious with 35 calories on the skier, 28 chest-to-bar pull-ups, and 24 burpee box jump-overs. Don't blink, folks. It's over that quickly. Then they get a one-minute reset, and we're right into event seven. It's a 35 calorie, this time on a C2 bike, 28 bar muscle-ups, and 24 burpee box jump-overs, both worth 100 points each. Your lane assignments for heat number two
As these here middle 10 athletes of the 30 that are competing this weekend and we have receded Since the one rep max back squat And your vision fuels victory athlete to watch Colton Mertens put up a staggering 370 pounds and if no if anyone needed 200 points more
I don't think anyone needs more than Colton Mertens. No, no, no. You said it. 570 on that back squat. It was crazy to watch. This is his fourth individual appearance at the CrossFit Games. His best finish overall is 18th. Right now sitting in 15th. This still isn't where Colton expected to be this year. And I know this isn't where he wants to end up. He's going to come out hungry. And I expect him to make some moves in this combination of scores 6 and 7. But watch out for him on number 7, setting a mean score and a hard one to beat.
Another athlete that was in the top 10 and looking to maybe get back in before we start the final day. Kyle Iansuzza has had himself a heck of a weekend. Absolutely. Consistency sitting in 12th place, and this is his third consecutive CrossFit Games. 35 cows on the skier. 22 pound vests.
And the race is to the rig. We saw in the previous heat, Moritz Fiebig was first to the rig, first to the box, but lost out on the last second on that final burpee box jump over to Isaac Newman. And Isaac Newman pulled a fast one and just sent event six and survived event seven. Is anyone in this heat gonna do the same?
I think everyone watching that has experienced tired burpees could relate to Isaac Newman there on that final stretch of those. We understand where he was and what he was feeling. Probably a lack of body control. The race has just started here for these men and they are churning and burning through these calories. Very aggressive. We don't expect to see a ton of lead change. Like you mentioned, Chase, we saw just a slight amount towards the end of those burpees on the last one.
They've got to get going here on the skier. Now, Mertens will probably slower up the skier, because Callum Clements is already to the rig, as he's four seconds ahead of the pace set by Newman. Now, once Mertens gets to the rig, the race is on. That's right.
That short range of motion that he gets to pull with as we're watching all these athletes execute a butterfly pull up, those feet coming forward as they pull their chin up and above the bar from behind. They got to make contact with the best breastplate of that vest. The number to get to is 63. That's at the top of your screen, Callum Clements. Looks like he's going for it in this heat.
He's on pace that Isaac Newman had at 143. Here comes Mertens and Ty Jenkins joined by the rest of the field. Callum Clements in lane number two, upper part of your screen, just past the two minute mark. Time to beat 318.35. After the fourth box, Isaac Newman
was done at 257. Callum Clemens is on the fourth box. Clemens moving smoothly, but still very urgently stepping up every burpee, making quick haze transition from box to box. Clemens is ahead of the pace set by Newman.
Looks like Colin Bossard is trying to stick with him, as Callie and Susan, the right side of your screen, isn't backing down just yet. 30 seconds before he hit the time to beat. Clemens, six reps left to go. He's got to go, it's going to be close.
Last jump before the last box. Three reps. 13 seconds left. It's going to be close. Can he get across the finish line? And Bossard, Mertens, Souza are in. Wow. 3.17, the new time to beat. Bossard actually snuck in.
at 3.18.23. Well, we talked about it being fast, and it's always fast at the end. These athletes only being separated by a matter of seconds. Nick Matthews across the finish line.
All athletes look to be done under the four minute mark. Now the time cap is six. They'll rest until the time cap and we'll have a minute transition. The question is, is Callum Clements taking a page out of the Isaac Newman playbook?
And this is where you really have to lean heavily on your preparation. Optimally, these athletes have all experienced this in the buildup to the CrossFit Games, where they've completely sold their soul to a workout, rested with a very short turnaround, and still tried to give it the same type of intensity and approach. Because if you've done your history, you know you're likely up against some kind of back-to-back scoring system at the CrossFit Games. These highlights by Rogue Fitness, and it was all Callum Clements from start to finish.
Yeah, he did a great job having that urgency off the skier, and he watched that heat before knowing, hey, if I can take the lead here, it's all about sheer grit and fortitude, a bit of urgency on these burpees, and I can get the job done. And that's exactly what Clements did here. Urgency with just the appropriate amount to edge out Isaac Newman from the last heat for event number six.
Your results from heat number two, Callum Clements, 3.17, the first athlete to break the 3.18 mark. With Colin Bossart's time of 3.18, that marks three athletes at the 3.18 mark, with another at 3.19. So you're top five with Colton Mertens at 3.20 in heat number two.
And you see the athletes chalking up strategically at this end of the floor so they don't have to worry about it as they sit down to that biker here in event seven that's quickly approaching. 10 seconds before the six minute cap. Athletes will get 60 seconds to work their way down the floor and get set for event seven. Throttle up is done. Hammer down is next.
We've got a whole different workout worth 100 points, 35 calories this time on the C2 bike, 28 bar muscle ups, and then 24 burpee box jump overs. We understand the bar muscle up is where a significant amount of the time is gonna be taken. We saw athletes in that last event, or last heat, accomplished a 28 in an average of two sets. It really just dictated on when and how long they broke.
Tying the beat, 443.70 by Moritz Fiebig in heat number one. This is heat two with one heat remaining. 35 cows on the Concept 2 bike.
You notice a lot of these guys start with that standing start to rev up those RPMs and get the wattage a bit high, so then they can ride the momentum created on that C2 bike. A lot of urgency here. They want to be one of the first athletes to the rig for the bar muscle-up. Colton Mertens, who desperately needs points.
And a lot of these athletes are just on the outside looking in of that top 10 as we receive going into the morning. And there is vital importance of being in that last heat going into Sunday. This is the opportunity to make a lot of moves. And there's going to be a lot of unknowns, even as we watch that final heat take the floor with those 200 points available. There's just going to be a tremendous amount of shakeup. It is almost going to feel blind until all the athletes are through this double scored event.
These men have to have an understanding that if Mertens is going to beat them to the rig, there's going to be a small chance for them to have an opportunity to beat this guy. When he gets there, he's going to be threatening to be one of those athletes to rip off 28 in a row if it's possible. Clements is off the bike again, or at least off the machine first. But Mertens is much closer than he was after the skier at Event 6. Tudor Magda on the right side of your screen, also on the bar muscle-ups.
And there's one thing that Colton Merton prides himself on. It's the ability to hang on to a pull-up bar. The time is now if Merton wants to get himself back into the top 10.
Tudor Mac down the right in the cutoff blue has a really unique cycle rate. It's much faster than a lot of the competitors. He's choosing not to pause at all through the transition and press out right away. This is going to afford him, I'm sure in his mind, hopefully a little bit of time for that break that we just watched him take. But you'll notice his press out is just a lot faster at the top. It allows him to cycle reps a bit quicker. Just past the two minute mark on the upper left corner of your screen. If you look at the hat on top, it's Mertens takes a break.
The number to get to is 63. Mertens eight reps away. Moritz Fiebig was done with the bar muscle-ups at 259. Mertens back on the bar. Even with the break, no one is yet to get close to him.
And this is where Clemens took a really long break right there, Chase. This is where you start to see the accumulation effects of taking the victory on that event six there to kick things off. One more rep for Mertens. Can he get it? Squeezes it out and now the race is on the box as he is 14 seconds ahead of pace.
Mearns is not racing these 10 guys. He's racing the next 10 guys. He needs another event win in the most desperate way. Unfortunately, he has to do it by himself in the second heat. And this is the climb that he's had from that slow start at a 26th spot. We've got a 20th, a 10th, a 19th, and a first. Where will these next two scores settle him on the leaderboard?
Moritz Fiebig, who has the time to beat in the upper left corner of your screen at 443.70. After this fourth box, he was at the 3.52 mark. Mertens, 15 seconds ahead of pace still.
Yeah, and this is the urgency you love to see from the athletes right here, as Mertens really is digging deep, staying as low as he can to the box. It's a race to the ground, every rep chase. This is where athletes can start to take things for granted. They flop down. Colton is attacking the ground after every repetition. This is gonna set him apart from the score to beat. Mertens on his sixth box. There's eight in every lane on the floor. Six more reps to go for Mertens. Just past the four minute mark.
30 seconds stands between Mertens and a new time to beat. Colton Mertens with one more box jump has to get across the finish line. And there you go, Heat 3. Have fun with that. 427.63. Ty Jenkins trying to get away from Chris Ibarra. Wow.
A little synchro action there from the boys to finish the event. 17 one hundredths of a second between Ibarra and Jenkins as Moritz time will at least stand for fourth best in the event with one heat left to go. Bossart's in. Callum Clements.
Still hanging tough for us, so definitely not sending the full event six, and trying to hang on here at event seven. Zanoni. Captain Jack. Souza. Souza's in. Magda. One athlete left on the floor, that is Nick Matthew.
Did we learn some lessons, Chase? Do you hold back just a touch now after seeing all the rest of the athletes take the floor for event six? Are you like, okay, I want to finish second in my heat on that one so then I can come back and do the thing. Colton Mertens. Sets the time to beat for event number seven. Here are your highlights. Mr. Mertens, presented by Rogue Fitness.
Mr. Mertens, we knew we had to have an eye for him, but it was Clements off the bike first. We, however, had a firm understanding that if Colton could rope someone in to stay close enough for these bar muscle-ups that this would be that movement, that he's got an advantage, a faster cycle rate, and we know he can go big when it comes to the volume here for these hanging gymnastics. And that's exactly what he did.
Set a great pace, was ahead of the previous heat already at this point, but then it was his effectiveness and efficiency with these burpees submitting to the discomfort and leading with his chest and torso for every rep that allowed him to now have the time to beat.
Your heat, two results. Colton Mertens at 427.63. Only athlete under 430 so far with Ibarra and Jenkins at 439. The third and final heat, 200 points up for grabs. Next, here in MVP Arena.
Saturday night at MVP arena as we get set for heat three men's event six and seven for the 2025 CrossFit Games. I'm Chase Ingram along with me is Adrian Conway. Mike Arsenault will be joining us shortly on the competition floor in your
standings after five events. Jason Hopper has reclaimed the leader jersey over James Crouch, but now a 20-point lead. And Justin Medeiros has now moved into a third-place position and is looking very dangerous. Individual events six and seven. Throttle up, hammer down.
The first one's for time with a vest, a 35-calorie ski, 28 chest-to-bar pull-ups, and 24 burpee box jump-overs. Folks, don't blink. It is going to be that quick. After a one-minute reset, they're going to get into a 35-calorie C2 bike, 28-bar muscle-up, and 24 burpee box jump-overs, all for time. But this time, no vest.
Adrian, what are your recipes for success? They're straightforward. On this first one, you've got to be full send chase. Once we exit the skier, there's not going to be much time to change the lead. And then on the back half, it's pace don't break for event seven. You've got to pace yourself and know when to break up those 28-bar muscle-ups.
Your lane assignments for your third and final heat. Your top three on the leaderboard will be in lanes five, six, and four. And the man in lane four is your two-time CrossFit Games champ, Justin Medeiros. With more on him, let's go down to Mike Arsenault.
Thanks, Chase. When Justin won his titles back in 2021 and 2022, he was the model of consistency, and he's lacked that the last couple of years. But now, for the first time in a couple of years, he finds himself on the podium this late in the competition, and he's reeled off four consecutive finishes in the top 10. And both Event 6 and Event 7 line up very well for him. We'll see if he can make it six in a row as he looks to return to the podium for the first time since 2022.
Lines up very well for two other athletes as our vision fuel victory athletes to watch. That is Jason Hopper and Roman Krennikoff. The big fellas came to play and they're going to like the looks of this skier with 20 extra pounds on their body chase. I'm looking at both of these guys as an all out race to be one of the first men off the skier and try to lead the rest of event six. We'll see how it plays out.
Jason Hopper back in the lead with 20 points. Jeff Adler did not have the squat we are accustomed to seeing, but perhaps he has a little left in the tank with 200 points up for grabs. Heat number three underway.
35 cows on the skier. Your top 10 athletes. After five events, we are cresting the halfway point. And we're doing with back-to-back events here in event number six and event number seven. Roman Krennikov.
Sitting outside of podium position in fourth place with 365 points. Justin Medeiros holds that third place position, 27 points more than him. But if anybody can crank on a skier and hang on to a pull-up bar,
That's right, and if people weren't paying attention to how he got here, they can go back and watch the final at the Mayhem Classic on one of the ways that he was able to accumulate a lot of points is by going unbroken on big sets of bar muscle-ups with bikers. So he lines it up, and he's willing to risk it for the biscuit, as they say, on a workout like this, as we see Jason Hopper already accumulating well past the 30-calorie range.
The time to beat is set by Callum Clements at 3.17. He was off the skier at 1.04. So Krennikov, everyone, is about four seconds behind Clements.
Here we go. These butterfly pull-ups are no problem for any of these athletes in this final heat. They're all going to go 28 unbroken. Who can be the most efficient with their range of motion? Meeting the minimum standard is going to be hitting that vest right on the top of that bar. Events 6 and 7 is presented by the U.S. Border Patrol. U.S. Border Patrol is hiring. Make an impact. Be an agent of strength. Apply now at cbp.gov forward slash crossfit as Dallin Pepper is on to the box.
But it is James Sprague all the way down in lane number 10 doing James Sprague things. Your 2024 CrossFit Games champion, wasting no time trying to get ahead of the pack.
Yeah, we like James Sprague in any ERG event, and he's doing exactly what he needs to do. Fast through the pull-up bar, he wore his vest a little bit loose chase, which has allowed him to travel a lesser distance to make contact with that pull-up bar. And what he really needs to do is he needs to be ahead of that 226 mark after this box. And he's five seconds ahead of the pace by Clemens. Sprague needs 100 points here. He's five seconds ahead of the pace, and about 10 seconds ahead of the field.
Nine more reps to go for James Sprague. Six burpee box jump overs left. No time wasted in transition between the boxes. James is making a very clean run here. It's a race between James and the clock and he has 20 seconds to set the time to beat.
James Sprague was sitting in 10th, but not much longer, because he just got 100 points. Gerrard's across, 314. Gerrard needed that. All these athletes needed that. Justin Medeiros is in.
And Hopper looked like he got out sprinted by about three athletes right at the end. Jay Crouch was one of them. And that is huge for Jay Crouch. We talked about this event coming down to tenths of seconds. James Spray gets first in the event. OK.
Hopper getting out sprinted at the finish. Got 17th in that event. Keep in mind, there are 30 athletes competing. A 17th place finish is 39 points. Crouch, a 16th. There was a big gap between your top four and the next six. Not anymore, and we got another 100 points waiting in the wings.
Let's check out these highlights presented by Rowe. Wow. Well, we were on it early. We were watching Roman. We were watching Jason. But there was another big fella in this heat by the name of James Sprague, who was handling business down to the bottom of the right of the screen here. First one to the Burpee Box Jumpovers, and there was absolutely no looking back for James.
It was technical proficiency from rep one all the way through 24 on those brick-a-box jump overs, and he just wrapped himself up in a big win here for 2025 CrossFit Games.
Adrian, if you wanted to ask me, name five athletes that make big points in a big way. Those names go James Sprague, Ricky Gerrard, Dallin Pepper, Austin Hatfield. We also needed the guys changing to have some big losses. And we just had that in event six. What was a four-pack running away is now compressed. But who had the best overall? Justin Medeiros. And that's what we like to see, Chase. We had a conversation.
walking through the halls of the MVP arena. And what we say it was time for? It's time to get desperate for some of these athletes. Some of these athletes that were on the cusp, this is the time to make your move. And they are making those moves right now, showing signs of desperation with high levels of execution. Jesse Medeiros finished the best of the guy's top four men. But it was still a 13th place position.
So we have 100 more points on the board up for grabs. And with the way that event just went down, what was a big gap is now compressed.
This could be a make or break event for everyone's podium hopes. It's only Saturday night. Don't get me excited. It's only Saturday night. That's right. But this is the Saturday night. This is the big event, baby. This is what we came to see. Every year at the CrossFit Games, Dave Cash has said this for years. There's an event that someone has a performance.
that shows you who the CrossFit Games champion could be. Could this be the event on Saturday night, in this heat, with some of the best athletes that all have a chance to stand on top of the podium? And this is what they have in store. 35 cals on the bike, 28-bar muscle-ups, 24 burpee box jump-overs. The vest is gone, and it's time to hammer down.
We saw from the previous heat, this is less about who is first off the bike and more about who is first off the bar. It's not an eco bike. It's just about ripping the handle.
off the bike to get it going. When you talk about desperation, that's what it looks like, Chase. That's hunger and desire there. James does a lot of interval-based training at really high intensity. He's got a great aerobic base. And his coach knows that he's got to dose him up with power and strength work. And that comes in the form of a lot of repeat intervals, just like this. We could be seeing that pay off in this back-to-back with 6 and 7. The time to beat is set by Colton Mertens in heat number 2.
Mertens was off the bike in 112, but that is not where he made up his time. He made up his time on the bar muscle-ups. We know almost every athlete in this heat can dance on these pedals better than anybody else, but can they hang on to that pull-up bar? And if we're comparing to Colton Mertens, not quite as good as Colton, because that cycle rate is almost impossible for a lot of these young men to match. But they could probably get close to matching that rep scheme. They're going to have to have a lot of urgency in getting off this bike faster than he did.
We're gonna see a lot of athletes off the bike at near the same time as we are past the 110 mark. Behind the pace of Mertens, but it is Dow and Pepper who is to the pull-up bar first.
Pepper with also a fast lockout at the top, a little bit faster than what we see as close to us as possible here from James. James almost rests on the rig, then presses out. Dallin Moore pressing out as he rises above the rig itself. That's the 90 second mark clock in the upper left corner of your screen. The rep counter is at the top of your screen. The number to get to is 63. Jason Hopper took a 17th place finish in that last event.
There's gonna be a lot of shakeups here between the six and seven score. These 200 points are, as we've alluded to, very impactful for tomorrow's lineup. Holton Merton's got to 55 before he took a break. Pepper's at 54. The time check is two minutes and 44 seconds. Pepper has nine reps to go as Sprague takes his first break. Don't sleep on Ricky Garrard over in lane number one as he's trying to keep pace with Pepper.
Hatfield drops for a break. Adler's down. Handful of reps left to go. Pepper took a break. Can Rickey make his move here? Rickey's got to hold on for two more. James Spragues at the bottom right also takes a break. And it is Rickey Gerard.
Ricky Garrard. He's got a full two reps on Dallin right now. Took second in the event in event six. Garrard has to have this if he wants a chance to chase his dream, and that's to stand on top of the podium at the CrossFit Games. Ricky Garrard's currently sitting
outside of a podium position, as he is in ninth place. He needs these points in a big way, but he's starting to get reeled in. After the fourth box, Burns was done at 338.
Ricky put on some amazing performances at the semi-final level in the in-affiliate testing stage, and he's doing it now. Ricky has three boxes left to go. That means nine reps. Make that six reps. 30 seconds, and Ricky could have himself a monster evening and have all the momentum going into Sunday.
Time to beat 427. One rep left for Ricky, and it is a Ricky Mack attack. Garrard takes Hammerdown. Here comes Dallin Pepper. He needs this just as much as anybody else. Oh, and we've got a showdown behind Pepper. Justin Medeiros just got a no rep.
And Roman's in. Sprague. Hopper. Medeiros. Wow. Now that might have been a tough no rep for Medeiros. Tough one for Pepper too. He was shaping up to be second in that heat. Merton should hang on a second overall in the event. Jane Sprague gets first and third. Ricky Gerrard gets second and first.
Harry Lightfoot just trying to hang. And boy, oh boy. Get your calculators out because this leaderboard.
is gonna change in a big way. Who will be wearing the leader jersey going into Sunday? Ricky Garrard gets second in event six, first in event seven, with an extra 196 points to his total going into Sunday. An absolute devastation. Devastation. On the finishing map.
That's what you love to see. That's called intensity, folks. We're familiar with that. We know what that's like. Replays by Rogue Fitness.
Well, these guys were all in full attack mode. Chase, we talked about it. If these guys want to be on the podium, it is time to execute with desperate measure. They've got to be intense. They've got to be calculating. They've got to go get it. And Ricky Guerrard did just that, coming out with a ferocious pace on event six. We hadn't seen many people be successful in the back-to-back. Ricky showed us it is possible when you've been training for these moments. High level of execution.
Ricky's just racked up 196 of them, and he's carrying in the momentum into Sunday morning. Ricky Garrard takes Event 7. Colton Mertens gets second. James Sprague, huge back-to-back finishes for him. It was important for Ricky. Your two winners in Event 6 and Event 7.
James Sprague and Ricky Garrard. What a performance by both of these gentlemen. Event 6 and Event 7 winners joining me. Both of you just squeaked into that final heat, 10th and 9th place respectively. Both of those performances going to push you a little bit further up the leaderboard. James, let's start with you. This is your title defense. How would you describe how your title defense has gone thus far? We've had some uneven performances.
Totally, yeah. It hasn't been the best executed weekend. There's a couple mishaps I've made early in the weekend, but today I woke up with a refreshed mindset, renewed headspace, just knowing that hungry dogs run faster. So I'm not going to slow down when things get hard. I'm going to speed up. What did you take from the experience winning at last year's games that is helping you adjust to maybe performances that you're not entirely happy with this year? Totally. It's just knowing this is a professional sport. You're not always going to win every race, but what you can do
is learn from your failures, learn from your hardships, learn from the things that go well, take it to the next one. I believe the more times I step out here, the better and more resilient I'm going to get. So just trying to keep stack experiences so in 10 years I can still be out here crushing it, hanging out with these awesome dudes. Your second career event win. Congratulations. Rest up. We'll see you tomorrow. Thank you very much, guys. Amazing crowd. Woo!
All right, Ricky, speaking of up and down performances, your second event win of the weekend thus far, with a few performances outside of the top 10. So how do you try and keep yourself on that even keel as you progress through these events, as we move through a difficult weekend of competition? Yeah, a couple of things haven't gone my way. Last night on the pegboard was unfortunate, but it is what it is. And the back squats. Yeah, it's just back squats. I hate them. I still pee hard, so I'll take that.
But I knew I could come out here in this event, and 200 points on the line, two good workouts for me. And I really needed those points back, so I was willing to fight with everything I had to do that. And I think I got second and first, so can't complain with that. And I'm here to win. This is my goal, to give everything to this achievement that I want to achieve. And I'm not giving it up yet. One more day to go. I might not be sitting in a good spot, but
Yeah, I appreciate all you guys for cheering me on. And hopefully that gets me up the leaderboard, and I can fight with everything I've got tomorrow to try and bring it home. Well, that's definitely going to push you up the leaderboard. Ricky, thank you very much. Congratulations. We'll see you tomorrow. Cool. Thank you. Thank you, guys. Congratulations to James Sprague and Ricky Garrard. Not often does the hype live up.
to the billing, but we had a fantastic race for the men. Don't go anywhere. It will be the individual women's turn after this.
I became the owner of CrossFit Spur after being introduced to CrossFit in probably 2010-2011. Coached at a local box for a bit. Really enjoyed it more than I thought I would. Ended up getting my L1 and decided that I'd like to go off of my own and give it a shot.
Way better. Good. We're just outside of Albany, a small town called Glenmont. I worked in the town that Crossfittsburg is in for many, many years. It's a neighboring town. Got to know the community really well. But after kind of being here and growing through word of mouth, organic growth, and people starting to understand that what we do is make people healthy, we sort of earned a reputation of making people better at anything, no matter what they wanted to do.
John and Lauren will do just about anything to help anybody get better at anything. I'm convinced of that for sure. You have an AMRAP for 14 minutes. My wife, Lauren, has been a member at the gym for longer than she was an employee here. She's an organizer for sure, so she does a great job keeping everything in line, taking care of the boring stuff that people don't quite understand, all the ins and outs of business ownership. I don't know that the gym would be able to run without her. It certainly would not have been able to expand the way it did without her.
We are probably the largest in the Capital District, definitely one of the largest. We've got 6,500 plus square feet of floor space. We've got two rigs, full corral of bikes and rowers and all the endurance machines you could possibly want.
COVID hit, the reality set in that we might not be opening for quite a while. We ended up creating sort of a fitness library. We labeled all of our equipment. And we allowed our members to come in twice a week and swap out their equipment. So they each got to take two pieces home. But through that, we didn't lose a single member.
In addition to the CrossFit space, we have some offices next door where we've got a therapy room with contrast therapy. We have a cold plunge. We have a sauna. We've also got a barber shop. We have two massage therapists that are here full time. We've also got a chiropractor. We've got a little bit of everything to offer for anyone looking to get healthy.
I've been a member here at CrossFit Spur for 10 years. It's just grown and grown and grown, this business. Doubled, almost tripled the size of it. So many new members, so many members that have been here for quite a long time, as long as me. So it's really great.
I moved here during grad school, and honestly, if it wasn't for this community here, I probably still wouldn't live here. John and Lauren have created such a great atmosphere. Everybody here is like-minded. Everybody supports each other. His programming is fantastic. And what's really impressive, when the people don't know this, they don't realize what goes into the coaching aspect. They don't see the notes that I see from him saying, this is what I want you to focus on today. Make sure they do this. Don't let them do this.
I want you to check this. He's not throwing stuff together. It gives you a different perspective. It's not just a place they go work out. This is where their friends are. This is where they enjoy spending time. It makes going to the gym something that they want to do, which I think is part of the reason that we've grown the way we have. It's their place.
What's the key component when we look at functional movements? What are we looking for?
The ability to move a large load. Long distances. Quickly. Ready, and go. And now reach up. Mastering the nine foundational movements is key to building strong, efficient CrossFit skills. The squat, front squat, and the overhead squat. The press, push press, push jerk, deadlift, sumo deadlift, high pull, and the med ball clean. We can basically break down all of our human and athletic movement to a foundation of these movements.
And stand, missy, send your hip back a little bit more. These movements teach essential themes like core stability, posterior chain engagement, and full range of motion across the joints. Skills that transfer to many other functional movements. Get these right and you'll have the foundation to confidently move, lift, and thrive.
you
I'm calling out
So,
Running it back one more time. We're at Albany, New York, inside the MVP arena for the 2025 CrossFit Games. As we're closing things out on a Saturday night with the individual women. And this is a testament to the volunteers breaking down the squats from event five and check out how much work goes into it.
Nothing is possible without our volunteers. No, years of competing on the competition floor, man. You see behind the lens of every single event that is almost completely supported by people willing to sacrifice their time and effort as volunteers. And you love it. They get to say, of course, that they were part of the inner workings of putting on the 2025 CrossFit Games. And of course, they get to peel back the layers and see behind the whole engine that puts this thing through. You can see the different color shirts representing different
Sections of our volunteer crew, judges, medical staff, scoring, equipment team, athlete control, security. Absolutely incredible. Absolutely will not be possible without our volunteers.
Still trying to catch my breath from the men as we get set for the women's turn for individuals six and seven. Throttle down, throttle up, hammer down. That's right. Well, Chase, catch your breath quickly, brother, because you know what happens fast. It's 35 calories on the skier, 28 chest-to-bar pull-ups, and 24 box over burpees with a 16-pound vest with a one-minute transition and rest into a 35-calorie C2 bike, then 28-bar muscle-ups
and 24 burpee box jump overs with a hard time cap of eight minutes. Andrew, what is your tempo recipe for success? On this first one, it's going to be full send. You want to be one of the first people off of that skier if you want to have success at a high-level finish in event six. And for event seven, it's a different approach. It's pace and break. We're specifically talking about those bar muscle-ups. Very calculated risk versus reward if you go all the way to failure there.
Your lane assignments for heat number one. We have three total heats of 10. We're closing things out here tonight on a Saturday in MVP Arena. Your vision fuels victory athletes to watch Sung Young Choi competing in her fourth CrossFit Games.
Yeah, she comes here as a tenured athlete now, four times at the CrossFit Games, finishing 24th last year in 2024, and looking to finish in a higher placing every single year. Right now sitting in 26, she's got to put herself higher on the leaderboard. And you have Maria Camila Quintero, and this is her second time competing. She hasn't qualified as an individual since 2019.
Yeah, she's one of those great athletes, Chase, that has towed the line on both sides. She was a team athlete three times, and now here's an individual again. Event number six, no change in reps between the men and the women. We don't often see that when we talk machine work.
Yeah, and this is one of those things where we understand because we're stationary, mass moving mass is a huge advantage. So what we're asking is that the women are essentially responsible for a touch more work being that often in stature and in body weight.
They compare in smaller size than the athletes for the most part. And that's going to demand more work for them to accomplish that 35 calories on the skier. Still going to be an all out race, but probably going to hit that at just a touch slower tempo. Does that make the first part on the machines more important to the success in this event? I think that what we'll see is more variability.
I don't know that it's any more important, but I do believe that there will be a greater disparity in the time off from the first athlete to the last here, especially as we sequentially go through heat after heat, making our way closer towards that heat one, or heat three, I'm sorry. Past the minute mark. Summer athletes have a little less than 10 cows remaining. Mariana Meza, one of those athletes. The number to get to is 35.
After the skier, they'll advance to the pull-up bar. For 28 chest-to-bar pull-ups, wearing that 16-pound vest. Now, a better consideration here, Chase, is will we see them break up the reps of the 28? We didn't see one male intentionally break off for the 28 chest-to-bars. Will the women have a different approach? First to the rig is Mariana Meza on the left and Alexis Raptis on the right.
both moving extremely fluidly through those butterfly chest-to-bar pull-ups. We see DeRoy there in the middle of our screen right beside Raptis. The number to get to is 63, and Raptis will be done. She's onto the box at the 2.15 mark. 24 burpee box jumpovers at 20 inches.
Remember, that standard is that these athletes have to do three burpee box jump overs at each box before advancing, and they have to step down until that third burpee box jump over in which they can clear the box however they'd like to advance forward. Alexis Raptis and Mariana Mesa still side by side as they are six reps in working on the set of nine. All athletes will do three burpee box jump overs.
And there are eight boxes. There are 80 boxes on the competition floor. We are past the three minute mark. Alexis Raptis in the yellow shoes in the center lane. Past the halfway point on these Burpee Box Jump Overs. Maya De Mesa on the left in lane number one is not going anywhere. Alexis Raptis, nine reps left to go.
And this is where that 16 pounds of excess weight starts to feel a lot more heavy on your triceps and your shoulders as you press out every rep of one of these burpees. Time cap, six minutes. As Raptis has six more burpee box jumpovers to go. No slowing for Alexis, looking great on these burpee box jumpovers. Raptis is on her final three.
Approaching the four-minute mark. Two minutes to the cap. She's not going to need it, but she will set the time to beat. 4.05.33 for Alexis Raptis, as Messa dies over the finish line to try to out-sprint Sung Young Choi. Adekanyo's in.
Now the men didn't need it, but that time cap is going to come into play potentially on the women's side. Yeah, we're going to see some athletes come very close to that six minute mark here. We talk about the difference. A lot of that difference is made up there on those calories on the skier. DeRoy still navigating her final burpee box jump overs here. She's across.
Unofficially 450 for DeRoy. Mejas still maneuvering through. Got one minute before he hit that five or six minute cap. Mejas done. We have two athletes left on the floor. Make that one, Quintero's in. And Luis and Marquez. Athletes can shed the vest.
and get as much recovery as they can until we hit the six minute cap and then they will have 60 seconds to get across the floor and get set for event number seven.
And right now, Alexis is trying to put as much effort and energy into recovery as possible. You'll notice her shaking her extremities. She's trying to flush away as much lactate as she can. That's a burning sensation that starts to accumulate. Anytime we really start to go through any physical activity or exertion that is towards our threshold, which means you're pushing hard, you're going to get that accumulation. And she's trying to shake it before it's time to sit back down on that bike and get after it. So we have these highlights presented by Rogue Fitness.
Yeah, it was Alexis Raptus early in this event. She came out aggressive on the skier. We had a little bit of back and forth all the way through the Chester bar. But Alexis, with her smooth and fluid movement, I mean, extremely efficient in her gymnastics. And then it was her willingness to lean in and suffer on the burpee. She started to create a bit more separation between her and Marina Meza. And she was the first one across the finish line.
And the question is, can she repeat this performance for event number seven? Raptis, 405.33, with Nessa six seconds behind her. Event number seven, same reps, different movements. Different movements, and it's a short turnaround. 35 calories this time on the C2 bike. That's why we saw Alexis shaking out those legs, getting ready. 28-bar muscle-ups and 24 burpee box jumpovers.
Heat one of three for event number seven. 35 cows on the concept two bike. So we get an idea of whose strategies were what. We've seen a variety of on the men's side. Sending the first one and surviving the second. As Alexis Raptis.
is hoping to have a back-to-back good performance. Hasn't had the games that we know she wanted. Yeah, doesn't look like herself, Chase. You know, when we think about the fitness that she's amassed through her years, and we think about what she can do at a high level, even under pressure.
just doesn't look like the athlete that we're used to seeing show up here. Now, it could be an off day or two, and we're going to start to see that. This is a great opportunity, though, for her, again, to reconcile some of the points in regards to a deficit of where she's sitting. Sungyoung Choi, who closed hard on those last 24 burpees, is trying to chase down Alexis Raptis and Mariana Mesa. And four-time CrossFit Games athlete,
actually qualified out of Wadlen Fest this year. She's out of the Republic of Korea. Goes across at Limelight. There are a lot of fans at home cheering her on. Raptors only three calories left now, down to two. Good forward lean. Notice that her elbows are bent there. She's leaning on her arms in a forearm position so that she doesn't have to waste energy in her triceps. Bent move.
Raptis is on the rig. What about the 1.48 mark? Adekanyo and Sung Young Choi close behind. The number to get to at the top of your screen is 63. We are just past the two minute mark here in event number seven, heat number one.
Emily DeRoy on the left side of your screens on her bar muscle-ups along with Sierra Mejia. Carolyn Frivo on the left side of your screen as well. All athletes on the rig. 28 bar muscle-ups. Raptis at the top part of your screen.
14 reps left to go. She's at 49 total. The number she needs to get to is 63. This is her second break. We saw a lot of athletes on the men's side break this once, perhaps twice. So they did it in three different sets. A lot of the women might take one to two extra breaks. And it's all about how they manage and anticipate that. They want to push, but can never reach failure. Otherwise, they're going to have to stand around a lot longer to recover.
Raptus has about nine reps left to go. On the right side of your screen, Hattie Kanyo is closing the gap, and she is matched up with her. Just as Raptus is back on the rig, but those reps are looking hard to come by. Much more labored for Raptus there. Yeah, you'll notice Chase, she's having to drive much harder with her lower body to get the transition, and then even wait for her heels to come up to help her triceps lock out each rep.
but she made it for that set. Four reps left for Raptis. Mariana Meza, you can see at the top part of your screen is one rep behind her. Patacano too. Raptis back up to the rig. Can she hang on and get to the box? We're at the four minute mark. The time cap is eight.
One more for Raptis. She is off. 24 burpee box jump overs. No vest this time. Messes off. Two reps behind Raptis. They'll do three at each box in advance forward for eight total sections.
This is where Raptis as a veteran is going to know all the other women are just waiting to see what the time to beat is going to be. And she's got that internal drive. I got to go regardless of where everyone else is, regardless of how many reps ahead she feels. She's got to push her internal threshold. She's got to max herself out right now. Maxing out was no more apparent than we saw in that men's final heat previously.
Honestly, as an athlete, that's not something I want to see before it's my turn. You don't want to see that at all, Chase. That is very similar to a kid. You and your sibling are both lined up for spankings, and you watch your sibling get the spanking first, and then you know what's coming. The classic, you're with your partner, and you're in the gym. It's like, do you want to go first or me? You never want to go first until it's your time to go second. Christina Olivedadakis has moved into third place. She's on the right side of your screen.
Alektis Raptis in the center lane still holding on a two-rep lead over Mariana Meza who's in lane number one. Six more reps for Raptis. She's starting to extend her lead a little bit on Meza over in lane one on the left side.
Three more. Caroline Prevost in lane two is trying to pass Meza. Two more reps for Raptis. Final, burpee over the box. And Raptis goes back to back in six and seven. Wow, Lividutakis with amazing cycle rate on her burpees. Made up a lot of ground there.
Brevo sneaks in just ahead of Christina. And let the fire drill begin. A little stop, drop, and roll on the finish line. 90 seconds before we hit the eight minute cap. Quintero is done.
Better finish in seven than she had in six. Same thing with Luisa Mett. Marquez. On the left side of Emily DeRoy. And then on the right, Syria Meja.
what we've been saw, chased, and talked about. Was it a good idea to come out and win, or do you want to leave a little in the tank? Alexis Raptors was the first one to do that. Take back to back. May has in. 40 seconds until the cap. Two athletes left on the floor. One of those is Emily DeRoy. The other is Sung Young Choi.
Sun Young Choi. Looks like she put all her eggs in the event six basket. We knew she was coming on strong at the end with those burpees. And right now she's just paying the price. Not one that she probably wouldn't exchange anyways. She knew what she was getting herself into. And that'll do it for heat number one.
As Alexis Raptis goes back to back in event six and event seven. We still have two more heats remaining for the women. Your highlights presented by Rogue Fitness.
These women didn't have much time to recover coming into event seven as they only get a one minute transition, but they sat down on that C2 bike and Alexis Raptis came out aggressive just as she did in event six. This put her in a very unique situation to of course lead the charge. We haven't seen many lead exchanges happen throughout the course of these 24 burpee box jump overs. And she is now leading the way as the first athlete to take an event six win and then followed up with a back-to-back dub in event number seven, Alexis Raptis.
Raftis sets the time to beat once again at 6 minutes, 0.39 seconds. As Heat One is done. Two more heats remaining. Coming up after this.
The 2025 CrossFit Games continues here in MVP Arena. As heat number two is making their way on the competition floor. I'm Chase Ingram, along with me is Adrian Conway. We'll be joined by Mike Arsenault shortly. As we have events six and seven, throttle up, hammer down.
They are doozies, and they go by fast, especially number six. It's for time with a vest. 16 pounds approximately, 35 calories on the skier, 28 chest-to-bar pull-ups, and 24 burpee box jump-overs. With a one-minute rest transition after that six-minute cap, it's 35 calories on the C2 bike, 28-bar muscle-ups, and 24 burpee box jump-overs. But this time, no vest. Back-to-back events. We'll be starting with event number six, presented by Border Patrol. Your start list.
for heat number two and in lane number two out of Scotland.
Jennifer Muir, it's like a second place finish in that last event. More on her. Let's go down to Mike Arsenault. Thanks, Chase. Yeah, Jen is one of four female athletes from the UK in her first appearance at the Games. And she had a bit of a struggle on day one of the competition. But as you mentioned, a second place in the back squat, 355 pounds. Can she build on that for event six and event seven? Well, while she was warming up for these two events in the warm up area, she's dealing with a blister issue on her hand. So that will make the
chest-to-bar pull-ups and the bar muscle-ups that much more difficult. Of course, she has some grips on her hands that will help alleviate that a little bit, but look for potential hand issues for Jen throughout these next two events. Thank you, Mike. And our vision fuels victory athletes to watch Lexi Neely, who had an event win last year at the 2024 CrossFit Games. Looking to make a move back up the leaderboard here in event number six. Haley Adams.
has not had the cleanest run so far, but she has two opportunities to get back to business. 35 cows on the skier, 28 chest-to-bar pull-ups, 24 burpees over the box, all wearing that 16-pound vest for event number six.
As we watch these athletes, you want to maximize two things. One is your stroke rate. So that means you want to hinge down and stand up quickly. But the other is your stroke power. You have to pull down with ferocity, sending the hips back and down, driving through your heels every time and reaching high with those straps. That is how you get the greatest reward on the ski yard.
Just past the 42nd mark. We just watched Alexis Raptis in the previous heat go back to back. The only athlete to do so so far. Raptis was done with the skier at the minute 42 mark. The running clock in the upper left corner of your screen. We are past the one minute mark as Visagophi is at 20 cows.
A lot of athletes to keep your eye on. Visa Goffey, Abby Doman, Claudia Gluck. Claudia Gluck actually had a fantastic performance last year in the finale with two back-to-back events. And this is a opportunity to get yourself into the top 10 going into Sunday. Holding on to that 11th place position, tied in points, is Claudia Gluck and Brooke Wells.
And Brooks going going for it Haley's going for it Danielle Brandon also going to be close to getting off But it's Haley Adams leading the way Add him to the rig first. He's in the left side of your screen in lane number three The time split off the pull-up bars to 13 The time to beat as we're passing the two-minute mark said by Alexis Raptis is four oh five point three three and
Your top five times in heat number one. Raftis holds your top time. Men's at 4'11", 4'13". If it's anything like the men, seconds are vital as Haley Adams is back to the box. And Brooke Wells got a no rep. Yeah, costly, especially on that last rep. Daniel Brayden in between Haley Adams and Brooke Wells. McGonigal going rep for rep right now with Haley Adams.
McGonigal down in lane number nine on the far right side of your screen as Haley Adams is keeping pace and moving ahead. Here comes Danielle Brandon. When we get to the box, it's more about grit and athleticism.
And McGonigal right now on the right of your screen is the one showing the most urgency. Her transitions over the box, she's keeping her hips low, and she's diving right to the ground to get that plate down with her chest to follow. We're at the fourth box of eight. Alexis Radtis is at 308, and so is Danielle Brandon and Haley Adams. Lucy McGonigal has now pulled ahead.
McGonigal on the far right side of your screen in light green. The youngest athlete in the field is trying to keep ahead of Danielle Brandon and Haley Adams. She's got about a second on her. She has 30 seconds to get four more. Make that three, and Lucy McGonigal
has an opportunity to set the tide of beat with Danielle Brandon breathing down her neck. McGonagall will do it. Wow. Brandon made a strong push there at the end on those burpee box jump overs. Brandon is in. Fee Sagafi. Haley Adams, then Raptis' time is good enough for fourth overall.
Still have one heat remaining. So Lucy McGonigal. Abby Domitz across there. Takes the time by 10 seconds over Raptis. Yeah, you talk about the power of cycling reps.
Folks, this is a great reminder. Efficiency on how you do something really matters, as that was the separator between her and Haley Adams and Danielle Brand. And as she pulled away on those burpees, because hers were simply faster. All these athletes are out there giving their all. She was committed to great technique that kept her low to the ground, and it really paid off. All athletes are done.
There is a six minute cap in event six. And we have one minute left before we hit the cap. Then there'll be a one minute transition before we start event number seven. Was the game plan, get the points when you can get them. Highlights presented by Rogue.
And this is where the race really began. Of course, everyone came out aggressive on the skier. It was Haley that led the way, ahead by a few steps on the rest of the field, quickly joined by Brooke, Danielle, and the rest of the heat. Smooth on the chest-to-bar pull-ups, but it was Lucy McGonigal about two boxes in, five to six reps where she was able to garner a lead.
But then there was also a late push by Danielle Brandon, who was specifically very quick to the ground on the latter 12 reps or so. But Lucy was able to hold her off here and finish across that finish line. Lucy McGonigal takes the heat. She also might have the record for the fastest unvesting we've seen from any athlete. Get it off me. In the field.
The youngest athlete in the field from Ireland sets the new time to beat in event six. Can she recover and repeat for event number seven?
hammered down, presented by the United States Border Patrol. Well, as you mentioned, she could win an award for stripping the vest the quickest. And it's because all the athletes get to remove it for this next piece. 35 calories now on a C2 bike, 28 bar muscle-ups, which is going to be a huge deciding factor, and 24 burpee box jumpovers to finish. This one has an eight-minute cap.
Lexus Raptus also holds the time to beat at six minutes point three nine seconds. Daniel Brannan took second in that heat. Good enough for second in the event. One more event to go for heat number two. 35 cows on the C2 bike.
28 bar muscle-ups and 24 more burpee box jump overs. The vest is gone. Brooke Wells and Claudia Gluck are sitting in 11th and 12th on the leaderboard, tied with 266 points.
After all the ups and downs for Brooke Wells, she still has an opportunity to get inside the top 10 going into Sunday. Yeah, Chase, on that last event six, she got a pretty costly no rep, finishing her chest to bars, having to get called back to actually reconcile a missed rep at the end. And she was still able to finish with a really solid time in that heat. And now she's got to take full advantage of another opportunity at 100 points here.
Raptors was off the bike at a minute and 42 seconds. What's wild is that it also took her a minute and 42 seconds to do the ski. Hailey Adams. Was that intentional? Was it luck? Either way, it plays out really cool and really highly executed for Alexis. Hailey Adams taking a peek over, trying to see if she can see what Daniel Brandon is biking at.
Has had a three-cow lead. You can see the signs just in front of their bikes. Five reps for Haley Adams. As Lucy McGonigal is not backing off the pace. McGonigal is done. Seven seconds behind Raptus's pace. Now we'll have to see how the bar muscle-ups look because the muscle-ups got tough for Raptus towards the end. Yes, sir.
And they're both starting off strong, no hesitation. Get ready to work. Your top five times from heat number one. Raptus holds the time to beat at six minutes, 0.39 seconds. Lucy McGonigal, Haley Adams, first to the rig. 28-bar muscle-ups. The time split off the rig is 4.03 for Alexis Raptus. The number to get to at the top part of your screen is 63.
as Lucy McGonigal is 17 reps away. Ripped off 11 in that opening set. Haley Adams back up on the rig, Jen Muir just to her left. On the right side, Abby Dolman has yet to come off the pull-up bar and she ripped off a huge set of 17 reps.
to start her first set of bar muscle-ups in a very quick break. As she's back up on the bar. Very strong in her pulling mechanics. Lucy McGonigal on your right, takes another break.
Lucy was flirting with that failure right there. She just got a no rep at the end chase. She's very quick at her lockout. It's two things. It's a great reward when you can do it well, but it's really costly when you get a no rep like that. Claudia Gluck in the all green on the left side of your screen is trying her best to hold on for the one more rep. Wow. And Gluck is done. 20 seconds ahead of Raptors' pace.
Gosh, I believe that was two sets there that she got that in. A minute and 33 seconds split for Gluck's bar muscle-up, but Domet is close behind as she was 11 seconds faster. The race is on. Gluck, Abby Domet,
No one else. One more on the box. That is Sidney McElishan, but it is a two course race in the middle between Claudia Gluck and Abby Domen. Sidney McElishan on the left side of your screen is about five reps behind.
Abby Domit, she's, Gluck is feeling her presence throughout, seeing her at the corner of her eye. It's helping continually to push her pace, and also she's moving fast enough just to keep her at bay. Gluck on the right, has nine reps to go. Lexi kneeling on the left side of your screen. Holding on to third. One minute before we hit the tie to beat by Raptis.
All these athletes trying to avoid the temptation of doing kickstand burpees, Chase. Kickstand meaning they want to put their hands down, pause for a second like it's a kickstand, then drop. You want to lead with your chest. You can reduce a tremendous amount of time, and it really adds up when you're doing a ton of burpees like this. Last rep for Gluck, and she's in. Abby Doman, also under the six-minute mark.
Left side in lane one, Lexi Neely. Right side, McGonigal has moved ahead of Neely and has about a half-rep lead on her. One more for McGonigal. She's in right underneath the six-minute mark, along with Neely. Daniel Brandon is done.
Two minutes before we have the eight minute cap. Fees in. Nicolichan stuck in just ahead of Haley Adams as Jen Muir is done with her last burpee box jump over.
Muir seemed to navigate that blister on her hand pretty well to be finishing this fast, to be honest. I didn't know what to expect, and we got that report about battling that. When you're battling skin care on your hands and you've got to do all those hanging reps, that's a huge obstacle to face. Last athlete on the floor is Brooke Wells. She has a minute to get these last nine reps.
Two solid back-to-back finishes for Lucy McGonigal, however. We're less than a minute remaining, as well as has six minutes, six reps left to go.
It's one of those moments where Brooke knowing this is gonna be one of her last opportunities on the competition floor, trying to soak it up a little bit. Never a position a competitor wants to be in. Got a Scott Panchik siding in the crowd. And Brooke Walls is in.
just under that eight minute cap as Claudia Gluck has set the time to beat in event seven for heat number two. If you check out our highlights by Rogue Fitness.
This is a lot of up and down and all around, just like much of this weekend has been. We saw different leaders. McGonigal was one of the first ones off, followed by Adams, but they were not the ones to leave the heat coming off the bar muscle-ups. It was Claudia Gluck who seemed to work through all 28 bar muscle-ups in simply two sets to get herself a huge advantage and dictate the pace here on the Burpee Box Jump Overs. And again,
This is where that will and sheer fortitude is able to be highlighted. And she did it and had it in droves, willing her way to, at least for right now, a time to beat in event number seven. We talked about how important that was for Claudia Gluck to have two back-to-back good finishes. She's got fifth in event six after two heats, first in event seven. And she is six points out of a top 10 position going into Sunday.
That'll do it for Heat 2. Final action for individual women coming up next.
Saturday night at the 2025 CrossFit Games is about to come to a close, but hold the fireworks because we have one more heat remaining. I'm Chase Ingram. Along with me is Adrian Conway. Mike Arsenault will be joining us on the floor shortly. It's been a long day as we just finished event five, and that was that heavy one rep max back squat.
That's right. We had some shaking up and heavy lifting to do earlier today. And Maddie Sturt put on a show. Able to climb the leaderboard with her consistency. She really put on a clinic on how to show up and execute three quality lifts.
And then it was the champ doing champ things. She took it personal when she wasn't wearing the red and the white chase, and she handled business, executing a squat that, from what we know, is the best that we've seen since 2020 on the competition floor of 335 pounds. And it was a flawless lift, especially for an athlete that's been saying, hey, I've been focusing on my endurance last year.
Your standings after five events, and she's back on top by 65 points. Lucy Campbell still holding on to second, but Maddie Sturt has moved herself in to podium contention, holding on third. It's an individual event, six and seven, presented by the United States Border Patrol.
Throttle up and hammer down, and if we think that we've seen some shaking up, Chase, we got something to come. It's 35 calories on the skier, 28 chest-to-bar pull-ups, 24 burpee box jump-overs, all while wearing a 16-pound weight vest. They get a one-minute hard reset into 35 calories on a bike, 28 bar muscle-ups, and 24 burpee box jump-overs. And for that, the weight is removed. It's time to see your body weight skills.
Adrian, what is your tempo recipe for success? It's pretty simple, and I think it holds true. For event number six, it's got to be full send. There's no time to pace and no time to wait. And on number seven, you've got to pace and break. We're going to need to be strategic with how we attack these 28-bar muscle-ups. Your lane assignments for the third and final heat.
for women's event number six. In lane number five, back in the red and white leader jersey. Let's go down to Mike Arsenault. Well, we mentioned it yesterday that Tia has had an endurance focus in her training so far in 2025. However, still 335 pounds good for fourth in event number five, turning that deficit into a 65-point lead. 200 points up for grabs, though, in event six and event seven. So that lead is far from safe. We'll see if some of these ladies can
bite into that lead over the next two events. Your vision fuels victory athletes to watch. Obviously, we saw Tia go from minus 2 to plus 65. But she is not alone on the podium with Maddie Sturt sitting there in third. 35 cows on the skier, starting things off. 16-pound vest. Now, two athletes keeping pace.
All from the same place. Maddie Sturt on the left, currently sitting in third overall. Gracie Walton on the right, she's holding on to 10th. However, if we're talking about burpees over a box, there's no one better in the space than Gracie Walton. If you don't have a memory back to what she did in 2024 in a workout called Firestorm, which is all that, and then some,
You better remind yourself because she's going to be coming when it comes to getting over these burpees in a sprint-style workout. So you named it, Chasen. You're right. You got to keep your eyes out on her. But then Maddie Stirk coming up with all this momentum. We know that she spends so much time with Tia Claire Toomey, has adopted that mindset of a champion, and she's really showing that she's executing at that type of level. 35 cows on the skier.
The time split here by Lucy McGonigal's 144. She has the time to beat. Lucy Campbell on the right side of your screen may not be wearing the leader jersey anymore after the backswap, however, still sitting solidly in second place.
Again, these women all rep for rep or calorie for calorie right now on the skier. Different strategies, Lucy showing a little bit of a slower cycle rate with more power. Tia more often with the strokes, a little bit higher turnover there. And again, it's calorie for calorie with Tia with a slight edge over Lucy right now, but they are not first off the skier. It looks like it is Amy Kringle. Kringle in the all pink on the left.
The time to beat, 355.56. That was set by Lucy McGonigal in the second heat. She was off the pull up bar at two minutes and 14 seconds. U.S. Border Patrol is hiring. Make an impact and be an agent of strength. Apply now at CBP.gov forward slash CrossFit. Kringle is done and onto the box.
Looks like Lydia Fish. That is Olivia Kerstetter, right next to her in the black. Tia Toomey, Lucy Campbell in the center two lanes. Toomey in the white and red. Campbell in the all light green. Ariel Lohan right there with them all. This is gonna be a tight one, Chase.
At the fourth box, McGonigal was done at 3.03. They're advancing to the fourth box now. All five athletes about a rep apart. And as Ariel Lohan, on pace of Lucy McGonigal.
Can Amy Kringle, Olivia Kerstetter, Tia or Lucy Campbell get underneath it? Ariel Lohan still holding a slight edge on the far right side of your screen. Here comes Tia and Lucy. Ariel's to the box first, six reps left to go.
She's trying to hold off four other athletes and the time to beat. Lucy just got hit with a huge no rep. She jumped off the box on her second rep. You got to step down, so she's going to drop behind. Ariel Lohan, sitting in eighth, is going to get herself 100 points in event number six, followed by Tia Toomey.
Leweski is done underneath the four minute mark followed by Kersetter. Pringles in. Ariel Lohan did not hold back on those last burpees. Able to take the heat and take the win as Lydia Fish is finishing up her last burpee box jump over.
Tia takes third overall, as McGonigal's time is good enough for second. Campbell takes fifth. Walton's in. Last in this heat, actually 24th in the event for event number six, as we have about one minute remaining on the time cap.
And another minute reset before we hit our final event of the afternoon. The champ doing champ things. She knows where she's sitting on the leaderboard. She's handling her business, focusing on recovery. If we get a shot there of young Willow.
Lydia Fish 20th in event six after getting ninth in the heat. There's the school of fish. They're supporting their girl Lydia. Great execution there on loan on the latter half of that workout.
She did exactly what she needed to do. And here is an example of our highlights. We thought it was going to be the lead coming off the skier that was going to set the precedent. But it was Amy Kringle who got off to that. First into the chest of our pull-ups by a couple reps, closely followed by Olivia Kerstetter. It looked like we had a race really brewing between the two of them. And then they were joined by the rest of the field. But it was Ariel Lohan who was a bit displaced from that middle pack that was making a charge to the front.
We had a little back and forth. Lucy got hit with a costly no rep there, jumping down from her box top rep too. These athletes had to step down all those boxed burpee getovers until the third rep of each transition. But it was Mrs. Ariel Lohan that came across first and then Tia Claire Toomey with a close second. Your results.
For event number six, Ariel Owen will take the event at 352. McGonigal at 355. And Tia Claire Toomey rounding out your top three at 356. And event seven, heat number three underway. Final opportunities to get points here on Saturday night. 35 cows on the Concept 2 bike.
28 bar muscle-ups and 24 burpees over the box. The weight vest is gone and the intensity is up. Yeah, the intensity is up. Lucy Campbell absolutely blistering these concept two calories right now. Lucy Campbell sitting in second overall.
She has 357 points. Gave a few points back to Ariel Lowen, who's in eighth. McGonigal is absolutely spinning those pedals. Campbell.
Did I say McGonigal? You did. Ah, I thought I was going to have a clean run this weekend. Hey, listen. And what I want to point out is that Lucer's one of the first athletes to reach the seated position. A lot of people stand up. They're trying to gain momentum. That should be a very short-lived period in order to get up the wattage and the momentum. Get to that high seated position so that you can become weightless and use your legs to lean forward over the pedals and really keep them turning. Off the bike first. Saw the same thing for the skier as Amy Kringle.
The time to beat set by Claudia Gluck in heat number two is 527.14. She was off the bike at 205. That said, she absolutely demolished those 28-bar muscle-ups, and that might have been according to plan as far as how she paced out the bike.
Right now, all these women looking really strong. We saw from the last heat, it's not a matter of if you break, it's when you break and how long you get on the ground and stay on the ground that dictates the outcome of this one. You've got to get back up to the rig. Your top five times in the bottom left corner of your screen, Claudia Gluck, Abby Domet, Lucy McGonigal, and Lexi Neely. Three 100s of a second between third and fourth. The number to get to in the top part of your screen
is 63. Amy Kringle has 10 reps left to go. The time off the rig by Claudia Gluck was 3.39. Lucy Cam on the far right side of your screen currently has eight reps left to go. As Toomey and Kringle just past her.
Lucy on the right side of your screen, back up to the bar. Can she hang on for the rest of this set? Yep, this is where Campbell has an opportunity to make her move right now. Five reps left to go for Campbell. Left side of your screen, Kringle, behind by two. Toomey, two reps back as well. That was it. Here we go. And the race is on the box.
Lucy Campbell is seven seconds ahead of the pace set by Gluck. And we know how fast Gluck went. And we know how fast you need to go because the seven time CrossFit Games champion is trying to run you down. Maybe a little retribution this morning for Tia Claire Toomey after what happened in event number four. Past the four minute mark.
Claudia Gluck was at 434 after the fourth box, and that is where Lucy Campbell is at the moment. And she is opening up the lead, not just on Claudia Gluck, but on Tia Claire Toomey as well. And Tia knows exactly where she needs to be. She's looking.
at exactly where Lucy's settling with her pace on these burpee box jumpovers, and Tia knows she's just gotta keep her close. With the point spread that she's got right now in first place, it's all about staying as close as she needs to, so there's very little to no gap between her and Lucy Campbell, and she'll be just fine. Tia came in with a 65-point lead on Lucy Campbell, and Lucy Campbell almost popped off the box again.
And that's what cost her in that first event, number six. Three more reps for Campbell. The time to beat is 5.27. That's not going to stand. And Lucy Campbell is going to get her second event win of the day. Tia Toomey's final three reps.
It's a time to beat his 527 coming into this and she will sneak right underneath that. There's Amy Kringle's on her last two burpee box jump overs. Ariel Lohan on the right side of your screen on her final two as well. Wow, gonna be a great showing for Ariel. Great back to back vents for Ariel Lohan. Erin Von Rohr clears the box.
Maddie Sturt is in. Annika Greer. She'll get across the finish line.
Something very unique about this back-to-back stimulus chase as we see Lydia Fish come across the finish line. Every athlete just completely loses body control and submits to gravity with no choice. They're not doing that on purpose, folks. This ain't no show. First setter is in, and what we thought was going to be a great opportunity for Gracie Walton to make a move up the leaderboard turned out to be anything but that with two very tough finishes.
And on the opposite side of the spectrum, you've got Lucy Campbell. And outside of an athlete named Tia Claire Toomey, that might be one of the best single day performances we've seen from any athlete at the CrossFit Games. Absolutely. Lucy Campbell put on an absolute show. And if the world didn't recognize her fitness, they're recognizing it now. Lucy Campbell.
Got fifth in event six and first in event seven. Your highlights presented by Rogue Fitness. Well, if it was a race off the erg, Amy Kringle would have won both of them, but it didn't stop there. It simply started there. She had the urgency needed to put herself in a good position to have some solid finishes.
But it was Lucy Campbell who paced it appropriately, specifically at the bar muscle-ups. We talked about break, don't wait being one of the keys to success. And she followed it through all the way. Now, she had a costly no rep in event six. She learned the hard way. She stepped down all the appropriate reps here, leading all the way through. Jumped down the ones that she could, kept her urgency, and it put her on her way to a second event win here on Saturday in the MVP arena at the 2025 CrossFit Games. Lucy Campbell is putting the world on notice. I'm back.
Year results for individual event number 7, Lucy Campbell gets her second event win for the day. That was her and Ariel Lohan who took event 6 and 7. Both seeing green with Mike Arsenault with our two event winners.
Aira, your second career event win in your CrossFit Games career. Very impressive, your fifth appearance at the Games in Event 6, and then you followed up in Event 7 with a really strong performance as well. How were you able to manage your rest to come back with a strong performance in Event 7? I train a lot with a lot of fun people in my home gym, but I really do think a burpee box jump over is like the most truest test of fitness. So I'm really proud that I have good fitness and I can show up on this event.
Well, speaking of training, as a parent, I like to use my kids and excuses as an excuse of why I can't train as much as I should. And you put a big hole into that argument that you're a professional athlete appearing at the CrossFit Games. How do you manage your time effectively that you can train like this and put results on the floor like you have?
Thank you. I think number one is just mindset. There'll always be an excuse of why you can't do it, why you shouldn't do it. But if you set boundaries and prioritize your time, absolutely. I'm not saying you should be training three hours a day like me, but a 30-minute walk is just as good. Sounds good. Congratulations. We'll see you tomorrow. Thank you. Thank you.
Now, good things come in twos. Apparently, Lucy, this is your second win of the 2025 CrossFit Games. Terrific performance in event number seven. Looks like you're definitely going to keep yourself on the podium, potentially closing that gap with Tia. How would you evaluate your performance today?
I know that I've just won an event, but mixed. Like, event six, I made a stupid mistake. I got carried up in the heat of the moment racing tier, and I think I got a little bit too excited and jumped off the box. But I think that comes with practice, and I still feel pretty new back into it. So it's those little things that I know that I can improve, and then I really just had to refocus.
every single box jump over, I was like, step, step, jump, step, step, jump. I didn't even know what box I was on. I was just making sure that I didn't mess it up again. When we talked earlier today, we talked about your injury and some of the limitations that you have. Is there an aspect of your fitness that has actually improved since dealing with that injury that maybe took more of a focus when you had to alleviate concerns with your wrist?
Yes, but ironically not in this event. I think if anything, we saw that more with the deadlifts and I know that the squat wasn't my best finish objectively, but it's something that I've been working a hell of a lot on and it really has come on a lot. So it's those things that are just filling in the gaps and it's still a work in progress coming back into it, but you know, showing the results overall.
Well, that work in progress is on the podium heading into the final day of competition at the 2025 CrossFit Games. Congratulations. Thank you. Hey.
What a day from Lucy Campbell. I mean, and what a great attitude. Look, she just won an event chase, and she's so hyper-focused on getting better and executing to her potential. She's like, I'm a little disappointed with that missed cue. I got excited competing against Tia. And folks, take a listen from Lucy. Get hyper-focused on a cue. She said, all I knew was step, step, jump, step, step, jump. I didn't even know what rep I was on. And that's called self-cueing at its finest. Well, Lucy Campbell had a heck of a day, but she did not have the moment of the day.
And that moment, our Sotva sleeper moment of the day, goes to another Australian. Jake Crouch's performance in individual event number four, not only got him his first event win at the CrossFit Games, but allowed him to wear that jersey for the first time.
What do we like from Jay today? Hey, we might have been sleeping on him to start the day. We are sleeping no more. He came and kicked down the walls with his event win. And it's been an honor to watch what Jay's been able to do. And he is far from done when it comes to the tests that are still looming in the course of this weekend. So we're going to see a lot of Mr. Crouch.
Boy, oh, boy. Check out that leaderboard. These are your standings going into Sunday. Jason Hopper still holding the leaderboard. Ricky Garrard has launched himself all the way into second, and James Sprague now sitting in third. Look, man, we got 41 points to separate first to seventh place.
Get your popcorn ready. It's going to be a close one. And we have three more events on Sunday. But that is not all. Your standings after seven events for the women. Tia Claire Toomey sits on top of the leaderboard with 610. Lucy Campbell, 541. And Ariel Lohan has now launched herself back on top of the podium.
400 points were today, we have 300 points coming up tomorrow. And on Sunday, team events will kick things off. Individuals have three of them. We still don't know what the final event is going to be, but we know we have a race on our hands for the men and the women.
The Wild Saturday has come to a close, and we were treated to a spectacle all day long. We say you had to be here. You had to be here. Good news, we got one more day of competition left. For Agent Conway, Mike Arsenault, I'm Chase Ingram. We say goodnight to Saturday, and we'll see you crowning champions tomorrow here in MVP Arena at the 2025 CrossFit Games.
you